<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03879460</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-044</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03879460</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Evaluation of Safety and Tolerance of Commercially Available Naltrexone Administered Daily - Assessment for CBRN Operations</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEST CANADA</acronym>
  <official_title>The Evaluation of Safety and Tolerance of Commercially Available Naltrexone Administered Daily - Assessment for CBRN Operations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Timothy Smith</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Canadian Department of National Defense</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the tolerance and safety of naltrexone while
      performing military specific tasks, and to assess plasma concentrations following naltrexone,
      administered orally at 50 mg per day for 7 days. The physical and mental/cognitive
      performance assessments will be conducted at various times prior, during and following drug
      administration. Daily blood draws will also be taken to assess blood levels of naltrexone and
      active metabolites for correlation to performance parameters associated with the Military
      Skill &amp; Tasked Based Fitness Test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Open label safety assessment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentration of naltrexone and its active metabolite, 6 beta naltrexol</measure>
    <time_frame>Study day 4 - 10</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Intoxication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open Label</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open label</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naltrexone Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg per os naltrexone hydrochloride</description>
    <arm_group_label>Open Label</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Non pregnant

          -  between 18 and 55 years;

          -  Body weight with a BMI range of 18.5 to 27.0 [or weight within 15% of ideal weight for
             subject's height and frame (to be based on Metropolitan Life Insurance Company weight
             tables);

          -  Healthy, with normal findings in the physical examination and vital signs (BP between
             100-140/60-90 mmHg, HR between 60 to 90 beats/min, respiration between 12 to 24
             breaths/min, SpO2 &gt;90% breathing room air) and no clinically-significant findings in a
             12-lead electrocardiogram;

          -  No clinical laboratory values outside of the laboratory normal reference range, unless
             the investigator determines them to be not clinically significant;

          -  Non-smoking (i.e. having no history of tobacco, or other substance, smoking for
             greater than or equal to 12 months, and not having smoked within the past year by
             self-report);

          -  Negative tests for smoking tobacco (urine cotinine test), alcohol (urine test),
             hepatitis B- surface antigen, hepatitis C antibody, tuberculin skin-prick test at
             screening;

          -  Negative urine screen for drugs of abuse;

          -  Willing and able to communicate well with the investigator and clinic staff, comply
             with the study procedure and schedule, and provide written informed consent;

          -  Able to understand the requirements of the study and sign informed consent;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current major Axis I psychiatric disorder for which the subject is currently receiving
             treatment or which would make study compliance an issue;

          -  Pregnant. A test will be available for prospective participants;

          -  Breast-feeding women;

          -  Any condition or therapy which, in the opinion of the investigator, may be
             significantly worsened by the administration of naltrexone or is likely to interfere
             with the successful collection of the measures required;

          -  Acute disease at the time of enrolment (i.e. presence of a moderate or severe illness
             or infection with or without a fever);

          -  Febrile illness (oral temperature &gt;37.6ยบ C at the time of drug administration);

          -  Unstable chronic illnesses;

          -  Chronic liver, renal or inflammatory bowel disease or collagen vascular disease;

          -  Clinically significant elevation of ALT and/or AST;

          -  Active neurological disorder;

          -  Clinically significant uncontrolled illness or clinically significant surgery within 4
             weeks prior to administration of study drug;

          -  Cancer within the previous 5 years, other than squamous cell or basal cell carcinoma
             of the skin;

          -  History of any clinical laboratory abnormality deemed significant by the Principal
             Investigator;

          -  History of serious adverse reaction or hypersensitivity to any drug;

          -  Bleeding tendency resulting from disease or medication rendering blood collection or
             the injection itself unsafe (use of antiplatelet agents is allowed);

          -  Coagulation disorders or receiving anticoagulant therapy;

          -  Inability to tolerate abstinence from caffeine for 24 hours prior to and during the
             study treatment phase;

          -  Consumption of alcohol within 24 hours prior to dosing and during the treatment phase;

          -  History of significant alcohol or drug abuse within one year prior to the screening
             visit or regular use of alcohol within six months prior to the screening visit (more
             than 14 units of alcohol per week [1 Unit = 150 mL of wine, 360 mL of beer, or 45 mL
             of 40% alcohol]);

          -  Use of soft drugs (such as marijuana) within three months prior to the screening visit
             or hard drugs (such as cocaine, phencyclidine or crack) within one year prior to the
             screening visit or positive urine drug screen at screening or positive urine drug
             screen at screening;

          -  Donation of plasma (500 mL) within 7 days prior to drug administration. Donation or
             loss of whole blood (excluding the volume of blood that will be drawn during the
             screening procedures of this study) prior to administration of the study medication as
             follows:

               -  50 mL to 300 mL of whole blood within 30 days;

               -  301 mL to 500 mL of whole blood within 45 days; or

               -  more than 500 mL of whole blood within 56 days prior to drug administration.

          -  Any known or suspected allergy to any constituent of naltrexone;

          -  Any food allergy, intolerance, restriction or special diet that, in the opinion of the
             Principal Investigator or Sub-Investigators, contraindicates the subject's
             participation inthis study;

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered drug or participation in an
             investigational study within 30 days prior to administration of study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of National Defence</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1A 0K2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Canadian Department of National Defense</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Timothy Smith</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Regulatory &amp; Product Development Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

