<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03872557</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAS2124</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK104740</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03872557</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Modulating Glucose Tolerance With Dietary Tyrosine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Modulating Glucose Tolerance With Dietary Tyrosine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic or Bariatric surgery is an effective treatment for type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM)
      diabetes associated with obesity. There remain some questions about the biochemical mechanism
      that drive how these surgeries work to reverse hyperglycemia. In the proposed human studies,
      the investigators will test the hypothesis that the amino acid tyrosine is a key metabolite
      in regulating blood sugar levels and that manipulation of the amount tyrosine supplied by
      nutrition is able to achieve some of the metabolic benefits seen in the early post-surgical
      period following bariatric surgery. The central hypothesis is that that the tyrosine content
      of the meal challenge affects post-prandial intestinal and plasma dopamine and levodopa and
      L-3,4-dihydroxyphenylalanine (L-DOPA) levels, which, in turn, impact β-cell insulin secretion
      and glucose excursions. The investigators now propose to characterize the possible effects of
      manipulating dopamine and L-DOPA levels in the gut and plasma on glucose tolerance, insulin
      secretion, and insulin sensitivity in healthy volunteers with a range of body mass indexes
      (BMIs).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Several biochemical mechanisms explaining how Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass (RYGB) provides an
      effective treatment for obesity associated type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and improves
      hyperglycemia independently of weight loss have been proposed. Two are of particular
      interest; a) the hindgut hypothesis suggesting that nutrient delivery to the distal intestine
      drives the production of &quot;incretins&quot; which enhance insulin secretion (e.g. glucagon-like
      peptide-1 (GLP-1)), and b) the foregut hypothesis, positing that foregut bypass reduces the
      secretion of factors (i.e. anti-incretins) that normally defend against hypoglycemia. The
      investigators have been actively investigating this topic and have developed a hypothesis
      based on past studies that they wish to test in a limited human clinical study. In addition,
      preclinical data suggest that there exists a gut-to-beta cell pathway, responsive to
      nutritional tyrosine, regulating insulin secretion, and this pathway provides a mechanism for
      the early postoperative improvements in hyperglycemia observed in RYGB.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole blood glucose level</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge define glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma insulin concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma insulin concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge define glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma dopamine concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma dopamine concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge may affect glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma L-DOPA concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma L-DOPA concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge may affect glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>L-tyrosine concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma L-tyrosine concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge may affect glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma glucagon concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma glucagon concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge impacts glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma GLP-1 concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 minutes from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma GLP-1 concentration versus time profile following glucose challenge impacts glucose tolerance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Glucose Tolerance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tyrosine (TYR) depletion, then oral TYR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>TYR supplementation: Subjects will be directed to avoid consumption of L-DOPA and TYR enriched foods for 48 hours before oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT). On the evening prior to OGTT, subjects will substitute normal meal and snack for three prepackaged tyrosine-phenylalanine-free liquid meals.
Visit 2. Placement of intravenous catheter for the collection of serial blood samples and an OGTT with supplementation with oral tyrosine supplement. To supplement the OGTT with Tyrosine, the contents of four (4) L-Tyrosine 500 mg capsule are given 45 minutes before the oral glucose solution is administered. The capsules are to be administered with less than eight ounces of water to minimize dilution of gastric acidity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TYR depletion, then no oral TYR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be directed to avoid consumption of L-DOPA and TYR enriched foods for 48 hours before OGTT. On the evening prior to OGTT, subjects will substitute normal meal and snack for three prepackaged tyrosine-phenylalanine-free liquid meals.
Subsequent Visit 3. This visit will consist of placement of intravenous catheter for the collection of serial blood samples and an OGTT without supplementation with oral tyrosine supplement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tyrosine (TYR) Supplementation</intervention_name>
    <description>L-Tyrosine dietary supplement will be provided as 500 mg capsules and 4 (four) 500 mg capsules are to be given before OGTT. The capsules are formed from animal gelatin, and the contents are formulated with magnesium stearate as a flow agent, but without binders, coatings or colorings and also have no added flavorings, sugars, salt, artificial sweeteners, preservatives or salicylates. The capsules are to be administered with less than eight ounces of water to minimize dilution of gastric acidity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tyrosine (TYR) depletion, then oral TYR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        i. Inclusion Criteria

          1. Capable of giving written as well as oral informed consent.

          2. A fasting plasma glucose level (FPG) &lt; 126 mg/dL (&lt; 7.0 mmol/L) and an Hb1ac in the
             5.7-6.4 % range.

          3. BMI in the range of 18-45 kg/m2.

          4. Normal Complete blood count (CBC), renal and liver function tests.

        ii. Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any diabetes medication within previous three (3) months.

          2. Fasting plasma Glucose (FPG) &gt;126 mg/dl or HbA1c &gt; 6.4%

          3. Current use (or within 6 months) of antipsychotic, anti-anxiety, or antidepressant
             medications (e.g. monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors, 5-Hydroxytryptophan (5HT)
             inhibitors, tricyclic antidepressants, L-DOPA), reserpine, β-2-receptor agonists
             (e.g., terbutaline), steroids, weight loss medication, anticoagulant medication,
             over-the-counter nutritional supplements other than standard vitamin and mineral
             supplements

          4. History of Phenylketonuria or other inherited disorders of amino acid metabolism.

          5. History of movement disorder such as Parkinson's disease or Huntington's disease

          6. Cardiovascular, renal, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, migraines or other medical
             conditions deemed significant by investigators

          7. History of/ or psychiatric illness such as major depression, bipolar disease, anxiety
             or schizophrenia.

          8. History of bariatric surgery with the exception of gastric band if the band has been
             removed

          9. Female of child-bearing age, currently pregnant, breastfeeding or not using a form of
             birth control.

         10. Previous or current use of cocaine, methamphetamine, ecstasy (3-4
             methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA))

         11. Current daily intake of caffeine &gt;500 mg/day (&gt;4-5 cups of coffee; &gt;10 12-oz cans of
             soda)

         12. Consumption of more than 1 alcoholic drink per day or smoking more than 5
             cigarettes/day.

         13. Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) &gt; 150 mmHg; Diastolic Blood Pressure (DBP) &gt; 100 mmHg.

         14. Recent history (in the past three months) of more than a 3% gain or loss in body wt.

         15. Difficulty in swallowing capsules.

         16. Concurrent use of antacids or proton pump inhibitors (e.g.,Prilosec Prevacid,
             dexilant, Aciphex, Protonix, Nexium, Vimovo, Zegerid)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith Korner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Harris, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-7363</phone>
    <email>peh1@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Judith Korner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-5568</phone>
    <email>jk181@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korner J, Cline GW, Slifstein M, Barba P, Rayat GR, Febres G, Leibel RL, Maffei A, Harris PE. A role for foregut tyrosine metabolism in glucose tolerance. Mol Metab. 2019 May;23:37-50. doi: 10.1016/j.molmet.2019.02.008. Epub 2019 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>30876866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Judith Korner</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glucose tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>Tyrosine</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

