<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03876769</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CCTL019G2201J</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-002116-14</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03876769</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Efficacy and Safety of Tisagenlecleucel in HR B-ALL EOC MRD Positive Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>CASSIOPEIA</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Tisagenlecleucel in First-line High-risk (HR) Pediatric and Young Adult Patients With B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (B-ALL) Who Are Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) Positive at the End of Consolidation (EOC) Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single arm, open-label, multi-center, phase II study to determine the efficacy and
      safety of tisagenlecleucel in de novo HR pediatric and young adult B-ALL patients who
      received first-line treatment and are EOC MRD positive. The study will have the following
      sequential phases: screening, pre-treatment, treatment &amp; follow-up, and survival. After
      tisagenlecleucel infusion, patient will have assessments performed more frequently in the
      first month and then at Day 29, then every 3 months for the first year, every 6 months for
      the second year, then yearly until the end of the study. Efficacy and safety will be assessed
      at study visits and as clinically indicated throughout the study. The study is expected to
      end in approximately 8 years after first patient first treatment (FPFT). A post-study long
      term follow-up for lentiviral vector safety will continue under a separate protocol per
      health authority guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 19, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 26, 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Free Survival (DFS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years after tisagenlecleucel infusion</time_frame>
    <description>DFS is defined as the time from the date of tisagenlecleucel infusion to the date of the first documented morphological relapse, occurrence of secondary malignancy or death due to any cause.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who are disease free without allogeneic stem cell transplant (SCT)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after last infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) negative remission (complete remission (CR) or Complete remission with incomplete blood count recovery CRi)) at Month 12 without SCT after tisagenlecleucel infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from tisagenlecleucel infusion to the death due to any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants achieving MRD negative CR or CRi at Month 3</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after the tisagenlecleucel infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>MRD negative status as determined by central laboratory using multi-parameter flow cytometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with in CR or CRi with persistent B-cell aplasia over time post tisagenlecleucel infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Absolute lymphocyte CD19 count of &gt;50/uL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who have tisagenlecleucel product successfully manufactured over the total number of subjects enrolled for the age ≥1 year and &lt; 3 years</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Success in manufacturing of tisagenlecleucel dose for patients who are ≥1 year and &lt;3 years as respective time points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pediatric Quality of Life (PedsQL)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patient reported outcome to assess quality of life in patients aged 8 and above. The 23 items PedQL (Pediatrics Quality of Life Inventory) measure core dimensions of health as delineated by the World Health Organization, as well as role (school) functioning.
Items measured include 1) Physical Functioning (8 items), 2) Emotional Functioning (5 items), 3) Social Functioning (5 items), and 4) School Functioning (5 items).
Each item is measured on a 5 point Likert scale with 0 indicating &quot;never&quot; and 4 indicating &quot;almost always&quot;.
The Likert scores are reversed scored and linearly transform to a 0-100 scale with 0=100, 1-75, 2=50, 5=25, and 4=0. A higher score indicates better health-related quality of life (HRQoL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Quality of Life 5 dimensions (EQ-5D-3L &amp; EQ-5D-Y))</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patient reported outcome to assess health status in patients aged 8 and above. The EQ-5D (European Quality of Life -5 Dimensions) measures a wide range of health conditions and treatments; it is composed of 5 dimensions (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression) and a visual analogue scale (EQ-visual analogue scale [EQ-VAS]) that records the patient's self-rated overall health state.
Respondents rate each of these 5 dimensions from &quot;no problem&quot;, &quot;some problem,&quot; or &quot;extreme problem&quot;.
The EQ-VAS records the respondents' self-related health on a vertical, visual analogue scale. The range for EQ-VAS is from 0 (=the worst health you can imagine) to 100 (=the best health you can imagine).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of tisagenlecleucel on cognitive functioning using Computerized neurocognitive assessment: Detection test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Speed of performance (mean of the log10 transformed reaction times for correct responses)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of tisagenlecleucel on cognitive functioning usingComputerized neurocognitive assessment: Identification test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>This test measures the speed of performance (mean of the log10 transformed reaction times for correct responses)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of tisagenlecleucel on cognitive functioning using Computerized neurocognitive assessment: Groton Maze Learning test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>This test looks at the total number of errors made in attempting to learn the hidden pathways during a single session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of tisagenlecleucel on cognitive functioning using Computerized neurocognitive assessment: One Back test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>This test measures the accuracy of performance (arcsine transformation of the square root of the percentage of correct responses). The test also measures the speed of performance (mean of the log10 transformed reaction times for correct responses).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of tisagenlecleucel on cognitive functioning usingComputerized neurocognitive assessment: One card learning test</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>This test measures the accuracy of performance (arcsine transformation of the square root of the proportion of correct responses).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with pre-existing antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Prevalence of immunogenicity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with anti-m CAR19 antibodies post infusion with tisagenlecleucel and % of patients without measureable anti-mCAR19 antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of immunogenicity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients that have measureable anti-mCAR19 antibodies above patient specific cut-point (reported as a %) pre and post tisagenlecleucel infusion categorized by Day 28 response</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of immunogenicity on clinical response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tisagenlecleucel transgene concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Transgene concentration as detected by qPCR in target tissue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Expression of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Summary of tisagenlecleucel CAR-positive viable T cells measured by flow cytometry in target tissue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence of CAR (reported as copies/ug) categorized by the time to B-cell recovery (recovery &lt; 3 months, &gt;3 months to &lt; 6months, &gt; 6 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Relationship between B-cell recovery and transgene levels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum (peak) observed in peripheral blood or other body fluid drug concentration after single dose administration (% or copies/μg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time to reach maximum (peak) peripheral blood or other body fluid drug concentration after single dose administration (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-29d and 84d; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC from time zero to day 29 and 84 or other disease assessment days, in peripheral blood (% or copies/μg x days )</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-Tmax; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC from time zero to Tmax in peripheral blood (% or copies/μg x days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/2; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The half-life associated with the elimination phase slope of a semi logarithmic concentration-time curve (days) in peripheral blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clast; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The last observed quantifiable concentration in peripheral blood (% or copies/μg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tlast; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time of last observed quantifiable concentration in peripheral blood (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of tisagenlecleucel dose on day 29 response</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical response summarized by quartile of administered doses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC 0 - 29d; cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of tisagenlecleucel exposure on day 29 response; The AUC from time zero to day 29 in peripheral blood (% or copies/μg x days )</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax: cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of tisagenlecleucel exposure on day 29 response; The maximum (peak) observed in peripheral blood or other body fluid drug concentration after single dose administration (% or copies/μg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax: cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of tisagenlecleucel exposure on day 29 response; The time to reach maximum (peak) peripheral blood or other body fluid drug concentration after single dose administration (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/2: cellular kinetic parameter of tisagenlecleucel</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of tisagenlecleucel exposure on day 29 response; The half-life associated with the elimination phase slope of a semi logarithmic concentration-time curve (days) in peripheral blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>B-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single dose of CTL019</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Based on the subject's weight one of two possible dose ranges will be prepared for the subject:
Subjects ≤ 50 kg: 0.2 to 5.0 x 10(6) CAR-positive viable T cells per kg body weight
OR
Subjects &gt; 50 kg: 0.1 to 2.5 x 10(8) CAR-positive viable T cells</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CTL019</intervention_name>
    <description>Based on the subject's weight, one of two possible dose ranges will be prepared for the subject:
Subjects ≤ 50 kg: 0.2 to 5.0 x 10(6) CAR-positive viable T cells per kg body weight
OR
Subjects &gt; 50 kg: 0.1 to 2.5 x 10(8) CAR-positive viable T cells</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single dose of CTL019</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. CD19 expressing B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia

          2. De novo NCI HR B-ALL who received first-line treatment and are MRD ≥ 0.01% at EOC. EOC
             bone marrow MRD will be collected prior to screening and will be assessed by
             multi-parameter flow cytometry using central laboratory analysis.

          3. Age 1 to 25 years at the time of screening

          4. Lansky (age &lt; 16 years) or Karnofsky (age ≥ 16 years) performance status ≥ 60%

          5. Adequate organ function during the screening period:

             A. Renal function based on age/gender B. ALT ≤ 5 times ULN for age C. AST ≤ 5 times
             ULN for age D. Total bilirubin &lt; 2 mg/dL (for Gilbert's Syndrome subjects total
             bilirubin &lt; 4 mg/dL)

             E. Adequate pulmonary function defined as:

               -  no or mild dyspnea (≤ Grade 1)

               -  oxygen saturation of &gt; 90% on room air F. Adequate cardiac function defined as
                  LVSF ≥ 28% confirmed by echocardiogram or LVEF ≥ 45% confirmed by echocardiogram
                  or MUGA within 6 weeks of screening

          6. Prior induction and consolidation chemotherapy allowed: 1st line subjects: ≤ 3 blocks
             of standard chemotherapy for first-line B-ALL, defined as 4-drug induction,
             Berlin-Frankfurt-Münster (BFM) consolidation or Phase 1b, and interim maintenance with
             high-dose methotrexate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. M3 marrow at the completion of 1st line induction therapy

          2. M2 or M3 marrow or persistent extramedullary disease at the completion of first-line
             consolidation therapy or evidence of disease progression in the peripheral blood or
             new extramedullary disease prior to enrollment. Patients with previous CNS disease are
             eligible if there is no active CNS involvement of leukemia at the time of screening.

          3. Philadelphia chromosome positive ALL

          4. Hypodiploid: less than 44 chromosomes and/or DNA index &lt; 0.81, or other clear evidence
             of a hypodiploid clone

          5. Prior tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy

          6. Subjects with concomitant genetic syndromes associated with bone marrow failure
             states: such as subjects with Fanconi anemia, Kostmann syndrome, Shwachman syndrome or
             any other known bone marrow failure syndrome. Subjects with Down syndrome will not be
             excluded.

          7. Subjects with Burkitt's lymphoma/leukemia (i.e. subjects with mature B-ALL, leukemia
             with B-cell [sIg positive and kappa or lambda restricted positivity] ALL, with FAB L3
             morphology and /or a MYC translocation)

          8. Has had treatment with any prior anti-CD19 therapy 9. Treatment with any prior gene or
             engineered T cell therapy

        Other protocol-defined inclusion/exclusion may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-669-6682</phone>
    <email>novartis.email@novartis.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <phone>+41613241111</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phoenix Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dresden Whitehead</last_name>
      <phone>602-546-0985</phone>
      <email>dwhitehead@phoenixchildrens.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jessica Boklan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>+1 626 256 4673 Ext 85013</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Pawlowska</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens Hospital Los Angeles SC CTL019</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cathy Salata</last_name>
      <phone>323-361-8670</phone>
      <email>csalata@chla.usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Pulsipher</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mattel Childrens Hospital UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Villeda</last_name>
      <email>mvilleda@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William May</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rady Children s Hospital CTBM100C2401</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92123</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alessandra Rohrman</last_name>
      <phone>858-966-8153</phone>
      <email>ARohrman@rchsd.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Deborah Schiff</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>415-353-1351</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelle Hermiston</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Universtiy Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne Marcy</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-4000</phone>
      <email>Acmarcy@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kara Davis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta Emory University IRB</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judson Russell</last_name>
      <email>Judson.Russell@choa.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Muna Qayed</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>James Whitcomb Riley Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Pencek</last_name>
      <phone>317-274-4281</phone>
      <email>jpencek@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jodi Skiles</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Oncology Center Cancer Research Building</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>410-502-5940</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick Brown</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children s Mercy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robin Ryan</last_name>
      <phone>816-234-3977</phone>
      <email>rryan@cmh.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary D. Myers</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University CTBM100C2412</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Monahan</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-2253</phone>
      <email>amy.monahan@bjc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sima Bhatt</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elana Smilow</last_name>
      <phone>201-996-2000</phone>
      <email>elana.smilow@hackensackmeridian.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alfred Gillio</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Victoria Szenes</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3112</phone>
      <email>szenesv@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin Curran</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children s Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229-3039</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Courtney Blank</last_name>
      <phone>800-344-2462</phone>
      <email>courtney.blank@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christine Phillips</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239-3098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nycole Ferguson</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-5893</phone>
      <email>ferguson@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bill Chang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Childrens Hospital of Philadelphia Div Gastroint., Hepat. &amp; Nutr.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina S. Fausano</last_name>
      <phone>215-590-2985</phone>
      <email>seminackc@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shannon Maude</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390-9034</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yolanda Burnom</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-1390</phone>
      <email>yolanda.burnom@childrens.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samuel John</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Candace Taylor</last_name>
      <email>candace.taylor@mhshealth.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Eckrich</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Clinical Trials Office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Genesis Arko</last_name>
      <phone>801-587-5711</phone>
      <email>Genesis.Arko@imail2.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Phillip Barnette</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Hospital and Clinics Pharmacy/Drug Shipping Address</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jenny Weiland</last_name>
      <email>PedsHemOncResearch@lists.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian Capitini</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T 1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00029</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 19</city>
        <zip>75935</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muenchen</city>
        <zip>81377</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>ITA</state>
        <zip>00165</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prinses Maxima Centrum voor Kinderoncologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <state>CS</state>
        <zip>3584</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>R. Pieters</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0424</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Esplugues de Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08950</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1E 6HX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1N 3JH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CTL019</keyword>
  <keyword>Kymriah</keyword>
  <keyword>B-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>ALL</keyword>
  <keyword>tisagenlecleucel</keyword>
  <keyword>HR B-ALL EOC MRD</keyword>
  <keyword>Minimal Residual Disease (MRD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Positive at the End of Consolidation (EOC)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Novartis is committed to sharing with qualified external researchers, access to patient-level data and supporting clinical documents from eligible studies. These requests are reviewed and approved by an independent expert panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations.
This trial data is currently available according to the process described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

