<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03874494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>331-403-00027</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03874494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Brexpiprazole in the Treatment of Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Active-Controlled Study (Aripiprazole Tablets) to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Brexpiprazole in the Treatment of Adults With Acute Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Otsuka Beijing Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Otsuka Beijing Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a phase III, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, active-controlled,
      non-inferiority trial designed to assess the efficacy and safety of Brexpiprazole in the
      Treatment of Adults With Acute Schizophrenia. A total of approximately 370 subjects will be
      included in the study, and randomized to Brexpiprazole (2~4 mg/d) or Aripiprazole (10~20
      mg/d) in a 1:1 ratio.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Screening Phase: It will begin when informed consent form (ICF) is signed and be a maximum of
      14 days, to evaluate the inclusion/exclusion criteria, collect information such as
      demographic data, medical history, wash out previous antipsychotic agents and other
      prohibited concomitant medications.

      Double-blind Treatment Phase: It lasts 6 weeks; the purpose is to compare the efficacy and
      safety of Brexpiprazole with Aripiprazole in the treatment of adults with acute
      schizophrenia.

      Follow-up Phase: All subjects will be followed up for safety reasons via telephone contact or
      clinic visit 30 (+ 2) days after the last dose of investigational medicinal product,
      collecting safety information (adverse events and concomitant medication).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) measures psychotic symptoms in patients with schizophrenia. PANSS includes 30 items (7 items for positive symptoms, 7 items for negative symptoms, and 16 items for general psychopathology symptoms), and each item ranges from 1 to 7. The PANSS total score is a sum of scores from all items, ranging from 30 to 210, where a higher score represents severer psychotic symptoms in patients with schizophrenia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Severity (CGI-S) score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Clinical Global Impression-Severity (CGI-S) score ranges from 1 to 7. A higher score represents a severer clinical impression on the patient's severity based on investigator/clinician's judgment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Personal and Social Performance Scale (PSP) global score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Personal and Social Performance Scale (PSP) contains four domains: socially useful activities, personal and social relationships, self-care, and disturbing and aggressive behavior. A higher domain score represents worse functional performance in each domain. The final global score is defined according to a summary instruction table converting four domain scores into a single, overall rating from 1 to 100, where a higher score represents better personal and social function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) positive scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) positive scale includes 7 items, assessing positive symptoms in schizophrenia such as delusion, hallucinatory or excitement, and each item ranges from 1 to 7. The positive scale score is a sum of scores from the 7 items, ranging from 7 to 49, where a higher score represents severer schizophrenia positive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) negative scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) negative scale includes 7 items, assessing negative symptoms in schizophrenia such as blunted affect or emotional withdrawal, and each item ranges from 1 to 7. The negative scale score is a sum of scores from the 7 items, ranging from 7 to 49, where a higher score represents severer schizophrenia negative symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Improvement (CGI-I) score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Clinical Global Impression-Improvement (CGI-I) score ranges from 1 to 7. A higher score represents a poorer clinical impression on the patient's improvement based on investigator/clinician's judgment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>defined as reduction of ≥ 30% from baseline in PANSS Total Score OR CGI-I score of 1 [very much improved] or 2 [much improved]) at Week 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">370</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brexpiprazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2-4 mg/day, once daily for 6 weeks, oral administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aripiprazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10-20 mg/day, once daily for 6 weeks, oral administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brexpiprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Brexpiprazole 2-4 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brexpiprazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brexpiprazole Tablets</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aripiprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Aripiprazole 10-20 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aripiprazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aripiprazole Tablets</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provide written informed consent form by subjects and subject's legal guardian or
             legally acceptable representative.

          2. The subjects and subject's legal guardian or legally acceptable representative have
             the ability to understand the nature of the trial, agree to comply with the prescribed
             medication and dosage regimens, complete the scheduled visits, report the adverse
             events and concomitant medication to investigators, and to be reliably rated on
             psychiatrically scales.

          3. At the time of signing informed consent, 18 ≤ age of the subject ≤ 65.

          4. Subjects who are diagnosed with schizophrenia according to Diagnostic and Statistical
             Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition, Text Revision (DSM-IV-TR) and confirmed by
             Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI).

          5. Subjects who are experiencing an acute exacerbation of psychotic symptoms and marked
             deterioration of usual function as demonstrated by meeting ALL of the following
             criteria at the screening and baseline visit:

             ● PANSS total score ≥ 70;

               -  Score ≥ 4 on at least 2 of the following PANSS items :

             ( P2 Conceptual disorganization, P3 Hallucinatory behavior, P6 Suspiciousness /
             persecution, G9 Unusual thought content ) ● CGI-S score ≥ 4;

          6. Subjects willing to discontinue all prohibited psychotropic medications to meet
             protocol-required washouts prior to and during the trial period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. From ICF to 30 days after the last dose, females of childbearing potential and male
             subjects who are not willing or cannot practice contraceptive methods.

          2. Females who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          3. Subjects who have been hospitalized for &gt; 21 days for the current acute episode at the
             time of the Baseline visit, excluding hospitalization for psychosocial reasons.

          4. Subjects with improvement of ≥ 30% in total PANSS score between the screening and
             baseline assessment. Improvement in PANSS score= (score at screening-score at
             baseline)/ (score at screening-30)*100%.

          5. Subjects with schizophrenia who are considered resistant/refractory to antipsychotic
             treatment by history of failure to respond to 2 adequate different antipsychotic
             medications with a minimum of 6 weeks at clinically efficacious tolerated doses.
             Subjects who have a systemic treatment of clozapine.

          6. Subjects with a current DSM-IV-TR Axis I diagnosis (including but not limited to):
             schizoaffective disorder, MDD, bipolar disorder, post-traumatic stress disorder,
             anxiety disorders, delirium, dementia, amnestic or other cognitive disorders.

          7. Subjects with a current DSM-IV-TR Axis II diagnosis: borderline, paranoid, histrionic,
             schizotypal, schizoid, or antisocial personality disorders.

          8. Subjects who present a serious risk of suicide:

             ● Subjects who answer &quot;Yes&quot; on the C-SSRS Suicidal Ideation Item 4 or 5 and meeting
             the criteria for this C-SSRS Item 4 or 5 occurred within the last 6 months; OR

             ● Subjects who answer &quot;Yes&quot; on any of the 5 C-SSRS Suicidal Behavior Items and meeting
             the criteria for any of these 5 C-SSRS Suicidal Behavior Items occurred within the
             last 2 years; OR

             ● Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, present a serious risk of suicide

          9. Subjects with clinically diagnosed tardive dyskinesia, as determined by a score of ≥ 3
             in Item 8 of the AIMS at the Screening visit.

         10. Subjects with a score of 5 in the BARS global clinical assessment of akathisia at
             Screening or Baseline.

         11. Subjects who have met DSM-IV-TR criteria for substance abuse or dependence within the
             180 days prior to Screening Visit; including alcohol and benzodiazepines, but
             excluding caffeine and nicotine.

         12. Subjects with uncontrolled thyroid disease and/or abnormal free thyroxine (FT4)
             examination results at Screening, unless it has been confirmed by the investigator
             that the condition has been stabilized by medication &gt; 90 days before screening

         13. Subjects with type I diabetes or uncontrolled type II diabetes. Subjects with type II
             diabetes may be eligible for the trial if their condition is stable as determined by
             satisfying ALL of the following criteria:

               -  HbA1c &lt; 7.0%, AND

               -  Glucose must be ≤ 125 mg/dL or ≤ 6.94 mmol/L (fasting) or &lt; 200 mg/dL or &lt; 11.1
                  mmol/L (non-fasting) at Screening. If the non-fasting glucose is ≥ 200 mg/dL or ≥
                  11.1 mmol/L, subjects must be retested in a fasted state and the retest value
                  must be ≤ 125 mg/dL or ≤ 6.94 mmol/L, AND

               -  Subjects have maintained a stable regimen of oral anti-diabetic medication(s) for
                  at least 28 days prior to screening or diabetes has been well-controlled by diet
                  for at least 28 days prior to screening, AND

               -  Subjects have not had any hospitalizations within the 12 months prior to
                  screening due to diabetes or complications related to diabetes, AND

               -  Subjects whose diabetes is not newly diagnosed during screening for the trial.

         14. Subjects with uncontrolled hypertension (diastolic blood pressure &gt; 95 mmHg in any
             position) or symptomatic hypotension, or orthostatic hypotension which is defined as a
             decrease of ≥ 30 mmHg in systolic blood pressure and/or a decrease of ≥ 20 mmHg in
             diastolic blood pressure after at least 3 minutes standing compared to the previous
             supine blood pressure, OR development of symptoms.

         15. Subjects with a history of ischemic heart disease or history of myocardial infarction,
             congestive heart failure (whether controlled or uncontrolled), angioplasty, stenting,
             or coronary artery bypass surgery.

         16. Subjects who have a history or severe organic disease of vital organs (including but
             not limited to hepatic, renal, respiratory, cardiovascular, endocrine, neurologic,
             hematologic, or immunologic disease).

         17. Subjects with epilepsy or a history of seizures, except for a single seizure episode,
             for instance childhood febrile seizure and post traumatic or alcohol withdrawal.

         18. The following laboratory test and ECG results are exclusionary:

        1) Platelets ≤ 75,000/mm3 (≤ 75 x 109 /L) 2) Hemoglobin ≤ 9 g/dL (90 g/L) 3) Neutrophils ≤
        1,000/mm3 (1 x 109 /L) 4) AST or ALT &gt; 2 × ULN 5) CPK &gt; 3 × ULN 6) Creatinine ≥ 2 mg/dL
        (176.8 µmol/L) 7) HbA1c ≥ 7.0% 8) QTc ≥ 450 msec (for males) or ≥ 470 msec (for females) in
        ECG 19. Subjects who received ECT within 60 days of screening. 20. Subjects with a history
        of neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS). 21. Subjects with a history of true allergic
        response (ie, not intolerance) to more than one class of medications.

        22. Subjects who participated in a clinical trial within the last 90 days or who
        participated in two or more clinical trials within the past year.

        23. Any subject who, in the opinion of the investigator, should not participate in the
        trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hongyan Zhang, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University Sixth Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haiwei Li</last_name>
    <phone>010-85182966</phone>
    <phone_ext>8018</phone_ext>
    <email>lihw@obri.otsuka.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>No.15 Yanyin Road, Yanta District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shanxi</state>
        <zip>710061</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bin Wu, Bachelor</last_name>
      <phone>＋8613572222831</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Brexpiprazole</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-inferiority</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aripiprazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brexpiprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

