<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03101891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00164021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03101891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Renal Anhydramnios Fetal Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAFT</acronym>
  <official_title>Renal Anhydramnios Fetal Therapy (RAFT) Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Early pregnancy renal anhydramnios or EPRA is a condition where a pregnant woman does not
      have any amniotic fluid around her fetus because of a problem with the fetus's kidneys. This
      condition is thought to be fatal once the fetus is born because of inadequate lung growth.
      The Renal Anhydramnios Fetal Therapy (RAFT) Trial offers eligible pregnant women with a
      diagnosis of EPRA an experimental therapy of repeated or serial &quot;amnioinfusions&quot; of fluid
      into the womb. An amnioinfusion involves placing a small needle through the pregnant woman's
      skin into the womb next to the fetus. Warm sterile fluid with balanced electrolytes and
      antibiotics is then slowly infused into amniotic space inside the womb. The aim is to help
      the fetus's lungs grow enough so he or she can survive after birth. These amnioinfusions will
      be carried out by an expert in fetal interventions at a RAFT center. There is a significant
      risk of early rupture of membranes and early delivery in subjects who receive amnioinfusions,
      and any potential trial participants will be counseled about these risks before they decide
      whether to join the trial. Any eligible patients who, after counseling, elect to terminate
      the pregnancy will not be eligible to participate in the trial. All eligible patients who
      choose to join the RAFT trial will be able to choose their assignment into one of two arms of
      the study: (1) to receive serial amnioinfusions (2) to not receive amnioinfusions but receive
      monitoring for the remainder of the pregnancy at the RAFT center. Thus, assignment of
      patients to study arm will not be random, but will be decided by the participant. Fetuses who
      do survive after birth will require intensive medical management for kidney failure including
      placement of a dialysis catheter and dialysis therapy with the eventual need for a kidney
      transplant. Treatment for lung disease secondary to abnormal lung development may also be
      required. The study will follow babies and their families until non-survival or transplant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Amniotic fluid is critical for normal lung development. After the first trimester of
      pregnancy amniotic fluid is composed nearly completely of fetal urine. The absence of
      amniotic fluid due to lack of urine production by the fetal kidneys is known as anhydramnios.
      Early pregnancy renal anhydramnios or EPRA is thought to be 100% lethal after birth if left
      untreated because of neonatal respiratory failure. The two causes of EPRA are bilateral renal
      agenesis or fetal renal failure (such as from multicystic dysplastic kidneys or obstructed
      kidneys). Recently there have been clinical case reports of repeated or serial infusions of
      isotonic fluid (amnioinfusions) into the amniotic cavity leading to respiratory survival in
      neonates with a history of EPRA. Some surviving neonates have gone on to undergo successful
      dialysis and kidney transplant as toddlers. However, no prospective trial has investigated
      the safety of amnioinfusions in EPRA, the feasibility of doing serial amnioinfusions in EPRA
      pregnancies without causing rupture of membranes, or the neonatal survival rate after serial
      amnioinfusions for EPRA. Accordingly the goal of the Renal Anhydramnios Fetal Therapy (RAFT)
      trial is to determine the safety, feasibility, and efficacy of serial amnioinfusions to
      promote normal fetal lung development in EPRA. Pregnant patients presenting to a RAFT center
      with a diagnosis of EPRA will undergo an evaluation including diagnostic amnioinfusion with
      ultrasound imaging to verify the diagnosis. Counseling by a team of subspecialists including
      a maternal fetal medicine doctor, a pediatric nephrologist, a pediatric surgeon, a
      neonatologist, a kidney transplant specialist, a genetic counselor and a social worker will
      be given to every patient. This counseling is meant to provide the clearest picture possible
      of what serial amnioinfusions entail and what life will be like for a surviving neonate with
      no kidney function. Survivors will require urgent dialysis with a peritoneal or hemodialysis
      catheter. These children are prone to significant infections and often need a gastrostomy
      tube in order to receive sufficient nutrition. The goal is for these children to ultimately
      undergo the most robust form of renal replacement therapy with a kidney transplant once they
      are large enough to tolerate it.

      Once the diagnosis of EPRA is confirmed, counseling is complete and a patient is deemed
      eligible for serial amnioinfusions, enrollment into the study will be offered. Patients may
      choose to enroll in the study, may choose to continue the pregnancy and not be a part of the
      study or may choose to terminate the pregnancy. If the patients elect to enroll in the study,
      they will be given a further choice of intervention with serial amnioinfusions or expectant
      management with repeat imaging. Participants will not be randomized because there is no
      realistic hope that expectant management will lead to postnatal survival. Patients who do not
      choose to undergo amnioinfusions but who also do not elect to terminate will provide
      invaluable insight into the in utero natural history of EPRA if they enroll in the trial. The
      sample size of this trial is based on a calculation of the number of patients required to
      adequately determine a postnatal survival rate of amnioinfusions for EPRA with narrow
      confidence intervals. Postnatal survival will be defined as survival to successful dialysis
      for 15 continuous days; this is the primary outcome measure. We have determined that 35
      maternal/fetal participants are required in order to calculate a survival rate of anywhere
      from 20-80%. We plan to study two 35 participant cohorts of EPRA patients, those with EPRA
      from bilateral renal agenesis and those with EPRA from fetal renal failure. We will therefore
      aim for a total of 70 maternal/fetal pairs with EPRA to undergo serial amnioinfusions.
      Additionally we will aim to recruit 30 maternal/fetal pairs with EPRA in the expectant
      management group for a total of 100 participants.

      During the prenatal portion of the trial we plan to collect a small specimen of amniotic
      fluid from participants in the amnioinfusion group during each amnioinfusion. This fluid will
      be assayed for different protein and lipid measures of lung maturity at a research lab at
      Johns Hopkins. Additionally, in both the amnioinfusion group and the expectant management
      group we will study ultrasound, MRI and echocardiogram measures of lung growth. We will
      correlate these biochemical and radiologic markers with survival in order to better
      understand who is likely to respond to amnioinfusions and why that response is occurring. We
      also plan to study several secondary and tertiary outcomes in our surviving EPRA patients.
      These outcomes include survival to discharge from a RAFT center, survival to transplant and
      quality of life measures for both participants and their families.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 18, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 18, 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 18, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All eligible patients will be offered participation in the study. Participants can elect for invasive therapy with amnioinfusions or expectant management.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to successful dialysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth to either successful dialysis or nonsurvival.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of serial saline amnioinfusions to prevent lethal pulmonary hypoplasia in patients with EPRA. Survival or nonsurvival to the endpoint of successful dialysis defined as 15 continuous days of dialysis catheter usage will be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal safety: the rate of maternal adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>These outcomes will be measured at every prenatal visit, after every prenatal procedure, at delivery and 30 days after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of serial amnioinfusions in patients with EPRA. Safety of the infusions will be determined by the rate of maternal adverse events (if any) with infusion. superficial wound infection requiring antibiotics, bleed requiring transfusion, and death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of serial amnioinfusions before preterm premature rupture of membranes or preterm delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Pregnancy</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the feasibility of serial amnioinfusions without rupture of membranes or preterm birth for EPRA pregnancies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth to either successful renal transplant (usually around 2 years of life) or nonsurvival</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the proportion of patients treated with RAFT who successfully receive renal transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life using Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory 4.0 (PedsQL TM) survey</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years of life and then 1, 2 3 and 4 years after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the quality of life of patients that undergo RAFT. The parent proxy score will be used until the child is 5 years of age.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Bilateral Renal Agenesis</condition>
  <condition>Oligohydramnios</condition>
  <condition>Anhydramnios</condition>
  <condition>Potter Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Lung Hypoplasia</condition>
  <condition>Multicystic Dysplastic Kidney</condition>
  <condition>Multicystic Renal Dysplasia, Bilateral</condition>
  <condition>Lower Urinary Tract Obstructive Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Fetal Renal Anomaly</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Serial amnioinfusions with isotonic fluid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo amnioinfusions with isotonic fluid every 1-2 weeks. A spinal needle will be used to perform the infusion. The latest infusions will begin is 26 weeks gestation. Standard postnatal care will occur at a RAFT center.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Expectant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be observed serially by ultrasound, fetal echocardiogram and MRI. Standard postnatal care will occur at a RAFT center.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Serial amnioinfusions with isotonic fluid</intervention_name>
    <description>Amnioinfusions will be performed by an expert in fetal procedures with a 20 or 22 gauge needle using sterile technique and ultrasound guidance. Local anesthetic will be employed. The fluid will consist of warmed isotonic fluid. Infusions may take up to 1 hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Serial amnioinfusions with isotonic fluid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Renal Anhydramnios Fetal Therapy (RAFT)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spinal needle</intervention_name>
    <description>A 20 or 22 gauge spinal needle will be used with sterile technique to access the uterus under ultrasound guidance and to infuse isotonic fluid.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Serial amnioinfusions with isotonic fluid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Obstetrics and gynecology needle</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isotonic fluid</intervention_name>
    <description>Isotonic fluids, including normal saline or lactated ringers solution, will be infused into the uterus through a spinal needle under ultrasound guidance using sterile technique. This fluid will act as replacement amniotic fluid.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Serial amnioinfusions with isotonic fluid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normal saline</other_name>
    <other_name>Lactated ringers solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed anhydramnios before 22 weeks GA for patients with FRF or confirmed diagnosis
             of CoBRA

          -  Eligible for first amnioinfusion before 26 weeks GA

          -  Confirmation that the expectant mother does not wish to undergo termination of the
             pregnancy

          -  Age greater than 18 years of age for expectant mothers

          -  Willingness to be followed and deliver at a RAFT center

          -  Willingness for postnatal care to be performed at a RAFT center until discharge
             Completed consults with Pediatric Nephrology, Neonatology, Transplant Surgery,
             Pediatric surgery, Maternal-Fetal Medicine Specialist, and Licensed Clinical Social
             Worker.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cervix less than 2.5 cm in length

          -  Abnormal Karyotype or Microarray

          -  Other significant congenital anomalies in the fetus

          -  Evidence of chorioamnionitis or abruptio placentae

          -  Evidence of rupture of membranes or chorioamniotic separation

          -  Evidence of preterm labor

          -  Multiple gestation

          -  Severe maternal medical condition in pregnancy.

          -  Maternal depression as assessed by a Beck Depression Inventory score equal to or
             greater than 17 that is refractory to treatment

          -  Technical limitations precluding amnioinfusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant women are the focus of this study</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric B Jelin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric B Jelin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>4432873384</phone>
    <email>ejelin1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jena Miller, MD</last_name>
    <phone>844-JHFETAL</phone>
    <email>jmill260@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yair Blumenfeld, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-724-2221</phone>
      <email>yairb@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stephanie Neves, RN</last_name>
      <phone>650-724-2221</phone>
      <email>sneves@stanforchildrens.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric B Jelin, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/gynecology_obstetrics/specialty_areas/fetal_therapy/</url>
    <description>The Center for Fetal Therapy</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/johns-hopkins-childrens-center/what-we-treat/specialties/fetal-therapy/</url>
    <description>Johns Hopkins Children's Center Fetal Program</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Hare EM, Jelin AC, Miller JL, Ruano R, Atkinson MA, Baschat AA, Jelin EB. Amnioinfusions to Treat Early Onset Anhydramnios Caused by Renal Anomalies: Background and Rationale for the Renal Anhydramnios Fetal Therapy Trial. Fetal Diagn Ther. 2019;45(6):365-372. doi: 10.1159/000497472. Epub 2019 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>30897573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huber C, Shazly SA, Blumenfeld YJ, Jelin E, Ruano R. Update on the Prenatal Diagnosis and Outcomes of Fetal Bilateral Renal Agenesis. Obstet Gynecol Surv. 2019 May;74(5):298-302. doi: 10.1097/OGX.0000000000000670. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31098643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bienstock JL, Birsner ML, Coleman F, Hueppchen NA. Successful in utero intervention for bilateral renal agenesis. Obstet Gynecol. 2014 Aug;124(2 Pt 2 Suppl 1):413-5. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0000000000000339.</citation>
    <PMID>25004316</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Amnioinfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Fetal therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Bilateral Renal Agenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Fetal Renal Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Lower Urinary Tract Obstruction (LUTO)</keyword>
  <keyword>Anhydramnios</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oligohydramnios</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multicystic Dysplastic Kidney</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

