<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02999984</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OTL-101-4</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02999984</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of the Cryopreserved Formulation of OTL-101 in Subjects With ADA-SCID</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety of Cryopreserved Formulation of Autologous CD34+ Hematopoietic Stem Cells Transduced Ex Vivo With EFS Lentiviral Vector Encoding for Human ADA Gene in Subjects With Severe Combined Immunodeficiency Due to ADA Deficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Orchard Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>California Institute for Regenerative Medicine (CIRM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Orchard Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, non-randomized, single-cohort, longitudinal, single-center, clinical
      study designed to assess the efficacy and safety of a cryopreserved formulation of OTL-101
      (autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells transduced ex vivo with EFS (Elongation
      Factor 1α Short form) Lentiviral Vector (LV) encoding for the human ADA gene) administered to
      ADA-SCID subjects between the ages of 30 days and 17 years of age, who are not eligible for
      an Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) matched sibling/family donor and meeting the
      inclusion/exclusion criteria. The OTL-101 product is infused after a minimal interval of at
      least 24 hours following the completion of reduced intensity conditioning. For subjects who
      successfully receive the OTL-101 product, pegademase bovine (PEG-ADA) Enzyme Replacement
      Therapy (ERT) is discontinued at Day+30 (-3/+15) after the transplant. After their discharge
      from hospital, the subjects will be seen at regular intervals to review their history,
      perform examinations and draw blood samples to assess immunity and safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 26, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 11, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of subjects with treatment success post OTL-101 infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as meeting or exceeding the threshold for all three of the following parameters:
Erythrocyte ADA enzyme activity above baseline/pre-treatment level (&gt;0 Units),
Evidence of immune reconstitution as measured by absolute number of CD3 cells ≥200/mm3),
Detectable gene-marked granulocytes as measured by differential polymerase chain reaction (dPCR)/ quantitative PCR (qPCR) (≥1/10,000 cells).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the proportion of subjects alive.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival is defined as the proportion of subjects alive with no &quot;event&quot;, an &quot;event&quot; being the resumption of PEG-ADA ERT or the need for a rescue allogenic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant (HSCT), or death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the proportion of subjects alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival is defined as the proportion of subjects alive with no &quot;event&quot;, an &quot;event&quot; being the resumption of PEG-ADA ERT or the need for a rescue allogenic HSCT, or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Combined Immunodeficiency Due to ADA Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gene Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infusion of autologous cryopreserved EFS-ADA LV CD34+ cells</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Infusion of autologous cryopreserved EFS-ADA LV CD34+ cells (OTL-101)</intervention_name>
    <description>autologous cryopreserved EFS-ADA LV CD34+ cells (OTL-101) are infused intravenously</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gene Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OTL-101</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>Busulfan is used for non-myoablative conditioning</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gene Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PEG-ADA ERT</intervention_name>
    <description>PEG-ADA ERT is discontinued at Day +30 (-3/+15 days) after successful engraftment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gene Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provision of written informed consent prior to any study related procedures. In this
             study consent must be provided by the parents/legal guardians and, where applicable
             according to local laws, a signed assent from the child,

          2. Subjects ≥30 days and &lt;18 years of age,

          3. With a diagnosis of ADA-SCID based on:

             Evidence of ADA deficiency, defined as:

             i. Decreased ADA enzymatic activity in erythrocytes, leukocytes, skin fibroblasts, or
             in cultured fetal cells to levels consistent with ADA-SCID as determined by the
             reference laboratory, or ii. Identified mutations in ADA alleles consistent with a
             severe reduction in ADA activity,

             Evidence of ADA-SCID based on either:

             i. Family history of a first order relative with ADA deficiency and clinical and
             laboratory evidence of severe immunologic deficiency, or ii. Evidence of severe
             immunologic deficiency in subjects prior to the institution of immune restorative
             therapy, based on

               -  Lymphopenia (absolute lymphocyte count (ALC) &lt;400 cells/µL) OR absence or low
                  number of T cells (absolute CD3+ count &lt; 300 cells/µL), or

               -  Severely decreased T lymphocyte blastogenic responses to phytohemagglutinin
                  (either &lt;10% of lower limit of normal controls for the diagnostic laboratory, or
                  &lt;10% of the response of the normal control of the day, or stimulation index &lt;10),
                  or

               -  Identification of SCID by neonatal screening revealing low T cell Receptor
                  Excision Circle (TREC) levels.

          4. Ineligible for matched family allogeneic Bone Marrow (BM) transplantation, defined as
             the absence of a medically eligible HLA-identical sibling or family donor, with normal
             immune function, who could serve as an allogeneic bone marrow donor.

          5. Females of child-bearing age will be required to provide a negative pregnancy test 30
             days prior to Visit 2.

          6. Subjects and their parents/legal guardians must be willing and able to comply with
             study restrictions and to remain at the clinic for the required duration during the
             study period and willing to return to the clinic for the follow up evaluation as
             specified in the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Ineligible for autologous HSCT as per clinical site criteria.

          2. Other conditions which in the opinion of the Principal Investigator and/or Co
             Investigators, contraindicate the harvest of bone marrow, the administration of
             Busulfan and the infusion of transduced cells, or which indicate an inability of the
             subject or subject's parent/legal guardian to comply with the protocol.

          3. Hematologic abnormality, defined as:

               -  Anemia (Hb &lt;8.0 g/dl).

               -  Neutropenia (ANC &lt;500/mm3). Note: ANC &lt;500 with absence of myelodysplastic
                  syndrome on bone marrow aspirate and biopsy and normal marrow cytogenetics are
                  acceptable for eligibility.

               -  Thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt;50,000/mm3, at any age).

               -  Prothrombin time or international normalized ratio (INR) and partial
                  thromboplastin time (PTT) &gt;2 x upper limit of normal (ULN) (subjects with a
                  correctable deficiency controlled on medication will not be excluded).

               -  Cytogenetic abnormalities on peripheral blood or bone marrow or amniotic fluid
                  (if available).

               -  Prior allogeneic HSCT with cytoreductive conditioning.

          4. Pulmonary abnormality, defined as:

               -  Resting O2 saturation by pulse oximetry &lt;90% on room air.

               -  Chest X-ray indicating active or progressive pulmonary disease. Note: Chest X ray
                  indicating residual signs of treated pneumonitis is acceptable for eligibility.

          5. Cardiac abnormality, defined as:

               -  Abnormal ECG indicating cardiac pathology.

               -  Uncorrected congenital cardiac malformation with clinical symptoms.

               -  Active cardiac disease, including clinical evidence of congestive heart failure,
                  cyanosis, hypotension.

               -  Poor cardiac function as evidenced by left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;40% on
                  echocardiogram.

          6. Neurologic abnormality, defined as:

               -  Significant neurologic abnormality revealed by examination.

               -  Uncontrolled seizure disorder.

          7. Renal abnormality, defined as:

               -  Renal insufficiency: serum creatinine ≥1.2 mg/dl (106 µmol/L), or ≥3+
                  proteinuria.

               -  Abnormal serum sodium, potassium, calcium, magnesium or phosphate levels at &gt;2 x
                  ULN.

          8. Hepatic/gastrointestinal abnormality, defined as:

               -  Serum transaminases &gt;5 x ULN.

               -  Serum bilirubin &gt;2 x ULN.

               -  Serum glucose &gt;1.5 x ULN.

          9. Oncologic disease, defined as:

               -  Evidence of active malignant disease other than dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans
                  (DFSP).

               -  Evidence of DFSP expected to require anti-neoplastic therapy within the 5 years
                  following the infusion of genetically corrected cells (if anti-neoplastic therapy
                  has been completed, a subject with a history of DFSP can be included).

               -  Evidence of DFSP expected to be life limiting within the 5 years following the
                  infusion of genetically corrected cells.

         10. Known sensitivity to Busulfan.

         11. Confirmation of an infectious disease by deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) PCR positive at
             time of screening assessment for the following:

               -  HIV-1,

               -  Hepatitis B,

               -  Parvovirus B19.

         12. The subject is pregnant or has a major congenital anomaly.

         13. Is likely to require treatment during the study with drugs that are not permitted by
             the study protocol.

         14. The subject has previously received another form of gene therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald B. Kohn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3944341/</url>
    <description>Pre-clinical activity and safety data</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carbonaro DA, Zhang L, Jin X, Montiel-Equihua C, Geiger S, Carmo M, Cooper A, Fairbanks L, Kaufman ML, Sebire NJ, Hollis RP, Blundell MP, Senadheera S, Fu PY, Sahaghian A, Chan RY, Wang X, Cornetta K, Thrasher AJ, Kohn DB, Gaspar HB. Preclinical demonstration of lentiviral vector-mediated correction of immunological and metabolic abnormalities in models of adenosine deaminase deficiency. Mol Ther. 2014 Mar;22(3):607-622. doi: 10.1038/mt.2013.265. Epub 2013 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24256635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>January 24, 2020</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2020</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gene therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>hematopoietic and progenitor cells</keyword>
  <keyword>lentiviral vector</keyword>
  <keyword>ADA-SCID</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Severe Combined Immunodeficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

