<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02995733</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016P001839</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02995733</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Empowered Strategy to Reduce Asthma Morbidity in Highly Impacted Populations; PeRson EmPowered Asthma RElief</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREPARE</acronym>
  <official_title>Patient Empowered Strategy to Reduce Asthma Morbidity in Highly Impacted Populations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Academy of Family Physicians</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Asthma imposes a significant burden in the US in terms of morbidity, costs to society,
      individual suffering, loss of productivity and mortality. African Americans (AA) and
      Hispanic/Latinos (H/L) bear a disproportionate share of that morbidity. Despite national
      guidelines for asthma treatment, the gap between these groups and whites has been stable or
      widening. The need for pragmatic research to address the continuing burden is widely
      recognized. Patients use asthma reliever inhalers to provide immediate relief of symptoms.
      Controller inhalers (inhaled corticosteroids (ICS)) are intended to be used regularly to
      prevent symptoms and attacks. Guidelines suggest that they be used daily, on a fixed basis,
      in all but the mildest asthma. However, adherence by patients and implementation of
      evidence-based guideline recommendations by clinicians has been poor. Gap analysis suggests
      that it is difficult to improve adherence to the current recommendations without complex and
      resource-intensive interventions. Studies have examined symptom-activated use of ICS
      triggered by use of a reliever medication. The Investigators call this approach PARTICS -
      Patient Activated Reliever-Triggered Inhaled CorticoSteroid. Explanatory, non-real world
      studies suggest that PARTICS can produce up to 50% reductions in asthma attacks compared with
      usual care, while reducing ICS use by half or more. These studies have been performed in
      pre-selected populations, which represent less than 5% of asthma patients. The previous
      studies have been done with repeated education and adherence checks in both the intervention
      and control arms.

      The investigators have consulted with AA and H/L patients, health care providers, leaders of
      professional societies, advocacy groups, health policy leaders, pharmacists, and
      pharmaceutical manufacturers. All groups have indicated that asthma decision making would be
      changed if we demonstrated that implementing PARTICS improves important asthma outcomes such
      as reducing exacerbations. The Investigators have designed a study with the stakeholders to
      determine whether PARTICS can improve outcomes that are important to patients when
      superimposed on a background provider-educated standard of care through the Asthma IQ system.
      The Investigators propose a study entitled PREPARE: Patient Empowered Strategy to Reduce
      Asthma Morbidity in Highly Impacted Populations. The Investigators aim to determine whether
      PARTICS can reduce asthma morbidity in AA and H/L.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Asthma imposes a significant burden on the US population in terms of morbidity, costs to
      society, individual suffering, loss of productivity and mortality. African Americans (AA) and
      Hispanic/Latinos (H/L) bear a disproportionate share of that morbidity. Despite introduction
      of national guidelines for asthma treatment, the gap between these groups and whites has been
      stable or widening. The need for pragmatic research to address the continuing burden is
      widely recognized. Patients use asthma reliever inhalers to provide immediate relief of
      symptoms. Controller inhalers (inhaled corticosteroids (ICS)) are intended to be used
      regularly to prevent symptoms and attacks. Guidelines suggest that they be used daily, on a
      fixed basis, in all but the mildest asthma. However, adherence by patients and implementation
      of evidence-based guideline recommendations by clinicians has been poor. Gap analysis
      suggests that it is difficult to improve adherence to the current recommendations without
      complex and resource-intensive interventions.

      Studies have examined symptom-activated use of ICS triggered by use of a reliever medication.
      We call this approach PARTICS - Patient Activated Reliever-Triggered Inhaled CorticoSteroid.
      Explanatory, non-real world studies suggest that PARTICS can produce up to 50% reductions in
      asthma attacks compared with usual care, while reducing ICS use by half or more. However,
      these studies have been performed in pre- selected populations, which represent less than 5%
      of patients with asthma. They have been done with repeated education and adherence checks in
      both the intervention and control arms.

      The investigators have consulted with AA and H/L patients, health care providers, leaders of
      professional societies, advocacy groups, health policy leaders, pharmacists, and
      pharmaceutical manufacturers. All groups have indicated that asthma decision making would be
      changed if it was demonstrated that implementing PARTICS improves important asthma outcomes
      such as reducing rates of exacerbations. Together with our partners and stakeholders, the
      investigators have designed a study to determine whether PARTICS can improve outcomes that
      are important to patients when superimposed on a background provider-educated standard care
      through the Asthma IQ system. The investigators therefore propose a study entitled PREPARE:
      Patient Empowered Strategy to Reduce Asthma Morbidity in Highly Impacted Populations. The aim
      is to determine whether a PARTICS strategy can reduce asthma morbidity in AA and H/L. The
      primary outcome will be asthma exacerbations which have been shown to be important to patient
      and healthcare stakeholders. The secondary outcomes will include additional outcomes
      important to patients (i.e. days lost from work or school, asthma control, &amp; asthma quality
      of life). The investigators have broad input and involvement from multiple stakeholder groups
      in study design, implementation, and commitments for dissemination. AA and H/L patients and
      their advocates have been involved and will continue to play a central role in all phases of
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 27, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Asthma Exacerbations per year</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly through study completion an average of 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Our primary outcome, the rate of asthma exacerbations per year, is defined as the number of exacerbations, emergency room visits, or hospitalizations requiring oral or parenteral corticosteroids, per patient per year</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>days lost from work or school/ days unable to carry out usual activities due to asthma</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly through study completion an average of 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as days not able to work or go to school because of asthma symptoms OR days not able to carry out usual activities due to asthma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preference Based Quality of Life: Asthma Symptom Utility Index (ASUI)</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly through study completion an average of 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>The ideal outcome measure for any comparative effectiveness analysis captures the risks and benefits for each of the interventions from the patient's point of view. The use of a preference-based instrument, the Asthma Symptom Utility Index (ASUI), captures this important information (Revicki 1998</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma Control: Asthma Control Test (ACT) score</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly through study completion an average of 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Asthma control represents the degree to which impairment (impact of asthma on patient's daily life) is minimized and the goals of therapy are met.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PARTICS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>addition of PARTICS strategy - Patient Activated Reliever-Triggered Inhaled CorticoSteroid (PARTICS) using QVAR . Patient will use inhaled corticosteroid at time of rescue inhaler use</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Provider-enhanced usual care arm; no change in asthma management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PARTICS using QVAR</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient takes inhaled corticosteroid at the time of rescue inhaler use</description>
    <arm_group_label>PARTICS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Patient Activated Reliever-Triggered Inhaled CorticoSteroid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Black or Hispanic based on self-identification (Hispanic if identify as both)

          -  Male and female, ages 18-75 years

          -  Ability to provide informed consent

          -  Clinical history consistent with asthma for &gt; 1 year.

          -  Prescribed ICS as daily maintenance therapy

          -  Participant must also have an ACT score of 19 or less, or a history of one or more
             exacerbations in the past year that required patient report of systemic corticosteroid
             use.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Life expectancy less than one year

          -  Known allergy to the ICS inhaler used in the study

          -  Having COPD or other chronic lung disease other than asthma; with the exception of the
             following:

               -  Dx of COPD in a never smoker without any other lung disease or any other disease
                  that might cause airway obstruction such as: Cystic Fibrosis, Connective Tissue
                  Disease, premature birth, organ transplantation, bronchiectasis, sarcoid, and
                  obliterative bronchiolitis

               -  Dx of COPD in former smoker with normal PFTs done after the person quit smoking

               -  Dx of COPD in current smoker with normal PFTs done in past 24 months

               -  Dx of COPD IN CURRENT OR FORMER SMOKER with obstruction on PFTs: normal diffusing
                  capacity in past 24 months and demonstrated reversibility of 12% or more at any
                  time

          -  Regular systemic corticosteroid use daily or every other day for any reason—including
             asthma or other medical reasons

          -  Use of systemic corticosteroid, or visit to the doctor's office, emergency department
             (ED) or urgent care, or overnight hospitalization for an asthma exacerbation in the
             past month (can wait and re-check eligibility after one month)

          -  Use of biologics (injections or infusion medicines): with the exception of the
             following:

               -  the patient has been on a stable dose of a biologic for at least 6 months and,

               -  must have had an exacerbation at least 2 months after starting on a biologic to
                  be considered eligible OR

               -  must have a current ACT score &lt;=19 to be considered eligible.

          -  Bronchial thermoplasty less than 6 months ago (can re-check eligibility 6 months after
             procedure)

          -  Another family member living in the same household already enrolled in study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elliot Israel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nancy Maher, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>857-307-3892</phone>
    <email>NMAHER@BWH.HARVARD.EDU</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elliot Israel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-8110</phone>
    <email>eisrael@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lynn Fukushima</last_name>
      <phone>323-409-5383</phone>
      <email>Lynn.Fukushima@med.usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ahmet Baydur, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Denver Health and Hospital Authority</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hilde Heyn</last_name>
      <phone>303-602-4859</phone>
      <email>hilde.heyn@dhha.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laura Hurley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lois Ravage</last_name>
      <phone>203-499-9260</phone>
      <email>lois.ravage-mass@yale.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Geoffrey Chupp, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ben Rooks</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-8025</phone>
      <email>brooks@ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ku-Lang Chang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Rebolledo</last_name>
      <email>PRebolledo@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rafael Calderon Candelario, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grace Medical Home</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32827</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monica D'Apice</last_name>
      <phone>407-936-2785</phone>
      <phone_ext>2061</phone_ext>
      <email>mdapice@gracemedicalhome.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Magdalena Pasarica, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Central Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32827</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zinnia Valdes</last_name>
      <phone>407-823-3702</phone>
      <email>Zinnia.Valdes@ucf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Magdalena Pasarica, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33613</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tiffani Kaage</last_name>
      <phone>813-631-4024</phone>
      <phone_ext>200</phone_ext>
      <email>tiffanik@health.usf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Casale, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois- Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jasmin Sanchez</last_name>
      <phone>608-438-6830</phone>
      <email>jsanch59@uic.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Stranges, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baystate Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01199</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Romain</last_name>
      <phone>413-794-4889</phone>
      <email>sarah.romain@baystatehealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sherell Thornton-Thompson</last_name>
      <email>Sherell.Thornton-Thompson@baystatehealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victor Pinto Plata, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mt. Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Walter Ramos</last_name>
      <email>walter.ramos@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paula Busse, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>25799</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atrium Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeremy Thomas</last_name>
      <email>Jeremy.Thomas@atriumhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hazel Tapp, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MetroHealth</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MaryJo Day</last_name>
      <phone>216-778-8456</phone>
      <email>mday@metrohealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Cindy Newman</last_name>
      <email>cnewman@metrohealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Kaelber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Temple University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sylvia Johnson</last_name>
      <phone>215-707-4679</phone>
      <email>sylvia.johnson@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kartik Shenoy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ponce Health Sciences University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ponce</city>
        <zip>00717</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Puerto Rico</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Juan</city>
        <zip>00926</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bonnie Telon</last_name>
      <phone>787-379-5490</phone>
      <email>bonnie.telon@upr.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sylvette Nazario, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Puerto Rico</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elliot Israel, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>African Americans</keyword>
  <keyword>Hispanics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 5, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/33/NCT02995733/Prot_SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

