<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03735641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KY20182035-C-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03735641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Postoperative Effect of Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap to Repair the Facial-Cervical Scars</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Postoperative Effect of Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap to Repair the Facial-Cervical Scars</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xijing Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xijing Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effect of Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap on facial-cervical
      scars repair, including flap sensation, L*a*b* value,flap's elasticity,melanin content,
      hemoglobin content, and evaluation of scar and patient, doctor, and third-party satisfaction
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The scars of face and neck caused by burning often show as large faciocervical scar.Important
      areas of current focus in face and neck scars management are functional outcomes and quality
      of patient life.The deltopectoral flap was first described by Bakamjian in 1965, and was
      recognized as one of the first choices for facial reconstruction, as the texture, color of
      the flap skin is similar to the facial skin. Since the tissue expansion technique was used to
      the flap, the flap became one of the best choices for the facial defect
      reconstruction,especially for Asian patients. It can be used with pedicled or free
      transferred.Complications at the donor or recipient site have been widely reported and often
      include dilator exposure,the flap blood circulation disorder and delayed healing, but the
      pattern of sensory recovery ,flap's elasticitycolor change have been studied less well.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Flap Color（the value of L*a*b*）</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>The Antera 3D is a camera for image acquisition and analysis of the skin.Every color is expressed in a three-dimensional coordinate system in terms of three units. L* expresses the luminance and gives the relative brightness of the color ranging from total black (L* ¼ 0) to total white (L* ¼ 100).The terms a* and b* are coordinates of chromaticity, with a* representing the balance between green (negative values)and red (positive values) and b* representing the balance between blue (negative values) and yellow (positive values)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>Test tubes were equilibrated in water at 0◦C (cold) or 45-50 ◦C (warm) and applied for 5 s.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Light Touch</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>The tactile sensation of the flap after surgery is assessed by Semmes-Weinstein monofilaments and the change in tactile sense is detected at least 3 months after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Two-point Discrimination（2PD）</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>Two-point Discrimination of the flap after surgery was assessed by Touch-Test discriminator, and changes in 2PD were detected at least 3 months after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Flap Elasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>The elasticity of the flap after surgery was assessed by CK-MC960 and the change in elasticity was measured at least 3 months after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Melanin Content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>The melanin content of the flap after surgery was evaluated by Antera 3D, and the change of melanin was detected at least 3 months after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin Content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>The hemoglobin content of the flap after surgery was evaluated by Antera 3D, and the change of melanin was detected at least 3 months after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month later</time_frame>
    <description>At least 3 months after the patient's surgery, use a self-made satisfaction questionnaire to obtain patient satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scar scaling</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month later</time_frame>
    <description>The scar around the flap after surgery was evaluated by Patient and Observer Scar Assessment and the scar was assessed at least 6 months after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgical Flaps</condition>
  <condition>Skin Pigmentation</condition>
  <condition>Sensory Defect</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>postoperative</arm_group_label>
    <description>Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap is a type of surgical flap that has been cut away from surrounding areas for transplantation.The postoperative patients are studied . Tested sensory recovery,skin color and Skin elasticity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap</intervention_name>
    <description>Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap is a type of surgical flap</description>
    <arm_group_label>postoperative</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who underwent Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap to repair facial-cervical scars
        in 2006 -2018
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who underwent Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap to repair facial-cervical
             scars in 2006 -2018.

          2. In compliance with ethical requirements, patients were voluntarily tested and signed
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Peripheral neuropathy

          2. Serious aphasia or cognitive impairment, and first-degree relatives can not get in
             touch.

          3. Can not follow up

          4. Allergic constitution

          5. Connective tissue disease

          6. Hormone or chemotherapy drugs are being used.

          7. Diabetes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital, the Air Force Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xian</city>
        <state>Shaanxi</state>
        <zip>710000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ensat F, Greindl M, Skreiner A, Schubert H, Hladik M, Stuflesser A, Spies M, Wechselberger G. Colorimetric examination of typical free flap donor sites and comparison to recipient sites in the extremities. J Reconstr Microsurg. 2013 Jan;29(1):21-6. doi: 10.1055/s-0032-1326734. Epub 2012 Oct 23.</citation>
    <PMID>23093467</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Netscher D, Armenta AH, Meade RA, Alford EL. Sensory recovery of innervated and non-innervated radial forearm free flaps: functional implications. J Reconstr Microsurg. 2000 Apr;16(3):179-85.</citation>
    <PMID>10803620</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ma X, Li Y, Li W, Liu C, Peng P, Song B, Xia W, Yi C, Lu K, Su Y. Reconstruction of Large Postburn Facial-Scalp Scars by Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap and Random Scalp Flap: Technique Improvements to Enlarge the Reconstructive Territory. J Craniofac Surg. 2017 Sep;28(6):1526-1530. doi: 10.1097/SCS.0000000000003902.</citation>
    <PMID>28749842</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ma X, Li Y, Li W, Liu C, Liu H, Xue P, Cui J. Reconstruction of Facial-Cervical Scars With Pedicled Expanded Deltopectoral Flap. J Craniofac Surg. 2017 Sep;28(6):1554-1558. doi: 10.1097/SCS.0000000000003901.</citation>
    <PMID>28708657</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abrar Y, Muntaha ST, Khan K, Hameed U. Successful Use of Deltopectoral Flap in Reconstruction of Defect Caused by Squamous Cell Carcinoma. J Coll Physicians Surg Pak. 2018 Jun;28(6):S125-S127. doi: 10.29271/jcpsp.2018.06.S125.</citation>
    <PMID>29866245</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ding J, Li Y, Li W, Liu C, Liu H, Cui J, Su Y, Ma X. Use of expanded deltopectoral skin flaps for facial reconstruction after sizeable benign tumor resections. Am J Transl Res. 2018 Jul 15;10(7):2158-2163. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30093952</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Okochi M, Okochi H, Sakaba T, Ueda K. The Reconstruction of the Donor Site of DP Flap Using Thoracodorsal Artery Perforator Flap. Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open. 2017 Oct 23;5(10):e1521. doi: 10.1097/GOX.0000000000001521. eCollection 2017 Oct.</citation>
    <PMID>29184736</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hwang K. The Origins of Deltopectoral Flaps and the Pectoralis Major Myocutaneous Flap. J Craniofac Surg. 2016 Oct;27(7):1845-1848. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27763977</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ibrahim A, Atiyeh B, Karami R, Adelman DM, Papazian NJ. The Deltopectoral Flap Revisited: The Internal Mammary Artery Perforator Flap. J Craniofac Surg. 2016 Mar;27(2):e189-92. doi: 10.1097/SCS.0000000000002445.</citation>
    <PMID>26854779</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Murono S, Ishikawa E, Nakanishi Y, Endo K, Kondo S, Wakisaka N, Yoshizaki T. Closure of tracheoesophageal fistula with prefabricated deltopectoral flap. Asian J Surg. 2016 Oct;39(4):243-6. doi: 10.1016/j.asjsur.2014.01.003. Epub 2014 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24674898</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aldelaimi TN, Khalil AA. Reconstruction of Facial Defect Using Deltopectoral Flap. J Craniofac Surg. 2015 Nov;26(8):e786-8. doi: 10.1097/SCS.0000000000002056.</citation>
    <PMID>26595007</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moreno-Sánchez M, González-García R, Ruiz-Laza L, Manzano Solo de Zaldívar D, Moreno-García C, Monje F. Closure of the Radial Forearm Free Flap Donor Site Using the Combined Local Triangular Full-Thickness Skin Graft. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2016 Jan;74(1):204-11. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2015.08.003. Epub 2015 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26342949</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kesting MR, MacIver C, Wales CJ, Wolff KD, Nobis CP, Rohleder NH. Surface-optimized free flaps for complex facial defects after skin cancer. J Craniomaxillofac Surg. 2015 Nov;43(9):1792-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jcms.2015.08.010. Epub 2015 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26355025</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yangqun L, Yong T, Wen C, Zhe Y, Muxin Z, Lisi X, Chunmei H, Yuanyuan L, Ning M, Jun F, Weixin W. [Reconstruction of facial soft tissue defects with pedicled expanded flaps]. Zhonghua Zheng Xing Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2014 Sep;30(5):326-9. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>25522480</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Beugels J, Cornelissen AJM, Spiegel AJ, Heuts EM, Piatkowski A, van der Hulst RRWJ, Tuinder SMH. Sensory recovery of the breast after innervated and non-innervated autologous breast reconstructions: A systematic review. J Plast Reconstr Aesthet Surg. 2017 Sep;70(9):1229-1241. doi: 10.1016/j.bjps.2017.05.001. Epub 2017 May 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28687258</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Germann G, Rudolf KD, Levin SL, Hrabowski M. Fingertip and Thumb Tip Wounds: Changing Algorithms for Sensation, Aesthetics, and Function. J Hand Surg Am. 2017 Apr;42(4):274-284. doi: 10.1016/j.jhsa.2017.01.022. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28372640</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhao G, Wang B, Zhang W, Tang P, Chen C. Sensory reconstruction in different regions of the digits: A review of 151 cases. Injury. 2016 Oct;47(10):2269-2275. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2016.07.035. Epub 2016 Jul 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27480911</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cao G, Zheng D, Sun F, Shou K. [RECONSTRUCTION OF AVULSED INJURIES OF HEEL WITH A SENSORY PREFABRICATED FLAP]. Zhongguo Xiu Fu Chong Jian Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2015 Feb;29(2):198-201. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>26455150</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Xie A, Zhang J, Lu A, Yuan J, Wang B, Yang H, Zhang J, Wang H. [Effectiveness of retrograde island neurocutaneous flap pedicled with lateral antebrachial cutaneous nerve in treatment of hand defect]. Zhongguo Xiu Fu Chong Jian Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2014 Dec;28(12):1498-501. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>25826894</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lu S, Chai Y. [Clinical application of sural fasciomyocutaneous perforator flap in repair of soft tissue defect in weight-bearing area of foot]. Zhongguo Xiu Fu Chong Jian Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2014 Dec;28(12):1494-7. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>25826893</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Trevatt AE, Filobbos G, Ul Haq A, Khan U. Long-term sensation in the medial plantar flap: a two-centre study. Foot Ankle Surg. 2014 Sep;20(3):166-9. doi: 10.1016/j.fas.2014.03.001. Epub 2014 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25103702</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Expanded Pedicled Deltopectoral Flap</keyword>
  <keyword>skin color</keyword>
  <keyword>Sensory recovery</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

