<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03735277</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BHI17-IS-A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03735277</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Safety and Efficacy of Hemacord HPC, Cord Blood in Subjects With Acute Ischemic Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Safety and Efficacy of HPC, Cord Blood</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BHI Therapeutic Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BHI Therapeutic Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase one study investigating the safety and efficacy profile of allogeneic cord
      blood hematopoietic progenitor cells (HPC, Cord Blood), when administered by intravenous
      infusion and intrathecal injection, in subjects who have sustained an acute ischemic stroke
      within the past 9 days. Treatment period consisting of 3 sessions of both intravenous
      infusion and intrathecal injection (or intravenous infusion in conjunction with mannitol for
      subjects unable to tolerate intrathecal injection). Follow-up phone calls for adverse event
      (AE) assessment will be conducted at 1 week, 1 month, and 2 months after the first
      intravenous/intrathecal treatment. A follow up clinic visit at 3 months, 6 months and 12
      months will include a neurological exam, MRI, and clinical laboratory tests/urinalysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety of HPC, Cord Blood (administered
      via intravenous infusion and intrathecal injection, or intravenous infusion in conjunction
      with mannitol for subjects unable to tolerate intrathecal injection) in subjects with acute
      ischemic stroke. The secondary objective is to evaluate the efficacy of HPC, Cord Blood (as
      assessed by changes in neurological tests and cerebral infarct volume as measured by
      diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)) in subjects with acute ischemic stroke.

      This is a prospective, open-label, single-center, exploratory clinical study in subjects ≥ 18
      years of age who have sustained a recent ischemic stroke. A total of 10 subjects will be
      enrolled. Subjects will be given a series of baseline neurological assessments, blood tests,
      and MRI.

      All subjects will be administered only ABO- and Rh-matched units of HPC, Cord Blood. Subjects
      will not be matched for human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-typing. For each administration of HPC,
      cord blood, the total dose (2.5 × 10^7 cells/kg; 150 × 10^7 cells) will be split for
      intrathecal injection followed immediately by intravenous infusion. HPC, Cord Blood will be
      administered via intravenous infusion and intrathecal injection, in subjects who have
      sustained an acute ischemic stroke within the past 9 days. Intravenous infusion in
      conjunction with mannitol will be used in instances where a subject is unable to tolerate
      intrathecal administration. Treatment period consisting of 3 sessions, timed 5 to 12 days
      apart. Subjects will be monitored for 6 hours post-infusion, and follow up will occur 24
      hours after each therapy session. Follow-up phone calls for adverse event (AE) assessment
      will be conducted at 1 week, 1 month, and 2 months after the first intravenous/intrathecal
      treatment. A follow up clinic visit at 2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, and 12 months after the
      first intravenous/intrathecal treatment will include a neurological exam, MRI, and clinical
      laboratory tests/urinalysis.

      Risks of cord blood infusion include infusion-related reactions such as anaphylaxis,
      urticaria, dyspnea, hypoxia, cough, wheezing, bronchospasm, nausea, vomiting, hives, fever,
      hypertension, hypotension, bradycardia, tachycardia, rigors, chills, infection, and
      hemoglobinuria. Less likely, long-term risks include transmission of infection or Graft vs
      Host Disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects experiencing any study related Adverse Event (AE) (including clinical laboratory tests, vital signs, 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), and physical examination findings) during the 12-month follow-up period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft Versus Host Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects experiencing Graft Versus Host Disease (GVHD) at 12-month follow-up period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale from baseline to 3 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale from baseline to 6 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale from baseline to 12 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in modified Rankin Score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in modified Rankin Score from baseline to 3 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in modified Rankin Score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in modified Rankin Score from baseline to 6 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in modified Rankin Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in modified Rankin Score from baseline to 12 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in Barthel Index score from baseline to 3 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in Barthel Index score from baseline to 6 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change in Barthel Index score from baseline to 12 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Infarct Volumes measured by Magnetic Resonance Imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Describe changes in infarct volumes from baseline to 3 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Infarct Volumes measured by Magnetic Resonance Imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Describe changes in infarct volumes from baseline to 6 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Infarct Volumes measured by Magnetic Resonance Imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Describe changes in infarct volumes from baseline to 12 months post-administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HPC, Cord Blood</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HPC, Cord Blood is supplied as a cryopreserved cell suspension in a sealed bag containing a minimum of 5 × 10^8 total nucleated cells with a minimum of 1.25 × 10^6 viable CD34+ cells in a volume of 25 milliliters.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HPC, Cord Blood</intervention_name>
    <description>HPC, Cord Blood is supplied as a cryopreserved cell suspension in a sealed bag containing a minimum of 5 × 10^8 total nucleated cells with a minimum of 1.25 × 10^6 viable CD34+ cells in a volume of 25 milliliters. The exact precryopreservation nucleated cell content is provided on the container label and accompanying records.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HPC, Cord Blood</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Allogeneic umbilical cord blood, hematopoietic stem cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects are eligible for the study if all of the following criteria are met:

          -  Subject is ≥ 18 years old

          -  Has had a recent (within the past 9 days), acute, cortical, hemispheric, ischemic
             stroke in the MCA distribution without a midline shift as detected by MRI as a
             diffusion-weighted image (DWI) abnormality

          -  Has a persistent neurological deficit (NIHSS ≥ 7) at the time of enrollment with no
             more than a 4-point increase (worsening of score) from the screening baseline score
             compared to NIHSS baseline score at 24 hours prior to infusion.

          -  A platelet count &gt; 100,000/µL, hemoglobin &gt; 8 g/dL, and white blood cell count (WBC) &gt;
             2500/µL

          -  Subjects who received tPA or underwent mechanical reperfusion may be included in the
             study

          -  Is able to provide consent to study or consent is obtained from the subject's legally
             authorized representative

          -  Subjects of childbearing potential must practice effective contraception during the
             study, and be willing to continue contraception for at least 6 months after
             intervention so that, in the opinion of the investigator, they will not become
             pregnant during the course of the study

          -  Is a good candidate for the study, in the opinion of the investigator

          -  Agrees to participate in follow-up visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects are excluded from the study if any of the following criteria are met:

        Medical Conditions

          -  Has a medical history of neurological or orthopedic pathology with a deficit as a
             consequence that results in an mRS &gt; 1 before stroke or has a pre-existing cognitive
             deficit

          -  Has clinically significant and/or symptomatic hemorrhage associated with stroke

          -  Has new intracranial hemorrhage, edema, or mass effect that may place the subject at
             increased risk for secondary deterioration when assessed prior to infusion

          -  Has hypotension as defined as the need for intravenous pressor support of systolic
             blood pressure &lt; 90 mm Hg

          -  Has isolated brain stem stroke

          -  Has pure lacunar stroke

          -  Requires mechanical ventilation

          -  Requires a craniotomy

          -  Has a serious psychiatric or neurological disease that could alter evaluation on
             functional or cognitive scales

          -  Has an active systemic infection or is human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive or
             hepatitis C positive

          -  Has had an active malignancy within 3 years prior to the start of screening excluding
             skin cancers other than melanoma

          -  Has known coagulopathy such as Factor V Leyden, antiphospholipid syndrome (APS),
             Protein C, Protein S deficiency, sickle cell, anticardiolipin antibody, or
             phospholipid syndrome

          -  Has any concurrent illness or condition that in the opinion of the investigator might
             interfere with treatment or evaluation of safety

          -  Has a life expectancy &lt; 6 months

          -  Has current or recent history of alcohol or drug abuse, or stroke associated with drug
             abuse

          -  Pregnant as documented by urine or blood test

          -  Renal insufficiency with estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt; 60 mL/min/1.73
             m2

          -  Hepatic insufficiency (bilirubin &gt; 2.5 mg/dL or transaminases &gt; 3 × the upper limit of
             normal). Subjects with Gilbert's syndrome are eligible for study enrollment if other
             liver function tests are normal, regardless of bilirubin level

          -  Uncontrolled or poorly controlled type 1 or type 2 diabetes with HbA1c &gt; 7%

          -  Has a history of impaired hemostasis or has a prothrombin time &gt; 14
             seconds/international normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.3 second and activated partial
             thromboplastin time (aPTT) of &gt; 70 seconds.

          -  Has a severe persistent neurological deficit (NIHSS &gt; 24) at the time of enrollment or
             24 hours prior to infusion.

          -  Has New York Heart Association Class III or IV congestive heart failure.

        Concomitant or Prior Therapies

          -  Subjects currently receiving immunosuppressant drugs

          -  Clinical signs and symptoms of infection requiring antibiotic therapy at the time of
             enrollment that prevent adequate completion of study-related assessments as judged by
             the investigator

          -  Current therapy with anabolic steroids or appetite stimulants

          -  History of prior transfusion reaction

          -  History of intolerance or allergic response to similar biological products

          -  Known sensitivity to dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), Dextran 40, or plasma proteins

          -  Currently on dialysis

          -  Recipient of bone marrow or organ transplant

          -  Any previous or current treatment with angiogenic growth factors, cytokines, gene or
             stem cell therapy

          -  Subjects participating in another interventional clinical study of an investigational
             therapy within 30 days of screening

        Other

          -  Lactating women

          -  Unable to be evaluated for follow-up visits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Mehling, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>BHI Therapeutic Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brian Mehling, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2013427662</phone>
    <email>mmanvelyan@bluehorizoninternational.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marina Manvelyan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>2013427662</phone>
    <email>mmanvelyan@bluehorizoninternational.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BHI Therapeutic Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Mehling, MD</last_name>
      <phone>201-342-7662</phone>
      <email>mmanvelyan@bluehorizoninternational.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>BHI Therapeutic Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brian Mehling</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human Umbilical Cord Blood</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic stem cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

