<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03733041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E2961-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03733041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neuromodulation for Exercise Adherence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neuromodulation for Exercise Adherence in Older Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lack of adherence to an exercise program is a major problem for older Veterans. Several fall
      prevention programs fail in the home setting due to lack of adherence. Exercise adherence is
      dependent on brain function among other factors. Magnetic stimulation of the front part of
      the brain improves brain function necessary for planning and following-through. The
      investigators propose a three-phase study in 106 sedentary older Veterans. Everyone will be
      trained on use of the exergame, Nintendo Wii-Fit, that the investigators' team has found
      beneficial in improving balance and gait. They will be asked to exercise using Wii-Fit at
      home for 45 minutes daily five days/week for 12-weeks. Those that exercise less than
      recommended dose and those that exercise adequately but have low executive function will
      receive either real or sham magnetic stimulation to the front part of their brain over ten
      sessions paired with exercise training. All subjects will further complete 24-weeks of
      Wii-Fit home exercises. Adherence, executive function, balance and gait, self-efficacy, delay
      discounting, and falls will be measured periodically.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Fall-related hospitalizations and consequent morbidity and mortality continue to
      rise despite the availability for over two decades of evidence-based fall-prevention
      programs. This is a major problem since more than 2.5 million older adults are treated
      annually for fall-related injuries in the US. Fall-prevention programs focusing on strength
      and balance exercises have been successful in facility settings but exercise programs are
      ineffective at home due to lack of adherence. Estimates indicate that only 1 in 5 individuals
      adhere to home exercise programs for fall prevention. Thus, there is an urgent need to
      improve adherence to exercise performed at home by older adults seeking to improve balance
      for the sake of fall prevention. Behavioral interventions have failed to consistently improve
      adherence to exercise. Biological reasons for poor exercise adherence, such as executive
      dysfunction, have not been explored. Adherence to long-term exercise is dependent on
      executive function (EF), which is controlled by the [dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC)]
      of the brain. EF influences choices in scheduling, forgoing competing activities, enduring
      subtle costs of time and inconvenience, and the ability to delay gratification. Repetitive
      transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) is a non-invasive neuromodulation increasingly used
      for neural network specific interventions. rTMS of the DLPFC improves EF, memory, motivation,
      and mental flexibility. rTMS studies to date have stimulated the motor cortex for gait and
      balance improvements. The role of DLPFC in exercise adherence has not been explored. The
      proposed study will be the first to test DLPFC stimulation for improving exercise adherence.

      Objective: The study objective is to determine the effects of rTMS treatment of the
      dorsolateral prefrontal cortex compared to sham on: [1. Short-term (2-wk) changes in
      executive function;] 2. Long-term (24-wk) adherence to a home-based exercise program; 3.
      Long-term (24-wk) changes in balance and gait; and [4. Short-term (2-wk) changes in
      self-efficacy and delay discounting.]

      Methods: Sedentary community-dwelling older Veterans (age 65 years, [N=106]) will participate
      in a double-blind randomized sham-controlled three-phase study. The proposed study will use
      Nintendo Wii-Fit exercises. Phase I will include two weeks of facility-based exercise for
      safety assessment and learning the program, followed by 12 weeks of home-based exercises.
      [Subjects with poor adherence and those with good adherence with low EF] will then be
      randomized to rTMS or sham treatments. Phase II will include ten consecutive weekdays of rTMS
      or sham treatment along with exercise training for subjects with poor adherence [and for
      those with good adherence and low EF] and continuation of home-based exercises for those with
      good adherence and EF. Phase III includes 24-weeks of a home-based exercise program. All
      subjects will exercise for 45 minutes five days/week. [Objective measure of adherence
      collected from Wii-Fit console and Conner's continuous performance test for EF will be the
      primary outcome measures.] Balance and gait will be assessed. [Self-efficacy, delay
      discounting along with fear of falls, and falls incidence will be assessed. Outcome measures
      will be assessed at baseline, and at 14, 16, and 40 weeks.]

      Significance: This project will have a major impact in improving adherence to an exercise
      program and in turn, improve balance in sedentary community-dwelling older Veterans. At the
      end of the proposed project, the investigators will gain knowledge about the efficacy of rTMS
      in improving EF and exercise adherence. Knowledge gained about the adherence to home-based
      exercises would be applicable to multiple conditions such as diabetes. Since Wii-Fit and rTMS
      are readily available, translation of the study results to clinical practice would be
      expeditious.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized to parallel groups to receive either the rTMS or sham treatment with allocation ratio of 1:1. The stratified randomization scheme will be generated by a statistician using a random block design with random block sizes, and assignments (X or Y) will be placed in sealed envelopes for sequential opening.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Subjects and the study team (staff responsible for administering treatment or rating outcomes and study physicians) will not know the coil assignment since coils are labeled 'X' or 'Y' and are identical.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Adherence as measured by number of minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks, 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of minutes exercised</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Conner's Continuous Performance Test</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks, 16 weeks, 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Commission Error percentage Range 0-100% Higher score is improvement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Adherence as measured by number of sessions</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks, 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of sessions exercised</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gait speed</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks, 16 weeks, 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The test measures habitual walking speed in meters/sec</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Timed Up and Go</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks, 16 weeks, 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is a widely accepted test of pro-active balance and mobility and measured in secs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">106</enrollment>
  <condition>Executive Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Poor Exercise Adherence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be randomized to receive rTMS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be randomized to receive sham treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rTMS</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive rTMS treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive sham treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive no intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Sedentary Community Dwelling Veterans age 60 years

          -  Have TV at home

          -  Subjects reporting spending long periods of time in sedentary behavior by answering
             affirmatively to the question: 'For most days, do you feel you sit for too long (6-8
             hours or more a day)?

               -  Some examples might include when watching TV, working at the computer / laptop or
                  when doing sitting-based hobbies such as reading and sewing' will be included

        Exclusion Criteria:

        GENERAL EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Those that participate in regular physical activity for at least 30 minutes five or
             more days of the week

        EXCLUSIONARY DUE TO Wii-Fit Exercises

          -  Use of wheel chair for mobility

          -  Cognitive impairment [Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA &lt; 26)]

          -  Weight 325 lbs. (weight restriction of the Wii-Board)

          -  Absolute contraindications to exercise per The American College of Sports Medicine
             guidelines

          -  Those with medical conditions that in the opinion of the study physician are likely to
             compromise safe participation

        EXCLUSIONARY DUE TO rTMS

          -  Taking medications known to increase risk of seizures from 2012 Beers criteria such as
             bupropion, chlorpromazine, clozapine.

          -  Taking other medications known to increase risk of seizures such as tricyclic
             antidepressants.

          -  Taking ototoxic medications: Aminoglycosides, CisplatinHistory of seizures/ seizures
             in first degree relatives

          -  Those with implanted device

          -  History of stroke, aneurysm, or cranial neurosurgery

          -  History of bipolar disorder

          -  History of abnormal electroencephalogram (EEG)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kalpana P Padala, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Central Arkansas Veterans Healthcare System Eugene J. Towbin Healthcare Center, Little Rock, AR</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kalpana P Padala, MD MS</last_name>
    <phone>(501) 257-2044</phone>
    <email>kalpana.padala@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Prasad R Padala, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>(501) 257-2537</phone>
    <email>Prasad.Padala@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Arkansas Veterans Healthcare System Eugene J. Towbin Healthcare Center, Little Rock, AR</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72114-1706</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kalpana P Padala, MD MS</last_name>
      <phone>501-257-2044</phone>
      <email>kalpana.padala@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Prasad R Padala, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>(501) 257-2537</phone>
      <email>Prasad.Padala@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kalpana P Padala, MD MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Older veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>home based exercise</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

