<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03738527</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5271</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03738527</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SEroma Reduction pOst MAstectomy &quot;SEROMA Study&quot;</brief_title>
  <acronym>SEROMA</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot RCT: Use of Tranexamic Acid (TXA) in Post Mastectomy Patients for Seroma and Hematoma Prevention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hamilton Health Sciences Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hamilton Health Sciences Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study to evaluate the feasibility of conducting a larger trial to determine
      if the use of intraoperative topical tranexamic acid (TXA) decreases the rate of
      post-operative hematomas and seromas in breast cancer patients after their mastectomy. In
      other words, the investigators want to determine if applying TXA inside the surgical wound
      before it is closed helps reduce blood or serous fluid accumulation at the operative site.
      Dependent on the results of this study, a further larger trial may or may not take place.

      Post-operative seromas and hematomas are common complications of mastectomy surgery not only
      leading to infection, discomfort, wound dehiscence or emergency room visits; they also delay
      in some instances post-operative adjuvant radiotherapy. Establishing whether or not topical
      TXA is an effective strategy to decrease those complications can potentially impact
      positively the breast cancer treatment.

      To achieve this aim, this randomized pilot study will first determine whether a larger
      multicenter study if feasible. This study will replicate a formal randomized trial at a
      smaller scale in a single center in order to assess the recruitment and randomization
      process, as well as provide preliminary results for our research question.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to investigate the novel use of topical application of
      Tranexamic Acid (TXA) to the surgical wound as a means to decrease seroma and/or hematoma
      formation compared to placebo in post-mastectomy patients. This project is designed as a
      single-center pilot RCT to evaluate the feasibility of conducting a formal RCT (multicenter
      trial including more patients) to evaluate the effectiveness of topical TXA.

      Patients will be randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups for intraoperative
      treatment of their mastectomy wound before it is closed.

      The first group will consist of those who will be treated with the intravenous form of TXA
      that will be applied to the surface of the mastectomy wound area rather than being injected
      into a vein. The second group consists of those individuals who will be treated with a
      topical normal saline solution (a placebo, or inactive substance that looks identical to the
      study drug but contains no therapeutic ingredients).

      Both groups will receive the same number of drains and the same post-operative follow-up
      schedule consisting of visits 2 to 4 weeks and 3 months after the surgery, as well as a last
      12 months follow-up. Standard of care will be practiced with respect to all procedures and
      visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) with 2 arms: the interventional arm (receiving topical TXA) and the control arm (receiving placebo).
Intervention: Topical application of 20 mL of TXA (100 mg/mL injection solution) to the mastectomy cavity
Placebo: Topical application of 20 mL of 0.9% NaCl (normal saline) to the mastectomy cavity</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients will be randomized on the REDCap system. Their assignment will be made available to pharmacy, which will be prepare syringes with either TXA or placebo.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>About 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients recruited over the total number of eligible patients screened</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Randomization rate</measure>
    <time_frame>About 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients randomized over total number recruited</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow-up visit rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with successful follow-up visits at 3 weeks and 3 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability to adhere to protocol</measure>
    <time_frame>About 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients randomized to TXA who received TXA vs number of patients randomized to placebo who received the placebo</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroma rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of seroma formation within 3 months following mastectomy in each arm of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroma volume</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of drainage (volume) in patients who did have a seroma, for patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroma aspiration</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Aspirated volume in patients who did have a seroma, for patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delay in adjuvant treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time (number of weeks) of delay in adjuvant treatment due to seroma/hematoma complication, for patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Other complications rate: Hematoma rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of hematoma within 3 months following mastectomy in each arm of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Other complications rate: Infection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of infection within 3 months following mastectomy in each arm of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Other complications rate: Wound dehiscence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of wound dehiscence within 3 months following mastectomy in each arm of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Daily output volume</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Daily drain output (volume), in patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Drain discontinuation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to drain discontinuation (number of days) in patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Drain complications</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of drain complications (leakage, dislodgement, blockage), in patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety outcomes: rate of thromboembolic events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of Thromboembolic events within 3 weeks following mastectomy, in patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety outcomes: rate of myocardial events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of myocardial events within 3 weeks following mastectomy, in patients in both arms of the study
• Rate of other adverse events within 3 weeks following mastectomy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety outcomes: rate of other adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of other adverse events within 3 weeks following mastectomy, in patients in both arms of the study</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Seroma Complicating A Procedure</condition>
  <condition>Hematoma Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TXA arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid 100mg/mL, 20mL topical</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: Tranexamic Acid
20 mL TXA (100 mg/mL injection solution, total 2g TXA) applied topically to the mastectomy cavity for 5 minutes before wound closure</description>
    <arm_group_label>TXA arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Saline Flush, 0.9%, 20mL topical</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: Normal Saline
20 mL 0.9% NaCl (normal saline) applied topically to the mastectomy cavity for 5 minutes before wound closure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Breast cancer diagnosis

          -  Age 18-80

          -  Fluent in English

          -  Female undergoing mastectomy with or without axillary intervention

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Immediate reconstruction

          -  Pre-surgical radiation

          -  Known allergy to TXA

          -  Known thromboembolic disease

          -  High-risk of thromboembolism and/or receiving anticoagulants

          -  History of myocardial infarction (MI), transient ischemic attack or stroke within the
             last year

          -  History of subarachnoid hemorrhage

          -  Premenopausal women with irregular menstrual bleeding of unknown cause

          -  Acquired disturbances of colour vision

          -  Hematuria with renal cause

          -  History of seizure disorder

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicole Hodgson, MD, MSc, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hamilton Health Sciences, McMaster University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Isabelle Duchesnay, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>905-521-2100</phone>
    <phone_ext>#4843</phone_ext>
    <email>isabelle.duchesnay@medportal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 4A6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Juravinski Hospital - Hamilton Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8V 1C3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Porter KA, O'Connor S, Rimm E, Lopez M. Electrocautery as a factor in seroma formation following mastectomy. Am J Surg. 1998 Jul;176(1):8-11.</citation>
    <PMID>9683123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pogson CJ, Adwani A, Ebbs SR. Seroma following breast cancer surgery. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2003 Nov;29(9):711-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14602488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Bemmel AJ, van de Velde CJ, Schmitz RF, Liefers GJ. Prevention of seroma formation after axillary dissection in breast cancer: a systematic review. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2011 Oct;37(10):829-35. doi: 10.1016/j.ejso.2011.04.012. Epub 2011 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21849243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coveney EC, O'Dwyer PJ, Geraghty JG, O'Higgins NJ. Effect of closing dead space on seroma formation after mastectomy--a prospective randomized clinical trial. Eur J Surg Oncol. 1993 Apr;19(2):143-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8491318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baker E, Piper J. Drainless mastectomy: Is it safe and effective? Surgeon. 2017 Oct;15(5):267-271. doi: 10.1016/j.surge.2015.12.007. Epub 2016 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>26907221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>He XD, Guo ZH, Tian JH, Yang KH, Xie XD. Whether drainage should be used after surgery for breast cancer? A systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Med Oncol. 2011 Dec;28 Suppl 1:S22-30. doi: 10.1007/s12032-010-9673-2. Epub 2010 Sep 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20827578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ker K, Roberts I, Shakur H, Coats TJ. Antifibrinolytic drugs for acute traumatic injury. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 May 9;(5):CD004896. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004896.pub4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25956410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta K, Rastogi B, Krishan A, Gupta A, Singh VP, Agarwal S. The prophylactic role of tranexamic acid to reduce blood loss during radical surgery: A prospective study. Anesth Essays Res. 2012 Jan-Jun;6(1):70-3. doi: 10.4103/0259-1162.103378.</citation>
    <PMID>25885506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perel P, Ker K, Morales Uribe CH, Roberts I. Tranexamic acid for reducing mortality in emergency and urgent surgery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 Jan 31;(1):CD010245. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD010245.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23440847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oertli D, Laffer U, Haberthuer F, Kreuter U, Harder F. Perioperative and postoperative tranexamic acid reduces the local wound complication rate after surgery for breast cancer. Br J Surg. 1994 Jun;81(6):856-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8044602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ker K, Beecher D, Roberts I. Topical application of tranexamic acid for the reduction of bleeding. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 Jul 23;(7):CD010562. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD010562.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23881695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu X, Xiong S, Wang Z, Li X, Liu W. Topical administration of tranexamic acid in total hip arthroplasty: A meta-analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials. Drug Discov Ther. 2015 Jun;9(3):173-7. doi: 10.5582/ddt.2015.01018.</citation>
    <PMID>26193938</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ausen K, Fossmark R, Spigset O, Pleym H. Randomized clinical trial of topical tranexamic acid after reduction mammoplasty. Br J Surg. 2015 Oct;102(11):1348-53. doi: 10.1002/bjs.9878.</citation>
    <PMID>26349843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennett C, Klingenberg SL, Langholz E, Gluud LL. Tranexamic acid for upper gastrointestinal bleeding. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Nov 21;(11):CD006640. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006640.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25414987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tranexamic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>mastectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>topical</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>seroma</keyword>
  <keyword>hematoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hematoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Seroma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

