<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03730363</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-18-HEM-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03730363</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pentamidine + Salvage Chemo for Relapsed/Refractory Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Pentamidine in Combination With Salvage Chemotherapy for Relapsed/Refractory Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Reinhold Munker</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective:

      To evaluate dose limiting toxicity and to determine the recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D) of
      pentamidine in combination with salvage chemotherapy with ifosfamide, carboplatin and
      etoposide (ICE) on a 3-weeks schedule in relapsed/refractory classical Hodgkin lymphoma
      (cHL).

      Secondary Objective:

        -  To estimate the overall best treatment response at 5- and 16-weeks from study
           enrollment. Although the clinical benefit of these drugs in combination has not been
           established, offering this treatment may provide a therapeutic benefit. The patients
           will be carefully monitored for tumor response and symptom relief, in addition to safety
           and tolerability.

        -  To estimate the duration of response to the proposed combined therapy.

        -  To measure the protein of regenerating liver-3 (PRL-3) level of expression in patients
           at time of relapse.

        -  To measure circulating biomarkers of response (soluble CD30 (sCD30), and thymus and
           activation-related chemokine (TARC)) in serum samples collected throughout treatment and
           inhibition of (pSTAT, pAKT) in peripheral blood mononucleated cells (PBMC).

      Exploratory Objective:

        -  To measure cell-free messenger RNA (cfmRNA) in peripheral blood.

        -  To measure cell-free DNA in peripheral blood
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this Phase I study is to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD)
      of Pentamidine. A two-stage continual reassessment method (CRM) will be employed to determine
      dose escalation levels and the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Pentamidine.

      Specifically, a modified two-stage CRM will be employed with 2 patients per cohort at each
      dose level. The trial starts with an escalation design from the lowest dose (2 mg/kg) with a
      traditional 2+2 dose escalation method. After occurrence of the first DLT, dose assignment
      will be determined by the CRM (2 patients/per cohort) using empirical model with restrictions
      to avoid dose-skipping and escalation immediately after a toxicity outcome.

      A maximum of 12 patients will be enrolled into the trial during the escalation phase. Once
      the MTD is reached, an additional 4 patients will be treated at this dose. Thus, 6 or more
      patients will be treated at the MTD.

      The target DLT rate is 33% and the investigators choose to use 0.10, 0.20 and 0.33 as prior
      toxicity distribution. CRM simulations indicate optimal performance of this design with high
      dose recommendation probabilities (at least 48%) and more patients allocated to the correct
      dose
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Low enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicity (DLT) for hematological and non-hematological toxicities will be graded using National Cancer Institute (NCI) CTCAE Version 5.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine Efficacy: best overall response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Individual best overall response at 5 and 16 weeks from enrollment, patients will be categorized as either a responder (complete response, partial response) versus nonresponders (stable disease, progressive disease).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Define the Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of response as defined starting from the first occurrence of response until disease progression or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify Immunohistochemistry Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Immunohistochemistry staining of paraffin fixed tissue sample and peripheral blood will be done to assess the ability of pentamidine to inhibit its pharmacological target through PRL-3 expression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polymerase Chair Reaction (PCR) analysis of Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Digital PCR analysis of paraffin fixed tissue sample and peripheral blood will be done to assess PRL-3 expression and compare to the immunohistochemistry staining to determine the ideal testing modality for PRL-3 in cHL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify Phosphorylation Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pentamidine concentration/protein phosphorylation will be measured in PBMC and plasma samples collected throughout treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify sCD30 and TARC Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Biomarkers: ELISA testing will be used to assess levels of sCD30 and TARC in serum samples collected prior to initiation of therapy and subsequent cycles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measure cfmRNA Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>Digital PCR analysis of the peripheral blood plasma will be used to measure cfmRNA during therapy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measure Circulating-free DNA (cfDNA) Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 112 days</time_frame>
    <description>digital PCR analysis of the peripheral blood plasma will be used to measure cfDNA during therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pentamidine + ICE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pentamidine, Ifosfamide, Carboplatin, and Etoposide (ICE) by IV Infusion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pentamidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Pentamidine will be administered as an IV infusion on treatment day 1-3 of a 21-day cycle 3 cycles using 2, 3, and 4 mg/kg dose escalation schedules. Non-investigational agents will be administered as follows: Ifosfamide 5000 mg/m2, Carboplatin 5 area under curve (AUC), and Etoposide 100 mg/mg2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pentamidine + ICE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years old or older

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤2

          -  Subjects with histologically confirmed relapse or refractory cHL who had received a
             front-line anthracycline-containing regimen.

          -  Subjects must have at least one measurable lesion &gt;1.5cm as defined by the lymphoma
             response criteria.

          -  Subjects must have recovered from their last prior chemotherapy; if they have received
             an investigational agent, at least 5 half-lives must have expired to assure clearance
             of prior therapy.

          -  Prior radiation should have been completed at least 4 weeks prior to study Day 1.

          -  Toxicities related to prior therapy must have returned to Grade 1 or less except for
             alopecia. Peripheral neuropathy must be grade 2 or less.

          -  Adequate bone marrow function defined as: 1) Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1000/µl and
             2) Platelet count ≥ 50,000/µl

          -  Adequate organ function: 1) Creatinine Clearance (CrCl) &gt;60 mL/min and 2) Aspartate
             Aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3 upper limit normal (ULN), and Alanine Aminotransferase
             (ALT) ≤3 ULN, and Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 ULN (Unless they have Gillbert's disease)

          -  Ability to comply with the treatment, evaluations and required study follow-up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with central nervous system involvement.

          -  Subjects with concomitant second malignancy (except adequately treated non-melanoma
             skin cancer, ductal carcinoma in-situ, superficial bladder cancer, prostate cancer or
             in situ cervical cancer) are excluded unless a complete remission was achieved at
             least 3 years prior to study entry and no additional therapy is required or
             anticipated.

          -  A serious uncontrolled medical disorder or active infection which impairs the ability
             of the subject to receive protocol therapy or whose control is jeopardized by the
             complication of this therapy.

          -  Prior organ allograft or allogeneic bone marrow transplantation.

          -  Positive for HIV (1/2) or known acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.

          -  Positive for hepatitis B Surface Ag, or antibody to hepatitis B core ag, or hepatitis
             C antibody or hepatitis C RNA in serum.

          -  Ejection fraction less than 45% in subjects with prior anthracycline therapy
             (measurement of ejection fraction is mandatory).

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) prolongation of more than 500.

          -  Women of reproductive age who are unwilling or unable to use an acceptable method to
             minimize the risk of pregnancy for the entire study period and for at least 18 weeks
             after the last dose of pentamidine.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Women with a positive pregnancy test (serum assay) on enrollment or prior to
             pentamidine administration.

          -  Sexually active men not using birth control if their partners are women of
             reproductive age.

          -  Prisoner or subjects who are involuntarily incarcerated.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to pentamidine and/or ifosfamide, carboplatin and etoposide.

          -  No investigational or commercial agents or therapies other than those specified by the
             protocol may be administered with the intent to treat the patient's malignancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hayder Saeed, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lucille P. Markey Cancer Center at University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky Markey Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Reinhold Munker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pentamidine</keyword>
  <keyword>Salvage Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pentamidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

