<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03737916</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E171616</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03737916</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Perineural Dextrose Injection in Patients With Ulnar Neuropathy at the Elbow</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Evaluate the Effect of Perineural Dextrose Injection in Patients With Ulnar Neuropathy at the Elbow and to Compare the Control Group</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ankara Education and Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ankara Education and Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Ulnar neuropathy at the elbow (UNE) is the second most common neuropathy and occurs after
      recurrent or elongated elbow flexion. Diagnosis of UNE depends on clinical symptoms, physical
      examination, and electrophysiological findings. Imaging methods such as ultrasonography (USG)
      and magnetic resonance imaging show cross-sectional area and echogenicity of ulnar nerve and
      give information about to surrounding structures around the ulnar nerve. In mild and moderate
      cases, conservative treatments are administered up to 6 months, who do not benefit from
      conservative treatment are referred to surgery. There are not many options for conservative
      treatment. Activity modification, nerve gliding exercises and night splints are conservative
      treatment methods. Steroid injection is no longer recommended. Perineural dextrose injection
      is applied in tendinopathies and entrapment neuropathies (especially carpal tunnel syndrome).
      In the literature, there is no study showing effect of perineural dextrose injection in
      patients with UNE. The investigators design a randomized, double-blind, controlled trail to
      evaluate the effect after ultrasound-guided perineural injection with 5% dextrose in patients
      with UNE.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After obtaining written informed consent, patients of clinically diagnosed with UNE were
      randomized into intervention and control group. Participants in intervention group received
      one-session ultrasound-guided perineural injection with 5% dextrose and control group
      received one-session ultrasound-guided perineural injection with normal saline. No additional
      treatment after injection through the study period. The primary outcome is visual analog
      scale (VAS) and secondary outcomes include Quick-DASH (Disabilities of Arm, Shoulder and
      Hand), cross-sectional area (CSA) of the ulnar nerve, motor nerve conduction velocity and
      distal latency of the ulnar nerve. The evaluation was performed pretreatment as well as on
      the 2nd week, 1st and 3rd month after the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 18, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 18, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of pain on 2nd week, 1st and 3rd months after treatment: VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: Pre-treatment, 2nd week, 1st and 3rd months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Visual analog scale (VAS) to measure the pain scale before treatment and multiple time frame after treatment. Recorded on a visual analogue scale (VAS), scores range from 0 to 100 mm, with higher scores indicating worse pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in activity and functional status on 2nd week, 1st and 3rd months after treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 2nd week, 1st and 3rd months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Quick-DASH to measure the activity and functional status before treatment and multiple time frame after treatment. The Quick-DASH is a shortened version of the DASH Outcome Measure. Instead of 30 items, the QuickDASH uses 11 items to measure physical function and symptoms in people with any or multiple musculoskeletal disorders of the upper limb. The higher scores indicate worse functional status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in cross-sectional area of the ulnar nerve on 1st and 3th months after treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 2nd week, 1st and 3rd months after treatment treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using the musculoskeletal ultrasonography to measure the cross-sectional area of the ulnar nerve.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in motor nerve conduction velocity of the ulnar nerve</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, 1st and 3rd months after treatment treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using Electromyography to measure the motor nerve conduction velocity (m/sn) of the ulnar nerve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulnar Neuropathies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dextrose group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure: Ultrasound-guided perineural injection with 5% dextrose. Ultrasound-guided perineural injection with 5% Dextrose (1cc) to ulnar nerve into the elbow, 2 and 4 cm before and after the elbow (total 5 cc).
Drug: 5% Dextrose 5% Dextrose could decrease the release of CGRP (Calcitonin Gene Related Peptide) and substance P to reduce the nerve inflammation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure: Perineural injection with normal saline Ultrasound-guided perineural injection with normal saline (1cc) to ulnar nerve into the elbow, 2 and 4 cm before and after the elbow (total 5 cc).
Drug: Normal Saline Normal saline is safe for perineural injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5 cc 5% Dextrose solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Ultrasound-guided perineural injection with 5% Dextrose (1cc) to ulnar nerve into the elbow, 2 and 4 cm before and after the elbow (total 5 cc).</description>
    <arm_group_label>dextrose group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5 cc salin</intervention_name>
    <description>Ultrasound-guided perineural injection with salin (1cc) to ulnar nerve into the elbow, 2 and 4 cm before and after the elbow (total 5 cc).</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18-65 year-old.

          -  Neuropathic pain on the ulnar nerve distribution area for at least 1 months

          -  Diagnosis was confirmed using an electrophysiological studies and ultrasonography

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of trauma to the upper extremity

          -  Central or peripheral neurologic disease

          -  Electromyography (EMG)-proven carpal tunnel syndrome, radiculopathy or any other
             neuropathy

          -  Pregnancy or any systemic disease that might cause swelling on nerves (e.g., diabetes
             -mellitus, renal failure, and thyroid disease)

          -  USG-detected bifid or trifid median nerve, persistent median artery, or
             space-occupying lesions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Basak Mansiz-Kaplan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Basak Mansiz-Kaplan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <zip>06230</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ankara Education and Research Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Basak Mansiz-Kaplan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation (the principal investigator)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulnar Neuropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

