<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03730831</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NET PSYCH 2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03730831</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Narrative Exposure Therapy in Patients With Psychotic Disorders and a Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</brief_title>
  <acronym>NETPSYCH</acronym>
  <official_title>Narrative Exposure Therapy in Patients With Psychotic Disorders and a Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Konstanz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre for Psychiatry Reichenau</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Konstanz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adverse childhood experiences in psychotic disorders are associated with increased cognitive
      deficits, severe psychotic symptoms, and increased comorbidity. The number of different
      stress experiences also increases the probability of trauma-associated symptoms. Furthermore,
      neurobiological changes play a key role in the vulnerability of individuals with early
      traumas for mental and physical illnesses, among others for diseases of the schizophrenic
      spectrum disorder and the further course of the disease.

      The current project pursues a detailed recording of the course of symptoms in inpatients with
      psychosis to link this data with a systematic recording of childhood experiences and
      traumatic experiences and biological data.

      On a subsample of inpatients with psychosis and a comorbid post-traumatic stress disorder
      (PTSD), the researchers want to investigate whether symptom traits of existing psychotic
      disorders, biomolecular parameters and cognitive functions can be influenced by a
      trauma-specific treatment (NET), that has been proven to be effective in the treatment of
      PTSD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Numerous scientific findings point to the influence of stressful childhood experiences and
      traumatic experiences on the risk of mental and physical illnesses, their severity and their
      course. Traumatic experiences also increase the risk of demonstrating psychotic symptoms or
      even develop psychotic disorders. Furthermore, the number of different stress experiences
      also increases the probability of trauma-associated symptoms (symptoms of post-traumatic
      stress disorder (PTSD) and dissociative experiences).

      Neurobiological changes in the immune system, the defense of stress and also central nervous
      circuits and structures play a key role in the vulnerability of individuals with early
      traumas for mental and physical illnesses, e.g. for diseases of the schizophrenic spectrum
      disorder and the further course of the disease.

      The recording of stressful and traumatic life experiences has been largely neglected in
      everyday clinical practice, especially in patients with a schizophrenia spectrum disorder.
      The diagnosis of PTSD is rarely given in everyday clinical practice, so that trauma-specific
      treatment is often not offered.

      The targeted use of a scientifically proven intervention to reduce the symptoms of PTSD (NET:
      Narrative Exposure Therapy) involves a change in stress-associated biomolecular parameters
      and normalizes neuronal brain activity.

      The current project pursues a systematic recording of childhood experiences and traumatic
      experiences possibly experienced as stressful as well as a detailed recording of the course
      of symptoms in inpatients with psychosis. The researchers want to investigate whether symptom
      traits of existing psychotic disorders, biomolecular parameters and cognitive functions can
      be influenced by a trauma-specific treatment (NET).

      The current project thus is divided into two work programs:

        1. The first work program includes a weekly prospective assessment of psychotic symptoms on
           a sample of n=100 inpatients and links this data with results from a cross-sectional
           review of traumatic and distressing childhood experiences and biological data (cortisol
           awakening, tonic cortisol concentration in hair and determination of mitochondrial
           respiratory activity in mononuclear cells).

        2. The second work program includes the subgroup of psychotic patients with comorbid PTSD
           (n=20) and includes a randomized controlled pilot study to determine the impact of
           trauma therapy (NET) on the course of symptoms. In addition to the symptoms of PTSD,
           psychosis-specific parameters such as cognitive functions and biological characteristics
           will be repeatedly recorded pre and post (6 months and 12 months after completing trauma
           therapy).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychotic Symptom Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from from admission to study (T1) to T2 (4 weeks after admission) to T3 (3 months after admission or - if released earlier - at release from inpatient treatment)</time_frame>
    <description>The course of psychotic symptoms is measured during inpatient treatment (from admission to study until release from inpatient treatment, typically for 6-8 weeks) with the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS; Kay, S. R., Fiszbein, A., &amp; Opfer, L. A. (1987). The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) for schizophrenia. Schizophrenia Bulletin, 13 (2), 261.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD symptom severity (PCL-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (T1) to 6 and 12 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>PTSD symptoms are measured by self-report (reporting period: previous 4 weeks) with the PTSD Checklist - 5 (PCL-5; Weathers, Litz, et al., 2013).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cortisol awakening response (CAR)</measure>
    <time_frame>at awaking, 30 min, 45 min and 60 min after awakening</time_frame>
    <description>During the first hour after awakening saliva samples will be repeatedly collected following the established procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MATRICS Consensus Cognitive Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in cognitive functions is measures pre intervention (T1) and 4 weeks after T1, as well as 6 and 12 months after T1</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive change is measures with the MATRICS Consensus Cognitive Battery (Nuechterlein, K. H., Green, M. F., Kern, R. S., Baade, L. E., Barch, D. M., Cohen, J. D., ... &amp; Goldberg, T. (2008). The MATRICS Consensus Cognitive Battery, part 1: test selection, reliability, and validity. American Journal of Psychiatry, 165 (2), 203-213.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>PTSD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Narrative Exposure Therapy The Narrative Exposure Therapy (NET) is a brief manualized trauma-focussed treatment and will be performed according to the manual of Schauer et al., 2011. In the NET the experiences experienced as traumatic are worked on and placed in the context of the entire life story.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Waiting List</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Narrative Exposure Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>8-10 sessions: 1 lifeline session, 6-10 sessions narrative exposure, 1-2 sessions of future-oriented counselling</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with schizophrenia spectrum disorder

          -  for treatment and non treatment group: Patients with schizophrenia spectrum disorder
             and comorbid PTSD Diagnosis (DSM-5)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients not able to participate in trauma-focused therapy due to mental impairment
             (e.g. dementia)

          -  non-compliance with appointments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Odenwald, Dr. rer. nat.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7531 884621</phone>
    <email>michael.odenwald@uni-konstanz.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susanne Breinlinger, MA</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Konstanz, Psychotherapy Outpatient Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Konstanz</city>
        <zip>78464</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Odenwald, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 7531 884621</phone>
      <email>michael.odenwald@uni-konstanz.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anne Schawohl, MA</last_name>
      <phone>+49 7531 883589</phone>
      <email>anne.schawohl@uni-konstanz.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Konstanz</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Odenwald</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of psychological outpatient clinic, head of psychology at the research ward</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Course</keyword>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia spectrum disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Narrative Exposure Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

