<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03734068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LIFDOX</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03734068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chemoembolization Using LifePearl Polyethylene Glycol Drug Eluting Microspheres With Doxorubicin in HCC</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIFDOX</acronym>
  <official_title>Observational Prospective Study on Chemoembolization Using LifePearl Polyethylene Glycol Drug Eluting Microspheres With Doxorubicin in Patients With Primary Un-resectable Liver Cancer (Hepatocellular Carcinoma)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Group of Endovascular Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Group of Endovascular Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to collect data on efficacy and tolerability on a large series of
      patient of different Italian hospitals in order to support the validation of LifePearl with
      robust and consistent clinical evidence. Since TACE in treating HCC is considered a more
      common and accepted approach, this study will be focused on evaluating treatment efficacy and
      safety of LIFDOX for un-resectable hepatocellular carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the fifth most common type of cancer in men and the seventh
      in women and is the third most common cause of death from cancer worldwide. The overall
      incidence of HCC remains high in developing countries and is steadily increasing in most
      industrialized countries.

      Trans-arterial chemoembolization (TACE) is the most used treatment for patients with
      un-resectable hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), because it improves median survival and tumor
      response. The application of drug-eluting bead to this procedure has significantly increased
      TACE efficacy, while reducing systemic drug leakage, liver toxicity and adverse events. These
      beads deliver the toxic drugs directly to the arterial capillary bed of the tumor, and
      release them in a controlled manner. This method lower the systemic exposure to
      chemotherapeutics, while increasing their local concentration, resulting in a greater tissue
      necrosis than classic trans-arterial chemoembolization.

      TACE is indicated for patients with multinodular liver cancer that have no vascular invasion
      and extrahepatic diffusion. TACE is also strongly suggested for patients with un-resectable
      liver primary tumor (HCC and cholangiocarcinoma) and chemo-resistant liver metastases, mainly
      from colorectal cancer carcinoma (CRC), and is widely performed in 32% of patients with
      un-resectable HCC at initial diagnosis and in 58% of those with recurrent HCC. It appears,
      moreover, to be particularly useful if carried out with new embolization materials, such as
      doxorubicin.

      Trans-arterial chemoembolization is constantly improving; from the original conventional TACE
      using Lipiodol and sponge particles, some years ago it evolved into precision TACE, thanks to
      the availability of drug-eluting microspheres. Microspheres retain the ability to bind
      positively charged chemotherapeutic drugs (i.e.: doxorubicin) and release them in a prolonged
      and sustained kinetic at tumor site while determining a permanent embolization of the feeding
      arteries. Consequently, less systemic exposure of drug is observed, with a benefit for the
      patients in term of toxicity, quality of life and hospitalization.

      Recently, new drug-eluting beads in polyethylene glycol has been made available, termed
      LifePearl Polyethylene glycol drug eluting microspheres (Terumo, Microvention, Tustin, CA,
      USA), which are offered as a syringe presentation, for an easier loading process. More
      interestingly, LifePearl are precisely calibrated, in a range ≤ 50 micron, potentially
      leading to a more distal and targeted distribution into the tissues; in addition, they are
      endowed with a prolonged time in suspension after dilution in contrast medium, which makes
      the administration more smooth, predictable and reproducible. Because of the above
      improvements, LifePearl are now widely used in several hospital for the Transarterial
      chemoembolization as everyday clinical practice, for the hepatic intra-arterial infusion of
      doxorubicin or irinotecan respectively for the therapy of primary and metastatic liver
      cancer.

      The aim of this study is to collect data on efficacy and tolerability on a large series of
      patient of different Italian hospitals in order to support the validation of LifePearl with
      robust and consistent clinical evidence. Since TACE in treating HCC is considered a more
      common and accepted approach, this study will be focused on evaluating treatment efficacy and
      safety of LIFDOX for un-resectable hepatocellular carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>CT scan will be performed to assess tumor response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>number and intensity of adverse events will be monitored</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>1 months</time_frame>
    <description>time from first treatment to progression will be computed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of treatment required to achieve objective response in HCC patients</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>number of treatment required to achieve objective response (partial or complete response) will be recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chemoembolization</arm_group_label>
    <description>Chemoembolization Using LifePearl and Doxorubicin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chemoembolization Using LifePearl</intervention_name>
    <description>Chemoembolization Using LifePearl</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemoembolization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Doxorubicin is loaded to LIfePearl</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemoembolization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        un-resectable hepatocellular carcinoma that are indicated for TACE treatment
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with confirmed diagnosis of HCC with CT scan, MRI or biopsy

          -  Patient with un-resectable HCC and not indicated for other radical therapies, or
             waiting for transplant

          -  Multinodular or single nodular tumor extended to &lt;50% of the liver

          -  Hyper vascular lesion showing contrast enhancement in the early stage at the contrast
             media bolus injection CT or MRI.

          -  At least one uni-dimensional lesion measurable according to the Modified RECIST
             criteria by CT-scan or MRI

          -  No invasion in the blood vessel (hepatic portal, hepatic vein) or bile duct by the CT
             or MR

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status is 0 - 1

          -  Proper blood, liver, renal, heart function

          -  Over 18 years old

          -  Expected survival more than 6 months

          -  Prior written patient consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Extrahepatic metastasis (Any lymph nodes measuring ≥ 10mm along the short axis)

          -  Tumor burden involving more than 50% of the liver

          -  History of biliary tract repair or endoscopic biliary tract treatment

          -  Clinically important refractory ascites or pleural fluid

          -  Any contraindications for hepatic embolization procedures

          -  Any contraindication for doxorubicin administration

          -  Contrast media allergy contraindicating angiography

          -  Acute or active cardiac, hepatic or renal diseases

          -  Pregnant, nursing or childbearing age women and men who are sexually active and don't
             want to or can't do contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio Nicolini, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UOSD Radiologia Interventistica, Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico, Via Francesco Sforza, 28, 20122 Milano, Italia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giammaria Fiorentini, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Oncology-Hematology, Azienda Ospedaliera Ospedali Riuniti Marche Nord, P.O. San Salvatore, via C. Lombroso 1, 62122 Pesaro, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Antonio Nicolini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+390255035604</phone>
    <email>anicolini54@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Giammaria Fiorentini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+390721364005</phone>
    <email>g.fiorentini@alice.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Antonio Nicolini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Nicolini, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+390255035604</phone>
      <email>anicolini54@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Giammaria Fiorentini, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+390721364005</phone>
      <email>g.fiorentini@alice.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Antonio Nicolini, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giammaria Fiorentini, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Transarterial chemoembolization</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor response</keyword>
  <keyword>Lifepearls</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The researchers will provide full protocol to interested researchers</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>12 months</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>request by email to Principal investigator</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

