<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03730493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ILBS-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03730493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of a Pictorial Flashcard Regarding Self-care of Peripheral Intravenous Cannula (PIVC) on Its Indwelling Time and Related Complications Among Inpatients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Evaluate the Effectiveness of a Pictorial Flashcard Regarding Self-Care of Peripheral Intravenous Cannula (PIVC) on Its Indwelling Time and Related Complications Among Inpatients at ILBS, New Delhi</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study title is &quot;A Study to evaluate the Effectiveness of a Pictorial Flashcard regarding
      Self-Care of Peripheral Intravenous Cannula (PIVC) on its indwelling time and related
      complications among inpatients at ILBS, New Delhi.&quot; and it aim to evaluate the Effectiveness
      of a Pictorial Flashcard regarding Self-Care of PIVC on its indwelling time and related
      complications among inpatients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives of the Study

        1. To evaluate the Effectiveness of a Pictorial Flashcard regarding Self-Care of PIVC on
           its indwelling time and related complications among inpatients.

        2. To find out the association between indwelling time of PIVC with selected demographic
           and clinical variables.

        3. To find out the association between PIVC related complications with selected demographic
           and clinical variables.

      Setting of the Study General wards of ILBS, New Delhi

      Population Inpatients with PIVC

      Sampling Technique Convenient sampling technique.

      Data collection Data will be collected from the study subjects as well as from medical
      records. Subjects were taken from General wards of Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences,
      New Delhi.

      Methodology Research Approach: Quantitative research approach. Research Design: Quasi
      Experimental Research design (Post-test only comparison group Design) Sample size: 80 (40 in
      each group), finalize after power analysis

      Data Analysis Method Descriptive statistics: Mean, frequency, percentage distribution and
      Standard Deviation Inferential Statistics: Chi Square, t- test ANOVA, RM-ANOVA and
      Man-Whitney U test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 29, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 9, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 9, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of Pictorial Flashcard on Indwelling time of Peripheral Intravenous Cannula (PIVC) among inpatients.</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Effectiveness refers to the significant increase in indwelling time of PIVC and reduction in PIVC related complication after using pictorial flash card on self-care of PIVC which calculated in hours i.e. 72 hours.
Indwelling time refers to the time duration i.e. 72 hours between insertion and removal of PIVC.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (complications related to PIVC) in both groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events or complications related to PIVC refers to complications, such as Phlebitis, Infiltration, Pain,Blockage and Dislodgement which occurs on PIVC site during the indwelling time of PIVC i.e. within or till 72 hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Inpatient Facililty Diagnoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pictorial flashcard</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the experimental group researcher explained self-care of PIVC using pictorial flashcard on one to one basis. Patients were explained Do's and Don'ts, they have to keep in mind during self-care. Doubts of the patients were also addressed simultaneously. After this a copy of pictorial flashcard was given to the subjects to be used in future (during PIVC in-situ). Time was noted and kept for observation till 72 hours or removal in between.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In control group, standard care was given as per the hospital protocol.Time was noted and kept for observation till 72 hours or removal in between.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teaching subjects regarding self-care of PIVC with Pictorial Flashcard.</intervention_name>
    <description>In the experimental group researcher explained self-care of PIVC using pictorial flashcard on one to one basis. Patients were explained Do's and Don'ts, they have to keep in mind during self-care or management. Doubts of the patients were also addressed simultaneously. After this a copy of pictorial flashcard was given to the subjects to be used in future (during PIVC in-situ). In control group, standard care was given as per the hospital protocol. After 24 hours/one day, PIVC was observed for presence of any complications such as Phlebitis, Infiltration, Pain, Blockage and Dislodgement using V.I.P. Score, Infusion nurses society infiltration scale, Universal pain assessment tool and PIVC Documentation Tool and need for PIVC removal was also assessed. After 72 hours PIVC removed (whatever applicable) site of PIVC was reassessed, reason for removal was recorded and indwelling time was noted.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pictorial flashcard</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Patients who:

          -  were conscious &amp; oriented.

          -  could understand Hindi or English.

          -  were between the age group of 18 to 60 years.

          -  were admitted in general wards and scheduled for PIVC insertion

          -  received IV infusion and/or medication for at least 3 days (72 hours)

        Exclusion Criteria

        Patients who:

          -  were on physical restraints

          -  were on sedative drugs.

          -  in whom PIVC was removed for the sole purpose of discharge before 72 hours.

          -  had short admission period, i.e less than 72 hours
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <state>Delhi</state>
        <zip>110070</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rahul Ranjan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

