<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03733522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IsolationFOUSP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03733522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Isolation of the Operative Field Influences the Survival Rate of Composite Restorations</brief_title>
  <acronym>IsolationC3</acronym>
  <official_title>Does the Isolation of the Operative Field Influence the Survival Rate of Bulkfill Composite Restorations in Primary Teeth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study was to evaluate the survival of direct composite resin restorations in
      primary molars using different methods of isolation of the operative field: absolute
      isolation (local anesthesia, use of dental clamp and rubber dam) and relative isolation
      (cotton rollers and saliva ejector) by a randomized clinical trial. Two hundred (200)
      restorations will be performed on children aged 4 to 10 years who present at least one dentin
      caries lesion or restoration needing replacement, without pulp involvement in a primary
      tooth. The treatments will be performed in the dental clinic of the University of São Paulo
      (FOUSP) by trained operators. The teeth will be randomized between the groups: Absolute
      Isolation (AI) and Relative Isolation (IR) and restored with composite resin (Scotchbond
      Universal Adhesive adhesive system and Filtek BulkFill composite resin - 3M ESPE) stratified
      by surface (single or multi surface). Restoration evaluation will be performed after 6, 12,
      18, and 24 months by a blind, trained and calibrated examiner. As a primary outcome, the
      survival of the restorations will be evaluated. The secondary outcomes involve the procedure
      time (in minutes), professional and material cost (in Brazilian reais), as well as the
      cost-effectiveness of the restorations and the discomfort reported by the patient (measured
      using the Wong-Baker scale). The Kaplan-Meier survival analysis and log-rank test will be
      applied to the survival of the restoration. All variables will be modeled and compared with a
      Cox regression model of shared fragility. The discomfort reported by the patient will be
      analyzed by Ordinal Logistic Regression (α = 5%).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      The aim of this study is to evaluate the survival of direct composite resin restorations in
      primary molars using different methods for isolation of the operative field: absolute
      isolation (local anesthesia, use of dental clamp and rubber dam) and relative isolation
      (cotton rollers and saliva ejector) by a randomized clinical trial.

      Materials and Methods:

      Two hundred (200) restorations will be performed on children aged 4 to 10 years who present
      at least one dentin caries lesion or restoration needing replacement, without pulp
      involvement in a primary tooth. The treatments will be performed in the dental clinic of the
      University of São Paulo (FOUSP) by trained operators. The teeth will be randomized between
      the groups: Absolute Isolation (AI) and Relative Isolation (IR) and restored with composite
      resin (Scotchbond Universal Adhesive adhesive system and Filtek BulkFill composite resin - 3M
      ESPE) stratified by surface (single or multi surface).

      Restoration evaluation will be performed after 6, 12, 18, and 24 months by a blind, trained
      and calibrated examiner.

      The sample calculation was performed based on the primary outcome of the randomized clinical
      trial, which is the longevity of composite resin restorations in deciduous teeth. For this
      calculation, a 3-year failure rate of approximately 5% for composite resin restorations
      reported by a systematic review [5] was considered. Considering the hypothesis of
      non-inferiority between the groups and an inferiority limit of 10% between the groups, we
      reached the number of 118 restorations. As a child can contribute with more than one
      restoration, 40% was added to this value (n = 166). 20% for possible sample losses was added
      to this number, a minimum of 200 restorations were reached.

      As a primary outcome, the survival of the restorations will be evaluated. The secondary
      outcomes involve the procedure time (in minutes), professional and material cost (in
      Brazilian reais), as well as the cost-effectiveness of the restorations and the discomfort
      reported by the patient (measured using the Wong-Baker scale).

      The Kaplan-Meier survival analysis and log-rank test will be applied to the survival of the
      restoration. All variables will be modeled and compared with a Cox regression model of shared
      fragility. The discomfort reported by the patient will be analyzed by Ordinal Logistic
      Regression (α = 5%).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Only the evaluator of the restorations will be blind to the type of treatment (absolute or relative isolation). As the procedures are different, it will not be possible to blind operators and patients.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival of the restorations</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>The restorations will be evaluated according to the Roeleveld et al., 2006 criteria and World Dental Federation (FDI) criteria.
Roeleveld et al. codes success (0-10) or failure (11-50). FDI criteria codes succes 1 to 3 and failure 4 and 5 (any category)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child self-reported discomfort (0-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after treatment (in the same appointment)</time_frame>
    <description>Wong-Baker Facial scale (Wong; Baker, 1998) from 0 to 5. The higher the score, higher the child self-reported discomfort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time spent during treatment (in minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after treatment (in the same appointment)</time_frame>
    <description>The total time spent in each restorative session will be recorded in minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure cost (in brazilian reais - R$)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after treatment (in the same appointment)</time_frame>
    <description>Direct costs - all materials used in each procedure will be recorded. The average price of three different places in Brazilian market will be used (in Brazilian Reais).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incremental Cost (in brazilian reais)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 12 months up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>For the calculation of the final cost (Brazilian reais) of the treatment of each tooth will be used the result of the sum of the initial cost of the restorative procedure with the cost of repairs when necessary (incremental cost).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">87</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Caries in Children</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rubber dam isolation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Absolute isolation
local anesthesia
use of dental clamp and rubber dam
restoration using Universal Adhesive in a self etch mode (Single Bond Universal - 3M ESPE) and bulkfill composite resin (Filtek Bulkfill - 3M ESPE)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Relative isolation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Relative isolation
no local anesthesia
use of cotton roll and saliva ejector
restoration using Universal Adhesive in a self etch mode (Single Bond Universal - 3M ESPE) and bulkfill composite resin (Filtek Bulkfill - 3M ESPE)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rubber dam isolation</intervention_name>
    <description>Local anesthesia, use of dental clamp and rubber dam, followed by restoration using universal adhesive system and bulkfill composite restoration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relative isolation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Relative isolation</intervention_name>
    <description>No local anesthesia, use of cotton rollers and saliva ejector, followed by restoration using universal adhesive system and bulkfill composite restoration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rubber dam isolation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  who have sought treatment in the University;

          -  between 4 and 10 years of age;

          -  with at least one dentin caries lesion without pulp involvement (ICCMS C score);

          -  need for restoration replacement diagnosed by FDI criteria or CARS criteria;

          -  absence of pulp involvement diagnosed by interproximal radiography (presence of dentin
             layer between the caries lesion and the pulp chamber).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  children whose parents did not agree to participate in the study:

          -  children who did not agree to participate or had behavioral problems during the
             initial consultations.

          -  signs or symptoms of pulp pathology: spontaneous pain, pulp exposure, abscess or
             fistula near the tooth to be included, mobility or presence of communication between
             the caries lesion and the pulp (evaluated by interproximal digital radiography of the
             diagnosis).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniela P Raggio, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Isabel C Olegário, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of São Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Sao Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>05508900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hickel R, Peschke A, Tyas M, Mjör I, Bayne S, Peters M, Hiller KA, Randall R, Vanherle G, Heintze SD. FDI World Dental Federation: clinical criteria for the evaluation of direct and indirect restorations-update and clinical examples. Clin Oral Investig. 2010 Aug;14(4):349-66. doi: 10.1007/s00784-010-0432-8. Epub 2010 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20628774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ismail AI, Sohn W, Tellez M, Amaya A, Sen A, Hasson H, Pitts NB. The International Caries Detection and Assessment System (ICDAS): an integrated system for measuring dental caries. Community Dent Oral Epidemiol. 2007 Jun;35(3):170-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17518963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chisini LA, Collares K, Cademartori MG, de Oliveira LJC, Conde MCM, Demarco FF, Corrêa MB. Restorations in primary teeth: a systematic review on survival and reasons for failures. Int J Paediatr Dent. 2018 Mar;28(2):123-139. doi: 10.1111/ipd.12346. Epub 2018 Jan 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29322626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roeleveld AC, van Amerongen WE, Mandari GJ. Influence of residual caries and cervical gaps on the survival rate of Class II glass ionomer restorations. Eur Arch Paediatr Dent. 2006 Jun;7(2):85-91.</citation>
    <PMID>17140533</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniela Prócida Raggio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associated Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

