<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03736291</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JunCai</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03736291</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in Schizophrenia——A Randomized , Double-blind fMRI Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Mental Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Mental Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) can modulate neuronal activity and has
      been shown to improve symptoms in patients with schizophrenia, but the underlying neural
      mechanism is unknown.This study hypothesized that repetitive transcranial magnetic
      stimulation of the cerebellar vermis can alter the ciliary-related functional connections in
      schizophrenia, thereby improving negative symptoms, cognitive function, and emotional
      symptoms. Therefore, this study will firstly explore the difference in cerebellar functional
      connectivity between patients and healthy controls, and on this basis, patients undergo a
      resting state functional magnetic resonance scan before and after rTMS intervention in the
      cerebellar vermis, and observe the cerebellar function connection in the treatment. Before
      and after changes, analyze the relationship between these changes and clinical efficacy to
      explore the neural mechanisms of efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) can modulate neuronal activity and has
      been shown to improve symptoms in patients with schizophrenia, but the underlying neural
      mechanism is unknown.This study hypothesized that repetitive transcranial magnetic
      stimulation of the cerebellar vermis can alter the ciliary-related functional connections in
      schizophrenia, thereby improving negative symptoms, cognitive function, and emotional
      symptoms. Therefore, this study will firstly explore the difference in cerebellar functional
      connectivity between patients and healthy controls, and on this basis, patients undergo a
      resting state functional magnetic resonance scan before and after rTMS intervention in the
      cerebellar vermis, and observe the cerebellar function connection in the treatment. Before
      and after changes, analyze the relationship between these changes and clinical efficacy to
      explore the neural mechanisms of efficacy.

        1. Aim of the study 1.1 Using resting state functional magnetic resonance imaging to
           observe the differences in cerebellar functional connections between schizophrenia
           patients and healthy controls, and to further understand the role of cerebellar
           abnormalities in the clinical symptoms of schizophrenia; 1.2 Provide evidence-based
           evidence and imaging evidence for the clinical efficacy of rTMS intervention in
           cerebellar palsy for patients with schizophrenia, and further understand the neural
           mechanism of efficacy.

        2. Content of the study 2.1 Based on previous studies, this study will use resting-state
           functional magnetic resonance imaging to observe abnormalities in behavioral and
           cerebellar neural networks in patients with schizophrenia compared with healthy
           controls, and to explore these abnormalities and schizophrenia. The relationship between
           clinical symptoms. 2.2 According to the research hypothesis, this study will perform a
           resting-state functional magnetic resonance scan of the patient before and after rTMS
           intervention in the cerebellar vermis. The functional connection analysis method is used
           to observe the changes of the cerebellar nerve network before and after treatment, and
           the imaging data and clinical evaluation. The data of the scale is combined to explore
           the neural mechanisms of treatment.

        3. Study design This study used resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging to
           investigate the differences in cerebrospinal function connections between schizophrenia
           and healthy controls. Based on this, a randomized double-blind control design was used
           to study the repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation of the cerebellar vermis for
           patients with schizophrenia. The clinical efficacy of the treatment and the neural
           mechanisms of the therapeutic effect. Inpatients with schizophrenia were admitted to the
           Shanghai Mental Health Center, and patients who met the criteria and successfully
           enrolled were randomly grouped (by random number table method), corresponding to the
           rTMS true stimulation group or the rTMS pseudo-stimulation group. Except for the rTMS
           operator, neither the patient nor the evaluator of the scale knew the patient's
           grouping.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FCS</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>FCS (functional connectivity strength) value. The Pearson's correlation analysis was used to analyze the time series signals of the brain voxels, and the functional connection matrix model of each subject was established. The gray matter template is used to calculate the mean value of the functional connection between each brain voxel and other voxels, which is the FCS value of the voxel.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PANSS</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The clinical efficacy was determined according to the PANSS reduction rate. The PANSS reduction rate was calculated as the difference between the PANSS total score before and after treatment divided by the pre-treatment PANSS total score. The PANSS reduction rate was judged to be significant progress, progress, and ineffective by 50% to 100%, 20% to 49%, and 0 to 19%, respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>active rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Active rTMS: The magnetic head uses the Magro X100's &quot;8&quot;-shaped coil, and the intervention site is the cerebellar vermis (1 cm below the occipital carina). The stimulation intensity is gradually increased by the 80%-100% exercise threshold according to the patient's tolerance. The total number of stimulation pulses per day is 600, the basic frequency is 5 Hz, and one short burst stimulus is given every 200 milliseconds. In each short array, three single pulses with a frequency of 50 Hz are buried, and every 10 short bursts are stimulated for 8 s. A total of 200 short bursts of stimulation. Intervention once a day, 5 times a week, intervention for 2 weeks, a total of 10 times.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The sham rTMS: The sham stimulation method was to invert the &quot;8&quot; shaped coil, which was 180° to the scalp, and other intervention parameters were consistent with the study group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) is a widely used non-invasive neuromodulation technique that induces excitatory changes in the cerebral cortex stimulated by repeated pulsed magnetic fields on the scalp.</description>
    <arm_group_label>active rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sham rTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient met the diagnostic criteria for schizophrenia in DSM-IV;

          -  18-55 years old;

          -  Right handed;

          -  On stable doses of psychotropic medications.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  DSM-IV diagnosis of other Axis I disorders；

          -  Contraindications to TMS or MRI；

          -  Patients receiving ECT (electro-convulsive therapy) in last 6months；

          -  Left-handedness。
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jun Cai</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shanghai Mental Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hongxia Zhu</last_name>
    <phone>86-13867362975</phone>
    <email>MiyaZhu@sjtu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

