<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03734081</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLD-012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03734081</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Feasibility Assessment of the Bio-electrical One Day Capsule System in Overweight and Class I Obese Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A First in Human (FIH) Study to Assess the Safety and Feasibility of the Bio-electrical One Day Capsule (ODC) System (Type 1 and 2 Capsules) in Overweight and Class 1 Obese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Melcap Systems Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Melcap Systems Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study represents the first effort to prospectively investigate the Melcap's
      bio-electrical ingestible ODC system in human. The study goal is to evaluate the safety and
      feasibility of GES treatment in stomach and in the small and large bowel during and following
      the ingestion of the bio-electrical capsule under tight and controlled conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The problem of obesity in the adult population requires the exploration and development of
      new, safe and effective therapies to combat increasing growth. A novel Implantable Gastric
      Electrical Stimulation (GES), MEASTRO(R) Rechargeable System, has been recently approved by
      the American Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for use in weight reduction in patients aged
      18 years through adulthood who have a Body Mass Index (BMI) of 40 to 45 kg/m2 with one or
      more obesity related co-morbid conditions, and have failed at least one supervised management
      program within the past 5 years.

      Melcap System Ltd. has developed an innovative ingestible capsule system device that uses GES
      for the treatment of overweight and obesity. The system is intended to suppress hunger,
      reduce appetite, increase satiation and promote weight reduction in overweight and class I
      obese adults who have a Body Mass Index of 27 kg/m2 to 34.9 kg/m2 with no related co-morbid
      conditions.

      The study is a FIH prospective, open label, randomized study. It will include a 3 days
      screening period and 4 days treatment session under a close supervision and follow up. Each
      subject will ingest a total of 2 capsules (ODC) on the first and the third day of the study.
      The total duration of subject participation including the termination visit will be eight
      days.

      The study will be conducted at a single medical center, Meir Hospital, Israel.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The first cohort of 6 subjects that has been enrolled is being analyzed and evaluated on all
    safety parameters as described in the study protocol.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence and severity of all adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>During the whole study duration (approximately 8 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of device-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>During the whole study duration (approximately 8 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of clinically significant abnormal laboratory values as determined by the investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>During the whole study duration (approximately 8 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Excretion of the study capsules in a natural manner</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 days after the days of the capsules ingestion</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation - confirmation of the capsule excretion from the body</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satiety levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Day #1 and #3 of the treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in satiety levels resulting of the electrical stimulation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Appetite levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Day #1 and #3 of the treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in appetite levels resulting of the electrical stimulation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postprandial symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Day #1, #2, #3 and #4 of the treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of postprandial symptoms during the treatment period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to nutrient drink test</measure>
    <time_frame>Day #3 of the screening period and and day #4 of the treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of the maximum tolerable drinking volume followed by postprandial symptoms measurement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Appetite-related hormone</measure>
    <time_frame>Day #1 and Day #3 of the treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of appetite- related hormones levels change as a result of the stimulation applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight and Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gastric electrical stimulation with type 2 ODC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Safety and feasibility assessment of the ODC system (type 2) capsule during and following gastric electrical stimulation protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Electrical stimulation with type 2 ODC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Safety and feasibility assessment of the ODC system (type 2) capsule during and following small and large bowel electrical stimulation protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Electrical stimulation with type 1 ODC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Safety and feasibility assessment of the ODC system (type 1 capsule) during and following small and large electrical stimulation protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ODC system (type 1 capsule)</intervention_name>
    <description>ODC (one day capsule) type 1 is ingested by a subject and passes through the gastrointestinal tract. Electrical stimulation is the transferred from the capsule to the surrounding GI tissues. The capsule is excreted from the body through the intestinal tract in a natural manner with bowel movement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Electrical stimulation with type 1 ODC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ODC system (type 2 capsule)</intervention_name>
    <description>ODC (one day capsule) type 2 is ingested by a subject and passes through the gastrointestinal tract. Electrical stimulation is the transferred from the capsule to the surrounding GI tissues. The capsule is excreted from the body through the intestinal tract in a natural manner with bowel movement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Electrical stimulation with type 2 ODC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Gastric electrical stimulation with type 2 ODC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age of 21-65 years old at time of screening

          2. Body mass Index (BMI) &gt;= 27 and &lt;35

          3. The subject has been under routine care of the investigator or another single
             physician that can supply a medical record for at least 4 months prior to enrollment

          4. Female subjects at reproductive age that are tested negative for pregnancy

          5. Women with childbearing potential (i.e., not post-menopausal or surgically sterilized)
             must agree to use adequate birth control methods during the whole study duration

          6. No significant weight loss (&lt;5%) within four months prior to enrollment (by self
             -report)

          7. No recorded or treated psychological disorder(s) for at least six months prior to
             enrollment (by self report)

          8. Not taking anti-depressant medication, for at least six months prior to enrollment.

          9. Willingness to refrain from using prescription, over the counter or herbal weight loss
             products for the duration of he trial.

         10. Personally motivated and willing to comply with all the requirements of the clinical
             trial

         11. Able to understand, read and voluntary sign the inform consent form

         12. Agree and able to sign the consent form for the Pillcam(R) patency capsule test as is
             in use at Meir MC.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History o abdominal or gastrointestinal surgery (appendectomy, hernia repair,
             gynecological surgeries and cholecystectomy more than a year ago are allowed)

          2. Prior bariatric surgery

          3. Implanted electrical stimulation devices (e.g. pacemaker, defibrillator,
             neurostimulator)

          4. Unwillingness to stop medication altering gastric pH and/or affecting GI motility
             during the entire study duration.

          5. Known diagnosed psychiatric conditions that may impair subject's ability to comply
             with the study procedures (by self-report)

          6. Use of anti-psychotic medications

          7. Diagnosed with an eating disorder including bulimia and binge eating

          8. Swallowing difficulties

          9. Significant active or unstable acute or chronic illnesses/ diseases including
             gastrointestinal, systemic (non-gastrointestinal) and psychiatric conditions

         10. Use of another investigation device or agent in the 30 days prior to enrollment

         11. Women who are pregnant, lactating or anticipate to becoming pregnant within the study
             duration

         12. Planned or contemplated use of Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) or any (e.g.
             oncologic) radiation during the course of the trial.

         13. Have a family member who is currently participating in this clinical trial

         14. Any other conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, would make the subject
             unsuitable for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timna Naftali, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Meir Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meir Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kfar Saba</city>
        <zip>4428164</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

