<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03732872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Oxford DC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03732872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epithelial Mesenchymal Transition Markers in OSMF</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk Assessment of Malignant Transformation in Oral Submucous Fibrosis Using Epithelial Mesenchymal Transition (EMT) Signatures in Tissue Samples and Saliva</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Oxford Dental College, Hospital and Research Center, Bangalore, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Credora Life Sciences, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Oxford Dental College, Hospital and Research Center, Bangalore, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Oral Sub mucous Fibrosis (OSMF) is essentially an imbalance between collagen metabolism and
      wound healing mechanism induced by arecanut chewing habit. Clinically the disease progresses
      in stages with patients presenting with burning sensation, intolerance to spicy food,
      vesicles particularly on the palate, ulceration and dryness of the mouth , fibrosis of the
      oral mucosa, leading to lips, tongue, and palate rigidity and finally trismus. As the disease
      is progressively debilitating and has potential to turn in to malignant cancer a study was
      designed to assess if there any tissue or saliva markers that can be assessed for early
      diagnosis and indicate malignant transformation if any.

      Participants who had OSMF and habit history, patients without OSMF but habit history formed
      the case group where as normal patients without OSMF and no habit history were in control
      group. Eligible candidates who consented to participate in study were subjected to biopsy
      procedure and also their saliva samples were collected. Biopsy samples were subjected to
      immunohistochemistry (IHC) and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to assess the EMT markers like
      vimentin, e-cadherin and collagen IV. miRNA copies were extracted from saliva and were
      subjected RT-PCR.

      Research question was:

        1. Is EMT a positive signature in OSMF.

        2. Does histopathological grading and dysplasia in OSMF have any correlation with EMT.

        3. Can aberrant EMT markers be a reliable indicator for risk assessment of early malignant
           transformation.

        4. Can expression of mi RNA 21 in saliva predict the disease severity and more importantly
           assess risk of early malignant transformation in OSMF.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) describes the process whereby cells shed their
      epithelial properties and adopt a more mesenchymal and invasive phenotype. A continuous
      molecular cross talk between epithelial and mesenchymal cells is required during embryonic
      development (epithelial mesenchymal transition) and probably plays an important role in
      pathologic process like wound healing and tumour progression. The development of carcinomas
      is due to the genetic changes within the target epithelium. As there is conversion of normal
      epithelium to potentially malignant and to squamous cell carcinoma, the stroma also changes
      from normal to activated or tumor associated called as the stromal reaction. 10 EMT can
      generate mesenchymal cells that express α-smooth muscle actin (αSMA), as seen in
      myofibroblasts. It is, however, unclear whether functional myofibroblasts seen in fibrosis or
      cancer derived from epithelial or endothelial cells

      Hence EMT markers in OSMF were assessed in this study. the following markers chosen as:

        1. miRNA-21 regulates cell proliferation, apoptosis and the epithelial to mesenchymal
           transition during neoplastic progression and is up regulated in a variety of cancers.An
           increased expression of miRNA-21 is seen in myofibroblasts.12 Since we know the role of
           myofibroblasts in OSMF, salivary expression of mi RNA- 21 was included as marker.

        2. Type IV collagen has the unique feature of self-associating through intramolecular
           covalent bonds, providing barrier and mechanical strength properties to basement
           membranes.The increased collagen deposition in OSMF involves numerous fibroblasts that
           are converted to myofibroblasts found in histologic sections of tissue specimens. an
           altered micro environment or stroma such as persistent myofibroblasts has been shown to
           result in tumorigenesis and tumor progression

        3. Cadherins are a class of type-1 trans-membrane proteins known for its calcium-dependent
           cell-cell adhesion property. E-cadherins are members of this protein family found in
           epithelial cells which serve important roles in cell adhesion by ensuring that cells
           within tissues are bound together. The loss of E-cadherin function or expression has
           been implicated in cancer progression and metastasis.E-cadherin expression in the head
           and neck epithelium is essential for the morphogenesis and homeostasis of epithelial
           tissues. The cadherin-mediated cell-cell contacts are required for the
           anchorage-dependent growth of epithelial cells.

           Hence lower expression of E- cadherin is a sign of loss of epithelial integrity

        4. The intermediate filament protein vimentin is involved in the regulation of cell
           behavior, morphology, and mechanical properties. Vimentin is a EMT marker expressed in
           connective tissue. Expression of vimentin in epithelium is a positive signature of EMT,
           and its evaluation in OSMF can unveil the importance of EMT signature in oral fibrosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 20, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expression of E-cadherin levels in all the groups in IHC</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>For IHC: The criteria used to define E-cadherin positive cells was brown staining in cell membrane of epithelial cells; the percentage of positively stained cells were scored as -
Percentage of POSITIVE CELLS SCORE No cells 0 ≤ 10% 1 11% -50 % 2 51%-80% 3
≥81% 4
Staining Intensity was also assessed in comparison with the positive control tissue and scored accordingly
INTENSITY SCORE Negative 0 Weak 1 Moderate 2 Strong 3</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expression of vimentin levels in all the groups in IHC</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>vimentin positive cells was brown staining in cytoplasm of epithelial cells; the percentage of positively stained cells were scored as -
Percentage of POSITIVE CELLS SCORE No cells 0 ≤ 10% 1 11% -50 % 2 51%-80% 3
≥81% 4
Staining Intensity was also assessed in comparison with the positive control tissue and scored accordingly
INTENSITY SCORE Negative 0 Weak 1 Moderate 2 Strong 3</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expression of collagen IV levels in all the groups in IHC</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>collagen IV positive cells was brown staining in basement membrane cells; the percentage of positively stained cells were scored as -
Percentage of POSITIVE CELLS SCORE No cells 0 ≤ 10% 1 11% -50 % 2 51%-80% 3
≥81% 4
Staining Intensity was also assessed in comparison with the positive control tissue and scored accordingly
INTENSITY SCORE Negative 0 Weak 1 Moderate 2 Strong 3</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expression of miRNA 21 in all three groups using Real Time-PCR</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>Considering the expression of miRNA21 in normal sample (N) as 1, the expression of all the samples were calculated The formula used is: number of copies = (amount * 6.022x1023) / (length * 1x109 * 650)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CHange in E cadherin levels in PCR</measure>
    <time_frame>20 days after sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>After extraction of DNA from biopsy samples the primers for E-cadherin were designed using Primer Express software, synthesized and HPLC purified for real time PCR for quantification.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vimentin levels in PCR</measure>
    <time_frame>20 days after sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>After extraction of DNA from the biopsy samples the primers for Vimentin were designed using Primer Express software, synthesized and HPLC purified for real time PCR for quantification</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in e-cadherin expression with respect to disease category clinically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>E cadherin level in tissue samples with respect to different Clinical expression of disease according to Kerr et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in e-cadherin expression with respect to disease category histologically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>E cadherin level in tissue samples with respect to different Clinical expression of disease according to Kanna and Andrade et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vimentin expression with respect to disease category clinically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>Vimentin level in tissue samples with respect to different Clinical expression according to Kerr et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vimentin expression with respect to disease category histologically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>Vimentin level in tissue samples with respect to different histological expression according to Khanna and Andrade classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in collagen IV expression with respect to disease category clinically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>Collagen-IV level in tissue samples with respect to different Clinical expression category according to Kerr et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in collagen IV expression with respect to disease category hstologically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>Collagen-IV level in tissue samples with respect to different histological expression according to Khanna and Andred et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mi RNA 21 expression with respect to disease category clinically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>miRNA 21 level in saliva samples with respect to different Clinical expression of OSMF according to Kerr et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mi RNA 21 expression with respect to disease category histologically in OSMF patients with habits</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days from sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>miRNA 21 level in saliva samples with respect to different histological expression according to Khanna and Andred et al classification system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">185</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Submucous Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient with habits and having OSMF</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who had history of arecanut chewing habit in any form and composition and who were not undergone any treatment for their current condition i.e, OSMF</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with habits and had no clinical symptoms of OSMF</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who had history of arecanut chewing habit in any form and composition and had no symptoms of OSMF clinically</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy human volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients who reported no history of areacnut chewing habits and had no clinical symptoms of OSMF</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biopsy tissue analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>biopsy samples for IHC staining and PCR</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy human volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patient with habits and having OSMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with habits and had no clinical symptoms of OSMF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saliva analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Saliva samples for miRNA 21 expression analysis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy human volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patient with habits and having OSMF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with habits and had no clinical symptoms of OSMF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      1. Patient tissue samples taken in biopsy from all three groups

        2. Saliva samples taken from all three groups
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects were selected from outpatient department of Dental College OPD
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient who had history of arecanut chewing habit with clinical manifestations of
             OSMF.

          -  Patients who had arecanut chewing habit history of more than 1 year and had no
             clinical symptoms of OSMF.

          -  Healthy human volunteers who are indicated for extraction of tooth and had no clinical
             features of OSMF and had no habit history

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who had bleeding disorders

          -  patients who are diagnosed with salivary gland disorders that can alter salivary flow
             or composition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang Y, Li YX, Yang X, Jiang L, Zhou ZJ, Zhu YQ. Progress risk assessment of oral premalignant lesions with saliva miRNA analysis. BMC Cancer. 2013 Mar 19;13:129. doi: 10.1186/1471-2407-13-129.</citation>
    <PMID>23510112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sawant SS, Vaidya Mm, Chaukar DA, Alam H, Dmello C, Gangadaran P, Kannan S, Kane S, Dange PP, Dey N, Ranganathan K, D'Cruz AK. Clinical significance of aberrant vimentin expression in oral premalignant lesions and carcinomas. Oral Dis. 2014 Jul;20(5):453-65. doi: 10.1111/odi.12151. Epub 2013 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23865921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinto GA, Vassallo J, Andrade LA, Magna LA. Immunohistochemical study of basement membrane collagen IV in uterine cervix carcinoma. Sao Paulo Med J. 1998 Nov-Dec;116(6):1846-51.</citation>
    <PMID>10349192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Oxford Dental College, Hospital and Research Center, Bangalore, India</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Shesha Prasad</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OSMF</keyword>
  <keyword>EMT</keyword>
  <keyword>miRNA 21</keyword>
  <keyword>vimentin</keyword>
  <keyword>e-cadherin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oral Submucous Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

