<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03736434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018H0136</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03736434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Connections and Blood Pressure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brain Connections, Self-care and Blood Pressure in Black and African Americans With Problems With Memory</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot randomized controlled study evaluates Mindfulness and DASH Diet resting state
      network and blood pressure in 36 (n=12 intervention; n=12 attention control; n = 12 control)
      Black and African American older adults with early Alzheimer's disease and related dementia
      disorders and hypertension.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this pilot randomized controlled study is to adapt a previously tested
      intervention to improve resting state network and blood pressure in 36 (n=12 intervention;
      n=12 attention control; n = 12 control) Black and African American older adults with early
      Alzheimer's disease and related dementia disorders and hypertension.

      The study aims are to:

      A.1. Establish the feasibility and acceptability of the intervention in Black and African
      Americans with Alzheimer's disease and related dementia disorders and hypertension.

      H1: The intervention will be feasible and acceptable to Black and African Americans with
      Alzheimer's disease and related dementia disorders. Feasibility will be measured by
      recruitment, attendance, and attrition. Acceptability will be measured by a garnering
      feedback in a debriefing after each session.

      A.2. Determine the effect size of the difference between the intervention, attention control,
      and control groups in resting state network connectivity and working memory and blood
      pressure to inform the sample size for the R01 trial.

      H2: We hypothesize that compared to both control groups; the intervention group will have
      greater improvement in process measures of self-management mechanisms (self-efficacy,
      self-regulation, and emotion regulation), chronic stress, diet, and physical activity. The
      functional magnetic resonance imaging and blood pressure will be obtained at baseline and 3
      months. The intervention group (Mindfulness + DASH) will have improved resting state network
      connectivity and blood pressure as compared to the attention control (2-hour group social
      time and brief lecture on a non-diet/mindfulness topic such as personal safety, fire safety,
      and disaster preparedness) and the control group (care as usual with no intervention). The
      Center for Cognitive and Behavioral Brain Imaging, Arts &amp; Sciences co-investigators will
      analyze imaging data using their newly published statistical network model to quantify the
      subnetwork structures of the resting state network and evaluate changes of their topological
      properties.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Data collectors masked as to the hypotheses of the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Resting State Network</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>functional magnetic resonance imaging scans of brains utilizing and working memory test will be employed to measure change in resting state network</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Omron automatic blood pressure machine with small and large cuff sizes will be used to obtain blood pressure readings</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness plus DASH group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives Mindfulness and DASH Diet education once a week for 8 weeks (2.5-hour sessions)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The sham intervention includes general education on non-health related topics such as fire-safety and learning how to dispose of medication properly, once a week for 8 weeks (2.5-hour sessions)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continue care as usual without intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness and DASH Diet Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Mindfulness and DASH diet education will include a didactic presentation on stress, theoretical material related to mindfulness, the somatic mind/body connection, relaxation, yoga, meditation, self-awareness, and bodily cues relating to emotional reactivity. Practices will include the body scan, gentle yoga movement, walking/sitting meditation, breathing, relaxation. Additionally, daily 20 min individual practices are done at least 5x/week delivered via a compact disc player or on a preloaded device. Each participant is asked to track his/her daily meditation practice and given a diary for adherence records. A combination of didactic, experiential, and &quot;hands-on&quot; activities will be done to deliver DASH diet guidelines.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness plus DASH group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education group</intervention_name>
    <description>The attention control group will attend eight, 2.5 hours sessions on non-health topics such as personal safety, fire prevention, cold weather protection, disaster preparation, internet safety, aging in place, how to know when it's time to move and managing your money.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness plus DASH group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of hypertension with or without medication use

          -  Diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease or related dementia disorder or, if no formal
             diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease, then a Self-Assessment Gerocognitive Evaluation
             score 17-10 or a Montreal Cognitive Assessment Screen 25-19

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to understand spoken English

          -  Expect to move out of the area within six months

          -  fMRI imaging contraindicated (history of shrapnel, metal in the body, heart pacemaker,
             heart defibrillator, metal in the eye, gunshot wound, or some types of metal elsewhere
             within the body such as certain surgical clips for aneurysms in the head, heart valve
             prostheses, electrodes, and some other implanted devices) or claustrophobia. However,
             the participant can be included in the study without fMRI.

          -  Self-reported history of a stroke

          -  &lt;6 on the Brief Assessment of Understanding of the Study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathy D Wright, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kathy D Wright, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>614-292-0309</phone>
    <email>wright.2104@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Salome D Beyene, BA</last_name>
    <email>Beyene.8@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University College of Nursing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Wright</last_name>
      <phone>614-292-0309</phone>
      <email>wright.2104@osu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kathy D. Wright</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild Cognitive impairment (MCI)</keyword>
  <keyword>functional Magnetic resonance Imaging (fMRI)</keyword>
  <keyword>Hair cortisol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

