<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03735927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FTI-820555-DeltaScan-study2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03735927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Evaluation Program of DeltaScan (Ward)</brief_title>
  <official_title>DeltaScan for the Assessment of Delirium in the Ward: a Multicenter Stepped Wedge Cluster Randomized Trial (Study 2).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>KU Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Prolira</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Factory CRO</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Implementation IQ</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Union</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Delirium, or acute brain failure, presents as an acute confusional state, and is
      associated with prolonged hospitalization, an increased risk of dementia,
      institutionalization and mortality, as well as increased costs. Early detection of delirium
      would allow for early treatment and improved patient outcomes, but delirium is often not
      recognized and treatment is therefore delayed or not applied at all. Additionally, current
      screening tools are subjective, so an alternative, more objective diagnostic tool for early
      delirium detection is desired. The DeltaScan, a CE-certified device to detect delirium using
      brief EEG recording, has been recently been found have diagnostic properties that outperform
      the currently used screening tools.

      Objective: To quantify the impact of the use of the DeltaScan on patient outcome (detection
      rate of delirium and duration of admission) in patients with high risk of delirium compared
      to the currently used delirium screening tools.

      Study design: A prospective multicenter stepped wedge cluster randomized trials in (at least)
      6 non-ICU departments.

      Study population: Elderly admitted to non-ICU departments with high risk of delirium.

      Intervention: During 12 months, frail elderly admitted to a non-ICU department of
      participating hospitals with high risk of delirium will be included in the study. First, all
      hospitals will apply 'usual care' to all patients, i.e. standard delirium screening (e.g.
      Delirium Observation Screening (DOS) or other currently used tools) in combination with a
      delirium treatment protocol and subsequent management without application of the DeltaScan
      for a period of 3 months. Then, during a 6 month period, each 5 weeks, starting at day 0,
      randomly allocated hospitals will sequentially start to apply the DeltaScan in all eligible
      patients (intervention period). During the last 3 months of the study all hospitals will
      participate in the intervention period.

      Main study endpoints:

      Primary endpoints: delirium detection rate (i.e. proportion of positive assessments according
      to the delirium detection tool), and duration of admission at the non-ICU department.
      Secondary endpoints: time interval between admission and the first delirium positive
      assessment, number of days with at least one positive delirium assessment, delirium
      incidence, hospital mortality, and direct medical costs of hospitalization.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: During the intervention period EEG recordings using the CE-certified DeltaScan
      will be made using a strip with EEG electrodes that will be mounted to the head using
      self-adhesive gel. The EEG recording will be performed two to three times daily and takes 3-4
      minutes. During the usual care period the patients will receive the standard delirium
      screening tool for delirium assessment by a nurse. This assessment will be performed two to
      three times daily and takes 2-4 minutes depending on the screening tools that is used. Since
      the DeltaScan has shown to have superior diagnostic performance compared to the DSM5 the
      burden/risk of misclassification is lower than with the current standard for delirium
      assessment. Based on the above we consider the burden to participants in this study to be
      minimal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In this study hospital departments will be randomized with respect to the time they will introduce the DeltaScan following a stepped wedge cluster randomization design. All departments apply 'usual care' in combination with a harmonized delirium treatment protocol during the control phase. After this first time period, each new time period a department switches to the intervention period.
This design has a number of advantages. It is especially appropriate when the intervention encompasses the implementation of a change in logistics, procedures, or information use, which is the case in our trial comparing two diagnostic strategies in patients at risk of delirium (usual care delirium screening and the introduction of the DeltaScan). Furthermore, it allows adjusting the implementation to the local setting in each participating hospital. This ensures that the study design more closely resembles daily clinical practice, resulting in realistic effect estimates conform daily practice.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium detection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The detection rate of delirium will be defined as the proportion of delirium positive assessments during conditions that a patient can be assessed for delirium. A positive delirium assessment in the usual care period will be defined as a positive score on the delirium detection tool that is currently used in the participating department according to the protocol of that department. A positive delirium assessment in the intervention period will be defined as a DeltaScan score of 4 or 5.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of admission (days)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of admission will be defined as the length of stay in the non-ICU hospital department (in case of intermediate ICU admission: the cumulative duration of stay in the non-ICU department that participates in this study). The criteria for discharge will be the same in the usual care period and the intervention period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time interval between admission (i.e. admission at the non-ICU departement) and the first delirium positive assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of delirium days</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcomes is defined as the number of days with at least one positive assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of death from any cause during hospitalization, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Direct medical costs of hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>We aim to collect health care consumption in detail for every included patient. This health care consumption for instance consists of number of hospitalization days, medication, diagnostic procedures. These data will be extracted from the hospital systems. General reference prices (open source, National Tariffs) will be applied to this health care consumption to calculate total costs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to new delirium treatment protocol</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Steps that are taken (e.g. pharmacological or non-pharmacological treatment, consults of specialist etc.) by the hospital staff after a delirium screener gives a delirium positive score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days alive without delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Age</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sex</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Type of admission, defined as acute or elective</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reason for not using DeltaScan</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of admission on the ward until date of discharge from the ward or death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3559</enrollment>
  <condition>Delirium</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control phase</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>no intervention, i.e. care as usual</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention phase</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>experimental intervention: spot monitoring device (excl. sham), i.e. use of DeltaScan</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spot monitoring device, excl. Sham</intervention_name>
    <description>During the control phase the 'care as usual' regarding delirium screening is studied. During the intervention phase the DeltaScan will be studied as screening method for delirium. During the intervention phase the DeltaScan will be used on the exact same moments, i.e. same time and same amount of measures per day, as the screening methods used in the 'care as usual'.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention phase</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Admitted to the non-ICU hospital department, defined as a cardio thoracic surgery or
             geriatric traumatology

          -  At risk of delirium, defined according to local protocol:

        A. Frail elderly, defined according to local protocol B. That underwent surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Admitted because of a primary neurological or neurosurgical disease.

          -  Patients who cannot clinically assessed for delirium, e.g. due to a language barrier
             or deafness.

          -  Known pre-existing dementia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arjen JC Slooter, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0031 88 75 596 77</phone>
    <email>A.Slooter-3@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Simone JT van Montfort, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>0031 88 75 578 38</phone>
    <email>s.j.t.vanmontfort-2@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Numan T, van den Boogaard M, Kamper AM, Rood PJT, Peelen LM, Slooter AJC; Dutch Delirium Detection Study Group. Delirium detection using relative delta power based on 1-minute single-channel EEG: a multicentre study. Br J Anaesth. 2019 Jan;122(1):60-68. doi: 10.1016/j.bja.2018.08.021. Epub 2018 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>30579407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Kooi AW, Zaal IJ, Klijn FA, Koek HL, Meijer RC, Leijten FS, Slooter AJ. Delirium detection using EEG: what and how to measure. Chest. 2015 Jan;147(1):94-101. doi: 10.1378/chest.13-3050.</citation>
    <PMID>25166725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>A.J.C. Slooter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Intensive Care Neuropsychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Electroencephalography</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Confusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurobehavioral Manifestations</keyword>
  <keyword>Nervous System Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Signs and Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocognitive Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Mental Disorders</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

