<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03738124</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC31/18/0234</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03738124</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System in Thoracic Aortic Aneurysms and Chronic Dissections</brief_title>
  <acronym>MONA-LSA</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System in Thoracic Aortic Aneurysms and Chronic Dissections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic Vascular</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To ensure adequate seal of currently available stent grafts, a proximal 20 mm of healthy
      aorta is recommended. Extending the proximal landing zone into the arch by intentional
      covering of the left subclavian artery (LSA) without revascularization expose to serious
      neurologic complications. Serious risks are also known to accompany subclavian
      revascularization. The Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System (Medtronic,Santa Rosa,
      Calif) consists of a main stent graft and a branch stent graft designed to maintain LSA
      patency. The purpose of this study is to characterize the safety and effectiveness of this
      device for the treatment of Aneurysms and chronic Type B dissections of the arch.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stent graft coverage of the left subclavian artery (LSA) may be required to achieve an
      adequate landing zone in up to 40% of descending thoracic aneurysms (DTAs). To ensure
      adequate seal of currently available off-the-shelf stent grafts, 20 mm of healthy aorta is
      recommended between the proximal neck of the aneurysm and the leading edge of the stent
      graft. Stent graft placement can be facilitated by extending the proximal landing zone into
      the arch and covering the LSA; however, there may be a higher risk of serious neurologic
      outcomes (cerebral and paraplegia), although this is still a matter of debate. Serious risks
      are also known to accompany subclavian revascularization, which may involve bypass or
      transposition. The Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System (Medtronic,Santa Rosa, Calif)
      consists of a main stent graft and a branch stent graft designed to maintain LSA patency
      while diverting circulation through the encroaching aneurysm.

      The purpose of the feasibility study is to characterize the safety of the Valiant Mona LSA
      Thoracic Stent Graft System, including an assessment of the safety and effectiveness of the
      device acutely and at the 1-month visit in the identified subject population (Aneurysms and
      chronic, Type B dissections). A follow up of this population will be annually during 5 years.

      This pilot, non-randomized, single-arm prospective study will concern 20 patients. Inclusion
      criteria required patients with a thoracic aortic aneurysm (TAA) or dissection with an
      indication of a stent-Graft insertion. Primary end points will be aneurysm-related mortality,
      stroke, paraplegia, left arm/hand ischemia, and treatment success. Technical success will be
      assessed by imaging at 1 month, 6 months then annually during 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety events (aorta related mortality, stroke, paraplegia, left arm/hand ischemia)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Composite endpoint defined as the occurrence of one of the following events: aorta related mortality, stroke, paraplegia, left arm/hand ischemia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Effectiveness defined as technical success and successful exclusion of the aneurysm or false lumen while maintaining patency of the main stent graft (MSG) and branch stent graft (BSG)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aorta related mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of aorta related mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Paraplegia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of paraplegia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left arm/hand ischemia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of left arm/hand ischemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness (Successful exclusion of the aneurysm)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Successful exclusion of the aneurysm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness (patency)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>False lumen while maintaining patency of the main stent graft (MSG) and branch stent graft (BSG)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Necessary time for the branch placement</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Necessary time for the branch placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristics of the intervention (general anaesthesia)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>General anaesthesia performing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristics of the intervention (blood loss)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Blood loss volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristics of the intervention (transfusion)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Transfusion performing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of the stay in intensive care</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of the stay in intensive care</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of the hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of the hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristics of the hospitalization (intraoperative complications)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of intraoperative complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life with EuroQol-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of life will be measured with the EuroQol-5D (5 levels) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minor adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of minor adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months, 48 months and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of serious adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Aneurysm, Thoracic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System is administered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System</intervention_name>
    <description>The Valiant Mona LSA device is a modular two-component system consisting of a main stent graft (MSG) and a branch stent graft (BSG), delivered separately, designed to maintain LSA perfusion. Briefly, under general anesthesia and after heparin injection, a MSG access is achieved via a femoral artery. A Through-and-through wire access for delivery of the BSG is achieved via a brachial artery. After the placement of the main aortic stent graft in the arch with the cuff at the level of the ostium of the LSA, the BSG is placed through a femoral access.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is at least 18 years of age.

          -  Subject understands and has signed an Informed Consent

          -  Subject must be considered a candidate for revascularization of the LSA.

          -  Subject must be able to tolerate a surgical revascularization of the LSA.

          -  Subject has a descending thoracic aneurysm (DTA) which will require coverage of the
             LSA

          -  Subject has a healthy, non-diseased aortic proximal seal zone of at least 10 mm from
             the left carotid to the LSA and at least 5 mm landing zone distal to the LSA and
             proximal to the start of the aneurysm/ulcer/or the proximal entry tear for dissection.

          -  Subject has a non-diseased aortic diameter between 25 mm and 42 mm (fusiform/saccular
             aneurysms or penetrating ulcers) or 28 mm to 44 mm (chronic type B dissections),

          -  Subject has a LSA with a diameter between 8 mm and 13 mm.

          -  Subject has sufficient landing zone within the LSA to accommodate the BSG without
             occlusion of any significant vessels

          -  Subject has patent brachial arteries, iliac or femoral arteries (without
             circumferential calcifications and a diameter of ≥ 10mm), or can tolerate a conduit
             that will allow endovascular access to the aneurysmal site with the delivery system of
             the appropriate sized device chosen for treatment.

          -  Subject has a condition requiring prospective revascularization of the LSA

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has an aneurysmal, tortuous, or atherosclerotic LSA, conflicting the branch
             graft insertion.

          -  Subject has an aortic atheroma classified as grade IV or grade V.

          -  Subject has prohibitive calcification, occlusive disease, or tortuosity of intended
             fixation sites.

          -  Treatment with the Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft system would require
             intentional coverage of the left common carotid artery with the stent graft fabric.

          -  Subject has significant and/or circumferential aortic mural thrombus at either the
             proximal or distal attachment sites that would compromise fixation and seal of the
             device.

          -  Subject is a pregnant or breastfeeding female.

          -  Subject has a known allergy or intolerance to the device components.

          -  Subject is in acute renal failure or has renal insufficiency with a serum creatinine ≥
             2.0 mg/dL or is on dialysis.

          -  Subject has coronary artery disease with unstable angina and has not received
             treatment.

          -  Subject has a connective tissue disease (e.g. Marfan's syndrome, medial degeneration).

          -  Subject has active systemic infection and/or a mycotic aneurysm.

          -  Subject is currently participating in an investigational drug or device clinical trial
             that would interfere with the observations of this study.

          -  Subject has other medical, social, or psychological problems that, in the opinion of
             the investigator, will interfere with treatment and follow-up procedures.

          -  Subject has a life expectancy of less than 1 year.

          -  Subject has a history of bleeding diathesis, coagulopathy, or refuses blood
             transfusion.

          -  Subject has a known hypersensitivity or contraindication to anticoagulants or contrast
             media, which is not amenable to pre-treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hervé ROUSSEAU, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital of Toulouse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hervé ROUSSEAU, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0561322881</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>rousseau.h@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Timone Adultes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13385</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mariangela DE MASI - JACQUIER, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mariangela DE MASI - JACQUIER, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Toulouse, Hôpital Rangueil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hervé ROUSSEAU, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0561322881</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>rousseau.h@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hervé ROUSSEAU, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Pierre BOSSAVY, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bertrand SAINT-LEBES, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stent graft</keyword>
  <keyword>branch stent graft</keyword>
  <keyword>thoracic aneurysm</keyword>
  <keyword>endovascular aortic repair</keyword>
  <keyword>aortic dissection</keyword>
  <keyword>Valiant Mona LSA Thoracic Stent Graft System</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm, Dissecting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm, Thoracic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

