<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03732417</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEIC P18/071</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03732417</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telematic Model Integrated in the Transversal Care of the Secondary Prevention of Patients With Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Telematic Model Integrated in the Transversal Care of the Secondary Prevention of Patients With Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut Investigacio Sanitaria Pere Virgili</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut Investigacio Sanitaria Pere Virgili</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Spain, stroke is the leading cause of death in women and disability in adults, which is
      why it is currently one of the most important public health problems. It is known that the
      main cause of stroke is the lack of control of cardiovascular risk factors (CRF). Strategies
      have been diversified for patients with severe neurological involvement, while those without
      or with mild involvement, susceptible to repeat a stroke, have a very heterogeneous approach.

      Objective: Design, implement and evaluate the effectiveness of the transversal telematic
      model of secondary prevention in patients who have suffered a stroke.

      Methodology: Randomized clinical trial with a control group, open and multicentre. A total of
      70 patients (35 per group) will be included who meet all the inclusion criteria and none of
      exclusion, attended by an acute stroke in the Hospital Verge de la Cinta de Tortosa.
      Variables: sociodemographic and clinical, FRC, stage of change, therapeutic compliance and
      CV. Outcome variables: impact of the stroke using the scale (SIS-16); control of CRF, new
      vascular events and mortality at 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months, integrable in the practice and
      computerized clinical history (HCI). Interventions: control and education for the patient's
      health to promote self-care and empowerment, and enhance pharmacological compliance. The
      telematic model has been developed through clinical practice guides of primary care and the
      most recent publications on the subject referenced. Export of data directly from the HCI.

      Analysis of results with the SPSS 23.0 program, using regression and survival models.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the enrollment, 3, 6 ,12, 18 and 24 months later.</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline The Stroke Impact Scale for disability at 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months. Score range [16-80].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Risk Factor, Cardiovascular</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stroke patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Control group included people with ischemic or haemorragic stroke in Terres de l'Ebre, Spain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telematic model treatment of patients with Stroke</arm_group_label>
    <description>The intervention group included control and education for the patient's health to promote self-care and empowerment, and enhance pharmacological compliance. The telematic model has been developed through clinical practice guides of primary care and the most recent publications on the subject referenced.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Secondary prevention of cardiovascular risk factors</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention group (n=35) Control group (n=35)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telematic model treatment of patients with Stroke</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Calculated for two independent samples, variable SIS stroke impact scale result (DS 1.6).
        Accepting an alpha risk of 0.05 and a beta risk of less than 0.2 in a bilateral contrast,
        35 subjects are needed in the first group and 35 in the second to detect a difference equal
        to or greater than 0.18 units. It is assumed that the common standard deviation is 0.25. A
        tracking loss rate has been estimated of 10%.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female patients ≥18 years old, diagnosed of established ischemic stroke and /
             or TIA and attended by the HTVC neurology service, on discharge from home and with
             habitual residence in the Ebro Lands to be able to follow up .

          -  Informed consent of the signed study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suffering from other neurological injuries that interfere with the follow-up
             (established strokes, with or without MCA deviation, glioblastomas, etc.), life
             expectancy &lt;6 months, modified Rankin scale score (MRS) ≥3 and present language
             barrier and / or aphasia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Silvia Reverté</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tortosa</city>
        <state>Tarragona</state>
        <zip>43500</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Silvia Reverté-Villarroya, PhD</last_name>
      <email>silvia.reverte@urv.cat</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nurse's Role</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>risk factors</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

