<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03733574</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LY03005/CT-USA-106</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03733574</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of LY03005 vs Pristiq</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-Label, 2-Treatment, 2-Sequence, 2-Period Crossover Trial to Assess the Bioequivalence of 80 mg LY03005 to 50 mg Pristiq After Single Dose Administration Under Fasting Conditions to Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Luye Pharma Group Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Luye Pharma Group Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate relative bioavailability between 80 mg LY03005
      oral tablets and 50 mg Pristiq® oral tablets after a single dose of each drug in a cross-over
      2-period design under fasting condition in healthy subjects between 18 and 50 years of age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fifty six (56) eligible subjects will be enrolled and assigned to either Group A or Group B
      at a 1:1 ratio.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 26, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 17, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>concentration-time curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma ODV area under the concentration-time curve (AUC)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 cross-over to Pristiq® (Desvenlafaxine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive an 80 mg oral dose of LY03005. After a washout period of up to 4 days, the subjects will be switched and will receive a 50 mg oral dose of desvenlafaxine (Pristiq®).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pristiq® (Desvenlafaxine) cross-over to LY03005</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive a 50 mg oral dose of desvenlafaxine (Pristiq®) After a washout period of up to 4 days, the subjects will be switched and will receive an 80 mg oral dose of LY03005</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY03005</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: LY03005 80 mg, oral tablets, single dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 cross-over to Pristiq® (Desvenlafaxine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pristiq® (Desvenlafaxine) cross-over to LY03005</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pristiq</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: Pristiq 50 mg, oral tablets, single dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 cross-over to Pristiq® (Desvenlafaxine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pristiq® (Desvenlafaxine) cross-over to LY03005</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Desvenlafaxine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Capable of giving informed consent and complying with trial procedures;

          2. Male and female subjects between the ages of 18 and 50 years, inclusive;

          3. Considered healthy by the Investigator based on a detailed medical history, full
             physical examination, clinical laboratory tests, 12-lead ECG, and vital signs;

          4. Nonsmoker, defined as not having smoked or used any form of tobacco for at least 6
             months before Screening based on subject report;

          5. Body mass index (BMI) of 19 to 30 kg/m2 inclusive and body weight not less than 50 kg;

          6. Willing and able to adhere to trial procedures and to be confined at the clinical
             research unit (CRU).

          7. All female subjects (childbearing potential and non-childbearing potential) must have
             a negative serum pregnancy test result at Screening. In addition, female subjects must
             meet 1 of the following 3 conditions: (i) postmenopausal for at least 12 months
             without an alternative medical cause, (ii) surgically sterile (hysterectomy, bilateral
             oophorectomy, bilateral salpingectomy, or bilateral tubal occlusion) based on subject
             report, or (iii) if of childbearing potential and heterosexually active, practicing or
             agree to practice a highly effective method of contraception. Highly effective methods
             of birth control include an intrauterine device (IUD), intrauterine hormone-releasing
             system (IUS), and contraceptives (oral, skin patches, or implanted or injectable
             products) using combined or progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with
             inhibition of ovulation. A vasectomized male partner is an acceptable birth control
             method if the vasectomized partner is the sole sexual partner of the female subject
             and the vasectomized partner has received medical confirmation of surgical success.

        Highly effective methods of birth control must be used for at least 14 days prior to study
        drug dosing, through the end of study (EOS) visit or early termination, and for a minimum
        of 1 month after the last dose of study drug to minimize the risk of pregnancy. Sexually
        active, fertile, male subjects must be willing to use acceptable contraception methods
        (such as double-barrier methods of a combination of male condom with either cap, diaphragm,
        or sponge with spermicide) from the first dose of study drug through the EOS visit or early
        termination, and for a minimum of 1 month after the last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinically significant past medical history of gastrointestinal, cardiovascular,
             musculoskeletal, endocrine, hematologic, psychiatric (including life-long history of
             depression and/or anxiety), renal, hepatic, bronchopulmonary, neurologic, immunologic,
             ophthalmological, or lipid metabolism disorders; or drug hypersensitivity; or any
             other condition that in the judgement of the Investigator will affect the trial
             results or the subject's safety;

          2. History of suicide attempt in the past 12 months and/or seen by the Investigator as
             having a significant history of risk of suicide or homicide;

          3. History or presence of malignancy other than adequately treated and cured basal cell
             carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma (skin cancer);

          4. Clinically relevant illness within 1 month prior to Screening or at Screening that may
             interfere with the conduct of this trial;

          5. Medically uncontrolled high blood pressure with mean systolic blood pressure &gt;140 mmHg
             or mean diastolic blood pressure &gt;90 mmHg at Screening after 3 measurements (after at
             least 5 minutes of rest in a seated position);

          6. History of Long QT Syndrome (LQTS) or a marked baseline prolongation of QT/QTc
             interval (e.g., repeated demonstration of a QTc interval &gt;450 ms);

          7. Positive blood screen for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B surface
             antigen (HBsAg), or hepatitis C antibody;

          8. History of seizure (history of febrile seizure allowed);

          9. Hospital admission or major surgery within 30 days prior to Screening;

         10. Participation in any other investigational drug trial within 30 days prior to
             Screening;

         11. History of prescription drug abuse or illicit drug use within 6 months prior to
             Screening;

         12. History of alcohol abuse according to medical history within 6 months prior to
             Screening;

         13. Positive screen for alcohol and/or drugs of abuse;

         14. Tobacco use within 6 months prior to Screening based on positive nicotine screen;

         15. History of intolerance or hypersensitivity to ODV or medicines containing ODV or its
             precursor venlafaxine;

         16. Participation in a previous clinical trial of either LY03005 or ODV or medicines
             containing ODV or its precursor, venlafaxine, within 30 days prior to Screening;

         17. Unwillingness or inability to comply with food and beverage restrictions during trial
             participation;

         18. Donation of blood of more than 1 unit (approximate 450 mL) or blood products or acute
             loss of blood during the 90 days prior to Screening;

         19. Use of prescription or over-the-counter (OTC) medications and/or herbals (including St
             John's Wort, herbal teas, garlic extracts) within 14 days prior to dosing (Note: Use
             of acetaminophen at &lt;3g/day is permitted until 24 hours prior to dosing).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Sun, MD, PhD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Luye Pharma Group Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pharmaron CPC, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://druginfo.nlm.nih.gov/drugportal/</url>
    <description>Drug information</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://druginfo.nlm.nih.gov/drugportal/name/Desvenlafaxine</url>
    <description>Desvenlafaxine</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://druginfo.nlm.nih.gov/drugportal/name/desvenlafaxine%20succinate</url>
    <description>Desvenlafaxine Succinate</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/info/fdalinks</url>
    <description>U.S. FDA Resources</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2012/021992s030lbl.pdf</url>
    <description>Pristiq (Desvenlafaxine) Label - FDA</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depressive Disorder, Major</keyword>
  <keyword>Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Mood Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Mental Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Desvenlafaxine Succinate</keyword>
  <keyword>Serotonin and Noradrenaline Reuptake Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurotransmitter Uptake Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Membrane Transport Modulators</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular Mechanisms of Pharmacological Action</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurotransmitter Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiological Effects of Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Antidepressive Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychotropic Drugs</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Desvenlafaxine Succinate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

