<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03866538</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-008639</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03866538</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Budesonide in Patients With Immune Mediated Enteropathies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-label Withdrawal Trial of Budesonide in Patients With Immune Mediated Enteropathies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Researchers are trying to determine if withdrawal of budesonide therapy in patients with
      immune-mediated enteropathies doing well on therapy will result in worsening symptoms,
      histology, quality of life, and micronutrient/nutritional status when compared to continued
      therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to evaluate patients with small intestinal diseases caused by the immune
      system (refractory celiac disease type 1, CVID enteropathy, autoimmune enteropathy, and
      collagenous enteropathy) who have had improvement in symptoms and small intestine healing
      with oral budesonide.

      Patients who meet inclusion criteria and agree to enter the study will be included for 12
      weeks or until they choose to discontinue or there are concerns for safety.

      At the beginning of the study, patients will undergo questionnaires, blood draw, urine and
      stool collections, physical exam, and an upper scope (esophagogastroduodenoscopy) with
      biopsies from the small intestine. They will then be randomized to either continued therapy
      on their current dose and formulation of budesonide (medication provided by the study) or to
      withdrawal of the medication over 2 weeks and then no medication during the study. Daily
      questionnaire on symptoms will be recorded.

      Patients will be assessed in the clinical research unit monthly during the study with a
      questionnaire, physical exam, blood draw, and urine/stool collections.

      Finally, at the end of the trial (12 weeks) or at the time of withdrawal from the trial, the
      patients will complete questionnaires, physical exam, blood collection, urine/stool
      collection, and upper scope (esophagogastroduodenoscopy) with small bowel biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, open-label withdrawal of budesonide versus continued budesonide therapy in patients with immune-mediated enteropathies that have had symptomatic and histologic improvement</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Histology</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will determine change in small bowel villi after withdrawal of budesonide compared to continued therapy to assess small intestinal injury. This will be accomplished by esophagogastroduodenoscopy (upper scope) with biopsies from the small intestine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms (monitored daily) will be compared between patients that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue budesonide therapy. Symptoms will be measured on the Celiac Disease Symptom Diary (CDSD) questionnaire. First question asks if subject has diarrhea and how many times. Second question asks if subject has spontaneous bowel movement and how many. Third question asks if subject had abdominal pain and to rate on a scale from 0 to 10 with higher numbers being worse pain. Fourth question asks if experiencing bloating and if it is very mild, mild, moderate, severe, or very severe. Fifth question asks if subject has nausea and if it is ranked very mild, mild, moderate, severe, or very severe. The sixth question asks if the subject has experienced tiredness and to rank very mild, mild, moderate, severe or very severe. Each question is evaluated for changes or trends over time, and a composite score including multiple questions can be calculated and compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life: Celiac Disease Quality of Life Questionnaire (CD-QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be assessed monthly comparing those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed by the Celiac Disease Quality of Life Questionnaire (CD-QOL). This survey includes 20 questions with scores for each ranging from 1 to 5, with higher numbers indicating improved quality of life. Total scores will range from 20 to 100 with higher numbers indicating better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Weight in kilograms will be monitored throughout the study. Changes will be compare between those withdrawing from budesonide compared to those continuing therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Iron</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Iron in the blood will be compared to those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed at the initiation and completion of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Vitamin D</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>25-hydroxy vitamin D in the blood will be compared to those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed at the initiation and completion of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Vitamin B12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vitamin B12 in the blood will be compared to those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed at the initiation and completion of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Folate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Folate in the blood will be compared to those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed at the initiation and completion of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Zinc</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Zinc in the blood will be compared to those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed at the initiation and completion of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Copper</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Copper in the blood will be compared to those that withdraw from budesonide compared to those that continue therapy. This will be assessed at the initiation and completion of the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Enteropathy</condition>
  <condition>Celiac Disease</condition>
  <condition>CVID Enteropathy</condition>
  <condition>Collagenous Sprue</condition>
  <condition>Autoimmune Enteropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continued Budesonide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this arm continue budesonide at the dose they were taking at the time of enrollment in the trial</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Withdrawal of Budesonide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients are weaned off of budesonide over 2 weeks and continued off of the medication for the duration of the trial</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Withdrawal of Oral Budesonide</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention arm will taper and stop budesonide therapy (withdrawal).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Withdrawal of Budesonide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Patients will be recruited from the Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology and
             the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, MN.

          -  Adult patients with immune mediated enteropathies who have had improvement in symptoms
             and histology on oral budesonide therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Positive stool gluten testing in patients with refractory celiac disease

          -  Small bowel malignancy or history of small bowel malignancy

          -  Refractory celiac disease type 2

          -  Post-transplant lymphoproliferative disorder associated enteropathy

          -  No prior improvement in symptoms and histology with budesonide therapy

          -  Discontinuation of budesonide therapy prior to the trial

          -  Other concurrent systemic corticosteroids

          -  Other immune mediating medications, for example but not limited to azathioprine,
             6-mercaptopurine, cyclosporine, methotrexate, anti-TNF monoclonal antibodies, alpha-4
             beta-7 integrin inhibiting monoclonal antibody, interleukin 12/23 inhibiting
             monoclonal antibody, JAK inhibitors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph A Murray, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carol T Van Dyke, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>507-266-7842</phone>
    <email>VanDyke.Carol@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carol T Van Dyke, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>507-266-7842</phone>
      <email>VanDyke.Carol@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph A Murray, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ludvigsson JF, Leffler DA, Bai JC, Biagi F, Fasano A, Green PH, Hadjivassiliou M, Kaukinen K, Kelly CP, Leonard JN, Lundin KE, Murray JA, Sanders DS, Walker MM, Zingone F, Ciacci C. The Oslo definitions for coeliac disease and related terms. Gut. 2013 Jan;62(1):43-52. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301346. Epub 2012 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22345659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choung RS, Unalp-Arida A, Ruhl CE, Brantner TL, Everhart JE, Murray JA. Less Hidden Celiac Disease But Increased Gluten Avoidance Without a Diagnosis in the United States: Findings From the National Health and Nutrition Examination Surveys From 2009 to 2014. Mayo Clin Proc. 2016 Dec 5. pii: S0025-6196(16)30634-6. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2016.10.012. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>28017411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leffler DA, Dennis M, Hyett B, Kelly E, Schuppan D, Kelly CP. Etiologies and predictors of diagnosis in nonresponsive celiac disease. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2007 Apr;5(4):445-50. Epub 2007 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>17382600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubio-Tapia A, Murray JA. Classification and management of refractory coeliac disease. Gut. 2010 Apr;59(4):547-57. doi: 10.1136/gut.2009.195131. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20332526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mukewar SS, Sharma A, Rubio-Tapia A, Wu TT, Jabri B, Murray JA. Open-Capsule Budesonide for Refractory Celiac Disease. Am J Gastroenterol. 2017 Jun;112(6):959-967. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2017.71. Epub 2017 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>28323276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenberg GR, Feagan BG, Martin F, Sutherland LR, Thomson AB, Williams CN, Nilsson LG, Persson T. Oral budesonide for active Crohn's disease. Canadian Inflammatory Bowel Disease Study Group. N Engl J Med. 1994 Sep 29;331(13):836-41.</citation>
    <PMID>8078529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campieri M, Ferguson A, Doe W, Persson T, Nilsson LG. Oral budesonide is as effective as oral prednisolone in active Crohn's disease. The Global Budesonide Study Group. Gut. 1997 Aug;41(2):209-14.</citation>
    <PMID>9301500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tremaine WJ, Hanauer SB, Katz S, Winston BD, Levine JG, Persson T, Persson A; Budesonide CIR United States Study Group. Budesonide CIR capsules (once or twice daily divided-dose) in active Crohn's disease: a randomized placebo-controlled study in the United States. Am J Gastroenterol. 2002 Jul;97(7):1748-54.</citation>
    <PMID>12135030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubio-Tapia A, Malamut G, Verbeek WH, van Wanrooij RL, Leffler DA, Niveloni SI, Arguelles-Grande C, Lahr BD, Zinsmeister AR, Murray JA, Kelly CP, Bai JC, Green PH, Daum S, Mulder CJ, Cellier C. Creation of a model to predict survival in patients with refractory coeliac disease using a multinational registry. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2016 Oct;44(7):704-14. doi: 10.1111/apt.13755. Epub 2016 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27485029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph A. Murray, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Celiac Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Collagenous Sprue</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Budesonide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

