<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03860909</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AssiutU10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03860909</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pelvic Endometriosis: Correlation of US and MRI With Laparoscopic Findings</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Pelvic Endometriosis: Correlation of US and MRI With Laparoscopic Findings</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endometriosis is classically defined as the presence of endometrial glands and stroma outside
      the uterine cavity and its musculature.

      The definition of deep endometriosis is based on anatomic assumptions that may prove
      erroneous.

      In fact, the term '' deep endometriosis '' should be reserved for lesions in the
      retroperitoneal tissue. For practical purposes, several reports included in the so-called
      deep endometriosis the infiltrative forms that involve vital structures such as the bowel,
      ureters, and bladder, as well as forms such as many rectovaginal lesions. For the term
      ''deep'' to apply, there should be ectopic endometrial tissue penetrating the peritoneum more
      than 5 mm in depth.

      The ectopic endometrium responds to hormonal stimulation with various degrees of cyclic
      hemorrhage which result in suggestive symptoms and appearances.

      A common symptom is infertility. Pelvic pain is a frequent complaint among patients with
      endometriosis. Such pain generally manifests as secondary dysmenorrhea, worsening primary
      dysmenorrhea, dyspareunia, or even noncyclic lower abdominal pain and backaches. The pain may
      be site-specific when endometriosis is found in unusual locations outside the pelvis.

      Diagnosis Physical examination and laparoscopic exploration may not allow diagnosis or
      prediction of the extension of deep pelvic endometriosis, especially in pelvic
      retroperitoneal sites.

      Transvaginal sonography is recommended for diagnosis of endometriomas and endometriosis of
      the bladder but its value for assessment of superficial peritoneal lesions, ovarian foci, and
      deep pelvic endometriosis is uncertain.

      MR imaging is now commonly used for diagnosis of endometriosis and provides a tremendous
      advantage over other methods of investigation, owing to the possibility of making a complete
      survey of the anterior and posterior compartments of the pelvis at one time.

      MRI is becoming a mainstay of preoperative diagnosis, in particular for diagnosis deep
      infiltrating endometriosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective study including 30 Female patients of reproductive who were previously
      clinically diagnosed to have endometriotic lesions. these will be sent to our department to
      identify the extent of the lesions and clarify the exact location for proper treatment.

      All patients were evaluated with ultrasound and MRI. the sensitivity, specificity and
      diagnostic accuracy for both examination were calculated.

      Transvaginal ultrasound and MRI will be done in our Radiology department to all patients
      after signing an informed consent to be enrolled in the study.

      All our imaging results were finally compared to the laparoscopic results which are our gold
      standard.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Mri with Us in correlation with laparoscopic findings in female patients with endometriosis</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>comparison between MRI imaging and ultrasound combined with laproscopy in diagnosis of endometriosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The additive value of Mri in diagnosis of endometriosis</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>MRI better than ultrasound in diagnosis of endometriosis in correlated with laproscopy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometriosis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        females with endometriosis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female patients who have symptoms consistent with endometriosis such as pelvic pain,
             dysmenorrhea, deep dyspareunia, and infertility

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The common contraindication to MRI, peacemaker, metallic foreign bodies, and
             claustrophobia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amal y Abd ellah, MIS</last_name>
    <phone>01068440071</phone>
    <email>amlyusef123@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Reham A Abdel-Aleem, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01006464101</phone>
    <email>rehamali79@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrao MS, Gonçalves MO, Dias JA Jr, Podgaec S, Chamie LP, Blasbalg R. Comparison between clinical examination, transvaginal sonography and magnetic resonance imaging for the diagnosis of deep endometriosis. Hum Reprod. 2007 Dec;22(12):3092-7. Epub 2007 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>17947378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anaf V, Simon P, El Nakadi I, Fayt I, Buxant F, Simonart T, Peny MO, Noel JC. Relationship between endometriotic foci and nerves in rectovaginal endometriotic nodules. Hum Reprod. 2000 Aug;15(8):1744-50.</citation>
    <PMID>10920097</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bazot M, Malzy P, Cortez A, Roseau G, Amouyal P, Daraï E. Accuracy of transvaginal sonography and rectal endoscopic sonography in the diagnosis of deep infiltrating endometriosis. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2007 Dec;30(7):994-1001.</citation>
    <PMID>17992706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ros C, Martínez-Serrano MJ, Rius M, Abrao MS, Munrós J, Martínez-Zamora MÁ, Gracia M, Carmona F. Bowel Preparation Improves the Accuracy of Transvaginal Ultrasound in the Diagnosis of Rectosigmoid Deep Infiltrating Endometriosis: A Prospective Study. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2017 Nov - Dec;24(7):1145-1151. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2017.06.024. Epub 2017 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>28673872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang JL. Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging of the Kidneys-With and Without Gadolinium-Based Contrast. Adv Chronic Kidney Dis. 2017 May;24(3):162-168. doi: 10.1053/j.ackd.2017.03.006. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28501079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whittaker CS, Coady A, Culver L, Rustin G, Padwick M, Padhani AR. Diffusion-weighted MR imaging of female pelvic tumors: a pictorial review. Radiographics. 2009 May-Jun;29(3):759-74; discussion 774-8. doi: 10.1148/rg.293085130. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19448114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcal L, Nothaft MA, Coelho F, Choi H. Deep pelvic endometriosis: MR imaging. Abdom Imaging. 2010 Dec;35(6):708-15. doi: 10.1007/s00261-010-9611-y. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20390267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koninckx PR, Martin D. Treatment of deeply infiltrating endometriosis. Curr Opin Obstet Gynecol. 1994 Jun;6(3):231-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8038409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mais V, Guerriero S, Ajossa S, Angiolucci M, Paoletti AM, Melis GB. The efficiency of transvaginal ultrasonography in the diagnosis of endometrioma. Fertil Steril. 1993 Nov;60(5):776-80.</citation>
    <PMID>8224260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guerriero S, Mais V, Ajossa S, Paoletti AM, Angiolucci M, Labate F, Melis GB. The role of endovaginal ultrasound in differentiating endometriomas from other ovarian cysts. Clin Exp Obstet Gynecol. 1995;22(1):20-2.</citation>
    <PMID>7736636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fedele L, Bianchi S, Raffaelli R, Portuese A. Pre-operative assessment of bladder endometriosis. Hum Reprod. 1997 Nov;12(11):2519-22.</citation>
    <PMID>9436698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roseau G, Dumontier I, Palazzo L, Chapron C, Dousset B, Chaussade S, Dubuisson JB, Couturier D. Rectosigmoid endometriosis: endoscopic ultrasound features and clinical implications. Endoscopy. 2000 Jul;32(7):525-30.</citation>
    <PMID>10917184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amal yusef</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometriosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

