<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03868878</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03868878</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Capoeira Training Decrease Plasma Triglycerides</brief_title>
  <official_title>Twelve Weeks of Capoeira Training Decrease Plasma Triglycerides in Advanced-age Frail Adults of a Long-term Institution</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Federal do vale do São Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regional Hospital of Juazeiro, BA, Brazil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Research support foundation of the Pernambuco State - FACEPE, Brazil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Federal do vale do São Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Among the risk factors associated with aging, a special highlight has been
      attributed to cardiovascular dysfunctions, insulin resistance, central obesity and
      dyslipidemia, which is marked by low levels of cholesterol (high density lipoprotein) and in
      particular by high levels of plasma triglycerides. Individuals with high levels of plasma
      triglycerides tend to have a prolonged postprandial hypertriglyceridemia after a fat-meal
      challenge, which would potentially further increase the risk associated with cardiovascular
      disease. Due to the impact of aging and its associated risk factors on the older adults
      health, several strategies have been proposed to avoid the progression of chronic diseases.
      These diseases are frequent in this population, especially the ones that resides in long-term
      institutions and they are mainly characterized by sedentary lifestyle and functional
      inability. Systematic reviews have shown that the implementation of physical activity
      programs associated with a favorable dietary pattern may benefit the lipid profile of the
      older adults. Moreover, it is suggested as a primary strategy, the realization of physical
      exercise as a therapy for this disease. In the physical exercise programs aspects,
      unconventional modalities such as Capoeira, which is practiced in more than 150 countries, it
      has aroused interest in the scientific research. Characterized by a system composed by attack
      and defense movements and from Afro-Brazilian origin, Capoeira combines sports elements of
      the fight, gymnastics, dance and musicality. However, there is no study investigating the
      effect of Capoeira training on the lipid profile of older adults, which would have an
      important clinical application in the health of this population, especially living in
      conditions of sedentarism and frailty in long-term institutions.

      Aim: The present study analyzed the effects of twelve weeks of Capoeira training on the lipid
      profile of advanced-age frail adults of a long-term institution, which are characterized by
      sedentary lifestyle and affected by several diseases.

      Methods: Participants were assigned into two groups (CONTROL: n = 07; 82.4±13.6 years and
      CAPOEIRA: n = 07; 79.4±6.9 years). The CAPOEIRA group performed twelve weeks of Capoeira
      training program, being twice a week lasting 60 minutes each at light to moderate intensity.
      Samples of 10 ml of blood were collected from participants' antecubital vein at the pre- and
      post-intervention moments in both groups. Plasma concentrations of triglycerides, total
      cholesterol, low density lipoprotein cholesterol and high density lipoprotein cholesterol
      were evaluated using the enzymatic colorimetric method. Anthropometry measures were performed
      and to internal control the energy consumption evaluations were carried out through daily
      food diaries during intervention period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 18, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline triglycerides concentration at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- (week zero) and Post- (through study completion, 12 weeks) in Capoeira training group and Control group</time_frame>
    <description>Samples of 10 ml of blood (to analyse triglycerides concentration in mg.dL-1) were collected from participants' antecubital vein from a 12-hour fast at the pre- and post-intervention moments of the CONTROL and CAPOEIRA groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Conditioning, Human</condition>
  <condition>Lipid Metabolism</condition>
  <condition>Aged</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Capoeira training group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental protocol for Capoeira program lasted 12 weeks and was performed twice a week with duration of 60 minutes each with warm-up, basic movements in the modality, and 20 minutes with theoretical instructions related to Capoeira and musicality.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>While the Capoeira group performed the entire class, the Control group performed only the final part (20 minutes) with musicality - singing and touch of typical instruments - and theoretical instructions related to Capoeira.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capoeira training</intervention_name>
    <description>The Capoeira training protocol, based in the modern styles was applied by an instructor with 16 years of experience. The protocol followed the directions of the ABADÁ Capoeira system, being adapted to the sample of older adults of the present study. The experimental protocol for Capoeira progressive training program lasted 12 weeks and was performed twice a week with duration of 60 minutes each. Each session was divided in three parts, being: 1) initial part: consisting of 10 minutes warm-up with recreational activities at low intensity; 2) main part: consisting of 30 minutes of basic movements in the modality and; 3) final part: consisting of 20 minutes with theoretical instructions related to Capoeira and musicality (singing and touch of typical instruments). In order to perform the Capoeira progressive training program, the technical improvement naturally occurred every week, resulting in a higher speed in movements execution and thus to a gradual increase in training intensity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Capoeira training group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Physical training: attack / defense movements</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age greater than 60 years;

          -  is not engaged in physical exercise programs for at least one year;

          -  do not present severe cardiovascular disease, kidney disease, liver disease or
             limiting cognitive or neuromuscular disease and;

          -  does not present visual or auditory inability.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  failing to perform any of the evaluations suggested during the intervention protocol
             and;

          -  absence in five or more Capoeira training sessions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sérgio R Moreira, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Vale do São Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Federal University of Vale do São Francisco (UNIVASF).</name>
      <address>
        <city>Petrolina</city>
        <state>Pernambuco</state>
        <zip>56304-205</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreira SR, Teixeira-Araujo AA, Dos Santos AO, Simões HG. Ten weeks of capoeira progressive training improved cardiovascular parameters in male practitioners. J Sports Med Phys Fitness. 2017 Mar;57(3):289-298. doi: 10.23736/S0022-4707.16.06030-8. Epub 2016 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26842867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreira SR, Teixeira-Araujo AA, Numata Filho ES, Moraes MR, Simões HG. Psychophysiological characterization of different capoeira performances in experienced individuals: A randomized controlled trial. PLoS One. 2018 Nov 15;13(11):e0207276. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0207276. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30440010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreira SR, Carvalho FO, Moraes JFVN, Carvalho RGS, Araújo RC, Teixeira-Araújo AA, Okano AH. Eight weeks of Capoeira progressive training program increases flexibility of beginners. Sport Sci Health 12: 329-337, 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Federal do vale do São Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sérgio Rodrigues Moreira</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor (PhD)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Capoeira Training (martial arts)</keyword>
  <keyword>Triglycerides</keyword>
  <keyword>Aging</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

