<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03862313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201802353</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03862313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Repetitive Transorbital Alternating Current Stimulation in Acute Autoimmune Optic Neuritis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACSON</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessing Repetitive Transorbital Alternating Current Stimulation in Acute Autoimmune Inflammatory Optic Neuritis Using the NextWave® 1.1 System: A Prospective, Randomized, Patient-blinded, Sham-controlled Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Zürich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss MS Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Data Management, Clinical Trials Center, Zurich, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Optic neuritis (ON) is an acute inflammatory, demyelinating attack of the optic nerve that
      triggers neurodegeneration in the entire visual pathway; translating into visual dysfunction.
      Currently, no neuroprotective therapy with satisfying evidence can be offered to patients.
      Repetitive transorbital alternating current stimulation (rtACS) is a methodology applied to
      electrically stimulate the retina and the optic nerve and is considered having
      neuroprotective- and restorative potential. The goal of this pilot study is to assess safety,
      tolerability and preliminary efficacy of rtACS as a treatment to improve visual functional as
      well as structural retinal outcomes in patients with a first-ever episode of autoimmune acute
      ON.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary functional outcome measure will be low-contrast visual acuity [LogMAR] at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary structural outcome measure will be the mean change in macular ganglion cell and inner plexiform layer thickness [µm] of the affected ON eye at 16 weeks in comparison to baseline of the unaffected contralateral NON eye (pre-treatment).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), 3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary safety outcome measure will be the total number of adverse events during the entire study period</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low-contrast visual acuity [LogMAR] at 4 (post-treatment) weeks in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The mean change in macular ganglion cell and inner plexiform layer thickness [µm] of the affected ON eye at 4 weeks in comparison to baseline of the unaffected contralateral NON eye (pre-treatment).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>High-contrast visual acuity [LogMAR] at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>High-contrast visual acuity [LogMAR] at 4 weeks (post-treatment) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Colour vision [tritan] at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Colour vision [tritan] at 4 weeks (post-treatment) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual field testing [dB] at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual field testing [dB] at 4 weeks (post-treatment) in ON eyes.</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery of pattern-reversal visual evoked potential conduction velocity of the affected optic nerve [ms] compared to the intra-individual baseline of the unaffected optic nerve at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), 3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported vision-related quality of life assessed by the National Eye Institute Visual Function Questionnaire-25 (NEI-VFQ-25) at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
    <description>The questionnaire contains the following 12 sub-scales: general health, general vision, ocular pain, near activities, distance activities, vision-specific social functioning, vision-specific mental health, vision-specific role difficulties, vision-specific dependency, driving, colour vision and peripheral vision. The mean VFQ-25 composite score (calculated as an unweighted average of responses to all items except for the general health sub-scale) and selected sub-scale scores will be analysed. Each sub-scale, and also the composite score, will be quantified with values between 0-100, with zero being the worst and 100 being the best.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported vision-related quality of life assessed by the National Eye Institute Visual Function Questionnaire-25 (NEI-VFQ-25) at 4 weeks (post-treatment).</measure>
    <time_frame>post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
    <description>The questionnaire contains the following 12 sub-scales: general health, general vision, ocular pain, near activities, distance activities, vision-specific social functioning, vision-specific mental health, vision-specific role difficulties, vision-specific dependency, driving, colour vision and peripheral vision. The mean VFQ-25 composite score (calculated as an unweighted average of responses to all items except for the general health sub-scale) and selected sub-scale scores will be analysed. Each sub-scale, and also the composite score, will be quantified with values between 0-100, with zero being the worst and 100 being the best.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The mean change in peripapillary retinal nerve fibre layer (pRNFL) thickness [µm] of the affected ON eye at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up) in comparison to baseline of the contralateral NON eye.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), 3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The mean change in peripapillary retinal nerve fibre layer (pRNFL) thickness [µm] of the affected ON eye at 4 weeks (post-treatment) in comparison to baseline of the contralateral NON eye.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The mean change in macular inner nuclear layer (INL) thickness [µm] of the affected ON eye at 16 weeks (3 month follow-up) in comparison to baseline of the contralateral NON eye.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), 3 month follow-up (16 weeks after recruitment, i.e. 3 months after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The mean change in macular inner nuclear layer (INL) thickness [µm] of the affected ON eye at 4 (post-treatment) weeks in comparison to baseline of the contralateral NON eye.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (pre-treatment, i.e. 1 week after recruitment), post-treatment (4 weeks after recruitment, i.e. one week after the last treatment day)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Autoimmune Inflammatory Optic Neuritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>active-rtACS arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active rtACS on 10 consecutive working days, in addition to standard-of-care corticosteroid treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham-rtACS arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham rtACS on 10 consecutive working days, in addition to standard-of-care corticosteroid treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>active-rtACS treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>For the active-rtACS treatment arm, a CE-certificated proprietary class IIa medical device will be used to apply transorbital symmetrical rectangular current pulses in bursts (NextWave® 1.1 system; EBS Technologies GmbH, Germany). The stimulation protocol will be patient-individualized, with a stimulation current strength of 125% of the phosphene threshold recorded during 5Hz stimulation and stimulation frequencies between the individual's EEG alpha frequency and their flicker fusion frequency.</description>
    <arm_group_label>active-rtACS arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NextWave® 1.1 system, EBS Technologies GmbH, Germany</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sham-rtACS treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>For the sham-rtACS treatment arm, exactly the same medical device, setup, time schedule, etc. will be used as for the patients of the active-rtACS arm. However, sham-treated patients will receive no actual current stimulation during the therapy sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>sham-rtACS arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NextWave® 1.1 system, EBS Technologies GmbH, Germany</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants fulfilling all of the following inclusion criteria are eligible for the study:

          -  Informed Consent as documented by signature

          -  Participants are capable of giving informed consent

          -  Participant who have a good knowledge of German (patient information and consent must
             be understood)

          -  Patients, presenting with typical signs and symptoms suggestive of a first-ever
             episode of unilateral acute autoimmune, inflammatory, demyelinating ON, including
             idiopathic ON and ON suggestive of multiple sclerosis (MS) (typical clinically
             isolated syndrome, or with an established diagnosis of relapsing-remitting MS
             according to latest panel criteria and no better explanation)

          -  Patients with high-contrast visual acuity of ≤ 0.63 (decimal system) corresponding to
             a LogMAR value of ≥ 0.2 on the affected eye (assessed using a Snellen chart during
             clinical routine)

          -  Patients presenting in clinics within 14 days of symptom onset

          -  In principle 18-50 year old female and male patients may be recruited. However, since
             the randomization of patients will be controlled for gender and participants will be
             enrolled one at a time on a continuous basis, the gender might become relevant late in
             the study (e.g. if the female block has already been fully recruited and only males
             might still be enrolled).

          -  Patients are receiving standard-of-care treatment for ON (cortisone therapy)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The presence of any one of the following exclusion criteria will lead to exclusion of the
        participant:

          -  Patient without legal capacity who is unable to understand the nature, significance
             and consequences of the trial

          -  Women who are pregnant or have the intention to become pregnant during the course of
             the study (For women who can get pregnant, pregnancy will be omitted using a pregnancy
             test when checking for inclusion and exclusion criteria. Patients will be informed
             that they must use contraception during the study)

          -  Patients with a previous clinical history of ON in the respective eye

          -  Patients with obvious retinal pathology other than that associated with ON

          -  Patients who are unable to perform the study assessments (e.g. OCT examination)
             because of a severe nystagmus (repetitive, uncontrolled eye movements causing unsteady
             fixation)

          -  Patients with a recent eye surgery

          -  Patients with known anti-aquaporin-4- or myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein- antibody
             seropositivity

          -  Patients with contraindications to the class of device under study (for rtACS):
             implanted electronic devices, metallic artefacts in the head (excluding dentition),
             epilepsy, brain cancer, pregnancy, breastfeeding, increased intraocular pressure
             without appropriate treatment, arterial hypertension without appropriate treatment,
             skin irritations at intended positions of electrodes, cognitive deficits (unable to
             provide written informed consent or follow the instructions)

          -  Known or suspected non-compliance, drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Inability to follow the procedures of the study, e.g. due to language problems,
             psychological disorders, dementia, etc. of the participant

          -  Participation in another study with investigational drug/device within the 30 days
             preceding and during the present study

          -  Previous enrolment into the current study

          -  Enrolment of the investigator, his/her family members, employees and other dependent
             persons
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>In principle 18-50 year old female and male patients may be recruited. However, since the randomization of patients will be controlled for gender, and participants will be enrolled continuously in an unbiased fashion, gender might become relevant in an advanced phase of the study (e.g. if the female block has already been fully recruited and only males might still be enrolled). As female preponderance is a well-known fact in multiple sclerosis, the investigators anticipate that approximately 2/3 of the patients will be females.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andreas Lutterotti, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Neuroimmunology and Multiple Sclerosis Research, Department of Neurology, University Hospital Zurich and University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andreas Lutterotti, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <phone>+41 44 255 49 84</phone>
    <email>Andreas.Lutterotti@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carla A Wicki, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+41 44 253 78 98</phone>
    <email>Carla.Wicki@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neurology and Department of Ophthalmology, University Hospital Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <zip>8091</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andreas Lutterotti, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 44 255 49 84</phone>
      <email>Andreas.Lutterotti@usz.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carla Andrea Wicki, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+41 44 253 78 98</phone>
      <email>Carla.Wicki@usz.ch</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sven Schippling, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carla A Wicki, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>optic neuritis</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>repetitive transorbital alternating current stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>optical coherence tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>low-contrast visual acuity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

