<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03862209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KBC Zagreb RECOVER-E</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03862209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community-based Mental Health Care for People With Severe and Enduring Mental Ill Health (RECOVER-E) Croatia</brief_title>
  <acronym>RECOVER-E</acronym>
  <official_title>Large-scale Implementation of Community-based Mental Health Care for People With Severe and Enduring Mental Ill Health in Europe</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Klinički Bolnički Centar Zagreb</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>STICHTING TRIMBOS INSTITUT, NETHERLANDS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Klinički Bolnički Centar Zagreb</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To contribute to improving the level of functioning and quality of life and mental health
      outcomes for people with severe and enduring mental ill health (SMI) (schizophrenia, bipolar
      disorder, depression) by adapting and up scaling the implementation of a community‐based
      service delivery model in Croatia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For nearly 900 million people living in Europe, mental disorders constitute the most
      significant yet most neglected public health problem: depression affects an estimated 30.3
      million Europeans, and psychotic disorders 5 million Europeans. People with severe and
      enduring mental ill health want the same things out of life as other citizens but are often
      placed in a vulnerable position and are hence afforded less opportunities to attain their
      goals and thus experience a lower quality of life, and have a lower life expectancy compared
      to the general population. For many countries that have undergone mental health services
      reform or have health systems in transition, efforts to make such comprehensive
      community-based mental health services available resulted in short-lived outcomes or are
      still to demonstrate substantial impact. RECOVER-E's aims to ensure well-functioning
      community mental health teams in 5 countries in Europe (Macedonia, Romania, Bulgaria,
      Croatia, and Montenegro), which will serve as the central node for coordination and provision
      of care for people with SMI. Our project narrows the implementation gap by going beyond
      infrastructure changes and pursuing the development of human resource capacity and care
      pathways that can be distilled in a comprehensive pathway to scale for regional and national
      decision-makers for uptake after the project's life span. RECOVER-E will: 1) Develop evidence
      based care pathways and treatment protocols for transition to scale for regional and national
      decision makers in 5 implementation sites; 2) Establish a peer to peer capacity building
      partnership in community mental health by linking a European expert panel with key
      stakeholders in 5 implementation sites to co-create community mental health services for
      people with SMI) 3) Evaluate intervention elements that will enhance sustainable adoption and
      implementation of community-based mental health care for people with SMI, by carrying out
      implementation research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two study groups both consisting of patients with SMI (severe mental illness). One group will be receiving care as usual, which in the actual setting means mostly medical treatment, without home care and assertive treatment through community based outreach teams. Another, intervention group, will be receiving assertive treatment care, with mobile assertive teams, consisting of at least three team members.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in daily functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule 2 (WHODAS2) measures health and disability-level of functioning in 6 domains:Cognition, Mobility, Self-care,Getting along, Life activities, Participation in community activities.The instrument is self-reporting; can be administered by a health worker if needed. Answers are distributed into 5 categories:&quot;none&quot;,&quot;mild&quot;,&quot;moderate&quot;,&quot;severe&quot;and&quot;extreme or cannot do&quot;. It ends with 3 items where answers are presented as number of days (when difficulties were present). Score on any dimension ranges 0 to 7, results are depicted in a diagram which reflects relation between dimensions(the higher the score, the lower level of difficulties/better functioning) and changes over time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Euro Quality of Life Index (Euro QoL 5-D 3-L). The instrument measures five dimensions: Mobility, Self-care, Daily activities, Pain/Discomfort and Anxiety/ Depression. Each dimension can be rated at three levels: from no problems to major problems. The five dimensions can be summed into a descriptive health state with 11111 representing no problems in any of the five health dimensions and 33333 indicating major problems in any of the five health dimensions. Second part of the instrument is the Visual Analogue Scale to assess health status at baseline, where 0 signifies worst imaginable health state, and 100 signifies best imaginable health state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Mental Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Severe Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community mental health team (CMHT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CMHTs will be multidisciplinary; that is, staff will be appointed to the CMHTs that include nurses, social workers, psychiatrists, psychologists, and in this project, a peer expert (a person with lived experience of mental health services). All staff within the CMHT will have defined roles and responsibilities that align with the staff functions, roles and linkages detailed in evidence-based service delivery models for community mental health teams. Participant will randomly be assigned to CMHT that will provide outreach mental health care during the project.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Health care settings and their providers randomised to the control condition receive usual care: participant will gain standard care; ambulatory care, day hospitals or hospital admission.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community mental health team</intervention_name>
    <description>CMHT will provide home-based treatment inclusive of crisis resolution services and procedures for early recognition of subclinical psychosis and bipolar disorder, and intensive case management. Integrated care (i.e. health and social care interventions) will be provided to all clients. Furthermore, health and social care evidence-based interventions for severe mental illness (SMI) will be employed during home treatment, such as family-based interventions, motivational interviewing, and cognitive behavioural therapies, combined with medication management and identifying employment (paid and non paid options) and support in finding and maintaining this employment, recovery groups and housing opportunities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community mental health team (CMHT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CMHT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Adults (ages 18-65), current service users, with severe and enduring mental ill-health,
        which, for clinical purposes, typically relates to diagnostic categories of bipolar
        disorder, severe depression, or schizophrenia. We use the following definition for SMI:

          -  Presence of a psychiatric disorder that requires care and treatment (so, they are NOT
             in symptom remission)

          -  Has severe limitations in social and community functioning (i.e. they are not in
             functional remission)

          -  These problems are not transient (e.g. temporary, one-off) in nature (They are
             systematic and long-term)

          -  Coordinated care provided by care networks or teams is needed to implement the
             treatment plan

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion criteria at the patient level includes patients who do not consent to their data
        being collected who are part of the intervention or control conditions, those who are under
        the age of 18 at the start of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martina Rojnić Kuzman, A/Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Psychiatry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martina Rojnić Kuzman, A/Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+385 1 2388 888</phone>
    <email>mrojnic@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sara Medved, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+385 1 2388 394</phone>
    <email>smedved@kbc-zagreb.hr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KBC Zagreb</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zagreb</city>
        <zip>10000</zip>
        <country>Croatia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martina Rojnić Kuzman, A/Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+385 1 2388 888</phone>
      <email>mrojnic@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martina Rojnić Kuzman, A/Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Croatia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Community implementation</keyword>
  <keyword>Community engagement</keyword>
  <keyword>patient centerednessP</keyword>
  <keyword>Implementation science</keyword>
  <keyword>Co-creation</keyword>
  <keyword>Iterative learning processes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data will be shared with the coordinating institute and Heidelberg University Hospital (two institutions that will be in charge of analyzing data from all participating project sites).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>During the project and for a period of five years after the end of the project; each beneficiary will disseminate its results by disclosing them to the public by appropriate means as soon as possible, including scientific publications in any medium.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>In order to protect participant privacy, data will only be released if the request abides by national and European patient data laws and guidelines, by guidelines for use of mental health data, and by the guidelines set by each research site's ethical review board. Those requesting access to the data will be asked to verify their identity, provide information on how the data will be used, and provide information about their institutions. All requests and releases of data will be logged by the Data Protection Officer. All identifiable data will be kept confidential and will not be released. Data access will be limited to a need only basis. All research partners involved in RECOVER-E will have access to open data sets. As well, datasets will be made available to the European Commission or Global Alliance for Chronic Diseases on request. All de-identified data sets will be stored at the coordinating institute on password-protected, non-networked servers with limited access.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

