<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03865446</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A7471058</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03865446</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate Severe Hepatic Impairment on Dacomitinib PK</brief_title>
  <official_title>A PHASE 1, OPEN-LABEL, SINGLE-DOSE, PARALLEL-GROUP STUDY TO EVALUATE THE PLASMA PHARMACOKINETICS AND SAFETY OF DACOMITINIB IN PARTICIPANTS WITH SEVERELY IMPAIRED HEPATIC FUNCTION RELATIVE TO PARTICIPANTS WITH NORMAL HEPATIC FUNCTION</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a post approval requirement to study the effect of severe hepatic impairment on the
      pharmacokinetics of dacomitinib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, open label, parallel group study to investigate the effect of severe
      hepatic impairment on the plasma PK, safety and tolerability after a single oral 30 mg dose
      of dacomitinib under fasted conditions.

      Approximately 18 participants will be enrolled into the study to ensure at least 6 PK
      evaluable (having data for estimating primary PK parameters for dacomitinib) participants in
      each cohort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 24, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 24, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to infinity (AUCinf) of dacomitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameter of dacomitinib to be calculated from the plasm concentration time data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of dacomitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameter of dacomitinib to be calculated from the plasma concentration time data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experienced treatment emergent adverse event assessed by investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>Type, incidence, severity, seriousness, and relationship to study medications of adverse events (AE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experienced treatment related adverse event assessed by investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>Type, incidence, severity, seriousness, and relationship to study medications of adverse events (AE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experienced serious adverse event assessed by investigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>Type, incidence, severity, seriousness, and relationship to study medications of adverse events (AE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal laboratory test values assessed by investigator (Hematology)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>The total number of participants with hematology laboratory test abnormalities will be assessed by investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal laboratory test values assessed by investigator (Blood chemistry)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>The total number of participants with blood chemistry test abnormalities will be assessed by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with change from baseline and absolute values in vital signs (blood pressure) meeting criteria of potential clinical concern</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure (BP) will be summarized using actual values and changes from baseline. The participants meeting criteria of potential clinical concern will be judged by investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with change from baseline and absolute values in QTcF meeting criteria of potential clinical concern</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>Federicia corrected QT (QTcF) will be summarized using actual values and changes from baseline. The participants meeting criteria of potential clinical concern will be judged by investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with change from baseline and absolute values in heart rate meeting criteria of potential clincial concern</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 12</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate will be summarized using actual values and change from baseline. The participants meeting criteria of potential clinical concern will be judged by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Hepatic Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 (Dacomitinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>severe hepatic impairment group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 (Dacomitinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>normal hepatic function</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dacomitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>anti-cancer agent</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 (Dacomitinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 (Dacomitinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PF-00299804; VIZIMPRO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Participants are eligible to be included in the study only if all of the following criteria
        apply:

          1. Male and/or female participants of non childbearing potential must be 18 to 75 years
             of age, inclusive, at the time of signing the informed consent document (ICD).

          2. Participants who are willing and able to comply with all scheduled visits, treatment
             plan, laboratory tests, lifestyle considerations, and other study procedures.

             Weight:

          3. Body mass index (BMI) of 17.5 to 40 kg/m2; and a total body weight &gt;50 kg (110 lb).

          4. Capable of giving signed informed consent as described in Appendix 1, which includes
             compliance with the requirements and restrictions listed in the ICD and in this
             protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Participants are excluded from the study if any of the following criteria apply:

          1. Any condition possibly affecting drug absorption (eg, gastrectomy).

          2. Other acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition including recent (within the
             past year) or active suicidal ideation or behavior or laboratory abnormality that may
             increase the risk associated with study participation or IP administration or may
             interfere with the interpretation of study results and, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would make the participant inappropriate for entry into this study.

          3. History of or current positive results for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          4. Previous administration with an investigational drug within 30 days (or as determined
             by the local requirement) or 5 half lives preceding the first dose of IP used in this
             study (whichever is longer).

          5. Hypersensitivity to dacomitinib or its excipients.

          6. A positive urine drug test. Participants with severe hepatic impairment (Cohort 1)
             will be eligible to participate if their urine drug test is positive with a drug for a
             prescribed condition that is not expected to interfere with the PK of dacomitinib.

          7. Blood donation (excluding plasma donations) of approximately 1 pint (500 mL) or more
             within 60 days prior to dosing.

          8. History of sensitivity to heparin or heparin induced thrombocytopenia.

          9. Unwilling or unable to comply with the criteria in the Lifestyle Considerations
             section of this protocol.

         10. Investigator site staff members directly involved in the conduct of the study and
             their family members, site staff members otherwise supervised by the investigator, or
             Sponsor employees, including their family members, directly involved in the conduct of
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Drug Services (IDS) University of Miami Hospitals and Clinics, Research Pharmacy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Division of Clinical Pharmacology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orlando Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32809</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://pmiform.com/clinical-trial-info-request?StudyID=A7471058</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Dacomitinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatic Impairment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Pfizer will provide access to individual de-identified participant data and related study documents (e.g. protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP), Clinical Study Report (CSR)) upon request from qualified researchers, and subject to certain criteria, conditions, and exceptions. Further details on Pfizer's data sharing criteria and process for requesting access can be found at: https://www.pfizer.com/science/clinical_trials/trial_data_and_results/data_requests.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

