<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03860532</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009-011-00AU1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03860532</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Clinical Trial in Healthy Male Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Randomized,Double-Blind,Placebo-controlled Trial in Healthy Male Voluteers To Examine the Safety,Tolerability,and Pharmacokinetics of HMPL-011 After A Single Dose.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hutchison Medipharma Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hutchison Medipharma Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I Randomized,Double-Blind,Placebo-controlled Trial in Healthy Male Voluteers
      To Examine the Safety,Tolerability,and Pharmacokinetics of HMPL-011 After A Single Dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Eligible subjects will randomly recieve 1200 mg tablets (600 mg tablet X 2) or 1200 mg
      capsules (200 mg capsule X 6) of HMPL-011 under fed and fed circumstance in part 1. In part
      2, eight subjects will be enrolled and given 800 mg tablets (400 mg/tablet X 2) every 8 hours
      daily for 6 days (morning dose only on Day 6).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of HMPL-011 tablets vs capsules in fasted States</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of HMPL-011 tablets (600 mg tablet X 2) and capsules (200 mg capsule X 6) in fasted States.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of HMPL-011 tablets vs capsules in fed States</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of HMPL-011 tablets (600 mg tablet X 2) and capsules (200 mg capsule X 6) in fed States.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Steady State concentration of HMPL-011</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Steady State concentration of HMPL-011 will be caculated based on Ctrough</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of HMPL-011 tablets vs capsules in fed States.</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of HMPL-011 tablets (600 mg tablet X 2) and capsules (200 mg capsule X 6) in fed States.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of HMPL-011 tablets vs capsules in fasted States.</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of HMPL-011 tablets (600 mg tablet X 2) and capsules (200 mg capsule X 6) in fasted States.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall incidence of TEAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects reported at least 1 TEAE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HMPL-011 tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A sigle total oral dose of 1200 mg tablets (600 mg tablet X 2)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HMPL-011 capsules</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A sigle total oral dose of 1200 mg capsules (200 mg tablet X 6)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HMPL-011 tablets</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible subjects will recieve 1200 mg HMPL-011 tablets under fed and diet circumstance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HMPL-011 tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HMPL-011 capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible subjects will recieve 1200 mg HMPL-011 capsules under fed and diet circumstance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HMPL-011 capsules</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects meeting the following criteria at the Screening Visit will be eligible to
        participate in the study:

          -  Healthy adult male and female subjects, 18-70 years of age, inclusive, at the time of
             signing the informed consent;

          -  Body weight ≥ 50 kg and body mass index (BMI) within the range 19-30 kg/m2, inclusive,
             at screening;

          -  Medically healthy subjects with clinically insignificant screening and check-in
             results (medical histories, 12-lead ECG, physical exam and laboratory tests);

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential with a negative urine pregnancy test at
             screening who are not breastfeeding, do not plan to become pregnant during the study,
             and agree to use an approved method of birth control from the first dose until 7 days
             following the last administration of study drug;

          -  Male subjects must agree to use barrier contraception (condom with spermicide) in
             addition to having their female partner (if of child-bearing potential) use another
             acceptable form of contraception (IUD, diaphragm with spermicide, oral contraceptives,
             injectable progesterone, or subdermal hormonal implant) from first dose until 7 days
             following the last administration of study drug; and

          -  Subjects are able to understand and to give their signed informed consent before any
             trial related procedures being performed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects are excluded from participation in the study if any of the following criteria
        apply:

          -  Subjects with, or a history of, cancer, diabetes or any clinically significant
             cardiovascular, respiratory, metabolic, renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal,
             hematological, dermatological, venereal, neurological, psychiatric or other major
             disorder;

          -  Presence or history of GI, hepatic or renal disease or any other condition (including
             surgery) known to interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion
             of medicines; Hutchison MediPharma Ltd. Clinical Study Protocol HMPL-004-1002
             Confidential &amp; Proprietary 27 Final 20 July 2011

          -  Systolic blood pressure outside the range of 90 to 140 mmHg, diastolic blood pressure
             outside the range of 40 to 90 mmHg, and/or pulse rate outside the range of 40 to 100
             bpm after one repeat at screening or check-in;

          -  Abnormal ECGs at screening

          -  History of clinically significant drug and/or food allergies as determined by the
             Principal Investigator (PI);

          -  Subjects will be excluded if they experience arrhythmia of any clinical significance;

          -  Subject is not willing to abstain from alcohol for 48 hours prior to the start of the
             first dose until completion of the post-study follow-up assessments;

          -  Any history (within 2 years) or current diagnosed alcoholism defined as an average
             weekly intake of greater than 21 units or an average daily intake of greater than 3
             units (One unit is equivalent to a half-pint of beer or 1 measure of spirits or 1
             glass of wine.);

          -  Recent history or current diagnosed drug abuse;

          -  Tobacco or nicotine use within the 6 months prior to first dose until the follow-up
             assessment, or a positive urine screen for cotinine;

          -  Hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reaction to compounds related to the study drug;

          -  Use of substances known to be strong inhibitors or inducers of cytochrome P450 enzymes
             (eg, macrolides, calcium channel blockers, ritonavir, rifampin, St. John's Wort, etc.)
             within 30 days prior to the first dose;

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including high-dose vitamins, herbal
             and dietary supplements within 7 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to
             the first dose of study medication (except for strong inhibitors or inducers of
             cytochrome P450 enzymes);

          -  Consumption of food or beverage containing grapefruit or cranberry within 7 days prior
             to the dose of study medication;

          -  Recent significant changes in body weight due to dieting or nutritional treatment;

          -  Donation of whole blood in excess of 500 mL within 56 days prior to checkin;

          -  Plasma donation within 7 days prior to check-in;

          -  Subject participated in an investigational clinical study within 30 days prior to the
             first dosing, or days calculated as ten times the half-life of the compound which the
             subject was treated with, whichever is longer. Factors other than the half-life of the
             compound, such as accumulation of tissue, muscle or organ, should also be considered
             for the enrollment;

          -  Exposure to 4 or more investigational products within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day; Hutchison MediPharma Ltd. Clinical Study Protocol HMPL-004-1002
             Confidential &amp; Proprietary 28 Final 20 July 2011

          -  Positive screen for HIV, hepatitis B, and/or hepatitis C at screening;

          -  Positive urine screen for drugs of abuse at screening or check-in; and

          -  Any condition that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, would complicate or
             compromise the study, or the well-being of the subject 4.2.3 General and Dietary
             Restrictions

        The following items are not to be consumed for 48 hours (2 days) prior to the first dose
        until the last scheduled blood sample collection of the study:

          -  Caffeine/xanthine such as coffee, tea, chocolate, and all caffeine containing soft
             drinks or energy drinks;

          -  Alcoholic beverages and/or other alcohol containing products; and

          -  Any foods containing poppy seeds.

        The following items are not to be consumed for 14 days prior to the first dose and
        throughout the study until the last scheduled blood sample collection:

        • Grapefruit, pomelo, cranberry, or grapefruit, pomelo, or cranberry-containing products.
        While in the CPU, subjects will not be allowed additional sugar in beverages or on cereal,
        though limited use of other sweeteners is allowed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

