<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03864354</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Asthma and OMT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03864354</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Asthma and Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Immediate, Intermediate, and Long-Term Effects of Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment on Pulmonary Function in Adults With Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Des Moines University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Des Moines University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The effect of Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment (OMT) has been studied in adult patients
      with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and children with asthma, however, to the
      authors' knowledge, no current studies have evaluated the non-immediate effects of OMT on
      pulmonary function in adults with chronic asthma using spirometry. The objective of the
      current study was to quantify the immediate, intermediate, and long-term effects of OMT on
      adult patients with a history of asthma. The quantitative effects were measured with a
      spirometry device and include the forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1), the forced
      vital capacity (FVC), the FEV1/FVC ratio, and the peak expiratory flow (PEF). These four
      values are used clinically in the diagnosis and management of asthma. The long-term,
      subjective effects were measured via the Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire with
      Standardized Activities (AQLQ(S)).

      The study was conducted over a period of eight weeks. During week 0, participants completed
      the initial AQLQ and performed baseline spirometry testing. During weeks 1, 2, and 3 of the
      study, a standard OMT protocol was performed on each participant, followed by spirometry
      testing to measure the immediate effect. Spirometry testing was then performed again three
      days after each treatment to measure the intermediate effect of OMT. During week 7,
      participants completed the post-OMT AQLQ(S) and performed spirometry testing once more to
      measure the long-term effects of OMT. The OMT protocol performed on each patient included
      treatments to address somatic dysfunctions of the head, cervical spine, thoracic spine, ribs,
      and respiratory diaphragm. The authors hypothesized that OMT would improve pulmonary
      function, both subjectively and objectively. The authors predicted an increased overall mean
      AQLQ(S) score as well as an increased mean score within each domain, including symptoms,
      activity limitations, emotional function, and environmental stimuli. The authors also
      predicted a significant increase in the mean FEV1/FVC ratio, and PEF three days after each
      OMT session and a significant increase four weeks after the final OMT session, but no
      increase immediately after OMT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 10, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>8 Weeks</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) measured in liters by a spirometer</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured during weeks 0 (at baseline), 1, 2, 3, and 7 of the study to assess the change over time. During weeks 1, 2, and 3, spirometry was performed immediately after the OMT protocol was completed as well as three days later.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire with Standardized Activities (AQLQ(S))</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants completed the survey at baseline and four weeks after the last treatment to compare the change.</time_frame>
    <description>The AQLQ asks about a participant's past 2 weeks as they relate to their symptoms, activity limitations, emotional function, and environmental stimuli. Each item is a 7-point Likert scale, with 1 being severely impaired and 7 not impaired at all.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced vital capacity (FVC) measured in liters by a spirometer</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured during weeks 0 (at baseline), 1, 2, 3, and 7 of the study to assess the change over time. During weeks 1, 2, and 3, spirometry was performed immediately after the OMT protocol was completed as well as three days later.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced expiratory flow in one second to forced vital capacity ratio (FEV1/FVC ratio) by a spirometer</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured during weeks 0 (at baseline), 1, 2, 3, and 7 of the study to assess the change over time. During weeks 1, 2, and 3, spirometry was performed immediately after the OMT protocol was completed as well as three days later.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak expiratory flow (PEF) measured in liters per minute by a spirometer</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured during weeks 0 (at baseline), 1, 2, 3, and 7 of the study to assess the change over time. During weeks 1, 2, and 3, spirometry was performed immediately after the OMT protocol was completed as well as three days later.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants were adults with a diagnosis of asthma, treated using a standardized Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment (OMT) is a cost-effective, noninvasive treatment that is used to optimize the body's structure and function. By improving the biomechanical, autonomic, and circulatory mechanisms involved in the disease process of asthma, OMT can help maximize respiratory function. The specific OMT protocol used in this study included the following: supine OA joint myofascial release (MFR), supine cervical spine Still technique, supine thoracic inlet MFR, supine rib raising soft tissue, supine rib MFR, supine abdominal diaphragm MFR, seated thoracic spine Still technique, and seated posterior rib Still technique. Treatments were performed by Predoctoral Osteopathic Manipulative Medicine (OMM) Fellows at Des Moines University (DMU) and supervised and checked by one of two board-certified OMM/NMM physicians from the OMM Department at DMU. The treatment lasted an average of 21 minutes and repeated three times, spaced one week apart.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants included members of the Des Moines University community.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  previously diagnosed with asthma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current smoker

          -  Diagnosed with any other respiratory disease besides asthma

          -  Receiving OMM from a licensed physician, chiropractic treatment, or massage therapy
             for 30 days prior to and during the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Des Moines University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Des Moines</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>50312</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/guidelines/asthma_qrg.pdf</url>
    <description>Asthma Care Quick Reference: Diagnosing and Managing Asthma</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.cdc.gov/asthma/most_recent_data.htm</url>
    <description>CDC's Most Recent Asthma Data</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bockenhauer SE, Julliard KN, Lo KS, Huang E, Sheth AM. Quantifiable effects of osteopathic manipulative techniques on patients with chronic asthma. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2002 Jul;102(7):371-5; discussion 375.</citation>
    <PMID>12138951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCracken JL, Veeranki SP, Ameredes BT, Calhoun WJ. Diagnosis and Management of Asthma in Adults: A Review. JAMA. 2017 Jul 18;318(3):279-290. doi: 10.1001/jama.2017.8372. Review. Erratum in: JAMA. 2017 Oct 24;318(16):1615. Dosage error in article text.</citation>
    <PMID>28719697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thiadens HA, De Bock GH, Van Houwelingen JC, Dekker FW, De Waal MW, Springer MP, Postma DS. Can peak expiratory flow measurements reliably identify the presence of airway obstruction and bronchodilator response as assessed by FEV(1) in primary care patients presenting with a persistent cough? Thorax. 1999 Dec;54(12):1055-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10567623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guiney PA, Chou R, Vianna A, Lovenheim J. Effects of osteopathic manipulative treatment on pediatric patients with asthma: a randomized controlled trial. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2005 Jan;105(1):7-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15710659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noll DR, Degenhardt BF, Johnson JC, Burt SA. Immediate effects of osteopathic manipulative treatment in elderly patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2008 May;108(5):251-9.</citation>
    <PMID>18519835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henderson AT, Fisher JF, Blair J, Shea C, Li TS, Bridges KG. Effects of rib raising on the autonomic nervous system: a pilot study using noninvasive biomarkers. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2010 Jun;110(6):324-30.</citation>
    <PMID>20606239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juniper EF, Guyatt GH, Willan A, Griffith LE. Determining a minimal important change in a disease-specific Quality of Life Questionnaire. J Clin Epidemiol. 1994 Jan;47(1):81-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8283197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>osteopathic manipulative medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Spirometry</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory</keyword>
  <keyword>OMM</keyword>
  <keyword>OMT</keyword>
  <keyword>osteopathic manual medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>osteopathic manipulative treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>osteopathic manual treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigator's study is a pilot study. If members of the OMM department at DMU choose to continue researching the effects of OMT on asthma in the future, then the data collected in the present study would be shared with those department members.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 8, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/54/NCT03864354/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

