<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03865888</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N-75-2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03865888</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Effect of Topical Tacrolimus 0.03% Versus Cyclosporine 0.05% in Dry Eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Effect of Topical Application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) Eye Drops Versus Cyclosporine 0.05% Eye Drops in Treatment of Dry Eye in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pavly Moawd</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of the effect of topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus
      Cyclosporine 0.05% eye drops in treatment of dry eye in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sjogren syndrome is a chronic autoimmune disorder characterized by immune cell infiltration
      of exocrine glands (exocrinopathy or epitheliitis) and systemic complications due to
      autoantibody production, immune complex deposition and lymphocytic infiltration of many
      organs .The loss of aqueous tear flow in Sjogren syndrome is a result of inflammatory cell
      infiltration of the lacrimal glands.The principal ocular manifestation of which is decreased
      tear production leading to chronic irritation and damage to the corneal and conjunctival
      epithelium. Dry eye associated with Sjogren syndrome (SS dry eye) is often more severe than
      non-Sjogren dry eye (non-SS dry eye). Rose bengal staining, fluorescein staining, impression
      cytology, and brush cytology show greater changes in SS dry eye owing to a lack of both basic
      tearing and reflex tearing resulting from lacrimal gland destruction, which is the hallmark
      of deteriorating clinical conditions.

      The initial tear film ocular surface society dry eye workshop report noted the importance of
      ocular surface inflammation not only in the development of, but as a downstream effect and
      propagator of dry eye disease , and reviewed a range of therapies that function, at least in
      part, by anti-inflammatory mechanisms of action. Thus understanding the link between
      inflammation and dry eye validates the utilization of anti-inflammatory therapy in everyday
      practice.

      Cyclosporine is understood to be an immunomodulatory drug with anti-inflammatory properties,
      as well as having other actions relevant to managing dry eye disease . Topical cyclosporine
      was approved by the FDA for the treatment of moderate-to-severe dry eye disease in 2003,
      based on an improvement in tear production.

      Tacrolimus, a macrolide produced by Streptomyces tsukubaensis,was discovered in 1984 in Japan
      while searching for new immunosuppressive and cancer chemotherapeutic agents. The use of
      tacrolimus is of special interest in ophthalmology because it is indicated to be effective in
      the treatment of immune-mediated diseases Thus, the investigators performed this study to
      evaluate the effect of two different immunomodulatory eye drops on the ocular surface which
      are topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus Cyclosporine 0.05% eye
      drops in treatment of dry eye in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Evaluation of the effect of topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus Cyclosporine 0.05% eye drops in treatment of dry eye in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison between the effect of topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus Cyclosporine 0.05% eye drops on tear film volume in dry eyes in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Tear film volume will be evaluated using Schirmer I test in millimetres in seconds in dry eyes before and after prescribing either cyclosporine or tacrolimus eye drops in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating the effect of topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus Cyclosporine 0.05% eye drops on ocular surface damage in dry eyes in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Ocular surface damage will be assessed in term of calculating ocular surface staining score in dry eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients before start and at end of treatment in cyclosporine and tacrolimus treated eyes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Studying the effect of cyclosporine and tacrolimus eye drops on tear film stability in dry eyes in Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Tear film stability will be described in form of tear film break up time in seconds in treated dry eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients before and after adminstration of cyclosporine and tacrolimus eye drops.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating the effect of topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus Cyclosporine 0.05% eye drops on meibomian glands secretion in dry eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing between effect of topical cyclosporine 0.05% and tacrolimus 0.03 % on meibomian glands secretions quality score in dry eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Studying the effect of topical application of Tacrolimus 0.03% (FK506) eye drops versus Cyclosporine 0.05% eye drops on expressibility of meibomian glands in dry eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluating the effect of topical cyclosporine 0.05% and tacrolimus 0.03 % on meibomian glands expressibility score in dry eyes of Secondary Sjogren Syndrome patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Dry Eye</condition>
  <condition>Sjogren Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclosporins 0.05 % treated eyes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical Cyclosporins 0.05% eye drops twice in one eye for 3 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tacrolimus 0.03% treated eyes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical Tacrolimus 0.03% eye drops twice in one eye for 3 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclosporins</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclosporins eye drops to be administered in dry eyes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclosporins 0.05 % treated eyes</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Restasis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Tacrolimus eye drops to be administered in dry eyes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tacrolimus 0.03% treated eyes</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FK506</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed as Secondary Sjogren syndrome according to the 2002 American
             European consensus group (AECG) criteria, which require the presence of well defined
             major connective tissue disease (such as rheumatoid arthritis and systemic lupus
             erythematosus.

          -  All patients show chronic symptoms of burning, foreign body sensation, itching in both
             eyes, abnormal Schirmer test &lt;5 mm wetting of the paper after 5 minutes, and abnormal
             tear breakup time (TBUT) &lt; 10 seconds.

          -  Wash out period of 30 days before start of the immunomodulatory eye drops included in
             the investigator's study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any inflammation or active structural changes in the iris or anterior chamber.

          2. Patients receiving or who had received systemic cyclosporine or tacrolimus.

          3. Patients receiving any systemic drug that can cause dry eye as some antidepressants ,
             antihistaminic drugs , hormonal therapy…etc

          4. Glaucoma.

          5. Previous ocular surgery.

          6. Use of any topical medication other than artificial tears.

          7. Contact lens wearers.

          8. Presence of any corneal infection.

          9. Any corneal diseases (ulcer, opacity, scar, bullous keratopathy, symblepharon or
             tumors).

         10. Deforming structural lid or conjunctival abnormality.

         11. Pregnancy.

         12. Prior diagnosis of any of the following conditions would exclude participation in AECG
             study :

        Past head and neck radiation treatment Hepatitis C infection Acquired immunodeficiency
        disease (AIDS) Pre-existing lymphoma Sarcoidosis Graft versus host disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Omar El Zawahry</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gaafar Ragab</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rehab Shamma</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pavly Moawad</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11421</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pavly Moawd</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Lecturer of Ophthalmic Medicine and Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sjogren Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Dry eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Cyclosporine</keyword>
  <keyword>Tacrolimus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sjogren's Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Keratoconjunctivitis Sicca</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dry Eye Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 24, 2019</submitted>
    <returned>July 25, 2019</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

