<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03864562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>226-1901</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03864562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gastric Emptying - Implications for the Pathogenesis of Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gastric Emptying in Non-diabetic Individuals With Black African/Caribbean Heritage - Implications for the Pathogenesis of Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nottingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Adelaide</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nottingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People of black African and Caribbean descent have a greater risk of developing type 2
      diabetes than white Europeans. The aim of this study is to increase our knowledge of how the
      condition may arise, and what underlies this increased risk. Following a successful screening
      visit to confirm eligibility for the study, we will be investigating how quickly a glucose
      drink empties out of the stomach in 30 white Europeans and 30 people of black African or
      Caribbean descent. In addition, we will study the impact that gastric emptying rate has on
      blood glucose and satiety hormones released normally by the gut in response to eating. Blood
      and breath samples will be collected before and during an oral glucose tolerance test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background It is recognized that there are differences between ethnic groups in the risk of
      developing type 2 diabetes (T2D), but the underlying pathophysiology remains poorly defined.
      For example, whilst insulin resistance, exacerbated by obesity, is common in Caucasian,
      Hispanic and South Asian populations, impairment in insulin secretion appears to be the
      primary defect in the pathogenesis of T2D in East Asians. Within the United Kingdom (UK),
      diabetes and its complications disproportionately affect ethnic minority groups, particularly
      those of black African-Caribbean (AfC) descent. Studies indicate that the rate of gastric
      emptying is a major determinant of postprandial glycemia and insulinemia in those with a
      White European (WE) background in both health and T2D, and although there is evidence that
      gastric emptying is influenced by ethnicity (which may contribute to the development of T2D),
      gastric emptying has, to our knowledge, not been evaluated in those of AfC heritage.

      Aims The primary objective is to compare the gastric emptying rate in 2 UK ethnic groups.
      This will be done by conducting a descriptive, cross-sectional pilot study in 60 healthy
      participants. Secondary objectives are to determine any relationship between glycemia,
      insulinemia and incretin hormone secretion in these groups.

      Experimental protocol Sixty volunteers; 30 of WE and 30 of black AfC heritage will be
      recruited. Following a successful medical screening visit, participants will be asked to
      record their dietary intake over 3 days before attending the laboratory for their study
      visit. On the day before the study visit they will be asked to avoid strenuous exercise,
      alcohol and caffeine intake and to eat their normal diet. On the study day, participants will
      arrive at the laboratory in the morning following an overnight fast. A cannula will be
      inserted into a vein in the top of the hand and the hand placed in a warming box for repeat
      arterialized-venous blood sampling over the study day. After baseline breath and blood
      samples have been taken, participants will then be given a drink containing 75g of glucose
      dissolved in 300ml water (standard oral glucose tolerance test), to which has been added
      150mg of 13C labelled acetate, and asked to consume it within 5 minutes. The stable isotope
      label on the acetate allows us to assess gastric emptying by detecting the appearance of
      13CO2 in breath. Blood samples (6ml) will be collected prior to the drink, with further
      samples being taken every 15min for the first 2hrs, then every 30min for the next hour, with
      a final sample taken at 4hrs. Blood will be analysed for glucose, insulin, C-peptide,
      Glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1), glucagon, and Gastric inhibitory polypeptide (GIP).
      Following the drink, subjects will also be asked to complete satiety and GI symptom
      questionnaires every half hour throughout the study. At the end of the 4 hours, participants
      will be asked to complete a series of autonomic function tests, during which we will measure
      blood pressure and heart rate. These tests are 2mins of rhythmic breathing (5sec inhale: 5sec
      exhale) and postural change to standing from resting semi-supine. After this time, the
      cannula will be removed and the study is completed
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 28, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastric emptying rate</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time for clearance of half of the glucose drink (measured via a stable isotope breath test and area under the incremental postprandial blood glucose response curve)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Insulin concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Serum Insulin response to the glucose drink, measured by serial blood sampling and later analysis using a radio-immuno assay (RIA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole blood glucose concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Blood glucose response to the glucose drink, measured by serial blood sampling and immediate analysis using the glucose oxidase method</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma glucagon concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma glucagon response to the glucose drink, measured by serial blood sampling and later analysis using an RIA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma GLP-1 concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma GLP-1 response to the glucose drink, measured by serial blood sampling and later analysis using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma GIP concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma GIP response to the glucose drink, measured by serial blood sampling and later analysis using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum C-peptide concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Serum C-peptide response to the glucose drink, measured by serial blood sampling and later analysis using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attrition rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants completing the protocol as a proportion of those who were recruited to the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of people volunteering to take part in the study as a proportion of those expressing initial interest</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Black African or Caribbean</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy individuals of black African or Caribbean descent</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>White European</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy individuals of white European descent</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study cohort will be recruited from the general population of England who live within
        commuting distance from the study site, and will incorporate those from the counties of
        Nottinghamshire, Derbyshire and Leicestershire
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  White European or black African / Caribbean heritage

          -  BMI &gt;18 kg/m2

          -  Ability to give written informed consent

          -  English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any significant medical condition

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Alcohol consumption &gt;14 units / week

          -  Random blood Glucose concentration above 7.8mmol/l

          -  Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) &gt;47mmol/mol (&gt;6.4%)

          -  Use of regular medication, (oral contraceptive pill or antihypertensive medication are
             acceptable if use has been for &gt;6 months)

          -  History of Irritable Bowel Syndrome, food intolerances or any gastrointestinal
             disorders

          -  Previous bariatric surgery, or gastrointestinal surgery which may affect normal
             function (e.g. bowel resection)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Horowitz, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Adelaide</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Liz Simpson, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)7864982800</phone>
    <email>liz.simpson@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Melanie Marshall, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)115 951 5151</phone>
    <phone_ext>19105</phone_ext>
    <email>Melanie.Marshall@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>David Greenfield Human Physiology Unit, University of Nottingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nottingham</city>
        <state>Notts</state>
        <zip>NG72UH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara Brown</last_name>
      <phone>+44(0)115 8234034</phone>
      <email>sara.brown@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Melanie Marshall, BSc</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 115 951 5151</phone>
      <phone_ext>19105</phone_ext>
      <email>Melanie.Marshall@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ian A Macdonald, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Liz J Simpson, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kodama K, Tojjar D, Yamada S, Toda K, Patel CJ, Butte AJ. Ethnic differences in the relationship between insulin sensitivity and insulin response: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabetes Care. 2013 Jun;36(6):1789-96. doi: 10.2337/dc12-1235. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23704681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horowitz M, Edelbroek MA, Wishart JM, Straathof JW. Relationship between oral glucose tolerance and gastric emptying in normal healthy subjects. Diabetologia. 1993 Sep;36(9):857-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8405758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips WT. Gastric emptying in ethnic populations: possible relationship to development of diabetes and metabolic syndrome. Ethn Dis. 2006 Summer;16(3):682-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16937605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nottingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elizabeth Simpson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Research Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gastric emptying</keyword>
  <keyword>oral glucose tolerance test</keyword>
  <keyword>Ethnicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes risk</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

