<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03861351</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PSM36</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03861351</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-comparative Trial Following Participants Implanted Bilaterally With Mini WELL Toric Ready Intraocular Lens for 6 Months After the Second Eye Implant (FUSION)</brief_title>
  <acronym>FUSION</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Non-controlled and Open-label Trial Following Subjects Implanted Bilaterally With the Toric Extended-depth-of-focus Mini WELL Toric Ready Intraocular Lens for 6 Months After the Second Eye Implant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SIFI SpA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SIFI SpA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, non-comparative trial following participants implanted bilaterally
      with the Mini WELL Toric Ready intraocular lens (IOL) for 6 months after the second eye
      implant.

      The objective of the study is to evaluate the clinical performance of the Mini WELL Toric
      Ready intraocular lens (IOL), in particular, visual performance and rotational stability at 6
      months following the second eye implantation in participants suffering from bilateral
      cataract with corneal astigmatism.

      There are 2 hypotheses:

        -  Rotational Stability: the rotation of the Mini WELL Toric Ready IOL compared between
           Visit 0a (the day of surgery) and Visit 4 (120-180 days post-operative follow-up) shall
           be less than ±10° in 90 percents of the cases, less than ±20° in 95 percents of the
           cases, and less than ±30° in 99 percents of the cases.

        -  Severe Visual Distortions: the rate of severe visual distortions for the Mini WELL Toric
           Ready IOL reported at 6 months postoperative will be less than 10 percents.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an interventional, multicenter, non-comparative post-marketing clinical investigation
      in participants implanted bilaterally with the Mini WELL Toric Ready intraocular lens (IOL)
      for 6 months after the second eye implant.

      The objective of this study is to evaluate the clinical performance of the Mini WELL Toric
      Ready IOL, in particular, visual performance and rotational stability at 6 months following
      second eye implantation.

      The first hypothesis raised for this study is related to rotational stability. The rotation
      of the Mini WELL Toric Ready IOL between Visit 0a (the day of the surgery) and Visit 4
      (120-180 day post-operative follow-up) shall be less than 10° in 90 percents of the cases,
      less than 20° in 95 percents of the cases, and less than 30° in 99 percents of the cases.

      The second hypothesis is regarding severe visual distortions. The rate of severe visual
      distortions for the Mini WELL Toric Ready IOL reported 6 months post-operative will be less
      than 10 percents.

      The study will involve 69 participants in 3 countries in order to achieve a target number of
      60 evaluable participants completing the study.

      This clinical study is composed of 9 scheduled visits. Following completion of the Informed
      Consent process, a pre-operative examination will take place to determine each patient's
      eligibility. Eligible patients, who wish to continue with the study, will be invited to
      undergo their first surgical procedure within 30 days. They will be required to undergo their
      second surgical procedure within 2 weeks of the initial operation. They will also be required
      to return for additional post-operative follow-up visits, 1-2 days after each eye surgery,
      7-14 days after each eye surgery, 30-60 days after bilateral surgery and 120-180 days after
      bilateral surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Men and women aged ≥ 18 years old suffering from bilateral cataract and astigmatism</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraocular lens (IOL) rotation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after second eye implant</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the rotational stability of Mini WELL Toric Ready IOL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of severe visual distortions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after second eye implant</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the visual performance of Mini WELL Toric Ready IOL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of visual disturbances as detected with the Halometry test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after second eye implant</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of secondary surgical interventions (SSIs) related to the optical properties of the IOL for first and second operative eye separately</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after second eye implant</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">69</enrollment>
  <condition>Bilateral Cataract</condition>
  <condition>Astigmatism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mini WELL Toric Ready intraocular lens</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mini WELL Toric Ready intraocular lens</intervention_name>
    <description>The aim of cataract surgery is to remove the cloudy lens and replace it with the artificial intraocular lens called Mini WELL Toric Ready to correct presbyopia and to correct corneal astigmatism.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mini WELL Toric Ready intraocular lens</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eighteen years of age or older at the time of surgery and diagnosed with bilateral
             cataracts;

          -  Planned bilateral cataract removal by phacoemulsification;

          -  Preoperative total corneal astigmatism of 0.89 - 2.91 D, measured by corneal
             topography in both operative eyes;

          -  IOL power and cylinder requirement calculated by the specific web-based Mini Toric
             Calculator within the following range:

          -  Cylinder of: 1.50 D to 4.00 D

          -  Spherical Equivalent of: 18.00 to 28.00 D

          -  Willing and able to complete all required postoperative visits;

          -  Clear intraocular media other than cataract;

          -  Available for second-eye surgery within 2 weeks of the initial operation;

          -  Potential postoperative visual acuity of 0.3 logMAR in both eyes;

          -  Able to comprehend and sign a statement of informed consent consistent with local
             regulation for research in human subjects.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Irregular / asymmetric astigmatism;

          -  Significant irregular corneal aberration as demonstrated by corneal topography;

          -  Keratopathy / Kerectasia - any corneal abnormality, other than regular corneal
             astigmatism, including, but not limited to the following: keratoconus, keratoglobus,
             keratolysis, keratomalacia, keratomicosis and corneal plana;

          -  Any inflammation or edema (swelling) of the cornea, including but not limited to the
             following: keratitis, keratoconjuntivitis and keratouveitis;

          -  Subjects with diagnosed degenerative visual disorder (e.g. macular degeneration or
             other retinal disorders) that are predicted (by subjective assessment of the retina)
             to cause future acuity losses to a level worse than 0.3 logMAR;

          -  Subjects who may have reasonably been expected to require a secondary surgical
             intervention at any time during the study (other than Nd:YAG capsulotomy);

          -  Subjects in whom the intraocular lens might interfere with the ability to observe,
             diagnose or treat posterior segment conditions;

          -  Previous corneal refractive surgery;

          -  Other planned ocular surgery procedures, including, but not limited to LASIK,
             astigmatic keratotomy, retinal laser treatment and limbal relaxing incisions, for the
             duration of the study;

          -  Capsular or zonular abnormalities that may affect postoperative centration or tilt of
             the lens, including but not limited to the following: pseudo-exfoliation syndrome,
             chronic uveitis, Marfan's Syndrome;

          -  Absence of adequate capsular support for the implant of the intraocular lens in the
             capsular bag;

          -  Absence of adequate support for the lens from the posterior chamber or the zonule;

          -  Pupil abnormalities, including but not limited to the following: non-reactive, tonic
             pupils that do not dilatate under mesopic/scotopic conditions, abnormally shaped
             pupils or abnormally positioned pupils;

          -  Amblyopia;

          -  Clinically severe corneal dystrophy (e.g. epithelial, stromal, or endothelial
             dystrophy);

          -  Proliferative diabetic retinopathy;

          -  Microphthalmos;

          -  Suspected microbial infection;

          -  Previous retinal detachment;

          -  Previous corneal transplant;

          -  Optic nerve atrophy;

          -  Extremely shallow anterior chamber, not due to swollen cataract;

          -  Recurrent severe anterior or posterior segment inflammation of unknown aetiology (e.g.
             chronic uveitis);

          -  Iris neovascularization;

          -  Glaucoma (uncontrolled or controlled with medication);

          -  Aniridia or iris atrophy;

          -  Severe dry eye;

          -  Use of any systemic or topical drug known to interfere with visual performance;

          -  Subjects with any systemic disease that could increase operative risk or confound the
             outcomes (e.g. uncontrolled diabetes);

          -  Use of contact lens within the last 30 days before the preoperative visit;

          -  Vulnerable subjects (children &lt;18 years, people in guardianship or trusteeship or
             inability to give an informed consent);

          -  Pregnant or lactating or planning a pregnancy at the time of enrolment;

          -  Subjects with psychiatric disorders that could confound the outcomes;

          -  Subjects participating in a concurrent clinical trial or if they have participated in
             an ophthalmology clinical trial within the last 30 days.

        Intra-operative exclusion criteria:

          -  Irregularity and decentration of capsulorhexis;

          -  Other ocular surgery procedures, including, but not limited to LASIK, astigmatic
             keratotomy, retinal laser treatment and limbal relaxing incisions, for the duration of
             the study;

          -  Significant vitreous loss;

          -  Significant anterior chamber hyphema;

          -  Uncontrollable intraocular pressure (IOP);

          -  Zonular or capsular rupture;

          -  Ciliary sulcus, Bag-sulcus, sulcus-sulcus or unknown placement of the haptics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gianluca Stivale</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0957922335</phone>
    <email>Gianluca.Stivale@sifigroup.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service ophtalmologie Segment Antérieur- Hopital Pellegrin - CHU de Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33076</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitäts-Augenklinik Heidelberg International Vision Correction Research Centre (IVCRC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gerd Uwe Auffarth, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6221 566624</phone>
      <email>gerd.auffarth@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Raquel Willrich Amroussi, Study coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+49 6221 566624</phone>
      <email>Raquel.WillrichAmroussi@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OFTALVIST CIO JEREZ Clínica Jerez (Cadiz)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerez De La Frontera</city>
        <zip>11407</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ramon Ruiz Mesa, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>+34 956 357263</phone>
      <email>ramonruizmesa@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julia Ruiz, Study coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+34 956 357263</phone>
      <email>juliablanchruiz@yahoo.es</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cataract</keyword>
  <keyword>Astigmatism</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astigmatism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

