<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03862040</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1713R2117</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03862040</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cefiderocol Concentrations in the Lungs of Hospitalized Patients With Bacterial Pneumonia</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Study to Assess the Intrapulmonary Concentrations of Cefiderocol at Steady State in Hospitalized Subjects With Bacterial Pneumonia on Treatment With Standard of Care Antibiotics and Requiring Mechanical Ventilation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shionogi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shionogi Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of the study is to determine the degree of penetration of cefiderocol
      into infected lung tissue in hospitalized adults with bacterial pneumonia who are being
      mechanically ventilated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 8, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of Cefiderocol in Epithelial Lining Fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>After at least 3 doses of cefiderocol in participants with normal or mild or moderate RI and at least 6 doses in participants with severe RI (16 or 40 hours after first dose, respectively), at 3, 5, or 7 hours after the start of the infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>Samples for determination of cefiderocol concentrations in the epithelial lining fluid (ELF) will be collected by bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) procedure on the inflamed section of the lung (ie, a lobe where pneumonia is expected to be present based on chest radiologic imaging) after multiple doses of cefiderocol sufficient to approximate steady state concentrations of drug in blood. It is anticipated that steady state in blood will occur after 3 doses in participants with normal and moderate renal impairment (RI) and after 6 doses in participants with severe renal impairment. The ELF sample for the determination of cefiderocol concentrations will be collected at 3 hours after the start of administration of cefiderocol for the first 3 enrolled participants. Subsequently, the collection time point may be modified to 5 or 7 hours after administration of cefiderocol based on data analysis (i.e., the exact time of ELF will be iterative).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of the Concentration for Cefiderocol in Epithelial Lining Fluid Relative to Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>After at least 3 doses of cefiderocol in participants with normal or mild or moderate RI and at least 6 doses in participants with severe RI (16 or 40 hours after first dose, respectively), at 3, 5, or 7 hours after the start of the infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma samples for the determination of cefiderocol concentrations will be collected at prespecified time points corresponding to the time point at which the ELF sample is collected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacterial Pneumonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cefiderocol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive standard of care (SOC) antibiotic treatment for pneumonia. Forty hours after the start of SOC treatment, participants will be administered 2 g doses of cefiderocol infused intravenously over 3 hours, every 8 hours (q8h), for an expected minimum of 3 doses and up to a total of 6 doses in participants with normal renal function and participants with mild or moderate renal impairment, and for an expected minimum of 6 doses and up to a total of 9 doses in participants with severe renal impairment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cefiderocol</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered intravenously, at a dosage determined based on renal function.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cefiderocol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>S-649266)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care Antibiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care antibiotic treatment for pneumonia</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cefiderocol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is 18 years or older at the time written informed consent is obtained

          2. Subject has provided written informed consent or informed consent has been provided by
             subject's legally authorized representative

          3. Subject has a diagnosis or suspicion of bacterial pneumonia (even if later known that
             the subject does not have bacterial pneumonia, discontinuation of the study is not
             necessary)

          4. Subject is hospitalized and receiving SOC antibiotic treatment for pneumonia

          5. Subject is mechanically ventilated or expected to be mechanically ventilated at least
             48 hours (or 72 hours for subjects with severe renal impairment) after the first dose
             of cefiderocol

          6. Subject has a life expectancy of at least 3 weeks from the Screening visit

          7. Subject is male (no contraception required) or female and meets 1 of the following
             criteria:

               1. Surgically sterile (has had a hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy, or a
                  bilateral salpingectomy or tubal ligation for the purpose of contraception for at
                  least 6 weeks with appropriate documentation of such surgery)

               2. Postmenopausal (defined as older than 45 years of age with cessation of regular
                  menstrual periods for at least 6 months and a follicle-stimulating hormone level
                  of &gt; 40 mIU/mL, or amenorrhea for at least 12 months)

               3. Of childbearing potential and using combined (estrogen and progestogen) or
                  progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation
                  (including oral, intravaginal, injectable, implantable, and transdermal
                  contraceptives), or an intrauterine device (IUD), or intrauterine
                  hormone-releasing system for the entire duration of the study

               4. Of childbearing potential and practicing abstinence as a preferred and usual life
                  style and/or agrees to continue practicing abstinence from Screening for the
                  entire duration of the study

               5. Of childbearing potential and whose sole heterosexual partner has been
                  successfully vasectomized and agrees to not have other heterosexual partners for
                  the entire duration of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

          1. Subject has a chemical pneumonia that does not require antibiotic treatment (including
             aspiration of gastric acid, inhalation injury). The term chemical pneumonia refers to
             the aspiration of substances that are toxic to the lower airways causing chemical burn
             and injuries in the airway.

          2. Subject has a history of any moderate or severe hypersensitivity or allergic reaction
             to any β-lactam (Note: for β-lactams, a history of a mild rash followed by uneventful
             re-exposure is not a contraindication to enrollment)

          3. Subject has extensive cystic lesion(s) or severe structural abnormality (eg, cystic
             fibrosis, emphysema, cystic lesions of sarcoidosis or tuberculosis, postobstructive
             pneumonia due to lung cancer, etc) of the lung that hinders recovery of
             bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF)

          4. Subject is receiving peritoneal dialysis

          5. Subject has severe renal impairment requiring hemodialysis (HD) or end-stage renal
             disease requiring HD

          6. Subject is in refractory septic shock defined as persistent hypotension despite
             adequate fluid resuscitation or despite vasopressive therapy at Screening

          7. Subject is a female who has a positive pregnancy test at Screening or who is lactating

          8. Subject has received another investigational drug within 30 days prior to Screening

          9. Subject has previously participated in this clinical study and has received at least 1
             dose of cefiderocol within 7 days

         10. Subject has any condition or circumstance that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             would compromise the safety of the subject or the quality of the study data
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shionogi Clinical Trials Administrator Clinical Support Help Line</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shionogi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anschutz Medical Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hartford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U Miami Health Tower</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Western University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Creighton University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia, Bacterial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

