<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03869008</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>gammaCore RP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03869008</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Potential Benefit for Non Invasive Vagus Nerve Stimulation Using GammaCore in the Treatment of Raynaud's Phenomena.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Potential Benefit for Non Invasive Vagus Nerve Stimulation (nVNS) Using GammaCore in the Treatment of Raynaud's Phenomena.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Toledo Health Science Campus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ElectroCore INC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Toledo Health Science Campus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Raynaud's phenomenon (RP) is a common vascular disorder that affects approximately 10% of the
      general population. RP is associated with significant morbidity that may include loss of the
      digits due to repeated episodes of vasospasm of the digital arteries in addition to
      significant impairment of quality of life. It is well known that cold exposure precipitates
      episodes of RP, but the mechanism for cold sensitivity is not known, and treatment of RP is
      not satisfactory to the patients and their physicians.

      The goal in this study is to test the possibility that non invasive vagus nerve stimulation
      (nVNS) with gammaCore which is already approved by the FDA for headaches and migraines may be
      an effective and well tolerated therapy for Raynaud's Phenomenon.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Raynaud's phenomenon (RP) is a common vascular disorder that that affects approximately 10%
      of the general population. RP causes some areas of the body (i.e. fingers and toes) to feel
      cold and numb in response to cold exposure or emotional stress. Raynaud's phenomenon is
      characterized by reversible vasospasm of the fingers and toes. This reversible narrowing of
      the small arteries induces episodes of color changes of the fingers and toes. During an
      attack of Raynaud's, affected areas of the skin usually first turn white, then they often
      turn blue and feel cold and numb (pins and needles). As the fingers warm and circulation
      improves the affected areas may turn red, throb and tingle.

      Moreover, Raynaud's phenomenon can be associated with significant morbidity that may include
      ulceration of fingers and loss of the fingers and toes due to repeated episodes of reversible
      narrowing of arteries supplying blood to the finger and toes. It is well known that cold
      exposure leads to episodes of RP, but the mechanism for cold sensitivity is not known, and
      treatment of RP is not satisfactory to the patients and their physicians.

      Raynaud's phenomenon is classified as Primary Raynaud's phenomenon (PRP) in the absence of
      other vascular or connective tissue disease. Raynaud's phenomenon is classified as Secondary
      Raynaud's phenomenon (SRP) if it is associated with connective tissue disease, like systemic
      sclerosis (SSc, Scleroderma).

      Treatment of Raynaud's phenomenon is not satisfactory in general, as current therapy
      employing calcium channel blockers and other vasodilators are frequently ineffective or not
      well tolerated, due to significant side effects.

      Noninvasive vagus nerve stimulation (nVNS) is currently FDA approved for therapeutic uses in
      patient ages 12 and above to treat cluster and migraine headaches. Recent studies have shown
      that vagal nerve stimulation has vasodilatory and anti-inflammatory properties which has led
      to more preclinical research examining vagus nerve stimulation as treatment for a wider range
      of inflammatory and autoimmune disorders. Vagus nerve stimulation has shown promising results
      in treating chronic inflammatory disorders such as sepsis, lung injury, rheumatoid arthritis,
      and diabetes. Although there are no direct data to demonstrate vagus nerve stimulation's
      effect in Raynaud's phenomenon, the investigators believe that VNS's success in treating
      headache and migraine attacks indirectly support its use in Raynaud's phenomenon by its
      direct effect on vasospasms (narrowing of blood vessels). In fact migraine has been found as
      a risk factor for the development of Raynaud's phenomenon further supports this notion.

      GammaCore is a safe and effective non-drug treatment approved for treating cluster and
      migraine headaches. It is a patented device that activates the vagus nerve with gentle
      electrical stimulation. The vagus nerve is an important highway of communication between the
      brain and many parts of the body, it plays an important role in regulating pain. Noninvasive
      vagus nerve stimulation with GammaCore is believed to help block the pain signals that cause
      migraines and cluster headaches. Unlike traditional vagus nerve stimulation therapies,
      gammaGore stimulates the vagus nerve through the skin at the side of the neck without the
      need for surgery. This non-invasive method avoids many side effects and inconveniences
      associated with injectable, inhaled or pill-based medication.

      The investigators' goal is to test the possibility that noninvasive vagus nerve stimulation
      using gammaCore may be an effective and well tolerated therapy for Raynaud's phenomenon. The
      investigators aim to gain a fundamental understanding of the role of noninvasive vagus nerve
      stimulation as a potential therapy for Raynaud's phenomenon, a truly unmet medical need.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 16, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 16, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>At randomization subjects are randomized to 2 groups, the Experimental group and the Sham group.
The Experimental group will use the study device from randomization to the end of the study.
The Sham group will use the Sham device for 4 weeks after randomization then be switched to the study device for the rest of the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Subjects randomized to the Experimental group will use the gammaCore Sapphire till the end of the study. Subjects in this group will become un-blinded in the open label phase of the study at 4 weeks after randomization.
Subjects randomized to the Sham group will use the Sham device for 4 weeks. Subjects in the Sham group will become un-blinded in the open label phase of the study at 4 weeks after randomization and be switch to the gammaCore Sapphire for the rest of the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the clinical efficacy of the gammaCore nVNS device at preventing vasospasms, thus reducing the number of and duration of Raynaud's attacks in patients with Primary Raynaud's Phenomenon.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the clinical efficacy of gammaCore (15 patients) vs sham device (15 patients) in preventing vasospasms in 30 PRP patients.
The clinical efficacy of the nVNS device will be accessed through subject reported outcomes by way of the diary that will be handed out to subjects for the duration of the study, both before and after subjects have started using the gammaCore device. The diary will track daily the number of attacks of Raynaud's phenomenon and the duration of these attacks each day. The combination of the number of RP attacks and their duration will be used to evaluate the efficacy of the nVNS device at preventing vasospasms by analyzing changes in frequency and duration of RP attacks in subjects before and after they have started using the gammaCore device.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate improvements in Raynaud's condition scores after using the gammaCore nVNS device.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the clinical efficacy of gammaCore (15 patients) vs sham device (15 patients) on Raynaud's symptoms and chronic PRP in 30 patients for four weeks using Raynaud's condition score.
The Raynaud's Condition Score is presented in the diary that will be handed out to subjects for the duration of the study. The Raynaud's Condition Score will ask subjects from a scale of 0 to 10, &quot;0&quot; being no difficulty, &quot;10&quot; being extreme difficulty, the number that best indicates the difficulty the subjects had each day with Raynaud's condition.
The Raynaud's Condition Score is for subjects to rate how much difficulty the subjects had with Raynaud's each day by considering how much pain, numbness or other symptoms the Raynaud's caused in subjects' fingers and how much Raynaud's alone affected the use of the subjects' hands each day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Observe response rates in an open label fashion after subjects randomized to the sham device are transitioned to the gammaCore nVNS device.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Raynaud Phenomenon</condition>
  <condition>Primary Raynaud Phenomenon</condition>
  <condition>Raynaud Disease</condition>
  <condition>Raynaud Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 patients will be randomized to the Sham device for the first half of the treatment window then switch to the gammaCore Sapphire device (study device) for the rest of the study.
The Sham device will look exactly like the gammaCore Sapphire device but will not deliver non invasive vagus nerve stimulation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>gammaCore Sapphire (Study Device) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 patients will be randomized to the gammaCore Sapphire device for the full length of the treatment window.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gammaCore Sapphire</intervention_name>
    <description>gammaCore SapphireTM (non-invasive vagus nerve stimulator) is intended to provide non-invasive vagus nerve stimulation (nVNS) on the side of the neck. gammaCore provides a mild electrical stimulation to the vagus nerve, which runs through the neck and carries information to the central nervous system.
Subjects will be instructed to use the gammaCore Sapphire to stimulate 2 minutes on each side of the neck, twice a day, every day. The subject controls the intensity level of the electrical stimulation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>gammaCore Sapphire (Study Device) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The Sham device delivers no electrical stimulations but subjects randomized to the Sham device will received the same instructions to use the Sham device to stimulate 2 minutes on each side of the neck, twice a day, every day for the first 4 weeks after randomization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Clinical Diagnosis of Primary Raynaud's Phenomenon

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 18 years of age

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Current smokers

          -  Have Digital ulcers

          -  Diagnosed Pulmonary hypertension

          -  Currently on vasodilators (i.e. Phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibitors, prostacyclin,
             nitroglycerine, or other nitric oxide derivatives)

          -  Currently on Calcium Channel Blockers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bashar Kahaleh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Toledo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Gilmore, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>4193836761</phone>
    <email>jennifer.gilmore@utoledo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unversity of Toledo Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toledo</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43614</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Gilmore, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>419-383-6761</phone>
      <email>jennifer.gilmore@utoledo.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://gammacore.com/prescribing-gammacore/clinical-safety/</url>
    <description>Safety information on the gammaCore Sapphire device.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garner R, Kumari R, Lanyon P, Doherty M, Zhang W. Prevalence, risk factors and associations of primary Raynaud's phenomenon: systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. BMJ Open. 2015 Mar 16;5(3):e006389. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2014-006389. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25776043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brand FN, Larson MG, Kannel WB, McGuirk JM. The occurrence of Raynaud's phenomenon in a general population: the Framingham Study. Vasc Med. 1997 Nov;2(4):296-301.</citation>
    <PMID>9575602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merkel PA, Herlyn K, Martin RW, Anderson JJ, Mayes MD, Bell P, Korn JH, Simms RW, Csuka ME, Medsger TA Jr, Rothfield NF, Ellman MH, Collier DH, Weinstein A, Furst DE, Jiménez SA, White B, Seibold JR, Wigley FM; Scleroderma Clinical Trials Consortium. Measuring disease activity and functional status in patients with scleroderma and Raynaud's phenomenon. Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Sep;46(9):2410-20.</citation>
    <PMID>12355489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matucci-Cerinic M, Kahaleh B, Wigley FM. Review: evidence that systemic sclerosis is a vascular disease. Arthritis Rheum. 2013 Aug;65(8):1953-62. doi: 10.1002/art.37988. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23666787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ennis H, Anderson ME, Wilkinson J, Herrick AL. Calcium channel blockers for primary Raynaud's phenomenon. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Jan 30;(1):CD002069. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD002069.pub4. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016;2:CD002069.</citation>
    <PMID>24482037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coleiro B, Marshall SE, Denton CP, Howell K, Blann A, Welsh KI, Black CM. Treatment of Raynaud's phenomenon with the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor fluoxetine. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2001 Sep;40(9):1038-43.</citation>
    <PMID>11561116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pauling JD, Shipley JA, Harris ND, McHugh NJ. Use of infrared thermography as an endpoint in therapeutic trials of Raynaud's phenomenon and systemic sclerosis. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2012 Mar-Apr;30(2 Suppl 71):S103-15. Epub 2012 May 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22691218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James PB. Cooling patterns in Raynaud's phenomenon and allied peripheral vascular disorders. Br J Surg. 1968 Nov;55(11):860.</citation>
    <PMID>5686991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaproudina N, Varmavuo V, Airaksinen O, Närhi M. Reproducibility of infrared thermography measurements in healthy individuals. Physiol Meas. 2008 Apr;29(4):515-24. doi: 10.1088/0967-3334/29/4/007. Epub 2008 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18401069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pauling JD, Shipley JA, Raper S, Watson ML, Ward SG, Harris ND, McHugh NJ. Comparison of infrared thermography and laser speckle contrast imaging for the dynamic assessment of digital microvascular function. Microvasc Res. 2012 Mar;83(2):162-7. doi: 10.1016/j.mvr.2011.06.012. Epub 2011 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21763703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schlager O, Gschwandtner ME, Herberg K, Frohner T, Schillinger M, Koppensteiner R, Mlekusch W. Correlation of infrared thermography and skin perfusion in Raynaud patients and in healthy controls. Microvasc Res. 2010 Jul;80(1):54-7. doi: 10.1016/j.mvr.2010.01.010. Epub 2010 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>20144625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson RL, Wilson CG. A review of vagus nerve stimulation as a therapeutic intervention. J Inflamm Res. 2018 May 16;11:203-213. doi: 10.2147/JIR.S163248. eCollection 2018. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29844694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silberstein SD, Calhoun AH, Treppendahl C, Dodick DW, Rapoport AM, Mamidi A, Vargas P, Ebert TH, Tepper SJ. The emerging role of gammaCore® in the management of cluster headache: expert panel recommendations. Am J Manag Care. 2017 Nov;23(17 Suppl):S326-S333.</citation>
    <PMID>29144718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Toledo Health Science Campus</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bashar Kahaleh, M.D</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Raynaud Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

