<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03863873</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRPCTS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03863873</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Platelet-Rich Plasma in the Treatment of Patients With Idiopathic Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Platelet-Rich Plasma in the Treatment of Patients With Idiopathic Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled trial in a cohort of Egyptian patients suffered from mild to
      moderate idiopathic carpal tunnel. They were randomly divided into two groups. Group 1:
      patients received ultrasound-guided platelet-rich plasma injection and group 2 patients
      received ultrasound-guided corticosteroid injection. The outcome measures were assessed via
      Visual Analogue Scale, the Boston Carpal Tunnel Syndrome Questionnaire, electrophysiological
      findings in sensory and motor function of the median nerve and morphological changes of
      median nerve detected by ultrasound.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intervention:

      PRP Injection Group(PRP-inj-G) - This group included 49 patients (40 females and 9 males).
      Their age ranged from 20 to 60 years.

      PRP Preparation: 16 ml of blood was obtained from each patient using special PRP kits (GD
      medical pharma, Dutch company). The blood was collected on citrated tubes with a mixing ratio
      of 9:1 by volume. Tubes underwent 1st centrifugation at speed of 3000 rpm (704g) for 3
      minutes (to separate red blood cells from plasma). Plasma was then removed by syringe and
      then placed into another sterile tube with no anticoagulant and then underwent 2nd
      centrifugation at speed of at 4000 rpm (1252g) for 15 min. The supernatant platelet-poor
      plasma was then removed leaving 2 ml of PRP pellets in the sediment, and suspend the PRP
      pellets by gentle shaking of the tube. PRP is activated by adding 200 μl of 0.025 calcium
      chloride(Dhurat and Sukesh, 2014).

      Ultrasound-Guided Injection: Proper preparation with an antiseptic solution of skin overlying
      the point of injection was performed guided by ultrasonography (Siemens Acuson P300 machine).
      With the palm facing upward and the wrist joint in slight extension, the MN will be
      recognized at the inlet of the CT(Wu et al., 2017). The injection was guided by ultrasound
      with the use of the ulnar in-plane technique(Lee et al., 2014). Ulnar artery was identified
      by the means of Doppler imaging, and a 25-gauge needle was introduced from the ulnar side of
      the wrist between CT and MN. Then the entire CT was scanned to confirm that the injection had
      dispersed through the proximal to the distal area of the CT. All patients were observed for
      30 minutes post-injection for the possibility of dysesthesia or bleeding(Wu et al., 2017).

      PRP injection: A 25-gauge needle was gently introduced one cm proximal to the distal
      wrist-flexion crease just to the ulnar side of the palmaris longus tendon and 2 ml of PRP was
      injected into the CT.

      Steroid injection Group(St-inj-G) - included 49 patients (41 females and 8 males)with their
      age ranged from 20 to 60 years. A single injection of methylprednisolone acetate 40 mg/ml
      using a technique similar to that described for the PRP injection

      Post-injection care for both groups:

        -  Some patients may have minimal to moderate discomfort after injection. So, to control
           pain, patients should apply ice on the injection site and also modify activity as
           tolerated.

        -  Rest for one day.

        -  The patient immediately returns to work two days after injection.

        -  Pain medication in the form of paracetamol only was allowed for the next 3 months if
           needed. The patients were instructed to stop analgesics 48 hours before the visit to
           allow proper symptoms assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>three months</time_frame>
    <description>The VAS-pain score is composed of a continuous horizontal line. This line is 100 mm in length. To measure the intensity of pain, the score is anchored by (0 score = no pain) at one end and (100 score = worst imaginable pain) on the other end. The patient places a mark to the VAS line at the point which represents the intensity of his pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Function improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>three months</time_frame>
    <description>The Boston CT Questionnaire (BCTQ) is a patient-based outcome measure that was designed specifically for CTS patients. BCTQ has 2 distinct scales, the Symptom Severity Scale (BCTQ-SSS) containing 11 questions and the Functional Status Scale (BCTQ-FSS) containing 8 items. All questions were rated for degree of difficulty on a 5points scale. Each scale producesa final average score (sum of the scores divided by number of items) with a higher score indicative of greater disability. The BCTQ was used as an outcome measure in clinical trials, and has been reported as a validity and reliable tool for assessment of CTS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Edema</measure>
    <time_frame>three months</time_frame>
    <description>US examination of the m-CSA for all patients was performed using a 7-13 MHz linear array probe with a calibrated device (Siemens, Acuson P300 apparatus) on the same day of EDX examination and clinical evaluation. All US examinations were performed with the wrists at the neutral position. The US examiner applied a minimal pressure force to avoid induction of artificial nerve deformation. Three measurements of the m-CSA at the level of most-protuberant portion of the pisiform bone were performed. The mean of the three measurements is calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PRP Injection Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PRP Preparation: 16 ml of blood was obtained from each patient using special PRP kits (GD medical pharma, Dutch company). The blood was collected on citrated tubes with a mixing ratio of 9:1 by volume. Tubes underwent 1st centrifugation at speed of 3000 rpm (704g) for 3 minutes (to separate red blood cells from plasma). Plasma was then removed by syringe and then placed into another sterile tube with no anticoagulant and then underwent 2nd centrifugation at speed of at 4000 rpm (1252g) for 15 min. The supernatant platelet-poor plasma was then removed leaving 2 ml of PRP pellets in the sediment, and suspend the PRP pellets by gentle shaking of the tube. PRP is activated by adding 200 μl of 0.025 calcium chloride(Dhurat and Sukesh, 2014).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Steroid injection Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single injection of methylprednisolone acetate 40 mg/ml using a technique similar to that described for the PRP injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Platelet-Rich Plasma Injection Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Platelet-Rich Plasma Injection Group</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRP Injection Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Steroid injection Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with mild-to-moderate idiopathic CTS with clinical manifestations failed to
             respond to conservative treatment ( such as splint, medications, Physical therapy) for
             at least 3 months and they were diagnosed by electrophysiological study and
             musculoskeletal ultrasound.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetes

          -  Hypothyroidism

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis

          -  Previous carpal tunnel decompressive surgery

          -  Cervical radiculopathy, polyneuropathy, brachial plexopathy, traumatic nerve injury,
             thoracic outlet syndrome

          -  Previous corticosteroid injection into the carpal tunnel in the preceding 4 weeks

          -  Anemia (hemoglobin &lt;10gm%)

          -  Coagulopathy

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mansoura University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansoura</city>
        <zip>35516</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mansoura University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Reham Magdy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet-rich plasma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

