<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03868722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PreVent-ACaLL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03868722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acalabrutinib and Venetoclax Treatment of Newly Diagnosed Patients With CLL at High Risk of Infection or Early Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Short-term Combined Acalabrutinib and Venetoclax Treatment of Newly Diagnosed Patients With CLL at High Risk of Infection and/or Early Treatment, Who do Not Fulfil IWCLL Treatment Criteria.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stichting Hemato-Oncologie voor Volwassenen Nederland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many patients with CLL have a weakened immune system due to their disease. It increases their
      risk of developing serious, treatment-requiring infections such as blood poisoning or
      pneumonia, which in the worst case may end with fatal outcomes.

      Serious infections due to CLL are responsible for one third of all deaths among CLL patients.
      PreVent-ACaLL study will investigate whether a combination of two known types of cancer drugs
      can reduce the risk of infection and thus mortality when given preventively to newly
      diagnosed CLL patients.

      A newly developed register-based computer model can predict which patients are at high risk
      in order to develop infections as a result of their CLL. A preventive treatment might be
      initiated before patients need chemotherapy. In this way, the cancer disease might be &quot;reset&quot;
      so that the immune system, which is inhibited by CLL, is restored and the risk of fatal
      infections is minimized.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE AND HYPOTHESIS Phase 2, randomized study of short-term, combined venetoclax and
      acalabrutinib treatment of newly diagnosed patients with CLL. For patients identified by
      CLL-TIM (the Machine Learning predictive algorithm, Treatment Infection Model) at high risk
      of infection and/or early CLL treatment, it is tested whether grade 3-Infection-free,
      treatment-free survival can be improved by three months of venetoclax+acalabrutinib
      treatment. Changes in immune dysfunction are measured by an extensive translational program
      for correlation with changes in infection.

      BACKGROUND Infection and immune dysfunction in patients diagnosed with CLL leads to
      significant morbidity and mortality, as exemplified by the constant rate of infectious deaths
      in CLL over the last three decades, despite significant improvement in all other causes of
      death. This also affects patients who do not need treatment according to IWCLL criteria, thus
      infections are the leading cause of death among patients with CLL. Based on a novel machine
      learning algorithm, CLL-TIM, patients at high risk (&gt;65% 2-years risk) of severe infection
      and/or CLL treatment can be identified at diagnosis. By a short period of preemptive
      treatment for these patients, the aim is to change the natural history of CLL and immune
      dysfunction.

      METHODS The study is an intergroup study between the HOVON (Belgium, the Netherlands) and the
      Nordic (Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Finland) CLL study groups. For the phase 2 study, 4-8 sites
      with the capacity of the extensive translational immune phenotyping and/or timely shipment of
      samples will be selected. Patients are randomized between venetoclax+acalabrutinib treatment
      for three months or observation. For each treatment arm, 25 patients are needed (50 in
      total). Thorough assessment of immune function before, during and after treatment as well as
      detailed reporting on infectious complications, the proof of concept of the PreVent-ACaLL
      study's capacity to change the natural history of immune dysfunction in CLL by short-term
      venetoclax-acalabrutinib treatment will be made.

      PERSPECTIVES By addressing the unmet need of improving immune function for newly diagnosed
      CLL patients with high risk of infections and/or early CLL treatment, the aim is to change
      the paradigm for CLL treatment and the natural history of the disease.

      If the phase 2 trial demonstrates a clear signal for safety with indication of benefit for
      patients in the treatment arm, an extension phase 3 study is planned with the potential to
      change the future management of CLL.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2029</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomization has to occur within 42 days after the first tests for screening were performed. Patients will be randomly assigned to treatment vs observation through 1:1 randomization process with stratification according to country, TP53 aberration status and IGHV mutational status. Treatment or observation period has to be initiated within 14 days after randomization.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade 3-Infection-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after finishing treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Grade 3-Infection-free survival in the treatment arm compared to the observation arm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival, event being either grade ≥3 infection or CLL treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after treatment initiation,1 year and 2 years after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival, event being either grade ≥3 infection or CLL treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 12 weeks, 1 year and 2 years from treatment/observation initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 12 weeks, 1 year and 2 years from treatment/observation initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of infections</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed at 12 weeks, 1 year and 2 years from treatment/observation initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of infections</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of infections grade ≥3</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed at 12 weeks, 1 year and 2 years from treatment/observation initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of infections</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">212</enrollment>
  <condition>CLL</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with Acalabrutinib and Venetoclax is initiated within 14 days after randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Observation period is initiated within 14 days after randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acalabrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Acalabrutinib 100 mg BID from cycle 1 day 1 for 3 cycles of 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Calquence</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venetoclax</intervention_name>
    <description>Venetoclax, ramp up during the first five weeks starting cycle 1 day 1, 7 days treatment on each dose level (20-50-100-200-400 mg), thereafter 400 mg once daily for a total of 3 cycles of 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Venclexta</other_name>
    <other_name>Venclyxto</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. CLL diagnosed according to IWCLL criteria within one year prior to randomization

          2. High risk of infection and/or progressive treatment within 2 years according to
             CLL-TIM

          3. IWCLL treatment indication not fulfilled

          4. Life expectancy &gt; 2 years

          5. Age at least 18 years

          6. Ability and willingness to provide written informed consent and adhere to study
             procedures and treatment

          7. Adequate bone marrow function as indicated by platelets above 100 x 10E9, hemoglobin
             above 10 g/dL and neutrophils above 1 x 10E9

          8. Creatinine clearance above 30 mL/min directly measured with 24hr urine collection or
             calculated according to the modified formula of Cockcroft and Gault

          9. Adequate liver function as indicated by a total bilirubin≤ 2 x, AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 x the
             institutional ULN value, unless directly attributable to the patient's CLL or to
             Gilbert's Syndrome.

         10. Negative serological testing for hepatitis B (HBsAg negative and anti-HBc negative;
             patients positive for anti-HBc may be included if PCR for HBV DNA is negative and
             HBV-DNA PCR is performed every month until 12 months after last treatment cycle),
             negative testing for hepatitis C RNA within 6 weeks prior to registration.

         11. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status (ECOG) performance status 0-2.

         12. Woman of childbearing potential (WOCBP) who are sexually active must use highly
             effective methods of contraception during treatment and for 2 days after the last dose
             of investigational drugs.

         13. Willing and able to participate in all required evaluations and procedures in this
             study protocol including swallowing capsules without difficulty.

         14. Ability to understand the purpose and risks of the study and provide signed and dated
             informed consent and authorization to use protected health information

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior CLL treatment (including monoclonal antibodies, chemotherapy, small molecules)

          2. Transformation of CLL (Richter's transformation)

          3. Previous autoimmune disease as AIHA (autoimmune hemolytic anemia) or ITP (idiopathic
             thrombocytopenic purpura) treated with immune suppression or uncontrolled AIHA or ITP

          4. History of PML

          5. Uncontrolled or active infection

          6. Malignancies other than CLL requiring systemic therapies (except anti-hormonal
             therapies) or considered to impact survival

          7. Requirement of therapy with strong CYP3A4 and CYP3A5 inhibitors/inducers or
             anticoagulant therapy with vitamin K antagonists

          8. History of bleeding disorders or current platelet inhibitors or anticoagulant therapy

          9. History of clinically significant cardiovascular disease such as arrhythmias,
             congestive heart failure, or myocardial infarction within 6 months of screening, or
             any Class 3 or 4 cardiac disease as defined by the New York Heart Association
             Functional Classification, or corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 480 msec at screening.

         10. History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to registration.

         11. Use of investigational agents which might interfere with the study drug within 28 days
             prior to registration.

         12. Vaccination with live vaccines 28 days prior to registration.

         13. Major surgery less than 30 days before start of treatment.

         14. Known hypersensitivity to any active substance or to any of the excipients of one of
             the drugs used in the trial.

         15. Pregnant women and nursing mothers (a negative pregnancy test is required for all
             women of childbearing potential within 7 days before start of treatment; further
             pregnancy testing will be performed regularly).

         16. Fertile men or women of childbearing potential unless: surgically sterile or ≥ 2 years
             after the onset of menopause or willing to use two methods of reliable contraception
             including one highly effective contraceptive method (Pearl Index &lt;1) and one
             additional effective (barrier) method during study treatment and for 18 months after
             the end of study treatment.

         17. Legal incapacity.

         18. Persons who are in dependence to the sponsor or an investigator

         19. Persons not considered fit for the trial by the investigator

         20. Malabsorption syndrome, disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal function, or
             resection of the stomach or small bowel that is likely to affect absorption,
             symptomatic inflammatory bowel disease, partial or complete bowel obstruction, or
             gastric restrictions and bariatric surgery, such as gastric bypass.

         21. Presence of a gastrointestinal ulcer diagnosed by endoscopy within 3 months before
             screening.

         22. Requires treatment with a strong cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitor/inducer.

         23. Prothrombin time/INR or aPTT (in the absence of Lupus anticoagulant) &gt; 2x ULN.

         24. Requires treatment with proton pump inhibitors (eg, omeprazole, esomeprazole,
             lansoprazole, dexlansoprazole, rabeprazole, or pantoprazole). Subjects receiving
             proton pump inhibitors who switch to H2-receptor antagonists or antacids are eligible
             for enrollment to this study.

         25. Major surgical procedure within 7 days of first dose of study drug. Note: If a subject
             had major surgery, they must have recovered adequately from any toxicity and/or
             complications from the intervention before the first dose of study drug.

         26. Breastfeeding or pregnant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carsten U Niemann, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carsten U Niemann, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 35457830</phone>
    <email>carsten.utoft.niemann@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bitten Aagaard, RN</last_name>
    <phone>+45 35455791</phone>
    <email>bitten.aagaard@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carsten U Niemann, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 3545 7830</phone>
      <email>carsten.utoft.niemann@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carsten U Niemann, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herlev og Gentofte Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herlev</city>
        <zip>2730</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisbeth Enggaard, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 3868 9118</phone>
      <email>lisbeth.enggaard@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lisbeth Enggaard, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sjællands Universitetshospital Roskilde</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roskilde</city>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian B Poulsen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4547324809</phone>
      <email>cbpo@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian B Poulsen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barf T, Covey T, Izumi R, van de Kar B, Gulrajani M, van Lith B, van Hoek M, de Zwart E, Mittag D, Demont D, Verkaik S, Krantz F, Pearson PG, Ulrich R, Kaptein A. Acalabrutinib (ACP-196): A Covalent Bruton Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor with a Differentiated Selectivity and In Vivo Potency Profile. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2017 Nov;363(2):240-252. doi: 10.1124/jpet.117.242909. Epub 2017 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>28882879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradshaw JM. The Src, Syk, and Tec family kinases: distinct types of molecular switches. Cell Signal. 2010 Aug;22(8):1175-84. doi: 10.1016/j.cellsig.2010.03.001. Epub 2010 Mar 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20206686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Rooij MF, Kuil A, Geest CR, Eldering E, Chang BY, Buggy JJ, Pals ST, Spaargaren M. The clinically active BTK inhibitor PCI-32765 targets B-cell receptor- and chemokine-controlled adhesion and migration in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Blood. 2012 Mar 15;119(11):2590-4. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-11-390989. Epub 2012 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22279054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan WN. Regulation of B lymphocyte development and activation by Bruton's tyrosine kinase. Immunol Res. 2001;23(2-3):147-56. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11444380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohamed AJ, Yu L, Bäckesjö CM, Vargas L, Faryal R, Aints A, Christensson B, Berglöf A, Vihinen M, Nore BF, Smith CI. Bruton's tyrosine kinase (Btk): function, regulation, and transformation with special emphasis on the PH domain. Immunol Rev. 2009 Mar;228(1):58-73. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-065X.2008.00741.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19290921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ponader S, Chen SS, Buggy JJ, Balakrishnan K, Gandhi V, Wierda WG, Keating MJ, O'Brien S, Chiorazzi N, Burger JA. The Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor PCI-32765 thwarts chronic lymphocytic leukemia cell survival and tissue homing in vitro and in vivo. Blood. 2012 Feb 2;119(5):1182-9. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-10-386417. Epub 2011 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22180443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith TJ, Khatcheressian J, Lyman GH, Ozer H, Armitage JO, Balducci L, Bennett CL, Cantor SB, Crawford J, Cross SJ, Demetri G, Desch CE, Pizzo PA, Schiffer CA, Schwartzberg L, Somerfield MR, Somlo G, Wade JC, Wade JL, Winn RJ, Wozniak AJ, Wolff AC. 2006 update of recommendations for the use of white blood cell growth factors: an evidence-based clinical practice guideline. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Jul 1;24(19):3187-205. Epub 2006 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16682719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soucek L, Buggy JJ, Kortlever R, Adimoolam S, Monclús HA, Allende MT, Swigart LB, Evan GI. Modeling pharmacological inhibition of mast cell degranulation as a therapy for insulinoma. Neoplasia. 2011 Nov;13(11):1093-100.</citation>
    <PMID>22131884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carsten Utoft Niemann</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD, Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Venetoclax</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Restricted access based on individual agreements based on Danish and EU legislation</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

