<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03866174</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PSIL201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03866174</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Psilocybin for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Support-of-Concept Phase 2 Study of Single-Dose Psilocybin for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Usona Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Signant Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Emmes Company, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Usona Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Eighty participants, ages 21 to 65, who meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental
      Disorders (DSM-5) criteria for major depressive disorder (MDD) will be stratified by study
      site and randomized with a 1-to-1 allocation under double-blind conditions to receive a
      single 25 mg oral dose of psilocybin or a single 100 mg oral dose of niacin. Niacin will
      serve as an active placebo.

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the potential efficacy of a single 25 mg oral dose
      of psilocybin for MDD compared to the active placebo in otherwise medically-healthy
      participants, assessed as the difference between groups in changes in depressive symptoms
      from Baseline to Day 8 post-dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) has become a health crisis of epidemic proportions in the
      modern world. One in six individuals in the United States will experience an episode of major
      depression in his or her lifetime, and it is estimated that major depression will rank second
      after cardiac disease as a cause of international medical morbidity by the year 2020.
      Depression is associated with greater disability than are most other chronic illnesses and is
      a risk factor for mortality. Additionally, depression predicts the later development of a
      number of medical conditions, including cardiac and cerebrovascular disease, hypertension,
      diabetes, obesity, metabolic syndrome, dementia, and cancer. Unfortunately, most patients
      with depression do not experience a complete resolution of symptoms with antidepressant
      treatment. Partial—but incomplete—response to antidepressants is associated with an increased
      risk of full symptomatic relapse (even when on therapy) and a worse long-term disease course.
      Combined with the high prevalence and significant disability associated with MDD, the fact
      that currently available treatments are not fully adequate highlights the tremendous need to
      identify novel treatment strategies.

      Data suggest that psilocybin may have behavioral effects relevant to the treatment of
      depression and recent studies also suggest that psilocybin may possess antidepressant
      properties. To further assess the effects of psilocybin on MDD signs and symptoms, this trial
      will enroll 80 participants, ages 21 to 65, who meet criteria for MDD. Participants will be
      stratified by study site and randomized with a 1-to-1 allocation under double-blind
      conditions to receive a single 25 mg oral dose of psilocybin or a single 100 mg oral dose of
      niacin. Niacin will serve as an active placebo.

      To enhance participant safety, a Set and Setting (SaS) protocol will be utilized similar to
      the protocol that has been used in all modern studies of psilocybin. The SaS protocol for
      this study includes: 1) a period of preparation with session Facilitators prior to dosing; 2)
      administration of study medications in an aesthetically pleasing room under the supervision
      of two Facilitators who are present throughout the session; and 3) three post-dose
      integration sessions during which participants are encouraged to discuss their intervention
      experience with the Facilitators. The SaS protocol will be identical for those randomized to
      psilocybin or active placebo.

      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the potential efficacy of a single 25 mg
      oral dose of psilocybin for MDD compared to the active placebo (niacin), assessed as the
      difference between groups in changes in depressive symptoms from Baseline to Day 8 post-dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in central rater Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score from Baseline to post-dose Day 8</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; Day 8 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a clinician-rated scale designed to measure depression severity and to detect changes due to antidepressant treatment. The scale consists of 10 items, each of which is scored from 0 (item not present or normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of the symptoms), for a total possible score of 60. Higher scores represent a more severe condition. The total (composite) MADRS score is used as the endpoint.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in central rater MADRS score from Baseline to post-dose Day 43</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 43 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a clinician-rated scale designed to measure depression severity and to detect changes due to antidepressant treatment. The scale consists of 10 items, each of which is scored from 0 (item not present or normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of the symptoms), for a total possible score of 60. Higher scores represent a more severe condition. The total (composite) MADRS score is used as the endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in on-site rater administered Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS) score from Baseline to post-dose Day 43</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 43 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The SDS is a composite of three self-rated items designed to measure the extent to which three major sectors in the patient's life are impaired by psychiatric symptoms, including depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained depressive symptom response defined as a ≥ 50% reduction from Baseline central rater MADRS score at all post-dose assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 8, 15, 29, and 43 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a clinician-rated scale designed to measure depression severity and to detect changes due to antidepressant treatment. The scale consists of 10 items, each of which is scored from 0 (item not present or normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of the symptoms), for a total possible score of 60. Higher scores represent a more severe condition. The total (composite) MADRS score is used as the endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained depressive symptom remission defined as a central rater MADRS total score ≤ 10 at all post-dose assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 8, 15, 29, and 43 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a clinician-rated scale designed to measure depression severity and to detect changes due to antidepressant treatment. The scale consists of 10 items, each of which is scored from 0 (item not present or normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of the symptoms), for a total possible score of 60. Higher scores represent a more severe condition. The total (composite) MADRS score is used as the endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psilocybin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single 25 mg dose of psilocybin along with the Set and Setting protocol. Psilocybin is administered orally as a capsule and taken with water.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Niacin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single 100 mg dose of niacin along with the Set and Setting protocol. Niacin is administered orally as a capsule and taken with water.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psilocybin</intervention_name>
    <description>The psilocybin used in this study is synthetically manufactured in a laboratory and meets quality specifications suitable for human research use. The active drug is encapsulated using a hydroxypropyl methylcellulose (HPMC) capsule and contains 25 mg of psilocybin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Psilocybin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Psilocybine, Psilocibin, Indocybin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Niacin</intervention_name>
    <description>The active placebo is encapsulated using a HPMC capsule and contains 100 mg of pharmaceutical grade niacin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Niacin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vitamin B3</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  21 to 65 years old

          -  Able to swallow capsules

          -  If of childbearing potential, agree to practice an effective means of birth control
             throughout the duration of the study

          -  Have an identified support person and agree to be accompanied home by that person
             following dosing

          -  Have sustained moderate-severe depression symptoms at Screening and Baseline

          -  Meet DSM-5 criteria for a diagnosis of major depressive disorder and are currently
             experiencing a major depressive episode of at least a 60-day duration at the time of
             screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant or who intend to become pregnant during the study or who are
             currently nursing

          -  Have any of the following cardiovascular conditions: uncontrolled hypertension,
             coronary artery disease, congenital long QT syndrome, cardiac hypertrophy, cardiac
             ischemia, congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction, tachycardia, artificial
             heart valve, a clinically significant screening ECG abnormality, or any other
             significant cardiovascular condition

          -  Have a history of stroke or Transient Ischemic Attack (TIA)

          -  Have moderate to severe hepatic impairment

          -  Have epilepsy

          -  Have insulin-dependent diabetes

          -  Have a positive urine drug test

          -  Nicotine dependence that would disallow an individual to be nicotine free for the 7-10
             hours during the dosing period

          -  Meet DSM-5 criteria for schizophrenia spectrum or other psychotic disorders, including
             major depressive disorder with psychotic features, or Bipolar I or Bipolar II Disorder

          -  Meet DSM-5 criteria for antisocial personality disorder

          -  Meet DSM-5 criteria for a moderate or severe alcohol or drug use disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Raison, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Usona Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rob Barrow, MS</last_name>
    <phone>608-278-7662</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials@usonainstitute.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karlis Janelsins, BS</last_name>
    <phone>608-278-7662</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials@usonainstitute.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Catriona S Miller, BA</last_name>
      <phone>510-985-3522</phone>
      <email>psil_201@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer M Mitchell, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>510-985-3921</phone>
      <email>psil_201@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jane Wanyiri, RN</last_name>
      <phone>203-764-9131</phone>
      <email>jane.wanyiri@yale.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Cooper, BS</last_name>
      <phone>203-764-9182</phone>
      <email>elizabeth.cooper@yale.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Segal Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lauderhill</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33319</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Orbrena Wellons, MA</last_name>
      <phone>954-990-6326</phone>
      <email>owellons@segaltrials.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Courtney Talbert, MS</last_name>
      <phone>954-990-6326</phone>
      <email>ctalbert@segaltrials.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Lakes Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60640</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amber Holst</last_name>
      <phone>872-529-8805</phone>
      <email>aholst@greatlakesclinicaltrials.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nathan Sepeda, BS</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-2253</phone>
      <email>nsepeda1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Lombardi, BS</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-5243</phone>
      <email>jlomba15@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julia R Benville, BA</last_name>
      <phone>212-263-1507</phone>
      <email>Julia.Benville@nyulangone.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Leila Ghazal, MA</last_name>
      <phone>212-263-1507</phone>
      <email>leila.ghazal@nyulangone.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin - Madison</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53706</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bri Deyo, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>608-225-0718</phone>
      <email>protea.research@mailplus.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs369/en/</url>
    <description>World Health Organization Overview of Depression</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://usonaclinicaltrials.org/major-depressive-disorder-psilocybin-clinical-trial-psil201</url>
    <description>Usona Clinical Trials Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carhart-Harris RL, Leech R, Hellyer PJ, Shanahan M, Feilding A, Tagliazucchi E, Chialvo DR, Nutt D. The entropic brain: a theory of conscious states informed by neuroimaging research with psychedelic drugs. Front Hum Neurosci. 2014 Feb 3;8:20. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2014.00020. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24550805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nichols DE. Hallucinogens. Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Feb;101(2):131-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14761703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kessler RC, Berglund P, Demler O, Jin R, Koretz D, Merikangas KR, Rush AJ, Walters EE, Wang PS; National Comorbidity Survey Replication. The epidemiology of major depressive disorder: results from the National Comorbidity Survey Replication (NCS-R). JAMA. 2003 Jun 18;289(23):3095-105.</citation>
    <PMID>12813115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Global Burden of Disease Study 2013 Collaborators. Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 301 acute and chronic diseases and injuries in 188 countries, 1990-2013: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013. Lancet. 2015 Aug 22;386(9995):743-800. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60692-4. Epub 2015 Jun 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26063472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wulsin LR, Vaillant GE, Wells VE. A systematic review of the mortality of depression. Psychosom Med. 1999 Jan-Feb;61(1):6-17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10024062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joynt KE, Whellan DJ, O'Connor CM. Depression and cardiovascular disease: mechanisms of interaction. Biol Psychiatry. 2003 Aug 1;54(3):248-61. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12893101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas AJ, Kalaria RN, O'Brien JT. Depression and vascular disease: what is the relationship? J Affect Disord. 2004 Apr;79(1-3):81-95. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15023483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davidson K, Jonas BS, Dixon KE, Markovitz JH. Do depression symptoms predict early hypertension incidence in young adults in the CARDIA study? Coronary Artery Risk Development in Young Adults. Arch Intern Med. 2000 May 22;160(10):1495-500.</citation>
    <PMID>10826464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jonas BS, Lando JF. Negative affect as a prospective risk factor for hypertension. Psychosom Med. 2000 Mar-Apr;62(2):188-96.</citation>
    <PMID>10772396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eaton WW, Armenian H, Gallo J, Pratt L, Ford DE. Depression and risk for onset of type II diabetes. A prospective population-based study. Diabetes Care. 1996 Oct;19(10):1097-102.</citation>
    <PMID>8886555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kawakami N, Takatsuka N, Shimizu H, Ishibashi H. Depressive symptoms and occurrence of type 2 diabetes among Japanese men. Diabetes Care. 1999 Jul;22(7):1071-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10388970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barefoot JC, Heitmann BL, Helms MJ, Williams RB, Surwit RS, Siegler IC. Symptoms of depression and changes in body weight from adolescence to mid-life. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 1998 Jul;22(7):688-94.</citation>
    <PMID>9705031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pine DS, Goldstein RB, Wolk S, Weissman MM. The association between childhood depression and adulthood body mass index. Pediatrics. 2001 May;107(5):1049-56.</citation>
    <PMID>11331685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Räikkönen K, Matthews KA, Kuller LH. The relationship between psychological risk attributes and the metabolic syndrome in healthy women: antecedent or consequence? Metabolism. 2002 Dec;51(12):1573-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12489070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jorm AF. History of depression as a risk factor for dementia: an updated review. Aust N Z J Psychiatry. 2001 Dec;35(6):776-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11990888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spiegel D, Giese-Davis J. Depression and cancer: mechanisms and disease progression. Biol Psychiatry. 2003 Aug 1;54(3):269-82. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12893103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greden JF. The burden of disease for treatment-resistant depression. J Clin Psychiatry. 2001;62 Suppl 16:26-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11480881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Judd LL, Akiskal HS, Maser JD, Zeller PJ, Endicott J, Coryell W, Paulus MP, Kunovac JL, Leon AC, Mueller TI, Rice JA, Keller MB. A prospective 12-year study of subsyndromal and syndromal depressive symptoms in unipolar major depressive disorders. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1998 Aug;55(8):694-700.</citation>
    <PMID>9707379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller IW, Keitner GI, Schatzberg AF, Klein DN, Thase ME, Rush AJ, Markowitz JC, Schlager DS, Kornstein SG, Davis SM, Harrison WM, Keller MB. The treatment of chronic depression, part 3: psychosocial functioning before and after treatment with sertraline or imipramine. J Clin Psychiatry. 1998 Nov;59(11):608-19.</citation>
    <PMID>9862607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simon GE. Long-term prognosis of depression in primary care. Bull World Health Organ. 2000;78(4):439-45.</citation>
    <PMID>10885162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carhart-Harris RL, Bolstridge M, Rucker J, Day CM, Erritzoe D, Kaelen M, Bloomfield M, Rickard JA, Forbes B, Feilding A, Taylor D, Pilling S, Curran VH, Nutt DJ. Psilocybin with psychological support for treatment-resistant depression: an open-label feasibility study. Lancet Psychiatry. 2016 Jul;3(7):619-27. doi: 10.1016/S2215-0366(16)30065-7. Epub 2016 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>27210031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Griffiths RR, Johnson MW, Carducci MA, Umbricht A, Richards WA, Richards BD, Cosimano MP, Klinedinst MA. Psilocybin produces substantial and sustained decreases in depression and anxiety in patients with life-threatening cancer: A randomized double-blind trial. J Psychopharmacol. 2016 Dec;30(12):1181-1197.</citation>
    <PMID>27909165</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross S, Bossis A, Guss J, Agin-Liebes G, Malone T, Cohen B, Mennenga SE, Belser A, Kalliontzi K, Babb J, Su Z, Corby P, Schmidt BL. Rapid and sustained symptom reduction following psilocybin treatment for anxiety and depression in patients with life-threatening cancer: a randomized controlled trial. J Psychopharmacol. 2016 Dec;30(12):1165-1180.</citation>
    <PMID>27909164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psilocybin, Psychedelics, Depression, MDD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Niacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psilocybin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

