<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03860584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018H0564</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03860584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alleviation Of Metabolic Endotoxemia In Adults With Metabolic Syndrome With Milk Fat Globule Membrane</brief_title>
  <official_title>Alleviation Of Metabolic Endotoxemia In Adults With Metabolic Syndrome With Milk Fat Globule Membrane</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic syndrome (MetS) adults (n = 24; 18-65 y) will be enrolled to complete a 2-arm,
      double-blind, randomized controlled, crossover trial. They will be randomized in 4-unit
      blocks to receive, for 14 d, a controlled diet with dairy milk (3.5% fat; 3 servings/d)
      enriched with milk fat globule membrane (MFGM)-derived phospholipid or a matched dairy milk
      that instead contains soy lecithin/phospholipid (control). All foods during each study period
      will be provided to ensure weight maintenance and to increase homogeneity of gut and host
      responses. Anthropometrics and blood pressure will be assessed at days 0, 7, and 14. Prior to
      (day 0) and after each 2-wk arm (day 14), a fasting blood sample will be collected to assess
      serum endotoxin and metabolic chemistries (glucose, lipids, insulin), and Toll-like receptor
      4 /nuclear factor kappaB (TLR4/NFκB)-dependent genes from isolated peripheral blood
      mononuclear cells (PBMCs). A breath sample will be collected to assess the correlation
      analysis of plasma metabolic biomarkers. After the 2-week intervention, from fecal samples
      collected on day 13, the investigators will assess microbiota composition and function, short
      chain fatty acids (SCFA), and intestinal inflammatory markers (calprotectin,
      myeloperoxidase). On d 14, participants in the fasted state will receive a
      high-fat/high-glucose meal challenge to induce gut-derived endotoxin translocation. At
      30-minute intervals for 3-hour, the investigators will evaluate circulating endotoxin,
      glucose, and insulin; TLR4/NFκB-dependent genes will be assessed from PMBCs at 0 hour and
      3-hour. Gut permeability probes will be co-administered with the test meal challenge, and
      24-hour urine will be collected to assess gut barrier integrity. Participants will then
      undergo a 2-week washout prior to receiving the alternative treatment and completing all
      procedures in an identical manner.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and hypothesis:

      Our preclinical evidence shows that phospholipid-rich milk fat globule membrane (MFGM)
      attenuates lipopolysaccharide-induced increases in gut permeability and pro-inflammatory
      cytokines. MFGM also attenuates inflammation in association with a prebiotic and/or
      antimicrobial activity that modulates microbiota composition. Our central hypothesis is that
      MFGM-enriched dairy milk compared with a matched milk beverage containing soy lecithin
      (control) decreases metabolic endotoxemia and improves glucose tolerance in metabolic
      syndrome (MetS) adults by increasing gut barrier integrity in association with alleviating
      gut dysbiosis and inflammation.

      Study Design:

      The investigators will enroll male and female MetS adults (n = 24; 18-65 y) to complete a
      2-arm, double-blind, randomized controlled, crossover trial. They will be randomized in
      4-unit blocks to receive, for 14 days, a controlled diet with dairy milk (3.5% fat; 3
      servings/d) enriched with MFGM-derived phospholipid or a matched dairy milk that instead
      contains coconut and palm oil (control). The investigators will provide all foods during each
      study period to ensure weight maintenance and to increase homogeneity of gut and host
      responses.

      Subjects:

      Participants will be recruited from Columbus, OH area. Participants having no history of
      liver or cardiovascular disease or cancer will be enrolled. They will have ≥3 established
      criteria for MetS: i) glucose (100-126 mg/dL), ii) waist circumference (&gt;89 or &gt;102 cm for
      F/M), iii) HDL-C (&lt;50 or &lt;40 mg/dL in F/M), iv) TG &gt;150 mg/dL, and iv) blood pressure &gt;130/85
      mmHg. Major exclusion criteria include: unstable body mass (±2 kg over prior 3-mo)
      vegetarian; food allergies or lactose intolerance; user of dietary supplements or probiotics
      (within past 1-mo); pregnancy, lactation, changes in birth control (within 6-month); any
      gastrointestinal disorders; chronic diarrhea; smoker; excess alcohol (&gt;2 drinks/day); excess
      aerobic exercise (&gt;7 h/week); recent antibiotic or anti-inflammatory agent use; blood
      pressure &gt;140/90 mmHg.

      Dietary Control:

      The intervention will be performed in the Human Nutrition Metabolic Kitchen under the auspice
      of a registered dietitian (PI Bruno). In each 2-wk intervention, participants' diet will be
      rigorously controlled. All foods will be prepared, packaged, and provided every 3-4 days to
      supply a weight maintenance (i.e. eucaloric) diet. To assess compliance, participants will
      return MFGM/coconut/palm oil milk bottles for counting and any uneaten food portions for
      weighed measurement. Milk beverages will also be formulated to contain para-aminobenzoic acid
      (PABA; 80 mg/milk serving). Spot urine samples will be collected 4 times during each study
      arm coinciding when participants pick up test foods. Urinary PABA will be measured by
      spectrophotometry. Separate from this, participants will also keep food logs to document any
      dietary deviation. Diets will be standardized at 50-60% of energy from carbohydrate with low
      fiber intakes (~15 g/day) similar to Americans' diets to prevent potential masking of the
      benefits of MFGM, 15-20% from protein, and 25-30% from fat. Importantly, other than test
      beverages provided as part of the eucaloric diet, diets will be otherwise devoid of
      significant amounts of dairy foods, fermented products, and probiotics to prevent confounding
      effects.

      Measurements:

      Anthropometrics and blood pressure will be assessed at days 0, 7, and 14. Prior to (day 0),
      at day 7 and after each 2-wk arm (day 14), a fasting blood sample will be collected to assess
      serum endotoxin and metabolic chemistries (glucose, insulin, lipids (triglyceride, total and
      HDL cholesterol), and TLR4/NFκB-dependent genes from isolated peripheral blood mononuclear
      cells (PBMCs). A breath sample will be collected to assess the correlation analysis of plasma
      metabolic biomarkers. After the 2-week intervention, from fecal samples collected on day 13,
      the investigators will assess microbiota composition and function, SCFAs, and intestinal
      inflammatory markers (calprotectin, myeloperoxidase). During this period, participants will
      also record daily stool characteristics using a 7-point Bristol Stool scale. On days 14,
      participants in the fasted state will receive a high-fat/high-glucose meal challenge to
      induce gut-derived endotoxin translocation. At 30-minute intervals for 3 hours, the
      investigators will evaluate circulating endotoxin, glucose, and insulin; TLR4/NFκB-dependent
      genes will be assessed from PMBCs at 0 hour and 3-hour. Gut permeability probes will be
      co-administered with the test meal challenge, and 24-hour urine will be collected to assess
      gut barrier integrity. Participants will then undergo a 2-week washout prior to receiving the
      alternative treatment and completing all procedures in an identical manner.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2-arm, double-blind, randomized controlled, crossover trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Both participants and key research personnel will be blinded between MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk (treatment) and milk with soy phospholipid/lecithin (control).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Endotoxin (LPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in serum endotoxin (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Endotoxin (LPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 (0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 minutes post-meal challenge)</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in the area under the curve of serum endotoxin (0-3 hours) on day 14</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma glucose (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 (0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 minutes post-meal challenge)</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in the area under the curve of plasma glucose (0-3 hours) on day 14</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 (0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 minutes post-meal challenge)</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in the area under the curve of plasma insulin (0-3 hours) on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma HDL-C</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma HDL-C (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Triglyceride</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma triglyceride (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma total cholesterol (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma glucagon-like peptide-1</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma glucagon-like peptide-1 (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine Lactulose</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in 24 hour urinal excretion of lactulose post-meal challenge on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine sucralose</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in 24 hour urinal excretion of sucralose post-meal challenge on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine erythritol</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in 24 hour urinal excretion of erythritol post-meal challenge on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine mannitol</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in 24 hour urinal excretion of mannitol post-meal challenge on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal bacterial abundance and composition</measure>
    <time_frame>day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in fecal bacterial abundance and composition on day 13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Acetate</measure>
    <time_frame>day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in fecal acetate on day 13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Butyrate</measure>
    <time_frame>day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in fecal butyrate on day 13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Propionate</measure>
    <time_frame>day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in fecal propionate on day 13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma gastric inhibitory polypeptide (GIP)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in plasma gastric inhibitory polypeptide (GIP) (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Calprotectin</measure>
    <time_frame>day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in fecal calprotectin on day 13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal Myeloperoxidase</measure>
    <time_frame>day 13</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment difference in fecal myeloperoxidase on day 13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating Toll-like receptor 4 mRNA</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in circulating Toll-like receptor 4 mRNA (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating IL-6 mRNA</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in circulating IL-6 mRNA (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating TNFa mRNA</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in circulating TNFa mRNA (fasting) on day 14 relative to day 0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating Toll-like receptor 4 mRNA</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 (0, 3 hour post-meal challenge)</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in circulating Toll-like receptor 4 mRNA post meal challenge (0-3 h) on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating IL-6 mRNA</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 (0, 3 hour post-meal challenge)</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in circulating IL-6 mRNA post meal challenge (0-3 h) on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating TNFa mRNA</measure>
    <time_frame>day 14 (0, 3 hour post-meal challenge)</time_frame>
    <description>Between-treatment change in circulating TNFa mRNA post meal challenge (0-3 h) on day 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Endotoxemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will receive MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk (3 servings/d) that contains MFGM at 10% phospholipid (relative to total lipid content) delivering MFGM at ~10-times that in full-fat dairy milk.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Soy phospholipid/lecithin milk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will receive a matched dairy milk that instead contains soy phospholipid/lecithin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk</intervention_name>
    <description>MetS adults with metabolic endotoxemia will be enrolled to complete a 2-arm, double-blind, randomized controlled, crossover trial to test the independent benefits of MFGM. For each 2-wk arm, they will receive MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk (3 servings/d) or a matched dairy milk that instead contains soy phospholipid/lecithin (control). Milks have been formulated with soy lecithin or MFGM at 10% phospholipid (relative to total lipid content). This delivers MFGM at ~10-times that in full-fat dairy milk, which reflects that consumers obtain MFGM from dairy foods other than whole milk.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soy phospholipid/lecithin milk</intervention_name>
    <description>MetS adults with metabolic endotoxemia will be enrolled to complete a 2-arm, double-blind, randomized controlled, crossover trial to test the independent benefits of MFGM. For each 2-wk arm, they will receive MFGM-enriched full-fat dairy milk (3 servings/d) or a matched dairy milk that instead contains soy phospholipid/lecithin (control). Milks have been formulated with soy lecithin or MFGM at 10% phospholipid (relative to total lipid content).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Soy phospholipid/lecithin milk</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Serum Glucose 100-126 mg/dl

          -  Waist C &gt;89/102 cm; F/M

          -  Serum HDL-C: &lt;50/40 mg/dl; F/M

          -  Serum TG: &gt;150 mg/dl

          -  BP &gt;130/85 mmHg

          -  Serum Endotoxin &gt;25 EU/ml

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unstable body mass (±2 kg over prior 3-mo)

          -  Vegetarian

          -  Food allergies or lactose intolerance

          -  User of dietary supplements or probiotics (within past 1-mo)

          -  Pregnancy, lactation, changes in birth control (within 6-mo)

          -  Any gastrointestinal disorders

          -  Chronic diarrhea

          -  Smoker

          -  Excess alcohol (&gt;2 drinks/d)

          -  Excess aerobic exercise (&gt;5 h/wk)

          -  Recent antibiotic or anti-inflammatory agent use

          -  BP &gt;140/90 mmHg
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Bruno, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>William Qurales, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8167296876</phone>
    <email>Qurales.31@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Richard Bruno, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>614.292.5522</phone>
    <email>bruno.27@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Avinash Pokala, BS</last_name>
      <phone>740-417-0157</phone>
      <email>pokala.2@buckeyemail.osu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Bruno</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>metabolic endotoxemia</keyword>
  <keyword>milk fat globule membrane</keyword>
  <keyword>gut health</keyword>
  <keyword>endotoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endotoxemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

