<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04334993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AYA001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04334993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric-type Therapy With Pre-transplant Blinatumomab for HR Patients - Phase II Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Multicenter, Single Arm Trial to Assess the Safety and Efficacy of a Pediatric Approach to for Young Adults With Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia With Blinatumomab Therapy for High-risk Patients Prior to Allogeneic Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Israeli Medical Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Israeli Medical Association</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite recent therapeutic advancements, the outcome of young adults with
      Philadelphia-negative (Ph-neg) acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) and lymphoblastic lymphoma
      (LBL) remains unsatisfactory, especially in those patients with high-risk disease features.
      In young adults pediatric-based chemotherapy approaches improve outcome. Furthermore, there
      is evidence that pre-transplant antibody-based therapy may render patients with positive
      minimal residual disease (MRD+) to an MRD-negative status (MRD-) and that this may be
      associated with improved post-transplant outcome.

      This is prospective study to evaluate the potential benefit of a modified pediatric-based
      approach in young adults with Ph-neg ALL. Safety and efficacy of pre-transplant
      antibody-based consolidation in high-risk patients with Ph-neg ALL will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a national, multicenter, phase II clinical trial to evaluate the potential benefit of
      a modified pediatric-based approach in young adults with Ph-neg ALL. Safety and efficacy of
      pre-transplant antibody-based consolidation in high-risk patients with Ph-neg ALL will be
      assessed.

      Young-adult patients eligible with Ph-neg ALL, LBL and mixed phenotype acute leukemia (MPAL)
      will undergo risk stratification and started on the pediatric Italian Association of
      Pediatric Hematology Oncology-Berlin-Frankfurt-Münster (AIEOP-BFM) 2009 protocol. Patients
      defined as having non-high-risk disease features (non-HR) as defined by MRD and/or
      cytogenetic criteria will complete the non-HR chemotherapy arm per protocol. Patients
      designated as having HR disease features after 2 induction blocks will be treated with CNS
      directed block followed by up to 2 cycles of blinatumomab (for B-cell ALL) followed by
      allogeneic stem cell transplantation. All patients will be centrally assessed for MRD and for
      Ph-like status.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a national, multicenter, phase II clinical trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>NR</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured from the date of entry on study until treatment failure, relapse from CR, or death from any cause, whichever occurs first</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured from the date of entry on study until until death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early death during induction</measure>
    <time_frame>60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Death during the first 60 days from entering study from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD status</measure>
    <time_frame>MRD will be assess by PCR after induction I (day 33), after induction II (week 12), after blinatumomab therapy (prior to HSCT) and at days 30 and 100 post alloHSCT.</time_frame>
    <description>MRD status pre- and post-antibody-based therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Philadelphia-Negative ALL</condition>
  <condition>High-Risk Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Blinatumomab pre-transplant to high risk Ph-negative ALL pts.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients designated high risk based on protocol will receive 2 cycles of therapy followed by allogeneic transplantation. Patients ≥45 kg (fixed dose): Cycles 1 and 2: 28 mcg daily administered as a continuous infusion on days 1 to 28 of a 6-week treatment cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blinatumomab</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with high risk disease features after 2 induction blocks as defined per protocol will be treated with CNS directed block followed by up to 2 cycles of blinatumomab (for B-cell ALL) followed by allogeneic stem cell transplantation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Blinatumomab pre-transplant to high risk Ph-negative ALL pts.</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AIEOP-BFM 2009 protocol - multiagent chemothertapy protocol backbone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years and &lt;30 years of age at the time of signing the informed consent
             document.

          2. Have a documented diagnosis of Ph-neg ALL, LBL or MPAL according to the WHO 2016
             classification (appendix I).

          3. Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) may participate, providing they meet the
             following conditions:

             Agree to use at least two effective contraceptive methods (oral, injectable, or
             implantable hormonal contraceptive; tubal ligation; intra-uterine device; barrier
             contraceptive with spermicide; or vasectomized partner) throughout the study, and for
             3 months following EOT; and have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             (investigator's discretion; sensitivity at least 25 mIU/mL) at screening; and have a
             negative serum or urine pregnancy test (investigator's discretion) within 72 hours
             prior to starting study therapy in the treatment phase (note that the screening serum
             pregnancy test can be used as the test prior to starting study therapy in treatment
             phase if it is performed within the 72-hour timeframe).

          4. Male subjects with a female partner of childbearing potential must agree to the use of
             at least two physician-approved contraceptive methods throughout the course of the
             study and should avoid fathering a child during the course of the study and for 3
             months following the last dose of study drug.

          5. Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document prior to any study
             related assessments/procedures being conducted.

          6. Able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt;18 or over 30 years at the time of signing the informed consent document.

          2. Ph-positive disease.

          3. Known Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV).

          4. Known or suspected hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs.

          5. Pregnant or lactating females.

          6. Any significant medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from participating in the study.

          7. Any condition including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
             subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study.

          8. Participation to an investigational drug trial in the last month before randomization.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ofir Wolach, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+972-3-9378116</phone>
    <email>ofirw@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rambam Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yishai Ofran, MD</last_name>
      <email>y_ofran@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shaarei Tzedek Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacob Rowe, MD</last_name>
      <email>rowe@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rabin Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Petah Tikva</city>
        <zip>49100</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ofir Wolach, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+972-3-937-8116</phone>
      <email>ofirw@clalit.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Miri Pinhasov, MA</last_name>
      <phone>+972-3-9378078</phone>
      <email>miripi@clalit.org.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tel Aviv Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yakir Moshe, MD PhD</last_name>
      <email>yakirm@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Philadelphia-Negative ALL</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Blinatumomab</keyword>
  <keyword>Allogeneic transplantation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Blinatumomab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data will be coded and uploaded to an electronic CRF (red-cap) to manage abnd analyze data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

