<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04331782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INA104.02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04331782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integration of Mental Health in HIV Clinic to Increase the Success of ARV Treatment in PLWHA in Hospitals</brief_title>
  <official_title>Integration of Mental Health in HIV Clinic to Increase the Success of Antiretroviral Treatment: Screening for Depression Disorders in People With HIV in Hospitals</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ina-Respond</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Health Research and Development, Ministry of Health Republic of Indonesia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ina-Respond</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Integration of mental health in HIV clinics is needed in order to accelerate fast track
      90-90-90 for controlling HIV. Symptoms of depression are sometimes difficult to recognize. In
      people living with HIV (PLWHA), depression that fails to be recognized and uncontrolled
      increases the risk of unsuccessful antiretroviral treatment and mortality.

      The main purpose of this study is to estimate the proportion of depressive disorders in
      people living with HIV. The study included adult HIV patients aged ≥18 years, both men and
      women, who had received ARV treatment for at least six months, with no history of being
      diagnosed with depression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study was a cross-sectional, non-intervention and multicenter in adults with HIV-AIDS
      (PLWHA) who were treated at a hospital who had received ARV treatment for at least six
      months, without a history of being diagnosed with depression.

      Patients from HIV outpatient clinics in each research hospital were briefed on the study and
      offered to participate. Furthermore, based on the assessment of inclusion and exclusion
      criteria, PLWHA who meet the requirements were recruited and data were collected.

      Sociodemographic data, HIV risk factors, risk behaviors, clinical characteristics such as
      duration of HIV, family history of mental illness, AIDS-related illnesses, other serious
      non-AIDS-related illnesses, treatment (antiretroviral (ARV) and non-ARV) and history ARV
      treatment response (HIV and CD4 viral load) were collected from each participant. In
      addition, a rapid screening for depressive disorders was carried out using the Patient Health
      Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) which was translated and validated in Indonesian. The PHQ-9
      questionnaire was filled in by the patient with the assistance of health personnel. The total
      PHQ-9 questionnaire score were added up and the severity of depression associated with the
      score was reported to the patient's physician for further management.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of depressive disorders in PLWHA in hospitals.</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: 3 months] [No Safety Issue]</time_frame>
    <description>Number in percentage for Proportion of depressive disorders in PLWHA in hospitals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distribution of the severity of depressive disorders in PLWHA</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: 3 months] [No Safety Issue]</time_frame>
    <description>Distribution of the severity of depressive disorders in PLWHA catagorized into minimal, mild, moderate, moderate-severe and severe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The correlation of depression with various factors.</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: 3 months] [No Safety Issue]</time_frame>
    <description>The correlation of depression with various factors: the Risk behavior in the past 30 days, socio-demographic, clinical characteristic and ARV response history.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study included adult HIV patients aged ≥18 years, both men and women, who had received
        ARV treatment for at least six months, with no history of being diagnosed with depression
        from HIV outpatient clinics in research hospital in Indonesia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults aged ≥18 years.

          2. HIV positive based on diagnosis standards of care in research hospitals.

          3. Have received ARV treatment for at least six months.

          4. Without a history of being diagnosed with a depressive disorder beforehand.

          5. Has been given an explanation before the research and give approval after the
             explanation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Being pregnant / nursing.

          2. Currently undergoing a period of detention.

          3. Being seriously ill (according to the doctor's justification at the hospital).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Muhammad Karyana, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Health Research and Development, Ministry of Health Republic of Indonesia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 600 : Adam Malik Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medan</city>
        <state>North Sumatra</state>
        <zip>20136</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 650: Budi Kemuliaan Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Batam</city>
        <state>Riau Islands</state>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 630: M. Ansari Saleh Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Banjarmasin</city>
        <state>South Kalimantan</state>
        <zip>70125</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 640: St. Carolus Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <zip>10440</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

