<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04338529</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F076/AD1704/S606/18-2-2020</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2550/14-2-20</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04338529</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alendronate in an Weekly Effervescent Tablet Formulation Following Denosumab Discontinuation</brief_title>
  <acronym>BAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Alendronate in an Weekly Effervescent Tablet Formulation for Preservation of Bone Mass After Denosumab Discontinuation in Postmenopausal Women With Low Bone Mass. An Observational Study (Binosto After Denosumab - The BAD Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>251 Hellenic Air Force &amp; VA General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laikο General Hospital, Athens</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>424 General Military Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>251 Hellenic Air Force &amp; VA General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Discontinuation of denosumab results in a rebound response of bone turnover markers, which
      rise above baseline at 3 months and remain elevated until reaching again baseline levels
      approximately 30 months after the last dose. Bone mineral density (BMD) gains are also lost
      and BMD values reach original baseline values after 1-2 years off-treatment.For the above
      reasons, current literature recommends that patients who discontinue denosumab should
      continue to receive either intravenous (iv) or oral (peros) bisphosphonate therapy for some
      time. The study aims to investigate changes in the BMD of the lumbar spine 12 months after
      transitioning from denosumab to oral alendronate 70 mg in a weekly effervescent tablet
      formulation
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Denosumab, a monoclonal antibody against the receptor activator of nuclear factor κ-Β ligand
      (RANKL), is a potent antiresorptive agent commonly prescribed in patients with postmenopausal
      osteoporosis. Discontinuation of denosumab results in a rebound response of bone turnover
      markers, which rise above baseline at 3 months and remain elevated until reaching again
      baseline levels approximately 30 months after the last dose. Bone mineral density (BMD) gains
      are also lost and BMD values reach original baseline values after 1-2 years off-treatment, in
      contrast to bisphosphonates, which remain within the skeleton acting for several months or
      even years after discontinuation while preserving most of the BMD gains achieved despite the
      cessation of treatment.

      For the above reasons, current literature recommends that patients who discontinue denosumab
      should continue to receive either intravenous (iv) or oral (peros) bisphosphonate therapy for
      some time. Due to lack of specifically designed studies, the period of treatment with
      bisphosphonates after denosumab discontinuation has been arbitrarily proposed to be 1 to 2
      years. Preservation of BMD gains after denosumab discontinuation has so far been
      demonstrated: (a) with one year of alendronate treatment, in a study designed to investigate
      patients' compliance to treatment, and b) with a single dose of zolendronate 5mg iv in a
      recent study specifically designed to address this question in which BMD levels remained
      stable for the next two years.

      Preventing bone loss, and the reported high risk of multiple vertebral fractures after
      discontinuation of denosumab treatment, is a clinical issue of critical importance raising
      serious concerns to the international scientific community and needs to be addressed.
      Clinical studies specifically designed to investigate both the efficacy of various
      bisphosphonates and the optimal duration of their administration in order to avoid the
      reported adverse effects of denosumab discontinuation are currently lacking.

      This study aims to investigate changes in the BMD of the lumbar spine (LS) and femoral neck
      (FN) 12 months after transitioning from denosumab to oral alendronate 70 mg in a weekly
      effervescent tablet formulation. Alendronate will be given either for 6 or 12 months
      following Denosumab discontinuation
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone Mineral Density LS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the BMD of the lumbar spine 12 months after transitioning from denosumab to oral alendronate 70 mg in a weekly effervescent tablet formulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone Mineral Density FN</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the BMD of the femoral neck (FN) of the non-dominant hip 12 months after transitioning from denosumab to oral alendronate 70 mg in a weekly effervescent tablet formulation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>P1NP and CTX levels in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in bone turnover markers (BTM) 12 months after transitioning from denosumab to oral alendronate 70mg in a weekly effervescent tablet formulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Bone Mineral Density LS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in the BMD of the LS after transitioning from denosumab to 12 months versus 6 months of treatment with oral alendronate 70 mg in a weekly effervescent tablet formulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Bone Mineral Density FN</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in the BMD of the FN of the non-dominant hip after transitioning from denosumab to 12 months versus 6 months of treatment with oral alendronate 70mg in a weekly effervescent tablet formulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of P1NP and CTX levels in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in the BTM after 12 months versus 6 months treatment with oral alendronate 70mg in a weekly effervescent tablet formulation in patients previously treated with denosumab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Postmenopausal Osteoporosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group Alendronate 6m</arm_group_label>
    <description>Postmenopausal Caucasian women who were treated with denosumab and became osteopenic (BMD T-score of &gt; -2.5 at the LS and the non-dominant FN) and were assigned from their treating physician to receive treatment with alendronate in an effervescent tablet formulation for 6 months and then followed for another 6 months without medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group Alendronate 12m</arm_group_label>
    <description>Postmenopausal Caucasian women who were treated with denosumab and became osteopenic (BMD T-score of &gt; -2.5 at the LS and the non-dominant FN) and were assigned from their treating physician to receive treatment with alendronate in an effervescent tablet formulation for 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Binosto 70Mg Effervescent Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>As discussed in group descriptions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group Alendronate 12m</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group Alendronate 6m</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>calcium carbonate 1000 mg/d and cholecalciferol 800 IU/d</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Morning (8-9 am) fasting blood samples will be obtained at baseline and at 3, 6, 9 and 12
      months. Blood samples will be centrifuged immediately and serum will be separated and stored
      at -80 ºC; all study parameters will be measured in one batch at the end of the study.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will include postmenopausal Caucasian women who were treated with denosumab and
        became osteopenic (BMD T-score of &gt; -2.5 at the LS and the non-dominant FN) and were
        assigned from their treating physician to receive treatment with alendronate in an
        effervescent tablet formulation for either 6 months (Group 6, n=50) and then followed for
        another 6 months without medication, or 12 months of continuous treatment with alendronate
        (Group 12, n=50). As this is an observational study, patients could be either referred from
        their treating physicians or could be actually followed by the investigators themselves in
        case the investigator is the treating physician
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        i) osteopenic postmenopausal Caucasian women following Dmab treatment ii) assignment to
        treatment with alendronate in an effervescent tablet formulation following Dmab
        discontinuation

        Exclusion Criteria:

        i) secondary osteoporosis; ii) diseases that could affect bone metabolism iii) medications
        that could affect bone metabolism iv) chronic kidney disease (stage &gt;3b) and/or liver
        failure v) neoplastic disease vi) hypersensitivity to alendronate or to any of the
        excipients vii) abnormalities of the esophagus and other factors which delay esophageal
        emptying such as stricture or achalasia viii) inability to stand or sit upright for at
        least 30 minutes ix) hypocalcaemia x) confirmed esophagitis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Yavropoulou, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>LAIKO General Hospital, Athens, Greece</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Polyzois Makras, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>251 Hellenic Airforce Gen. Hospital, Athens, Greece</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Athanasios D Anastasilakis, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>424 Gen. Military Hospital Thessaloniki, Greece</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Polyzois Makras, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+306944549654</phone>
    <email>pmakras@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maria Yavropoulou, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+306936159517</phone>
    <email>maria.yavropoulou.my@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>251 Hellenic Air Force &amp; VA General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Attiki</state>
        <zip>11525</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Polyzois Makras, MD, Phd</last_name>
      <phone>+30 210 7463606</phone>
      <email>pmakras@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maria Yavropoulou, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+306936159517</phone>
      <email>maria.yavropoulou.my@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cummings SR, San Martin J, McClung MR, Siris ES, Eastell R, Reid IR, Delmas P, Zoog HB, Austin M, Wang A, Kutilek S, Adami S, Zanchetta J, Libanati C, Siddhanti S, Christiansen C; FREEDOM Trial. Denosumab for prevention of fractures in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis. N Engl J Med. 2009 Aug 20;361(8):756-65. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0809493. Epub 2009 Aug 11. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2009 Nov 5;361(19):1914.</citation>
    <PMID>19671655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller PD, Bolognese MA, Lewiecki EM, McClung MR, Ding B, Austin M, Liu Y, San Martin J; Amg Bone Loss Study Group. Effect of denosumab on bone density and turnover in postmenopausal women with low bone mass after long-term continued, discontinued, and restarting of therapy: a randomized blinded phase 2 clinical trial. Bone. 2008 Aug;43(2):222-9. doi: 10.1016/j.bone.2008.04.007. Epub 2008 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18539106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bone HG, Bolognese MA, Yuen CK, Kendler DL, Miller PD, Yang YC, Grazette L, San Martin J, Gallagher JC. Effects of denosumab treatment and discontinuation on bone mineral density and bone turnover markers in postmenopausal women with low bone mass. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Apr;96(4):972-80. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-1502. Epub 2011 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21289258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McClung MR, Wagman RB, Miller PD, Wang A, Lewiecki EM. Observations following discontinuation of long-term denosumab therapy. Osteoporos Int. 2017 May;28(5):1723-1732. doi: 10.1007/s00198-017-3919-1. Epub 2017 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28144701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anastasilakis AD, Polyzos SA, Makras P, Aubry-Rozier B, Kaouri S, Lamy O. Clinical Features of 24 Patients With Rebound-Associated Vertebral Fractures After Denosumab Discontinuation: Systematic Review and Additional Cases. J Bone Miner Res. 2017 Jun;32(6):1291-1296. doi: 10.1002/jbmr.3110. Epub 2017 Mar 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28240371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cummings SR, Ferrari S, Eastell R, Gilchrist N, Jensen JB, McClung M, Roux C, Törring O, Valter I, Wang AT, Brown JP. Vertebral Fractures After Discontinuation of Denosumab: A Post Hoc Analysis of the Randomized Placebo-Controlled FREEDOM Trial and Its Extension. J Bone Miner Res. 2018 Feb;33(2):190-198. doi: 10.1002/jbmr.3337. Epub 2017 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>29105841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Black DM, Bauer DC, Schwartz AV, Cummings SR, Rosen CJ. Continuing bisphosphonate treatment for osteoporosis--for whom and for how long? N Engl J Med. 2012 May 31;366(22):2051-3. doi: 10.1056/NEJMp1202623. Epub 2012 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22571169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anastasilakis AD, Polyzos SA, Makras P. THERAPY OF ENDOCRINE DISEASE: Denosumab vs bisphosphonates for the treatment of postmenopausal osteoporosis. Eur J Endocrinol. 2018 Jul;179(1):R31-R45. doi: 10.1530/EJE-18-0056. Epub 2018 Apr 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29691303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsourdi E, Langdahl B, Cohen-Solal M, Aubry-Rozier B, Eriksen EF, Guañabens N, Obermayer-Pietsch B, Ralston SH, Eastell R, Zillikens MC. Discontinuation of Denosumab therapy for osteoporosis: A systematic review and position statement by ECTS. Bone. 2017 Dec;105:11-17. doi: 10.1016/j.bone.2017.08.003. Epub 2017 Aug 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28789921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freemantle N, Satram-Hoang S, Tang ET, Kaur P, Macarios D, Siddhanti S, Borenstein J, Kendler DL; DAPS Investigators. Final results of the DAPS (Denosumab Adherence Preference Satisfaction) study: a 24-month, randomized, crossover comparison with alendronate in postmenopausal women. Osteoporos Int. 2012 Jan;23(1):317-26. doi: 10.1007/s00198-011-1780-1. Epub 2011 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21927922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anastasilakis AD, Papapoulos SE, Polyzos SA, Appelman-Dijkstra NM, Makras P. Zoledronate for the Prevention of Bone Loss in Women Discontinuing Denosumab Treatment. A Prospective 2-Year Clinical Trial. J Bone Miner Res. 2019 Dec;34(12):2220-2228. doi: 10.1002/jbmr.3853. Epub 2019 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>31433518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Denosumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Alendronate</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>discontinuation of treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis, Postmenopausal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium Carbonate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

