<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04334278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>53457</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04334278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of a Mind Body Program for Obese Knee Osteoarthritis Patients With Comorbid Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>DOORSTEP</acronym>
  <official_title>Development of a Mind Body Program for Obese Knee Osteoarthritis Patients With Comorbid Depression: Does a minD bOdy prOgram Reduces oSTEoarthritis Pain?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Kentucky</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Knee osteoarthritis (OA) is the most common joint disorder in the U.S. and a leading cause of
      disability. Depression and obesity are highly comorbid among knee osteoarthritis patients,
      and the combination of obesity and depression is associated with decreased physical activity,
      higher pain and disability, and more rapid cartilage degradation. Depression, obesity and
      osteoarthritis exacerbate one another and share a common pathophysiology involving systemic
      inflammation and pro-inflammatory cytokines, reflecting a complex mind-body interaction.
      Current treatments for knee osteoarthritis offer little to no benefit over placebo, and do
      not emphasize mind-body practices or physical activity to target the underlying
      pathophysiology. Mind-body interventions to lessen depressive symptoms and increase physical
      activity offer the ability to target biological, mechanical and psychological mechanisms of
      osteoarthritis progression in this high-risk subset. The long-term goals are to evaluate the
      mechanisms by which the Relaxation Response Resiliency Program (3RP) delivered via
      telehealth, and adapted for patients with depression, obesity and knee OA (3RP-OA) promotes
      increases in physical activity and improved subjective and objective aspects of knee health.
      The overarching hypothesis is that the synergistic interaction between mindfulness, adaptive
      thinking, positive psychology and healthy living skills of the 3RP-OA will reduce
      pro-inflammatory cytokine expression while also promoting optimal mechanical loading of the
      cartilage thereby slowing the progression of symptomatic knee osteoarthritis. This study aims
      to adapt the 3RP for the needs of knee osteoarthritis patients with depression and obesity
      with a focus of increasing physical activity, and iteratively establish the feasibility,
      credibility and acceptability of the programs and research procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The conceptual model of adaptation of the general 3RP to obese osteoarthritis patients with
      depression that specifically target improved function through combining mind body skills with
      physical activity, and recommendations of multimodal programs to improve outcomes in chronic
      pain clinical trials. Adaptations of the multimodal general 3RP will be done consistent with
      theoretical models of the fear-avoidance model of pain, cognitive model of pain and
      depression, acceptance and commitment therapy, mindfulness, and positive psychology. The goal
      is to help patients engage in activities that are meaningful and mapped to each individual's
      level of functioning and life circumstance through the use of quota-based pacing through
      adaptation of skills to directly address improved mood, healthy lifestyle (sleep, diet),
      correction of knee osteoarthritis misconceptions, and use of relaxation response elicitation
      and positive psychology skills to promote awareness and calm during activities, even when
      these are painful.

      The guiding hypothesis is that the synergistic interaction between mindfulness, adaptive
      thinking, positive psychology, physical activity and healthy living skills of the 3RP-OA
      reduces pro-inflammatory cytokine expression while also promoting optimal mechanical loading
      of the cartilage thus slowing the progression of symptomatic knee OA. In this project the 3RP
      will be iteratively adapted for the needs of knee osteoarthritis patients with depression and
      obesity with a focus on gradual increases in physical activity measured with accelerometers
      and establish feasibility markers for the program and procedures. A pilot randomized
      controlled trial of the 3RP-OA versus a time- and attention-matched health enhancement
      control will be performed to assess the feasibility of recruitment procedures, feasibility
      and acceptability of the 3RP-OA and control, and data collection procedures by group.

      A pilot randomized controlled trial (N=60 participants) of the 3RP-OA with a time and
      attention matched health enhancement control will be performed. The end goal of the pilot RCT
      is not to assess the efficacy of the 3RP-OA but rather to assess the feasibility of
      recruitment procedures (screening, eligibility, enrollment rates), feasibility and
      acceptability of the 3RP-OA and control intervention (adherence, retention, fidelity,
      satisfaction, group telehealth delivery, and data collection procedures by group (adherence,
      satisfaction, blood and urine biomarker data).

      A single blind pilot feasibility randomized controlled trial with a time, dose and attention
      matched health enhancement control will be conducted (N=60; approximately 4 3RP-OA groups and
      4 control, 7-8 per group). Participants will be randomized in a 1:1 design using a
      randomization scheme developed by the statistician. Research procedures will be identical for
      patients in 3RP-OA and control. The study will yield information on how participants might
      engage differently with the intervention and control, definitive information on feasibility
      and acceptability and signal of improvement in the intervention before investment of
      resources in the full randomized controlled trial.

      The 3RP-OA refined based on exit interviews and surveys. The control group will have the same
      format as the 3RP-OA, and the control group follows the format of the Health Enhancement
      Program. A pain specific adaptation of this program for chronic pain exists. This program
      will be adapted for the specific needs of patients with knee osteoarthritis. To control for
      in between session practice, participants will receive an mp3 recording and informational
      handout to complete after each session.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients that attend a minimum of 6 of 8 weekly sessions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accelerometer Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days participants wore the Accelerometers at least 8 hours per day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Missing Specimens</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of missing blood or urine specimens</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily Practice Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients that completed daily practice at least 4 days per week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3RP-OA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Relaxation Response Resiliency Program (3RP) is an 8-week group mind body program with efficacy in improving depression, physical function and aiding in weight loss, that has been adapted for the unique needs of patients with knee osteoarthritis, depression and obesity (3RP-OA). The 3RP-OA will be delivered by secure telehealth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Enhancement Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Health Enhancement Program is a chronic pain-specific program adapted for the specific needs of patients with knee osteoarthritis. It is an 8-week group mind body program that will be delivered via secure telehealth. To control for in between session practice, participants will receive an mp3 recording and informational handout to complete after each session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3RP-OA</intervention_name>
    <description>The Relaxation Response Resiliency Program (3RP) is an 8-week group mind body program with efficacy in improving depression, physical function and aiding in weight loss, that has been adapted for the unique needs of patients with knee osteoarthritis, depression and obesity (3RP-OA). The 3RP-OA will be delivered by secure telehealth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3RP-OA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Enhancement Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The Health Enhancement Program is a chronic pain-specific program adapted for the specific needs of patients with knee osteoarthritis. It is an 8-week group mind body program that will be delivered via secure telehealth. To control for in between session practice, participants will receive an mp3 recording and informational handout to complete after each session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health Enhancement Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Obese patients (BMI &gt; 30 kg/m2)

          -  Idiopathic knee OA per the American College of Rheumatology classification with mild
             to moderate radiographic changes (Kellgren/Lawrence grade 2 or 3)

          -  Current elevated depressive symptoms (PHQ-9 &gt; 10)

          -  Age 45 or older

          -  Free of concurrent psychotropics for &lt; 2 weeks prior to initiation of treatment or on
             stable doses for &gt; 6 weeks

          -  Access to a computer/smart phone with internet access

          -  Willingness to comply with the study protocol and assessments

          -  Cleared by a medical doctor to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any disorder requiring the use of systemic corticosteroids

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis

          -  History of cancer within 5 years of screening

          -  Unable to walk/wheelchair-bound

          -  Prior surgical fixation of a femur or tibia fracture

          -  Taking high doses of opioid pain medication (50 milligrams of morphine equivalent)

          -  Diagnosis of a medical illness expected to worsen in the next 6 months (e.g.,
             malignancy)

          -  Active suicidal ideation or past-year psychiatric hospitalization

          -  Non-English speaking

          -  Lifetime history of schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, or other psychotic disorder

          -  Current substance abuse or dependence

          -  Substance use disorder within the past 6 months

          -  Practice of yoga/meditation, or other mind body techniques that elicit the relaxation
             response, once per week for 45 min or more within the last 3 months

          -  Engagement in regular moderate or vigorous physical exercise for &gt;30 min daily
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cale Jacobs, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cale Jacobs, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(859) 218-0839</phone>
    <email>cale.jacobs@uky.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UK Healthcare at Turfland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40504</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UK HealthCare Joint Reconstruction and Replacement</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40508</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cale Jacobs, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>859-218-0839</phone>
      <email>cale.jacobs@uky.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cale Jacobs, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cale Jacobs, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

