<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04333095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>019-296</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04333095</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sternal Block With Liposomal Bupivacaine vs. Saline Prior to Incision in Cardiac Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Regional Blockade of the Sternum With Liposomal Bupivacaine Prior to Incision Decreases Opioid Use in Patients Undergoing Cardiac Surgery (Sternal Block)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects (good and bad) that the study medicine
      called &quot;liposomal bupivacaine&quot; has on subjects that are undergoing a sternotomy. Liposomal
      bupivacaine solution, is a drug that the doctor will inject before they make the cut through
      patient's breastbone (sternotomy). Normally pain medicine like this is given right before the
      surgeon closes up the patient's breastbone, at the end of the surgery. For this study, they
      want to see if giving the medicine before they make the cut into the patient's breastbone
      helps their pain. They also want to find out if patients feel less pain after surgery with
      the study drug than they do with saline and possibly decrease the need for pain medicine.
      Subjects will be in the study for about 72 hours or until they are discharged from the
      hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Prolonged and excessive narcotic usage in the postoperative setting has been linked to
      multiple complications. Use of complimentary pain management techniques such as regional
      analgesia can reduce postoperative pain and narcotic usage. This can enhance patient recovery
      and improve quality of life in the immediate postoperative period. Previous research
      investigating the benefits of local analgesia during cardiac surgery have been limited by the
      sparse amount of single-center randomized controlled trials, particularly evaluating the use
      of para-sternal injections.

      Of the available studies, the use of local analgesia injections compared to controls has led
      to improved pain scores and overall decreased perioperative opioid usage. Studies have shown
      this efficacy using 0.2% ropivacaine, 0.75% ropivacaine, and 0.53% liposomal bupivacaine all
      compared to control groups receiving normal saline injections in the para-sternal area. These
      studies all used injections just prior to sternal closure and no significant evidence is
      available for the use of ultrasound-guided regional block of the sternum prior to surgical
      incision. Injection of analgesia prior to surgical incision has been shown to decrease
      postoperative pain compared to injection after surgical closure.

      We hypothesize that injection of 1.3% liposomal bupivacaine and 0.5% bupivacaine (20mL dose)
      as a sternal block prior to surgical incision will lead to decreased pain and opioid usage in
      the intraoperative and postoperative setting for patients undergoing upper mini- and median
      sternotomy compared to controls.

      Methods:

      This is an investigator-initiated prospective randomized study with an 18-month patient
      accrual period and patient follow-up period dependent on postoperative length of stay
      following surgery.

      Regional Block: Liposomal Bupivacaine (1.3%) solution (20 mL dose) is proposed for use during
      this study. This solution has demonstrated increased efficacy in prolonged analgesia
      following injection. This solution will be injected as an ultrasound-guided subpectoral
      interfacial plane block.

      Normal Saline: Normal saline (0.9%) will be used as the control solution for patients not
      receiving the liposomal bupivacaine solution. Injection procedure of this solution will be
      identical to that of the liposomal bupivacaine solution.

      Procedures: Coronary artery bypass grafting and aortic valve replacement will be considered
      for inclusion in this study. There will be no deviation from routine surgical procedures
      following injection of para-sternal solution prior to surgical incision.

      Data elements:

      Patient Characteristics:

        1. Age

        2. Gender

        3. BMI

        4. Tobacco use

        5. Chronic lung disease

        6. Diabetes

        7. Hypertension (HTN)

        8. Hyperlipidemia (HLD)

        9. Ethnicity (Hispanic &amp; not Hispanic)

       10. Race (Caucasian, African Americans, Asians and others)

       11. Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)

       12. Cerebrovascular accident (CVA)

       13. Chronic home non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) use (excluding acetylsalicylic
           acid (ASA))

      Intraoperative Variables:

        1. Type of procedure being performed

        2. Prior procedures performed

      Postoperative Variables:

      Time to extubation, time to ambulation, time to oral diet, return of bowel function,
      postoperative atrial fibrillation incidence, post op nausea incidence, and intensive care
      unit (ICU) length of stay (LOS) and overall LOS. Maximum incentive spirometer maximum volume
      at 24, 48 and 72 hours, Confusion assessment method (CAM) at 24, 48 and 72 hours, post op
      opioid usage up to 72 hours post op. If additional days of post-op opioid usage is documented
      in the existing medical record, this may be used also.

      Pain scores (Scale 0-10) at 1, 2, 4, 8, 12,24,36,48, 60, and 72 hours after ICU arrival for
      extubated patients and Clinical Care Pain Observation Tool (CPOT)scores (Scale 0-8) for
      intubated patients

      Adverse Events: Allergic reaction, pneumothorax, pericardial tamponade, vascular injury,
      hematoma, intravascular injection, wound infection, paresthesia, persistent numbness

      Protocol Deviations: If certain data elements are not in the existing medical record and were
      not collected, this is not a protocol deviation. Nevertheless, all effort will be made to
      collect these data points.

      Risks and Benefits

      Risks: The risks are the same as the Standard of Care surgery performed outside this study.
      This is discussed in the ICF. A confidentiality breach is a risk associated with research.
      However, all data collection protocols follow HIPAA guidance.

      Benefits: If participants receive the drug, they could experience less pain than those that
      don't receive the drug. However, not all participants are likely to benefit from the proposed
      research. The investigators will benefit from the knowledge gained, as it will provide
      deepened insight on the main challenges, advantages and disadvantages of the procedure.

      Data Analytic Methods

      The mean, standard deviation, median, and interquartile ranges of narcotic usage (in morphine
      equivalent units) will be reported for each group. The difference of narcotic usage between
      the two groups will be reported as a single value. Additional variables analyzed in this
      study include the following:

      Patient Characteristics:

        1. Age

        2. Gender

        3. BMI

        4. Tobacco use

        5. Chronic pain medication usage

        6. Diabetes

        7. HTN

        8. HLD

        9. Race &amp; Ethnicity

       10. CKD

       11. CVA

      Intraoperative Variables:

        1. Type of procedure being performed

        2. Prior procedures performed

      Postoperative Variables:

        1. Time to extubation

        2. Time to ambulation

        3. Time to oral diet

        4. Postoperative nausea

        5. ICU LOS

        6. Total LOS

        7. Return of bowel function

        8. Postoperative atrial fibrillation

        9. Maximum spirometry at 24, 48, 72 hours post op

       10. CAM at 24, 48, 72 hours post op

       11. Pain Scores (Scale 0-10) at 1, 2, 4, 8, 12,24,36,48, 60, and 72 hours after ICU arrival
           for extubated patients and CPOT scores (Scale 0-8) for intubated patients

       12. Post op opioid usage up to 72 hours post op

      Standard descriptive statistics will be used throughout (mean, range, standard deviation, and
      median, IQR), with comparative statistics for normally and non-normally distributed data with
      p&lt;0.05 considered as significant. For categorical variables, 2 Sample t-test or chi-squared
      test will be used to determine statistical significance. For continuous variables, logistic
      regression will be used to determine the value of significance to variables with
      postoperative outcomes. Depending on the enrollment rate, the stratification of data based on
      the type of sternotomy (full or mini) could be performed and analyzed respectively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The surgeon, coordinator and anesthesiologist on the case are blinded to the block drug. A 2nd (unblinded) anesthesiologist performs the block on the patient.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative opioid measured in Milligram Morphine Equivalent (MME)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 hours post-op</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of opioid medications used will be recorded during the routine postoperative course.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Pain Scores measured with standard pain scores (0-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 hours post-op</time_frame>
    <description>Range 0 (No pain) to 10 (Worst pain)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative opioid usage measured in Milligram Morphine Equivalent (MME)</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Block</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal Bupivacaine Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Liposomal Bupivacaine (1.3%) solution (20 mL dose). This solution has demonstrated increased efficacy in prolonged analgesia following injection. This solution will be injected as an ultrasound-guided subpectoral interfacial plane block.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Normal saline (0.9%) will be used as the control solution for patients not receiving the liposomal bupivacaine solution. Injection procedure of this solution will be identical to that of the liposomal bupivacaine solution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liposomal bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Sternal Block during Coronary Artery Bypass Graft Surgery and/or surgical aortic valve replacement through mini- or full sternotomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Liposomal Bupivacaine Block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Saline Flush, 0.9% Injectable Solution_#1</intervention_name>
    <description>Sternal Block during Coronary Artery Bypass Graft Surgery and/or surgical aortic valve replacement through mini- or full sternotomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline Block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age greater than 18 years

          2. Undergoing Coronary Artery Bypass Graft Surgery and/or surgical aortic valve
             replacement through mini- or full sternotomy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinical instability

          2. Allergic to liposomal bupivacaine solution or any of its ingredients

          3. Maximum-allowed dosage of local analgesia will be exceeded by the injection amount of
             liposomal bupivacaine used in this study (&lt;50 kg).

          4. BMI &gt;45

          5. Pregnant or nursing

          6. Chronic home opioid usage

          7. Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 30%

          8. Low cardiac output requiring mechanical or inotropic support

          9. End-stage renal disease

         10. Cirrhosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Scott &amp; White Heart Hospital - Plano</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plano</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah M Hale, BA</last_name>
      <phone>469-814-4720</phone>
      <email>sarah.hale@bswhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katherine B Harrington, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bignami E, Castella A, Pota V, Saglietti F, Scognamiglio A, Trumello C, Pace MC, Allegri M. Perioperative pain management in cardiac surgery: a systematic review. Minerva Anestesiol. 2018 Apr;84(4):488-503. doi: 10.23736/S0375-9393.17.12142-5. Epub 2017 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29027773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dowling R, Thielmeier K, Ghaly A, Barber D, Boice T, Dine A. Improved pain control after cardiac surgery: results of a randomized, double-blind, clinical trial. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2003 Nov;126(5):1271-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14665996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barr AM, Tutungi E, Almeida AA. Parasternal intercostal block with ropivacaine for pain management after cardiac surgery: a double-blind, randomized, controlled trial. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2007 Aug;21(4):547-53. Epub 2006 Dec 22.</citation>
    <PMID>17678782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee CY, Robinson DA, Johnson CA Jr, Zhang Y, Wong J, Joshi DJ, Wu TT, Knight PA. A Randomized Controlled Trial of Liposomal Bupivacaine Parasternal Intercostal Block for Sternotomy. Ann Thorac Surg. 2019 Jan;107(1):128-134. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2018.06.081. Epub 2018 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30170012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Labrum JT 4th, Ilyas AM. Preemptive Analgesia in Thumb Basal Joint Arthroplasty: Immediate Postoperative Pain with Preincision versus Postincision Local Anesthesia. J Hand Microsurg. 2017 Aug;9(2):80-83. doi: 10.1055/s-0037-1603734. Epub 2017 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>28867907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>At this point, we do not plan to shared IPD but will share cumulative results in an abstract and manuscript.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 12, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/95/NCT04333095/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 5, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/95/NCT04333095/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

