<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04336436</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-1378</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04336436</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Combined Mindfulness-Based Interventions and Nutritional Counseling on Physician Burnout</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Combined Mindfulness-Based Interventions and Nutritional Counseling on Physician Burnout: A Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Betul Hatipoglu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Cleveland Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to tackle the issue of physician burnout via a wide-lens approach,
      integrating both mindfulness-based training and nutritional counseling in the management of
      professional burnout. The investigators will evaluate the effects of mindfulness training and
      nutritional counseling interventions through assessment of changes in physiological and
      biochemical parameters known to be adversely affected in burnout, in addition to the
      standardized Professional Fulfillment inventory scores at 3-6 months post-intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a preponderance of data to support the detrimental effects of burnout on physicians'
      health and wellbeing. Physician burnout is defined as severe emotional exhaustion,
      depersonalization towards others and reduced sense of personal achievement. Burnout is often
      accompanied by feelings of moral distress, loss of interest and energy, and detachment from
      patients, colleagues and personal relatives. With the recent rapid expansion in global
      healthcare systems in response to societal changes, rates of physician burnout have been on
      the rise. It is estimated that 54% of physicians in the United States suffer from
      professional burnout, a 2-fold higher prevalence than that estimated for the general working
      population of 28%.

      Burnout has serious negative implications on the physical health and wellbeing of
      individuals. In recent studies, burnout was associated with higher incidence of coronary
      heart disease and hospitalization from cardiovascular causes. Additionally, burnout was found
      to be an independent risk factor for type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypercholesterolemia (total
      cholesterol ≥220 mg/dl). Higher incidence of musculoskeletal pain and pain-related disability
      were also reported amongst subjects with high burnout. Excessive fatigue, insomnia,
      headaches, gastrointestinal and respiratory issues were all positively correlated with
      burnout level. More strikingly, burnout was found to be a significant predictor of mortality
      in those below the age of 45-years.

      Burnout carries its repercussions on mental health as well. In a study of 2,555 dentists,
      burnout was a significant predictor of depression occurrence during the 3-year follow-up
      period. Increased psychotropic and antidepressant use was associated with high burnout, with
      a stronger correlation observed for men than women. High level of burnout was also linked to
      increased risk of anxiety, substance abuse, alcohol abuse, and even suicidal ideation.

      Burnout is a serious threat to the medical profession at large. With more than half of the US
      physicians suffering from professional burnout, its implications ripple through the entirety
      of the healthcare system. Burnout decreases both patient care quality and physician
      productivity. Increased sickness absences have been reported in high burnout. In a recent
      report, severe burnout independently accounted for 52 sickness absences in a 2-year follow-up
      period. Additionally, burnout has resulted in more physicians leaving practices or reducing
      their work hours. A healthcare system loses on average $500,000 to $1,000,000 with the
      departure of a physician, in addition to the ever-increasing workload of physicians who
      remain in practice. Most significant of all, burnout leads to major medical errors. With the
      estimated 250,000 deaths in the United States occurring due to medical errors, developing
      effective strategies to eliminate physician burnout has become an ever-present priority.

      A number of prospective studies and clinical trials have been conducted to assess the
      efficacy of different interventions on mitigating physician burnout. A major cluster of these
      studies have focused on behavioral interventions, more specifically, mindfulness-based
      approaches aimed at reducing the mental and emotional repercussions of burnout. Such
      behavioral interventions included practices of contemplation-meditation exercises,
      discussions on enhancing self-care and intensification of present-moment awareness. Efficacy
      in the latter studies was mostly assessed via quantification of change in burnout and
      stress-related scores, most notably the Maslach Burnout Inventory score, a well-established
      tool for assessment of burnout in the occupational setting. The majority of these studies
      reported favorable effects on burnout scores. However, limited to no-data exist on the
      physiological and biochemical effects of mindfulness-based interventions on physician
      burnout.

      A second cluster of studies implemented lifestyle changes, more specifically, incentivized
      exercise programs and nutritional counseling for burnout. However, studies examining the
      effects of physical activity tended to be short in duration, of small magnitude, and lacked
      adequate assessment of the physiological and biochemical effects of exercise on burnout [23].
      Additionally, a significant lack of research on nutritional and dietary interventions in
      physician burnout exist in the literature, despite the vitality of good nutrition in the
      health and wellbeing of physicians.

      Therefore, this study intends to tackle the issue of physician burnout via a wide-lens
      approach, integrating both mindfulness-based training and nutritional counseling in the
      management of professional burnout. The effects of the interventions will be evaluated
      through assessment of changes in physiological and biochemical parameters known to be
      adversely affected in burnout, in addition to the standardized Professional Fulfillment
      Inventory, at 3-6 months post-intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All participants will receive mindfulness based training and nutritional consultation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Professional Fulfillment Index (PFI) score</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured at baseline and at 3-6 months for each participant to determine if intervention was effective. A higher score indicates improvement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Neff Self-Compassion Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured at baseline and at 3-6 months for each participant to determine if intervention was effective. A higher score indicates improvement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in diastolic and systolic blood pressure between baseline and 3-6 months after intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resting heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in resting heart rate between baseline and 3-6 months after intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in weight between baseline and 3-6 months after intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Athens Insomnia Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in insomnia scale between baseline and 3-6 months after intervention. Range from 0-24 with lower score being favorable outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily average time spent reviewing electronic health records</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self reported time spent (in hours) reviewing electronic health records</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in total cholesterol post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in HbA1c post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting plasma glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in fasting plasma glucose post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in fasting insulin value post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>C-reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in C-reactive protein levels post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin Resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Homeostatic Model Assessment of Insulin Resistance (HOMA-IR) to assess presence of and extent of insulin resistance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>High density lipoprotein (HDL)</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in HDL value post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low density lipoprotein (LDL)</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in LDL value post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in triglycerides post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Burnout, Professional</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness Training and Nutrition Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Baseline and 3-6 month follow up visits will be arranged for all participants.
Visits will be conducted at baseline prior to initiation of mindfulness training and nutrition counseling, and at the 3-6 month follow up. Clinical and laboratory assessments will be obtained at each visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness training</intervention_name>
    <description>Mindfulness training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness Training and Nutrition Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nutritional consult</intervention_name>
    <description>Nutrition counseling and development of a personalized nutrition plan</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness Training and Nutrition Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician employed by Cleveland Clinic

          -  Located in Ohio

          -  Must anticipate remaining employed for at least 6 months post-enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-MD or non-DO healthcare providers

          -  Unable to commit to intervention sessions

          -  Current diagnosis of uncontrolled hypertension, and/or uncontrolled diabetes mellitus
             (defined as hemoglobin A1c ≥9%)

          -  Current or previous history of Cushing's disease or pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Betul Hatipoglu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Staff Physician</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahola K, Hakanen J. Job strain, burnout, and depressive symptoms: a prospective study among dentists. J Affect Disord. 2007 Dec;104(1-3):103-10. Epub 2007 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17448543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fred HL, Scheid MS. Physician Burnout: Causes, Consequences, and (?) Cures. Tex Heart Inst J. 2018 Aug 1;45(4):198-202. doi: 10.14503/THIJ-18-6842. eCollection 2018 Aug. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30374225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rothenberger DA. Physician Burnout and Well-Being: A Systematic Review and Framework for Action. Dis Colon Rectum. 2017 Jun;60(6):567-576. doi: 10.1097/DCR.0000000000000844. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28481850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pantenburg B, Luppa M, König HH, Riedel-Heller SG. Burnout among young physicians and its association with physicians' wishes to leave: results of a survey in Saxony, Germany. J Occup Med Toxicol. 2016 Jan 22;11:2. doi: 10.1186/s12995-016-0091-z. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>26807138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dyrbye L, Shanafelt T. A narrative review on burnout experienced by medical students and residents. Med Educ. 2016 Jan;50(1):132-49. doi: 10.1111/medu.12927. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26695473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Betul Hatipoglu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Endocrinologist, Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burnout, Professional</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burnout, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

