<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04335643</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00003882</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04335643</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telehealth CBT for Adolescents and Young Adults With Childhood-onset Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</brief_title>
  <acronym>cSLE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Remotely Delivered CBT Intervention for Youth With cSLE: A Multi-site Patient-engaged Investigation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Michigan State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Arthritis Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Hospital for Sick Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Montefiore Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Michigan State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to investigate the feasibility and effectiveness of a remotely delivered
      psychological intervention for youth with cSLE. This intervention aims to teach participants
      skills in order to cope with fatigue, pain, and depressive symptoms--symptoms that commonly
      affect adolescents and young adults with lupus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project is investigating whether a remotely delivered psychological intervention is
      acceptable and beneficial to teens and young adults coping with cSLE. This study uses a
      cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) intervention called the Treatment and Education Approach
      for Childhood-onset Lupus (TEACH) to address symptoms of fatigue, depression, and pain that
      commonly occur in individuals with cSLE. The TEACH program includes six-weekly, one hour
      sessions, conducted over HIPAA-compliant video conferencing.

      Participation in this study will take approximately 8-15 weeks. After qualifying for the
      study, participants will be randomly selected, like flipping a coin, to the TEACH program
      plus medical treatment as usual (TAU) OR medical TAU alone for six weeks. After this six-week
      time period, a post-assessment will be completed. Participants that only continued medical
      TAU will then be eligible to receive TEACH after completing the post-assessment. If these
      participants choose to undergo the TEACH treatment, they will be asked to complete a short
      interview about the program and answer questions about how their mood, pain, and fatigue.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will either be randomly assigned to the intervention or to a wait-list period.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rates of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>After enrollment period, approximately 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Recruitment rates will be measured by the number of participants who agree to participate in the study. This information will be collected after the enrollment period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention rates of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>After data collection period, approximately 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Retention rates will be measured by the number of participants who complete the study. This information will be collected after the data collection period ends.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of remotely-delivered TEACH</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be measured by participant feedback in a qualitative interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fatigue, as measured by the PROMIS Fatigue SF</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The adult PROMIS Fatigue SF measures fatigue one a scale of 10-40; 10 indicating no fatigue, 40 indicating high levels of fatigue. The pediatric PROMIS Fatigue SF measures on a scale of 0-40; 0 indicating no fatigue and 40 indicating high levels of fatigue. This is to assess changes at a midpoint in the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fatigue, as measured by the PROMIS Fatigue SF</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The adult PROMIS Fatigue SF measures fatigue one a scale of 10-40; 10 indicating no fatigue, 40 indicating high levels of fatigue. The pediatric PROMIS Fatigue SF measures on a scale of 0-40; 0 indicating no fatigue and 40 indicating high levels of fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in fatigue, as measured by the PROMIS Fatigue SF</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The adult PROMIS Fatigue SF measures fatigue one a scale of 10-40; 10 indicating no fatigue, 40 indicating high levels of fatigue. The pediatric PROMIS Fatigue SF measures on a scale of 0-40; 0 indicating no fatigue and 40 indicating high levels of fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in depressive symptoms, as measured by the CDI-2 and BDI-II</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CDI-2 measures depressive symptoms on a scale of 0-54, with 0 indicating low levels of depressive symptoms, and 54 indicating high levels of depressive symptoms. The BDI-II measures depressive symptoms on a scale of 0 to 63, with 0 indicating low levels of depressive symptoms and 63 indicating high levels of depressive symptoms. This is to assess changes at a midpoint in the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in depressive symptoms, as measured by the CDI-2 and BDI-II</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CDI-2 measures depressive symptoms on a scale of 0-54, with 0 indicating low levels of depressive symptoms, and 54 indicating high levels of depressive symptoms. The BDI-II measures depressive symptoms on a scale of 0 to 63, with 0 indicating low levels of depressive symptoms and 63 indicating high levels of depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in depressive symptoms, as measured by the CDI-2 and BDI-II</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CDI-2 measures depressive symptoms on a scale of 0-54, with 0 indicating low levels of depressive symptoms, and 54 indicating high levels of depressive symptoms. The BDI-II measures depressive symptoms on a scale of 0 to 63, with 0 indicating low levels of depressive symptoms and 63 indicating high levels of depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in pain, as measured by the Pain VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Pain VAS measures three items on a scale of 0-10, with 0 indicating no pain and 10 indicating the worst possible pain. This is to assess changes at a midpoint in the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in pain, as measured by the Pain VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Pain VAS measures three items on a scale of 0-10, with 0 indicating no pain and 10 indicating the worst possible pain</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in pain, as measured by the Pain VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Pain VAS measures three items on a scale of 0-10, with 0 indicating no pain and 10 indicating the worst possible pain</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The number of adverse childhood experiences, as measured by ACEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ACEs questionnaire poses 9 different potential adverse childhood experiences in which participants indicate if they have or have not had that experience. The total is calculated by adding the items indicated as &quot;yes.&quot;</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in caregivers' depression, anxiety, and stress as measured by the DASS21</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The DASS21 depression, anxiety, and stress on a scale of 0-63 with 0 indicating low levels of these feelings, and 63 indicating high levels. This measure will only be completed by caregivers participating in the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in caregivers' depression, anxiety, and stress as measured by the DASS21</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The DASS21 depression, anxiety, and stress on a scale of 0-63 with 0 indicating low levels of these feelings, and 63 indicating high levels. This measure will only be completed by caregivers participating in the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in disease activity as measured by a VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Disease activity will be measured by the physician on a VAS ranging from 0, indicating no activity, to 10 indicating high activity. This VAS used will be from the pediatric global health assessment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in disease activity as measured by a VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Disease activity will be measured by the physician on a VAS ranging from 0, indicating no activity, to 10 indicating high activity. This VAS used will be from the pediatric global health assessment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life, as measured by the PedsQL</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PedsQL measures quality of life in several aspects such as health, school, daily activities. Each item is reversed scored and transformed to a linear scale of 0-100, such that 100 indicates a high quality of life and 0 indicates a low quality of life</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in quality of life, as measured by the PedsQL</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PedsQL measures quality of life in several aspects such as health, school, daily activities. Each item is reversed scored and transformed to a linear scale of 0-100, such that 100 indicates a high quality of life and 0 indicates a low quality of life</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in pain interference, as measured by the PROMIS Pain Interference SF</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PROMIS Pain Interference SF measures how pain interferes with aspects of life, such as daily activities or family life. Scores range from 8 to 40 for adults and 0 to 32 for children, such that lower scores indicate little pain interference and high scores indicate high pain interference.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in pain interference, as measured by the PROMIS Pain Interference SF</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The PROMIS Pain Interference SF measures how pain interferes with aspects of life, such as daily activities or family life. Scores range from 8 to 40 for adults and 0 to 32 for children, such that lower scores indicate little pain interference and high scores indicate high pain interference.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in anxiety, as measured by the SCARED and SCAARED</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SCARED measures anxiety in children on a scale of 0 to 82, such that lower scores indicates low levels of anxiety, and high scores indicated high levels of anxiety. The SCAARED measures anxiety in adults on a scale of 0 to 88 such that lower scores indicated lower levels of anxiety and high scores indicate higher levels of anxiety. Both scales are comprised of sub-scales to measure types of anxiety (such as separation anxiety).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in anxiety, as measured by the SCARED and SCAARED</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SCARED measures anxiety in children on a scale of 0 to 82, such that lower scores indicates low levels of anxiety, and high scores indicated high levels of anxiety. The SCAARED measures anxiety in adults on a scale of 0 to 88 such that lower scores indicated lower levels of anxiety and high scores indicate higher levels of anxiety. Both scales are comprised of sub-scales to measure types of anxiety (such as separation anxiety).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in disease activity, as measured by the SLEDAI 2K</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SLEDAI 2K measures disease activity in SLE, and takes into consideration descriptors of the disease such as arthritis and vasculitis. Higher scores indicate more active disease/flares, and lower scores indicated less disease activity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in disease activity, as measured by the SLEDAI 2K</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SLEDAI 2K measures disease activity in SLE, and takes into consideration descriptors of the disease such as arthritis and vasculitis. Higher scores indicate more active disease/flares, and lower scores indicated less disease activity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in disease activity, as measured by the SLICC</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SLICC measures disease activity by assessing descriptors in SLE. Higher scores indicate greater disease activity, lower scores indicate lesser disease activity</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in disease activity, as measured by the SLICC</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SLICC measures disease activity by assessing descriptors in SLE. Higher scores indicate greater disease activity, lower scores indicate lesser disease activity</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in resilience, as measured by the BRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Resilience Scale (BRS) measures resilience on a scale of 1 to 5 such that higher scores indicate greater resilience and lower scores indicate lower resilience.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in resilience, as measured by the BRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Resilience Scale (BRS) measures resilience on a scale of 1 to 5 such that higher scores indicate greater resilience and lower scores indicate lower resilience.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in medication adherence, as measured by the MASRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Medication Adherence Self-Report Inventory (MASRI) measures medication adherence on a scale of 0%-100%, such that lower scores indicate less adherence and higher scores indicate more adherence.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term changes in medication adherence, as measured by the MASRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 20 and 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Medication Adherence Self-Report Inventory (MASRI) measures medication adherence on a scale of 0%-100%, such that lower scores indicate less adherence and higher scores indicate more adherence.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concomitant medications</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Medications will be collect through medical charts and reported by participants and caregivers of participants who are under 18 years.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TEACH</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will undergo CBT and continue medical TAU.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will only continue medical TAU.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TEACH</intervention_name>
    <description>TEACH is a remotely delivered psychological intervention. It consists of six one-hour weekly sessions that are HIPAA compliant and conducted over video conferencing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TEACH</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Treatment and Education Approach for Childhood-onset Lupus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be diagnosed with cSLE, meeting the revised American College of
             Rheumatology Classification Criteria for SLE by age 18 years

          -  Participants must have at least one elevation (based off of screening measures) in
             fatigue, or depressive symptoms, or pain

          -  Patient participants must have English language proficiency

          -  For participants under age 18, must have a primary caregiver willing to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with other chronic medical conditions (e.g., juvenile arthritis),

          -  Patients with a documented developmental delay, severe cognitive impairment, or
             thought disorder

          -  Patients with an untreated major psychiatric illness (e.g., bipolar disorder,
             psychosis, severe depression, or active suicidal ideation)

          -  Patients currently receiving psychological treatment for depression, fatigue or pain
             will be excluded to prevent overlapping treatments that may confound outcomes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>22 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Natoshia Cunningham, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Samantha Ely, BA</last_name>
    <phone>616-234-2820</phone>
    <email>elysaman@msu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Natoshia Cunningham, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>616-234-2821</phone>
    <email>natoshia@msu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Michigan State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Natoshia Cunningham</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lupus</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>depressive symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>SLE</keyword>
  <keyword>rheumatic disease</keyword>
  <keyword>rheumatology</keyword>
  <keyword>telehealth</keyword>
  <keyword>CBT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

