<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04336605</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Killing Pain</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>A pill for the pain</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04336605</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Killing Pain - Use of Analgesic, Sedative and Anxiolytic Medication and the Development of Psychiatric Illness in Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Killing Pain - Use of Analgesic, Sedative and Anxiolytic Medication and the Development of Psychiatric Illness in Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Norwegian Center for Violence and Traumatic Stress Studies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Change Factory</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Norwegian Council for Mental Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dam Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Norwegian Institute of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Norwegian Center for Violence and Traumatic Stress Studies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prescription of analgesic, sedative, and anxiolytic medication for children and adolescents
      is increasing in Western countries. In recent decades, rates have also increased in Norway,
      despite a relatively restrictive prescription practice. Analgesics, sedatives, and
      anxiolytics are among the medications most commonly prescribed to young people by general
      practitioners and others. Overuse of such medication adversely impacts individual and
      societal health, social and economic measures. For example, the risk of chronification of
      pain, development of addiction, and dropout from school and the workforce is high.
      Epidemiological research has largely failed to integrate vulnerable, young service users'
      perspectives in planning, interpretation and dissemination of results. This has resulted in
      limited identification of potential causes for the increasing exposure to prescription and
      overuse of analgesics and other addictive drugs among of children and adolescents, and the
      long-term consequences this may have for morbidity and addiction in early adulthood.
      Knowledge of early risk factors and plausible causal mechanisms is crucial for the
      development of timely and effective interventions to prevent inappropriate prescriptions in
      clinical practice.

      This prospective, longitudinal cohort study examines the use of analgesic, sedative, and
      anxiolytic medication among about 25,000 children throughout adolescence and young adulthood
      (1995 to 2020), specifically addressing changes in prescription over time, and early risk
      factors for the prescription of addictive drugs in adolescence and young adulthood and the
      subsequent development of mental health disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Linking data from the renowned, representative, population-based Nord-Trøndelag Health
      studies of adolescents (Young-HUNT, 1995-2019) to longitudinal, individual data from the
      Norwegian prescription Database (NorPD) (2004-2020) provides a unique, longitudinal dataset
      which will be examined in this study. Thus, the study design allows for examination of early
      predictors, risk factors, and potential causal mechanisms of prescription drug (analgesic,
      sedative, and anxiolytic medication) overuse, and development of severe mental illness in
      young people.

      The Young-HUNT3 (2006-2008) study is among the world's first representative health surveys of
      youth encompassing questions about violence and other traumatic events, self-reported somatic
      and psychological health measures, a clinical examination, and consent to linkage to
      longitudinal health registries. The Young-HUNT4 (2017-2019) additionally includes validated
      actigraphy measures of activity and sleep. The full cohort of adolescents living in
      Nord-Trøndelag county were invited to participate in each of the study waves (HUNT1-4).
      Participation rates have been exceptionally high ranging from 78-90%. During school hours,
      the youth answered a number of health-related questions, including items on: physical
      violence, sexual abuse, bullying, and a range of other traumatic events (in the youngHUNT3
      and 4); diagnosed chronic disease such as epilepsy, migraine, or juvenile rheumatoid
      arthritis; somatic and psychological symptoms, including recurrent headaches, abdominal pain,
      other musculoskeletal pain, autonomic somatic symptoms, sleep difficulties, post-traumatic
      stress reactions, psychological distress (anxiety/depression), and loneliness; use of
      non-prescription analgesics; pubertal onset and developmental stage; lifestyle, such as
      physical activity and nutrition; socio-economic and psychosocial factors. The study
      additionally comprised a validated headache interview, and clinical anthropometric measures.
      The HUNT4 included a week's measure of activity and sleep by the use of actigraphs.
      Information on age and gender was obtained from the Norwegian National Population Registry.

      Each Young-HUNT participant's 11-digit social security number will be linked to individual
      data in the NorPD at the Norwegian Institute of Public Health. The NorPD registers all
      prescription drugs dispensed from pharmacies in Norway, and the database therefore contains a
      complete overview of all prescription drugs dispensed to individual patients outside
      hospitals, since 2004. Non-prescription drugs and medicines purchased abroad are not
      registered. Registered drugs are classified according to the International Anatomical
      Therapeutic Chemical Classification System (ATC). In this study, the investigators include
      information on the number of dispensed prescriptions of drugs classified within the following
      ATC codes: M01 (anti-inflammatory and anti-rheumatic agents), N01A (anesthetics, general),
      N02 (analgesics; opioids, other analgesics, and antipyretics and migraine agents), N05
      (psycholeptics; antipsychotics, anxiolytics, hypnotics and anxiolytics), N06
      (psychoanaleptics; antidepressants, ADHD and nootropics, and psycholeptics in combinations)
      and N07B (drugs for addiction disorders) from 2004 up to time of linkage (2019/2020).

      To obtain good, reliable follow-up data and outcome measures for the young-HUNT3 participants
      (2006-2008) the investigators will additionally include longitudinal data from the HUNT4
      study of young adults (2017-2019); applicable for those participating in both the YoungHUNT3
      and the YoungHUNT4.

      The data material provides a unique opportunity to study the following research questions:

        1. Prevalence and comorbidity of migraine, other headache, chronic widespread pain,
           fatigue, insomnia and posttraumatic stress reactions and related risk profiles among
           adolescents.

        2. How do discrepancies in risk &amp; comorbidity profiles differentially affect young peoples'
           risk of analgesic, sedative, and anxiolytic medication overuse over time?

        3. Do early somatic and psychological symptoms and self-medication in adolescence mediate
           risk of prescription drugs overuse in young people?

        4. The role of early symptomatology and prescription drug overuse as predictive factors for
           development of severe psychiatric illness by young adulthood (age 29).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>25 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prescription drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>2006-2020</time_frame>
    <description>Analgetic, sedative &amp; anxiolytic medication</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric Illness</measure>
    <time_frame>2006-2020</time_frame>
    <description>Medically treated severe mental illness, i.e. depression, psychosis, dependency or addiction disorders</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25000</enrollment>
  <condition>PTSD</condition>
  <condition>Psychiatric Illness</condition>
  <condition>Prescription Drug Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Addiction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
    <description>The young-HUNT study is a renowned, representative, population-based study where all adolescents living in the Nord-Trøndelag county have been invited to participate in four subsequent waves, from 1995 to 2019. Information about the study can be found here: https://www.ntnu.edu/hunt/young-hunt. In this study data from the Young-HUNT1-4 studies (1995-2019) will be linked to longitudinal, individual data from the Norwegian prescription Database (NorPD) (2004-2020), providing a unique, longitudinal dataset in which research questions will be explored. To obtain good, reliable follow-up data and outcome measures for the young-HUNT3 participants (2006-2008) the investigators will additionally include longitudinal data from the HUNT4 study of young adults (2017-2019); applicable for those participating in both the YoungHUNT3 and the YoungHUNT4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Age &amp; Development</intervention_name>
    <description>Age, sex, pubertal onset and development</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Socioeconomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Family structure and economy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Traumatic Events</intervention_name>
    <description>Violence and other traumatic events</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychosocial conditions</intervention_name>
    <description>Family/social support</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle</intervention_name>
    <description>Physical activity, BMI, nutrition, smoking …</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chronic conditions</intervention_name>
    <description>I.e. Epilepsy or juvenile rheumatoid arthritis ...</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Somatic symptoms</intervention_name>
    <description>Headache, pain, sleep disturbances ...</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychological symptoms</intervention_name>
    <description>PTSS, anxiety, depressive symptoms &amp; loneliness ...</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-prescription analgesics</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-prescription analgesics</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prescription drugs</intervention_name>
    <description>Analgetic, sedative &amp; anxiolytic medication</description>
    <arm_group_label>Young-HUNT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All youth in Nord-Trøndelag county in Norway between 13-19 years were invited to
        participate in the four Young-HUNT study waves (1995-2019), and followed up after
        approximately 10 years between 2017-2020. In this study data from the Young-HUNT1-4 studies
        (1995-2019) will be linked to longitudinal, individual data from the Norwegian prescription
        Database (NorPD) (2004-2020), providing a unique, longitudinal dataset. To obtain good,
        reliable followup data for the young-HUNT3 participants (2006-2008) the investigators will
        additionally include longitudinal data of for those participating in both the YoungHUNT3
        and the YoungHUNT4 (2017-2019).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All youth in Nord-Trøndelag county were invited to participate in four subsequent
             Young-HUNT study waves (1995-2019), https://www.ntnu.edu/hunt/young-hunt

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>32 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Synne O Stensland, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Norwegian Centre for Violence and Traumatic Stress Studies</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Norwegian Centre for Violence and Traumatic Stress Studies</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0409</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Norwegian Center for Violence and Traumatic Stress Studies</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Synne O. B. Stensland</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator (MD, PhD)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric Illness</keyword>
  <keyword>Prescription drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Addiction</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Behavior, Addictive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

