<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04338646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GREEN GRC01 P</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04338646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Is the Severity of Urinary Disorders Related to Falls in People With Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Is the Severity of Urinary Disorders Related to Falls in People With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gérard Amarenco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pierre and Marie Curie University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Falls are a common problem in people with multiple sclerosis (PwMS) and can lead to severe
      consequences (trauma, fear of falling, reduction of social activities). Prevention of falls
      is one of the priority targets of rehabilitation for PwMS and walking difficulties, which can
      result of different factors (motor impairment, ataxia, sensitive disorders, fatigability…).
      Urinary incontinence has been evoked as predictive of falls. But lower urinary tract symptoms
      (LUTSs) are frequent in PwMS, the prevalence of LUTSs is high (32-96.8%) and increases with
      MS duration and severity of neurological deficiencies and disabilities. Overactive bladder
      (OAB) is the most common symptom. Despite its high prevalence and impact on quality of life,
      the severity of LUTSs has never been studied as specific risk factor of falling. However,
      urinary urgency and urinary incontinence could lead to precipitation and thus could increase
      the risk of falling in these patients.

      The aim of the study was to assess the relationship between severity of LUTSs and risk of
      falling in PwMS.

      Patients were asked about the number of falls in the past three months and in the past year,
      and the circumstances in which they occurred (frequency, home, outdoors, going to void,
      during urinary urgency, nocturia). Severity of LUTSs were assessed by the Urinary Symptoms
      Profile (USP) Score and patient were classified as with or without urinary incontinence.
      Number of micturition by night were specifically asked. To take into account motor
      difficulties and fear of falling, other clinical evaluations were done. The impact of MS on
      walking was assessed by the 12-Item Multiple Sclerosis Walking Scale (MSWS12) questionnaire,
      the Expanded Disability Status Scale score, and by clinical test with the Time to be Ready to
      Void (TRV). Fear of falling was assessed by a simple question and with Falls Efficacy
      Scale-International (FES-I) Questionnaire.

      The primary aim was to assess the relationship between severity of LUTSs and occurrence of
      falls during the past 3 months. The primary outcome was the importance of overactive bladder
      (OAB) symptoms with OAB USP score. The secondary outcomes were the existence of urinary
      incontinence, the warning time (defined as the time from the first sensation of urgency to
      voiding or incontinence), the importance of nocturia and the other scores of USP
      questionnaire (low stream and stress urinary incontinence).

      The secondary aims were to look for the relationship between severity of LUTSs and occurrence
      of falls during the past year, and to assess the relationship between falls and the classical
      risk factors of falls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of falls in the past 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Patients were asked about the number of falls in the past three months, and the circumstances in which they occurred (frequency, home, outdoors, going to void, during urinary urgency, nocturia)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of falls in the past year</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Patients were asked about the number of falls in the past year, and the circumstances in which they occurred (frequency, home, outdoors, going to void, during urinary urgency, nocturia)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between number of falls in the past 3 months and in the past year and clinical datas and characteristics of the patient</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of MS on walking was assessed by the 12-Item Multiple Sclerosis Walking Scale (MSWS12) questionnaire, the EDSS score, and by clinical test with the Time to be Ready to Void (TRV). Fear of falling was assessed by a simple question and with Falls Efficacy Scale-International (FES-I) Questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Fall</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients enrolled</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient with multiple sclerosis and lower urinary tract symptoms, age &gt;18 Expanded Disability Status Scale score between 1 and 6.5</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical tests</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaire about urinary symptoms, gait difficulties, fear of falling. Clinical test: Time to be Ready to Void</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients enrolled</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients consulting in a tertiary center in neuro-urology
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age ≥ 18 years

          -  Multiple sclerosis (MS) diagnosis

          -  Lower urinary tract symptoms with or without treatment,

          -  Expanded Disability Status Scale score between 1 and 6.5

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  relapse of MS in the past month

          -  urinary tract infection the day of inclusion

          -  impossibility to complete the symptoms' questionnaires
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sorbonne Université, GRC 001, GREEN, AP-HP, Hôpital Tenon, Paris, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claire Hentzen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0156017040</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0156017040</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>department of Neuro-Urology, Hôpital Tenon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75020</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claire Hentzen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0156017040</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gérard Amarenco, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0156017040</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>greengrc01@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pierre and Marie Curie University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gérard Amarenco</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Neuro-Urology department, Tenon Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fall</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>lower urinary tract symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>overactive bladder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lower Urinary Tract Symptoms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

