<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04330885</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SLS-683231</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04330885</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PRE Surgery reHABilitation for Spinal Stenosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>PreShab</acronym>
  <official_title>PRE Surgery reHABilitation for Patients Suffering From Spinal Stenosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lumbar spinal stenosis is a spinal disorder that affects mainly people over the age of 60.
      LSS is the most common reason to perform spinal surgery for people aged &gt;65 years and have
      been shown to be superior to conservative treatment. Hitherto, studies on lumbar spinal
      stenosis are sparse with only 3 trials including approximately 300 patients. There is also a
      paucity in studies investigating if people with lumbar spinal stenosis improve their outcome
      following surgery undergoing a pre-surgery rehabilitation programme including physical
      fitness exercises, abdominal and back muscle strengthening and a core control approach.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lumbar spinal stenosis is a spinal disorder that affects mainly people over the age of 60.
      This age group with neurogenic claudication is expected to rise dramatically over the next 20
      years when an estimated 23-25 % of the population will be &gt; 60 years. Lumbar spinal stenosis
      is the most common reason to perform spinal surgery for people aged &gt;65 years and have been
      shown to be superior to conservative treatment. Conservative treatment post-operatively have
      recently been described in a Cochrane review to be of importance. Hitherto, studies on lumbar
      spinal stenosisare sparse with only 3 trials including approximately 300 patients. There is
      also a paucity in studies investigating if people with lumbar spinal stenosis improve their
      outcome following surgery undergoing a pre-surgery rehabilitation programme including
      physical fitness exercises, abdominal and back muscle strengthening and a core control
      approach.

      Aim: The aim of the current study was to evaluate a pre-surgery rehabilitation intervention
      for patients diagnosed with lumbar spinal stenosis found eligible for a decompression
      surgery. A further aim was to conduct a qualitative study to explore the experience of
      symptoms in relation to all-day-living and quality of life among those who have undergone a
      decompression surgery for lumbar spinal stenosis.

      Methods: Patients consecutively seeking or referred for orthopaedic surgery at Spine Clinic
      in Stockholm will, if found eligible and given their informed consent be randomized into two
      separate groups following a consultant visit to an orthopaedic surgeon; 1) A pre-habilitation
      program of 8 weeks before decompression surgery 2) Care as usual, that is information from
      physiotherapists 2 weeks before surgery and the advice to stay active. Those eligible for
      decompression surgery are patients aged 50-75 with pseudo-claudication in one or both legs
      and back pain (VAS&gt;30), magnetic resonance camera with 1-2 adjacent stenotic segments (L3-S1)
      (area ≤75mm2), duration of symptoms &gt;6 months.

      Both written and oral information of the study will be given and the patients will give their
      written consent. An independent physiotherapist blinded to patient assignment will
      sequentially number the envelopes containing intervention assignments according to a
      computer-generated randomization. Opaque and sealed envelopes will be opened in front of the
      participants at the end of the initial assessment visit. The main applicant will be
      responsible for data collection, to set up the program and educate included physiotherapists,
      to be responsible for analyses of data and for ethical application.

      For the secondary aim a strategic sample of patients from both groups following the surgery
      will be included to conduct semi-structured deep interviews to explore their experience of
      facilitators and barriers to every day life both before and after the surgery. The interviews
      will take place 3 months following the surgery. The collected data will be analysed according
      a content analysis with categories, sub categories and themes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled study with two treatment arms; one with care as usual and the intervention group with prehab before surgery. This is a feasibility study to determine how many subjects who need to be included to be able to a obtain an estimate of variance in an outcome when an important difference between groups</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Investigator does not take part in data collection. All data collected via web based surveys.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Pain level: Numeric pain rating scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks pre-surgery, pre-surgery, 3 and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Numeric pain rating scale 0-10, higher value means more pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Disability level</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks pre-surgery, pre surgery, 3 and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Oswestry Disability Index 0-100, higher value means more functional limitations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Fear of movement</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks pre-surgery, pre-surgery, 3 and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Fear Avoidance Belief Questionnaire physical activity 0-25, higher score indiactes higher fear</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self efficacy: Self efficacy scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks pre-surgery, pre-surgery, 3 and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Self efficacy scale for physical activity in low-back pain, 0-64, higher value indicates a better self-efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of General Health</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks before surgery, pre surgery, 3 and 12 months after surgery. HIgher values menas better health</time_frame>
    <description>EuroQol-5 Dimensions Index (EQ5D), 3-point adjectival scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Global recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Global recovery, Question to value the overall change of symtoms, measured with lickert scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change of 6 minutes walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks pre-surgery, pre -surgery, 3 and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Walk test - , assessed distance managed on 6 minutes, self chosen pace</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Rehabilitation</condition>
  <condition>Physiotherapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prehab group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in the PREHAB group will meet with a PT for 6 weeks pre surgery. The PT will coach the patient in 1:1 visits with a graded activity program with the purpose to affect fear of movement and raising level of self-efficacy with physical activity. The intervention comprises; cycling on a stationary cycle. Instructions of exercises that strengthen the deep and the superficial abdominal muscles and the back muscles. Information to contract the abdominal muscles in posturally loaded position to support their back. Information on flexion exercises of their lumbar spine and to keep the back in a flexed position when standing and walking (as opposed to extension). Recommendation to use &quot;Nordic walk (stavar)&quot; for outdoor walking</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Care as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group will be treated with care as usual meaning information from a PT two weeks prior to the surgery with information on the surgery and to stay active. Both groups will be given information on to stay active and home exercises following the surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Supervised abdominal exercises and stationary biking</intervention_name>
    <description>Explain pain to the patients in order to minimize fear of movement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prehab group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Explain pain</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Spinal stenosis

          -  Eligible for decompression surgery

          -  aged 50-75 years

          -  pseudo-claudication in one or both legs

          -  back pain (VAS&gt;30),

          -  MRI with 1-2 adjacent stenotic segments (L3-S1) (area ≤75mm2),

          -  duration of symptoms &gt;6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eva Rasmussen Barr, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eva Rasmussen Barr, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0707400045</phone>
    <phone_ext>0707400045</phone_ext>
    <email>eva.rasmussen.barr@ki.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Per Svedmark, PhD</last_name>
    <email>per.svedmark@rkc.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ryggkirurgiskt Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Per Svedmark, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <email>per.svedmark@rkc.se</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yrsa Frode, RPT, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eva Rasmussen Barr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associated professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>spinal stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>physiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

