<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04330235</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HDB-NYC</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HD100983-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04330235</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating a Healthy Restaurant Kids Meals Policy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating a Healthy Restaurant Kids Meals Policy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harvard School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harvard Pilgrim Health Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RTI International</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      More than a dozen municipalities have passed healthy default kids' beverage policies. These
      policies seek to reduce child consumption of sugar-sweetened beverages (SSBs) by requiring
      that restaurants serve only healthy beverages (e.g., water, milk, or 100% juice) instead of
      SSBs as the default choice with children's meals in restaurants. These policies have
      potential to meaningfully reduce child SSB consumption. However, there are significant gaps
      in our knowledge of the effects of healthy default beverage policies on children's health.
      This study uses a natural experiment to evaluate the effects of a healthy default beverage
      policy in two U.S. cities, New York City and Philadelphia, on children's fast-food restaurant
      meal orders and dietary intake. The primary hypothesis is that the policy will reduce
      children's SSB purchases and consumption, reduce children's total caloric intake, and improve
      diet quality at the fast-food restaurant meal and on the day of the restaurant meal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study uses a quasi-experimental approach to evaluate the effects of a healthy default
      kids' beverage policy on children's fast-food restaurant meal purchases and dietary intake.
      Annotated receipt and survey data will be collected from parents purchasing a food or
      beverage for a child 2-10 years of age at fast-food restaurants. Eligible participants will
      be asked to participate in a telephone dietary recall the following day. Data will be
      collected from a repeated cross-section of children in two intervention cities implementing a
      healthy default kids' beverage policy (New York City and Philadelphia) and a control area not
      implementing the policy (northern New Jersey) before the policy is implemented and after the
      policy goes into effect. A difference-in-differences analytic approach will be used to
      compare the change in children's fast-food restaurant meal orders and dietary intake pre- to
      post-implementation in the intervention versus control groups. A Holm-Bonferroni correction
      for multiple comparisons will be applied to p-values for secondary outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline total caloric intake at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total calories consumed by the child on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline calories consumed from sugar-sweetened beverages at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calories consumed by the child from sugar-sweetened beverages on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline calories consumed from healthy beverages at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calories consumed by the child from healthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline calories consumed from other unhealthy beverages at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calories consumed by the child from unhealthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law, excluding sugar-sweetened beverages, on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Healthy Eating Index 2015 score at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child's diet quality, measured using the Healthy Eating Index 2015, on the day of the restaurant meal. The Healthy Eating Index 2015 measures how well a diet aligns with the Dietary Guidelines for Americans. It is measured on a scale from 0-100, where higher scores indicate a healthier diet.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline total caloric intake during the restaurant meal at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total calories consumed by the child during the restaurant eating occasion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline calories consumed from sugar-sweetened beverages during the restaurant meal at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calories consumed by the child from sugar-sweetened beverages during the restaurant eating occasion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline calories consumed from healthy beverages during the restaurant meal at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calories consumed by the child from healthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law during the restaurant eating occasion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline calories consumed from other unhealthy beverages during the restaurant meal at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calories consumed by the child from unhealthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law, excluding sugar-sweetened beverages, during the restaurant eating occasion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Healthy Eating Index 2015 score during the restaurant meal at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child's diet quality, measured using the Healthy Eating Index 2015, during the restaurant eating occasion. The Healthy Eating Index 2015 measures how well a diet aligns with the Dietary Guidelines for Americans. It is measured on a scale from 0-100, where higher scores indicate a healthier diet.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fluid ounces of sugar-sweetened beverages purchased at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fluid ounces of sugar-sweetened beverages purchased for the child at the restaurant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fluid ounces of healthy beverages purchased at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fluid ounces of healthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law purchased for the child at the restaurant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fluid ounces of other unhealthy beverages purchased at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fluid ounces of unhealthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law, excluding sugar-sweetened beverages, purchased for the child at the restaurant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline frequency of dining at fast food restaurants at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of lunch or dinner meals from fast food restaurants for the child in the past week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fluid ounces consumed from sugar-sweetened beverages at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fluid ounces consumed by the child from sugar-sweetened beverages on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fluid ounces consumed from healthy beverages at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fluid ounces consumed by the child from healthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline fluid ounces consumed from other unhealthy beverages at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fluid ounces consumed by the child from unhealthy beverages as defined by NYC/Philadelphia law, excluding sugar-sweetened beverages, on the day of the restaurant meal</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Diet Habit</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children 2-10 years of age dining at fast-food restaurants in New York City and Philadelphia, where a healthy default beverage policy will be enacted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children 2-10 years of age dining at fast-food restaurants in northern New Jersey, where a healthy default beverage policy will not be enacted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Healthy Default Kids' Beverage Policy</intervention_name>
    <description>The healthy default kids' beverage policy requires that all restaurants serve only healthy beverages (water, milk, or 100% juice) instead of sugary beverages as the default beverage with children's meals. The policy has been enacted in New York City and Philadelphia and will go into effect in April 2020.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Healthy Restaurant Kids' Meals Policy</other_name>
    <other_name>Healthy Default Beverage Policy</other_name>
    <other_name>Healthy Default Beverage Law</other_name>
    <other_name>Healthy-by-Default Policy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Parents/legal guardians of children 2-10 years of age will be recruited from fast-food
        restaurants in Philadelphia, northern New Jersey, and New York City that operate more than
        one location in both the intervention and control areas, serve kids' meals, and are not
        compliant with the healthy default kids' beverage policy at baseline.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult 18 years of age or older

          -  Parent or legal guardian of a child 2-10 years of age

          -  Purchasing at least one food or beverage item for the child at the restaurant (if
             purchasing foods or beverages for multiple children, only items purchased for the
             youngest child 2-10 years of age will be included)

          -  Able to speak and understand English or Spanish

        Additional criteria for dietary recalls:

          -  Parent or legal guardian 18 years of age or older is present for the recall

          -  If child for whom the restaurant meal was purchased is 6 years of age or older, child
             is present for the recall

          -  If child for whom the restaurant meal was purchased is 9 years of age or older, the
             child is present for the recall and is able to speak and understand English or Spanish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Younger than 18 years of age

          -  Is not a parent or legal guardian to a child 2-10 years of age

          -  Is not purchasing one or more food or beverage items for the child at the restaurant

          -  Does not speak or understand English or Spanish

        Additional criteria for dietary recalls:

          -  Parent or legal guardian is not present for the recall

          -  The restaurant meal was purchased for a child 6 years of age or older, who is not
             present for the recall

          -  Child 9 years of age or older, for whom the restaurant meal was purchased, is not able
             to speak or understand English or Spanish
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alyssa Moran, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angie Cradock, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Harvard School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alyssa Moran, ScD</last_name>
    <phone>410-614-0256</phone>
    <email>amoran10@jhu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55454-1087</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Harnack, DrPH</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-9398</phone>
      <email>harna001@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>RTI, International</name>
      <address>
        <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27709</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kristine Wiant, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>919-485-5531</phone>
      <email>fahrney@rti.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina Roberto, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-746-7064</phone>
      <email>croberto@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

