<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04334746</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OrduU8</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04334746</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Discriminative Ability of the Four Balance Measures for Fall History</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Discriminative Ability of the Four Balance Measures for.the Previous Fall Experience in Türkish Community-dwelling Older Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>T.C. ORDU ÜNİVERSİTESİ</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hacettepe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Giresun University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>T.C. ORDU ÜNİVERSİTESİ</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The fall rate is increased parallel to the aging process. The early determination and
      management of falls in older adults are quite crucial to preserve the independence of older
      adults. In the literature, there are used many measurement tools for predicting fall status.
      The discriminative ability of these measures is important for the accuracy of the assessment.
      In this study, four of the most commonly used balance measurement tools will be investigated
      in terms of the discriminative ability for fall status in the Turkish community-dwelling
      older adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fall History</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>History of fallings will be determined through a question: &quot;How many times have you fallen in the past year?&quot;.
According to the participants' answers, the participants will be categorized into two groups: fallers (one or more fall events) and non-fallers (no falls).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>One-leg Stance test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>The static balance ability will be determined by one-leg stance test. The participants will be asked to stand on her/his dominant leg as long as possible. The standing time will be recorded with a stopwatch in seconds. Higher times indicate the better balance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Berg Balance Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This scale will be used to evaluate the balance ability. It consists 14 items which are scored from 0 to 4, for a total score of 56 points possible. Higher scores indicate better balance performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed Up and Go Test</measure>
    <time_frame>3 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>In this test, participants will be asked to stand from a chair, walk 3 meters (to a line on the floor), turn around, walk back to the chair, and sit back down. Participants are instructed to walk at a comfortable and safe pace during the Timed Up and Go Test. The participant's score is the time it takes to complete the mentioned test. Lower scores indicate better balance performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Reach Test</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Functional reach will be measured by using a leveled yardstick attached to the wall at the height of the participant's right acromion. To measure the participant's reaching distance, an examiner should stand 4 feet away from the yardstick and should be record the initial and end reach positions. Participant should stand in a relaxed position with feet approximately shoulder-width apart, made a loose fist, and, without touching the wall, placed the right arm parallel to the yardstick (initial position). Participants then will be asked to reach as far forward as they could without losing their balance (end position). The position of the third metacarpal along the yardstick will be recorded at both the initial and end positions. All subjects will be supervised during the test to ensure safety. The mean difference between the initial position and the end position will be calculated as the functional reach score in centimeters. The higher score indicates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Older People--Abuse of</condition>
  <condition>Balance; Distorted</condition>
  <condition>Fall</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Balance measurement tools</intervention_name>
    <description>Timed Up and Go Test Functional Reach Test One-leg Stance Test Berg Balance Scale</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Community-dwelling older adults
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  being aged 65 or above,

          -  having a score of 21 or more from the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) [20,23],

          -  able to ambulate independently or with an assistive device.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  having visual and hearing problems that may cause restrictions in communication and
             also balance impairments,

          -  drug use (benzodiazepine, psychotropic drugs, etc.) with adverse effects on balance
             and walking,

          -  having any serious neurological, cardiopulmonary, or orthopedic disorders that
             adversely affected balance conditions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sevim Acaröz Candan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>T.C. ORDU ÜNİVERSİTESİ</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sevim Acaröz Candan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00904522265200</phone>
    <phone_ext>6536</phone_ext>
    <email>fzt_acaroz@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sevim ACARÖZ CANDAN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ordu</city>
        <state>Altinordu</state>
        <zip>52100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sevim ACARÖZ CANDAN</last_name>
      <phone>5071027447</phone>
      <email>fzt_acaroz@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>T.C. ORDU ÜNİVERSİTESİ</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sevim ACARÖZ CANDAN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Department of Physiotherapy and Rehabilitation</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

