<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04332068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PAR20001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04332068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ivermectin Safety in Small Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>ISSC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Trial to Assess the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of Escalating Doses of Oral Ivermectin in Scabies Infected Children Weighing 5 to Less Than 15 Kilograms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chittagong Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Fundação de Medicina Tropical Doutor Heitor Vieira Dourado (FMT-HVD)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kenya Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Manhiça Health Research Centre (CISM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will evaluate the safety, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy of ivermectin in scabies
      infected children weighing 5 to less than 15kg. This will allow future efforts to expand the
      indication of ivermectin treatment to infants weighing 5 to less than 15kg to treat numerous
      NTDs, allowing this young age group equitable access to the numerous benefits of ivermectin
      therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Scabies is a skin infestation caused by a mite called Sarcoptes scabiei. Scabies is
      characterised by a rash and severe itching, which is an allergic reaction to the eggs and
      feces the females deposit as they tunnel under the skin. Oral ivermectin is a very safe and
      beneficial drug which has been shown to be highly effective for the treatment of scabies and
      more than a dozen different neglected tropical diseases (NTDs), many of which are associated
      with important public health problems. Current label indications for ivermectin prevent use
      in small children weighing less than 15 kg, due to limited safety data in this group. Many of
      the NTD treatment options for small children rely on compounds that are less safe and/or
      efficacious compared to oral ivermectin. Our proposal will establish the safety and
      pharmacokinetics of escalating doses of ivermectin (200, 400, 800 µg/kg) to treat scabies
      infected children weighing 5 to less than 15 kg. The safety assessment will provide crucial
      evidence on the use of ivermectin for numerous diseases in children weighing 5 to less than
      15 kg. The information from measuring drug concentrations in the patients will inform the
      optimal dosing of this drug in small children. Assessment of the efficacy of ivermectin,
      compared to permethrin cream, for the treatment of scabies in small children can provide an
      important alternative treatment for this widespread disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The trial will initially randomize 30 participants at each site to receive control (permethrin cream), ivermectin 200 and 400 µg/kg (10:10:10) and review this data before escalation to ivermectin 800 µg/kg. Once the initial 30 participants have been treated a DSMB consultation will be performed for each site. If deemed safe to escalate to ivermectin 800 µg/kg, then remaining participants at each site will be treated with control (permethrin cream), ivermectin 200, 400, and 800 µg/kg (15: 15: 15: 25).
The Bangladesh site will initially randomize 30 participants receive control (permethrin cream) and ivermectin 200 µg/kg (15:15) and review this data before escalation to ivermectin 400 µg/kg. Once the initial 30 participants have been treated a DSMB consultation will be performed. If deemed safe to escalate to ivermectin 400 µg/kg, then remaining participants at the Bangladesh site will be treated with control (permethrin cream), ivermectin 200, 400 µg/kg (18: 18: 34).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>This is a double-blind trial so the participants, their parents, guardians or carers, administering clinicians, attending nurses, the central research team, and independent outcome assessors will all be blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing the occurrence of adverse events between the intervention (ivermectin) and control (permethrin) groups</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pruritus will be assessed through physical examination and via diary cards provided to the parents/carers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Population pharmacokinetic properties of ivermectin at escalating doses</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak plasma concentration (Tmax; hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Population pharmacokinetic properties of ivermectin at escalating doses</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Peak plasma concentration (Cmax; mg/L)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Population pharmacokinetic properties of ivermectin at escalating doses</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma drug concentration-time curve (AUC0-24; mg×h×L-1)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of oral ivermectin</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the reduction of dermatological manifestations by &quot;performing physical examination to quantify the number and size of scabies lesions on days 0, 7 and 14&quot; in the oral intervention (oral ivermectin) and control (permethrin cream) groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacogenomics of ivermectin</measure>
    <time_frame>day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Whole genome sequencing will be used to determine associations between pharmacogenetic variants with pharmacokinetic or pharmacodynamic parameters.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Scabies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Permethrin cream plus placebo tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ivermectin (200 µg/kg) plus placebo cream</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ivermectin (400 µg/kg) plus placebo cream</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ivermectin (800 µg/kg) plus placebo cream (except the Bangladesh site)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral ivermectin</intervention_name>
    <description>Ivermectin (Iver P®) 3 mg tablets are round, white, and scored on one side. Ivermentin 3mg tablets will be crushed and mixed thoroughly in 10mL of water.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Iver P®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Permethrin Cream</intervention_name>
    <description>permethrin cream 5% (Pioletal® Plus) is a white coloured lotion with a homogenous appearance and an odour of fennel and lavender.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pioletal® Plus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo tablets are round, white, scored on one side. There are no active substances in the placebo tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo cream</intervention_name>
    <description>A placebo cream is a white coloured lotion with a homogenous appearance and an odour of fennel and lavender but lacking the permethrin agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female child weighing 5 to &lt;15 kilograms

          -  ≥2 months old

          -  Scabies infestation

          -  Available to attend all study visits

          -  Parents/guardians/carers able to provide consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The participant may not enter the trial if ANY of the following apply:

          -  A history of renal or hepatic impairment.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder (e.g. moderate or severe malnutrition)
             which, in the opinion of the Investigator, may either put the participants at risk
             because of participation in the trial, or may influence the result of the trial, or
             the participant's ability to participate in the trial.

          -  Participants who have participated in another research trial involving an
             investigational product in the past 12 weeks.

          -  Children with Crusted/Norwegian scabies or severe secondary bacterial infections (e.g.
             sepsis)

          -  Children who have taken ivermectin or topical permethrin cream within the last month

          -  Children with known allergies to ivermectin or topical permethrin cream or excipients

          -  Loa loa infection risk, assessed based on travel history to endemic areas

          -  Use of prescription (especially CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers) or non-prescription
             drugs (except paracetamol at doses of up to 90 milligrams/kg/day), including vitamins
             (especially vitamin C), herbal and dietary supplements (including St. John's Wort)
             within 7 days (or 14 days if the drug is a potential enzyme inducer) or 5 times the
             drug half-life (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of study medication until
             the completion of the follow-up procedure, unless in the opinion of investigator, the
             medication will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise patient safety;
             the investigator will take advice from the manufacturer representative as necessary.

          -  The investigator, health care provider or study staff feel that the patient is not
             suitable for study participation due to chronic illness, suspected underlying illness,
             or concerns that the patient will adhere to follow-up schedule.

          -  Not previously enrolled into this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorenz von Seidlein, Ass.Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+66-(0)2-3549170</phone>
    <email>Lorenz@tropmedres.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kevin Kobylinski, phD</last_name>
    <phone>+66-(0)927298013</phone>
    <email>kobylinskikevin@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Scabies</keyword>
  <keyword>Ivermectin</keyword>
  <keyword>permethrin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Scabies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ivermectin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Permethrin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data collected for this study will be under the custodianship of MORU. With participant's consent, data from this study may be shared in a de-identified form with other groups or researchers in accordance with the MORU Data Sharing Policy.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>After completion of trial activities and reporting</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>MORU Data Sharing Policy. (http://www.tropmedres.ac/data-sharing-policy)</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

