<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04334577</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F20190717</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04334577</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study on Efficacy of Attenuated Zoster Vaccine, Live</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Efficacy of Attenuated Zoster Vaccine, Live From Herpes Zoster in Adults Aged 40 Years or older---a Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blinded,Placebo-controlled Trial Phase III</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Changchun BCHT Biotechnology Co.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Changchun BCHT Biotechnology Co.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Varicella-zoster virus (VZV) is a herpesvirus that causes two distinct clinical syndromes.
      Primary infection is manifested as varicella (chickenpox) , whereas reactivation of latent
      VZV results in a localized eruption known as herpes zoster. The investigational vaccine of
      this study is produced by Changchun BCHT biotechnology Co. It's a live attenuated herpes
      zoster vaccine based on the production process of live attenuated chickenpox vaccine.This
      study plans to have 25000 adults aged 40 years or older and involves in a randomized,
      double-blind, placebo-controlled trial . The primary outcome is to evaluate the efficacy of
      the vaccine against herpes zoster 30 days after vaccination and the safety of the vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of herpes zoster 30 days to 13 months after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days - 13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of herpes zoster diagnosed in participants 30 days to 13 months after vaccination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of herpes zoster after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>0 day-13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of herpes zoster diagnosed in participants after vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of laboratory-confirmed herpes zoster 30 days to 13 months after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days- 13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of laboratory-confirmed herpes zoster diagnosed in participants 30 days to 13 months after vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of solicited adverse reactions after the vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>within 14 days after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of solicited adverse reactions within 14 days after the vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of adverse reactions after the vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 42 days after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of adverse reactions within 42 days after the vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of severe adverse reactions after the vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>within 13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of severe adverse reactions within 13 months after the vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean titre of serum for antibody responses 42 days post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric mean titre of Serum for antibody responses at day 42 post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean fold increase of serum for antibody responses 42 days post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric mean fold increase of Serum for antibody responses at day 42 post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Four-fold increase rate of serum for antibody responses 42 days post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Four-fold increase rate of Serum for antibody responses at 42 day post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean titre of serum for antibody responses 6 months post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric mean titre of Serum for antibody responses at 6 months post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean fold increase of serum for antibody responses 6 months post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric mean fold increase of Serum for antibody responses at 6 months post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Four-fold increase rate of serum for antibody responses 6 months post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Four-fold increase rate of Serum for antibody responses at 6 months post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean titre of serum for antibody responses 13 months post-vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric mean titre of Serum for antibody responses at 13 months post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean fold increase of serum for antibody responses 13 months post-vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Geometric mean fold increase of Serum for antibody responses at 13 months post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Four-fold increase rate of serum for antibody responses 13 months post-vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Four-fold increase rate of Serum for antibody responses at 13 months post-vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of postherpetic neuralgia （PHN）30 days to 13 months after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days -13 months after the vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of postherpetic neuralgia （PHN）diagnosed 30 days to 13 months after vaccination</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25000</enrollment>
  <condition>Herpes Zoster</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Attenuated Zoster Vaccine, Live</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One shot of the vaccine (with live viruses titer &gt;=4.3 LgPFU per dose)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>one shot of placebo with no live virus</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>live attenuated zoster vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Attenuated Zoster Vaccine, Live</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  01 Healthy volunteers aged 40 years or older;

          -  02 Able to understand and give informed consent;.

          -  03 Able to comply with requirements of all clinical trial protocol for completing the
             study;

          -  04 Axillary temperature ≤37.0 at the time of enrollment;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  05 History of herpes zoster;

          -  06 History of vaccination against herpes zoster or varicella ;

          -  07 Allergic sensitivity to any of the components (including neomycin) in the study
             vaccine and a history of severe allergies to other vaccine;

          -  08 Premenopausal with positive pregnancy test, pregnant or lactating female, or female
             planning to become pregnant within 6 months;

          -  09 Subjects with congenital history of immunity deficiency (e.g., primary
             immunoglobulin deficiency, isolated IgA deficiency, etc.) or family history;

          -  10 Receipt of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the 5 months preceding
             of study vaccine or planning to receive these products during the study period;

          -  11 Immunosuppression resulting from disease,such as immunodeficiency, malignant tumor,
             HIV infection, organ and bone marrow transplantation, leukemia, lymphoma, Hodgkin's
             disease caused by low immunity; Receipt of immunosuppressive therapy with
             corticosteroids (except intermittent topical or inhaled corticosteroids [&lt; 800 g/ d
             Beclomethasone or equivalent]); Other immunosuppressive/cytotoxic treatments (cancer
             chemotherapy or organ transplantation);

          -  12 Subjects with acute infections (such as mumps, etc.), chronic infections in the
             acute phase (such as active untreated tuberculosis, etc.) or any advanced immune
             disease;

          -  13 Use of any investigational or non-registered product (drug, biological product or
             device) other than the study vaccine within 1 month before study vaccination , or
             planed use during the study period;

          -  14 Administration or planned administration of any other immunizations within 1 month
             before study vaccination or scheduled within the study period after study vaccination.

          -  15 Any non-local antiviral active treatment within 1 month prior to vaccination,
             including but not limited to acyclovir, famciclovir, valacyclovir and ganciclovir;

          -  16 Taking certain pharmaceuticals to be like salicylate kind, including aspirin, and
             diflunisal, or going to take these medicine during the study period.

          -  17 history of thrombocytopenia or coagulation disorders that may cause subcutaneous
             injection contraindications;

          -  18 significant diseases or significant underlying diseases (such as pulmonary heart
             disease, pulmonary edema, hypertension that cannot be effectively controlled with
             drugs [systolic blood pressure ≥160 mmHg, diastolic blood pressure ≥100 mmHg] that may
             interfere with or hinder the completion of the study, serious liver and kidney
             diseases, diabetes with concurrent symptoms, etc.);

          -  19 Various infectious, suppurative and allergic skin diseases;

          -  20 History of psychiatric and neurological disorders (e.g., depression, epilepsy or
             convulsion);

          -  21 Any other conditions may compromise the safety or availability of participants in
             the judgment of the investigator.(e.g., malleable psoriasis, chronic pain syndrome,
             cognitive impairment, severe hearing loss, and other conditions that may interfere
             with study evaluation).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Na Xu, Master</last_name>
    <phone>13596159728</phone>
    <email>xuna@bchtpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Xinyue Zhang, Master</last_name>
    <phone>13552207168</phone>
    <email>zhangxinyue@bchtpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jiangsu Province Center for Disease Control and Prevention</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210009</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhu Feng-cai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>86-25-83759418</phone>
      <email>jszfc@vip.sina.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhejiang Provincial Center for Disease Control and Prevention</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hanzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310051</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chen Zhiping, MD</last_name>
      <phone>86-13858051826</phone>
      <phone_ext>0571-87115091</phone_ext>
      <email>Zhpchen@cdc.zj.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Herpes Zoster</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

