<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04150757</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-10379</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04150757</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intranasal Ketamine For Pain Control In Patients With Sickle Cell Disease And Vaso-occlusive Episode (VOE) In The PED</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use Of Intranasal (IN) Ketamine For Pain Control In Patients With Sickle Cell Disease And Vaso-occlusive Episode (VOE) In The Pediatric Emergency Department</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abigail Nixon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a descriptive cohort study of intranasal ketamine as the initial analgesic for
      children with sickle cell disease who present to the pediatric emergency department with
      vaso-occlusive crisis and are awaiting intravenous line placement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a prospective observational cohort involving patients 3 to 25 years of age who
      present to the Pediatric Emergency Department (PED) at Jacobi Medical Center with
      vaso-occlusive episode (VOE) in moderate-severe pain (FACES or numeric rating scale ≥5) as
      determined at triage. Currently, the standard of treatment for VOE at our institution is
      intravenous (IV) line placement and IV opioid analgesia. The patient will receive intranasal
      (IN) Ketamine as the first parental analgesic, so as to provide more immediate pain relief
      while they wait for IV placement and IV analgesia, for opioid pain control, which is
      currently the standard of care at our institution. The primary objective of this study is to
      describe the analgesic effect of IN ketamine in treating moderate-to-severe pain due to VOE
      in the pediatric ED as measured by a pain scale rating at various time intervals following
      administration. Secondary objectives are to describe the effect of IN ketamine on the need
      for additional doses of opioid medications, patient satisfaction and disposition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Enrolled patients will receive one dose of Intranasal Ketamine dosed at 1mg/kg (Ketamine 500mg/10 mL solution) after triage while waiting for IV placement (max 50mg). This is an observational study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients and treating providers will be aware of the medication administration.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score Using Wong Baker/FACES (age&lt;11yr)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain rating from baseline to 30 minutes after initial administration of Ketamine. Pain assessments will be made using the Wong Baker FACES scale for children aged 10 years and younger. The Wong Baker/FACES scale is scored in multiples of 2 (each associated with a facial reaction), starting from a minimum of 0 to a maximum of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score Using Numeric Rating Scale (age&gt;11yr)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain rating from baseline to 30 minutes after initial administration of Ketamine. For patients 11 yrs and older, pain will be assessed using the Numeric Rating Scale, which is a scale from a minimum of 0 to a maximum of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score Using Wong Baker/FACES (age&lt;11yr)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain rating from baseline to 15 minutes after initial administration of Ketamine. Pain assessments will be made using the Wong Baker FACES scale for children aged 10 years and younger. The Wong Baker/FACES scale is scored in multiples of 2 (each associated with a facial reaction), starting from a minimum of 0 to a maximum of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score Using a Numeric Rating Scale (age&gt;11yr)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain rating from baseline to 15 minutes after initial administration of Ketamine. For patients older than 11 years and older, pain will be assessed using the Numeric Rating Scale, which is a scale from a minimum of 0 to a maximum of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score Using Wong Baker/FACES (age&lt;11yr)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain rating from baseline to 60 minutes after initial administration of Ketamine. Pain assessments will be made using the Wong Baker FACES scale for children aged 10 years and younger. The Wong Baker/FACES scale is scored in multiples of 2 (each associated with a facial reaction), starting from a minimum of 0 to a maximum of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score Using a Numeric Rating Scale (age&gt;11yr)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain rating from baseline to 60 minutes after initial administration of Ketamine. For patients 11 years and older, pain will be assessed using the Numeric Rating Scale, which is a scale from a minimum of 0 to a maximum of 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional Opiate Medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of ED visit, an average of 5 hrs</time_frame>
    <description>Number of opiate analgesic doses and a comparison of opiate equivalents/kilogram versus mean dose for prior visits (if the patient has been seen for VOE prior)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>At patient disposition, an average of 5 hrs</time_frame>
    <description>Patient/Parent satisfaction based on questionnaire. Patients will answer based on a 4 point scale (not happy at all/a little happy/happy&amp;satisfied/very happy)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Admission</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of ED visit, an average of 5 hrs</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients within each group who are admitted (vs discharged)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Return Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients within each group who have a return visit documented in the electronic medical record within 1 week of the ER visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <condition>Vaso-Occlusive Pain Episode in Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <condition>Vaso-occlusive Crisis</condition>
  <condition>Ketamine</condition>
  <condition>Intranasal Ketamine</condition>
  <condition>Analgesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving &quot;no intervention&quot; will receive no intranasal ketamine while awaiting intravenous line placement for parenteral pain control.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal Ketamine + Standard Analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Enrolled patients will receive one dose of Intranasal Ketamine dosed at 1mg/kg (Ketamine 500mg/10 mL solution) after triage while waiting for IV placement (max 50mg).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intranasal ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with vaso-occlusive episode and sickle cell disease in moderate to severe pain determined at triage will receive intranasal ketamine while awaiting IV placement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal Ketamine + Standard Analgesia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  History of Hemoglobin SS or SC disease

          -  Age 3 years old to 25 years old presenting to the PED with vaso-occlusive with
             moderate-severe pain determined at triage as pain score (FACES or numeric rating
             scale) ≥ 5

          -  Parent or patient willing to provide consent/assent

          -  English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with concern for more severe complications including acute chest, splenic
             sequestration, sepsis, stroke, non-VOC pain, asthma exacerbation

          -  Allergy to ketamine

          -  GCS&lt;15

          -  Obstructive nasal anatomy as per parent history

          -  History of a psychiatric disorder

          -  Pregnant patients will be excluded. Female patients &gt; 12 years old are routinely
             tested for pregnancy in our PED. Patients found to be pregnant will not be enrolled in
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jacobi Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abigail Nixon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-918-5875</phone>
      <email>abigail.nixon@nychhc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Miller Mantell, DO</last_name>
      <phone>718-918-5875</phone>
      <email>millerj18@nychhc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Abigail Nixon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

