<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04150861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000152</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04150861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rekovelle PK Trial in Chinese Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Trial Investigating the Pharmacokinetics of FE 999049 Given as a Single Subcutaneous Dose in Gonadotropin Down-regulated Healthy Chinese Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ferring Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ferring Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      FE 999049 is a gonadotropin preparation containing recombinant human follicle stimulating
      hormone (rhFSH) under development by Ferring Pharmaceuticals for controlled ovarian
      stimulation for the development of multiple follicles in women undergoing assisted
      reproductive technologies (ART) such as in vitro fertilisation (IVF) or intracytoplasmic
      sperm injection (ICSI) cycle. In previous trials the exposure to and dose proportionality of
      FE 999049 in a clinically relevant dose range in Caucasian and Japanese healthy women have
      been shown to be very similar. This is a trial in healthy Chinese women investigating the
      pharmacokinetics, safety, and tolerability of a single subcutaneous dose of FE 999049.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 16, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the serum concentration-time curve from dosing to infinity (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the serum concentration-time curve from dosing up to time t (AUCt)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
    <description>AUCt is defined as the area under the serum concentration-time curve from dosing up to time t, where t is the last time point at which the concentration is above the lower limit of quantification.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum serum concentration observed (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of maximum observed serum concentration (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent total systemic clearance (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent volume of distribution associated with the terminal phase (VZ/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination half-life (t½)</measure>
    <time_frame>At predose (-1, -0.5 and 0 hour) and at 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32, 36, 40, 48 hours, and 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 days postdose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal changes in electrocardiogram (ECG)</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening (Day -63 to Day -29) up to follow up (up to Day 11)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormal changes in ECG will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening (Day -63 to Day -29) up to follow up (up to Day 11)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormal vital signs (systemic blood pressures, heart rate and body temperature) will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening (Day -63 to Day -29) up to follow up (up to Day 11)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormal findings in laboratory parameters (clinical chemistry, hematology, and urinalysis) will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs) and type of AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening (Day -63 to Day -29) up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical occurrence in a participant participating in a clinical trial. Number of participants with any AE (serious or non-serious) and type of AEs will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Injection Site Reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours after administration of IMP</time_frame>
    <description>The injection site reactions (redness, pain, itching, swelling, and bruising) will be assessed by the investigator after injection, 30 minutes, and 24 hours after administration of the investigational medicinal product (IMP). Each injection site reaction will be assessed as none, mild, moderate, or severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-induced anti-follicle-stimulating hormone (anti-FSH) antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Follitropin delta 12 μg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received single subcutaneous abdominal injection of Follitropin delta 12 μg on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Follitropin delta 18 μg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received single subcutaneous abdominal injection of Follitropin delta 18 μg on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Follitropin delta 24 μg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received single subcutaneous abdominal injection of Follitropin delta 24 μg on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Follitropin Delta</intervention_name>
    <description>Solution for Injection, subcutaneous administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Follitropin delta 12 μg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Follitropin delta 18 μg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Follitropin delta 24 μg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>REKOVELLE</other_name>
    <other_name>FE 999049</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female of Chinese origin, with two ethnic Chinese parents and four ethnic Chinese
             grandparents 21-40 years of age (both inclusive)

          -  Willing to stop using combined oral contraceptives (COC) in relation to the first
             DECAPEPTYL Depot administration on Day -28

          -  Agrees to use a double barrier method of contraception between Day -63 and Day 28, if
             not abstinent. A double barrier method of contraception should also be used after Day
             28 until menses resumes or until another contraceptive method has been established

          -  Normal menstrual cycles with a range of 24-35 days in the absence of oral
             contraceptives

          -  Serum FSH less than equal to (≤)5 IU/L on Day -3 and Day -1

          -  Body mass index (BMI) of 18.5 -25 kg/m^2 (both inclusive)

          -  Negative serology for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody, hepatitis B
             (surface antigen), hepatitis C antibody, and syphilis bacteria

          -  Healthy according to medical history, physical examination, gynaecological
             examination, ECG, blood pressure, and laboratory profile of blood and urine

          -  Negative urine drug screen and alcohol breath test at screening and on Day -1

          -  Non-smoker or light smoker (≤ 5 cigarettes/day) for at least 6 months prior to trial

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence or a history of clinically significant diseases of the renal, hepatic,
             gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, or musculoskeletal systems, or presence or history
             of clinically significant reproductive, psychiatric, immunological, endocrine or
             metabolic diseases

          -  Cancer within the last 5 years except for adequately managed basal cell carcinoma and
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Current or a history of endocrine abnormalities such as hyperprolactinaemia,
             polycystic ovary syndrome or other ovarian dysfunction, tumours of the pituitary gland
             or hypothalamus, thyroid or adrenal disease

          -  Clinically significant findings on the trans-vaginal ultrasound, cytology,
             gynaecological or breast examination at screening or on Day -1 including ovarian cysts
             or tumours of the ovaries or uterus

          -  Contraindications for the use of gonadotropins and gonadotropin-releasing hormone
             (GnRH) agonists

          -  Previously treated with gonadotropins within the last 6 months prior to screening

          -  History within the last two years or current abuse of alcohol or drugs

          -  Presence or history of severe allergy or anaphylactic reactions

          -  Intake of prescribed medication, over-the-counter (OTC) medication, or herbal
             medicines, with the exceptions of COC, cromoglycate, and paracetamol according to the
             labelling, within 2 weeks or 5 half-lives of the drug, whichever is longer, prior to
             first dose of DECAPEPTYL Depot. Topical treatments of bacterial or fungal infection
             are allowed if stopped before first dose of IMP

          -  Intake of any non-registered investigational drug within the last 12 weeks preceding
             screening, or longer if judged by the investigator to possibly influence the outcome
             of the current trial

          -  High daily consumption of caffeine-containing beverages (e.g. more than five cups of
             coffee or equivalent) with a risk of withdrawal symptoms arising during the trial that
             may confound the safety evaluation

          -  Blood donation or major blood loss (greater than equal to [≥]500 mL) within the last 8
             weeks, or plasma donation with the last 4 weeks preceding the first day of IMP dosing

          -  Current non-smokers or light smoker with a history of long-term, heavy smoking (&gt;10
             pack-years)

          -  Previously dosed in this trial

          -  Mental incapacity or language barrier precluding adequate understanding or
             co-operation

          -  Considered by the investigator to be unsuitable to participate in the trial for any
             other reason
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Global Clinical Compliance</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ferring Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First Hospital Affiliated to Nanjing Medical University Jiangsu Province Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>In vitro fertilisation</keyword>
  <keyword>Controlled ovarian stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Follicle Stimulating Hormone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

