<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04154891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C16-110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-A00680-55</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04154891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genome Sequencing Strategies for Genetics Diagnosis of Patients With Intellectual Disability</brief_title>
  <acronym>DEFIDIAG</acronym>
  <official_title>Etude Pilote Des différentes stratégies de séquençage Haut débit du génome Pour le Diagnostic génétique Des Patients Atteints de déficience Intellectuelle</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Commissariat à l'énergie atomique et aux énergies alternatives</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Dijon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Rouen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Strasbourg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>APHP</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction : Intellectual Disability (ID) is the most common cause of referral in the
      pediatric genetic centers and is characterized by an extreme genetic heterogeneity
      corresponding to a myriad of rare diseases that complicates the identification of ID's.

      Overall today in France, for non-syndromic ID affected patients, the Fra-X detection, the
      chromosomal microarray analysis and Gene Panel Strategy of 44 ID selected genes leads to a
      global diagnostic yield for 1/3 patients leaving 2/3 of patients still with no diagnosis.

      The advent, and burst, of Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) technologies has clearly
      revolutionized the approaches to diagnosis and research in the field of rare diseases at an
      international. That's why the main hypothesis of DEFIDIAG is that Whole Genome Sequencing
      (WGS) could allow to improve the diagnostic performance and cost-effectiveness for French
      patients with ID.

      Objective : The main objective of this study is to compare ther percentage of genetic causal
      diagnosis identified in ID patients by performing trio WGS analysis vs the use of the current
      French reference strategy (ACPA, X-Fra, DI 44).

      Methods and design : This is a prospective study. The investigators expect to include 1275
      index case with his/her 2 biological unaffected parents.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective multicenter diagnostic study comparing the percentage of Intellectual Deficiency (ID) causal diagnosis obtained using 2 main different strategies (Whole Genome Sequencing using a trio strategy (WGST), and reference strategy) applied blindly to consecutive patients with no obvious diagnosis. Each included patient will be his own control; he will benefit from the two main strategies compared, in parallel. The diagnostic yield of Whole Genome Sequencing using a simplex strategy (WGSs) will be also investigated in parallel to the two main strategies but only in a randomized subgroup of the overall population coming for a first genetic advice.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The results of the different strategies will be interpreted blindly, each participating laboratory being in charge for a given investigation center, either of 1) the trio or 2) the 44GPS (part of the reference strategy) and, for the randomized sub-population of the overall population coming for a first genetic advice, simplex analyses. Fra-X and chromosomal microarray analysis corresponding to the reference strategy will follow the routine circuit, which is mainly independent from the WGS circuit.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic Yield</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary study endpoint is the identification of a causal diagnosis of ID defined as the identification of one class 4 or 5 variant (or two in case of autosomal recessive inheritance) that explains the symptoms presented by the patient. In addition variants classified as 3+, anticipated to become future 4 will be recorded. Specific analysis and follow up of the variant classified as 3+ (i.e. with a high probability of pathogenicity) will be done after the end of the protocol to determine the class 3+ to class 4-5 switch proportion and to describe the new genes/mechanisms involved in ID and revealed by DEFIDIAG.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Causal structural change</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of causal structural changes (CNV, translocation, inversion) in the first investigation population (confirmed during the MDM for the WGS strategies)
The clinical characteristics of patients and the diagnostic yield at each step of the incremental selection within WGS analyses (44GPS, OMIMOME, WES, WGS) according to the results of the preceding step as well as according to the results of chromosomal microarray analysis and 44GPS will also be parameters of interest in the whole population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incremental cost-effectiveness ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The cost-effectiveness endpoint will be an efficiency criterion based on the estimation of an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio, expressed in terms of cost per additional positive diagnosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean cost of wavering diagnostic research</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimation of the cost of wavering diagnostic research</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of at least one modification in medical, medico-social, rehabilitative and psychological follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and type of secondary data</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number and type of SFs (class 4 or 5 mutation(s)) identified in the parents that specifically consent to this study will be recorded in a specific report. The outcome will be defined by the percentage of SFs in the studied population and the number and type of medical consequences following their identification.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median time and type of skills required for analyzing genetic data and for genetic confirmation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median time to obtain results</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3825</enrollment>
  <condition>Intellectual Disability</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trio Whole Genome Sequencing</intervention_name>
    <description>WGS trio analysis will be performed using the genome data of the index case in addition to the genome data of his parents. This analysis will follow a consensus protocol that contains 3 obligatory steps: first of all, de novo variants (SNV, CNV and others SV) will be examined in the whole genome data set; then, a SNV/CNV/other SV analysis will be performed under a AR or X linked Mendelian mode hypothesis in the whole genomic regions of a OMIM extended list (that contains all genes already involved in human genetic diseases). Finally, analysis will focus on inherited pathogenic variants under an AD mode hypothesis (analysis of variations already reported as pathogenic in clinVar or HGMD pro; CNV or truncating variation in OMIM genes, etc). When these 3 steps analysis is completed then variants of interest identified at each step will be recorded until examination by a specific multidisciplinary meeting.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simplex Whole Genome Sequencing</intervention_name>
    <description>This analysis will be performed using only the index case following a similar strategy than the one used for the WGS trio</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Current French Reference strategy</intervention_name>
    <description>Actual ANPGM recommendations defined by the following analysis: Fra-X + chromosomal microarray analysis + 44GPS</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Inclusion criteria for children or adults with ID of unknown etiology (index case)

             In order to be eligible to participate in this study, an individual must meet all the
             following criteria:

               -  Age:

                    1. Between 0 and 5 years with stringent criteria (severe delayed development in
                       terms of motor skills, language, and/or sociability) OR

                    2. ≥ 6 years: patients with ID, whatever the severity (but with proven ID by ad
                       hoc neuropsychological testing) and the associated manifestations

               -  Without any obvious diagnosis identified during a genetic consultation in one of
                  the participating center (i.e., an obvious syndrome with ID with well-known
                  molecular diagnosis is excluded);

               -  Provision of signed and dated of &quot;participant&quot; consent form;

               -  Stated willingness to comply with all study procedures and availability for the
                  duration of the study.

             Patient with a social security in compliance with the French law (Provisions relating
             to research involving the human person provided for in Articles L 1121-1 et seq. of
             the French Public Health Code).

          2. Inclusion criteria for biological parents

             - Provision of signed and dated of both parents consent form.

          3. Non-inclusion criteria

               -  An individual, who presents any condition which in the investigator's opinion
                  makes it undesirable for the subject to participate in the trial or which would
                  jeopardize compliance with the protocol, will not be eligible;

               -  Patients with isolated learning disabilities;

               -  One or both parents with ID;

               -  Parent placed under judicial protection (tutelle, curatelle et sauvegarde de
                  justice) ;

               -  Patient with a known etiological diagnosis (non-genetic, previously proven Fra-X
                  syndrome, know chromosomal anomaly, known pathogenic or probably pathogenic
                  variant identified in an ID gene by any technique).

               -  For patient concerning by biobank project: hypersensitivity to local anesthesia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hélène DOLLFUS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hélène ESPEROU</last_name>
    <phone>+33 1 44 23 67 00</phone>
    <email>C16-110.isp@inserm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Didier LACOMBE</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospices Civil de Lyon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick EDERY</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Dijon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurence FAIVRE</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHRU Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roseline CAUMES</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance publique - Hôpitaux de Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicole PHILIP</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Montpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David GENEVIEVE</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Nantes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bertrand ISIDOR</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance publique - Hôpitaux de Paris - Groupe Hospitalier Pitié Salpétrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Delphine HERON</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance publique - Hôpitaux de Paris - Hôpital Necker - Enfants malades</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stanislas LYONNET</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Rennes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sylvie ODENT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Rouen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gael NICOLAS</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Strasbourg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helene DOLLFUS</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rare disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Next generation sequencing genome</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic study</keyword>
  <keyword>Medico-economic study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intellectual Disability</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

