<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04158544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-101-0125</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04158544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Monitoring in Metastatic Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immune Monitoring During Systemic Therapy of Metastatic Malignant Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Regensburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Regensburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The mean survival time in the advanced tumor stage in the presence of distant metastases in
      malignant melanoma was less than 9 months until a few years ago. Intensive research efforts
      have led to the development of promising new therapeutic strategies and their clinical
      application. These include on the one hand mutation-specific inhibitors of important for cell
      division serine-threonine kinase BRAF such as vemurafenib, dabrafenib and encorafenib and
      inhibitors of the downstream target protein, the mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase
      (MEK), such as trametinib, binimetinib and cobimetinib.

      The group of immunotherapeutics is a second new class of drugs, in which great hope for the
      treatment of metastatic melanoma is placed. Antibody-mediated blockage of surface molecules
      expressed on immune cells, referred to as immune checkpoints, results in activation of the
      immune system. As a result, an anti-tumor immune response is triggered, which has led to
      considerable therapeutic success in metastatic melanoma. To date, three checkpoint inhibitors
      have been approved for the treatment of metastatic melanoma. Ipilimumab is an antibody that
      binds cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen 4 (CTLA-4); Pembrolizumab and nivolumab cause
      immune stimulation by binding the Programmed Death Receptor (PD1).

      However, the impact of the therapy on the immune system as a whole is largely unknown. A
      comprehensive understanding of these effects is crucial to be able to further develop the
      therapy and to evaluate useful combination therapies with other immunomodulatory agents.

      Within the framework of this project changes of the immune response under a systemic therapy
      of the malignant melanoma are to be characterized. The material for the analysis comes from
      blood samples collected during routine patient check-ups.

      The aim of the analyzes is to precisely characterize the effects of the different
      therapeutics on the function of the immune system. In particular, the study will investigate
      whether certain therapeutic agents can weaken or activate the immune system and thus, in
      addition to the direct effect on the tumor cells, mediate indirect therapeutic effects via
      immune modulation. In the long term, the investigators want to use the knowledge gained to
      further improve the already existing therapeutic strategies of malignant melanoma by
      additional modulation of the immune system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite recent breakthroughs in the treatment of melanoma, the prognosis in the advanced
      stage of the disease continues to be very poor. 45-50% of all melanomas carry a point
      mutation in codon 600 of the BRAF gene encoding a serine-threonine kinase. The two most
      common BRAF mutations (V600E and V600K) constitutively activate the MAP kinase signaling
      pathway that drives the proliferation and survival of cancer cells. Specific BRAF V600
      inhibitors such as vemurafenib, dabrafenib and encorafenib and inhibitors of the downstream
      target MEK such as trametinib, binimetinib and cobimetinib are very effective regimens in
      BRAF-positive metastatic melanoma.

      Recent studies have shown that these inhibitors in addition to the effects on the tumor cells
      also have an influence on cells of the immune system. For example, vemurafenib leads to a
      loss of peripheral blood lymphocytes. Thus, the number of peripheral CD4 + positive cells
      decreases with vemurafenib therapy, while the number of natural killer cells (NK cells)
      increases. On the other hand, initial studies show that B cells and CD8 + positive cells are
      not affected numerically by vemurafenib. It has been demonstrated that vemurafenib but not
      dabrafenib reduces the number of peripheral lymphocytes in melanoma patients and changes the
      function and phenotype of CD4 + positive cells, although both drugs show comparable clinical
      efficacy. Selective inhibition of BRAF by inhibitors such as vemurafenib or dabrafenib thus
      has a significant influence on the peripheral lymphocyte populations of melanoma patients.
      Studies have been demonstrated that inhibition of BRAF can induce increased invasion of
      tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes into melanoma metastases. Tumor infiltration of CD4 + and CD8
      + positive lymphocytes is surprisingly enhanced by therapy with a BRAF inhibitor.
      Furthermore, it could be shown in this study that the number of immunoreactive cells
      correlated with a reduction in tumor size and an increased necrosis in the tumor areas. The
      data obtained so far suggest that treatment with BRAF inhibitors increases melanoma antigen
      expression and thus facilitates T cell cytotoxicity. This results in a more favorable tumor
      microenvironment for a synergistic BRAF-targeted therapy and immunotherapy. This therapeutic
      strategy is currently being evaluated in clinical trials.

      The group of immunotherapeutics is a second new class of drugs, in which great hope for the
      treatment of metastatic melanoma is placed. Ipilimumab is an antibody that binds the
      cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen 4 (CTLA-4), thereby stimulating T-cell activation
      and proliferation. The drug has been approved for the treatment of metastatic melanoma since
      July 2011 and significantly increases survival in some patients. In addition, at the end of
      2015, a monoclonal antibody directed against the Programmed Death Receptor (PD1) was approved
      by the European Medicines Commission for the treatment of unresectable or metastatic
      melanoma. PD1 is a receptor that is expressed on T cells and inhibits T cell activation upon
      binding of a ligand. Study results have shown that blocking this T-cell inhibition with PD1
      or PD-L1 antagonists is a very effective therapeutic strategy for melanoma and other tumor
      entities.

      Current data show that targeted therapy has a major impact on the tumor microenvironment and
      on the regulatory and effector cells of the immune system. However, the impact of the therapy
      on the immune system as a whole is largely unknown. A comprehensive understanding of these
      effects is crucial to be able to further develop the therapy and to evaluate useful
      combination therapies with other immunomodulatory agents.

      In the context of this study, the immune status, e.g. the number and the activation state of
      different immune cells at the beginning and in the course of a systemic therapy for
      metastatic melanoma should be determined. For this purpose, 10 ml of EDTA blood is taken as
      part of the guideline-compliant routine care (The blood samples taken in the study are given
      every 4 weeks for therapy with kinase inhibitors and every 2 weeks for therapy with
      checkpoint inhibitors). The blood samples taken before and during therapy will be analyzed by
      flow cytometry and the changes in the immunophenotype will be correlated with the response to
      therapy. In this way, the investigator want to identify both predictive and prognostic
      markers. The assessment of the immune status should help to optimize the effectiveness of
      melanoma therapy. Therefore, it would be important to identify suitable markers and to
      characterize subgroups of immune cells that have an impact on the tumor microenvironment.

      The evaluation of the immune status in melanoma patients could thus be incorporated into the
      treatment strategies in the future in order to combine a targeted therapy with
      immunomodulating substances or also from enriched sub-populations of immune cells in order to
      increase the effectiveness of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in frequency of peripheral immune cell populations assessed by immune monitoring through flow cytometry (ONE study FACS panel)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before start of treatment, 3 and 6 weeks after start of treatment as well as through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>As part of the course of therapy during routine check-up, blood samples are collected and then analyzed by flow cytometry (ONE study panel). Frequency of surface antigens of PBMC are analyzed and the characterized sub-populations are monitored during the follow-up. Thereby, changes in frequency of surface antigens will be assessed compared to baseline (before start of treatment). This allows to determine the individual immunophenotype of a patient.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in activation status of peripheral immune cell populations assessed by immune monitoring through flow cytometry (ONE study FACS panel)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before start of treatment, 3 and 6 weeks after start of treatment as well as through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>As part of the course of therapy during routine check-up, blood samples are collected and then analyzed by flow cytometry (ONE study panel). Expression level of surface antigens of PBMC are analyzed and the characterized sub-populations are monitored during the follow-up. Thereby, changes in expression level of surface antigens will be assessed compared to baseline (before start of treatment). This allows to determine the individual immunophenotype of a patient.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver inflammation (ALT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before start of treatment, 3 and 6 weeks after start of treatment as well as through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Screening for liver inflammation (serum ALT U/l)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver inflammation (AST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before start of treatment, 3 and 6 weeks after start of treatment as well as through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Screening for liver inflammation (serum AST U/l)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Checkpoint Inhibitors</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with metastatic melanoma receiving systemic therapy with checkpoint inhibitors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kinase Inhibitors</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with metastatic melanoma receiving systemic therapy with kinase inhibitors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      blood samples (10ml EDTA)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with metastatic melanoma of all ages and both sexes will be screened for inclusion
        if they qualify for systemic therapy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of metastatic melanoma expecting treatment with immune or targeted therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward K Geissler, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dept. of Exp. Surgery, University Hospital Regensburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sebastian Haferkamp</last_name>
    <phone>+499419440</phone>
    <email>Sebastian.Haferkamp@klinik.uni-regensburg.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept. of Dermatology; Univeristy Hospital Regensburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regensburg</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>93053</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sebastian Haferkamp, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+499419440</phone>
      <email>Sebastian.Haferkamp@klinik.uni-regensburg.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapman PB, Hauschild A, Robert C, Haanen JB, Ascierto P, Larkin J, Dummer R, Garbe C, Testori A, Maio M, Hogg D, Lorigan P, Lebbe C, Jouary T, Schadendorf D, Ribas A, O'Day SJ, Sosman JA, Kirkwood JM, Eggermont AM, Dreno B, Nolop K, Li J, Nelson B, Hou J, Lee RJ, Flaherty KT, McArthur GA; BRIM-3 Study Group. Improved survival with vemurafenib in melanoma with BRAF V600E mutation. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jun 30;364(26):2507-16. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1103782. Epub 2011 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21639808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Board RE, Ellison G, Orr MC, Kemsley KR, McWalter G, Blockley LY, Dearden SP, Morris C, Ranson M, Cantarini MV, Dive C, Hughes A. Detection of BRAF mutations in the tumour and serum of patients enrolled in the AZD6244 (ARRY-142886) advanced melanoma phase II study. Br J Cancer. 2009 Nov 17;101(10):1724-30. doi: 10.1038/sj.bjc.6605371. Epub 2009 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19861964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schilling B, Paschen A. Immunological consequences of selective BRAF inhibitors in malignant melanoma: Neutralization of myeloid-derived suppressor cells. Oncoimmunology. 2013 Aug 1;2(8):e25218. Epub 2013 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24167759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schilling B, Sucker A, Griewank K, Zhao F, Weide B, Görgens A, Giebel B, Schadendorf D, Paschen A. Vemurafenib reverses immunosuppression by myeloid derived suppressor cells. Int J Cancer. 2013 Oct 1;133(7):1653-63. doi: 10.1002/ijc.28168. Epub 2013 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23526263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schilling B, Sondermann W, Zhao F, Griewank KG, Livingstone E, Sucker A, Zelba H, Weide B, Trefzer U, Wilhelm T, Loquai C, Berking C, Hassel J, Kähler KC, Utikal J, Al Ghazal P, Gutzmer R, Goldinger SM, Zimmer L, Paschen A, Hillen U, Schadendorf D; DeCOG. Differential influence of vemurafenib and dabrafenib on patients' lymphocytes despite similar clinical efficacy in melanoma. Ann Oncol. 2014 Mar;25(3):747-753. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdt587. Epub 2014 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24504444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilmott JS, Long GV, Howle JR, Haydu LE, Sharma RN, Thompson JF, Kefford RF, Hersey P, Scolyer RA. Selective BRAF inhibitors induce marked T-cell infiltration into human metastatic melanoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2012 Mar 1;18(5):1386-94. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-2479. Epub 2011 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22156613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frederick DT, Piris A, Cogdill AP, Cooper ZA, Lezcano C, Ferrone CR, Mitra D, Boni A, Newton LP, Liu C, Peng W, Sullivan RJ, Lawrence DP, Hodi FS, Overwijk WW, Lizée G, Murphy GF, Hwu P, Flaherty KT, Fisher DE, Wargo JA. BRAF inhibition is associated with enhanced melanoma antigen expression and a more favorable tumor microenvironment in patients with metastatic melanoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2013 Mar 1;19(5):1225-31. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-12-1630. Epub 2013 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23307859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robert C, Ribas A, Wolchok JD, Hodi FS, Hamid O, Kefford R, Weber JS, Joshua AM, Hwu WJ, Gangadhar TC, Patnaik A, Dronca R, Zarour H, Joseph RW, Boasberg P, Chmielowski B, Mateus C, Postow MA, Gergich K, Elassaiss-Schaap J, Li XN, Iannone R, Ebbinghaus SW, Kang SP, Daud A. Anti-programmed-death-receptor-1 treatment with pembrolizumab in ipilimumab-refractory advanced melanoma: a randomised dose-comparison cohort of a phase 1 trial. Lancet. 2014 Sep 20;384(9948):1109-17. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60958-2. Epub 2014 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25034862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merelli B, Massi D, Cattaneo L, Mandalà M. Targeting the PD1/PD-L1 axis in melanoma: biological rationale, clinical challenges and opportunities. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol. 2014 Jan;89(1):140-65. doi: 10.1016/j.critrevonc.2013.08.002. Epub 2013 Aug 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24029602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Streitz M, Miloud T, Kapinsky M, Reed MR, Magari R, Geissler EK, Hutchinson JA, Vogt K, Schlickeiser S, Kverneland AH, Meisel C, Volk HD, Sawitzki B. Standardization of whole blood immune phenotype monitoring for clinical trials: panels and methods from the ONE study. Transplant Res. 2013 Oct 25;2(1):17. doi: 10.1186/2047-1440-2-17.</citation>
    <PMID>24160259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Regensburg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Edward Geissler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Experimental Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immune monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

