<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04155788</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB# 17.1288</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04155788</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Conquering Feared Foods Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>CFF</acronym>
  <official_title>Food Exposure Therapy in Individuals With or Without Eating Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Louisville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Louisville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to use ecological momentary assessment (EMA) data and
      physiological data to asses a client's eating disorder symptoms and behaviors before and
      after a meal with a feared food. The investigators are conducting a pilot clinical
      measurement study. Participants will be screened for eating disorder symptoms via a
      structured clinical interview. Participants with or without eating disorders will also
      complete self-reported measures of eating disorder symptoms and anxiety. Participants with
      eating disorders will complete assessments on their phone and will wear a sensor band to
      assess heart rate and galvanic skin response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Exposure therapy has been used in the treatment of Anorexia Nervosa (AN), as seen in mirror
      exposure to address body image and anxiety, as well as food exposure to address avoidant
      eating behavior. In food exposure therapy, individuals are exposed to feared foods in a
      clinical and/or non-clinical setting. Food exposure therapy has been effective in alleviating
      some anxiety in individuals with eating disorder behaviors and symptoms. However, the
      investigators do not yet know what characteristics predict response in food exposure therapy.
      The purpose of this study is to use EMA data and physiological data to asses a client's
      eating disorder symptoms and behaviors before and after a meal with a feared food.

      Lastly, the study would like to utilize individuals who do not meet criteria for an eating
      disorder (ED) and will act as controls in this study to address the research question: is
      there a difference between individuals with EDs and without EDs as they complete the entirety
      of the study, specifically in regards to physiological data? These controls will not complete
      the EMA data aspect of the study.

      The investigators are conducting a pilot clinical measurement study. Participants will be
      screened for eating disorder symptoms via a structured clinical interview or determined to
      not have eating disorder symptoms and will act as controls in the study. Both groups will
      also complete self-reported measures of eating disorder symptoms and anxiety. Participants
      will also complete assessments on their phone and will wear a sensor band to assess heart
      rate and galvanic skin response. However, control participants will not complete assessments
      on their phone. Both groups will wear the health-sensor band to assess heart rate and
      galvanic skin response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 9, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 9, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self Reported Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in Subjective Units of Distress Scale (SUDS) Ratings. The SUDS measures subjective units of distress on a scale from 0-100 where 0 indicates no anxiety and 100 indicates the most anxiety one has ever felt or could imagine feeling.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physiological Data</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in heart rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants' self-reported Safety Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in behaviors done to alleviate anxiety as reported via open-ended questions about mealtimes. Prior to the study, participants are provided a brief training to understand common safety behaviors in eating disorders. Then, throughout the food exposure, they are periodically asked to identify any safety behaviors they are currently engaging in.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating Disorder Symptoms &amp; Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in eating disordered symptoms and behaviors will be measured using a meal measure which identifies strategies used to avoid feelings of anxiety during meals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Eating Disorder Symptom</condition>
  <condition>Fear</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Food Exposure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Food Exposure</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will complete a meal exposure using one of their feared foods.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Food Exposure</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be between the ages of 13-65, must meet criteria for a current
             diagnosis of anorexia nervosa or bulimia nervosa.

          -  Must be local to the Louisville area or able to travel to the study location for the
             two lab sessions.

          -  For participants to be in the control group, participants must be between the ages of
             13-65.

          -  Must be local to the Louisville area or able to travel to the study location for the
             two lab sessions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who are younger than 13 or older than 65 at the time of enrollment.

          -  Participants who are not local or can not travel to the Louisville area for the two
             therapy sessions.

          -  We will also exclude anyone who is actively suicidal (e.g., has a suicide plan),
             psychotic, or manic.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cheri A Levinson, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(502) 852-7710</phone>
    <email>cheri.levinson@louisville.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Samantha P Spoor, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>(502) 208-9212</phone>
    <email>spspoo01@louisville.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40292</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheri A Levinson, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>502-852-7710</phone>
      <email>cheri.levinson@louisville.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cheri A Levinson, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.louisvilleeatlab.com/conquering-fear-foods-study.html</url>
    <description>Laboratory Website Description of Study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson HB, Wetterneck CT, Cahill SP, Steinglass JE, Franklin ME, Leonard RC, Weltzin TE, Riemann BC. Treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder complicated by comorbid eating disorders. Cogn Behav Ther. 2013;42(1):64-76. doi: 10.1080/16506073.2012.751124. Epub 2013 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23316878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Louisville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cheri Levinson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>eating disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>food exposure</keyword>
  <keyword>feared food</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

