<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04154163</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2-032-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04154163</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Appropriate Dosing to Optimise Personalised Cancer Treatments</brief_title>
  <acronym>ADOPT</acronym>
  <official_title>Appropriate Dosing to Optimise Personalised Cancer Treatments</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Dundee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Dundee</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study to assess feasibility of dried blood spot (DBS) samples for
      pharmacokinetic measurements of targeted anti-cancer drugs in oncology patients such as
      patients with BRAF-mutant melanoma receiving targeted treatment with BRAF and MEK inhibitors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the pharmacology laboratory, we have developed a method for measuring drug concentrations
      in animals using dried blood spots (DBS). DBS is a simple method that could be easily carried
      out by patients at home, using either filter paper-based DBS cards (e.g. Whatman 903, FTA
      DMPK-C) or small sponges (www.neoteryx.com).

      The routine use of DBS to clinically test blood was first used in the 1960s as a safe and
      simple method of testing for inherited metabolic disorders in new born babies. However, in
      recent years there has been increasing use of DBS to test blood for other things, including
      for drugs as a way to monitor the drug level in the blood.

      This method has great potential application in testing blood for drug levels in cancer
      patients. We wish to establish if this DBS technique is feasible in real-life practice for
      cancer patients on targeted anti-cancer therapies as should this be the case this innovation
      could herald a new era in personalised treatment of advanced human cancers allowing doctors
      to more safely use combinations of targeted therapies. These combinations of targeted
      therapies have been shown to inhibit development of drug resistance and are increasingly
      being used in clinical practice. However, targeted therapies often fail (especially
      combinations of targeted therapies) because of unacceptable toxicities making them
      intolerable for the patient. With an easy and acceptable method for monitoring the drug level
      in blood, as could be provided by DBS, the right amount of drug could be given to each
      individual patient and this 'personalised' drug dosing as standard of care might result in
      much greater success with combinations of anti-cancer drugs.

      This drug monitoring is especially important for targeted anti-cancer therapies because many
      of these (such as Dabrafenib, used for many cases of advanced melanoma) have profound affects
      on the liver enzymes that metabolise (get rid of) most medications. Dabrafenib is a potent
      inducer of P450 liver enzymes and this induction means that other drugs metabolised by the
      same liver pathway (the great majority of drugs are metabolised by the same pathways) will
      have significantly reduced blood levels if the patient is on Dabrafenib. So it is especially
      important to be able to monitor blood levels of both Dabrafenib and of other co-medications
      that the patient may be taking. The DBS sampling method would allow this and would provide a
      safe, convenient and cheap test that could be conducted in the patient's home and posted back
      to the laboratory.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The accuracy of DBS for measuring drug levels in venous blood following standard doses of targeted therapies for metastatic cancers such as BRAF mutant melanoma</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose,1 hour, 2 hours, 8 hours (if on a once daily drug regime) or pre-second dose (if on a twice daily drug regime) and 24 hours post-dosing</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of targeted anti-cancer drug in venous blood at timed intervals following oral dosing in standard clinical care pathway measured in venous blood and by DBS</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The ability of oncology patients receiving targeted cancer treatments to collect multiple DBS samples over a 24-hour period</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose,1 hour, 2 hours, 8 hours (if on a once daily drug regime) or pre-second dose (if on a twice daily drug regime) and 24 hours post-dosing</time_frame>
    <description>Successful collection of DBS samples both under supervision in hospital and when at home</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The safety and acceptability of DBS collections at timed intervals before and after taking anti-cancer targeted drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>After each 24-hour period of DBS sampling and during telephone consultations in weeks 1 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Adverse Events per participant and measures of patient acceptability for collection of DBS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The stability of the drug levels stored in DBS, taken by the patient at home and posted to the laboratory</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurement of repeat samples at the timepoints chosen at 1, 2 and 3-days post-collection to ensure stability.</time_frame>
    <description>Demonstration that the drug concentrations measured in fresh and DBS samples stored for several days is the same.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine inter-patient variability in Pharmacokinetics (PK)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurement of co-medication drug levels at repeat time intervals (Pre-dose,1-hour, 2-hours, 8-hours (once-daily drug regime) or pre-second dose (twice-daily drug regime) and 24-hours post-dosing both before and after starting targeted Dabrafenib</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in drug levels of co-medications over time following standard clinical dosing with targeted cancer treatments such as dabrafenib +/- trametinib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug tolerability collected from examination of clinical pathway for participating patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Before recruitment and after commencing relevant medication</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of drug tolerability data from examination of clinical pathway for participating patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma Stage III</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma Stage IV</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cancer Stage III</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cancer Stage IV</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer, Non-small Cell</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 1 Participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Blood test Day 1 DBS and venous blood
Blood test Day 2 DBS (+/- and venous blood)
Blood test Day 15 DBS only
Blood test Day 16 DBS only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 2 Participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-drug naive participants:
Blood test Day 1 DBS
Blood test Day 2 DBS
Blood test Day 15 DBS
Blood test Day 16 DBS
Drug naive participants:
Blood test Day 1 DBS
Blood test Day 2 DBS
Blood test Day 3, 4, or 5 DBS
Blood test Day 4, 5 or 6 DBS
Blood test Day 15 DBS
Blood test Day 16 DBS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dried blood Spot (DBS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Dried Blood Spot filter paper and sponges</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 1 Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 2 Participants</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DBS home collection kits</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venous blood sampling</intervention_name>
    <description>Venous blood</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 1 Participants</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Phlebotomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Biospecimens will be blood tests conducted in the form of either (i) whole blood which will
      be collected using Dried Blood Spots &quot;DBS&quot; +/- and (ii) venous blood samples.

      Stage 1:

      Five patients will be recruited for initial validation of drug dose measurements using the
      DBS method by comparison with venous blood samples.

      One or two drops of blood (10 microlitres) collected using triplicates of blood spots on to
      dry blood spot filter paper and micro-sampler sponge at specified time intervals.

      A phlebotomy serum sample (5 ml) will be collected in a heparin tube at the same time
      intervals before and after oral dosing of their targeted drugs over a single 24-hour period.

      Stage 2:

      One or two drops of blood (10 microlitres) collected using triplicates of blood spots on to
      dry blood spot filter paper and micro-sampler sponge at specified time intervals.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants will be recruited from the Oncology Unit and Dermatology or Oncology
        outpatient departments
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female participants

          -  Age 18 years and over

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of stage 4 or stage 3 unresectable cancers; BRAF+ melanoma, c-KIT+
             melanoma, advanced renal cell carcinoma, non-small cell lung carcinoma and ovarian
             carcinoma.

          -  Able to perform study assessments

          -  Individuals who are participating in the follow-up phase of another interventional
             trial/study, or who are enrolled in an observational study, will be co-enrolled where
             the CIs of each study agree that it is appropriate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give informed consent

          -  World Health Organisation (WHO) performance status 3-4

          -  Known allergy or intolerance to Dabrafenib +/- Trametinib, Prazopanib, Erlotinib,
             Gefitinib, Imatinib, Osimertinib or Olaparib

          -  Unstable co-morbidities; cardiovascular disease e.g. severe congestive cardiac
             failure, end stage renal failure, hepatic impairment, vasculopathy, inflammatory
             arthritis or interstitial lung disease/ pneumonitis which, in the opinion of the CI,
             would make the patient unsuitable to be enrolled in the study

          -  Language barrier preventing adequate understanding of the study and a lack of suitable
             translator service to overcome this barrier

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charlotte Proby, MBBS,FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chief Investigator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Angela Alani, MB Bch BAO</last_name>
    <phone>07490192716</phone>
    <email>a.alani@dundee.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charlotte Proby, MBBS,FRCP</last_name>
    <phone>01382383289</phone>
    <phone_ext>83289</phone_ext>
    <email>c.proby@dundee.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NHS Tayside and University of Dundee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dundee</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <zip>DD1 9SY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charlotte Proby, BA MBBS FRCP</last_name>
      <phone>01382383289</phone>
      <phone_ext>83289</phone_ext>
      <email>c.proby@dundee.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Angela Alani, MB Bch BAO, MRCP Derm</last_name>
      <phone>07490192716</phone>
      <phone_ext>36453</phone_ext>
      <email>a.alani@dundee.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robijns K, Koster RA, Touw DJ. Therapeutic drug monitoring by dried blood spot: progress to date and future directions. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2014 Nov;53(11):1053. doi: 10.1007/s40262-014-0197-3.</citation>
    <PMID>25312497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Wit D, den Hartigh J, Gelderblom H, Qian Y, den Hollander M, Verheul H, Guchelaar HJ, van Erp NP. Dried blood spot analysis for therapeutic drug monitoring of pazopanib. J Clin Pharmacol. 2015 Dec;55(12):1344-50. doi: 10.1002/jcph.558. Epub 2015 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26032288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nijenhuis CM, Huitema AD, Marchetti S, Blank C, Haanen JB, van Thienen JV, Rosing H, Schellens JH, Beijnen JH. The Use of Dried Blood Spots for Pharmacokinetic Monitoring of Vemurafenib Treatment in Melanoma Patients. J Clin Pharmacol. 2016 Oct;56(10):1307-12. doi: 10.1002/jcph.728. Epub 2016 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26918324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ouellet D, Gibiansky E, Leonowens C, O'Hagan A, Haney P, Switzky J, Goodman VL. Population pharmacokinetics of dabrafenib, a BRAF inhibitor: effect of dose, time, covariates, and relationship with its metabolites. J Clin Pharmacol. 2014 Jun;54(6):696-706. doi: 10.1002/jcph.263. Epub 2014 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24408395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedl B, Kurlbaum M, Kroiss M, Fassnacht M, Scherf-Clavel O. A method for the minimally invasive drug monitoring of mitotane by means of volumetric absorptive microsampling for a home-based therapeutic drug monitoring. Anal Bioanal Chem. 2019 Jul;411(17):3951-3962. doi: 10.1007/s00216-019-01868-1. Epub 2019 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>31093700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Dundee</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charlotte Proby</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participants data for full primary and secondary outcome measures maybe be made available</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

