<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04154137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACPM23</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04154137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self-reported Non-celiac Wheat Sensitivity (NCWS) in Patients Undergoing Digestive Endoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence of Self-reported Non-celiac Wheat Sensitivity (NCWS) in Patients Undergoing Digestive Endoscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Palermo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Palermo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Self-reported food hypersensitivity is common, particularly in women, with a reported
      prevalence of about 20% in the UK community. A wide range of gastrointestinal and systemic
      symptoms may be experienced related to consumption of the intolerant food(s). In addition,
      patients demonstrate considerably more generalized subjective health complaints in comparison
      with healthy controls. In this context, it has been reported that a consistent percentage of
      the general population consider themselves to be suffering from problems caused by wheat
      and/or gluten ingestion, even though they do not have celiac disease or wheat allergy. This
      clinical condition has been named non-celiac gluten sensitivity' (NCGS). In a previous paper
      the investigators suggested the term 'non-celiac wheat sensitivity' (NCWS), since it is not
      known what component of wheat causes the symptoms in NCGS patients, and the investigators
      also showed that these patients had a high frequency of coexistent multiple food
      hypersensitivity. In a previous study, the investigators demonstrated, in a population of
      teenagers, a frequency of self-reported NCWS of about 12%; the frequency of GFD use was 2.9%,
      which was much higher than the percentage of known CD in the same population (1.26%). The
      aims of this study were 1) to determine the prevalence of self-perceived wheat and/or
      gluten-sensitivity in patients undergoing digestive endoscopy, irrespective to the
      motivations of the test, and 2) to evaluate the demographic and clinical differences between
      patients self-reporting wheat and/or gluten sensitivity and patients not reporting food
      hypersensitivity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Self-reported food hypersensitivity is common, particularly in women, with a reported
      prevalence of about 20% in the UK community. A wide range of gastrointestinal and systemic
      symptoms may be experienced related to consumption of the intolerant food(s). In addition,
      patients demonstrate considerably more generalized subjective health complaints in comparison
      with healthy controls. In this context, it has been reported that a consistent percentage of
      the general population consider themselves to be suffering from problems caused by wheat
      and/or gluten ingestion, even though they do not have celiac disease or wheat allergy. This
      clinical condition has been named non-celiac gluten sensitivity' (NCGS). In a previous paper
      the investigators suggested the term 'non-celiac wheat sensitivity' (NCWS), since it is not
      known what component of wheat causes the symptoms in NCGS patients, and the investigators
      also showed that these patients had a high frequency of coexistent multiple food
      hypersensitivity. The clinical picture of NCWS is characterized by combined gastrointestinal
      (bloating, abdominal pain, diarrhea and/or constipation, nausea, epigastric pain,
      gastroesophageal reflux, aphthous stomatitis) and extra-intestinal and/or systemic
      manifestations (headache, depression, anxiety, 'foggy mind,' tiredness, dermatitis or skin
      rash, fibromyalgia-like joint/muscle pain, leg or arm numbness, and anemia). To our
      knowledge, there are few studies which assessed the prevalence of self-reported wheat and/or
      gluten-related symptoms in the community and analyze diagnostic outcomes in those referred to
      secondary gastrointestinal care. In one of these, performed in UK, the authors shown that
      gluten-related symptoms are self-reported by 13% of the population, with 3.7% consuming a
      gluten-free diet, despite only 0.8% being aware that they have a formal diagnosis of celiac
      disease. In this study individuals self-reporting gluten-related symptoms were predominantly
      female, reported an association with IBS, and experienced both intestinal and extraintestinal
      symptoms on gluten ingestion. Of those patients presenting to the gastroenterology
      department, the majority do not have CD but NCWS. In another study, the investigators
      demonstrated, in a population of teenagers, a frequency of self-reported NCWS of about 12%;
      the frequency of GFD use was 2.9%, which was much higher than the percentage of known CD in
      the same population (1.26%). The aims of this study were 1) to determine the prevalence of
      self-perceived wheat and/or gluten-sensitivity in patients undergoing digestive endoscopy,
      irrespective to the motivations of the test, and 2) to evaluate the demographic and clinical
      differences between patients self-reporting wheat and/or gluten sensitivity and patients not
      reporting food hypersensitivity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-perceived wheat and/or gluten-sensitivity in patients undergoing digestive endoscopy.</measure>
    <time_frame>January 2017 to January 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Prevalence of self-perceived wheat and/or gluten-sensitivity in patients undergoing digestive endoscopy by using an ad hoc questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences between patients self-reporting wheat and/or gluten sensitivity and patients not reporting food hypersensitivity.</measure>
    <time_frame>January 2017 to January 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Demographic and clinical differences between patients self-reporting wheat and/or gluten sensitivity and patients not reporting food hypersensitivity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-celiac Wheat Sensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients undergoing digestive endoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <description>All the patients, age ranged from 18 to 90 years, referred to Digestive Endoscopy Outpatients Clinic of the Department of Gastroenterology of the University Hospital &quot;Paolo Giaccone&quot; of Palermo, Italy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Enrolled patients will fill out a modified version of a previously validated written questionnaire, including two different sections. The first comprises basic demographic information, including age, sex and ethnicity, and a screening section for symptoms consistent with irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) in accordance with the Rome III criteria, also including their past gastrointestinal, allergic and psychiatric history. The second section enquires for self-reported gluten-related symptoms. Participants will be also asked for their use of a gluten-free diet and if they had seen a healthcare professional for their symptoms. A reported diagnosis of celiac disease and wheat allergy in the population group is defined by those who had a doctor diagnosis of celiac disease and wheat allergy and are also taking a gluten-free diet.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients undergoing digestive endoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will include patients undergoing digestive endoscopy (i.e.
        esophagogastroduodenoscopy, pancolonscopy and proctoscopy), at the Digestive Endoscopy
        Outpatients Clinic of the Department of Gastroenterology of the University Hospital &quot;Paolo
        Giaccone&quot; of Palermo, Italy, between January 2017 and January 2020.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients undergoing digestive endoscopic investigations, irrespective to the
             motivations of the test.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio Carroccio, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Palermo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Digestive Endoscopy Outpatients Clinic of the Department of Gastroenterology of the University Hospital &quot;Paolo Giaccone&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <state>PA</state>
        <zip>90129</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Internal Medicine Division of the &quot;Cervello-Villa Sofia&quot; Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <state>PA</state>
        <zip>90129</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, University Hospital of Palermo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <zip>90129</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carroccio A, Mansueto P, Iacono G, Soresi M, D'Alcamo A, Cavataio F, Brusca I, Florena AM, Ambrosiano G, Seidita A, Pirrone G, Rini GB. Non-celiac wheat sensitivity diagnosed by double-blind placebo-controlled challenge: exploring a new clinical entity. Am J Gastroenterol. 2012 Dec;107(12):1898-906; quiz 1907. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2012.236. Epub 2012 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22825366</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mansueto P, Seidita A, D'Alcamo A, Carroccio A. Non-celiac gluten sensitivity: literature review. J Am Coll Nutr. 2014;33(1):39-54. doi: 10.1080/07315724.2014.869996. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24533607</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carroccio A, Rini G, Mansueto P. Non-celiac wheat sensitivity is a more appropriate label than non-celiac gluten sensitivity. Gastroenterology. 2014 Jan;146(1):320-1. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2013.08.061. Epub 2013 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>24275240</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carroccio A, D'Alcamo A, Mansueto P. Nonceliac wheat sensitivity in the context of multiple food hypersensitivity: new data from confocal endomicroscopy. Gastroenterology. 2015 Mar;148(3):666-7. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2014.11.047. Epub 2015 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25625764</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carroccio A, Soresi M, D'Alcamo A, Sciumè C, Iacono G, Geraci G, Brusca I, Seidita A, Adragna F, Carta M, Mansueto P. Risk of low bone mineral density and low body mass index in patients with non-celiac wheat-sensitivity: a prospective observation study. BMC Med. 2014 Nov 28;12:230. doi: 10.1186/s12916-014-0230-2.</citation>
    <PMID>25430806</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mansueto P, Seidita A, D'Alcamo A, Carroccio A. Role of FODMAPs in Patients With Irritable Bowel Syndrome. Nutr Clin Pract. 2015 Oct;30(5):665-82. doi: 10.1177/0884533615569886. Epub 2015 Feb 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25694210</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Young E, Stoneham MD, Petruckevitch A, Barton J, Rona R. A population study of food intolerance. Lancet. 1994 May 7;343(8906):1127-30.</citation>
    <PMID>7910231</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aziz I, Lewis NR, Hadjivassiliou M, Winfield SN, Rugg N, Kelsall A, Newrick L, Sanders DS. A UK study assessing the population prevalence of self-reported gluten sensitivity and referral characteristics to secondary care. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2014 Jan;26(1):33-9. doi: 10.1097/01.meg.0000435546.87251.f7.</citation>
    <PMID>24216570</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sanders DS, Patel D, Stephenson TJ, Ward AM, McCloskey EV, Hadjivassiliou M, Lobo AJ. A primary care cross-sectional study of undiagnosed adult coeliac disease. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2003 Apr;15(4):407-13.</citation>
    <PMID>12655262</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Palermo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pasquale Mansueto</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-celiac wheat sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>celiac disease</keyword>
  <keyword>wheat allergy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

