<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04159324</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01NVF18022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04159324</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>StroCare - Optimised Cross-sectoral,Coordinated Treatment of Stroke Patients With Patient-orientated Outcome Measurement</brief_title>
  <acronym>StroCare</acronym>
  <official_title>StroCare - Optimised Cross-sectoral, Coordinated Treatment of Stroke Patients With Patient-orientated Outcome Measurement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Albertinen Krankenhaus gGmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Elbe Kliniken Stade-Buxtehude GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Reha Centrum Hamburg GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Klinikum Bad Bramstedt GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>MediClin Klinikum Soltau GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VAMED Klinik Geesthacht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VAMED Rehaklinik Damp</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BARMER Krankenkasse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lohmann und Birkner medizinisches ServiceCenter GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forcare GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Trial is a multi-centred controlled interventional study with a pre-post design. The
      primary aim of the study is the evaluation of the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of the
      StroCare treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is the second most common cause of death in Germany and the most common cause for
      life-long disability in adulthood. After stroke, patients often experience incisive changes
      in their health, daily routine and quality of life. The developed model of care (StroCare
      treatment) forms a cross--sectoral, structured and coordinated treatment pathway that
      integrates a patient-centred outcome evaluation. It aims to optimize the transition from
      acute inpatient treatment after an acute stroke to the ambulant neurological rehabilitation
      treatment. This is done firstly by creating an electronic portal solution for a safe and
      coordinated transmission of clinical data between the three participating hospitals and five
      stroke-specialized ambulant rehabilitation clinics and secondly by introducing a case-manager
      provided by the participating health insurance agency for patient support and aftercare
      coordination. The presented study is a multi-centred controlled interventional study with a
      pre-post design. Stroke patients in both groups are assessed after the index ischemic event
      and 12 months thereafter. Further sources of information are the medical record, the
      electronic portal (only intervention group), and routine data provided by the collaborating
      BARMER health insurance agency (for the Intervention and control group and additionally for a
      historic control). The main hypotheses are : (1) The StroCare treatment is more effective
      than the routine aftercare treatment (primary outcome: patient-reported quality of life) and
      (2) the StroCare treatment reduces costs for care and in the inpatient sector by providing
      more coordinated and thorough rehabilitation and outpatient aftercare.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>For a 12-months period patients undergoing aftercare treatment as usual are enrolled as an active control group. Subsequently, the intervention is implemented (StroCare treatment) and enrolment of the intervention group takes place for another 12 months. Patients in both groups are assessed after the index ischemic event and 12 months thereafter. Further sources of information are the medical record, the electronic portal (only intervention group), routine data provided by the collaborating BARMER health insurance agency (for the intervention and control group and additionally for a historic control).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported QoL: PROMIS-10</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported Quality of Life measured with Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System-10 (PROMIS-10); this provides two global scores: Global Physical Health and Global Mental Health with scores ranging from 0-20 each and higher scores indicating better health state.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported mental health status</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Patient reported mental health Status measured with the Patient health questionnaire (PHQ-4); the questionnaire provides two sub-scores measuring anxiety and depression with scores ranging from 0-6 each with higher scores indiciating more symptoms of anxiety or depression, respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Status modified Rankin Scale questionnaire (smRSq)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Status measured with the modified Rankin Scale (mRS); the nRS ranges from 0 (no disability) to 6 (death)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival measured with the ICHOM Standard set</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Stroke recurrence measured with the ICHOM Standard set</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Utilisation of health care Services</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Utilisation of health care Services extracted from the medical record and the electronic Portal (only Intervention Group), i.e., number of admissions to hospital, number of outpatient contacts, weekly hours of physiotherapy, speech therapy, occupational therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient' s waiting time between Treatment phases (Transition) to the ambulant neurological Rehabilitation Treatment)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Waiting time extracted from the medical record and the electronic Portal (only Intervention Group)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success in reahin target values of relevant risk factors (individually defined target values based on available guidelines): blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Current values Blood Pressure will be extracted from the medical record and the electronic portal and compared to the individually defined target values based on current guidelines and individuall assessement of the overall patient's situation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success in reahin target values of relevant risk factors (individually defined target values based on available guidelines): LDL-cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Current values of LDL-cholesterol will be extracted from the medical record and the electronic portal and compared to the individually defined target values based on current guidelines and individuall assessement of the overall patient's situation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success in reahin target values of relevant risk factors (individually defined target values based on available guidelines): HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Current values of HbA1c will be extracted from the medical record and the electronic portal and compared to the individually defined target values based on current guidelines and individuall assessement of the overall patient's situation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Costs</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after index ischemic event</time_frame>
    <description>Routine data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>StroCare treatment group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Optimized cross-sectoral, structured and coordinated treatment pathway that integrates a patient-centred outcome evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>routine aftercare stroke treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>optimized cross-sectoral, structured and coordinated treatment pathway that integrates a patient-centred outcome evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>the optimized treatment pathway includes coordinated transitions between rehabilitation phases and institutes using individual case management and portal solutions</description>
    <arm_group_label>StroCare treatment group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients in inpatient care in the stroke unit of one of the participating acute
             clinics who are insured at the BARMER health insurance agency with the following
             diagnosis (ICD-10):

          -  Ischemic attack (I63)

          -  Transient ischemic attack and related syndromes (G45)

          -  Intracerebral haermorrhage (I64)

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Sufficient mastery of German language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Substantially impaired communication capacity due to aphasia or dementia

          -  Patients with artificial Respiration

          -  Insufficient adherence

          -  Premorbid score of mRS≥4

          -  Patients with artificial Respiration (Z99.1)

          -  Dementia (F00.x., F01.x. or G30.x) or aphasia (R47)

          -  Death during inpatient Treatment or the Admission to a nursing home following the
             acute treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Götz Thomalla, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Centre Hamburg-Eppendorf</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Götz Thomalla, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+4940741050137</phone>
    <email>thomalla@uke.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Goetz Thomalla, MD</last_name>
      <email>wakeup@uke.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christian Gerloff, MD</last_name>
      <email>wakeup@uke.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Götz Thomalla, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-reported outcomes (PROs)</keyword>
  <keyword>Cross-sectoral care</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke aftercare</keyword>
  <keyword>Aftercare coordination</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-rehabilitation support</keyword>
  <keyword>Evidence based treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-centred care</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Morbidity</keyword>
  <keyword>Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional status</keyword>
  <keyword>Feasibility</keyword>
  <keyword>Acceptance</keyword>
  <keyword>Process evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Health economics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

