<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04151186</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CART-TM4SF1/CART-EpCAM-CAN-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04151186</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Study on the Safety and Efficacy of CAR-T Therapy for the TM4SF1- and EpCAM-positive Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Study on the Safety and Efficacy of Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-cell Therapy for the TM4SF1- and EpCAM-positive Recurrent/Refractory Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>suhaichuan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Biomed-union Biotechnology Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tang-Du Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  Transmembrane 4 L Six Family Member 1 (TM4SF1) and Epithelial cell adhesion molecule
           (EpCAM) are both highly expressed in many epithelial-derived solid tumors.

        -  The Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-cells (CAR-T) that target TM4SF1 or EpCAM have been
           generated respectively in our good manufacturing practices (GMP) facility and their
           anti-tumor effects have been demonstrated in multiple in vitro and in vivo studies.

        -  Clinical studies are proposed here to evaluate the anti-tumor activity of these cell
           therapy products for treatment of patients with TM4SF1 or EpCAM positive tumors. In this
           study, the safety, tolerance, and preliminary efficacy of CART-TM4SF1 and CART-EpCAM
           cells will be examined inpatients with refractory/recurrent advanced pancreatic cancer,
           colorectal cancer, gastric cancer or lung cancer. And 9 patients for each cancer will be
           evaluated.

        -  Clinical and immunological responses will be evaluated about 30 days and last up to 2
           years after CAR-T cell infusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  While great progress has been made in CAR T-cell therapy for the treatment of
           hematologic malignancies, its use in solid tumors is still at the exploratory stage.

        -  Transmembrane 4 L Six Family Member 1 (TM4SF1) protein mediates signal transduction
           events that play a role in the regulation of cell development, activation, growth and
           motility. It is a cell surface antigen and is highly expressed in different carcinomas.
           Epithelial cell adhesion molecule (EpCAM),is a transmembrane glycoprotein of 40
           kilodaltons (kDa). EpCAM is highly expressed in many epithelial-derived tumors, such as
           colon, stomach, pancreas, lungs, ovaries and breasts. Recently, EpCAM has been
           identified as the surface marker of circulating tumor cells (CTCs) and cancer stem cells
           (CSCs).

        -  The investigators have developed novel TM4SF1-targeting CAR T-cells (CART-TM4SF1 cells)
           and EpCAM-targeting CAR T-cells (CART-EpCAM cells) for solid tumor treatment. These
           engineered T-cells can target and kill the TM4SF1- or EpCAM-positive tumor cells in
           vitro or in mice. Both of the CAR molecules contain a safety switch based on epidermal
           growth factor receptor (EGFR) to ensure the safety.

        -  The investigators propose to investigate the feasibility, safety, and efficacy of
           CART-TM4SF1 cells and CART-EpCAM cells for solid cancers in patients.

      Objectives:

      Primary objectives:

        1. To determine the safety/tolerance dosages and adverse effects of CART-TM4SF1 cells or
           CART-EpCAM cells in the treatment of TM4SF1- or EpCAM-positive recurrent/refractory
           advanced solid tumors.

        2. To preliminarily evaluate the efficacy of CART-TM4SF1 cells and CART-EpCAM cells in the
           treatment of TM4SF1- and EpCAM-positive recurrent/refractory advanced solid tumors.

      Secondary objectives:

        1. To determine the pharmacokinetic (PK)/pharmacodynamic (PD) characteristics of
           CART-TM4SF1 cells and CART-EpCAM cells in humans.

        2. To evaluate the overall survival (OS) and tumor regression after treatment.

        3. To assess the life quality of patients

      Study population:

      The study population includes 72 patients with refractory/recurrent advanced solid tumors
      positive for TM4SF1 or EpCAM expressions, each cancer including 9 patients . Among these
      patients with pancreatic cancer, colorectal cancer, gastric cancer or lung cancer, 9 subjects
      will receive 3 escalating doses (3 subjects in each dosage group)and safety and preliminary
      efficacy evaluation.

      Design:

        -  This is a single-center open-label clinical study.

        -  Recruit patients with refractory/recurrent pancreatic cancer, colorectal cancer, gastric
           cancer or lung cancer, with written consent for this study. Perform biopsy to determine
           the expression of TM4SF1 or EpCAM of the tumor with immuno-histochemistry (IHC).

        -  Collect peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) from the patients, isolate and activate
           the T cells and transfect them with TM4SF1, or EpCAM targeting CAR, expand the
           transfected T cells as needed, assess the quality and antitumor activity of the CAR-T
           products in vitro and then transfer them back the patients via systemic or local
           injections, and follow up closely to collect related results as needed.

        -  Clinical and immunological responses will be evaluated closely in about 30 days and last
           up to 2 years after back-transfusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 20, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 20, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety assessed by Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>After CAR-T cell infusion,the investigators will observe the potential adverse events related to the CAR-T cells infusion such as high fever, kidney failure and so on.
Adverse events are coded according to MedDRA 22.0. List total number of AEs and SAEs; Number of subjects with different types of AEs and SAEs, case-times and incidence.AEs and SAEs are graded by National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTC AE version 5.0).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CAR-T cell testing</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The level of CAR-T cells will be tested regularly by Real-time Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction Detecting System(qPCR) or Flow cytometry to evaluate the proliferation in vivo and long-term survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The ORR is defined as the percentage of participants who achieve partial response (PR) or better according to Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors（RECIST) criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TM4SF1 and EpCAM positive CAR-T cells for solid tumors</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The present study is proposed to study advanced malignant solid tumors in adults, and the three escalating doses, namely, 2.0~2.5. 4.0~5.0 and 8.0~10.0 (×10 ^6/kg), will be given.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TM4SF1- and EpCAM-positive chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Specification: 30 mL-100 mL, cell density of about (1-10) x10^6 cells/ml in each bag, number of T-cells about (1-10) x10^8 cells.) 300 ml for each infusion.
Storage: The prepared CAR T-cells are cryopreserved in a preserving medium . This product is manufactured under the current good manufacture practices (cGMP) conditions, with restrictions on chemical components, free from animal- or human-derived components and confirming to the United States Pharmacopeia (USP)&lt;71&gt; and &lt;85&gt; regulations.
Preservation: The frozen CAR T-cells are preserved in the liquid nitrogen transfer tank.
Usage: The frozen CAR T-cells are preserved at low temperature and transferred to the bedside. The cells are thawed by 36 degrees centigrade to 38 degrees centigrade. water bath. The frozen cells are gently massaged until complete thawing. Then they are transfused back to the patients intravenously. The transfusion will be finished within 5-10 min.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TM4SF1 and EpCAM positive CAR-T cells for solid tumors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged≥18 years old and ≤75 years old when signing the informed consent; regardless of
             gender;

          2. Body weight&gt;40kg;

          3. Pathologically confirmed as pancreatic cancer, colorectal cancer, gastric cancer or
             lung cancer;

          4. Recurrent/refractory solid tumors unresponsive to the current standard treatment;

          5. At least one measurable lesion according to the RECIST 1.1 criteria, that is, the long
             diameter of the non-lymph-node lesion≥10 mm, or the short diameter of the lymph node
             lesion ≥15 mm on CT or MRI cross-sectional imaging; the longest axis of the measurable
             lesion≥10 mm on CT scan (slice thickness≤5 mm in CT scan);

          6. Acceptable hemopoietic ability: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;1.5×10^9/L, platelet
             count &gt;1.0×10^11/L, hemoglobin (HGB) &gt;90g/L (no blood transfusion within two weeks),
             absolute lymphocyte count (ALC )&gt;500×10^9/L;

          7. Acceptable liver and kidney functions: aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) ≤2.5 ULN in subjects without liver metastases and ≤3.5 upper
             limit of normal (ULN) in those with liver metastases; bilirubin≤1.5 ULN (excluding
             hyperbilirubinemia or non-liver-derived hyperbilirubinemia); creatinine ≤1.5 ULN and
             creatinine clearance rate≥40 mL/min;

          8. prothrombin time (PT)/international normalized ratio (INR) &lt;1.5 ULN and partial
             thromboplastin time (PTT)/activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) &lt;1.5 ULN;

          9. Positive for TM4SF1 or EpCAM expression (expression≥25%), with three classifications;
             (1) Recurrent or existing lesions at the primary site with tumor tissue samples
             collected within 1 year, which are positive for TM4SF1 or EpCAM by
             immunohistochemistry; (2) New metastatic lesions at the non-primary sites, which are
             positive for TM4SF1 or EpCAM by immunohistochemistry; (3) Remaining tumor lesions at
             the primary site with tumor tissue samples collected more than 1 year ago, and the
             lesions are positive for TM4SF1 or EpCAM by immunohistochemistry based on re-biopsy.

         10. Women of child-bearing age (15-49 years old) must be negative for pregnancy test at 7
             days before initiation of the treatment.

         11. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) scores≤2.

         12. Expected survival no less than 12 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of any radiotherapy and chemotherapy within 4 weeks before a single blood
             collection;

          2. History of any anti-programmed cell death protein 1 (PD1) and anti-Programmed cell
             death 1 ligand 1 (PD-L1) treatments within 12 weeks before a single blood collection;

          3. History of organ transplantation;

          4. Pregnancy or lactation;

          5. Uncontrolled infectious diseases, such as baseline hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA≥2000
             IU/ml, positive for anti-human immunodeficiency virus （HIV） antibody and hepatitis C
             virus (HCV)-RNA;

          6. Other active infection with clinical significance;

          7. History of other active malignancies in the past 5 years, excluding basal or squamous
             skin carcinoma, superficial bladder cancer, and breast cancer in situ which have
             completely healed and require no follow-up treatment;

          8. Serious autoimmune diseases or immunodeficiency disease, including those with
             confirmed severe autoimmune diseases and requiring long-term use (over 2 months) of
             systemic immunosuppressants (steroids) or having immune-mediated symptomatic diseases,
             such as ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease, rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus
             erythematosus (SLE) and autoimmune vasculitis (eg., Wegener's granulomatosis);

          9. Allergic diathesis and allergic to immunotherapy or relevant drugs;

         10. Organ failure; Heart: Grade III and IV ; or with hypertension uncontrolled by the
             standard treatment, history of myocarditis or myocardial infarction within 1 year;
             Liver: Class C according to the Child-Turcottei-Pugh System (CTP); Kidneys: Kidney
             failure and uremic syndrome; Lungs: Serious symptoms of respiratory failure; Brain:
             Disturbance of consciousness;

         11. Active bleeding, and thrombotic diseases requiring treatment;

         12. Uncontrollable pleural and peritoneal effusion requiring clinical treatment or
             intervention;

         13. T-cell cancers, such as T-cell lymphoma;

         14. Current on systemic steroid or steroid inhalers;

         15. Any mental diseases, including dementia and changes in mental status that may
             influence the understanding about the informed consent and questionnaire;

         16. Participating in other clinical trials in the past 30 days;

         17. Judged as serious uncontrollable diseases by the researchers, or other conditions that
             may interfere with the treatment and therefore being ineligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helong Zhang, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>IEC of Institution for National Drug Clinical Trials ,Tangdu Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haichuan Su, professor</last_name>
    <phone>18629190366</phone>
    <email>suhc@fmmu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nmpa.gov.cn/WS04/CL2138/300457.html</url>
    <description>The guiding principle of research and evaluation of cell therapy product,</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Visintin A, Knowlton K, Tyminski E, Lin CI, Zheng X, Marquette K, Jain S, Tchistiakova L, Li D, O'Donnell CJ, Maderna A, Cao X, Dunn R, Snyder WB, Abraham AK, Leal M, Shetty S, Barry A, Zawel L, Coyle AJ, Dvorak HF, Jaminet SC. Novel Anti-TM4SF1 Antibody-Drug Conjugates with Activity against Tumor Cells and Tumor Vasculature. Mol Cancer Ther. 2015 Aug;14(8):1868-76. doi: 10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-15-0188. Epub 2015 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26089370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gao C, Yao H, Liu H, Feng Y, Yang Z. TM4SF1 is a potential target for anti-invasion and metastasis in ovarian cancer. BMC Cancer. 2019 Mar 15;19(1):237. doi: 10.1186/s12885-019-5417-7.</citation>
    <PMID>30876464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peng XC, Zeng Z, Huang YN, Deng YC, Fu GH. Clinical significance of TM4SF1 as a tumor suppressor gene in gastric cancer. Cancer Med. 2018 Jun;7(6):2592-2600. doi: 10.1002/cam4.1494. Epub 2018 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>29665316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang Y, Chen M, Wu Z, Tong C, Dai H, Guo Y, Liu Y, Huang J, Lv H, Luo C, Feng KC, Yang QM, Li XL, Han W. CD133-directed CAR T cells for advanced metastasis malignancies: A phase I trial. Oncoimmunology. 2018 May 7;7(7):e1440169. doi: 10.1080/2162402X.2018.1440169. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29900044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hellström I, Horn D, Linsley P, Brown JP, Brankovan V, Hellström KE. Monoclonal mouse antibodies raised against human lung carcinoma. Cancer Res. 1986 Aug;46(8):3917-23.</citation>
    <PMID>3731064</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hellström I, Beaumier PL, Hellström KE. Antitumor effects of L6, an IgG2a antibody that reacts with most human carcinomas. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1986 Sep;83(18):7059-63.</citation>
    <PMID>3462743</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goodman GE, Hellström I, Brodzinsky L, Nicaise C, Kulander B, Hummel D, Hellström KE. Phase I trial of murine monoclonal antibody L6 in breast, colon, ovarian, and lung cancer. J Clin Oncol. 1990 Jun;8(6):1083-92.</citation>
    <PMID>2161448</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goodman GE, Hellstrom I, Yelton DE, Murray JL, O'Hara S, Meaker E, Zeigler L, Palazollo P, Nicaise C, Usakewicz J, et al. Phase I trial of chimeric (human-mouse) monoclonal antibody L6 in patients with non-small-cell lung, colon, and breast cancer. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 1993;36(4):267-73.</citation>
    <PMID>8382560</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tang-Du Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>suhaichuan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CAR-T cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunologic Factors</keyword>
  <keyword>TM4SF1;EpCAM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

