<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04155125</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GXE4KGBio-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04155125</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Efepoetin Alfa in Treating Anaemia Associated With Chronic Kidney Diseases Patient</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-Label Randomised Controlled Trial of Efepoetin Alfa for Treatment of Anaemia Associated With Chronic Kidney Disease Patients Not on Dialysis (ND-CKD). A Non- Inferiority Trial Compared to Methoxy Polyethylene Glycol-Epoetin Beta (MIRCERA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PT Kalbe Genexine Biologics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PT Kalbe Genexine Biologics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, randomised, multicenter, Mircera-controlled, parallel-group, Phase III
      study to determine whether subcutaneous administered efepoetin alfa is as effective and well
      tolerated as subcutaneous Mircera for anaemia correction and maintenance in erythropoiesis
      stimulating agent (ESA)-naïve subjects who have CKD and are not on dialysis. ESA prior users
      who have stopped using ESA at least 12 weeks till screening will also be eligible for this
      study provided they fulfil all the subject entry criteria.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will consist of a 20-week correction period for dosage titration and Hb correction,
      followed by an 8-week evaluation period for efficacy assessments of corrective treatment.
      Subjects who respond to efepoetin alfa (defined as an increase in Hb ≥1.0 g/dL versus
      baseline and Hb level within 10 - 12 g/dL range without blood transfusion during the 28 weeks
      after the first dose) will be eligible to continue treatment, and will be randomised to
      receive subcutaneous efepoetin alfa either once every 2W or every 4W for an additional
      24-week extension period to assess long-term safety and maintenance effect. Mircera
      responders will also be allowed to continue the drug during the extension period, receiving
      it every 4 weeks using the dose equal to twice the previous once-every-two-week dose. The
      safety data collected will be part of an ongoing pooled analysis of safety data from the
      efepoetin alfa clinical development program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the efficacy of efepoetin alfa in the treatment of anaemia associated with CKD as measured by haemoglobin (Hb) response rate at the end of correction treatment evaluation period</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurement from the date of Randomization till the End of the Corrective Treatment period, assessed up to 20 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement is done by an increase in Hb more than or equal to 1 g/dL compared with baseline and a Hb concentration within range of 10 - 12 g/dL inclusive without transfusion during evaluation period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterise safety and tolerability of subcutaneous efepoetin alfa is being measured by based on the frequency of adverse events and on the number of out of range laboratory values.</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurement from the time the subject provides informed consent through and including 28 calendar days after the last study drug administration.</time_frame>
    <description>Safety endpoints parameters including Serious Adverse Events (SAE) specified below
Composite outcome of cardiovascular death or a nonfatal myocardial infarction or stroke
All-cause mortality
Cardiovascular mortality
Acute myocardial infarction
Heart failure
Acute kidney injury defined according to Acute Kidney Injury Network (AKIN) criteria
Abnormal clinical laboratory tests (haematology, biochemistry including serum ferritin and TSAT)
Anti-efepoetin alfa or anti-Mircera antibody titres
Clinically meaningful abnormal findings of vital signs
Development of clinically meaningful electrocardiogram abnormalities
Hospitalisations (excluding those for logistic reasons)
It is a composite outcome. Any abnormal test findings during the study will be helpful in reviewing the outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">386</enrollment>
  <condition>Anaemia Associated With Chronic Kidney Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>efepoetin alfa</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration: Subcutaneous Injection.
The administration interval and initial dosage for subjects who are randomly assigned to subcutaneous efepoetin alfa will be starting from 4 μg/kg BW once per 2 weeks, then titrated based on Hb level during study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mircera</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Route of administration: Subcutaneous Injection.
The starting dosage of Mircera arm will be 0.6 μg/kg BW per 2 weeks based on prior data in similar study populations with subsequent titration to achieve targeted Hb range. During the correction treatment period, the dosage of study drug will be adjusted to achieve a Hb level range within 10 - 12 g/dL and an increase ≥1.0 g/dL versus the individual patient's baseline Hb level. During the extension period, Hb levels should be maintained between 10 and 12 g/dL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>efepoetin alfa</intervention_name>
    <description>The administration interval and initial dosage for subjects who are randomly assigned to subcutaneous efepoetin alfa will be starting from 4 μg/kg BW once per 2 weeks, then titrated based on Hb level during study period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>efepoetin alfa</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mircera</intervention_name>
    <description>The starting dosage of Mircera arm will be 0.6 μg/kg BW per 2 weeks based on prior data in similar study populations with subsequent titration to achieve targeted Hb range. During the correction treatment period, the dosage of study drug will be adjusted to achieve a Hb level range within 10 - 12 g/dL and an increase ≥1.0 g/dL versus the individual patient's baseline Hb level. During the extension period, Hb levels should be maintained between 10 and 12 g/dL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mircera</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age should be greater than or equal to the minimum age of consent in the applicable
             country

          2. Stage 3 or 4 CKD (eGFR ≥ 15 and &lt; 60 mL/min/1.73 m2)

          3. ESA-naive (no prior ESA use) subjects whose Hb at baseline is ≥ 8 g/dL and &lt; 10 g/dL,
             or ESA prior users whose Hb at baseline is ≥ 8 g/dL and &lt; 10 g/dL and who have stopped
             using ESA at least 12 weeks till the screening

          4. Ferritin ≥ 100 ng/mL and transferrin saturation (TSAT) ≥ 20%

          5. Subject must be willing to complete all study-related activities and follow-up visits

          6. Evidence of a signed and dated informed consent document indicating that the subject
             has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Need for dialysis therapy expected in the next 12 months or rapid progression of CKD
             (e.g., eGFR decrease of &gt;20% within 12 weeks)

          2. Received a blood transfusion (including RBC transfusion) within the 12 weeks prior to
             screening, or blood transfusion is anticipated during the study period

          3. Have a history of overt gastrointestinal bleeding or any other bleeding episode
             associated with a fall in Hb of ≥ 1 g/dL, within the last 8 weeks prior to screening

          4. Have an unstable Hb for any reason, in the investigator's opinion

          5. Have non-renal anaemia (any anaemia where the investigator considers the anaemia is
             predominantly due to a non-renal cause. Non-renal causes include, but are not limited
             to vitamin B12 or folic acid deficiency, homozygous sickle-cell disease, thalassemia
             of all types, other non-renal cause of anaemia such as myelodysplasia or
             haematological malignancies)

          6. Platelet count of ≤ 50 x109/L

          7. Vitamin B12 deficiency defined as total serum levels of &lt; 181 pmol/L (246 pg/ml) 10

          8. Folic acid deficiency defined as total serum levels &lt; 7.63 nmol/L (3.37 ng/mL) 10

          9. Pure red cell aplasia, or a history of pure red cell aplasia

         10. Poorly controlled hypertension defined as a sitting SBP ≥170 mmHg and/or DBP ≥100 mm
             Hg

         11. Chronic congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association class IV) or are
             otherwise at high risk for early withdrawal or interruption of the study (due to
             myocardial infarction, severe or unstable coronary artery disease, stroke, or severe
             liver disease) within the 12 weeks before screening or during screening

         12. Active or not active malignancy (except non-melanoma skin cancer) within five years
             before screening

         13. Planned live kidney transplantation scheduled within 52 weeks after the screening
             visit

         14. Uncontrolled hyperparathyroidism, in the investigator's opinion

         15. Uncontrolled hypothyroidism determined by the investigator that they cannot
             participate in the study

         16. Active acute or chronic infection, or uncontrolled or symptomatic inflammatory disease
             (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus), or a C-reactive protein
             level &gt; 15 mg/L. (Routinely screening for hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus
             (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection is not required in this
             protocol. By history or current clinical evidence, patients with active acute HBV or
             HCV infection should be excluded. Chronic HBV/HCV infection with LFTs &gt; 3 times of
             normal are excluded. Known HIV positive patients are excluded)

         17. Immunosuppressive therapy (other than corticosteroids for a chronic condition, or
             tacrolimus/cyclosporine) within 12 weeks prior to baseline

         18. Life expectancy of less than 52 weeks

         19. Planned surgery during the study period (excluding minor skin excisions)

         20. Have received investigational drug(s) other than those of this study within 4 weeks
             prior to screening, or will receive investigational drug(s) other than those of this
             study during the study period

         21. History or clinical evidence of cardiovascular, haematologic or hepatic (ALT, AST,
             bilirubin values above three times the upper limit of normal [ULN] at screening) or
             any physical conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, would compromise
             participation in the study

         22. With a cognitive or psychiatric condition rendering the subject unable to be
             cooperative with and complete study requirements

         23. Hypersensitivity to any one of the investigational drugs

         24. Subjects are, in the judgement of the investigator, otherwise inappropriate for entry
             into the study

         25. Subjects who are investigational site staff members directly involved in the conduct
             of the trial and their family members, site staff members otherwise supervised by the
             Investigator, or subjects who are KGBio or CRO employees directly involved in the
             conduct of the trial

         26. Participation in other studies involving same investigational drug(s) (Phases 1-4) of
             this study within 12 weeks before screening

         27. Females of childbearing potential or males who are unable/unwilling to take adequate
             contraceptive precautions defined by the protocol for the duration of the study and
             for at least 28 days after last dose of investigational product. Females have a
             positive pregnancy test result within 24 hours prior to study entry, is otherwise
             known to be pregnant, plans to become pregnant in the next 12 months or is currently
             breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Srinivas Rao Jada</last_name>
    <phone>+6598474170</phone>
    <email>jada.rao@kalbe.co.id</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Paritosh Keertikar</last_name>
    <phone>+6597306165</phone>
    <email>paritosh.keertikar@innogene.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

