<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04154384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00115061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04154384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Life Pain Specialists (LPS) With a Focus on Patient Pain Management and Prevention of Substance Misuse</brief_title>
  <official_title>Life Pain Specialists (LPS) With a Focus on Patient Pain Management and Prevention of Substance Misuse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Christopher Wolf Crusade (CWC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot, single-center study where the Life Pain Specialist (LPS) will provide
      personalized Patient Pain Plan (PPP) to patients combating pain. LPS assessments will focus
      on the level of risk the patient has for potential substance misuse and the Pain Plans will
      be unique to each patient. Participants will be followed for one year post operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Opioids are psychoactive substances (narcotics) primarily used for pain relief by producing
      morphine-like effects. Although regularly prescribed by physicians, opioids (including
      morphine, codeine, and oxycodone) are highly addictive. Opioids block feelings of pain and
      trigger a release of dopamine. Dependence occurs with repeated use, as the parts of the brain
      naturally responsible for releasing dopamine rely on the drug for proper function. When
      avoided, patients quickly experience severe withdrawal symptoms similar to the flu.

      In the United States, millions are prescribed opioids for pain relief. Every day, more than
      115 people die from overdose. The highest among them are people aged 25 to 54 years.
      Addiction treatment costs near $78.5 billion and rising, less than 10% of people in need are
      receiving it.

      Within the orthopaedic trauma population at Grady Healthcare in Atlanta, Georgia, 20% of
      patients report a history of substance abuse, 30% have previously used opioid medications for
      pain, and nearly 25% report taking opioid pain medications up to 1 year after their trauma.
      Trauma patients are particularly at high risk.

      The Christopher Wolf Crusade (CWC) is a 501C3 non-profit providing preventative solutions,
      education, and advocacy for the American opioid epidemic. CWC's primary focus is to introduce
      a behavior-specific intervention at the time of inpatient hospitalization for trauma to
      decrease overall opioid utilization and improve pain control in the post-trauma time period.
      The goal of this study is to introduce Life Pain Specialists (LPS) to the healthcare field to
      focus on pain management and addiction prevention for patients. The LPS is a behavior-based
      pain &quot;coach&quot; who educates patients on risks of opioid dependence and offers non-traditional
      non-pharmacologic options for pain control. In addition, the LPS will act as a liaison
      between the patient and the physician to ensure that traditional pharmacologic-based pain
      control regimens are optimized.

      Potential patients will be identified during their initial presentation to Grady Hospital
      during morning trauma board rounds within the first 24 hours of admission. Once the consent
      process is complete, the participants will be referred to the LPS team. Participants will be
      followed in the orthopaedic trauma clinic at routine post-operative intervals (2 weeks, 6
      weeks, 3 months, 6 months, and 1 year post-operatively).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Pain Medication Usage</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of the study will be the utilization of opioid pain medication at 1 year after the operation. This value will be compared to the 23% of a historical control cohort reporting continuing to use opioids a year post operation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, Week 6, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be assessed using an 11-point Likert scale where 0 = no pain and 10 = severe pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Opioid Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (at hospital discharge), Week 2, Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Opioid utilization will be recorded in morphine equivalents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Pain Plan (PPP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Orthopedic trauma patients will work with a Life Pain Specialist (LPS) and will receive a personalized Patient Pain Plan (PPP) to avoid potential opioid misuse.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Pain Plan (PPP)</intervention_name>
    <description>The Life Pain Specialist (LPS) will work with the patient to develop a Patient Pain Plan (PPP) focused on behavioral education, and will act as a liaison with physicians to optimize the pharmacologic component of pain management. The PPP includes education about substance misuse and provides non-pharmacological pain management options.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Pain Plan (PPP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Orthopaedic trauma patients with planned operative fixation of one or more fractures

          -  Informed consent obtained

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients that did not undergo operative fixation of one or more fractures

          -  Incarceration

          -  Enrolled in a study that does not permit co-enrollment

          -  Unlikely to comply with the follow-up schedule

          -  Unable to converse, read or write English at elementary school level
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mara Schenker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grady Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mara Schenker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Orthopedic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid addiction</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral research</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

