<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03593967</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-2018-01-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03593967</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Project ARTISAN: Fostering Aspiration and Resilience Through Intergenerational Storytelling and Arts-based Narratives</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARTISAN</acronym>
  <official_title>Project ARTISAN: Fostering Aspiration and Resilience Through Intergenerational Storytelling and Arts-based Narratives</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nanyang Technological University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Museum of Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TOUCH Community Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Arts Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nanyang Polytechnic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NgeeAnn Polytechnic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nanyang Technological University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study adopts a Participatory Action Research (PAR) approach to develop a novel
      ARTISAN intergenerational arts programme that aims to promote life meaning, resilience and
      wellbeing, as well as to enhance social support and national identity, among the older and
      younger generations Singapore. Utilizing a wait-list Randomized Controlled Trial design, 30
      elderlies and 30 youths (N=60) will be invited to participate in a 5-weeks, 10-hours
      intervention programme.

      Through the integrative processes of curated museum visits (art space), facilitated
      storytelling (art facilitation), creative art-making and reflective writing (art content),
      the intervention will focus on the exploration of five unique themes to engage senior-youth
      dyads. They include: (a) Discovering National Heritage, (b) Strengthening Social Bonds, (c)
      Overcoming Adversities and Resilience, (d) Building Dreams and Aspirations, and (e) Sharing
      Stories and Legacies.

      Quantitative data obtained before and after the intervention will be triangulated with
      qualitative data generated from feasibility focus groups and reflective writings to explore
      its potential benefits and benefiting processes in achieving the aforementioned outcomes. To
      encourage social change and empowerment, public art exhibitions showcasing the artworks from
      this programme will also be held within the community. The findings from this study will form
      the foundation for a larger Population Health Project on Arts and Wellness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research Objectives

      In order to foster and cultivate aspiration and promote resilience in Singapore, stories of
      life and strength should be discovered and embraced. Through the reflective and expressive
      strength of arts, this proposed pilot study - Project ARTISAN: fostering Aspiration &amp;
      Resilience Through Intergenerational Storytelling &amp; Art-based Narratives - aspires to empower
      both seniors and youths through intergenerational storytelling and art making to achieve the
      following objectives:

        1. Empowerment: This research will develop and evaluate a novel, cultural-specific ARTISAN
           intergenerational arts programme with the aim to enhance youths' and seniors' sense life
           meaning, resilience and wellbeing, leading to greater social cohesion and national
           identity.

        2. Engagement: In the ARTISAN exhibition that showcases the creations generated from the
           study, the investigators aim to engage families and friends of study participants, as
           well as members of the public in gaining a renewed understanding towards Singaporean
           youths and seniors.

        3. Social change: Through the development of ARTISAN, the investigators aim to create a
           platform for intergeneration interaction and knowledge exchange, encouraging the
           cultivation of positive public social dialogue and change.

        4. Sustainability: Findings generated from this study will serve as the empirical
           foundation for a future Population Health study that aspires toward large-scale
           implementation of Project ARTISAN in greater community, which can in turn benefit more
           participants from different walks of life.

      Methodology

      This pilot study adopts a Participatory Action Research (PAR) approach to develop a novel
      ARTISAN intergenerational arts programme that aims to promote life meaning, resilience and
      wellbeing, as well as to enhance social support and national identity, among the older and
      younger generations Singapore. Utilizing a wait-list Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT)
      design, pre, post, and follow-up data will be collected and analysis to evaluate programme
      effectiveness in achieving the stated objectives. Finally, a feasibility assessment will be
      carried out to investigate programme acceptability and suitability for local population.
      Ethical approval will be obtained from Nanyang Technological University's Institutional
      Review Board. Informed consent will also be sought from the participants to ensure
      confidentiality, beneficence and non-maleficence.

      Sampling. Two groups of research participants will be involved in this study: (a) 30
      community dwelling seniors aged 60 and above; and (b) 30 youths aged 18 - 35.

      Procedures. Participants from each age group will be paired up to form one-to-one
      senior-youth dyads that will remain intact for the full project duration upon successful
      recruitment and informed consent, each dyads will then be randomized into 4 groups comprising
      7-8 dyads each, with 2 intervention groups and 2 wait-list control group. Wellbeing and
      self-concept assessments will be conducted for all groups at baseline (T1), thereafter the
      intervention groups will undergo a 5-weeks 15-hour ARTISAN intergenerational arts programme
      that integrates curated museum visits, facilitated storytelling, creative art-making, and
      reflective writing for exploring and sharing life narratives on heritage, adversity,
      strengths and unity, with the aim to foster aspirations, resilience, wellbeing and social
      cohesion. Upon completion of programme among the intervention group, all 4 groups will be
      assessed again (T2), and thereafter, the wait-listed controlled group will received the same
      5-week 15-hour programme. At the end of all intervention components, a final exit assessment
      will be conducted on all groups (T3). A public art exhibition will also be held at the end of
      the programme to reach out to friends and relatives of the participants, as well as the
      members of the public. If possible, the art pieces will be permanently showcased within the
      community. During the art exhibition, exhibition viewers will be encouraged to respond and
      reflect upon the artworks.

      To assess the implementation and delivery of the ARTISAN intergenerational arts programme in
      community settings, time needed to organize and conduct the intervention sessions, deviations
      from the intervention protocol and uncompleted interventions and the reasons; as well as the
      programme leaders' perceptions of competence as a result of training, will be recorded.
      Programme leaders will also record their experiences of delivering the intervention, their
      observations of participants' responses during and after the intervention, as well as any
      difficult or deviant cases. Finally, a randomly selected 24 study participants will be
      invited to participate in 4 feasibility focus groups after completion of the pilot study (2
      groups for 12 seniors and 2 groups for 12 youths). The purpose of these focus groups is to
      explore and elicit the lived experiences of participants going through Project ARTISAN,
      allowing space for them to share their thoughts, feelings and personal meaning and benefits
      of the programme, as well as to elicit their views on the inner workings of the programme so
      as to offer feedbacks for programme enhancement. All focus group sessions will be recorded,
      transcribed verbatim and analyzed using thematic framework analysis.

      Significance and Uniqueness of Research

      Project ARTISAN utilizes the methods of participatory action research in identifying the
      needs, raising the voices, and illuminating the lives of both seniors and youths in Singapore
      who are increasingly faced with the challenges of social isolation and decreasing mental
      health. Through an unique integrative approach that examines the interplay between curated
      art space, art content and art facilitation, it further aspires to develop a structured
      intervention protocol for enhancing participants' aspirations, resilience, personhood and
      nationhood, one that can be adopted and implemented widely across all art, education, health
      and social care settings in the local context. In sum, this first-of-its-kind study fills a
      critical gap in knowledge and practice between the intersection of arts, health and culture,
      while fostering community engagement for enhancing societal wellbeing and social cohesion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Based on availability of schedule, participants will sign up for one of the 4 groups available (ie. 2 intervention groups and 2 wait-list control group). Wellbeing and self-concept assessments will be conducted for all groups at baseline (T1), thereafter the intervention groups will undergo a 5-weeks 15-hour ARTISAN intergenerational arts programme that integrates curated museum visits, facilitated storytelling, creative art-making, and reflective writing for exploring and sharing life narratives on heritage, adversity, strengths and unity, with the aim to foster aspirations, resilience, wellbeing and social cohesion. Upon completion of programme among the intervention group, all 4 groups will be assessed again (T2), and thereafter, the wait-listed controlled group will received the same 5-week 15-hour programme. At the end of all intervention components, a final exit assessment will be conducted on all groups (T3).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ego-Resilience</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The 14-item Ego-Resilience Revised Scale (ER-89) assesses trait resilience. Participants will be asked to indicate their agreement for statements on a 7-point likert scale. Overall average scores and subscale scores on Active engagement with the world, Integrated performance under stress and Repertoire of (social, personal and cognitive) problem solving strategies will be calculated. Higher values represent greater levels of resilience.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Connectedness</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The 8-item Social Connectedness Scale (SCS) assesses Social Connectedness. Participants will be asked to indicate their agreement for statements on a 6-point likert scale. An overall score will be calculated, with higher scores reflecting a greater sense of connectedness. Potential scores range from 8 - 48.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>National Identity</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The revised 15-item National Identity Scale (NATID) assesses multiple domains of National Identity. Participants will be asked to indicate their agreement for statements on a 7-point likert scale. Overall average subscale scores for National Heritage, Culture Homogeneity and Belief system will be calculated. Higher values represent greater levels of National Identity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Loneliness</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The 8-item UCLA Loneliness Scale (ULS-8) assesses Loneliness. Participants will be asked to indicate their agreement for statements on a 4-point scale. An overall score will be calculated, with higher scores reflecting a greater sense of loneliness. Potential score ranges from 8 - 32.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The 8-item World Health Organization Quality of Life Scale-8 (WHOQoL-8) measures subjective quality of life. Participants will be asked to respond to questions about areas of their lives on a 5-point likert scale. An overall score will be calculated, with higher values representing greater quality of life. Potential scores range from 8 - 40.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Life Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The single-item Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS) measures life satisfaction. Participants will be asked to respond on a 4-point scale with higher values representing better life satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Life Meaning</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The 'Presence of Meaning' Subscale from the Meaning in Life Questionnaire (MLQ) is a 5-item measure to assess the participant's sense of meaning in life. Participants will be asked to respond to statements about meaning on a 7-point scale with higher scores indicating a greater sense of life meaning. An overall score will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compassion</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>The 5-item Santa Clara Brief Compassion Scale (SCBCS) measures participant's sense of compassion towards others. Participants will be asked to rate statements on a 7-point scale. An overall average score will be calculated, with larger values representing a higher degree of compassion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Support</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed at three time points: [T1] baseline; [T2] immediately post-intervention/second baseline (5 weeks post T1); and [T3] 5 weeks follow-up/ immediately post-intervention (5 weeks post T2)</time_frame>
    <description>Three subscales from the Medical Outcomes Study Social Support Survey (MOS-SS) will be used to measure social support. Specifically, the 8-item Emotional/Informational Support subscale, the 4-item Positive Social Interactions as well as the 3-item Affectionate Support. Participants will be asked to rate on a 5-point likert scale. Subscale scores will be calculated, with higher values representing greater sense of social support.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Intergenerational Relations</condition>
  <condition>Loneliness</condition>
  <condition>Identity, Social</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Youths and seniors in the intervention group will be paired to receive a novel five-week (3 hours/ week) bilingual (English/ Mandarin), intergenerational arts programme which includes guided museum tours, collaborative art-making and story telling as well as reflective writing. These sessions will be held at the National Museum, and facilitated by experienced artists and trained art therapists.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will serve as a waitlist control group before receiving the intervention that the intervention group receives at the end of 5 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ARTISAN</intervention_name>
    <description>In the first four weeks, dyads will engage in museum tours facilitated by a docent from the National Museum, followed by a guided storytelling/art-making session (inspired by the artifacts in the gallery), writing activity and group sharing/debrief. The first three weeks of art making will be pair-work by the seniors and youth, while the fourth week will be a collaborative art piece that is created by all participants in the working group. In the last week, the participants will be involved in a mini-exhibition where they will share their works with the group and members of the public, and engage in guided reflection on each other's artworks.
The main content and discussion point for each session are as follows:
Week 1: Food and Play as our National Heritage
Week 2: Our Voices, Our Singapore: Strengthening Bonds
Week 3: Overcoming Adversities: Stories of Resilience
Week 4: Beholding the Future: Dreams and Aspirations
Week 5: Passing It On: The Stories We Share</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Youths: Aged 18 to 35

          -  Seniors: Aged 60 and above

          -  No mobility issues

          -  Able to provide informed consent (or assent)

          -  Not suffering from major mental health problems

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide consent

          -  Suffering from major mental health problems
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andy HY Ho</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nanyang Techological University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nanyang Technological University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>637332</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho, A.H.Y., Chui, C.H.K., Borschel, M. (2017). Understanding and managing youth and elderly suicide in Developed East Asia: The imperative of compassion in public health. In G. Cox &amp; N. Thompson (eds.), Handbook of Traumatic Loss: A Guild to Theory and Practice (Chapter 8, pp. 107-122). UK: Routledge.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho, A.H.Y. (2017). The Arts for Ageing Well: A Singapore Experience. Keynote Speaker at the Arts in Eldercare Symposium 2017. Singapore, 6 September 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho, A.H.Y., Ho, R.H.M., Pang, J. Ortega, E., &amp; Ma, S.H.X. (2018). Research Report on the Arts for Ageing Well - A Landscape Study on Art Participation and Holistic Wellbeing among Current and Future Older Generations of Singapore. Singapore: Action Research for Community Health, Nanyang Technological University.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho, A.H.Y., &amp; Tan-Ho, G. (2018) Mindful-Compassion Art Therapy: A Handbook for Practitioners. Singapore: Action Research for Community Health (ARCH), Psychology, School of Social Sciences, Nanyang Technological University.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho, R.T.H., Potash, J.S., Ho, A.H.Y., Ho, V.F.L. &amp; Chen, E.Y.H. (2016). Reducing mental illness stigma and fostering empathic citizenship: Community arts collaborative approach. Social Work in Mental Health, 15(4), 469-485, DOI: 10.1080/15332985.2016.1236767</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nanyang Technological University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andy Hau Yan Ho, PhD, EdD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>intergenerational arts</keyword>
  <keyword>aspiration</keyword>
  <keyword>resilience</keyword>
  <keyword>storytelling</keyword>
  <keyword>art making</keyword>
  <keyword>seniors</keyword>
  <keyword>youth</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

