<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03597347</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SAV008-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03597347</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Inhaled Molgramostim in CF Subjects With NTM Infection</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENCORE</acronym>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Non-controlled, Multicenter, Pilot Trial, Using Inhaled Molgramostim in Cystic Fibrosis Subjects With Nontuberculous Mycobacterial (NTM) Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Savara Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Savara Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A study to evaluate the efficacy of inhaled molgramostim administered open-label to adult
      cystic fibrosis subjects with chronic pulmonary nontuberculous mycobacterial (NTM) infection,
      with or without ongoing antimycobacterial guideline based combination therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methodology:

      The Screening period will begin up to 10 weeks prior to the Baseline visit for collection of
      the sputum sample, but the remainder of the assessments including Safety labs will be
      completed within 6 weeks of Baseline, to determine eligibility. Adult subjects with a history
      of cystic fibrosis (CF) and chronic pulmonary NTM infection will be considered for
      enrollment. Chronic pulmonary NTM infection will be defined by at least three positive NTM
      cultures (sputum or broncho-alveolar lavage (BAL)) for the same species/subspecies of MAC or
      MABSC within the 2 years prior to screening, with at least one positive within the past 6
      months prior to screening and a minimum of 50% of NTM cultures positive over the past 2
      years. Subjects must additionally provide a positive sputum culture with the same
      species/subspecies obtained from the central laboratory during the Screening period to be
      eligible.

      Three groups of subjects will be recruited:

        -  Group 1: Subjects with chronic pulmonary MAC or MABSC infection who have not
           consistently achieved negative NTM sputum cultures while currently on a multidrug NTM
           guideline-based antimycobacterial regimen, which has been ongoing for at least 9 months
           prior to the Baseline visit.

        -  Group 2: Subjects with chronic pulmonary MAC or MABSC infection who remain sputum
           culture positive but have stopped a multidrug NTM guideline-based antimycobacterial
           regimen at least 28 days prior to Screening due to lack of response or intolerance.

        -  Group 3: Subjects with chronic pulmonary MAC or MABSC infection not meeting
           recommendations for treatment with a multidrug NTM guideline-based antimycobacterial
           regimen based on failure to meet American Thoracic Society/Infectious Diseases Society
           of America (ATS/IDSA) criteria for NTM pulmonary disease (i.e. absence of radiologic
           findings and clinical symptoms beyond what is expected from underlying CF).

      All subjects will have Screening, Baseline, Week 1, 2 and followed by monthly Treatment
      visits from week 4 during the Treatment period. The Treatment period will be 48 weeks.
      Following the End of Treatment (Week 48), subjects will have a Follow-up visit at 4 and 12
      weeks, and the End of Study visit 24 weeks after the End of Treatment. At the Baseline visit,
      eligible subjects will start treatment with inhaled molgramostim. A detailed Schedule of
      Assessments is outlined in Table 1. At each visit any changes in concomitant medication will
      be recorded. Participating subjects will be encouraged to contact the clinic between visits
      if they experience adverse events (AE), worsening of their condition or have any other
      concerns. If needed, unscheduled visits will be conducted at the Investigator's discretion.
      All subjects will be maintained on their standard CF treatment and medications independent of
      NTM treatment status.

      Treatment with inhaled molgramostim will be given at a dosage of 300 μg once daily for 48
      weeks. Dosing will be done in the morning, after completion of the subject's normal airway
      clearance routine, where medications should be taken in the following order: bronchodilator,
      dornase alfa (Pulmozyme), inhaled antibiotics (e.g. TOBI) and lastly inhaled molgramostim.

      Subjects on a cyclical on-off anti-Pseudomonal regimen will have their trial visits (Baseline
      and subsequent visits in the Treatment Period) scheduled during a week after at least three
      weeks off treatment or after at least one week on-treatment of the antibiotic. Subjects on a
      continuous inhaled regimen, including continuous alternating therapy (CAT), should have been
      on a stable regimen for at least 28 days prior to Baseline.

      A data review will be conducted after the first 6 subjects have completed 12 weeks of
      treatment. If safety concerns or poor tolerability are identified in this review, the review
      committee may decide on less frequent dosing for subsequent subjects in the study. Additional
      safety reviews will be conducted at regular intervals thereafter. During the study, subjects
      in Group 1 will continue use of antimycobacterial treatment, whereas subjects in Groups 2 and
      3 will receive inhaled molgramostim as monotherapy for their NTM infection. For subjects in
      Group 1, the antimycobacterial therapy should preferably not change during the treatment
      period except in case of drug toxicity or adverse reactions. Antibiotics discontinued due to
      toxicity may be replaced, with drug selection and dose modification at the discretion of the
      treating physician. All changes in antimycobacterial treatment will be recorded, including
      reasons for each change. In the event the Investigator has evidence of infection while on
      treatment which requires more intensive therapy (i.e. additional antibiotics in Group 1 or
      addition of antibiotics to Group 2 or 3) the subject may be allowed to continue after
      discussion with the Sponsor medical monitor.

      Number of subjects (planned):

      No formal sample size calculation was done as this is an initial pilot study. To be able to
      assess response in each of the three groups, a minimum of 8 subjects with MAC or MABSC will
      be enrolled into each of the 3 groups, and a minimum of 30 subjects will be enrolled across
      all 3 groups. The maximum number of subjects enrolled into each group will be 12, and the
      maximum number of subjects enrolled into the study will be 34.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sputum NTM culture conversion to negative</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>NTM sputum culture conversion to negative (defined as at least three consecutive negative mycobacterial cultures collected at least 4 weeks apart during the Treatment period).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NTM sputum culture microbiological cure</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>NTM sputum culture microbiological cure (defined as multiple consecutive negative but no positive cultures with the causative species after last culture conversion and until the End of Treatment (Week 48).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first NTM sputum culture conversion</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first NTM sputum culture conversion during the Treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sputum smear conversion to negative</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sputum smear conversion to negative (defined as at least three consecutive negative acid-fast bacilli (AFB) stained sputum smears on microscopy, collected at least 4 weeks apart in subjects who were smear positive at Baseline) during the Treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consistent sputum smear conversion to negative Treatment (Week 48) in subjects who were smear positive at Baseline).</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Consistent sputum smear conversion to negative (defined as multiple consecutive negative but no positive smears after last smear conversion and until the End of Treatment (Week 48) in subjects who were smear positive at Baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first NTM sputum smear conversion.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first NTM sputum smear conversion during the Treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Durable NTM sputum microbiological cure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks after End of Treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Durable NTM sputum microbiological cure for the NTM isolate(s) treated without recurrence at Week 12 after End of Treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Durable NTM sputum smear conversion to negative</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks after End of Treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Durable NTM sputum smear conversion to negative without subsequent positive smears at Week 12 after End of Treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in semi-quantitative grade of number of NTM</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks and 12 Weeks after End of Treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in semi-quantitative grade of number of NTM on microscopy of AFB stained sputum smears from Baseline to End of Treatment and Week 12 after End of Treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pulmonary function</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks and 12 Weeks after End of Treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Absolute change in FEV1 (percent predicted) from Baseline to End of Treatment and Week 12 after End of Treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks and 12 Weeks after End of Treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in respiratory domain score assessed by Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R) from Baseline to End of Treatment and Week 12 after End of Treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body mass index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks and 12 Weeks after End of Treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in BMI from Baseline to End of Treatment and Week 12 after End of Treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Mycobacterium Infections, Nontuberculous</condition>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis (CF)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled molgramostim</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Molgramostim nebulizer solution (300 µg/dose) administered once daily for 48 weeks utilizing the PARI eFlow nebulizer system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Molgramostim nebulizer solution</intervention_name>
    <description>300 µg / dose molgramostim (recombinant human GM-CSF) for inhalation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled molgramostim</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>rhGM-CSF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PARI eFlow nebulizer system</intervention_name>
    <description>Nebulizer</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled molgramostim</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent obtained from participant.

          2. Confirmed diagnosis of CF according to the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation (CFF) 2017
             Consensus Guidelines.

          3. History of chronic pulmonary infection with M. avium complex (MAC) or M. abscessus
             complex (MABSC) (defined as at least three positive NTM cultures (sputum or BAL for
             the same species (MAC) or subspecies (MABSC) within the 2 years prior to the screening
             visit, with at least one positive within the past 6 months and a minimum of 50% of NTM
             cultures positive over the past 2 years) that does not demonstrate response to current
             treatment course based on decreasing NTM burden or frequency of positive cultures, and
             in the opinion of the Investigator is unlikely to resolve with current treatment
             course.

          4. Subject fulfills criteria for inclusion in one of the following groups:

             Group 1: Subject with chronic pulmonary MAC or MABSC infection currently on a
             multidrug NTM guideline-based antimycobacterial regimen, which has been ongoing for at
             least 9 months prior to the Baseline visit.

             Group 2: Subject with chronic pulmonary MAC or MABSC infection who has stopped a
             multidrug NTM guideline-based antimycobacterial regimen at least 28 days prior to
             Screening due to lack of response or intolerance.

             Group 3: Subjects with chronic pulmonary MAC or MABSC infection not meeting
             recommendations for treatment with a multidrug NTM guideline-based antimycobacterial
             regimen based on failure to meet ATS/IDSA criteria for NTM pulmonary disease (i.e.
             absence of radiologic findings and clinical symptoms beyond what is expected from
             underlying CF).

          5. Ability to produce sputum or be willing to undergo an induction protocol that produces
             sputum for clinical evaluation.

          6. An additional sputum culture performed by the central laboratory, which is positive
             for the same species (MAC) or subspecies (MABSC) of NTM as before the trial within 10
             weeks of Baseline.

          7. CF which in the Investigator's opinion is clinically stable and not expected to
             require lung transplantation within the next year.

          8. FEV1 ≥ 30% of predicted at screening that is normalized for age, gender, race, and
             height, using the Global Lung Function Initiative (GLI) equation.

          9. Subjects who are co-infected with a respiratory pathogen, e.g. P. aeruginosa or S.
             aureus, must either be stable on a regular suppression antibiotic regimen or must be,
             in the opinion of the Investigator, stable despite the lack of such treatment.

         10. Female or male ≥18 years of age.

         11. If female, subjects who have been post-menopausal for more than 1 year or females of
             childbearing potential after a confirmed menstrual period using a highly efficient
             method of contraception (i.e. a method with less than 1% failure rate) during and
             until 30 days after last dose of trial treatment, having a negative serum pregnancy
             test at Screening (Visit 1) and a negative urine pregnancy test at dosing at Baseline
             (Visit 2) and must not be lactating.

             For purposes of this study, the Sponsor defines &quot;acceptable methods of contraception&quot;
             as:

               -  Oral birth control pills administered for at least 1 monthly cycle prior to
                  administration of the study drug.

               -  A synthetic progestin implanted rod (eg, Implanon®) for at least 1 monthly cycle
                  prior to the study drug administration but not beyond the 4th successive year
                  following insertion.

               -  Intrauterine devices (IUDs), inserted by a qualified clinician for at least 1
                  monthly cycle prior to study drug administration.

               -  Medroxyprogesterone acetate (eg, Depo-Provera®) administered for a minimum of 1
                  monthly cycle prior to administration of the study drug and continuing through 1
                  month following study completion.

               -  Hysterectomy or surgical sterilization.

               -  Vasectomized partner

               -  Abstinence.

             Double barrier method (diaphragm with spermicidal gel or condoms with contraceptive
             foam) is not considered an acceptable form of contraception.

             NOTE: For subjects prescribed Orkambi: Orkambi may substantially decrease hormonal
             contraceptive exposure, reducing the effectiveness and increasing the incidence of
             menstruation-associated adverse reactions. Hormonal contraceptives, including oral,
             injectable, transdermal, and implantable, should not be relied upon as an effective
             method of contraception when co-administered with Orkambi.

         12. If male, subjects who, if sexually active of reproductive potential and non-sterile
             (i.e., male who has not been sterilized by vasectomy for at least 6 months and not
             diagnosed with infertility through demonstration of azoospermia in a semen sample
             and/or absence of vas deferens through ultrasound) are willing to use a barrier method
             of contraception, or their female partner must use an acceptable method of
             contraception, during the study and until 30 days after last dose of medication.

         13. Willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory tests,
             and other trial procedures specified in the protocol as judged by the Investigator.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Use of non-maintenance antibiotic for a concurrent pulmonary or extrapulmonary
             infection within 28 days prior to the Baseline visit.

          2. Use of a maintenance antibiotic regimen containing azithromycin for a concurrent
             non-NTM pulmonary infection within 28 days prior to the Baseline visit. For subjects
             in Group 1, azithromycin is allowed if part of ongoing multidrug NTM guideline-based
             antimycobacterial regimen.

          3. Prior therapy with inhaled or systemic granulocyte macrophage colony stimulating
             factor (GM-CSF).

          4. Subjects with hemoptysis of ≥60 mL in a 24-hour period within 4 weeks prior to
             Screening.

          5. Life expectancy of less than 6 months according to Investigator's judgement.

          6. History of, or present, myeloproliferative disease, leukemia or other hematological
             malignancy.

          7. Active pulmonary malignancy (primary or metastatic); or any malignancy requiring
             chemotherapy or radiation therapy within 1 year prior to Screening or anticipated
             during the study period.

          8. Active autoimmune disorder or other condition requiring therapy associated with
             significant immunosuppression, e.g. such as systemic corticosteroids at a dose
             equivalent of 10 mg/day or more of prednisolone or other significant immunosuppressant
             medications, within 3 months prior to Screening or anticipated during the study
             period. Inhaled or topical corticosteroids, or brief courses (&lt;14 days) of systemic
             corticosteroids for pulmonary exacerbations or other self-limited conditions are
             permitted.

          9. Changes in antimicrobial, bronchodilator, anti-inflammatory or corticosteroid
             medications, or changes in Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator (CFTR)
             modulators, within 28 days prior to the Baseline visit.

         10. Pulmonary tuberculosis requiring treatment or treated within 2 years prior to
             Screening.

         11. History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or other disease associated
             with significant immunodeficiency.

         12. History of lung or other solid organ transplantation or currently on the list to
             receive lung or other solid organ transplantation.

         13. History of congestive heart failure (CHF) New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III
             or greater in severity.

         14. History of cardiovascular ischemic event within 6 months of Baseline.

         15. Any change in chronic NTM multi-drug antimycobacterial regimen within 28 days prior to
             Screening.

         16. Treatment with any investigational medicinal product within 28 days of Screening.

         17. Previous experience of severe and unexplained side-effects during aerosol delivery of
             any kind of medicinal product.

         18. Any other condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would preclude informed
             consent or assent, make study participation unsafe, complicate interpretation of study
             outcome data, or otherwise interfere with achieving the study objectives.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jerry Nick, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Jewish Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Jewish Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Florida Pulmonary Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwell Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Hyde Park</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11042</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill - UNC Marisco Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27517</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nontuberculosis mycobacterial (NTM) infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Cystic Fibrosis (CF)</keyword>
  <keyword>M. avium complex (MAC)</keyword>
  <keyword>M. abscessus complex (MABSC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Mycobacterium Infections, Nontuberculous</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycobacterium Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycobacterium Infections, Nontuberculous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Molgramostim</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sargramostim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

