<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03590834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01DK109323</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK109323</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03590834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Míranos! Program, a Preschool Obesity Prevention RCT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Obesity Prevention in Head Start: Míranos! Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas at San Antonio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Texas at Austin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland, College Park</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Family Service Association of San Antonio Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Parent/Child Incorporated (PCI) of San Antonio and Bexar County</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas at San Antonio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of obesity remains high in American children aged 2-5 while one in three Head
      Start children is overweight or obese. The proposed study is designed to test the efficacy of
      an early childhood obesity prevention program which promotes healthy growth in predominantly
      Latino children in Head Start.

      The program is a group clustered randomized controlled trial in partnership with two local
      Head Start organizations to address key enablers and barriers in obesity prevention in young
      children. The study has three specific aims:

        1. To test the efficacy of the Miranos! intervention on healthy weight growth (primary
           outcome) in normal weight, overweight, and obese children.

        2. To test the impact of the Miranos! intervention on children's physical activity,
           sedentary behavior, sleep, and dietary behaviors (secondary outcomes).

        3. To evaluate cost-effectiveness of the Miranos! intervention.

      Miranos! will be delivered in Fall and Spring (8 months) and followed by a summer health
      campaign.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Using a three-arm design, 12 Head Start (HS) centers in equal number will be randomly
      assigned to one of three conditions: 1) a combined center- and home-based intervention, 2)
      center-based intervention only, or 3) active control. The interventions will be delivered
      during the academic year (an 8-month [mo] period). A total of 525 3-year-old children (52%
      females; in two cohorts) will be enrolled in the study at baseline and followed prospectively
      one-year post-intervention. The first cohort will be recruited in summer 2018. The second
      cohort will be recruited in summer 2019.

      Data collection will be conducted at baseline (T0), immediate post-intervention (T1), and
      1-year post-intervention follow-up (T2) and include children's height, weight,
      accelerometry-based PA and sedentary behavior, TV watching and sleep by parent reports, gross
      motor development, dietary intakes, food preference. Information on family background,
      parental PA- and nutrition-related practices, parental weight and health behaviors, PA and
      nutrition policies and environments at the center and home, and costs associated with
      intervention delivery will be collected. The primary endpoint for the study is the BMI at the
      posttest immediately following the completion of the intervention (T1).

      Recruitment: Participant recruitment will take place during summer by sending a recruitment
      packet to child's home. This packet includes: study information sheet, recruitment flyer,
      informed consent form, a letter from center director and study PIs.

      Process Evaluation: The process evaluation is informed by the NIH Behavior Change Consortium
      Treatment Fidelity Workgroup's best practice recommendations and recent multi-component RCTs.
      Míranos! has multiple components with multiple activities, the investigators will use many
      indicators to evaluate the fidelity and completeness of the implementation of all components
      and determine contribution of each component by linking it to the primary and secondary
      outcomes. The investigators will collect both quantitative/qualitative data to assess
      cross-site treatment consistency, non-treatment-related effects, and document protocol
      changes.

      First, intervention dose delivered will be measured by: 1) pre-/post-study center
      environmental assessment by the Environment and Policy Assessment and Observations (EPAO) and
      auditing of meal menus; 2) completion of delivery schedule of staff, peer leader training,
      parent education sessions, home visits; 3) evaluation of staff, peer leader training; 4)
      monthly auditing of weekly lesson plans; and 5) monthly checklist of use of Míranos! Activity
      Cards, children's story books, HHL learning activities.

      Second, the intervention dose received will be assessed by: 1) attendance records of staff,
      peer leader training, parent education sessions; 2) certification test of staff, peer leader
      training; 3) monthly staff evaluation (rating scale) of children's learning of HHL content,
      gross motor skills, eating behaviors; 4) post-study parent intercept interviews; and 5)
      post-study focus groups on program delivery process with staff (n=24) and parents (n=32).

      Third, participants' responses to the intervention will be evaluated by: 1) random
      observations of staff behavior (rating scale) during outdoor play and lunch by research
      staff; 2) assessments on children's PA by the System for Observing Fitness Instruction Time
      for Preschoolers and diet by group plate waste test in 3 randomly selected centers; 3)
      in-depth interviews with staff (n=48) for program feedback; and 4) post-study staff and
      parent evaluation (rating scale) of satisfaction with intervention components/activities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The parents of the children were informed that their Head Start center will be randomly assigned to one of the three study groups.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 months, 21 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child's height and weight will be measured twice with no shoes and light clothing in an area separated by a privacy screen, using a stadiometer and digital weight scale. Discrepancy between the two measures must be ≤0.2 cm and≤ 0.10 kg. BMI, BMI-percentile, and zBMI for age and gender will be calculated using the average of the two measures based CDC Growth Charts.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Physical Activity, Sedentary Activity, and Sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 months, 21 months</time_frame>
    <description>7-d accelerometry to measure the minutes of light-, moderate- and vigorous-intensity physical activity, sedentary activity, and sleep/day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Parent report of screen time and sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 months, 21 months</time_frame>
    <description>7-d parent log to track time that child spends watching TV/DVD and sleeping each day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fruit, vegetable, and beverage consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 months, 21 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of children's consumption of fruits, vegetables and beverages by screener on the frequency and portion size of food items that will be completed by the parents as well as aggregate plate waste to asses intake at sites.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Food preference</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 months, 21 months</time_frame>
    <description>A computer-assisted pictorial test to measure young children's preferences for healthy food</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Parent Behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 8 months, 21 months</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will complete: 1) the Home Health Environment survey, 2) the Parenting Strategies for Eating and Activity Scale, 3) health knowledge assessment; and 4) parental confidence/self-efficacy scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic Information</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Information will be collected from the parents on family socioeconomic status (parent education, income, employment, health insurance, food insecurity, race/ethnicity, age, sex), acculturation (a 12-item bidirectional measure), family structure, type of residence, and family health history at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">525</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Eating</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <condition>Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</condition>
  <condition>Gross Motor Development</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Center-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In-person, child-focused intervention taking place only at the Head Start centers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Center-and-home-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In-person, child-focused intervention taking place only at the Head Start centers. Delivered in-person at Head Start centers and the family home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active comparison group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Center-based Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Center nutrition and physical activity policy modification to increase fruit and vegetable servings and more physical activity throughout the day
Staff training and technical assistance
Health education on healthy habits (diet, physical activity, sleep, screen time) using the Sesame Workshop Healthy Habits for Life (HHL) resource kit
Health contests
Gross motor and physical activity program
Miranos! activity cards based on children storybooks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Center-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CBI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home-based Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Monthly interactive poster education sessions led by parent peer educators during child pick-up time. Held at Head Start Center. These sessions include family health challenges and take-home activities.
Three Home Visits delivered by Head Start staff. Obesity prevention goal-setting integrated into existing Head Start home visits
16 semi-monthly, Family Newsletters with stories, tips, and strategies to promote healthy habits for preschool children
Incorporating activities related to PA, nutrition and sleep into existing Head Start Center Summer Calendars</description>
    <arm_group_label>Center-and-home-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>C+HBI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Children will receive Head-Start-approved health education program for children: &quot;I Am Moving, I Am Learning&quot;. In addition, the investigators will deliver an early childhood literacy program to all active control children to increase buy-in and retention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The child must be enrolled in a full-day Head Start center

          -  The child must be 3 years old at baseline, one child per family, parental consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  N/A
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zenong Yin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas at San Antonio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah Parra-Medina, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas at Austin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas at San Antonio</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All IPD collected will be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will become available after data has been analyzed for primary and secondary outcome measures</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data will be made available for research educational purposes.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

