<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03592771</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00109957</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01CA218155</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03592771</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>THRIVE Breast Cancer App Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>THRIVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Communication App to Manage Symptoms and Improve Adjuvant Endocrine Therapy Adherence for Women With Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>West Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vector Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the use of a web-enabled app that is integrated directly with patients'
      electronic health records, with and without tailored feedback. The app-based intervention is
      designed to improve patient-provider communication outside of clinic visits, resulting in
      improved symptom management and adjuvant endocrine therapy adherence among diverse patients
      with hormone receptor-positive breast cancer. The researchers will evaluate the impact of the
      intervention on a comprehensive set of outcomes, including rigorous measures of long-term
      adherence, quality of life, and costs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For women with hormone receptor-positive breast cancer, long-term use of adjuvant endocrine
      therapy (AET) significantly reduces the risk of hospitalizations, cancer recurrence and
      mortality, and increases quality of life. Despite the known benefits of AETs, many patients
      are nonadherent due to adverse side effects. Furthermore, lower AET adherence among black
      women may be contributing to the large and growing disparities in mortality outcomes.
      Real-time monitoring of treatment-related adverse symptoms and adherence could result in more
      effective management of symptoms, higher medication adherence, and ultimately lower
      recurrence and mortality. To date, however, only a few interventions have aimed to improve
      AET adherence, even fewer have targeted symptom management as a means to improve adherence,
      and none have found a statistically significant improvement on adherence. This study will
      fill this research gap by testing a web-enabled app designed with the explicit goal of
      improving long-term AET adherence. Patient-reported symptoms will be integrated directly with
      the patient's electronic health record, and concerning reports will trigger an alert to the
      patient's care team in order to improve timely patient-provider communication and care
      outside of clinic visits. In a small pilot trial of the study app, the researchers found that
      participants who had recently initiated a new AET and received weekly reminders to use the
      app reported significantly higher adherence to AETs at 8 weeks compared with a control group
      (91% vs. 68%, p=0.02). The proposed study builds on the success of the pilot by: 1) expanding
      the intervention period to six months in order to capture later-onset adverse symptoms that
      are slower to develop; 2) following participants for one to three years, depending on
      enrollment year, to test longer-term effects of the intervention on medication adherence and
      other outcomes; 3) including a larger sample powered to test multiple levels of the
      intervention; and 4) race-stratifying to test for a differential impact by race. This study
      will randomize 360 participants to one of three arms: 1) an &quot;App&quot; group (n=120) that will
      receive weekly reminders to use the study app; 2) an &quot;App+Feedback&quot; group (n=120) that will
      receive weekly reminders and personalized feedback based on their use of the app; or 3) a
      &quot;Usual Care&quot; group (n=120) that will receive usual care only. The app will include questions
      about AET adherence and adverse symptoms with built-in alerts sent to the patient's care team
      if any concerning symptoms or trends are reported. The researchers hypothesize that
      monitoring symptoms and adherence with actionable alerts and tailored feedback reports to
      patients will result in timelier symptom management and higher long-term adherence to AET. By
      evaluating the impact of the intervention on a comprehensive set of measures, including AET
      adherence, patient outcomes, racial disparities and resource use-related costs, this study
      will provide valuable and actionable results for providers, policy makers, and insurers who
      strive to achieve the &quot;Triple Aim&quot; - reduce costs while improving health outcomes and the
      patient experience.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adjuvant endocrine therapy (AET) medication (aromatase inhibitor or tamoxifen) adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will capture medication adherence using an electronic monitoring pillbox (Wisepill).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Assessment Of Cancer Therapy-Endocrine Subscale (FACT-ES) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will measure relative changes in adverse symptom burden using the Functional Assessment Of Cancer Therapy-Endocrine Subscale (FACT-ES) questionnaire. The FACT-ES is a 46-item questionnaire asking participants to report how much they have been impacted by a variety of symptoms on a 5-point scale where 0 = not at all and 4 = very much. Total raw scores range from 0 to 184, with higher scores indicating greater impact from symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Short Form Health Survey (SF-12) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will measure differences in quality of life between the three study arms with the SF-12 instrument. The SF-12 is a multipurpose short form survey with 12 questions, all selected from the SF-36 Health Survey. SF-12 is a standardized self-report questionnaire that assesses mental and physical functioning. The SF-12 consists of 12 items with a Likert-type response format that measures quality of life with a Physical Component Summary (PCS) and Mental Component Summary (MCS). Subscales associated with the PCS include physical functioning, role limitations due to physical problems, bodily pain, and general health perceptions. Subscales associated with the MCS include vitality (energy and fatigue), social functioning, role limitations due to emotional problems, and mental health. A scoring algorithm is used to generate a total score for each component ranging from 0 to 100. Low values represent a poor health state while high values represent a good health state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Self-Efficacy for Managing Symptoms Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will measure relative changes in adverse symptom burden using the 4-item PROMIS Self-Efficacy for Managing Symptoms short form questionnaire. Participants indicate how confident they are that they can manage their symptoms on a 5-point scale where 1 = not confident at all and 5 = very confident. Total scores range from 4 to 20 and higher scores indicate greater self-efficacy for managing symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasm Female</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, and then once every 6 months until March 2022 and agree to use an electronic pill monitoring device with their AET medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will be asked to use a web-based app to report their AET use in the previous 7 days and any treatment-related symptoms or changes in the severity of symptoms. Participants will receive reminders via text or email to use the app once per week during the 6-month intervention phase.
Participants will complete a survey at baseline, and then once every 6 months until March 2022 and agree to use an electronic pill monitoring device with their AET medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>App+Feedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will be asked to use a web-based app to report their AET use in the previous 7 days and any treatment-related symptoms or changes in the severity of symptoms. Participants will receive reminders via text or email to use the app once per week during the 6-month intervention phase.
In addition, participants in this group will also receive weekly tailored feedback text messages or images during the 6-month intervention phase.
Participants will complete a survey at baseline, and then once every 6 months until March 2022 and agree to use an electronic pill monitoring device with their AET medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prompts to report adherence and symptoms via study app</intervention_name>
    <description>Text message prompts to report medication adherence and symptoms via the web-enabled study app Weekly prompts to report AET use in the previous 7 days and treatment-related adverse symptoms via the web-enabled study app. All participant-reported data will be automatically entered into the patient's electronic health record and easily available to the care team for review. Any concerning symptoms or changes will trigger an email alert to the patient's oncology team.</description>
    <arm_group_label>App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>App+Feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Feedback messages</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive weekly tailored feedback messages and/or images.</description>
    <arm_group_label>App+Feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult female patients (age≥18)

          -  Diagnosis of ductal carcinoma in situ or Stage I-III hormone receptor-positive breast
             cancer

          -  New prescription for an aromatase inhibitor or tamoxifen

          -  Have a mobile device with a data plan or a home computer with Internet

          -  Have a valid email address

          -  Willing to complete brief surveys on a web-enabled device

          -  AET is indicated as standard of care

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to communicate in English

          -  Prior use of adjuvant endocrine therapy (aromatase inhibitor or tamoxifen) for current
             diagnosis

          -  Concurrently undergoing surgery, chemotherapy or radiation

          -  Current diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis

          -  Chronic daily narcotic usage

          -  Patient plans to move or transfer their care within the next year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ilana Graetz, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ilana Graetz, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(901)322-9095</phone>
    <email>thrive@westclinic.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrew Paladino, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(901)212-2480</phone>
    <email>apaladin@uthsc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Cancer Center, MIDTOWN, 1588 Union Ave.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Greg Vidal, MD</last_name>
      <phone>901-683-0055</phone>
      <email>gvidal@westclinic.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Cancer Center, EAST MEMPHIS, 7945 Wolf River Blvd</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38138</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Greg Vidal, MD</last_name>
      <phone>901-683-0055</phone>
      <email>gvidal@westclinic.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ilana Graetz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

