<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03598595</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-0224</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-01414</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-0224</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03598595</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gemcitabine, Docetaxel, and Hydroxychloroquine in Treating Participants With Recurrent or Refractory Osteosarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Study of Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination With Hydroxychloroquine (Autophagy Inhibitor) in Patients With Recurrent Osteosarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of hydroxychloroquine and how
      well it works when given together with gemcitabine and docetaxel in treating participants
      with osteosarcoma that has come back or does not respond to treatment. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as gemcitabine, docetaxel, and hydroxychloroquine, work in different ways
      to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from
      dividing, or by stopping them from spreading.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and preliminary safety of hydroxychloroquine
      (HCQ) when administered with gemcitabine and docetaxel (G+D) in patients with
      recurrent/metastatic osteosarcoma. (Phase I) II. To determine whether gemcitabine and
      docetaxel (G+D) in combination with hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) increases the disease control
      rate in patients with recurrent/metastatic osteosarcoma at 4 months as compared to historic
      controls. (Phase II)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the objective response rate by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
      (RECIST) of the combination of G + D + HCQ in patients with recurrent/metastatic
      osteosarcoma.

      II. To estimate the event-free survival (EFS), progression-free survival (PFS), and overall
      survival (OS) for patients with recurrent/metastatic osteosarcoma treated with G+D+HCQ.

      III. To estimate the toxicity rates of oral HCQ when administered in conjunction with G+D.

      IV. To investigate the pharmacokinetics (PK) of the combination in patients with
      recurrent/metastatic osteosarcoma.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the metabolic response rates of G + D + HCQ in patients recurrent/metastatic
      measurable osteosarcoma by positron emission tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT) at 6
      weeks.

      II. To assess pre-/post-treatment changes in autophagy biomarkers (autophagic vesicles, LC3B
      puncta, p62, and HMGB1), HSP27, and pHSP27 expression in tumor samples at baseline and during
      cycle #2 of treatment with G + D + HCQ.

      III. To assess the relationship between probability of response and/or disease control and
      tumor HSP27, pHSP27, ALDH1A1, and HLTF expression.

      IV. To complete functional proteomic profiling of autophagic and apoptotic pathways on tumor
      samples by RPPA and correlate findings with the probability response and disease control.

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of hydroxychloroquine followed by a phase
      II study.

      Participants receive hydroxychloroquine orally (PO) once daily (QD) or twice daily (BID) on
      days 1-21, gemcitabine intravenously (IV) over 90 minutes on days 1 and 8, and docetaxel IV
      over 1 hours on day 8. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, participants are followed up at 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 28, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of hydroxychloroquine (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From enrollment to disease progression, death, or discontinuation of treatment for any reason, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response (complete response [CR] or partial response [PR] versus not CR or PR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Osteosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Osteosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (hydroxychloroquine, gemcitabine, docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive hydroxychloroquine PO QD or BID on days 1-21, gemcitabine IV over 90 minutes on days 1 and 8, and docetaxel IV over 1 hours on day 8. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (hydroxychloroquine, gemcitabine, docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Docecad</other_name>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere Injection Concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (hydroxychloroquine, gemcitabine, docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dFdC</other_name>
    <other_name>dFdCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>Difluorodeoxycytidine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxychloroquine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (hydroxychloroquine, gemcitabine, docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient or patient's legally acceptable representative has provided informed consent

          -  Patients must have a pathological diagnosis of osteosarcoma at original diagnosis or
             time of recurrence

          -  Patients must have relapsed or become refractory to conventional therapy, with a
             regimen containing some combination of high dose methotrexate, doxorubicin, cisplatin,
             and/or ifosfamide

          -  Patients may have either unresectable or potentially resectable disease. However,
             patients with potentially resectable disease must be willing to await surgery until
             after the primary efficacy endpoint is reached at 4 months

          -  Patients must have measurable disease by RECIST 1.1

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 2. Use Karnofsky
             for patients &gt; 16 years old and Lansky for patients =&lt; 16

          -  Has archived tumor tissue and is willing to provide a tumor block or unstained slides
             or the patient is willing to undergo a pretreatment biopsy. Biopsy during cycle #2 of
             therapy is required. Biopsy at progression is strongly encouraged but will be optional

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.0 x 10^9/L

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 8 g/dL

          -  Prothrombin time (PT) or partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &lt; 1.5 x upper limit of
             normal (ULN), except subjects on anticoagulation for venous thromboembolism

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance or radioisotope glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &gt; 60
             mL/min

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 2.5 x ULN for
             age

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x ULN for age

          -  Serum albumin &gt;= 2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any disorder that compromises the ability of the patient or patient's legally
             acceptable representative to give written informed consent and/or to comply with the
             study procedures

          -  Patients who will not be available for protocol required study visits, to the best of
             the subject and investigator's knowledge

          -  History of hypersensitivity to any of the study agents (gemcitabine, docetaxel, or
             hydroxychloroquine) or to any component of the formulation

          -  Patients who have previously received gemcitabine or docetaxel

          -  Men and woman of reproductive potential, unwilling to practice a highly effective
             method of birth control for the duration of the study and continuing for 2 weeks (for
             women) and 12 weeks (for men) after receiving the last dose of study drug. Highly
             effective methods of birth control include sexual abstinence (men, women); vasectomy
             or a condom used with spermicide (men) in combination with barrier methods, hormonal
             birth control or intrauterine device (IUD) (women)

          -  Women who are lactating/breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant during the
             duration of the study

          -  History or current diagnosis of a second neoplasm. Exception: adequately treated
             non-melanoma skin cancer, curatively treated in-situ disease, or other solid tumors
             curatively treated with no evidence of disease for &gt;= 2 years

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months of study day 1, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure (New York Heart Association &gt; class II), unstable angina, or unstable cardiac
             arrhythmia requiring medication, or uncontrolled hypertension (systolic &gt; 160 mmHg or
             diastolic &gt; 100 mmHg)

          -  Active infection requiring intravenous (IV) antibiotics within 2 weeks of study
             enrollment

          -  Significant gastrointestinal disorder(s) that in the opinion of the investigator
             (e.g., Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis, extensive gastrointestinal resection) may
             influence drug absorption

          -  Known positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Subjects with acute hepatitis B and C are not eligible. Subjects with chronic
             hepatitis B or C are eligible if their condition is stable and, in the opinion of the
             investigator and Amgen physician, if consulted, would not pose a risk to subject
             safety

          -  Toxicities from prior anti-tumor therapy not resolved to Common Terminology Criteria
             for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade 0 or 1, or to levels dictated in the eligibility
             criteria. Grade 2 toxicities from prior anti-tumor therapy that are considered
             irreversible (defined as having been present and stable for &gt; 4 weeks), such as stable
             grade 2 peripheral neuropathy or ifosfamide-related proteinuria, may be allowed if
             they are not otherwise described in the exclusion criteria AND there is agreement to
             allow by the principal investigator

          -  Prior participation in an investigational study and/or procedure within 21 days of
             study day 1

          -  Anti-tumor therapy within 21 days of study day 1 including chemotherapy, antibody
             therapy, or other investigational agent. Enrollment of subjects that have received
             molecularly targeted agents less than 28 days prior to study day 1 will be permitted
             if more than 14 days and at least 5 drug half-lives have passed prior to receiving the
             first dose of HCQ

          -  Major surgery within 28 days of study day 1

          -  Any co-morbid medical disorder that may increase the risk of toxicity, in the opinion
             of the investigator

          -  All herbal supplements, vitamins, and nutritional supplements taken within the last 30
             days prior to dosing on day 1 (and continued use, if appropriate), must be reviewed
             and approved by the principal investigator (PI)

          -  Patients with pre-existing maculopathy or retinopathy of the eye
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John A Livingston</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Livingston</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-3626</phone>
    <email>jalivingston@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John A. Livingston</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-3626</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John A. Livingston</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxychloroquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

