<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03597048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01MH095254-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH095254</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03597048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A School-Based Intervention to Reduce Stigma &amp; Promote Mental-Health Service Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>A School-Based Intervention to Reduce Stigma &amp; Promote Mental-Health Service Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Riverside</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Riverside</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a school-based field experiment conducted in sixth grade classrooms to evaluate a
      multifaceted intervention designed to change attitudes and behaviors regarding mental
      illnesses. The research tests hypotheses as to whether alone or in combination interventions
      that are 1) a curriculum-based in-class presentations, 2) contact-based with a person who has
      experienced a mental illness, or 3) or based on educational materials distributed in classes
      improve knowledge/attitudes and encourage help seeking for mental health problems in a follow
      up study lasting two years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose.

      Research has documented that stigma and discrimination are painfully present in the lives of
      people with mental illnesses and their families, blocking opportunities, compromising
      self-esteem and keeping people from accessing helpful treatments The proposed project seeks a
      rigorous test, with long term follow-up, of an intervention in sixth grade classrooms that is
      designed to 1) improve knowledge, attitudes and beliefs about mental illnesses, 2) change
      behaviors toward people with mental illnesses and 3) facilitate appropriate help seeking for
      mental health problems. This study evaluates the short- and long- term effectiveness, both
      individually and in combinations, of 1) the Eliminating the Stigma of Differences curriculum,
      2) contact with a young adult with a mental illness, and 3) the use of supplemental
      materials, including posters and other media that reinforce an anti-stigma message.

      Design

      The study involves two phases. Phase I is a pre-post design to assess changes in knowledge,
      attitudes, and behaviors in sixth-grade students from before the intervention to 3 weeks
      after its conclusion. Phase II is a longitudinal assessment of Phase I participants who were
      willing to participate in home-visit assessments at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post
      intervention.

      The study was designed as a fully crossed two by two by two factorial cluster randomized
      behavioral field experiment. Sixteen schools with separate zip codes from an urban school
      district in Texas were ranked according to performance on the statewide standardized
      assessment of math, English, and science. We randomly assigned the top eight schools to one
      of eight cells; the bottom-ranked eight schools were then assigned to a cell in the reverse
      order so that, for example, the top- and bottom- ranked schools were paired. Each cell (two
      schools in each) was randomly assigned to a study condition. Before the study began, two
      schools dropped out for non-study-related reasons. For this reason the study was repeated
      during a second academic year with a new set of sixth-grade students in ﬁve of the original
      schools chosen because they had demographic characteristics similar to the lost schools. Thus
      a total of 19 sixth-grade classes from 14 schools were included in the study.

      Recruitment Procedures.

      In each school a member of the research team met with students to explain both phases of the
      study and provide students with information to take home to their guardians. The information
      included a detailed description of the study, contact numbers for Principal Investigator's,
      and a request for their children's participation in the study (both phases). In addition,
      consent/assent forms and a demographic questionnaire were included for guardians who wished
      to participate to complete. A form declining their child's participation was also included. A
      self-addressed stamped envelope was provided for return of either the questionnaire and
      consent/assent forms or the declination form. Youths were not included in the study without
      signed consent/assent forms.

      Phase I pre- and post- test -instruments were self-administered in physical education classes
      on laptop computers from February to May and September to December 2012. Each class received
      its assigned combination of interventions within one week of pretesting. Post-test
      instruments were administered within a week after the intervention all students in the
      classroom were exposed to the assigned intervention(s); only the students who provided
      consent completed the assessment instruments. In the longitudinal Phase II component of the
      study, members of the research team arranged to meet participants in their homes where
      participants completed surveys on laptop computers.

      Interventions

      Curriculum. Eliminating the Stigma of Differences is a three-module, three-hour curriculum
      delivered by teachers over a three- to six-day period. Module 1 of the intervention addresses
      the bases on which we judge others to be different; the definition, causes, and consequences
      of stigma, including for students themselves; ways to end stigma; a definition and
      description of mental illness; causes of mental illness; treatment for mental illness;
      barriers to help seeking; how stigma applies to mental illness; and sharing personal
      experiences with people who have mental illness. Modules 2 and 3 address attention deficit
      hyperactivity disorder, anxiety disorders, depression, schizophrenia, and bipolar disorder
      and include descriptions of the disorders, discussion of causes and treatments, and content
      that stimulates empathy. Fidelity to the curriculum content, quality of delivery, and level
      of student engagement were assessed by two independent observers in each classroom with a
      60-item measure based on two existing tools with good psychometric properties . Possible
      scores range from 60 to 240, with scores of 148 to 192 considered &quot;good&quot; and scores of 193 to
      240 &quot;high fidelity.&quot;

      Contact. Two young adults with a history of mental illness each made a ten-minute in-class
      presentation (20 minutes total) describing onset and course of their symptoms,
      hospitalizations and treatments, their feelings about the illness, coping strategies, and
      impact of the illness on social relationships and functioning at school, college, and work.
      Based on previous research, the talks were constructed to moderately disconfirm stereotypes
      of mental illness.

      Printed materials. Teachers prominently displayed posters in the classroom for two weeks and
      provided students with bookmarks. The materials focused on individuals' personal traits and
      abilities as opposed to language that labels a person as &quot;mentally ill.&quot;

      Samples

      Phase I Sample. A total of 751 students (60% of those invited) agreed to participate in Phase
      I. Based on calculations conducted before the study was implemented, the minimum sample size
      to conduct analysis was deemed to be 242, with alpha = .05, power = .95, and a moderate
      effect size. The achieved Phase I sample size of 721 is therefore more than adequate for
      analysis.

      Phase II Sample. Of the 751 consenting in Phase I, 479 (64%) agreed to participate in Phase
      II. and eventually 416 (87%) of those who consented were interviewed at least once during
      follow up. Of the 416 who participated in any follow up, 99% (N=412) participated in the
      6-month interview, 89% (370) at 12 months, 81% (338) at 18 months and 75% (312) at 24 months.
      Based on pre-study calculations, the minimum sample size to conduct the analysis is 273, with
      alpha =.05, power = .95, and a moderate effect size .

      Outcome measures

      Described in Section 9

      Covariates.

      A self-reported mental health symptoms checklist based on screening questions from the
      National Institute of Mental Health Diagnostic Interview Schedule for Children, Version IV,
      was administered to youths pre-intervention, 3 weeks post-intervention and at 18 and 24
      months follow up. This compact symptom screen was used to identify mental health need so that
      we could assess whether interventions led to help seeking among youths with high need.

      Other covariates assessed included sociodemographic variables a 7-point scale assessing the
      closeness of contact with a person with mental illness and a reliable 6-item measure of
      social desirability bias for children.

      Statistical Analysis.

      Phase I Short Term Effects. We use analysis of covariance to test the effects of each
      intervention on the knowledge/attitudes and social distance outcomes. We included pretest
      values of the corresponding outcome measures in the main analyses to control for any
      pre-intervention group differences that randomization msy not have accounted for. We also
      conduct analyses including any personal characteristics that may have differed at baseline to
      determine whether adding these additional controls alters conclusions.

      Phase II Longitudinal Effects. The cluster randomized longitudinal design involves 1)
      clustering of youths within classrooms and 2) assessments at multiple follow-ups within
      youths. In order to assess the extent of clustering at each level we will calculate
      intra-class correlation coefficients for each of the dependent variables. We will use
      Generalized Estimating Equations (GEE's) to account for the nesting of occasions within
      individuals. We examine whether there are significant differences by pre-intervention
      characteristics in the 8 cells of our intervention so that any differences might be accounted
      for by controlling these variables in our analysis. We begin analysis by testing a fully
      saturated model that allows for interaction between the interventions in our fully crossed
      design. We further test whether intervention effects persist across time by examining
      interaction between interventions and time periods. Finally, we explore whether the
      interventions appear to be more or less effective for groups of individuals as defined by
      gender, age, race/ethnicity and the educational level of the child's caregiver.

      Missing data. To address missing data, multiple imputation by chained equations in Stata 15.1
      is used to impute missing values. We will impute twenty five data sets, conduct regression
      analyses on these twenty five imputations and then recombine them using Rubin's rules.
      Analyses will present results that impute all missing values except when the missing value is
      the dependent variable. Sensitivity analyses include 1) analyses without imputation (complete
      case analysis) and 2) analyses with imputation of all variables including dependent
      variables. The impact of missing data on study conclusions is assessed in these sensitivity
      analyses by determining whether conclusions vary according to these different specifications.

      Strengths and Limitations.

      Beyond addressing a critically important problem for people with mental illnesses, the
      strengths of this study include: 1) the multi-component intervention that allows not one but
      three different chances for success; 2) the development of the intervention within the
      ecology of the school environment that both helps assure its acceptability in that context
      and the likelihood of its broad dissemination in other contexts like it; 3) the
      implementation of the intervention during the important developmental period of early
      adolescence; 4) the assessment of not only knowledge and attitudes but help seeking
      behaviors; 5) the relatively long follow-up period of two years, 6) the inclusion of measures
      of youths' mental health, and 7) an ethnically and socioeconomically diverse sample.

      As with any experimental study, recruitment bias can be problematic. This is important
      because nonparticipating students or their families may hold particularly negative views
      about mental illness, possibly limiting the generalizability of our findings. Our study is
      limited in its use of self-report data for both attitudes and help-seeking behaviors. Our
      inclusion of a measure of social desirability bias and our ability to control for
      pre-intervention values of dependent variables (which would include any tendency toward
      biased reporting) somewhat mitigates our concerns about reporting bias. Loss to follow up, a
      common problem for longitudinal studies, is another limitation. To gauge how large of a
      problem it is we will assess whether differential drop out occurs by assigned intervention
      and other measured variables. Further we will use sensitivity analyses to impute and missing
      values for dependent variables so that all individuals who completed at least one wave are
      included in the analysis. Despite matching schools on test scores, our cluster randomization
      of classrooms could result in pre-intervention differences between groups on some of the
      baseline characteristics we measured. As a result, we adjust for covariates and
      pre-intervention measures of dependent variables.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A two by two by two cluster randomized fully -crossed factorial design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes were self-reported and completed on lap top computers without interaction with assessors. Research staff conducting home visits were not aware of which arm participants received.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Knowledge and Attitudes about Mental Illness</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed 3 weeks post-intervention, and then 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 21-item measure (alpha .78) adapted from items created by Wahl and colleagues. It asks children their level of agreement (from strongly agree to strongly disagree) with statements such as &quot;it would be embarrassing to have a mental illness,&quot; &quot;people with mental illness tend to be violent and dangerous,&quot; &quot;schizophrenia is a mental disorder that involves multiple personalities,&quot; and &quot;I would be frightened if a person with a mental illness approached me.&quot; High scores indicate greater knowledge and more positive attitudes. Regressed change is assessed by controlling pre-intervention values of the variable. Regressed change outcomes variables are 3 weeks post intervention, 6 months post intervention, 12 months post intervention, 18 months post intervention and 24 months post intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Help Seeking Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed 3 weeks post-intervention, and then 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Participants reported whether they had talked to 1) friends, 2) parents, 3) a doctor, 4) a therapist or whether they had 5) taken medication for a mental health problem. To gauge the intensity of help seeking an index was created that assigned a 4 to youths who either saw a therapist or took medications, a 3 to youths who talked to a doctor but did not see a therapist or take medication, a 2 to youths who talked to their parents but did not see a doctor, a therapist or take medication, a 1 to youths who talked to friends but engaged in none of the other help seeking behaviors and finally a 0 to youths who engaged in none of these help seeking behaviors. Regressed change is assessed by controlling pre-intervention values of the variable. Regressed change outcomes variables are 3 weeks post intervention, 6 months post intervention, 12 months post intervention, 18 months post intervention and 24 months post intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Children's Social Distance Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed pre-intervention, 3 weeks post-intervention, and then 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>This scale is a six item is a shortened and slightly modified version of Wahl and colleagues children's social distance scale (alpha = .89). Participants are presented with the question &quot;Would it be okay with you to….&quot; followed by six questions including the following, &quot;Have someone with mental illness as a neighbor?&quot; &quot;Sit next to someone with a mental illness in class?&quot; and &quot;Work on a class project with someone with mental illness?&quot; Response categories were &quot;definitely yes&quot; (1), &quot;probably yes&quot; (2), &quot;probably no&quot; (3) and &quot;definitely no&quot; (4). Regressed change is assessed by controlling pre-intervention values of the variable. Regressed change outcomes variables are 3 weeks post intervention, 6 months post intervention, 12 months post intervention, 18 months post intervention and 24 months post intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Problem Behavior Frequency Aggression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed 3 weeks post-intervention, and then 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Is a 19-item scale measuring the frequency of acted and received aggressive behaviors. In includes items assessing physical contact such as hitting or pushing, verbal harassment and threats of physical violence and relational items including spreading rumors or intentionally being left out. Regressed change is assessed by controlling pre-intervention values of the variable. Regressed change outcomes variables are 3 weeks post intervention, 6 months post intervention, 12 months post intervention, 18 months post intervention and 24 months post intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Mental Health Problem Recognition</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed 3 weeks post-intervention, and then 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Given that a critical step in help seeking is recognizing a problem this aspect is measured by asking participants: &quot;Was there a time in the past six months, when your you seemed to have an emotional or behavioral problem like being anxious, depressed, hyperactive, withdrawn, or always getting into trouble?&quot; (Yes=1/No=0). Regressed change is assessed by controlling pre-intervention values of the variable. Regressed change outcomes variables are 3 weeks post intervention, 6 months post intervention, 12 months post intervention, 18 months post intervention and 24 months post intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">751</enrollment>
  <condition>Stigma, Social</condition>
  <condition>Mental Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received only the curriculum intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received only the contact intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received only the materials intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum and Contact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received both curriculum and contact interventions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received curriculum and materials interventions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received contact and materials intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum, Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received curriculum, contact and materials interventions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Curriculum</intervention_name>
    <description>The curriculum intervention is a three- module, three-hour curriculum delivered by teachers in sixth grade classrooms over a three- to six-day period. The curriculum is designed to increase knowledge and improve attitudes about mental illnesses so as to improve the school climate with respect to mental illness stigma and encourage help seeking for youth in need.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum and Contact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum, Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Eliminating the Stigma of Differences</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Contact</intervention_name>
    <description>The contact intervention involves two college students—a 27-year-old male with a history of bipolar I disorder and a 24-year-old female with a history of bipolar II disorder—who each make a ten-minute in-class presentation (20 minutes total) describing onset and course of their symptoms, hospitalizations and treatments, their feelings about the illness, coping strategies, and impact of the illness on social relationships and functioning at school and work.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum and Contact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum, Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Materials</intervention_name>
    <description>The materials intervention is implemented by teachers who prominently display posters in the classroom for two weeks and provide students with bookmarks. The materials focus on individuals' with mental illnesses emphasizing their personal traits and abilities as opposed to language that labels a person as &quot;mentally ill.&quot;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Curriculum, Contact and Materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Materials</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        • Sixth-grade students enrolled in required physical education/health classes at 14
        participating schools in the Arlington, Texas School district.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Sixth grade students who did not have caregiver's consent to participate.

          -  Sixth grade students who did not give assent to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corrigan P. How stigma interferes with mental health care. Am Psychol. 2004 Oct;59(7):614-625. doi: 10.1037/0003-066X.59.7.614.</citation>
    <PMID>15491256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corrigan PW, Larson JE, Michaels PJ, Buchholz BA, Rossi RD, Fontecchio MJ, Castro D, Gause M, Krzyżanowski R, Rüsch N. Diminishing the self-stigma of mental illness by coming out proud. Psychiatry Res. 2015 Sep 30;229(1-2):148-54. doi: 10.1016/j.psychres.2015.07.053. Epub 2015 Jul 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26213379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>CRANDALL VC, CRANDALL VJ, KATKOVSKY W. A CHILDREN'S SOCIAL DESIRABILITY QUESTIONNAIRE. J Consult Psychol. 1965 Feb;29:27-36.</citation>
    <PMID>14277395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dusenbury L, Brannigan R, Falco M, Hansen WB. A review of research on fidelity of implementation: implications for drug abuse prevention in school settings. Health Educ Res. 2003 Apr;18(2):237-56. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12729182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Link BG, Struening EL, Neese-Todd S, Asmussen S, Phelan JC. Stigma as a barrier to recovery: The consequences of stigma for the self-esteem of people with mental illnesses. Psychiatr Serv. 2001 Dec;52(12):1621-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11726753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Link BG, Yang LH, Phelan JC, Collins PY. Measuring mental illness stigma. Schizophr Bull. 2004;30(3):511-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15631243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pullmann MD, Bruns EJ, Sather AK. Evaluating fidelity to the wraparound service model for youth: application of item response theory to the Wraparound Fidelity Index. Psychol Assess. 2013 Jun;25(2):583-98. doi: 10.1037/a0031864. Epub 2013 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23544392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raudenbush SW, Bryk AS. Hierarchical linear models: Applications and data analysis methods. Newbury Park, CA: Sage; 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snijders TAB, Bosker R. Multilevel analysis. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage; 1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wahl OF, Susin J, Kaplan L, Lax A, Zatina D. Changing Knowledge and Attitudes with a Middle School Mental Health Education Curriculum. Stigma Res Action. 2011;1(1):44-53.</citation>
    <PMID>21731851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>West P, Sweeting H, Der G, Barton J, Lucas C. Voice-DISC identified DSM-IV disorders among 15-year-olds in the west of Scotland. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2003 Aug;42(8):941-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12874496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Painter K, Phelan JC, DuPont-Reyes MJ, Barkin KF, Villatoro AP, Link BG. Evaluation of Antistigma Interventions With Sixth-Grade Students: A School-Based Field Experiment. Psychiatr Serv. 2017 Apr 1;68(4):345-352. doi: 10.1176/appi.ps.201600052. Epub 2016 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27842475</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Riverside</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bruce Link</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Distinguished Professor of Public Policy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stigma intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

