<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03599700</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MPN</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HABIBA</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03599700</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk Factors and Predictors of Thrombosis in Myeloprolferative Neoplasms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk Factors and Predictors of Thrombosis in Patients With Philadelphia Negative Myeloprolferative Neoplasms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the clinical risk factors and predictable biomarkers of thrombotic complications in
      cases of philadelphia negative myeloproliferative disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Classic BCR-ABL negative chronic myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN) are stem cell disorders
      characterized by abnormal myeloid proliferation and increased blood cell counts and comprise
      polycythemia vera (PV), essential thrombocythemia (ET) and primary myelofibrosis (PMF).

      Myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN) are common malignancies in elderly individuals as the
      combined annual incidence rates of classical MPNs were reported to be 0.84, 1.03, and 0.47
      per 100,000 respectively for PV, ET, and PMF but with a wide variation in prevalence rates
      reported in different studies. The 5-year relative survival rates are 84.8, 89.9, and 39% for
      PV, ET and PMF patients, respectively.

      Thromboembolic complications represent a major cause of morbidity and mortality in MPN,
      particularly in PV and ET. The mechanisms underlying increased thrombotic risk in chronic
      myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN) are incompletely understood.

      Several pathophysiological mechanisms help explain the increased likelihood of thrombosis in
      these patients. Factors, such as leukocyte and platelet activation leading to the formation
      of leukocyte-platelet aggregates, activation of the coagulation cascade by microparticles,
      high levels of inflammatory cytokines, and endothelial dysfunction have a crucial role in
      thrombosis in MPN patients.

      Accurate prediction of the thrombotic risk still represents a challenge and adequate
      predictive biomarkers are not available. The mechanisms underlying thrombosis involve a
      complex interplay among blood cells, the endothelium and the coagulation system. Both
      increased blood counts and cellular activation, which is due to hyperactivation of
      intracellular signaling pathways and enhanced interaction between blood cells, are implicated
      in the thrombotic predisposition.

      The JAK2V617F mutation is a diagnostic marker for MPN and it also plays an important role in
      patient treatment since inhibition of JAK2-associated proliferative pathways has the
      potential to inhibit cell proliferation in MPNs. This mutation is present in ~95% of PV
      patients and 50% of ET or PMF patients. Thrombosis and hemostasis are major complications
      that affect the life expectancy of patients with MPN.

      Current guidelines recommend testing for JAK2 mutations in any patient suspected to have an
      MPN. JAK2 mutation leads to distinct changes in hematopoietic cells that increase the
      likelihood of thrombus formation.

      The risk of thrombosis, in both PV and ET, exceeds 20% and a substantial proportion of
      patients experience vasomotor disturbances (e.g. headaches, lightheadedness, acral
      paresthesias, erythromelalgia, atypical chest pain, ocular disturbances, tinnitus) and in
      case of PV, pruritus.

      Mean platelet volume (MPV) is largely considered as a useful indirect marker of platelet
      activation. Larger platelets are metabolically and enzymatically more active, and have a
      greater prothrombotic potential. Elevated MPV is associated with other markers of platelet
      activity, including increased platelet aggregation, increased thromboxane synthesis and
      beta-thromboglobulin release, and increased expression of adhesion molecules.

      High sensitivity CRP is an inflammatory marker might be useful to reflect a condition of
      chronic inflammation which is associated with the disease severity .

      In addition, Elevated CRP and elevated LDH are risk factors for survival in MPN patients.

      Elevated γ-Glutamyl (γ-GT) transferase is an independent risk factor for Splanchnic venous
      thrombosis (SVT) presence in MPN.

      About 30% of vascular events in Ph-negative MPN patients are VTE, which generally present as
      lower limb deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary artery embolism. However, in Ph-negative MPN,
      VTE characteristically occurs in uncommon locations such as splanchnic veins, including
      hepatic veins (presenting Budd-Chiari syndrome), portal and mesenteric veins, or, less
      frequently, cerebral veins or sinuses. In patients with MPN, the prevalence of CVT is 3-7% of
      cases.

      Myeloproliferative neoplasms are known to be pro-thrombotic diseases (arterial and venous).
      For both of ET and PV, thromboses occur more frequently in arterial sites (between 64 and 75%
      for PV, and between 72 and 91% for ET).

      JAK2 mutation can affect cardiac arteries and veins in ET and PV, which results in
      thrombosis, ischemia and other cardiovascular events. JAK/STAT signaling pathway plays an
      important role in heart diseases. High incidence of atrial arrhythmias among patients with ET
      or PV. The patients were older, cumulating more cardiovascular risk factors inducing more
      thrombotic events mainly in arteries, and have a higher incidence of death.

      The importance of treatment compliance has now been clearly established in many pathological
      conditions as poor adherence has a negative impact on clinical evolution and non-adherence to
      cytoreductive therapy was associated with a significant reduction in the complete
      haematological remission rate but no significant association between thrombosis or death and
      non-adherence was found. This may be related to the fact that thrombosis is a more acute
      event, depending on the immediate hemostatic status at the time of thrombus constitution,
      whereas the phenotypic evolution of chronic haematological malignancies may be more the
      result of long term evolution of the clone, reflecting its exposure to therapeutic pressure.

      Patients with MPN should also avoid factors that are known to increase risk of VTE, including
      systemic hormone therapy such as oral contraceptive pills and smoking, and optimize
      cardiovascular risk factors, including control of blood pressure, diabetes, and cholesterol,
      in order to minimize thrombotic complications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of thromboembolic events in Philadelphia negative myeloproliferative neoplasms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of thromboembolic events e.g. portal vein thrombosis, deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism at patients newly diagnosed as philadelphia negative myeloproliferative neoplasms during the period of the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>survival of patients with Philadelphia negative myeloproliferative neoplasms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>life expectancy and causes of death( e.g. thrombosis, bleeding, infections, leukemic transformation)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">165</enrollment>
  <condition>Thrombosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>myeloproliferative neoplasms</arm_group_label>
    <description>history taking
physical examination
laboratory investigations: Complete blood counts Bone marrow examination JAK2 V617F mutation. High-sensitivity C-reactive protein ESR Uric acid level LDH GGT BCR- ABL fusion gene IL-8 , TNF-Alpha Serum ferritin Serum albumin, transferrin, alpha feto protein Complement system: C3, C4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>myeloproliferative neoplasms</intervention_name>
    <description>BLOOD SAMPLING</description>
    <arm_group_label>myeloproliferative neoplasms</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        prospective cohort study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        age &gt; 18 years

        All patients diagnosed as BCR-ABL negative myeloproliferative neoplasm e.g:

        Polycythemia vera Essential thrombocythemia Primary myelofibrosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BCR- ABL positive MPN e.g CML

          -  Secondary erythrocytosis.

          -  Secondary thrombocytosis.

          -  Secondary bone marrow fibrosis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>howida nafady</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>extracted from this organization's records</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>maha mohammed</last_name>
    <phone>01097278659</phone>
    <email>maha.azez@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>safenazh hussein</last_name>
    <phone>01007711092</phone>
    <email>drsafenazh@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Hematology Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <zip>22413749</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbui T, Finazzi G, Falanga A. Myeloproliferative neoplasms and thrombosis. Blood. 2013 Sep 26;122(13):2176-84. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-03-460154. Epub 2013 Jul 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23823316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marin Oyarzún CP, Carestia A, Lev PR, Glembotsky AC, Castro Ríos MA, Moiraghi B, Molinas FC, Marta RF, Schattner M, Heller PG. Neutrophil extracellular trap formation and circulating nucleosomes in patients with chronic myeloproliferative neoplasms. Sci Rep. 2016 Dec 13;6:38738. doi: 10.1038/srep38738.</citation>
    <PMID>27958278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ball S, Thein KZ, Maiti A, Nugent K. Thrombosis in Philadelphia negative classical myeloproliferative neoplasms: a narrative review on epidemiology, risk assessment, and pathophysiologic mechanisms. J Thromb Thrombolysis. 2018 May;45(4):516-528. doi: 10.1007/s11239-018-1623-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29404876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang W, Qi J, Zhao S, Shen W, Dai L, Han W, Huang M, Wang Z, Ruan C, Wu D, Han Y. Clinical significance of circulating microparticles in Ph(-) myeloproliferative neoplasms. Oncol Lett. 2017 Aug;14(2):2531-2536. doi: 10.3892/ol.2017.6459. Epub 2017 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28789461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>How J, Zhou A, Oh ST. Splanchnic vein thrombosis in myeloproliferative neoplasms: pathophysiology and molecular mechanisms of disease. Ther Adv Hematol. 2017 Mar;8(3):107-118. doi: 10.1177/2040620716680333. Epub 2016 Dec 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28246554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tefferi A. Polycythemia vera and essential thrombocythemia: 2013 update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and management. Am J Hematol. 2013 Jun;88(6):507-16. doi: 10.1002/ajh.23417.</citation>
    <PMID>23695894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kissova J, Bulikova A, Ovesna P, Bourkova L, Penka M. Increased mean platelet volume and immature platelet fraction as potential predictors of thrombotic complications in BCR/ABL-negative myeloproliferative neoplasms. Int J Hematol. 2014 Nov;100(5):429-36. doi: 10.1007/s12185-014-1673-0. Epub 2014 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25227185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lussana F, Carobbio A, Salmoiraghi S, Guglielmelli P, Vannucchi AM, Bottazzi B, Leone R, Mantovani A, Barbui T, Rambaldi A. Driver mutations (JAK2V617F, MPLW515L/K or CALR), pentraxin-3 and C-reactive protein in essential thrombocythemia and polycythemia vera. J Hematol Oncol. 2017 Feb 22;10(1):54. doi: 10.1186/s13045-017-0425-z.</citation>
    <PMID>28228104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Görtzen J, Hunka LM, Vonnahme M, Praktiknjo M, Kaifie A, Fimmers R, Jansen C, Heine A, Lehmann J, Goethert JR, Gattermann N, Goekkurt E, Platzbecker U, Brossart P, Strassburg CP, Brummendorf TH, Koschmieder S, Wolf D, Trebicka J. γ-Glutamyl Transferase Is an Independent Biomarker of Splanchnic Thrombosis in Patients With Myeloproliferative Neoplasm. Medicine (Baltimore). 2016 May;95(20):e3355. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000003355.</citation>
    <PMID>27196445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamy M, Palazzo P, Agius P, Chomel JC, Ciron J, Berthomet A, Cantagrel P, Prigent J, Ingrand P, Puyade M, Neau JP. Should We Screen for Janus Kinase 2 V617F Mutation in Cerebral Venous Thrombosis? Cerebrovasc Dis. 2017;44(3-4):97-104. doi: 10.1159/000471891. Epub 2017 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28609766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahé K, Delluc A, Chauveau A, Castellant P, Mottier D, Dalbies F, Berthou C, Guillerm G, Lippert E, Ianotto JC. Incidence and impact of atrial arrhythmias on thrombotic events in MPNs. Ann Hematol. 2018 Jan;97(1):101-107. doi: 10.1007/s00277-017-3164-x. Epub 2017 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29164292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haybar H, Khodadi E, Shahjahani M, Saki N. Cardiovascular Events: A Challenge in JAK2-positive Myeloproliferative Neoplasms. Cardiovasc Hematol Disord Drug Targets. 2017;17(3):161-166. doi: 10.2174/1871529X17666171030122345. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29086702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le Calloch R, Lacut K, Le Gall-Ianotto C, Nowak E, Abiven M, Tempescul A, Dalbies F, Eveillard JR, Ugo V, Giraudier S, Guillerm G, Lippert E, Berthou C, Ianotto JC. Non-adherence to treatment with cytoreductive and/or antithrombotic drugs is frequent and associated with an increased risk of complications in patients with polycythemia vera or essential thrombocythemia (OUEST study). Haematologica. 2018 Apr;103(4):607-613. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2017.180448. Epub 2017 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29246923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin K. Risk Factors for and Management of MPN-Associated Bleeding and Thrombosis. Curr Hematol Malig Rep. 2017 Oct;12(5):389-396. doi: 10.1007/s11899-017-0400-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28948496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maha Mohammed Abdel-Aziz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>thrombosis</keyword>
  <keyword>myeloproliferative neoplasms</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

