<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03590210</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GISG-15</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-001083-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03590210</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combined Treatment With Nivolumab and Trabectedin in Patients With Metastatic or Inoperable Soft Tissue Sarcomas</brief_title>
  <acronym>NiTraSarc</acronym>
  <official_title>NiTraSarc Combined Treatment With Nivolumab and Trabectedin in Patients With Metastatic or Inoperable Soft Tissue Sarcomas - The NiTraSarc Phase II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medicine Greifswald</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut für Klinische Krebsforschung IKF GmbH at Krankenhaus Nordwest</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PharmaMar</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medicine Greifswald</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The &quot;NiTraSarc&quot; trial evaluates the efficacy and feasibility (as determined by the safety and
      tolerability) of combined treatment with trabectedin and nivolumab in patients with
      metastatic or inoperable soft tissue sarcomas
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Undoubtedly, there is a strong medical need for new efficacious therapies for patients with
      advanced soft tissue sarcomas. While immune oncology treatment approaches like inhibition of
      immune checkpoints by administration of anti PD-1 / PD-L1 antibodies displayed very promising
      clinical activity in several types of tumors, current data points out to only limited
      activity of mono-agent immunotherapy in soft tissue sarcomas (especially in leiomyosarcomas)
      - although this type of tumor demonstrably displays a certain grade of immunogenicity. That
      means, STS patients are currently not able to benefit from the advancements in cancer
      immunotherapy which led to remarkable improvements in outcome in some other tumor entities in
      the last few years.

      Interestingly, most recent data indicates that trabectedin could enhance the activity of
      immune-modulating agents via its influence on the tumor micro-environment and the reduction
      of tumor associated macrophages. Furthermore, first clinical data obtained from a feasibility
      study on combined nivolumab/trabectedin therapy in STS patients did not report on significant
      toxicities when combining the two agents, thereby justifying combination of nivolumab and
      trabectedin utilizing standard dosages.

      Therefore, this phase II study will examine if combination of nivolumab with trabectedin is
      feasible (safe and well tolerated) and efficacious by utilizing potential synergistic effects
      of both agents. In the long run, the results of this phase II trial could build the basis for
      further evaluation of the efficacy of the trabectedin / nivolumab combination in a randomized
      clinical trial involving larger patient numbers. Finally, this could render patients with STS
      accessible to immunotherapeutics - a promising new class of drugs for anti-cancer treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 8, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two group, non-randomized</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>progression free survival rate at 6 months - PFSR6</measure>
    <time_frame>after 6 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint of the trial is the progression-free survival rate after 6 months (PFSR6), assessed by applying RECIST 1.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>safety, as measured by: - Incidence of adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), adverse events leading to discontinuation, and deaths - Incidence of clinical laboratory test abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary safety endpoint is to assess the feasibility of combined treatment with trabectedin and nivolumab in patients with metastatic or inoperable soft tissue sarcomas as determined by the safety and tolerability of the combination treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Objective Response Rate (ORR) defined as the number and percentage of participants with a best overall response (BOR) of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR). Best overall response (BOR) is defined as the best response designation, recorded between the date of first dose and the date of the initial objectively documented tumor progression per RECIST v1.1 or the date of subsequent therapy or death date, whichever occurs first. For participants without documented progression or subsequent therapy, all available response designations will contribute to the BOR determination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as the time from date of the first dosing date of any study medication to the date of death (due to any cause). Subjects who are alive will be censored at the last known alive dates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time from the first dosing date of any study medication to the date of the first objectively documented tumor progression, as determined by investigators (per RECIST v1.1), or death due to any cause. Subjects who die without a reported prior progression will be considered to have progressed on the date of their death. Subjects who did not progress or die will be censored on the date of their last tumor assessment. Subjects who did not have any on study tumor assessments and did not die will be censored on the first dosing date of study medication. Subjects who started any subsequent anti-cancer therapy without a prior reported progression will be censored at the last tumor assessment prior to initiation of the subsequent anti-cancer therapy. In addition to PFS according to RECIST v1.1, PFS according to immune related RECIST 1.1 (irRECIST 1.1) will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of disease stabilization (DoDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of disease stabilization is defined as the sum of duration of response (DoR) and duration of stable disease (DoS) in months. So DoDS is applicable to subjects with best overall response as either CR or PR or SD and it is defined as time from the first assessment of CR or PR or SD until the date of the first occurrence of PD, or until the date of death (if occurred within predefined time period). In case of censored event, the DoDS is censored on the date of last tumor assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PDL-1 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>PDL-1 expression will be quantified during central pathological examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Adult Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - L-sarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with unresectable or metastatic liposarcoma or leiomyosarcoma who received a prior anthracycline-containing regimen will receive drug treatment with trabectedin (1 cycle mono-therapy) followed by trabectedin/nivolumab combination (up to 15 additional cycles); 16 cycles in total</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - non-L-sarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with unresectable or metastatic soft tissue sarcoma other than liposarcoma or leiomyosarcoma who received a prior anthracycline-containing regimen (GIST excluded) will receive drug treatment with trabectedin (1 cycle mono-therapy) followed by trabectedin/nivolumab combination (up to 15 additional cycles); 16 cycles in total</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trabectedin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cycle 1 to 16 1.5mg/m² IV over 24 hours, q3w</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - L-sarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - non-L-sarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yondelis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Cycle 2 to 16 240 mg IV over 30 minutes, q3w</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - L-sarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - non-L-sarcoma</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Group A:

        1 Patients must have histologically confirmed liposarcoma or leiomyosarcoma

        Group B:

          1. Patients must have histologically confirmed soft tissue sarcoma (STS) other than
             liposarcoma or leiomyosarcoma (GIST excluded)

             Both Groups (A and B):

          2. ≥ 1 prior systemic therapy for sarcoma, including adjuvant systemic therapy
             (anthracycline-containing regimen)

          3. Signed Written Informed Consent

          4. Men and women aged ≥ 18 years.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 1.

          6. Measurable disease (according to RECIST criteria version 1.1)

          7. Locally advanced/unresectable or metastatic disease

          8. No prior therapy with ipilimumab or nivolumab, or any agent targeting programmed cell
             death 1 (PD-1), PD-L1 or cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein 4 (CTLA-4), or any
             other antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell costimulation or immune
             checkpoint pathways

          9. No treatment with biologic therapy, immunotherapy, chemotherapy, investigational agent
             for malignancy, or radiation ≤ 28 days before study registration; no treatment with
             nitrosourea or mitomycin ≤ 42 days before study registration

         10. Patients should have resolution of any toxic effects of prior therapy (except
             alopecia) to NCI CTCAE, version 4.0, grade 1 or less

         11. Patients must have a formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor block OR 1
             representative hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) and 20 unstained sarcoma tissue slides
             available for submission to central pathology review. If no archival tissue is
             available, a fresh biopsy has to be performed during screening.

         12. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500/mm3

         13. Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3

         14. Creatine phosphokinase (CPK) ≤2,5 x ULN

         15. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) OR calculated (calc.) creatinine
             clearance ≥ 60 mL/min (calculated by using the Cockcroft-Gault formula)

         16. Total bilirubin ≤ upper limit of normal (ULN). If total bilirubin is greater than (&gt;)
             ULN, measure indirect bilirubin to evaluate for Gilbert's syndrome (if direct
             bilirubin is within normal range, participant may be eligible).

         17. AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

         18. AP ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

         19. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dl. If hemoglobin &lt;9 g/dl, blood transfusion is permitted. If
             hemoglobin cannot be enhanced to ≥ 9 g/dl, patient cannot be included into the study.

         20. Thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) within normal limits (WNL); supplementation is
             acceptable to achieve a TSH WNL; in patients with abnormal TSH if free T4 is normal
             and patient is clinically euthyroid, patient is eligible

         21. Not pregnant and not nursing; for women of childbearing potential who are sexually
             active, a negative pregnancy test (urinary or serum beta-HCG) at screening (performed
             ≤7 days prior to registration) is required.

         22. Female participants must be postmenopausal (no spontaneous menses for at least 2
             years), surgically sterile (have had a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy, tubal
             ligation, or otherwise be incapable of pregnancy), abstinent (at the discretion of the
             investigator), or if sexually active, follow the contraceptive guidance in Appendix 4
             throughout the duration of study treatment and for a minimum of 5 months after the
             last dose of study medication. Male participants must agree to use an adequate
             contraception method as deemed appropriate by the investigator (e.g., vasectomy,
             double-barrier, partner using effective contraception) and to not donate sperm for a
             minimum of 7 months after the last dose of study medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior exposure to trabectedin

          2. Active known or suspected autoimmune disease (e.g. autoimmune colitis, autoimmune
             panhypopituitarism, autoimmune adrenal insufficiency)

             EXCEPT:

             i) Subjects with vitiligo, type 1 diabetes mellitus, resolved childhood asthma or
             atopy are permitted to enroll.

             ii) Subjects with suspected autoimmune thyroid disorders may be enrolled if they are
             currently euthyroid or with residual hypothyroidism requiring only hormone
             replacement.

             iii) Subjects with psoriasis requiring systemic therapy must be excluded from
             enrollment.

          3. Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection are excluded unless cluster
             of differentiation (CD)4+ cells are &gt; 350 and no viral load is detectable

          4. Symptomatic, untreated, or uncontrolled brain metastases present

          5. Known significant chronic liver disease, such as cirrhosis or active hepatitis B or C

               -  Hepatitis B can be defined as (all of the following conditions must be met):

                    -  Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) &gt; 6 months

                    -  Serum hepatitis B virus (HBV) deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) ≥2,000 IU/ml (104
                       copies/ml)

                    -  Persistent or intermittent elevation in alanine aminotransferase
                       (ALT)/alanine aminotransferase (AST) levels

                    -  Liver biopsy showing chronic hepatitis with moderate or severe
                       necroinflammation

               -  Hepatitis C can be defined as:

                    -  Hepatitis C antibody (Ab) positive

                    -  Presence of hepatitis C virus (HCV) ribonucleic acid (RNA)

          6. Known active pulmonary disease with hypoxia defined as:

               -  Oxygen saturation &lt; 85% on room air or

               -  Oxygen saturation &lt; 88% despite supplemental oxygen

          7. Systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents)
             or other immunosuppressive medications within 14 days of registration

          8. Myocardial infarct within 6 months before enrollment, New York Heart Association Class
             II or greater heart failure, uncontrolled angina, severe uncontrolled ventricular
             arrhythmias, clinically significant pericardial disease, or electrocardiographic
             evidence of acute ischemic or active conduction system abnormalities

          9. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, poorly controlled
             hypertension or diabetes, ongoing active infection, or psychiatric illness/social
             situation that may potentially impair the participant's compliance with study
             procedures

         10. Unwilling or unable to have a central venous catheter

         11. Known allergies, hypersensitivity, or intolerance to trabectedin, dexamethasone, or
             their excipients, or monoclonal antibodies (biologics) therapy

         12. Pregnant or breast-feeding

         13. Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would compromise the
             well-being of the participant or the study or prevent the participant from meeting or
             performing study requirements

         14. On-treatment participation in another clinical study in the period 30 days prior to
             start of study treatment and during the study.

         15. History of allogeneic solid organ or tissue transplant including allogeneic
             hematopoetic stem cell transplantation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Pink, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Klinik und Poliklinik für Innere Medizin C, Hämatologie und Onkologie, Transplantationszentrum, Universitätsmedizin Greifswald</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Pink, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 33631 7-3527</phone>
    <email>daniel.pink@helios-gesundheit.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Helios Klinikum Bad Saarow, Klinik für Hämatologie, Onkologie und Palliativmedizin, Sarkomzentrum Berlin-Brandenburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bad Saarow</city>
        <zip>15526</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Simone Micheel</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Pink, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Helios Klinikum Berlin Buch, Klinik für interdisziplinäre Onkologie, Sarkomzentrum Berlin-Brandenburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13125</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Miriam Hammermeister</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Reichardt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Campus Virchow Klinikum Medizinische Klinik mit Schwerpunkt Hämatologie, Onkologie und Tumorimmunologie (CC14)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13353</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mario Lorenz</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anne Flörcken, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Fakultät &quot;Carl Gustav Carus&quot; der TU Dresden, Medizinische Klinik I</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <zip>01307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diana Löscher</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephan Richter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin Greifswald, Klinik und Poliklinik für Innere Medizin C, Hämatologie und Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greifswald</city>
        <zip>17475</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeanette Bahr</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian Schmidt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Medizinische Fakultät Mannheim der Universität Heidelberg, Interdisziplinäres Tumorzentrum Mannheim (ITM)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <zip>68167</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monika Mathew</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bernd Kasper, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Münster, Medizinische Klinik A Hämatologie / Onkologie / Pneumologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Friederike Heckmann</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thorsten Kessler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Tübingen, Innere Medizin II - Medizinische Onkologie und Pneumologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <zip>72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gabi Jany</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barbara Hermes, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Würzburg, Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik II Hämatologie / Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Würzburg</city>
        <zip>97080</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ruth Dunkel</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Kortüm, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trabectedin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

