<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03599921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>47919</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03599921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment Outcome in Eating Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment Outcome in Eating Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Do the current eating disorder treatments, i.e., Family-based Treatment (FBT) and Enhanced
      Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT-E), offered at the Center for the Treatment of Eating
      Disorders (CTED) demonstrate effectiveness? Specifically, which type of treatment is most
      effective for which diagnoses? Participants with Anorexia Nervosa (AN), Bulimia Nervosa (BN),
      Other Specified Feeding or Eating Disorder (OSFED), or Unspecified Feeding or Eating Disorder
      (UFED) in this study will self select one of the two treatment groups, FBT or CBT-E.

      Additionally, does Family-based Treatment (FBT) modified for Avoidant/Restrictive Food Intake
      Disorder (ARFID) and Family-based Treatment (FBT) combined with the Unified Protocol (UP) for
      Transdiagnostic Treatment of Emotional Disorders (FBT+UP for ARFID) demonstrate effectiveness
      for patients with an Avoidant/Restrictive Food Intake Disorder (ARFID) diagnosis?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given a significant number of patients who presented for treatment at the Center for the
      Treatment of Eating Disorders (CTED) and were enrolled in this effectiveness study met
      criteria for a diagnosis of Avoidant/Restrictive Food Intake Disorder (ARFID), and because
      there are currently no randomized control trials systematically evaluating
      children/adolescents with ARFID, a secondary aim was added to this study.

      The secondary aim will evaluate the preliminary effectiveness of two treatment groups
      including: Family-based Treatment (FBT) modified for ARFID and Family-based Treatment (FBT)
      combined with the Unified Protocol (UP) for Transdiagnostic Treatment of Emotional Disorders
      (FBT+UP for ARFID) for ARFID patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 6, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Therapy effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at end of treatment (an average of 6-9 months) and at 6 and 12 month follow-up.</time_frame>
    <description>1) Evaluate which therapies work effectively for the treatment of eating disorders, and which types of treatments are most effective for specific diagnoses.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment moderators</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at end of treatment (an average of 6-9 months) and at 6 and 12 month follow-up.</time_frame>
    <description>1) Explore predictors and moderators of treatment outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">190</enrollment>
  <condition>Eating Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Family-based Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants will receive family-based treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Cognitive behavioral therapy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants will receive enhance cognitive behavioral therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Family-based Treatment for ARFID</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants will receive family-based treatment modified for Avoidant/Restrictive Food Intake Disorder (ARFID).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FBT + UP for ARFID</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants will receive family-based treatment with the Unified Protocol for the Transdiagnostic Treatment of Emotional Disorders in Children and Adolescents, named FBT + UP for ARFID.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Family-based treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Family-based treatment, or FBT, is the leading evidenced based therapy for children and adolescents with an eating disorder.
The treatment is a talking type of treatment that involves the whole family and primarily focuses on helping parents play an active and positive role in helping to restore the patient's weight, then hand control of eating back to the patient as is age appropriate. Toward the end of treatment, it is concerned with developmental issues that may have been impacted by the illness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Family-based Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Cognitive behavioral therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Enhanced Cognitive behavioral therapy, or CBT-E, is a leading evidence based treatment for adolescents and adults with an eating disorder.
The treatment is a one-to-one talking type of treatment that primarily focuses on what is keeping the eating problem going. It is therefore mainly concerned with the present and the future. It addresses the origins of the problem as needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Cognitive behavioral therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Family-based treatment modified for ARFID</intervention_name>
    <description>Family-based treatment modified for individuals with an ARFID diagnosis is a proposed therapy for treating ARFID.
The treatment is a talking type of treatment that involves the whole family and primarily focuses on helping parents play an active and positive role in helping to restore patient's weight and variety in eating, as needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Family-based Treatment for ARFID</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FBT + UP for ARFID</intervention_name>
    <description>Family-based treatment combined with the Unified Protocol for the Transdiagnostic Treatment of Emotional Disorders in Children and Adolescents is a proposed therapy for treating ARFID.
The treatment is a talking type of treatment that involves the whole family and begins with focus on psychoeducation, family engagement, and weight gain as needed. The Unified Protocol is then added to build skills that empower the patient to cope with difficult emotions, address avoidance, and increase tolerance of emotions or disgust responses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FBT + UP for ARFID</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Labs
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The investigators plan to enroll 1000 patients, both male and female, ages 6 to adult (18
        and older) over a 5 year period. Patients who have been given a Diagnostic and Statistical
        Manual, 5th Edition (DSM-5) eating disorder diagnosis, and who are seeking outpatient
        treatment will all be approached for consent to participate in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be at least 6 years of age, attending the CTED clinic for outpatient
             treatment of a Diagnostic and Statistical Manual, 5th Edition (DSM-5) diagnosed eating
             disorder in order to be included in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who are receiving inpatient services only and will not return to CTED for
             outpatient treatment.

          -  Participants with a co-morbid medical disorder known to influence eating or weight.

          -  Participants presenting with a significant psychotic disorder.

          -  Participants who are acutely suicidal.

          -  Participants who demonstrate significant substance abuse and/or substance dependence.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sarah Eckhardt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Family-based Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Enhanced Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Anorexia Nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Other Specified Feeding or Eating Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Bulimia Nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Unspecified Feeding or Eating Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Avoidant/Restrictive Food Intake Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Unified Protocol for the Transdiagnostic Treatment of Emotional Disorders in Children and Adolescents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

