<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03596320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>crbchildren</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03596320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Yield of Colonoscopy in Children With Rectal Bleeding</brief_title>
  <official_title>Yield of Colonoscopy in Children With Bleeding Per Rectum Attending Gastrointestinal Endoscopic Unit In Assuit University Children Hospital</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      description study of colonscopy in children with bleeding per rectum attending
      gastrointestinal endoscopic unit in assiut university children hospital from 2014-2019
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rectal bleeding is a source of anxiety for both children and parents and is frequently
      encountered clinical complaint in routine practice in pediatric patient . Lower
      gastrointestinal bleeding means bleeding from sites distal to the ligament of treitz and
      presents as rectal bleeding while passage of bright red blood from the rectum is called
      hematochezia.

      The etiology of rectal bleeding is different in children than in adult according to age group
      which enables physicians to make appropriate differential diagnosis. There are several
      etiologies for rectal bleeding in pediatric practice ranging from mild condition requiring
      little or no treatment to severe and life-threating ones requiring immediate intervention.
      The etiologies include anal fissure, food allergy, infectious enterocolitis,
      Meckel'sdiverticulum, intussusceptions, volvulus, lymphonodular hyperplasia, inflammatory
      bowel disease, angiodysplasia, hemorrhoids, and hemolytic -uremic syndrome. Common causes of
      bleeding per rectum in children vary between studies . Once the bleeding is suspected to be
      coming from lower gastrointestinal tract it warrant an evaluation in all cases by
      proctosigmoidoscopy followed by colonoscopy .

      Colonoscopy is the examination of choice for diagnosis and management of bleeding per rectum
      in children . The benefits of colonoscopy include identification of the site of bleeding
      regardless of the rate or presence of bleeding through visualization the entire length of the
      colon often include the distal ileum by possibility of endoscpic intervention and biopsy
      taking to make and confirm the diagnosis and follow up evaluation, so gastrointestinal
      endoscopy with biopsy is an essential tool for diagnosis of crohns disease and ulcerative
      colitis in children, as well as therapeutical intervention of colonoscopy by hemostasis,
      removing polyps, dilating stricture or decompressing the obstructed bowel .

      Colonoscopy is considered a safe and low risk procedure. Complications of colonoscopy are
      rare and usually minor, as adverse effects of sedative medicine as (nausea,vomiting or
      allergies) can ocurr.

      Bleeding after colonoscopy is usually minimal but may follow mucous biopsy or polypectomy,
      Perforation is very rare but it is the most serious complication of colonoscopy in children,
      it is usually related to polypectomy and can be successfully managed with surgical
      intervention. In case of infection in which cause the child will be given antibiotics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants free and recurrance of colonic disease after colonoscopy procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants were monitored with recurrance of rectal bleeding and underwent colonoscopy up to 2 years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Colonic Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>colonoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>description of the results of colonoscopy im managment of children with rectal bleeding</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        all children with bleeding per rectum underwent colonoscopy
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all children with rectal bleeding underwent colonoscopy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  children underwent colonoscopy rather than rectal bleeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Soha Iraqi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zeinab Mohi eldeen, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+020122397149</phone>
    <email>Zeenabmohielden1957@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nagla Hassan, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+020111187227</phone>
    <email>Nhi_af@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut U</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zeinab Mohi eldeen, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+0201223971490</phone>
      <email>Zeenabmohielden1957@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nagla Hassan</last_name>
      <phone>+0201111872237</phone>
      <email>Nhi_af@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pedneo.2015.01.005</url>
    <description>Ting wu C, Chen C. Characteristics and diagnostic yield of pediatric colonoscopy in Taiwan, Pediatric of neonatology 2015; 56(5): 334-8</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpg.2016.09.006</url>
    <description>Tringali A,Balassone V,Angelis P.Complication in pediatric colonoscopy.2015;30(5):825-39.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>GELB AM, MINKOWITZ S, TRESSER M. Rectal and colonic polyps occurring in young people. N Y State J Med. 1962 Feb 15;62:513-8.</citation>
    <PMID>13897571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baxter NN, Goldwasser MA, Paszat LF, Saskin R, Urbach DR, Rabeneck L. Association of colonoscopy and death from colorectal cancer. Ann Intern Med. 2009 Jan 6;150(1):1-8. Epub 2008 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19075198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bai Y, Peng J, Gao J, Zou DW, Li ZS. Epidemiology of lower gastrointestinal bleeding in China: single-center series and systematic analysis of Chinese literature with 53,951 patients. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2011 Apr;26(4):678-82. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1746.2010.06586.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21083610</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fox VL. Gastrointestinal bleeding in infancy and childhood. Gastroenterol Clin North Am. 2000 Mar;29(1):37-66, v. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10752017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ladas SD, Karamanolis G, Ben-Soussan E. Colonic gas explosion during therapeutic colonoscopy with electrocautery. World J Gastroenterol. 2007 Oct 28;13(40):5295-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17879396</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Park JH. Role of colonoscopy in the diagnosis and treatment of pediatric lower gastrointestinal disorders. Korean J Pediatr. 2010 Sep;53(9):824-9. doi: 10.3345/kjp.2010.53.9.824. Epub 2010 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21189966</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zahmatkeshan M, Fallahzadeh E, Najib K, Geramizadeh B, Haghighat M, Imanieh MH. Etiology of lower gastrointestinal bleeding in children:a single center experience from southern iran. Middle East J Dig Dis. 2012 Oct;4(4):216-23.</citation>
    <PMID>24829660</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>SHIraqi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

