<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03592147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12521/001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03592147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of Different Relaxation Techniques in Eliciting a Relaxation Response</brief_title>
  <official_title>Identification of the Most Effective Relaxation Tool for Use in a Trial to Improve Breastfeeding Outcomes in Mothers of Late Preterm Infants: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      While the stress response, characterised by an increase in heart rate, blood pressure, and
      cortisol, has evolved to ensure the survival of the organism in face of danger, chronic
      stress due to psychological stressors can be harmful. The opposite of the stress response is
      the &quot;relaxation response&quot;. Mind-body techniques such as meditation, guided imagery and music
      therapy are thought to induce this response. The relaxation response is characterized as a
      wakeful hypometabolic state, where a decrease in central nervous system arousal is observed.
      Some studies reported a reduction in stress hormones, and in symptoms of anxiety and
      depression following the use of mind-body relaxation techniques. Other studies noted a
      reduction in stress measured using physiological measurements such as heart rate and blood
      pressure.

      Light therapy is another technique that is suggested to induce physiological changes similar
      to those seen in the relaxation response. Some studies have shown a reduction in heart rate,
      blood pressure, oxygen consumption and carbon dioxide production following exposure to blue
      light.

      These relaxation therapies can be useful for the general population and for vulnerable groups
      where alternative therapies, such as medication and psychotherapy, are difficult. Limited
      amount of studies have quantified the decrease in stress in physiological measurements such
      as heart rate and blood pressure.

      The aim of this study is to investigate which relaxation technique among five different
      interventions (and one control) is the most effective in improving relaxation and reducing
      stress in adult women of reproductive age (18-45 years). The results of this study will be
      used to inform the intervention of a study testing the impact of relaxation therapy on
      breastfeeding outcomes in mothers of late preterm infants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 4, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 4, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Within-subject pilot study, where each participant will undergo five different relaxation therapies (guided imagery meditation, music listening, &quot;relaxation&quot; lighting, combination of light and meditation, and a combination of light and music) and one silence/control state.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Relaxation</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-intervention, an average of 10 mins</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived relaxation was assessed using a visual analogue scale (VAS), which is a 10 cm horizontal line spanning from the minimum to the maximum of the variable measured. The minimum (left) represents &quot;completely unrelaxed&quot; and the maximum (right) &quot;completely relaxed&quot;. The women mark a point on the scale to indicate their feelings of relaxation. The distance between the mark and the minimum point was measured in centimetres (two decimal points).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-intervention, an average of 10 mins</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) were measured three times using a digital sphygmomanometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-intervention, an average of 10 mins</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate (bpm) was measured three times using a digital sphygmomanometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fingertip Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-intervention, an average of 10 mins</time_frame>
    <description>A non-contact digital thermometer was used to measure fingertip temperature as an indication of sympathetic nervous system activation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preference</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the study, at approximately 3-6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The women were asked to rank the relaxation therapies in order of preference</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress, Psychological</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a within-subject pilot study, where each participant received, in random order, five different relaxation therapies (Guided Imagery Relaxation Tape, Music Listening, Relaxation Lighting, Meditation and Relaxation Light, and Music and Relaxation Light) and one Control/Silence state spanning across 3-6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Guided Imagery Relaxation Tape</intervention_name>
    <description>The meditation is approximately 7 minutes in duration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mediation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Music Listening</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants have the option of selecting one of the following music categories: New age, classical, and oriental. The songs were selected based on criteria established in a previous study to induce relaxation. All songs were also modified in length to be approximately 7 minutes in duration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Music</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Relaxation Lighting</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants were asked to select either orange or blue lighting settings using the Philips Hue lighting. The intensity of the light will be fixed to control for that measure. They were asked to sit for approximately 7 minutes in duration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meditation and Relaxation Light</intervention_name>
    <description>The guided imagery meditation and relaxation lighting were combined.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Music and Relaxation Light</intervention_name>
    <description>The music and relaxation lighting were combined.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control/Silence</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants were asked to relax for a duration of 7 minutes, with no explicit advice given. Lighting was adjusted to a specific intensity and colour (basic yellow light) as was used in the music and guided imagery interventions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relaxation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women of reproductive age (18-45 years)

          -  Fluent in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any condition that may affect blood pressure, heart rate or energy expenditure i.e
             hypertension, hyperthyroidism, heart failure

          -  Smokers

          -  Recent surgeries or injuries
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College London Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1N 1EH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>Music</keyword>
  <keyword>Relaxation</keyword>
  <keyword>Light Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

