<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03036930</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2017-00116</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-00116</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01-CN-2012-00035</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI2015-06-02</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NWU2015-06-02</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CN00035</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA060553</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03036930</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventive Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Vaccine Trial in Kidney Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity of Nonavalent HPV Vaccine Administered Prior to Renal Transplantation in Adult Women: A Prospective, Single-Arm, Multi-Center Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial studies whether the nonavalent human papillomavirus vaccine given to adults prior
      to kidney transplantation can help the body build and maintain an effective immune response
      during the post-transplant period when they receive immunosuppressive drugs to prevent
      transplant rejection. This study will help inform our scientific understanding about
      vaccine-induced immune responses among immunosuppressed individuals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccine-type-specific seroconversion rates at
      12-months post-transplantation among kidney transplant recipients who receive &gt;= 1 doses of
      the recombinant human papillomavirus nonavalent vaccine (Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine) &gt;= 30 days
      prior to transplantation.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the following in adult kidney transplant recipients who receive &gt;= 1 doses of
      the Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine prior to transplantation:

      Ia. HPV vaccine-type-specific seroconversion rates at 12-months post-transplantation.

      Ib. Persistence and stability of HPV vaccine-type-specific geometric mean titers (GMT) at 6
      and 12-months post-transplantation, and rise in HPV vaccine-type-specific GMT at the 13 month
      post-transplant visit.

      Ic. Vaccine safety profile and allograft rejection/opportunistic infections stratified by
      number of vaccine doses and time between the last vaccine dose and the transplant procedure.

      Id. HPV detection in self-collected samples from the cervix/vagina, and oral cavity at
      baseline (pre-vaccination) and at 6- and 12-months post-vaccination, overall and by number of
      vaccine doses (1, 2, or 3), sexual behavior, type-specific seroconversion rates, and time
      elapsed between the last vaccine dose and the transplant procedure.

      Ie. Descriptive analysis to explore differences or similarities between the genders from the
      secondary objective outcomes above.

      OUTLINE:

      Participants receive the first dose of the recombinant human papillomavirus nonavalent
      vaccine intramuscularly (IM) at baseline, at least 30 days prior to the kidney transplant
      surgery. The second dose is given at least one month after the first dose. The third dose is
      given at least five months after the first dose and at least three months after the second
      dose. The timing of the second and third doses is dependent on the scheduling of the kidney
      transplant surgery. Patients are followed up at 6- and 12-months after the kidney transplant
      surgery to measure vaccine-induced immune responses. Patients may receive either one, two, or
      all three vaccine doses prior to the kidney transplant surgery, and are offered additional
      visits at least one year after the surgery to complete any remaining doses of the three-dose
      vaccine series.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 23, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccine-type-specific seroconversion rates among kidney transplant recipients who receive &gt;= 1 doses of the vaccine &gt;= 30 days prior to transplantation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Will provide an estimate of the rate and two approximate and one exact 95% confidence intervals (CIs). For approximate CI will use a) approximate normality of p-hat, and b) approximate normality of log(p-hat); and for exact CI will use the Clopper-Pearson exact confidence interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HPV vaccine-type-specific seroconversion rates</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Will provide descriptive statistics such as means, rates, and exact or approximate 95% CI. Will compare stratified rates to each other, using an exact test for number doses. Will provide mean, median, and range for time elapsed for time elapsed for subgroups of interest between last vaccine dose and transplant procedure. Lists of dosing types by medication variety will be provided and summaries applied when possible and appropriate and interactions with type of transplant surgery (living donor/deceased donor) for variations in dosing and types of post-transplant immunosuppressant medications. Descriptive statistics and graphics will be used for visual comparison and assessment for differences in human leukocyte antigen histocompatibility between donor and recipient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence and stability of HPV vaccine-type-specific geometric mean titers (GMT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Will provide descriptive statistics such as means, rates, and exact or approximate 95% CI. Persistence will be measured as the difference in means between two times (6 and 12-months post-transplant) while stability will be assessed by measures of spread appropriate for the transformation at hand.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rise in HPV vaccine-type-specific GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Will provide descriptive statistics such as means, rates, and exact or approximate 95% CI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaccine safety profile and allograft rejection/opportunistic infections</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 13 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Will provide descriptive statistics such as means, rates, and exact or approximate 95% CI. Safety profile and injections will be listed, stratified by number of doses (1, 2, or 3) and time to transplant (long, short) and summarized as possible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HPV detection in samples from the cervix/vagina, and oral cavity</measure>
    <time_frame>Self-collected at baseline (pre-vaccination) and at 6- and 12- months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Will provide descriptive statistics such as means, rates, and exact or approximate 95% CI. HPV detection in samples from the cervix/vagina, and oral cavity at baseline (pre-vaccination) and at 6- and 12-months post-vaccination, overall and by number of vaccine doses (1, 2, or 3), sexual behavior, type-specific seroconversion rates, and time elapsed between the last vaccine dose and the transplant procedure will be evaluated. All rates of HPV detection will be specified, overall and stratified by number of doses (1, 2, or 3) and time to transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences and similarities between genders</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>A descriptive analysis will be performed to explore differences or similarities between genders from the secondary objective outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Papillomavirus Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the first dose of the recombinant human papillomavirus nonavalent vaccine IM at baseline, at least 30 days prior to the kidney transplant surgery. The second dose is given at least one month after the first dose. The third dose is given at least five months after the first dose and at least three months after the second dose. The timing of the second and third doses is dependent on the scheduling of the kidney transplant surgery. Patients are followed up at 6- and 12-months after the kidney transplant surgery to measure vaccine-induced immune responses. Patients may receive either one, two, or all three vaccine doses prior to the kidney transplant surgery, and are offered additional visits at least one year after the surgery to complete any remaining doses of the three-dose vaccine series.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recombinant Human Papillomavirus Nonavalent Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IM</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gardasil 9</other_name>
    <other_name>Nonavalent HPV VLP Vaccine</other_name>
    <other_name>Recombinant HPV Nonavalent Vaccine</other_name>
    <other_name>Recombinant Human Papillomavirus 9-valent Vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Candidate for renal transplant, expected to undergo transplant surgery &gt;= 30 days and
             =&lt; 12 months after enrollment

               -  For potential participants on the institutional waiting list for deceased donor
                  transplant, a study clinician confirms the candidate is likely to receive a
                  transplant within the next 12 months, taking into account the candidate's
                  priority on the waiting list, age, medical status, institutional policies, and
                  scores like the Estimated Post-Transplant Survival (EPTS) Score and Calculated
                  Panel Reactive Antibody (CPRA) percentage, etc

               -  For potential participants expected to undergo a living donor transplant, one or
                  more donor(s) have been identified and is/are in work-up (even though all work-up
                  status may or may not be complete); a study clinician confirms the living donor
                  transplant is likely to be scheduled within the next twelve months after taking
                  into account donor work-up progress, age and medical status, and institutional
                  policies

               -  Notes:

                    -  Living and deceased donor transplant recipients: The study was originally
                       restricted to participants who were expecting to receive only living donor
                       renal transplants; however, less than a third of kidney transplants in the
                       United States occur with kidneys from living donors; a majority of
                       transplants are in the setting of donation of kidneys from deceased donors;
                       to permit efficiencies in accrual, the study is amended (from version 3.5)
                       to also open enrollment to recipients of deceased donor kidneys

                    -  Transplant recipients of both genders: The study was originally designed to
                       be conducted only among women; however, in October 2018, the Food and Drug
                       Administration (FDA) approved an age expansion indication for the Gardasil 9
                       HPV vaccine for both women and men up to 45 years (from the originally
                       approved upper age limit of 26 years), thus opening a new clinical cancer
                       preventative option for middle-age adults of both genders; the primary
                       endpoint for the study is HPV-vaccine-type-specific seroconversion rates,
                       which are not expected to be differential by gender, based on extrapolating
                       from the uniformly high (&gt; 99%) seroconversion rates observed regardless of
                       gender in studies among immunocompetent individuals; however, HPV
                       vaccine-type-specific titer levels (geometric mean titre [GMT]) differences
                       by gender will be analyzed as a secondary endpoint, given variability in
                       immune response titer levels observed between males and females in
                       immunocompetent individuals (related to the differences in body mass index
                       or hitherto unproven factors related to hormone-immune interactions);
                       another advantage of expanding this study to males will be to facilitate
                       efficiencies in accrual, since men constitute the majority (55%-65%) of all
                       kidney transplant recipients in the United States; although a majority of
                       current HPV-associated cancers among solid organ transplant recipients occur
                       among women, there is increasing evidence of the link between HPV infection
                       and oropharyngeal cancers that disproportionately affect men; HPV-related
                       oropharyngeal cancers are now the most common HPV-related cancers in the
                       United States, surpassing even the incidence of cervical cancer; the
                       expansion of enrollment to men will also allow this study to look at the
                       effect of HPV vaccination on persistence of oral HPV infection as a
                       secondary/exploratory endpoint in the context of transplant-related
                       immunosuppression

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 1 (Karnofsky &gt;= 70%)

          -  The effects of the Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine on the developing human fetus at the
             recommended therapeutic dose are unknown; for this reason and because there have been
             no adequate and well-controlled studies of Gardasil 9 in pregnant women, women who are
             able to become pregnant must have a confirmed negative pregnancy test result within
             the past 28 days prior to enrollment and must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for
             the duration of study participation; women who have had a both ovaries removed or a
             tubal ligation will not be required to have a pregnancy test; should a woman become
             pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she should
             inform her study physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document
             and medical release form

          -  Willing and able to comply with trial protocol and follow-up

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous prophylactic HPV vaccination

          -  Prior organ transplant

          -  Anticipated desensitization treatment; this decision to exclude a participant who may
             need desensitization will be based on the site clinician's judgement; desensitization
             procedures vary somewhat among the five participating transplant centers, which does
             not permit proposing uniform criteria across all study sites for determining exclusion
             due to desensitization; in general, participants who have received a prior transplant,
             have unsuitable scores on Calculated Panel Reactive Antibody (PRA) percentage
             (institution-specific thresholds), or an ABO incompatible donor are likely to undergo
             desensitization at one or more of the study centers; these factors, among others, will
             be used by the study clinician to determine exclusion due to anticipated
             desensitization is warranted for a particular participant in the study

          -  Current use of any other investigational agents

          -  History of allergic reactions to yeast or attributed to compounds of similar chemical
             or biologic composition to Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  For female participants: Pregnant or intention to get pregnant, or breastfeeding;
             pregnant women are excluded from this study because the safety and effectiveness of
             Gardasil 9 HPV vaccine have not been established in pregnant women; it is not known
             whether Gardasil 9 is excreted in human milk; because many drugs are excreted in human
             milk, caution should be exercised when Gardasil 9 is administered to a nursing woman;
             because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants
             secondary to treatment of the mother with Gardasil 9, women who are breastfeeding will
             be excluded

          -  History of cervical cancer or anal cancer

          -  History of active malignancy, including basal/squamous cell skin cancer

          -  Concurrent illness, such as known psychiatric disorders or substance abuse (i.e.,
             average alcohol consumption of more than 3 drinks per day), which in the opinion of
             the investigators would compromise either the patient or the integrity of the data

          -  Patients on anticoagulation or with bleeding disorders should be evaluated by a
             physician for risk/benefit of bleeding disorders with intramuscular injections prior
             to study enrollment; patients determined to be at high risk for bleeding with
             intramuscular injections will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc T Goodman</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather Logan</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-6774</phone>
      <email>heatherlogan@uabmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>E. T. Overton</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yunhee Choi</last_name>
      <phone>424-315-2543</phone>
      <email>yunhee.choi-kuaea@cshs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Irene Kim</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Medical Center-Mount Zion</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ada Chao</last_name>
      <phone>415-476-2575</phone>
      <email>ada.chao@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Garrett R. Roll</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Bezler</last_name>
      <phone>312-694-0260</phone>
      <email>laura.bezler@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Ison</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ken Norman</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-7108</phone>
      <email>ken@unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lisa Rahangdale</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Papillomavirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

