<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03896165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018X0079</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PCRC_Pilot_Grant_2018-02p</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03896165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Teaching Parents Reiki for Their Adolescents Receiving Palliative Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Teaching Parents Reiki for Their Adolescents Receiving Palliative Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Akron Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study addresses National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR) priorities of
      advancing symptom science to &quot;develop [and] test … novel, scalable symptom management
      interventions, including complementary health approaches (CHAs), in real-world clinical
      settings to improve health outcomes and quality of life&quot; and the science of compassion to
      improve palliative and end-of-life care through &quot;developing, testing, and implementing
      personalized, culturally congruent, and evidence-based palliative and hospice interventions
      that best address the needs of underserved, disadvantaged, and diverse populations across the
      care continuum.&quot; A long-term bonus of teaching parents to deliver Reiki is that Reiki is
      highly scalable and once learned, costs nothing to use, an important potential overall cost
      savings over other CHAs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite advances in the assessment and treatment of symptoms, including pain in adolescents
      receiving palliative care, parents still report that their children suffer. Advances in
      medical science and care have led to a growing number of children living with life-limiting
      chronic conditions. Out of 83 million children under the age of 19,16 an estimated 600,000 to
      1,600,00017 are living with life-threatening/life-limiting conditions and over 180,000 are
      considered &quot;medically fragile.&quot; These children require intense medical and nursing care in
      the home and often experience lengthy, recurrent hospital stays, accounting for about 26% of
      hospital days and 41% of hospital charges. Adolescents with life-threatening/life-limiting
      conditions, many of whom are developmentally delayed, experience many symptoms and have
      complex co-morbidities requiring medical management.

      Many of these adolescents could benefit from complementary health approaches (CHAs) such as
      Reiki, a gentle light touch biofield energy therapy. Parents of adolescents receiving
      palliative care also experience high levels of stress. Previous studies have shown that
      empowering parents in the care of their chronically ill child help parents better cope with
      challenges. Some CHAs show promise for symptom management without side effects, such as
      sedation from additional medication, thereby permitting greater alertness and allowing more
      interaction with family and friends. Preliminary evidence from the PIs pilot study showed
      that professionally-delivered Reiki is feasible for children and adolescents receiving
      palliative care at home. The majority of parents said they wished they could learn Reiki so
      they might provide this relaxing therapy in the moment it was needed rather than waiting for
      the next professional session. One non-experimental program found that teaching parents Reiki
      was feasible and acceptable in the hospital. Parents who participated in two or more training
      sessions felt more confident providing Reiki. During informal interviews, parents said they
      felt good at being an active participant in their child's care and that their child
      experienced increased comfort, relaxation, and decreased pain.

      Parents of disabled adolescents receiving palliative care often suffer from high caregiver
      burden and chronic stress leading to co-morbidities and decreased QoL. A cross-sectional
      survey conducted in Europe examined stress in 818 parents caring for a child with cerebral
      palsy. Results showed that 26% of mothers had very high stress. When the child had a
      communication or intellectual impairment or moderate-to-severe pain, parental stress was
      higher. One study examined psychological burden for 204 parents of children with serious
      chronic conditions. This study found that 75% of parents reported depression, and 67% had
      anxiety. The investigators are interested in exploring whether adding a skill (Reiki) aimed
      at decreasing symptoms in the adolescent will result in a decrease in symptoms and chronic
      stress for the parent.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 24, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 24, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Mixed methods quasi-experimental one group design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction of parents learning Reiki in the home to use with their adolescent receiving palliative care.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction will be examined by computing the proportion of approached subjects who enroll in the study, the proportion of subjects who complete Reiki training, and the proportion of enrolled subjects who complete data collection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change in adolescents' and parents' stress response (as measured by hair sample).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Explore the adolescents' and parents' stress response. We will measure hair cortisol at the beginning and again at week 9.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change in adolescents' and parents' stress response (as measured by saliva alpha amylase).</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, week 2, week 3, week 4</time_frame>
    <description>We will also measure saliva alpha amylase twice per week for 4 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in adolescents' and parents' symptom profile as measured by Patient Reported Outcome Measurement Information System (PROMIS) symptom questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 4, Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Explore the adolescents' and parents' symptom profile (as measured by changes in physical function, anxiety, depression, fatigue, sleep, social roles, and pain level).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Explore the parents confidence in delivering Reiki through audio-recorded interviews</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Explore parents' confidence in delivering Reiki to their adolescent after completing Reiki training and practicing providing Reiki to their adolescent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Explore parents' confidence their ability to help their adolescent through audio-recorded interviews</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>Explore parents' confidence their ability to help their adolescent after completing Reiki training and practicing providing Reiki to their adolescent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Palliative Care</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching Reiki</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parent-adolescent pairs will be in the study for a total of nine weeks from enrollment to the follow up visit. During Week 1, the parent will receive Reiki training, a poster with suggested hand positions and a commercially-available book about Reiki in the home. During Week 2 the parent will receive a Reiki booster session with a repeat of the training and may ask questions in the home. At the end of Week 4, measures will be repeated either in person or by phone. During Week 8, measures will be repeated, another hair sample obtained and the parent will participate in a qualitative interview. The qualitative interview will be administered in person by trained Ohio State University College of Nursing study staff as part of the interview session. Interviews will be audio recorded using a hand-held audio recording device. Audio recording is voluntary and participants can choose to not have their interview recorded and still be a part of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reiki</intervention_name>
    <description>Reiki is a complementary health approach where trained providers place their hands lightly on or just above a person, in discrete positions, with the goal of facilitating the person's own healing response. A Reiki practitioner will perform the initial teaching and instruct the parent how to perform a simple 15-minute Reiki session. Parents will complete a return demonstration using light touch with their adolescent. Parents will be asked to complete a minimum of 15 minutes of Reiki with their adolescent at least five days per week for the four-week intervention period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching Reiki</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants will include adolescent-parent dyads. Dyads will be included if the

          -  Adolescent: (1) is 10 to 19 years old, (2) is receiving palliative care at home, (3)
             understands English

          -  Parent: (1) provides care for the adolescent most days of the week and (2) is able to
             read and write English at the 6th grade level.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  if (1) either the adolescent or the parent are taking or have taken corticosteroids
             within the last 30 days (affects the hair cortisol levels), or (2) either the
             adolescent or the parent has less than one inch of hair.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan E Thrane, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Akron Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University College of Nursing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Complementary Health Approach</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

