<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03895294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Universidad de Antioquia</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03895294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Strategies for the Treatment of Chronic Hepatitis C in Colombia</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEPCSTRATEGY</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Strategic Purchasing of Antiviral Drugs and the Clinical Pathway for the Treatment of Chronic Hepatitis C in Colombia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de Antioquia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de Antioquia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis C is a public health problem and the high cost of the Direct-Acting Antivirals
      (DAA) is one of the main limitations for treatment worldwide.

      In Colombia, the Ministry of Health and Social Protection (MoHSP) has made progress in
      addressing Hepatitis C problem in order to control the infection and resolve barriers to
      access to medicines. One of the strategies implemented was the purchase of DAA, in
      association with the PAHO, and the instauration of the Clinical Pathway for the treatment of
      chronic hepatitis C.

      The implementation of the Clinical Pathway has required the integration of health care
      processes and the respective report in the health information systems, allowing a high level
      of control in the monitoring of the Hepatitis C and the subsequent generation of indicators.
      However, there is limited information on the effects of the strategic purchase and the
      instauration of the Clinical Pathway on the costs of care, clinical outcomes and the quality
      of health care for patients with Hepatitis C in Colombia.

      The aim of this study is to establish the effect of strategic purchasing and the Clinical
      Pathway for the treatment of chronic Hepatitis C, in the clinical results, in the general
      costs and quality of health care of Hepatitis C patients in Colombia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A quasi-experimental design with a non-equivalent control group will be performed, where
      there will be an intervention group and a control group formed naturally before the
      investigation. In order to reduce the possible selection bias due to the lack of
      randomization, the propensity score method will be used. 62 patients will be included in each
      arm.

      An estimation and comparison of the direct costs of the care of patients with Hepatitis C,
      before and after the implementation of the strategic purchase and the Clinical Pathway will
      be made, using a &quot;top to bottom&quot; method.

      A questionnaire will be applied to the patients of the intervention group in order to
      identify barriers and facilitators to Hepatitis C health care and patient satisfaction with
      health care process under the Clinical Pathway.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Access to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who initiates treatment, in comparison with the total number of patients with indication of treatment (confirmed diagnosis and prescription of treatment).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opportunity at the start of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>The difference in days between the date of the first prescription of the antiviral treatment and the start date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of treated patients that achieved Sustained Virological Response (SVR), that is, undetectable HCV viral load (lower than the Lower Quantification Limit -LL-), 12 weeks after the end of the DAA therapy (SVR12) or 24 weeks after the end of treatment for the schemes that include interferon (SVR24)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug-related problem</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who initiated treatment and who presented at least one Drug-Related Problem registered in the clinical history, database and / or pharmacovigilance reports.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">124</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health care under the strategic purchase-Clinical pathway</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Health care under the strategic purchase and the Clinical pathway for the treatment of chronic Hepatitis C</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care process prior strategic purchase-clinical pathway</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care process prior to the establishment of the strategic purchase and the Clinical Pathway</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health care under the strategic purchase-Clinical pathway</intervention_name>
    <description>1) purchase of DAA by the MoHSP; 2) diagnosis of the patient (confirmed by quantitative HCV RNA test); 2) prescription of the treatment by a specialist in internal medicine, hepatology or Infectious disease; 3) daily supervised drug administration by a nurse or weekly treatment dispensing by pharmacist; 4) Pharmaceutical Care (includes: consultation with pharmacist at weeks 0, 4, week of the end of treatment (8, 12 or 24) and week of evaluation of effectiveness (week 12 or 24 after the end of treatment); health education and administrative support. In case of identifying any Drug-related Problem, the respective pharmaceutical intervention was made.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health care under the strategic purchase-Clinical pathway</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual care process prior strategic purchase-clinical pathway</intervention_name>
    <description>1) diagnosis of the patient (confirmed by quantitative HCV RNA test); 2) prescription of the treatment by a specialist in hepatology; 3) weekly treatment dispensing by pharmacist; 4) patient use; 5) Pharmaceutical Care (includes: consultation with pharmacist at weeks 0, 4, 8, week of the end of treatment (12 or 24) and week of evaluation of effectiveness (week 12 or 24 after the end of treatment); health education and administrative support). In case of identifying any Drug-related problem, the respective pharmaceutical intervention was made.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care process prior strategic purchase-clinical pathway</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with Chronic Hepatitis C confirmed by quantitative HCV RNA test

          -  Patient affiliated to the contributory system of one Health Promoting Enterprise from
             Colombia.

          -  Patients with prescription of pharmacological treatment for Hepatitis C.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with incomplete information in at least one of the following variables:
             fibrosis, cirrhosis (if applicable), antiviral drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mónica Ledezma, Msc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Antioquia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pedro Amariles, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Antioquia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea Salazar, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Antioquia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pedro Amariles, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+5742195476</phone>
    <email>pedro.amariles@udea.edu.co</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medicarte</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medellín</city>
        <state>Antioquia</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalia Duque, Msc</last_name>
      <email>nduque@medicarte.com.co</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julieth Gómez, Pharmacist</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.scielo.org.co/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0120-99572018000400483</url>
    <description>Clinical pathway for the treatment of chronic Hepatitis C, a look and a complement from the perspective of pharmaceutical services</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Direct-Acting Antivirals</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Services Accessibility</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

