<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03897049</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TransWomenConnected</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03897049</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Trans Women Connected Mobile App for Changes in Sexual Health-related Behavior Among Transgender Women</brief_title>
  <acronym>TWC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Trans Women Connected: a Mobile App Delivered Sexual Health Promotion Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ETR Associates</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>dfusion</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Portland State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ETR Associates</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a 2-arm cluster randomized controlled trial to be conducted with 450 trans women
      to assess the effectiveness of the Trans Women Connected mobile app. Those in the treatment
      arm will be provided with the Trans Women Connected app, to be downloaded to their own
      device, and asked to use it during a three month period. Those in the control arm will be
      asked to download a general health app and use it during the same three-month period.
      Participants will complete brief online surveys at baseline, immediately following the
      app-use period, and at 3- and 6-months following the conclusion of the app-use period. The
      baseline and follow-up assessments will collect data on demographic characteristics, measures
      related to our primary and secondary outcomes, and psychosocial measures. The primary outcome
      measures are self-reported STI/HIV testing and sex without a condom, with secondary measures
      including sexual risk behaviors, health care visits, perceived social support/connectedness,
      PrEP use, self-efficacy in negotiation/communication, and comfort with gender identity and
      appearance. In addition, process data, such as forum content, and usage data will be
      collected and analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A 2-arm cluster randomized controlled trial will be conducted with 450 trans women to assess
      the effectiveness of the Trans Women Connected mobile app. The Trans Women Connected
      intervention will address the unique needs of transgender women and the lack of
      evidence-based, transgender-specific HIV prevention. It is a mobile app delivered sexual
      health promotion program that engages transgender women through a strengths-based approach to
      HIV prevention and sexual health that uses the power of social networks to identify and
      encourage protective factors that support the health of transgender women. This approach
      recognizes the social and structural barriers that transgender women face. In the context of
      these barriers, which include stigma and discrimination in a number of interconnected
      spheres, individually-focused behavioral interventions are insufficient. This intervention
      takes a more comprehensive approach that intentionally targets community strengths and
      challenges. The mobile app will include more than 30 interactive activities including
      resource maps, PrEP/PEP content, and communication forums.

      To be eligible, participants will be required to self-identify as transgender women; report
      having had 2 or more sexual partners in the past 90 days with at least one of those partners
      having a penis; be age 18-49 at baseline; own a smartphone; and reside in any state in the
      United States. Those in the treatment arm will be provided with the Trans Women Connected
      app, to be downloaded to their own device, and asked to use it during a three-month period.
      Those in the control arm will be asked to download a general health app and use it during the
      same three-month period. Participants will complete brief online surveys at baseline,
      immediately following the app-use period, and at 3- and 6-months following the conclusion of
      the app-use period.

      Participants will be recruited using a variety of methods, including: 1) Regional transwomen
      recruitment/retention specialists who are responsible for facilitating recruitment in their
      regions, addressing study questions, and maintaining connections with each participant to
      support study engagement; 2) Organizations. Organizations from across the U.S., at least one
      per state, that serve transgender women will be approached to help recruit participants
      through social media and in-person. 3) Google Adwords. Placing study advertisements on Google
      based on keyword for participant recruitment has been shown to be effective. 4) Social Media
      Advertising including targeted advertising on social media sites (Facebook/Instagram) and
      sponsoring study posts with social media influencers in the Transwomen community. Social
      media advertising has been shown to be favorable in terms of its cost-effectiveness,
      usability, and reach, especially with hard-to-reach populations, young adults and LGBT
      populations. 5) Participant Recruitment. Once recruited and successfully entered into the
      study each participant will receive three digital referral coupons and each coupon will
      generate $15 for a successfully screened participant. Participants will complete 4 web-based
      surveys and will receive $20 for baseline survey, $20 for an immediate posttest, $40 at
      3-month follow up, $60 at final 6-month follow up.

      Randomization. Because the evaluation is using cluster randomization, the participants will
      be randomized by cluster. There will be 150 seeds and the first person in a cluster. Each
      will be given 3 referral coupons. Upon completing a baseline survey the seed will be
      randomized into treatment or control. Any participant using a referral coupon will be placed
      in the same condition as the initial seed with which they are associated.

      Implementation. After randomization, participants in the treatment group, will be granted
      access to download and install the Trans Women Connected mobile app. They will have three
      months to use the program. Participants will agree to complete core activities and use the
      app as often as they can with a target of two times per week. Participants can use the app as
      often as they want. Those in the control group will download and install a general health app
      that includes some sexual health content.

      Data Collection. Participants will be surveyed at 4 time points. 1) before randomization, 2)
      after using the mobile app for 3 months, 3) three months after completion of the
      intervention, and 4) six months after completion of the intervention. Surveys will be
      completed online via Survey Gizmo through emailed or texted links. All survey data will be
      transferred to SPSS for analysis. Data will also be collected through the app. This includes
      usage data, such as what activities participants used and for how long, and process data,
      which includes content on the communication forum, text answers in the app, and visual
      content such as vision boards. Participants will receive an incentive of $20 for the baseline
      and immediate post-intervention survey, $40 for the 3-month follow up survey, and $60 for the
      6 month follow up survey.

      Study Hypotheses. Primary Hypotheses 1 (representing sexual health risk reduction through
      engagement in care 1) Women in the intervention group will report more STI testing (higher
      rates of STI testing in the prior 90 days) than the comparison group. Primary Hypotheses 2,
      women in the intervention group will report fewer acts of receptive condomless anal
      intercourse or condomless vaginal intercourse. Secondary Hypotheses (representing other
      important sexual health risk, and psychosocial outcomes):1) Participants in the intervention
      group will report reduced sexual risk taking including fewer acts of receptive condomless
      anal intercourse or condomless vaginal intercourse; greater use of condom use at last
      intercourse (receptive anal or vaginal); and increased use of PrEP for those that are HIV- 2)
      Participants in the intervention group will engage more with proactive health care and report
      more health care visits. 3) Participants in the treatment group will report more
      connectedness with other transgender women, including perceived social support and engagement
      with a mentor. 4) Participants in the intervention group will report greater efficacy in
      having safer sex and in communication both with partners and health care workers. 5) Those in
      the treatment group will have greater acceptance of their gender identity/comfort with gender
      identity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a two arm cluster randomized controlled trial. Because the evaluation is using cluster randomization, the participants will be randomized by cluster into the control or treatment group. There will be 150 seeds and the first person in a cluster. Each will be given 3 referral coupons. Upon completing a baseline survey the seed will be randomized into treatment or control. Any participant using a referral coupon will be placed in the same condition as the initial seed with which they are associated.
Implementation. After randomization, educators in the treatment group, will be granted access to download and install the Trans Women Connected mobile app.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants are randomly assigned to their condition without being made aware of their assigned condition. Each condition downloads and uses an app so study activities are similar reducing the likelihood participants will be aware of their assigned condition.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported STI/HIV testing in past three months</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times reported having been tested for STI/HIV</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported STI/HIV testing in past three months</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times reported having been tested for STI/HIV</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Receptive condomless anal intercourse or condomless vaginal intercourse</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times receptive condomless anal intercourse or condomless vaginal intercourse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Receptive condomless anal intercourse or condomless vaginal intercourse</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times receptive condomless anal intercourse or condomless vaginal intercourse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of a condom at last receptive anal intercourse or vaginal intercourse</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month post, 6- month post</time_frame>
    <description>Used a condom at last receptive anal intercourse or vaginal intercourse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual partners, unprotected, in last 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description># partners with whom had anal or vaginal sex without using condoms or PrEP in past 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual partners, unprotected, in last 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description># partners with whom had anal or vaginal sex without using condoms or PrEP in past 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health care visits</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported # of visits to a health care provider (of any type and by type)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health care visits</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported # of visits to a health care provider (of any type and by type)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Immediate post, 3- month post, 6-month post</time_frame>
    <description>Perceptions of social support, mean score. Scale range is from 7 - 49 with a higher number indicating greater perceived social support which is a better outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engaged as/with mentor</measure>
    <time_frame>3-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported number of contacts as a mentor/mentee for guidance or support</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engaged as/with mentor</measure>
    <time_frame>6-months post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported number of contacts as a mentor/mentee for guidance or support</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP Uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Immediate post, 3- month post, 6-month post</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported uptake of PrEP among HIV since last measurement period- subsample</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV &amp; Safer Sex: Self Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures self-efficacy in decisions around safe sex behavior. Average of 7 items on a 5-point scale (1 to 5), with a range of 7 - 35, with a higher score indicating better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV &amp; Safer Sex: Self Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3- month post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures self-efficacy in decisions around safe sex behavior. Average of 7 items on a 5-point scale (1 to 5), with a range of 7 - 35, with a higher score indicating better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV &amp; Safer Sex: Self Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6-month post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures self-efficacy in decisions around safe sex behavior. Average of 7 items on a 5-point scale (1 to 5), with a range of 7 - 35, with a higher score indicating better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ask ,Understand, and Remember (AURA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate post, 3- month post, 6-month post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures patient communication self-efficacy within clinical encounters. Average of 4 items on a 4-point scale, with a range of 4 - 16, with a greater higher score indicating better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ask ,Understand, and Remember (AURA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures patient communication self-efficacy within clinical encounters. Average of 4 items on a 4-point scale, with a range of 4 - 16, with a greater higher score indicating better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ask ,Understand, and Remember (AURA)</measure>
    <time_frame>3- month post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures patient communication self-efficacy within clinical encounters. Average of 4 items on a 4-point scale, with a range of 4 - 16, with a higher score indicating better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transgender Congruence Scale (TCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Immediate post, 3- month post, 6-month post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures degree of comfort with external appearance as it relates to gender identity. Average of 12 items on a 5-point scale, with a range of 12 - 60, with a higher score indicating a perception that their appearance reflects their chosen gender identity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Gender Identity Reflection and Rumination Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Immediate post, 3- month post, 6-month post</time_frame>
    <description>Scale measures rumination in the context of gender identity among transgender persons. Average of 15 items on a 4-point scale, with a range of 15 - 60, with a lower score indicating less rumination and better outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reactions to Trans Women Connected</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate post</time_frame>
    <description>Reaction/satisfaction items related to the various components of the app, mean score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</condition>
  <condition>STI</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TWC App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention is a mobile app delivered sexual health promotion program designed specifically for transgender women. The mobile app will include more than 30 interactive activities including resource maps, PrEP and PEP content, and communication forums for connecting with other transgender women. The intervention/app is intended to be used regularly, approximately two times per week during the 90 day active participation period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>General Health App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will download a general health mobile app that contains sexual health information. The control mobile app is intended to be used regularly, approximately two times per week during the 90 day active participation period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trans Women Connected</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will address the unique needs of transgender women and the lack of evidence-based, transgender-specific HIV prevention. It is a mobile app delivered sexual health promotion program that engages transgender women through a strengths based approach to HIV prevention and sexual health that uses the power of social networks to identify and encourage protective factors that support the health of transgender women. This approach recognizes the social and structural barriers that transgender women face. In the context of these barriers, which include stigma and discrimination in a number of interconnected spheres, individually-focused behavioral interventions are insufficient. This intervention takes a more comprehensive approach that intentionally targets community strengths and challenges. The mobile app will include more than 30 interactive activities including resource maps, PrEP/PEP content, and communication forums.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TWC App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General Health App</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group will download a mobile app that addresses general health behaviors and concerns, including sexual health topics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>General Health App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. aged 18-49 at the start of the study.

          2. self-identify as transgender women

          3. self-identify as sexually active with more than one partner in the prior 90 days

          4. at least one sexual partner in the last 90 days had a penis

          5. has a smartphone

          6. resides in the U.S.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Anyone not meeting inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>All participants must identify as transgender women.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tamara Kuhn</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>dfusion</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tamara Kuhn, MA</last_name>
    <phone>831.440.2104</phone>
    <email>tamara.kuhn@dfusioninc.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charles Klein, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>503-725-3316</phone>
    <email>chklein@pdx.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ETR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scotts Valley</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95066</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karin Coyle, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>831-440-2140</phone>
      <email>karin.coyle@etr.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tamara Kuhn, MA</last_name>
      <phone>831-440-2104</phone>
      <email>tamara.kuhn@etr.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karin Coyle, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramirez-Valles J, Heckathorn DD, Vázquez R, Diaz RM, Campbell RT. From networks to populations: the development and application of respondent-driven sampling among IDUs and Latino gay men. AIDS Behav. 2005 Dec;9(4):387-402.</citation>
    <PMID>16235135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transgender Women</keyword>
  <keyword>STI</keyword>
  <keyword>Sexual Health</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV/AIDS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

