<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03896776</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01MH118213</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03896776</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pragmatic Trial of Two Strategies for Implementing an Effective eHealth HIV Prevention Program (Keep It Up! 3.0)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pragmatic Trial of Two Strategies for Implementing an Effective eHealth HIV Prevention Program (Keep It Up! 3.0)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Marquette University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates and compares two implementation strategies of an online HIV prevention
      intervention: Strategy 1 in which community-based organizations apply, and are selected, for
      funding to deliver Keep It Up! through current HIV testing programs; and Strategy 2 which is
      a &quot;direct-to-consumer&quot; model where centralized staff at Northwestern University recruit
      participants nationally through online advertising campaigns and manage engagement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Substantial effort has gone into developing and testing the efficacy of eHealth HIV
      prevention interventions, but these interventions will not affect the spread of the epidemic
      unless implemented effectively to reach the most at-risk populations. Despite emerging
      evidence that eHealth approaches can be highly effective in reducing HIV risk or improving
      care engagement, implementation requirements do not fit within established strategies for
      public health scale up, leaving it an open question as to how to bring these programs into
      practice. To date, little to no implementation science has examined strategies to effectively
      scale up eHealth HIV prevention programs.

      The overarching goal of this study is to address this need by developing and evaluating novel
      strategies for implementing eHealth HIV prevention programs. Keep It Up! (KIU!) is an online
      program proven to reduce HIV risk among diverse young men who have sex with men (YMSM). KIU!
      was designed for YMSM who just tested HIV negative to keep it up and maintain negative status
      by reducing risk and enacting protections. Strong evidence of effectiveness on behavioral
      (decreased condomless sex) and biomedical outcomes (reduced STI incidence) makes KIU! an
      ideal eHealth intervention for implementation research. Lessons learned from KIU!
      implementation will set the pathway for implementing the many HIV eHealth programs currently
      undergoing efficacy testing.

      Implementation strategies need to be evaluated using rigorous research designs. Through
      formative research with community-based organizations (CBOs), health departments, the CDC,
      and researchers, the investigators have identified two pragmatic implementation strategies
      that will be evaluated and compared:

      In Strategy 1, CBOs apply for, and are selected for, funding to deliver KIU! through current
      HIV testing programs. Because CBOs do not have the capacity to host the technology, KIU! is
      hosted centrally at Northwestern and deployed by local CBO staff. Training and coaching of
      CBO staff on how to use the technology and integrate it into routine HIV testing is provided
      through capacity building assistance.

      Strategy 2 is a &quot;direct-to-consumer&quot; (DTC) model where centralized staff at Northwestern
      recruit participants nationally through online advertising campaigns and manage participants'
      engagement. HIV/STI testing kits are shipped directly to YMSM, and upon documentation of an
      HIV negative test result, participants are delivered KIU! This DTC model has been widely
      adopted in technology dissemination but it is innovative in terms of implementation of HIV
      prevention programs.

      The investigators will accomplish the goal to inform eHealth intervention implementation with
      two specific aims:

      Aim 1: Compare two implementation strategies using a cluster randomized trial.

      The investigators selected a type III hybrid implementation-effectiveness design, which
      prioritizes empirical comparison of implementation strategies while also collecting evidence
      of effectiveness. The 75 counties with the largest YMSM populations will be randomized 2:1 to
      either Strategy 1 (CBO) or Strategy 2 (DTC). KIU! will be delivered in each county for two
      years. In this cluster randomized trial, the unit of randomization is the county, with
      implementation and effectiveness outcome data collected from YMSM participants, CBOs, and the
      technology vendor. The primary outcomes are public health impact (defined as reach X
      effectiveness) and cost per infection averted, a key component of CDC decision making about
      which HIV prevention programs will be supported.

      Aim 2: Examine adoption characteristics that explain variability in implementation outcomes.

      There is remarkable variability in implementation success when CBOs adopt evidence-based
      interventions. The investigators will seek to explain variability in implementation success
      across counties by conducting mixed-methods research on the domains from the consolidated
      framework for implementation research (CFIR), such as county characteristics, adaptations,
      support from organization leadership, and approach to planning adoption. Data on CFIR
      characteristics will be collected through administrative data, surveys, and telephone
      interviews with key stakeholders.

      In addition to these 2 specific aims, the investigators will explore sustainment of KIU! at
      the completion of the study. CBOs will be provided with materials to facilitate applying for
      external funding to continue to provide KIU! after study completion, including an Impact Tool
      to estimate local impact and costs. The investigators will also examine factors that predict
      applying for funding and ongoing sustainment. For Strategy 2, through consultation with the
      CDC, capacity building assistance providers, health departments, and small businesses
      involved in Health 2.0 initiatives, the investigators will examine models for ongoing
      sustainment of the DTC model.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Public Health Impact (reach X effectiveness)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Public Health Impact (PHI) involves the reach into the county's YMSM community, weighted by HIV risk (i.e., engagement of YMSM from higher risk communities is valued more), and effectiveness at reducing HIV risk, defined as condomless anal sex, STIs, and adherent PrEP use (i.e., three major risk factors for HIV expected to be modified by KIU!).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4400</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Gonorrhea</condition>
  <condition>Chlamydia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community Based Organization (CBO) Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CBOs will be selected through a Request for Proposal (RFP) process. The RFP will describe research and KIU! delivery activities to be conducted as part of the study and allowable budget to carry out the activities. The RFP will ask CBOs to describe past experience providing HIV services for YMSM. Selected CBOs will recruit participants into the intervention and encourage participants to complete each session of intervention content at baseline, 3 Month Follow-up, and 6 Month Follow-up.
Participants in the CBO delivery arm will receive baseline HIV and STI testing at a CBO. Participants will receive an at-home STI test kit at 12 Month Follow-up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Direct to Consumer (DTC) Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the DTC arm, participants will be recruited online via paid social media advertising (e.g., Facebook, Instagram). Advertisements will target placements by age, gender, sexual orientation, racial background, &quot;likes&quot; that are relevant to YMSM (e.g., local LGBT organizations, &quot;out&quot; celebrities), and location (i.e., target county). Dating/sex-seeking apps (e.g., Grindr) will also be used to recruit YMSM, using a similar advertising approach as social media. Study staff at Northwestern University will manage this recruitment process and encourage participants to complete each session of intervention content at baseline, 3 Month Follow-up, and 6 Month Follow-up.
Participants in the DTC delivery arm will receive at-home HIV and STI test kits at baseline. Participants will receive an at-home STI test kit at 12 Month Follow-up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Keep It Up! 3.0</intervention_name>
    <description>KIU! is an online HIV prevention intervention developed for high-risk young men who have sex with men (YMSM) who recently tested HIV negative. Content was developed in collaboration with YMSM-serving CBOs and subjected to usability testing with diverse YMSM. The Information-Motivation-Behavioral Skills model and eLearning principles guided development of highly interactive, engaging, and culturally relevant health messages. KIU! involves 7 modules completed across 3 sessions done at least 24 hours apart, totaling ~1 hour of main content, plus 2 booster sessions at 3- and 6-month follow-ups. Each module is based on a setting or situation relevant to YMSM (e.g., connecting to the gay community and meeting guys through apps), with developmentally appropriate behavior change content embedded. KIU! uses diverse delivery methods (e.g. videos, animation, games) to address HIV knowledge gaps, motivate safer behaviors, teach behavioral skills, and instill self-efficacy for preventive behaviors.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community Based Organization (CBO) Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Direct to Consumer (DTC) Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KIU! 3.0</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  recently received an HIV negative test result

          -  had condomless anal sex with another man in the prior 6 months

          -  resides in an eligible county

          -  speaks/reads English

          -  has an active email address

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  has not been on PrEP and adherent for 6 months prior
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Cisgender men</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Mustanski, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brian Mustanski, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>312.503.5421</phone>
    <email>brian@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Krystal Madkins, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>312.503.6529</phone>
    <email>krystal.madkins@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Mustanski, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-5421</phone>
      <email>brian@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Krystal Madkins, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>312.503.6529</phone>
      <email>krystal.madkins@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brian Mustanski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Institute for Sexual and Gender Minority Health and Wellbeing</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gonorrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The PI agrees to develop a de-identified database, codebook, and mechanism by which IPD could be shared with other investigators upon approval of the PI. Data will be available for request approximately 6 months after completion of the project. Interested investigators will be asked to complete a standardized request form stating the specific aims of the analysis, the analytic plans, resources the requestors have to carry out the project, the proposed timeline, and distribution goals (manuscripts and/or grant application). The PI will review these requests to determine whether the proposed analyses constitute an innovative and significant exploration of the data, whether the proposed team has sufficient resources to undertake the request, how data will be protected/managed, and whether there are sufficient resources to honor the request. If any of these issues are problematic, the PI will attempt to negotiate a fair resolution with the interested parties and/or with NIH program staff.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

