<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03894631</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00002910</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03894631</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Intra-subject Phaco/Trabectome vs. Phaco/Kahook Dual Blade on Intraocular Pressure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intra-subject Comparison Between the Effect of Combined Phaco/Trabectome vs. Phaco/Kahook Dual Blade on Intra Ocular Pressure and Other Surgical Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>State University of New York at Buffalo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>State University of New York at Buffalo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the safety and efficacy of Kahook dual blade over Trabectome in lowering
      intraocular pressure in glaucoma patients. Glaucoma surgery will be performed in conjunction
      with cataract surgery. The investigators hypothesize that the Kahook dual blade is as
      effective as Trabectome in lowering intra-ocular pressure (IOP), and as safe with a similar
      rate of post-operative complications such as hyphema.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Trabectome is a type of Minimally Invasive Glaucoma Surgery (MIGS) where the Trabectome
      handpiece tip uses electrical current to cauterized and remove a strip of trabecular meshwork
      and the roof of Schlemm's canal to ease the outflow of aqueous. Kahook Dual Blade (KDB)
      procedure is another type of MIGS where the dual blade is used to remove the trabecular
      meshwork and Schlemm's canal roof to increase the aqueous outflow but without any
      cauterization.

      Preclinical studies have evaluated the clinical outcome of Trabectome over KDB. Though
      Trabectome helps to lower IOP, it may remove only a portion of trabecular meshwork and
      possibly cause damage to surrounding tissue with leaflets of residual remaining tissue that
      may cause blockage of aqueous drainage. Unlike Trabectome, the KDB removes blocks of
      trabecular meshwork with no residual tissue leaflets, low rate of fibrosis, no damage to the
      surrounding tissue and lower cost. However, research studies have shown that although the
      Trabectome and KDB have different surgical techniques and both have surgical related risks as
      in any glaucoma surgery, the post-surgical clinical outcome and safety profile of Trabectome
      could be favorable to the KDB technique.

      Few studies have evaluated the clinical outcome of Trabectome over Trabeculectomy, while few
      other studies evaluated Trabectome over phaco-trabectome. Some studies evaluated the clinical
      outcome of Trabectome alone while other studies assessed the outcome of KDB alone. Some other
      studies compared KDB with iStent while another study compared Trabectome versus KDB in
      porcine eye perfusion model. Studies have also shown that Trabectome, when combined with
      phaco has a higher success rate than Trabectome alone. However, due to the infancy of KDB
      procedure, there are no robust prospective comparison studies comparing the clinical outcome
      of KDB over Trabectome when combined with phacoemulsification. The aim of the study is to
      systematically compare the clinical outcomes of KDB over Trabectome in treating glaucoma
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in intraocular pressure measurements between baseline and postoperative followup visits</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline (pre-operative condition) and post operative intraocular pressure will be measured on Day1, Week1, Months 1, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in visual acuity measurements measured using a Snellen Vision Chart between baseline and postoperative followup visits</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline (pre-operative condition) and post operative visual acuity will be measured on Day1, Week1, Months 1, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in number of medications between baseline and postoperative followup visits</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline (pre-operative condition) and post operative number of medications list will be measured on Day1, Week1, Months 1, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of post surgical complications</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of post surgical complications such as Hypotony, Corneal Edema, Hyphema, Iritis, Vitreous Hemorrhage and Cystoid Macular Edema.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phaco/KDB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eyes needing glaucoma and cataract extraction will receive combined KDB and phacoemulsification in one eye of a patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phaco/Trabectome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Contralateral eyes needing glaucoma and cataract extraction will receive combined Trabectome and phacoemulsification in contralateral eye of the same patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KDB/Phacoemulsification</intervention_name>
    <description>50 eyes of 50 patients will receive combined KDB/phaco surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phaco/KDB</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trabectome/Phacoemulsification</intervention_name>
    <description>The contralateral 50 eyes of the same 50 patients will receive combined Trabectome /phaco surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phaco/Trabectome</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients age ≥18 years old

          -  Patients already diagnosed with Glaucoma and Cataract in both eyes

          -  Patients with Primary open angle glaucoma (POAG), Low-tension glaucoma (LTG),
             Pseudoexfoliation glaucoma (PSXF), pigmentary glaucoma and other glaucoma types with a
             structurally-normal looking open angle in both eyes

          -  Glaucoma that is inadequately controlled on medical therapy or with the need to reduce
             the glaucoma medication burden

          -  Patients with a visually-significant cataract in both eyes

          -  Patients that could benefit from cataract removal combined with MIGS surgery in both
             eyes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients age less than 18 years

          -  Women of child bearing age

          -  Patients unable or unwilling to provide informed consent to participate in the study

          -  Aphakic and Pseudophakic patients

          -  Patients with primary open angle glaucoma with previously failed trabeculectomy or
             other glaucoma aqueous drainage surgical procedures

          -  Patients with a closed angle, angle neovascularization (NVG), traumatic glaucoma, or
             any other angle abnormality in either eye

          -  Patients potentially unavailable for follow up visits for the length of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asher Weiner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>State University of New York at Buffalo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Asher Weiner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>716-881-7900</phone>
    <email>aweiner7@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sharon A Michalovic, AAS, BA</last_name>
    <phone>716-881-7975</phone>
    <email>sab1@buffalo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ira G. Ross Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Asher Weiner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>716-881-7900</phone>
      <email>aweiner7@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sharon A Michalovic, AAS, BA</last_name>
      <phone>716-881-7975</phone>
      <email>sab1@buffalo.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Asher Weiner, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kahook dual blade</keyword>
  <keyword>Trabectome</keyword>
  <keyword>Intraocular Pressure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

