<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03893058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NP2963</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03893058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the NeuroMuscular Junction Using the Single Fiber Electromyography and Reliability of Train-Of-Four in Critically Ill Patients.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the NeuroMuscular Junction Using the Single Fiber Electromyography and Reliability of Train-Of-Four in Critically Ill Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Socio Sanitaria Territoriale degli Spedali Civili di Brescia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Socio Sanitaria Territoriale degli Spedali Civili di Brescia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients suffering from critical illnesses who are admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU)
      are often affected by multiple organ failure. Among those dysfunctions, it is very important
      to mention the neuromuscular system failure, known as Intensive Care Unit-Acquired Weakness
      (ICU-AW). In non-cooperative patients, the simplified electromyography (called Peroneal Nerve
      Test, PENT) allows diagnosing the Critical Illness Polyneuropathy (CIP) and/or the Critical
      Illness Myopathy (CIM), which are two causes of ICU-AW. The ICU-AW can involve both nerves
      and muscles, but so far there has been no evidence about the involvement of the third element
      of the neuromuscular system: the neuromuscular junction (NMJ). The gold standard technique to
      study the function of the NMJ is the Desmedt test, a particular type of Electroneurography
      (ENG); the Single Fiber Electromyography (SF-EMG ) might be a valid and more sensitive
      technique for this analysis. The spreading use of Neuromuscular Blocking Agents (NMBAs) has
      led to the introduction of the Train-Of-Four acceleromyography (TOF) monitoring in ICU;
      however, there is a lack of information on its reliability in critically ill patients.

      Some conditions related to critical illness, like the ICU-AW, could make TOF monitoring
      unreliable.

      The aims of the study are:

        1. To estimate the prevalence of NMJ disorders acquired during critical illnesses using
           SF-EMG.

        2. To assess the reliability of TOF in critically ill patients. The study will evaluate
           patients with critical illnesses hospitalised in the General Intensive Care Unit (UOC
           Anestesia e Rianimazione 2, Spedali Civili di Brescia). To diagnose CIP and/or CIM, PENT
           will be performed after 72 hours from the admission in the ICU and every 72 hours. To
           evaluate NMJ disorders, SF-EMG will be performed in patients with an abnormal PENT. To
           evaluate the reliability of TOF, the test will be performed before, during and after
           NMBAs treatment and in all studied patients, independently from NMBAs administration;
           the presence of neuromuscular blockade will be evaluated clinically and/or using
           instrumental tests like Desmedt test. Statistical analysis will be performed to
           represent the prevalence of NMJ disorders in the general intensivistic population and
           the reliability of TOF in terms of specificity and sensitivity for the diagnosis of the
           neuromuscular blockade.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      COMPLETE TITLE OF THE STUDY: EVALUATION OF THE NEUROMUSCULAR JUNCTION USING THE SINGLE FIBER
      ELECTROMYOGRAPHY AND RELIABILITY OF TRAIN-OF-FOUR IN CRITICALLY ILL PATIENTS. Author and
      responsible for the study: Dr. Matteo Filippini Sponsor: ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia -
      Italy

        1. RATIONALE OF THE STUDY Patients suffering from critical illnesses who are admitted to
           the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) are often affected by multiple organ failure. Among those
           dysfunctions, it is very important to mention the neuromuscular system failure, known as
           Intensive Care Unit-Acquired Weakness (ICU-AW). In non-cooperative patients, the
           simplified electromyography (called Peroneal Nerve Test, PENT) allows diagnosing the
           Critical Illness Polyneuropathy (CIP) and/or the Critical Illness Myopathy (CIM), which
           are two causes of ICU-AW. The ICU-AW can involve both nerves and muscles, but so far
           there has been no evidence about the involvement of the third element of the
           neuromuscular system: the neuromuscular junction (NMJ). The gold standard technique to
           study the function of the NMJ is the Desmedt test, a particular type of
           Electroneurography (ENG); the Single Fiber Electromyography (SF-EMG ) might be a valid
           and more sensitive technique for this analysis. The spreading use of Neuromuscular
           Blocking Agents (NMBAs) has led to the introduction of the Train-Of-Four
           acceleromyography (TOF) monitoring in ICU; however, there is a lack of information on
           its reliability in critically ill patients. Some conditions related to critical illness,
           like the ICU-AW, could make TOF monitoring unreliable.

        2. STUDY AIMS A. To estimate the prevalence of NMJ disorders acquired during critical
           illnesses using SF-EMG. B. To assess the reliability of TOF in critically ill patients.

        3. POPULATION Target population: patients with critical illnesses hospitalised in the
           General Intensive Care Unit (UOC Anestesia e Rianimazione 2, Spedali Civili di Brescia).
           Inclusion criteria: adult patients (18-year-old and older ones) hospitalised in ICU. In
           order to realise the first aim of the study, patients with a pathologic PENT will be
           evaluated. In order to realise the second aim of the study, patients who receive NMBAs
           will be evaluated; patients who do not receive NMBAs will also be evaluated, as a
           control group.

           Exclusion criteria:

             -  patients with a terminal disease;

             -  patients with an ICU-length-of-staying perspective less than 72 hours;

             -  patients with a chronic disease associated with known neuropathy or myopathy;

             -  patients treated with drugs that may cause neurotoxicity and myotoxicity;

             -  patients with primary or secondary acute Peripheral Nervous System (PNS) lesions or
                muscle lesions;

             -  patients with prosthesis, wounds or other conditions that prevent
                electrophysiological testing.

        4. STUDY DESIGN Observational, prospective, cohort study; retrospective analysis of
           prospectively collected data.

        5. OPERATIVE PROCEDURES

             -  to diagnose CIP and/or CIM, PENT will be performed after 72 hours from the
                admission in the ICU and every 72 hours.

             -  to evaluate NMJ disorders, SF-EMG will be performed in patients with an abnormal
                PENT.

             -  to evaluate the reliability of TOF, the test will be performed before, during and
                after NMBAs treatment and in all studied patients, independently from NMBAs
                administration; the presence of the neuromuscular blockade will be evaluated
                clinically and/or using instrumental tests like Desmedt test.

           PROCEDURES:

           SIMPLIFIED ELECTROMYOGRAPHY (EMG) The simplified EMG is called Peroneal Nerve Test
           (PENT), and it consists in measuring the compound muscle action potential (CMAP) of a
           single peroneal nerve (if the first peroneal nerve tested is pathologic) or of both
           peroneal nerves (if the first nerve is healthy). ICU-AW is diagnosed in case of
           reduction of CMAP under the usual cutoff (calculated as two standard deviations from the
           average laboratory value). SF-EMG - SINGLE FIBER ELECTROMYOGRAPHY The Single Fiber
           Electromyography (SF-EMG) is a test which studies action potentials of single muscular
           fibre. It allows the study of muscular fibres microphysiology, and it investigates early
           alterations (sometimes preclinical) of NMJ, typical of Myasthenia Gravis. The needle
           electrode for the single fibre analysis is composed of a small registration surface, and
           this is the cathode, while a second electrode is the anode. The muscle action potential
           registration follows the tested muscles activation and this activation can be voluntary
           (voluntary SF-EMG) or through stimulation (stimulated SF-EMG), with a stimulation
           frequency of 2-10 Hz, an intensity of 10-20 mA and a duration between 10-50 ms. The
           variation in the time interval between two action potentials of the same motor unit is
           called &quot;jitter&quot;. SF-EMG measures the variation of this inter potential interval
           (jitter), which can be increased in patients with NMJ diseases. TOF - TRAIN-OF-FOUR
           ACCELEROMYOGRAPHY The TOF acceleromyography consists in the consecutive application of
           four electrical stimuli (generally 200 ms, 50 mA) through the course of the ulnar nerve
           and in the recording of the induced thumb acceleration; the result of this test is
           expressed as the ratio of the fourth to the first magnitude of the response. If the
           ratio is greater than 90%, the response will be considered normal, and the clinical
           meaning of this finding is that the patient is not (or no more) under the effect of
           NMBAs. Conversely, if the ratio is less than 90%, the clinical meaning is that the
           patient is under the effect of non-depolarising NMBAs. TOOLS Paper and electronic
           detection boards. OTHER EVALUATIONS Collection of clinical data useful for describing
           the status of the investigated population. DATA MANAGEMENT Electrophysiological
           measurements data conducted to the patient's bed will be integrated with
           clinical-physical and laboratory data ordered in a worksheet (progressive number,
           diagnosis, initials, age, sex, weight, height, BMI, days of hospitalization, length of
           staying in the ICU, previous surgical procedures, inflammation indexes, liver and kidney
           function indexes, coagulation function indexes, mechanical ventilation mode, simplified
           acute physiology score II [SAPS II] and sequential order failure assessment [SOFA]
           score). Data collection: data will be collected daily by the principal investigator, as
           well as by students and resident physicians involved in the project and previously
           provided with appropriate authorisation to attend the centre for training purposes.
           Rules on personal data management: see the next point for the respect of privacy.
           Operational methods of data management: recording of data on paper and/or electronic
           card without uploading to file, management of electronic archives or linkage procedures
           with other databases.

        6. STATISTICAL ANALYSIS AND METHODS

           A descriptive statistical analysis will be performed to represent:

           A. The characteristics of the population: number of subjects, sex, age, body mass index
           (BMI), Glasgow Come Score (GCS), SOFA score and SAPS II, days of hospitalization in ICU,
           reason for admission to ICU, use of amines, presence and severity of the infectious
           state. In particular:

             -  Qualitative variables (e.g. sex, disease) will be expressed as mode and frequency
                distribution.

             -  Ordinal quantitative variables (e.g. GCS) will be expressed as median and
                interquartile range.

             -  Continuous quantitative variables (e.g. age, BMI) will be expressed as mean and
                standard deviation.

           B. The results of the applied diagnostic tests:

             -  the result of the PENT will be expressed as the magnitude of the potential (mV);

             -  the result of the SF-EMG will be expressed as the variation in the time interval
                between the two action potentials of the same motor unit (jitter) (msec)

             -  the result of the TOF will be expressed as the ratio of the fourth response
                magnitude to the first one. An inferential statistical analysis will be performed
                to represent the prevalence of NMJ disorders in the general intensivistic
                population and the reliability of TOF in terms of specificity and sensitivity for
                the diagnosis of the neuromuscular blockade. SAMPLE SIZE The investigator's
                hypothesis is that NMJ disorders in the study population are non-existent or in any
                case epidemiologically irrelevant: therefore a sample of 73 patients with a
                negative test will allow affirming that the prevalence of that disorder is less
                than 10%. If one or more SF-EMG tests are positive, the prevalence of NMJ disorders
                will be calculated from those results with a 95% confidence interval. After the
                enrolment of 35 patients studied with SF-EMG, an ad-interim analysis will be
                performed, and the prevalence of NMJ disorders will be estimated by an exact
                binomial test, and the 95% confidence interval will be calculated. In order to
                realise the second aim of the study (to assess the reliability of TOF in critically
                ill patients) a sample of 85 patients will allow estimating sensitivity and
                specificity with a precision of 10% under the realistic hypothesis that they are
                100% and 90% respectively.

        7. ETHICAL ASPECTS The study, being observational, will not entail, in itself, any risk for
           any patient. The data of the patients included in the study will be physical-technical
           (PENT and SF-EMG tests) and clinical-laboratoristic. They will be obtained from standard
           clinical practice. The investigator will proceed to exhaustive information about the
           nature of the study and the operations of analysis towards patients; the same patients,
           made aware of the nature of the collected data, will be required to express the informed
           consent, according to the regulations in force. In the case of patients unable to give
           valid consent, data collection and processing will only take place after the patients
           themselves have regained their lost capacity and have given consent or after this has
           been done by legal representatives. The study does not alter the risk/benefit ratio of
           the procedures used for data acquisition; concerning the specific acts of the study,
           this ratio is zero. This study will be conducted in accordance with this protocol, with
           the principles of good clinical practice in accordance with the International Conference
           on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Pharmaceuticals for Human Use (ICH GCP)
           guidelines and ethical principles set out in the Helsinki Declaration.

        8. INFORMATION TO THE PATIENT AND CONSENT The patients will express their informed consent
           to the conduct of the study and the management of sensitive data by signing their own
           form on the specially prepared forms. In the case of patients lacking the ability to act
           and for which there is a legal representative, the informed consent will be given by the
           latter. The informative note before the acquisition of consent will be provided by the
           principal investigator.

        9. APPROVAL BY THE RESPONSIBLE ETHICS COMMITTEE The documents of the study were reviewed
           and approved by the responsible Ethics Committee (Comitato Etico di Brescia, NP2963).

       10. CONFIDENTIALITY OF DATA AND PRIVACY The confidentiality of the collected data (including
           laboratory data) will be maintained through the rigorous conservation of data collection
           cards by the investigators and the patients involved will be identified with codes that
           guarantee anonymity, even in order to comply with the privacy of the subjects, according
           to the law in force.

       11. DATA PROPERTY The ownership of the data related to the study, its execution and its
           results belong to the sponsor.

       12. PUBLICATION OF RESULTS The investigator reserves the right to publish the results of the
           study through works published in specialised journals whose editorial policies respect
           the laws in force, with particular reference to the anonymity of the data.

       13. CONSERVATION OF STUDY DOCUMENTS All information related to the study participants,
           including data collection forms, documentation &quot;source&quot; (in addition to the medical
           records already stored by the hospital), all clinical and laboratory data used for the
           study, as well as all the documentation concerning the submission and approval by the
           Ethics Committee, the informed consent and all the regulatory documentation, etc. will
           be kept by the investigators in a safe and accessible place for possible inspections.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of NeuroMuscularJunction disorders acquired during critical illnesses.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence will be assessed as the proportion of patients found to be affected by NMJ disorders (assessed by SFEMG) among the population of critically ill patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reliability (specificity and sensitivity) of Train-Of-Four in critically ill patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The sensitivity of TOF for the diagnosis of the neuromuscular blockade will be expressed as the proportion of patients with the neuromuscular blockade and with abnormal TOF ratio (&lt;90%) among patients with the neuromuscular blockade and with normal or abnormal TOF ratio.
The specificity of TOF for the diagnosis of the neuromuscular blockade will be expressed as the proportion of patients without the neuromuscular blockade and with normal TOF ratio (&gt;90%) among patients without neuromuscular blockade and with normal or abnormal TOF ratio.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">85</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness Polyneuropathy</condition>
  <condition>Critical Illness Myopathy</condition>
  <condition>Weakness Due to Disease</condition>
  <condition>Neuromuscular Blockade</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients with critical illnesses hospitalised in the General Intensive Care Unit (UOC
        Anestesia e Rianimazione 2, Spedali Civili di Brescia)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Adult patients (18-year-old and older ones) hospitalised in ICU. In order to realise the
        first aim of the study (to estimate the prevalence of NMJ disorders acquired during
        critical illnesses using SF-EMG), patients with a pathologic PENT will be evaluated. In
        order to realise the second aim of the study (to assess the reliability of TOF in
        critically ill patients. The study will evaluate patients with critical illnesses
        hospitalised in the General Intensive Care Unit), patients who receive NMBAs will be
        evaluated; patients who do not receive NMBAs will also be evaluated, as a control group.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with a terminal disease;

          -  patients with an ICU-length-of-staying perspective less than 72 hours;

          -  patients with a chronic disease associated with known neuropathy or myopathy;

          -  patients treated with drugs that may cause neurotoxicity and myotoxicity;

          -  patients with primary or secondary acute Peripheral Nervous System (PNS) lesions or
             muscle lesions;

          -  patients with prosthesis, wounds or other conditions that prevent electrophysiological
             testing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <zip>25124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farhan H, Moreno-Duarte I, Latronico N, Zafonte R, Eikermann M. Acquired Muscle Weakness in the Surgical Intensive Care Unit: Nosology, Epidemiology, Diagnosis, and Prevention. Anesthesiology. 2016 Jan;124(1):207-34. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000874. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26445385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Argov Z, Latronico N. Neuromuscular complications in intensive care patients. Handb Clin Neurol. 2014;121:1673-85. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-7020-4088-7.00108-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24365440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eikermann M, Latronico N. What is new in prevention of muscle weakness in critically ill patients? Intensive Care Med. 2013 Dec;39(12):2200-3. doi: 10.1007/s00134-013-3132-4. Epub 2013 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24154675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Filosto M, Fagoni N, Gheza L, Guarneri B, Todeschini A, Lombardi R, Padovani A, Lauria G. Small nerve fiber pathology in critical illness. PLoS One. 2013 Sep 30;8(9):e75696. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0075696. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24098716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Tomelleri G, Filosto M. Critical illness myopathy. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 2012 Nov;24(6):616-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22918529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Bolton CF. Critical illness polyneuropathy and myopathy: a major cause of muscle weakness and paralysis. Lancet Neurol. 2011 Oct;10(10):931-41. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70178-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21939902</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Rasulo FA. Presentation and management of ICU myopathy and neuropathy. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2010 Apr;16(2):123-7. doi: 10.1097/MCC.0b013e328336a229. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20075723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katirji B, Kaminski HJ. Electrodiagnostic approach to the patient with suspected neuromuscular junction disorder. Neurol Clin. 2002 May;20(2):557-86, viii.</citation>
    <PMID>12152447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonoo M, Uesugi H, Mochizuki A, Hatanaka Y, Shimizu T. Single fiber EMG and repetitive nerve stimulation of the same extensor digitorum communis muscle in myasthenia gravis. Clin Neurophysiol. 2001 Feb;112(2):300-3.</citation>
    <PMID>11165533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Padua L, Caliandro P, Di Iasi G, Pazzaglia C, Ciaraffa F, Evoli A. Reliability of SFEMG in diagnosing myasthenia gravis: sensitivity and specificity calculated on 100 prospective cases. Clin Neurophysiol. 2014 Jun;125(6):1270-3. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2013.11.005. Epub 2013 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>24296278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tschida SJ, Hoey LL, Vance-Bryan K. Inconsistency with train-of-four monitoring in a critically ill paralyzed patient. Pharmacotherapy. 1995 Jul-Aug;15(4):540-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7479211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rudis MI, Guslits BG, Zarowitz BJ. Technical and interpretive problems of peripheral nerve stimulation in monitoring neuromuscular blockade in the intensive care unit. Ann Pharmacother. 1996 Feb;30(2):165-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8835051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lagneau F, Benayoun L, Plaud B, Bonnet F, Favier J, Marty J. The interpretation of train-of-four monitoring in intensive care: what about the muscle site and the current intensity? Intensive Care Med. 2001 Jun;27(6):1058-63.</citation>
    <PMID>11497139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenberg SB, Vender J. The use of neuromuscular blocking agents in the ICU: where are we now? Crit Care Med. 2013 May;41(5):1332-44. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e31828ce07c. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23591211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Puthucheary Z, Rawal J, Ratnayake G, Harridge S, Montgomery H, Hart N. Neuromuscular blockade and skeletal muscle weakness in critically ill patients: time to rethink the evidence? Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2012 May 1;185(9):911-7. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201107-1320OE.</citation>
    <PMID>22550208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strange C, Vaughan L, Franklin C, Johnson J. Comparison of train-of-four and best clinical assessment during continuous paralysis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1997 Nov;156(5):1556-61.</citation>
    <PMID>9372675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dieye E, Minville V, Asehnoune K, Conil C, Georges B, Cougot P, Fourcade O, Conil JM. Pharmacodynamics of cisatracurium in the intensive care unit: an observational study. Ann Intensive Care. 2014 Feb 11;4(1):3. doi: 10.1186/2110-5820-4-3.</citation>
    <PMID>24521394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Nattino G, Guarneri B, Fagoni N, Amantini A, Bertolini G; GiVITI Study Investigators. Validation of the peroneal nerve test to diagnose critical illness polyneuropathy and myopathy in the intensive care unit: the multicentre Italian CRIMYNE-2 diagnostic accuracy study. Version 3. F1000Res. 2014 Jun 11 [revised 2014 Jan 1];3:127. doi: 10.12688/f1000research.3933.3. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25309729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Gosselink R. A guided approach to diagnose severe muscle weakness in the intensive care unit. Rev Bras Ter Intensiva. 2015 Jul-Sep;27(3):199-201. doi: 10.5935/0103-507X.20150036. Epub 2015 Sep 15. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>26376161</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fan E, Cheek F, Chlan L, Gosselink R, Hart N, Herridge MS, Hopkins RO, Hough CL, Kress JP, Latronico N, Moss M, Needham DM, Rich MM, Stevens RD, Wilson KC, Winkelman C, Zochodne DW, Ali NA; ATS Committee on ICU-acquired Weakness in Adults; American Thoracic Society. An official American Thoracic Society Clinical Practice guideline: the diagnosis of intensive care unit-acquired weakness in adults. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2014 Dec 15;190(12):1437-46. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201411-2011ST.</citation>
    <PMID>25496103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latronico N, Bertolini G, Guarneri B, Botteri M, Peli E, Andreoletti S, Bera P, Luciani D, Nardella A, Vittorielli E, Simini B, Candiani A. Simplified electrophysiological evaluation of peripheral nerves in critically ill patients: the Italian multi-centre CRIMYNE study. Crit Care. 2007;11(1):R11.</citation>
    <PMID>17254336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vincent JL, Moreno R, Takala J, Willatts S, De Mendonça A, Bruining H, Reinhart CK, Suter PM, Thijs LG. The SOFA (Sepsis-related Organ Failure Assessment) score to describe organ dysfunction/failure. On behalf of the Working Group on Sepsis-Related Problems of the European Society of Intensive Care Medicine. Intensive Care Med. 1996 Jul;22(7):707-10.</citation>
    <PMID>8844239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cominotti S, Chiaranda M, Mascetti P, Lucchini E, Severgnini P. [Comparison of SAPS II, MPM II24 and SAPS in intensive care]. Minerva Anestesiol. 1999 Oct;65(10):717-23. Italian.</citation>
    <PMID>10598429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Unterbuchner C, Blobner M, Pühringer F, Janda M, Bischoff S, Bein B, Schmidt A, Ulm K, Pithamitsis V, Fink H. Development of an algorithm using clinical tests to avoid post-operative residual neuromuscular block. BMC Anesthesiol. 2017 Aug 4;17(1):101. doi: 10.1186/s12871-017-0393-4.</citation>
    <PMID>28778151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naguib M, Brull SJ, Johnson KB. Conceptual and technical insights into the basis of neuromuscular monitoring. Anaesthesia. 2017 Jan;72 Suppl 1:16-37. doi: 10.1111/anae.13738. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28044330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buderer NM. Statistical methodology: I. Incorporating the prevalence of disease into the sample size calculation for sensitivity and specificity. Acad Emerg Med. 1996 Sep;3(9):895-900. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8870764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Socio Sanitaria Territoriale degli Spedali Civili di Brescia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matteo Filippini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Train-Of-Four</keyword>
  <keyword>Single Fiber Electromyography</keyword>
  <keyword>NeuroMuscular Junction</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Illness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polyneuropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

