<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03895489</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00087023</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03895489</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of the Journey Total Knee Arthroplasty Versus Two Standard of Care Total Knee Arthroplasty Prostheses</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Effectiveness of the Journey Total Knee Arthroplasty Relative to Two Standard of Care Total Knee Arthroplasty Prostheses: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine if knee replacement performed using Journey II
      implant is different from two other standard-of-care knee replacements using Stryker and
      Zimmer in terms of knee movements and forces, walking patterns, pain, and function after
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Osteoarthritis is the most prevalent form of arthritis, with weight-bearing joints,
      particularly the knee commonly affected. Osteoarthritis is a leading cause of mobility
      disability and is associated with functional loss in adults. Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) is
      cost-effective and successful for those with end-stage knee osteoarthritis. In 2016/17, about
      67,169 TKAs were performed in Canada, an increase of 16% since 2012/13.

      Justification

      TKA aims to improve joint mechanics as well as knee pain and function. Patients indicate that
      their primary expectations following TKA are improved pain and walking ability. Most TKA
      implants are fixed bearing (such as Stryker and Zimmer) with no movement of the implant with
      knee motion. The Journey II TKA has a medial pivot function that may improve patient outcomes
      further, by replicating meniscal function. However, this has not yet been proven as it would
      require more specific measurement of knee kinetics and kinematics such as we propose here.

      The outcome of this study will provide information about knee pain, movements (kinematics)
      and forces (kinetics) and walking patterns after TKA using different implants. Through this
      study, we should be able to inform future research on rehabilitation protocols to alter knee
      movements after TKA, while enhancing patients' function and quality of life.

      Hypotheses

      Primary Hypothesis: We hypothesize that TKA performed using the Smith and Nephew Richards
      (SNR) Journey II TKA system will be superior to standard TKA prostheses (Stryker Triathlon
      Total Knee System and Zimmer Persona® The Personalized Knee) in terms of knee biomechanics
      (knee kinematics and kinetics) and spatio-temporal gait parameters at 1-year post-TKA using
      the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation ENvironment (CAREN).

      Secondary Hypothesis: We hypothesize that the Smith and Nephew Richards (SNR) Journey II TKA
      will provide increased improvement from preoperative levels in pain and function in
      comparison to standard TKA prostheses.

      Objectives

      Primary Objective: The primary objective of this randomized, comparative trial is to
      demonstrate that TKA performed using the Smith and Nephew Richards (SNR) Journey II TKA
      system is superior to standard TKA prostheses (Stryker Triathlon Total Knee System and Zimmer
      Persona® The Personalized Knee) in terms of knee biomechanics (knee kinematics and kinetics)
      and spatio-temporal gait parameters at 1-year post-TKA using the Computer-Assisted
      Rehabilitation ENvironment (CAREN). We will evaluate these parameters for level treadmill
      walking.

      Secondary Objective: The secondary objective of this study will be to demonstrate that the
      Smith and Nephew Richards (SNR) Journey II TKA provides increased improvement from
      preoperative levels in pain and function in comparison to standard TKA prostheses. The new
      Knee Society Clinical Rating Scores (KSCRS) will be calculated preoperatively and at 1 year
      and 2 years postoperatively with the potential for longer-term follow-up. Patient
      questionnaires will be assessed preoperatively and at each postoperative interval.

      Study Design: A prospective, randomized, post-market, comparative design will be employed.

      Participants: A total of 60 participants will be enrolled in this study. Twenty (20)
      participants will receive the Journey II TKA System. Forty (40) participants will receive
      standard TKA: 20 will receive the Stryker Triathlon Total Knee System and 20 will receive
      Zimmer Persona® The Personalized Knee, which are commonly used in this zone.

      Randomization: This study will utilize a computer-generated 1:1 randomization scheme. The
      randomization schedule will be maintained and controlled by Collaborative Orthopaedic
      REsearch (CORe) at the University of Alberta. The investigators and research associates will
      not have access to this schedule. When an eligible patient meets the criteria for inclusion
      in the study and signs the informed consent form, the research associate will open a
      sequentially-numbered envelope that contains the group allocation. Baseline gait evaluation
      will be completed for randomized patients. Any deviation from the assigned treatment group
      will be reported as a deviation from the protocol. Participants deviating from the
      randomization assignment will continue to be followed, and data collected will be reported as
      per intention to treat principles.

      Estimated Study Duration: The enrollment period is estimated to last a maximum of 18 to 24
      months. Participants will be evaluated per the evaluation schedule until the 2 year follow-up
      time point (secondary objective). It is possible that the study will be extended to
      longer-term follow-up to evaluate long-term performance.

      Pre-operative visit

      During the preoperative visit, patients who are possible candidates for this study will be
      screened to determine if they meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria. If the patient is a
      candidate, the investigator will propose participation in the study to the patient, and the
      patient will be given a consent-to-contact form by the investigator. If the patient consents
      to be contacted, the research associate would contact the patient to provide more details
      about the study. If the patient is willing to proceed with the study, an approved informed
      consent form must be signed by the patient prior to participating in any study related
      activities.

      Once the patient has consented to participate in the study, preoperative data will be
      collected including: demographics, medical history, preoperative gait analysis and functional
      evaluation (KSCRS), EQ-5D - a standardized instrument that measures health-related quality of
      life, UCLA activity-level rating (UCLA), knee injury and osteoarthritis outcome score (KOOS),
      and the Forgotten Joint Score.

      Follow-up visits

      Gait analysis and patient-reported outcomes (PRO) data will be collected at the following
      postoperative intervals: 1-year (gait and PRO), 2 years (PRO) and potentially during
      longer-term follow-up (PRO).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>knee flexion-extension range of motion (ROM) during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Angle of knee measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Degree</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>knee flexion-extension range of motion (ROM) during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Angle of knee measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Degree</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>knee abduction-adduction range of motion (ROM) during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Angle of knee measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Degree</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>knee abduction-adduction range of motion (ROM) during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Angle of knee measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Degree</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max velocity of knee flexion-extension during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee velocity measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN). Unit: degree/s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max velocity of knee flexion-extension during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee velocity measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN). Unit: degree/s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max velocity of knee abduction-adduction during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee velocity measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: degree/s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max velocity of knee abduction-adduction during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee velocity measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: degree/s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max moment of knee flexion-extension during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee moment measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Newton meter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max moment of knee flexion-extension during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee moment measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Newton meter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max moment of knee abduction-adduction during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee moment measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Newton meter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Max moment of knee abduction-adduction during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Knee moment measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Newton meter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking velocity during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Walking velocity (the quotient of the distance traveled by the time) measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: m/s</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking velocity during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Walking velocity (the quotient of the distance traveled by the time) measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: m/s</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cadence during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Cadence (the quotient of the number of steps taken per minute) measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Steps/min</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cadence during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Cadence (the quotient of the number of steps taken per minute) measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: Steps/min</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stride length during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Stride length (the distance between the position (e.g., heel strike) of one foot to the next similar position in the same foot (e.g. next heel strike)) measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: meter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stride length during level treadmill walking</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Stride length (the distance between the position (e.g., heel strike) of one foot to the next similar position in the same foot (e.g. next heel strike)) measured using the Computer-Assisted Rehabilitation Environment (CAREN).
Unit: meter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The new Knee Society Clinical Rating Scores (KSCRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>The function subscale of this scorning system (KSCRS) quantifies the function of the knee.
Score: 100</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The new Knee Society Clinical Rating Scores (KSCRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The function subscale of this scorning system (KSCRS) quantifies the function of the knee.
Score: 100</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The new Knee Society Clinical Rating Scores (KSCRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The function subscale of this scorning system (KSCRS) quantifies the function of the knee.
Score: 100</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Euro-Quality of Life five dimensions questionnaire (EQ-5D)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized instrument that measures health-related quality of life. consists of 2 parts:
EQ-5D-5L: self-report, generic health utility instrument with 5 domains (mobility, self-care, pain/discomfort, depression/anxiety, and usual activities) and 5 levels in each domain (no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems).
EQ Visual Analogue scale (EQ VAS): Scores: 100 = the best health you can imagine and 0 = the worst health you can imagine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Euro-Quality of Life five dimensions questionnaire (EQ-5D)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized instrument that measures health-related quality of life. consists of 2 parts:
EQ-5D-5L: self-report, generic health utility instrument with 5 domains (mobility, self-care, pain/discomfort, depression/anxiety, and usual activities) and 5 levels in each domain (no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems).
EQ Visual Analogue scale (EQ VAS): Scores: 100 = the best health you can imagine and 0 = the worst health you can imagine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Euro-Quality of Life five dimensions questionnaire (EQ-5D)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized instrument that measures health-related quality of life. consists of 2 parts:
EQ-5D-5L: self-report, generic health utility instrument with 5 domains (mobility, self-care, pain/discomfort, depression/anxiety, and usual activities) and 5 levels in each domain (no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems).
EQ Visual Analogue scale (EQ VAS): Scores: 100 = the best health you can imagine and 0 = the worst health you can imagine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>UCLA activity-level rating (UCLA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Scale to assess activity ranging from 1 to 10. The patient indicates her or his most appropriate activity level, with 1 defined as ''wholly inactive and dependent on others'' and 10 defined as ''regular participation in impact sports.''</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>UCLA activity-level rating (UCLA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Scale to assess activity ranging from 1 to 10. The patient indicates her or his most appropriate activity level, with 1 defined as ''wholly inactive and dependent on others'' and 10 defined as ''regular participation in impact sports.''</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>UCLA activity-level rating (UCLA)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Scale to assess activity ranging from 1 to 10. The patient indicates her or his most appropriate activity level, with 1 defined as ''wholly inactive and dependent on others'' and 10 defined as ''regular participation in impact sports.''</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>knee injury and osteoarthritis outcome score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire to assess knee outcomes: Pain, other Symptoms, Function in daily living (ADL), Function in sport and recreation (Sport/Rec) and knee related Quality of life (QOL).
A normalized score (100 indicating no symptoms and 0 indicating extreme symptoms) is calculated for each subscale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>knee injury and osteoarthritis outcome score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire to assess knee outcomes: Pain, other Symptoms, Function in daily living (ADL), Function in sport and recreation (Sport/Rec) and knee related Quality of life (QOL).
A normalized score (100 indicating no symptoms and 0 indicating extreme symptoms) is calculated for each subscale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>knee injury and osteoarthritis outcome score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire to assess knee outcomes: Pain, other Symptoms, Function in daily living (ADL), Function in sport and recreation (Sport/Rec) and knee related Quality of life (QOL).
A normalized score (100 indicating no symptoms and 0 indicating extreme symptoms) is calculated for each subscale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forgotten Joint Score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month preoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Scale that shows how aware patients are of their artificial hip/knee joint in everyday life. Total score range: 0 to 100. Finally, the score is subtracted from 100, to change the direction of the final score in a way that high scores indicate a high degree of &quot;forgetting&quot; the artificial joint, that is, a low degree of awareness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forgotten Joint Score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Scale that shows how aware patients are of their artificial hip/knee joint in everyday life. Total score range: 0 to 100. Finally, the score is subtracted from 100, to change the direction of the final score in a way that high scores indicate a high degree of &quot;forgetting&quot; the artificial joint, that is, a low degree of awareness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forgotten Joint Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Scale that shows how aware patients are of their artificial hip/knee joint in everyday life. Total score range: 0 to 100. Finally, the score is subtracted from 100, to change the direction of the final score in a way that high scores indicate a high degree of &quot;forgetting&quot; the artificial joint, that is, a low degree of awareness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Journey II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Smith and Nephew Richards (SNR) Journey II Knee prosthesis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stryker</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stryker Triathlon Total Knee prosthesis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zimmer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Zimmer Persona® The Personalized Knee prosthesis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Journey II</intervention_name>
    <description>Smith and Nephew Richards (SNR) Journey II Knee prosthesis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Journey II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stryker</intervention_name>
    <description>Stryker Triathlon Total Knee prosthesis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stryker</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zimmer</intervention_name>
    <description>Zimmer Persona® The Personalized Knee prosthesis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zimmer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant has signed an approved informed consent form.

          2. Participant is a male or non-pregnant female and aged 50 to 75 years at the time of
             study device implantation.

          3. Participant has a diagnosis of Non-Inflammatory Degenerative Joint Disease (NIDJD).

          4. Participant is a candidate for a primary posterior-stabilized total knee replacement.

          5. Participant is willing and able to comply with postoperative scheduled clinical and
             radiographic evaluations and rehabilitation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant has a Body Mass Index (BMI) ≥ 35 kg/m2.

          2. Participant has a varus or valgus deformity greater than 15º or flexion contracture
             greater than 20º or knee flexion range of motion &lt; 90º in either lower extremity.

          3. Participant has an active or suspected latent infection in or about the affected knee
             joint at time of study device implantation.

          4. Participant has received any orthopaedic surgical intervention to the lower
             extremities within the past 6 months or is expected to require any orthopaedic
             surgical intervention to the lower extremities, other than the TKA, within the next
             year.

          5. Participant requires bilateral total knee replacements, or has a history of
             contralateral partial or total knee replacement within the past 6 months.

          6. Participant has other medical conditions which limit the ability to evaluate the
             safety and efficacy of the device.

          7. Participant requires revision surgery of a previously implanted total knee replacement
             or knee fusion to the affected joint.

          8. Participant has a known sensitivity to device materials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ailar Ramadi, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>780-492-6713</phone>
    <email>Ailar.Ramadi@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Edmonton Bone and Joint Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T5E 5R8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ailar Ramadi, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>780-492-6713</phone>
      <email>Ailar.Ramadi@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

