<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03891927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>olive oil on glycemic control</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03891927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extra Virgin Olive Oil on Glycemic Control ,Insulin Resistance and Insulin Secretion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Extra Virgin Olive Oil on Glycemic Control ,Insulin Resistance and Insulin Secretion in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of this study to evaluate the effects of extra virgin olive oil on glycemic control
      ,insulin resistance and insulin secretion in patients with Type 2 diabetics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes is a major health problem and one of the leading causes of morbidity and mortality
      worldwide. Lifestyle and particularly dietary habits are considered key issues in both the
      prevention and management of the disease aimed at achieving an adequate glycemic control or
      at delaying the onset of diabetic chronic complications .

      Olive oil (OO) has been recognized for centuries for its nutritional properties and
      considered as the &quot;elixir of youth and health&quot; by antique Greeks. Extra virgin olive oil is
      the main source of dietary fat in the Mediterranean diet . Consumption of extra virgin olive
      oil might exert beneficial effects in the prevention, development and progression of T2D
      compared with refined olive oil .

      Several bioactive ingredients within OO have been repeatedly linked with anti-oxidant and
      anti-inflammatory preventative functions, particularly those from monounsaturated fatty acids
      (MUFA), and key biophenols such as oleuropein and hydroxytyrosol (HT) . Biophenols may
      influence glucose metabolism via several mechanisms; inhibition of carbohydrate digestion and
      glucose absorption in the intestine, activation of insulin receptors and glucose uptake in
      the tissues, antioxidative properties, potent free-radical scavenging and immunomodulatory
      effects. Multiple studies proven that EVOO improve metabolic control by affection of
      adipokines .The inhibition of carbohydrate digestion and absorption takes place through an
      inhibition of some digestive enzymes, especially the carbohydrate-hydrolyzing enzymes
      α-amylase and α glucosidase. Inhibition of these enzymes retards carbohydrate digestion, thus
      causing a reduction in glucose absorption rate .With their antioxidative properties,
      polyphenols diminish the production of advanced glycosylated end products such as HbA1c,
      AGEs, which are readily formed and accumulated with sustained hyperglycemia, contribute to
      the development of diabetic complications. As a consequence, inhibition of AGE formation
      constitutes an attractive therapeutic/preventive target .

      Studies both in healthy subjects and in persons with type 2 diabetes mellitus have
      demonstrated that levels of GLP-1are increased more by dietary MUFA than by dietary saturated
      fatty acids, and that the greater postprandial clearance of an oral overload of MUFA-rich
      fats is associated with a greater increase in postprandial incretins such as GLP-1 or gastric
      inhibitory polypeptide. MUFAs from olive oil, therefore, appear to significantly increase the
      insulin and GPL-1 secretion .
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized clinicl trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change of HBa1c (glycated hemoglobin) after intervention by extra virgin olive oil</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>change of HBa1c (glycated hemoglobin) after intervention by 30 ml extra virgin olive oil daily for three months and comparison that with other group (no intervention of olive oil) to evaluate glycemic control .
measurment of HBa1c for group of intervention at baseline and after 3 months intervention .
and other group (no intervention of olive oil) at baseline and after 3 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change of fasting glucose after intervention by extra virgin olive oil</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>change of fasting glucose after intervention by 30 ml extra virgin olive oil daily for three months and comparison that with other group (no intervention of olive oil) to evaluate glycemic control .
measurment of fasting glucose for group of intervention at baseline and after 3 months intervention .
and other group (no intervention of olive oil) at baseline and after 3 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>calculating of insulin resistance and insulin secretion after intervention by extra virgin olive oil</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months.</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of fasting insulin after intervention by 30 ml extra virgin olive oil daily for three months and comparison that with other group (no intervention of olive oil) to evaluate insulin resistance and insulin secretion by calculating HOMA -IR and HOMA-B The HOMA-beta cell function (HOMA-B) will be calculated by using the following formula: 360 x fasting insulin (μU/mL) / (fasting glucose (mg/dL) - 63).
(HOMA-IR) method: fasting glucose (mg/dl) x fasting insulin / 405</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>reduction of systolic and diastolic blood pressure after intervention by extra virgin olive oil .</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of systolic and diastolic blood pressure after intervention by 30 ml extra virgin olive oil daily for three months and comparison that with other group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>reduction of body mass index .</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>height , weight measuring and calculating BMI.Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as weight (kg) divided by squared height (m).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changing in waist circumference .</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>waist circumference change will be measured by tape measure at the umbilical level while patients standing after expiration by centimeter after intervention by 30 ml extra virgin olive oil daily for three months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change at Lipid profile (cholesterol, TG, LDL, HDL) after intervention .</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow up</time_frame>
    <description>change at Lipid profile (cholesterol, TG, LDL, HDL) (cholesterol by mg/dl ,triglyceride by mg/dl ,low density lipoprotein by mg/dl and high density lipoprotein by mg/dl ) after intervention by 30 ml extra virgin olive oil daily for three months and comparison that with other group (no intervention of olive oil)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>olive group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the experimental period (3 months ), participants will be requested to consume daily dose of 30 mL (3 tablespoons) of HP-EVOO ( high polypheol Extra virgin olive oil)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>non olive group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>extra virgin olive oil</intervention_name>
    <description>During the experimental period (3 months ), participants will be requested to consume daily dose of 30 mL (3 tablespoons) of HP-EVOO</description>
    <arm_group_label>olive group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Patients with type 2 diabetes with

          -  age 30-60 years regardless of their gender.

          -  Duration of diabetes less than 5 years.

          -  on oral antihyperglycemic medication.

          -  willing to participate in research.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes.

          -  Insulin treated type 2 DM patients.

          -  Pregnant women .

          -  Patients on cholesterol-lowering drugs, steroids and other drugs that affect the fat
             metabolism.

          -  Patients on regular (days) supplement that contain olive oil.

          -  Patients have aversion or allergy to olive oil.

          -  Smokers .

          -  Patients have gall bladder disease ,gastrointestinal disease
             (e.g.malabsorption),liver,kidney,heart and thyroid diseases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Salah Abdelazeem Argoon, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aml Ali Aboelghait, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01021191660</phone>
    <phone_ext>002</phone_ext>
    <email>amlaliaboelghait98@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>safaa AA Khaled, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01064170058</phone>
    <phone_ext>002</phone_ext>
    <email>safaakhaled2003@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwingshackl L, Lampousi AM, Portillo MP, Romaguera D, Hoffmann G, Boeing H. Olive oil in the prevention and management of type 2 diabetes mellitus: a systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies and intervention trials. Nutr Diabetes. 2017 Apr 10;7(4):e262. doi: 10.1038/nutd.2017.12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28394365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santangelo C, Filesi C, Varì R, Scazzocchio B, Filardi T, Fogliano V, D'Archivio M, Giovannini C, Lenzi A, Morano S, Masella R. Consumption of extra-virgin olive oil rich in phenolic compounds improves metabolic control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a possible involvement of reduced levels of circulating visfatin. J Endocrinol Invest. 2016 Nov;39(11):1295-1301. Epub 2016 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27344308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nigam P, Bhatt S, Misra A, Chadha DS, Vaidya M, Dasgupta J, Pasha QM. Effect of a 6-month intervention with cooking oils containing a high concentration of monounsaturated fatty acids (olive and canola oils) compared with control oil in male Asian Indians with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2014 Apr;16(4):255-61. doi: 10.1089/dia.2013.0178.</citation>
    <PMID>24625239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lama A, Pirozzi C, Mollica MP, Trinchese G, Di Guida F, Cavaliere G, Calignano A, Mattace Raso G, Berni Canani R, Meli R. Polyphenol-rich virgin olive oil reduces insulin resistance and liver inflammation and improves mitochondrial dysfunction in high-fat diet fed rats. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2017 Mar;61(3). doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201600418. Epub 2016 Dec 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27794174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aml Ali Aboelghait</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>olive oil</keyword>
  <keyword>glycemic control</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

