<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03899688</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CBCT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03899688</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tomographic Assessment on the Influence of the Use of a Collagen Membrane to Protect the Antrostomy After Maxillary Sinus Floor Augmentation.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cone Beam Computed Tomography Assessment on the Influence a Collagen Membrane Placed on the Antrostomy After Maxillary Sinus Floor Augmentation. A Randomized Clinical Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ARDEC Academy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ARDEC Academy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      the aim of the present study was to evaluate the dimensional variation and healing of the
      antrostomy left unprotected or protected with a collagen membrane
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Schneiderian mucosa will be elevated and the created space will be filled with a natural
      bovine bone grafting material (Cerabone® 1-2 mm, Botiss Biomaterials GmbH). In ten patients
      randomly selected (control sties), a native collagen membrane made of porcine dermis
      (Collprotect®, Botiss Biomaterials GmbH) will be placed on the antrostomy. In ten patients of
      the test group, the antrostomy will be left without the membrane. The flaps will be sutured
      and anti-inflammatory drugs and antibiotics will be administrated to the patients. The
      sutures will be removed after 7 days.

      CBCTs will be taken for all patients before surgery (T0), after 1 week from sinus floor
      augmentation (T1) and after 9 months of healing (T2) and evaluation of dimensional variations
      over time of soft and hard tissues will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 20, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 21, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>test and control group</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>the surgeon will be blinded until the maxillary sinus augmentation is filled with the biomaterial.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changing in height of the elevated zone.</measure>
    <time_frame>The CBCTs will be taken before surgery (T0) and 1-week (T1) and 9 months (T2) after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>will be assessed in the medial, middle and lateral regions of the elevated zone using the cone beam computerized tomographies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changing in area of the elevated zone</measure>
    <time_frame>The CBCTs will be taken before surgery (T0) and 1-week (T1) and 9 months (T2) after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The area will be delineated by the sinus bone walls and the sinus mucosa. The changes will be evaluated on the cone beam computerized tomographies (CBCTs) taken in various periods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Bone Loss</condition>
  <condition>Alveolar Bone Resorption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>test site</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The space obtained underneath the sinus mucosa will be filled with the xenograft without protecting the antrostomy with a collagen membrane in the test sites.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control site</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The space obtained underneath the sinus mucosa will be filled with the xenograft and a resorbable collagen membrane will be placed to cover the antrostomy only at the randomly selected control sites.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Maxillary sinus augmentation</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical technique for increasing the vertical bone height of the posterior maxilla an antrostomy of about 5 mm in height and 10 mm long will be prepared using a diamond insert mounted on a sonic-air surgical instrument. The Schneiderian membrane will be elevated and clinical measurements will be performed using an UNC 15 probe. The space obtained underneath the sinus mucosa will be filled with the xenograft and a resorbable collagen membrane will be placed to cover the antrostomy only at the randomly selected control sites.</description>
    <arm_group_label>control site</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>test site</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>maxillary sinus lift, maxillary sinus elevation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of an edentulous atrophic zone in the posterior segment of the maxilla

          -  Height of the sinus floor ≤4 mm.

          -  Desiring a prosthetic restoration of the zone using a fix prosthesis supported by
             implants

          -  ≥ 21 years of age

          -  Good general health

          -  No contraindication for oral surgical procedures

          -  Not being pregnant.

        Exclusion Criteria:The patients will be excluded if they present:

          -  A systemic disordered.

          -  Had a chemotherapic or radiotherapeutic treatment.

          -  Are smokers &gt;10 cigarettes per day

          -  Have an acute or a chronic sinusitis.

          -  Had a previous bone augmentation procedures in the zone of interest.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Gender identity</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colombia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cartagena de Indias</city>
        <state>Cartagena</state>
        <zip>5710</zip>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pjetursson BE, Tan WC, Zwahlen M, Lang NP. A systematic review of the success of sinus floor elevation and survival of implants inserted in combination with sinus floor elevation. J Clin Periodontol. 2008 Sep;35(8 Suppl):216-40. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2008.01272.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18724852</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barone A, Ricci M, Grassi RF, Nannmark U, Quaranta A, Covani U. A 6-month histological analysis on maxillary sinus augmentation with and without use of collagen membranes over the osteotomy window: randomized clinical trial. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2013 Jan;24(1):1-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0501.2011.02340.x. Epub 2011 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22151577</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Masuda K, Silva ER, Botticelli D, Apaza Alccayhuaman KA, Xavier SP. Antrostomy Preparation for Maxillary Sinus Floor Augmentation Using Drills or a Sonic Instrument: A Microcomputed Tomography and Histomorphometric Study in Rabbits. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2019 July/August;34(4):819–827. doi: 10.11607/jomi.7350. Epub 2019 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>30768660</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lundgren S, Andersson S, Gualini F, Sennerby L. Bone reformation with sinus membrane elevation: a new surgical technique for maxillary sinus floor augmentation. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2004;6(3):165-73.</citation>
    <PMID>15726851</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cricchio G, Sennerby L, Lundgren S. Sinus bone formation and implant survival after sinus membrane elevation and implant placement: a 1- to 6-year follow-up study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2011 Oct;22(10):1200-1212. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0501.2010.02096.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21906186</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moon YS, Sohn DS, Moon JW, Lee JH, Park IS, Lee JK. Comparative histomorphometric analysis of maxillary sinus augmentation with absorbable collagen membrane and osteoinductive replaceable bony window in rabbits. Implant Dent. 2014 Feb;23(1):29-36. doi: 10.1097/ID.0000000000000031.</citation>
    <PMID>24445918</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Omori Y, Ricardo Silva E, Botticelli D, Apaza Alccayhuaman KA, Lang NP, Xavier SP. Reposition of the bone plate over the antrostomy in maxillary sinus augmentation: A histomorphometric study in rabbits. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2018 Aug;29(8):821-834. doi: 10.1111/clr.13292. Epub 2018 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>29876969</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Corbella S, Taschieri S, Weinstein R, Del Fabbro M. Histomorphometric outcomes after lateral sinus floor elevation procedure: a systematic review of the literature and meta-analysis. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2016 Sep;27(9):1106-22. doi: 10.1111/clr.12702. Epub 2015 Oct 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26452326</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Caneva M, Lang NP, Garcia Rangel IJ, Ferreira S, Caneva M, De Santis E, Botticelli D. Sinus mucosa elevation using Bio-Oss(®) or Gingistat(®) collagen sponge: an experimental study in rabbits. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2017 Jul;28(7):e21-e30. doi: 10.1111/clr.12850. Epub 2016 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27080163</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>De Santis E, Lang NP, Ferreira S, Rangel Garcia I Jr, Caneva M, Botticelli D. Healing at implants installed concurrently to maxillary sinus floor elevation with Bio-Oss(®) or autologous bone grafts. A histo-morphometric study in rabbits. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2017 May;28(5):503-511. doi: 10.1111/clr.12825. Epub 2016 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26969193</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Riachi F, Naaman N, Tabarani C, Aboelsaad N, Aboushelib MN, Berberi A, Salameh Z. Influence of material properties on rate of resorption of two bone graft materials after sinus lift using radiographic assessment. Int J Dent. 2012;2012:737262. doi: 10.1155/2012/737262. Epub 2012 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22899930</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shanbhag S, Shanbhag V, Stavropoulos A. Volume changes of maxillary sinus augmentations over time: a systematic review. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2014 Jul-Aug;29(4):881-92. doi: 10.11607/jomi.3472. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25032768</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>antrostomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Maxillary sinus augmentation</keyword>
  <keyword>collagen membrane</keyword>
  <keyword>biomaterial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bone Resorption</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alveolar Bone Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 18, 2015</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/88/NCT03899688/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

