<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03897205</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-HMedIdeS-12</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-000022-66</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03897205</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Efficacy and Safety Study of Imlifidase in Treatment of Antibody-Mediated Rejection in Kidney Transplant Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-Label, Multi-Centre, Active Control, Efficacy and Safety Study of Imlifidase in Eliminating Donor Specific Anti-HLA Antibodies in the Treatment of Active Antibody-Mediated Rejection in Kidney Transplant Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hansa Biopharma AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hansa Biopharma AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate how efficiently the study medication imlifidase
      reduces the amount of donor specific antibodies (DSA) in comparison with plasma exchange (PE)
      therapy, in patients who have an active or chronic active antibody mediated rejection (AMR)
      after recently been kidney transplanted. The purpose is also to investigate and compare
      safety for these two treatments.

      20 patients will be treated with imlifidase and 10 with PE.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Antibodies to HLA antigens have a strong correlation with allograft injury and loss.
      Treatment with imlifidase, PE and immunoabsorption (IA) all aim to reduce antibody levels.

      This study will compare the reduction in DSA levels after treatment with imlifidase and PE in
      patients diagnosed with active or chronic active AMR (according to Banff 2017 criteria)
      having at least a 25% rise in serum creatinine compared with last measurement prior to the
      AMR (Patients with delayed graft function and AMR within 10 days after kidney transplantation
      can be included regardless of serum creatinine level).

      Included patients will be randomized to receive either 1 dose of imlifidase (0.25 mg/kg) or
      5-10 sessions of PEs (IA may replace PE at the discretion of the investigator). All patients
      will receive pulse methylprednisolone for 3 days, starting before the 1st treatment, followed
      by a tapering schedule with prednisolone/prednisone. The patients will also receive high dose
      IVIg 3 days after imlifidase treatment or directly after the last PE. In addition a single
      dose of rituximab will be given 5 days after completed IVIg infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum reduction in mean DSA level at any time point during the 5 days following the start of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until 5 days following start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum reduction (%) in the sum of DSAs at any time point during the 5 days following the start of treatment. Only DSAs with a pre-dose MFI ≥1000 will be included in the calculations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DSA levels up to 180 days after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>DSA levels will be assessed at all visits throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HLA-antibodies levels up to 180 days after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>HLA-antibodies levels will be assessed at all visits throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>P-creatinine levels up to 180 days after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>P-creatinine is a measure of kidney function. P-creatinine will be assessed at all visits throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>eGFR levels up to 180 days after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>eGFR as calculated from p-creatinine is a measure of kidney function. eGFR will be assessed at all visits throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Albumin/creatinine ratio in urine up to 180 days after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until 180 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The albumine/creatinine ratio in urine is a measure of kidney function. Urine sampling for analysis of albumine and creatinine will be done at all visits throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with graft loss within 180 days of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Information on graft loss will be collected throughout the study and proportion of subjects with graft loss will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with signs of transplant glomerulopathy 180 days after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>The biopsy collected 180 days after treatment will be analysed for signs of glomerulopathy and proportion of subjects with signs of transplant glomerulopathy will be reported</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in histopathology at day 29 and day 180 after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, 29 days and 180 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Kidney biopsies will be assessed according to the Banff (2017) criteria pre-dose (screening) and at day 29 and 180.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mRNA levels in kidney biopsies at day 29 and day 180 after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, Day 29 and Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Kidney biopsies will be taken at screening, day 29 and 180 and assessed for mRNA levels. Changes from baseline will be presented. If kidney biopsy is performed before screening, mRNA levels will be evaluated on day 29 and day 180 (no baseline will be available).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as evaluated by AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Type, frequency and intensity of treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) and post-treatment AEs. An AE is regarded as a TEAE if occurring up to Day 29 after start of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of sessions with PE</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>The number of PE sessions given throughout the study will be recorded in the CRF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with reduction of total serum IgG following treatment until administration of IVIg</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment (Day 1) up to administration of IVIg on Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction of total serum IgG is defined as YES if the subject's minimum IgG value at any timepoint following the start of treatment and prior administration of IVIg is less than 5% of the baseline level. Proportion of subjects with a reduction of total serum IgG until administration of IVIg will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with no intact IgG following treatment until administration of IVIg.</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment (Day 1) up to administration of IVIg on Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Intact IgG is analysed using SDS-PAGE/western blot. The endpoint is met if no detectable intact IgG is found at any time point following treatment until administration of IVIg.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DSA functionality determined by C1q or C3d analysis pre- and post-treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of DSA functionality assessed as mean MFI levels will be done at all visits throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of imlifidase: Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax = Maximum observed plasma concentration of imlifidase following dosing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of imlifidase: Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax = Time point for maximum observed plasma concentration of imlifidase following dosing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of imlifidase: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>t1/2 = terminal half-life of imlifidase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of imlifidase: AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>AUC = Area under the imlifidase plasma concentration vs time curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of imlifidase: CL</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>CL = Clearance of imlifidase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of imlifidase: V</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of treatment until Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>V = Volume of distribution</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with anti-drug antibodies (ADAs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening until Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Samples will be collected and analysed for presence anti-imlifidase IgE and anti-imlifidase IgG throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant Rejection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Imlifidase</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to imlifidase treatment will receive one intravenous dose of imlifidase, 0.25 mg/kg, administered over 15 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plasma Exchange</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to plasma exchange (PE) treatment will receive 5-10 sessions of PE, as judged by the investigator. Immunoadsorption (IA) may replace PE, at the discretion of the investigator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imlifidase</intervention_name>
    <description>Imlifidase is an IgG degrading enzyme of Streptococcus pyrogenes that cleaves all 4 human subclasses of IgG with strict specificity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Imlifidase</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HMED-IdeS, IdeS, IgG endopeptidase</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plasma Exchange</intervention_name>
    <description>The subject's plasma is removed and discarded and the subject receives replacement donor plasma, albumin, or a combination of albumin and saline. IA may be used instead of PE to the discretion of the investigator. IA is achieved by passing a subject's plasma over columns that bind immunoglobulins (Igs) and then the plasma is passed back to the subject.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Plasma Exchange</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed Informed Consent obtained before any study-related procedures

          2. Willingness and ability to comply with the protocol

          3. Male and/or female donor kidney recipients age ≥18 years at the time of screening

          4. Presence of DSA(s)

          5. Meet the Banff 2017 criteria for active or chronic active AMR

          6. At least 25% rise in serum creatinine compared to last individual value taken prior to
             the AMR. Patients with delayed graft function and AMR within 10 days after transplant
             (confirmed by kidney biopsy) can be included regardless of serum creatinine level

          7. Women of child-bearing potential willing or able to use at least one highly effective
             contraceptive method throughout the study. In the context of this study, an effective
             method is defined as those which result in low failure rate (i.e. less than 1% per
             year) when used consistently and correctly

          8. Men willing to use double-barrier contraception from the first day of treatment until
             at least 2 months after the dose of imlifidase, if not abstinent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous treatment with imlifidase

          2. Previous high dose IVIg treatment (2 g/kg) within 28 days prior to inclusion

          3. Lactating or pregnant females

          4. Significantly abnormal general serum screening lab results judged inappropriate for
             inclusion in the study by the investigator

          5. Intake of other investigational drugs within 5 half-lives (or similar) of the product
             prior to inclusion

          6. Clinically relevant active infection(s) as judged by the investigator

          7. Any condition that in the opinion of the investigator could increase the subject's
             risk by participating in the study such as severe immune deficiency and severe cardiac
             insufficiency [New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class IV] or severe uncontrolled
             heart disease

          8. Known allergy/sensitivity to imlifidase, IVIg and/or rituximab and the respective
             excipients

          9. Patient unable to tolerate treatment with plasmapheresis or immunoadsorption, as
             judged by the investigator

         10. Unsuitable to participate in the study for any other reason as judged by the
             investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elisabeth Sonesson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hansa Biopharma AB</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Central Contact</last_name>
    <phone>+46 46 16 56 70</phone>
    <email>clinicalstudyinfo@hansabiopharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University Grossman School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert A Montgomery, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-501-2418</phone>
      <email>robert.montgomery@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elaina Weldon</last_name>
      <phone>+1 646 3850902</phone>
      <email>elaina.weldon@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert A Montgomery, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Royal Melbourne Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Hughes</last_name>
      <phone>+61 393 427 053</phone>
      <email>Peter.Hughes@mh.org.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Hughes, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinik für Innere Medizin III, Klinische Abteilung für Nephrologie MUW</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Georg Böhmig, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 40400 43630</phone>
      <email>georg.boehmig@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Grenoble Alpes - Néphrologie, dialyse et transplantation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lionel Rostaing, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+33 4 76768945</phone>
      <email>lrostaing@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lionel Rostaing, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint-Louis. Service de Néphrologie et Transplantation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75475</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carmen Lefaucheur, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 6 76 60 49 46</phone>
      <email>carmen.lefaucheur@wanadoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carment Lefaucheur, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Necker - Service de Néphrologie - Transplantation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75743</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christophe Legendre, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+33 1 44 49 54 32</phone>
      <email>christophe.legendre@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christophe Legendre, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

