<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03898986</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>50200</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U19AI057229-15</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03898986</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Attenuated Versus Inactivated Flu Vaccine in Twin Sets</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLU-TW</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effects of Attenuated Versus Inactivated Flu Vaccine in Twin Sets</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is one project of a larger ongoing study related to the immune system's response to the
      flu virus. This study is designed to investigate the immune response to the live attenuated
      influenza vaccine (LAIV) vs. the Inactivated Influenza Vaccine (IIV) in identical and
      fraternal twins.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase IV study of licensed influenza vaccines. The study requires 10 monozygotic
      and 10 dizygotic sets of twins (40 total participants) to enroll.

      The duration of the study for an individual volunteer will be 4 weeks including screening and
      active participation. The study has a total of 3 visits.

      First visit: Procedures during this visit are: Informed consent process, enrollment, study
      assessments, 20 ml blood draw, and vaccination. Participants will be randomized to receive
      either LAIV or IIV.

      The time required to complete the first study visit will be about 30-40 minutes.

      2nd (day 7 post vaccination) and 3rd (day 28 post vaccination ) visit: 20 ml blood will be
      obtained and the visit will take approximately 15 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HAI titers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate HAI titers in response to influenza vaccination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MZ twins (IIV or LAIV4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Up to 20 healthy monozygotic (MZ) individual twin volunteers, 2-20 years old, will be randomized within the twin pair to receive either inactivated influenza vaccine quadrivalent (IIV4) Fluzone® Quadrivalent vaccine or live, attenuated influenza vaccine quadrivalent (LAIV4) FluMist® Quadrivalent. Each volunteer will complete a total of 3 visits: Day 0 (pre-immunization), Day 7 and Day 28 post-immunization. All visits will consist of drawing blood for study assays and monitoring for serious adverse events (SAEs).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DZ twins (IIV or LAIV4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Up to 20 healthy monozygotic (MZ) individual twin volunteers, 2-20 years old, will be randomized within the twin pair to receive either inactivated influenza vaccine quadrivalent (IIV4) Fluzone® Quadrivalent vaccine or live, attenuated influenza vaccine quadrivalent (LAIV4) FluMist® Quadrivalent. Each volunteer will complete a total of 3 visits: Day 0 (pre-immunization), Day 7 and Day 28 post-immunization. All visits will consist of drawing blood for study assays and monitoring for serious adverse events (SAEs).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Live attenuated influenza vaccine (LAIV4)</intervention_name>
    <description>LAIV4 vaccine dosage is 0.2 mL. The vaccine will be administered as an intranasal spray. Each sprayer contains a single dose of FluMist® Quadrivalent; approximately one-half of the contents should be administered into each nostril. 0.1 mL (i.e., half of the dose from a single FluMist sprayer) is administered into each nostril while the recipient is in an upright position. Insert the tip of the sprayer just inside the nose and rapidly depress the plunger until the dose-divider clip stops the plunger. The dose-divider clip is removed from the sprayer to administer the second half of the dose (0.1 mL) into the other nostril.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DZ twins (IIV or LAIV4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MZ twins (IIV or LAIV4)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FluMist® Quadrivalent</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inactivated Influenza Vaccine (IIV4)</intervention_name>
    <description>IIV4 vaccine will be administered as a 0.5 mL dose, with a sterile, disposable syringe and needle by IM injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DZ twins (IIV or LAIV4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MZ twins (IIV or LAIV4)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluzone® Quadrivalent vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 2-20 year old male and female patients

          2. Willing and able to complete the informed consent process

          3. Availability of twin pair also agreeable and eligible for study inclusion

          4. Availability for follow-up for the planned duration of the study

          5. Acceptable medical history by review of inclusion/exclusion criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior off-study vaccination with seasonal influenza vaccine within three months of
             study vaccination

          2. Life-threatening reactions to previous influenza vaccinations

          3. Asthma (contraindication for receipt of LAIV4)

          4. Allergy to egg or egg products or to vaccine components including gentamicin, gelatin,
             arginine or MSG.

          5. Active systemic or serious concurrent illness, including febrile illness on the day of
             vaccination

          6. History of immunodeficiency (including HIV infection)

          7. Known or suspected impairment of immunologic function; may include significant liver
             disease, diabetes mellitus treated with insulin or moderate to severe renal disease

          8. Hospitalization in the past year for congestive heart failure or emphysema.

          9. Chronic Hepatitis B or C.

         10. Recent or current use of immunosuppressive medication, including systemic
             glucocorticoids (corticosteroid nasal sprays and topical steroids are permissible).
             Use of oral steroids (&lt;20mg prednisone-equivalent/day) may be acceptable after review
             by the investigator.

         11. Participants in close contact with anyone who has a severely weakened immune system

         12. Malignancy, other than squamous cell or basal cell skin cancer (includes solid tumors
             such as breast cancer or prostate cancer with recurrence in the past year, and any
             hematologic cancer such as leukemia).

         13. Autoimmune disease (including rheumatoid arthritis treated with immunosuppressive
             medication such as Plaquenil, methotrexate, prednisone, Enbrel) which, in the opinion
             of the investigator might jeopardize volunteer safety or compliance with the protocol.

         14. History of blood dyscrasias, renal disease, or hemoglobinopathies requiring regular
             medical follow up or hospitalization during the preceding year

         15. Use of any anti-coagulation medication such as Coumadin or Lovenox, or anti-platelet
             agents such as aspirin (except up to 325 mg. per day), Plavix, or Aggrenox will be
             reviewed by investigators to determine if study participation would affect the
             volunteer's safety or compliance with the protocol.

         16. Has taken an influenza antiviral medication within 48 hours prior to study vaccination
             [If yes, may not eligible if unable to schedule at an appropriate interval].

         17. Receipt of blood or blood products within the past 6 months or planned used during the
             study.

         18. Medical or psychiatric condition or occupational responsibilities that preclude
             participant compliance with the protocol

         19. Receipt of an inactivated vaccine 14 days prior to study enrollment, or planned
             vaccinations prior to completion of last study visit (~ 14 days after study
             vaccination)

         20. Receipt of a live, attenuated vaccine within 60 days prior to enrollment of planned
             vaccination prior to completion of last study visit (~ 14 days after study enrollment)

         21. Need for allergy immunization (that cannot be postponed) until after the last study
             visit.

         22. History of Guillain-Barre# syndrome

         23. Pregnant woman

         24. Breastfeeding woman

         25. Use of investigational agents within 30 days prior to enrollment or planned use during
             the study.

         26. Donation of the equivalent of a unit of blood within 6 weeks prior to enrollment or
             donation of platelets within 2 weeks of enrollment or planned donation prior to
             completion of the last visit.

         27. Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, might interfere with
             volunteer safety, study objectives or the ability of the participant to understand or
             comply with the study protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philip Grant</last_name>
    <phone>6507239443</phone>
    <email>pmgrant@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philip Grant</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine (Infectious Diseases)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

