<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03897413</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0924M0618</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03897413</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Food and Calcium on Pharmacokinetics of a Single Dose of S-888711 in Healthy Adult Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Randomized, Three-period, Crossover Study to Assess the Effect of Food and Calcium on S-888711 0.25-mg Tablet Pharmacokinetics in Healthy, Adult Volunteer Subjects Following a Single 0.75-mg Oral Dose of S-888711</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shionogi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shionogi Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of this study were:

        -  To assess the effect of a high-fat diet on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of a 0.75 mg single
           dose of S-888711 orally administered as 0.25 mg tablets in healthy volunteer adults

        -  To assess the effect of a calcium supplement on the PK of a 0.75 mg single dose of
           S-888711 orally administered as 0.25 mg tablets in healthy volunteer adults
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 6, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 23, 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 23, 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration of S-888711</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, and 96 hours after dosing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration of S-888711</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, and 96 hours after dosing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-time Curve from Time Zero to the Time Point of the Last Quantifiable Concentration of S-888711</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, and 96 hours after dosing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-time Curve from Time Zero to Infinity of S-888711</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, and 96 hours after dosing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal Elimination Half-life of S-888711</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, and 96 hours after dosing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Total Clearance of S-888711</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36, 48, 72, and 96 hours after dosing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Treatment-emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 40 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fasted state in treatment period 1, a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fed state in period 2, and a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fasted state with 4000 mg of calcium carbonate in period 3. Each period consisted of 6 days, separated by a 5-day washout period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fed state in treatment period 1, a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fasted state with 4000 mg of calcium carbonate in period 2, and a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fasted state in period 3. Each period consisted of 6 days, separated by a 5-day washout period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fasted state with 4000 mg of calcium carbonate in treatment period 1, a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fasted state in period 2, and a single oral dose of 0.75 mg S-888711 in the fed state in period 3. Each period consisted of 6 days, separated by a 5-day washout period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S-888711</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered orally as three 0.25 mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calcium Antacid</intervention_name>
    <description>Calcium carbonate 4000 mg chewable tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. A signed and dated written informed consent obtained prior to Screening.

          2. Males and females ≥ 18 and ≤ 70 years of age, inclusive (at the time of informed
             consent).

          3. Judged healthy at screening examination by the investigator.

          4. Body mass index (BMI) of ≥ 19 to ≤ 29.9 kg/m².

          5. All subjects must have agreed to use 2 forms of barrier contraception if engaging in
             sexual intercourse for at least 7 days prior to the first dose of study drug and
             continuing throughout the study, excluding subjects who had been surgically sterilized
             or females who had been postmenopausal (confirmed by follicle stimulating hormone test
             levels) for at least 1 year.

          6. All female subjects must have had a negative urine pregnancy test.

          7. Platelet count of 100,000 to 325,000/μL.

          8. Willing to submit to blood sampling for the planned PK analysis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including herbal medicine or
             dietary supplements, within 14 days prior to dosing, with the exception of up to 3
             doses of acetaminophen ≤ 1 gram each permitted from 14 days prior to the first study
             drug dose through 72 hours prior to the first study drug dose.

          2. A history of regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products within 6 months
             prior to Screening as confirmed by a urine cotinine test.

          3. A history of use of inhibitors or inducers of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4 within 14 days
             prior to Screening.

          4. A history of use of platelet aggregation inhibitors, coronary artery vasodilators,
             calcium antagonists, beta blockers, diuretics, psychotropic drugs, prostaglandins,
             antibiotics, anticoagulants, and anticlotting or antiplatelet drugs (including aspirin
             and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs) within 4 weeks prior to Screening.

          5. History of use of thrombocytopenia-inducing drugs (eg, quinidine, trimethoprim
             sulfamethoxazole, etc.) within 4 weeks prior to Screening.

          6. Family history of a hematologic disorder.

          7. Hemorrhagic tendency.

          8. A history of cardiac episode(s) or abnormal finding on electrocardiogram (ECG) and
             judged as ineligible by the investigator.

          9. Chronic disease requiring medication and/or other treatment such as dietary
             restriction and physical therapy.

         10. A history of anaphylaxis or significant side effect induced by a drug.

         11. A history of allergic symptoms including food allergy, but excluding inactive pollen
             allergy.

         12. A history of abuse of alcohol and/or drugs.

         13. Positive urine screen for drug abuse.

         14. A history of gastrointestinal surgery making subject ineligible as judged by the
             investigator.

         15. Judged ineligible for this study by the investigator due to a history or clinical
             manifestations of significant metabolic, hepatic, renal, hematological, pulmonary,
             cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, or urological disease or other clinically important
             disorder.

         16. Positive laboratory results for hepatitis A IgM antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen,
             hepatitis C antibody, or human immunodeficiency virus at Screening.

         17. Donation of &gt;400 mL of blood within 12 weeks or &gt;200 mL of blood within 4 weeks prior
             to Screening.

         18. Prior administration of S-888711.

         19. Use of other investigational products within 30 days or 6 half-lives (whichever was
             longer) prior to the first dose of study medication.

         20. Judged ineligible for this study by the investigator for any other reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shionogi Clinical Trials Administrator Clinical Support Help Line</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shionogi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Healthcare Discoveries, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antacids</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium Carbonate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

