<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03890640</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-0320</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03890640</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound-assisted Thoracic Epidural Catheter Insertion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Accuracy of Real-time Ultrasound-assisted Thoracic Epidural Catheter Insertion: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asan Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the present study is to access the success rate of ultrasound-guided thoracic
      epidural catheter insertion, using fluoroscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thoracic epidural anesthesia has been associated with reduced acute postoperative pain for a
      wide variety of surgical procedures. It has also been associated with reductions in
      perioperative cardiac stress, chronic post-thoracotomy pain, and improvements in
      postoperative pulmonary function. Although a variety of methods can be used to confirm the
      position of the epidural needle in the epidural space, a blind technique and fluoroscopic
      guided approach are a widely used method. A thoracic epidural block is a relatively more
      difficult procedure than procedures used in other regions, because the spinous process of the
      thoracic vertebra is longer than that of the lumbar vertebra, and the area through which the
      needle can approach the epidural space is relatively smaller due to an acute angle and larger
      distance between the skin and the epidural space. Therefore, the success rate of thoracic
      epidural intervention is only about 68% under a blind technique due to inadequate position of
      the needle tip, misplacement, occlusion, and migration of the catheter.

      Although fluoroscopic guided thoracic epidural intervention is the safest and most accurate
      method to identify the correct anatomical structures and confirm the epidural space with
      contrast medium, its use is limited because of the difficulty of using fluoroscope and the
      burden of radiation exposure. As the use of ultrasound has become popularized and universal,
      it has been widely used in regional anesthesia and analgesia, has continuously replaced the
      modality such as a blind technique and fluoroscopic guidance. Ultrasound-guided thoracic
      epidural catheter insertion was also recently investigated, and then it was conducted
      successfully in 15 cases of thoracic and upper abdominal surgery. Moreover, it showed several
      advantages including lowering the number of needle passes and increasing the success rate.
      However, it has not yet been studied how accurately the catheter is located in the thoracic
      epidural space during thoracic epidural catheter insertion using real-time ultrasound.
      Although it is possible to speculate the success of the thoracic epidural catheterization
      clinically, the identification of the location of the catheter is only possible under
      fluoroscopic guidance. Therefore, in the present study, we aimed to confirm the success rate
      of ultrasound-guided thoracic epidural catheter insertion, using fluoroscopy with contrast
      medium.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 12, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Success rate of ultrasound-guided thoracic epidural catheter insertion</measure>
    <time_frame>on the day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmation success of ultrasound-guided thoracic epidural catheter insertion using fluoroscopic images; success means that the catheter tip is located in the epidural space.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of skin punctures</measure>
    <time_frame>on the day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>complete needle withdrawal from the skin and reinsertion at a new location</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of needle passes</measure>
    <time_frame>on the day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>First needle pass + additional needle passes (the needle returned to a plane perpendicular to the skin before reinsertion. Needle tip maneuvers toward the midline and cephalad were considered standard needle walking technique and were counted as a single pass)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>First attempt success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>on the day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>only first needle pass and first skin puncture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Abdominal Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Thoracic Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrasound-guided TECI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After assessment of the epidural space using the loss of resistance technique with saline under ultrasound guidance, fluoroscopic views will be obtained to confirm which the catheter tip is located in the epidural space or not.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasound-guided TECI</intervention_name>
    <description>When performing an ultrasound-guided thoracic epidural catheter insertion (TECI), an 18-gauge Tuohy needle will be used for interlaminar epidural access. All procedures will be performed with a paramedian approach under ultrasound-guidance and using the loss of resistance technique with saline. If the needle is deemed to be in the epidural space when the loss of resistance occurred, fluoroscopic views will be obtained to confirm which the catheter tip is located in the epidural space or not.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrasound-guided TECI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who will undergo upper abdomen or thoracic surgery

          -  Scheduled for thoracic epidural catheter insertion

          -  20 ≤ age &lt;80

          -  When obtaining informed consent voluntarily

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to local anesthetics and contrast dye, and steroid

          -  Use of anticoagulants or antiplatelet medication, coagulopathy

          -  Infection at the insertion site

          -  Neurological or psychiatric disorders

          -  Prior spine instrumentation

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jong-Hyuk Lee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Asan Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan medical center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>05505</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asan Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jong Hyuk Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Thoracic epidural catheter insertion</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluoroscopy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thoracic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abdominal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

