<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04278430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MU-1441-78</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04278430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation for Attention Deficit</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation Affect Selective Visual Attention in Children With Left-sided Infantile Hemiplegia? A Preliminary Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Majmaah University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Majmaah University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Infantile hemiplegia due to brain injury is associated with poor attention. Left-sided
      infantile hemiplegia affects the learning and acquisition of new skills. This study is aiming
      to improve the Selective visual attention (SVA) through transcranial direct current
      stimulation (tDCS) in children with Left-sided infantile hemiplegia .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infantile hemiplegia (IH) refers to brain injuries that occur before or at birth and lead to
      hemiplegia/ total paralysis of one side of the body, including the face, arm and leg. The IH
      is quit rare condition and occurs in 1 in 1000 live births. however, the condition is
      reported to cause functional and cognitive disability. Children with IH suffer from poor
      attention particularly visual attention, that is essential to be understand the written
      language. A focused reading is essential in learning and children with IH possess moderate
      intelligence and attend school.

      Transcranial direct current stimulation(tTCS) is a novel intervention that use small
      amplitude electrical currents to stimulate the essential areas of the brain through surface
      electrodes placed on the corresponding areas of the brain.

      The eligible children were divided into two groups. one group received tDCS with visual
      attention activities and the second group received sham tDCS with similar activities. The
      effect will be assessed before and after with Strops-color testing and a academic reading
      test.

      The experiment intends to explore the affect of tTCS on visual attention span among children
      with Left-sided infantile hemiplegia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 14, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The care provider were masked and the pre-post testing was performed by different therapist unaware of the assignment of children.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Computerized Stroop Color-Word Test</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Computerized Stroop Color-Word Test consists of two phases.The first phase is the preparation phase, where the children are asked to identify the color of a circle on the monitor (red, blue, green, or yellow) and press the corresponding key on the keyboard using the unaffected side. Scores obtained at this stage were not included in the final results. The second phase is the actual test, which consists of 96 colorful words, divided into 48 correctly matched colorful words and 48 incorrectly matched colorful words. The words that appeared on the computer screen were presented in a randomized sequence. Each word appeared on the computer screen for 2000 ms with an 800-ms interval. The children were asked to identify the color of the words regardless of their meanings.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>academic practical test</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An academic practical test will be needed to evaluate the improvement in SVA among children. Therefore, a reading comprehension test will be added to the outcome variables. All the three groups performed a reading comprehension test at the baseline, during the 5th and 10th sessions, and during the follow-up period. Two different stories (unread before and equal difficulty) will be selected from their English course and presented to them at the start and following the completion of the 10th session. These stories comprised of between 700 and 1000 words and the time allowed to complete the story was 20 minutes. In the end, the children were asked to answer 10 multiple-choice questions (MCQ) related to the story. Each correct answer will be assigned 1 point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Infantile Hemiplegia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Real tDCS group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The tDCS applied over dorsolateral prefrontal cortex for 20 minutes with 1.5 mA intensity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The tDCS applied over dorsolateral prefrontal cortex for 20 minutes with 0 mA intensity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The normal heathy children age matched undergo the same activity and brain stimulation as the real tDCS group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>transcranial direct current stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The tDCS stimulator (ActivaDose II tDCS Device; IOMED Inc., Salt Lake City, USA) is a standardized instrument used and tested in children. Two tDCS electrodes of dimensions 3&quot; x 3&quot; were used for the brain stimulation. The electrodes were inserted into a wet saline sponge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Real tDCS group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham tDCS</intervention_name>
    <description>Five children with LSIH were randomly allocated to this group. All participants received sham tDCS for 3 weeks on alternate days and completed 10 treatment sessions. The sham tDCS followed preparatory procedures similar to that used for the experimental group, except that the device was disconnected after the initial increase of the current. Children usually started the activity without noticing that the device was disconnected. The children were assessed at baseline, during the 5th and 10th sessions, and during a follow-up that was scheduled for 4 months later.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 8-15 years

          -  Left-sided infantile hemiplegia

          -  lesion to non-dominant hemisphere

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of epilepsy

          -  second stroke

          -  color blind

          -  under medication for psychiatric illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Majmaah University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>faizan kashoo, PT</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prinicipal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemiplegia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Data sharing depends on the permission from the parents of the children and research team.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

