<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04279418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HanYingsc2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04279418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-pharmacological Intervention for Preclinical Alzheimer's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Mixed Functional Foods Supplementation on Cognition and Neuroimaging Biomarkers in Adults With Subject Cognitive Decline</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>XuanwuH 2</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the most common form of neurodegenerative disorders leading to
      dementia. Currently, there has been no effective drugs targeting this disease. Functional
      food is considered as a potentially non-pharmacologic treatment. In this project, the
      investigators aim to investigate the effectiveness of a mixed functional food with main
      compositions of ginsenoside, green tea polyphenols and marine collagen peptide on cognition
      for individuals with subjective cognitive decline (SCD). Taking the randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled method, participants in the functional food group will take mixed
      functional foods for three months and those in the placebo group will take placebo. After
      that, the investigators will investigate the changes of cognitive function. Furthermore,
      based on the neuroimaging technique, the regulatory mechanism of functional food in
      intervening SCD will be revealed from the perspective of altered brain functional activity.
      In conclusion, these results are beneficial for understanding the therapeutic effect of mixed
      functional foods as a non-drug treatment for early AD and further elucidating the potential
      brain mechanism, which are of great values in solving scientific and clinical practice
      issues.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently, there has been no effective therapy for Alzheimer's disease (AD). Functional food
      is now considered as a potentially non-pharmacologic intervention and supplementation of
      functional food may positively affect cognitive function for patients with AD. However, there
      are few existing studies involving the role of mixed functional foods with multiple
      compositions on cognition and neuroimaging biomarkers for subjective cognitive decline (SCD).

      Sixty participants with SCD will be recruited in this three-month, randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled trial. Each group had thirty participants. Participants in the functional
      food group will take mixed functional foods for three months and those in the placebo group
      will take placebo. After that, the investigators will investigate the changes of memory
      measures, which is the primary outcome. Furthermore, based on the neuroimaging technique of
      functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS), the regulatory mechanism of mixed functional
      foods in intervening SCD will be revealed from the perspective of altered brain functional
      activity.

      In conclusion, these results are beneficial for understanding the therapeutic effect of mixed
      functional foods as a non-drug therapy for preclinical AD and further elucidating the
      potential brain mechanism, which are of great values in solving scientific and clinical
      practice issues.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
    <description>After intervention for three months, the investigators will compare memory changes based on Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT) scale in two groups, in order to investigate the therapeutic effectiveness of mixed functional foods supplementation. The scale of AVLT focuses on the memory domain, especially AVLT-long delayed memory, with cut-off points as 5 (50-59 years old), 4 (60-69 years old), 3 (70-79 years old) and AVLT-recognition, with cut-off points as 20 (50-59 years old), 19 (60-69 years old), 18 (70-79 years old). Higher scores mean a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FNIRS-based brain functional activity changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
    <description>At baseline and post-intervention visits, the brain functional activity data will be collected using functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) technique. The investigators will compare the changes of brain functional activity based on the measure of oxyhemoglobin concentration signal with relatively high signal to noise ratio (SNR) in two groups, in order to reveal the regulatory mechanism of mixed functional foods in intervening SCD persons.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Functional Food</condition>
  <condition>Subjective Cognitive Decline</condition>
  <condition>Intervention</condition>
  <condition>Neuroimaging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mixed functional foods group with SCD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Thirty participants in this group will take mixed functional foods for three months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group with SCD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Thirty participants in this group will take placebo for three months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mixed functional foods supplementation</intervention_name>
    <description>In this project, taking the method of random, double blindness and control, participants in the mixed functional foods group will take functional foods with main compositions of ginsenoside, green tea polyphenols and marine collagen peptide for three months. After that, neuropsychological tests and neuroimaging biomarkers will be compared between functional food group and placebo group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mixed functional foods group with SCD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>In this project, taking the method of random, double blindness and control, participants in the placebo group will take placebo for three months. After that, cognitive changes and neuroimaging biomarkers will be compared between functional food group and placebo group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group with SCD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  50-79 years old, right-handed and Mandarin-speaking subjects;

          -  self-experienced persistent decline in cognitive capacity in comparison with a
             previously normal status and unrelated to an acute event;

          -  normal age-adjusted, gender-adjusted and education-adjusted performance on
             standardised cognitive tests;

          -  concerns (worries) associated with memory complaint;

          -  failure to meet the criteria for MCI or dementia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  a history of stroke;

          -  major depression (Hamilton Depression Rating Scale score &gt; 24 points);

          -  other central nervous system diseases that may cause cognitive impairment, such as
             Parkinson's disease, tumors, encephalitis and epilepsy;

          -  cognitive impairment caused by traumatic brain injury;

          -  systemic diseases, such as thyroid dysfunction, syphilis and HIV;

          -  a history of psychosis or congenital mental growth retardation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ying Han, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xuanwu Hospital of Capital Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neurolgy, Xuanwu Hospital of Capital Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100053</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>XuanwuH 2</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Subjective cognitive decline</keyword>
  <keyword>Mixed functional foods</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-pharmacologic intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The information of neuropsychological tests, neuroimaging data are to be shared with other researchers.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>When summary data are published or starting 6 months after publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The information of neuropsychological tests, neuroimaging data will be shared.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

