<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04279548</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PSI-DBS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04279548</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Posterior-superior Insula Deep Brain Stimulation in Refractory Peripheral Neuropathic Pain Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PSI-DBS</acronym>
  <official_title>Posterior-superior Insula Deep Brain Stimulation in Refractory Peripheral Neuropathic Pain Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the long term pain relief after deep brain stimulation on
      posterior-superior insula (PSI) in patients with refractory peripheral neuropathic pain who
      responded to real but not to sham non-invasive stimulation by deep repetitive transcranial
      magnetic stimulation - PSI-drTMS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study has two phases:

      Study I) This study is an extension of 690.455/NCT01932905, in which non invasive stimulation
      of the posterior-superior insula (PSI) was performed by deep repetitive transcranial magnetic
      stimulation (drTMS) in patients with central neuropathic pain. Patients responding to active
      stimulation would be invited to join a phase II study aiming at the long term effects of
      drTMS by deep brain stimulation (DBS) of the PSI. The original 690.455/NCT01932905 study was
      negative concerning pain intensity reduction compared to sham stimulation, its main outcome.
      However, in this same study, active but not sham PSI stimulation provided significant
      anti-nociceptive effects, with anti-allodynic and anti-hyperalgesic properties.

      This, and a number of experimental studies on peripheral neuropathic pain relief after PSI
      stimulation has lead us to perform an extension of the initial study, now including patients
      with refractory peripheral neuropathic pain to receive an induction series (5 consecutive
      daily stimulation sessions) of navigated PSI-deep rTMS against sham stimulation in a
      cross-over design. The calculate sample size for this cross-over screening study is 32. The
      primary endpoint is number of patients reaching significant pain relief (&gt;50% pain intensity
      reduction assessed by visual analogue scale (VAS) ranging from 0: no pain, to 100mm:maximal
      pain imaginable) one week after the 5th stimulation session compared to baseline assessment.
      Other pain, quality of life and mood data were collected : pain interference with daily
      living (brief pain inventory), medication quantification score, neuropathic pain symptom
      inventory (NPSI).

      In this screening trial, actual responders: patients refractory peripheral neuropathic pain
      with &gt;50% pain intensity reduction after real but not sham PSI-drTMS will be offered the
      opportunity to join a subsequent PSI-DBS phase II trial.

      Study II) In this phase, the PSI-DBS phase II trial (ethics review board number #690.455)
      will enroll 10 patients with refractory peripheral neuropathic pain from study 1 who
      responded to real but not to sham PSI-drTMS. Patients will have a stimulation electrode
      inserted neurosurgically by neuronavigation to the PSI, on the target used for drTMS, on the
      insula contralateral to the pain side.

      After surgery, patients will be randomized to be in in either the ON or OFF DBS mode for
      three months, and then, after a flexible washout period, participants will be switched to the
      other corresponding mode (OFF or ON) for more three months. The study main outcome is number
      of responders (number of patients achieving &gt;30% pain intensity reduction). Pain intensity
      will be measured on a 11-point visual numerical scale anchored at 0 (no pain) and 10 (maximal
      pain imaginable) and the score at the end of the three-month ON/OFF conditions will be
      compared to the respective baseline values in order too classify patients as responders or
      non-responders in each of the ON/OFF conditions. The main secondary outcome is safety, along
      with other clinical and general patients characteristics such as quality of life( QoL), mood,
      pain characteristics (McGill Pain Questionnaire-MPQ) and neuropathic pain symptom clusters
      (Neuropathic Pain Symptom Inventory).

      After the ON/OFF double blinded period (main outcome) patients will be maintained for 3
      months in the ON mode in a single blinded design, and then for more 6 months, maintained in
      the open phase of the study. This followup phase will allow us to gain insights into the
      potential long term effects of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response (&gt;30% pain intensity reduction) after ON but not OFF stimulation periods.</measure>
    <time_frame>after 3 months in the ON / OFF conditions</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity measured on a Numeric Rating Scale (0-10) where 0 is no pain and 10 is the worst pain imaginable</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>% of patients with anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 15 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the anxiety and depression by Hospital Anxiety And Depression Scale. The possible scores ranged from 0 to 21 for anxiety and depression. 0 to 7 could be regarded as being in the normal range, a score of 11 or higher indicating probable presence of the mood disorder and a score of 8 to 10 being just suggestive of the presence of the respective state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of symptoms of neuropathic pain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 15 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of neuropathic pain evaluated by Neuropathic Pain Symptom Inventory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events as assessed by self reported</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 15 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of adverse events by self-report</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life related to pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 15 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life evaluated by WHOQOL-BREF</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuropathic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Neuropathy;Peripheral</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>On DBS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the on mode DBS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Off DBS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the off mode DBS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deep Brain Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will have a stimulation electrode inserted neurosurgically by neuronavigation to the PSI, on the target used for drTMS, on the insula contralateral to the pain side. After surgery will be randomized to be in in either the ON or OFF DBS</description>
    <arm_group_label>Off DBS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>On DBS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and non-pregnant women aged 21-70 years.

          -  Ability to give informed consent in accordance with institutional policy.

          -  Have a diagnosis of neuropathic pain according to Douleur neuropathique 4 questions
             (DN4).

          -  Patients with predominant pain on the face and upper extremities in relation to the
             lower limbs. In this study, predominance will be defined as the difference of ≥ 30% or
             ≥ 2 points on the VAS scale between upper limb / face pain and lower limb pain.

          -  Pain lasting more than 12 months.

          -  Documented resistance to clinical treatment, defined in this study as persistence of
             pain after a minimum of 2 appropriate pharmacological treatments, including at least
             one antidepressant / anticonvulsant and / or gabapentins. Adequacy of treatments will
             be defined by the use of drugs in doses considered adequate in the literature or below
             the threshold of side effects.

          -  Visual analog scale (EVA) scores of at least four during initial assessments.

          -  No change in the analgesic medication regimen for chronic neuropathic pain during the
             4 weeks preceding entry into the study.

          -  Ability to comply with the tests and follow-up defined by the study protocol;

          -  Absence of routine contraindications to the surgical procedure (eg Coagulopathies,
             blood dyscrasias). These will be evaluated by members of the neurosurgical team
             responsible for the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Alcohol abuse, medication, or addiction to illicit substances in the last 12 months.

          -  Diagnosis of idiopathic trigeminal neuralgia or atypical facial pain.

          -  Advanced cardiovascular disease stage that makes anesthesia and surgery unsafe, as
             determined by the neurosurgeon / clinical team.

          -  Clinically relevant lesions (tumor, for example) on preoperative magnetic resonance
             imaging.

          -  Cardiac pacemaker / implanted defibrillator or other active stimulators.

          -  Medical condition that requires repeated resonances.

          -  Patients using chemotherapy for the treatment of malignant tumors or who need chronic
             oral or intravenous treatment with immunosuppressants or steroids.

          -  Patients unable to comply with the study visit schedule.

          -  Brain ablative surgery or previous neurosurgery that prevents or increases the risk of
             implantation of the electrodes.

          -  Patients of childbearing potential or infants with a positive pregnancy test or
             without the use of adequate contraception.

          -  Other medical conditions that require probable hospitalization during the study.

          -  History of epilepsy or status epilepticus.

          -  Chronic infection.

          -  Diagnosis of fibromyalgia.

          -  Plans for using diathermy in the future.

          -  Have any intracranial metal implant

          -  Current participation in another device investigation study or experimentation with
             drugs or surgery of any kind.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Ciampi de Andrade, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+55 11 26 61 71 52</phone>
    <email>ciampi@usp.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Liu Dongyang</last_name>
    <phone>55 11 993220286</phone>
    <email>liu.dy2015@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de São Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <zip>05403-900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Ciampi de Andrade, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>55 11 997753538</phone>
      <email>ciampi@usp.br</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Ciampi Araujo de Andrade, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep Brain Stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Participant data for primary and secondary outcome measures will be made available only when requested according with local ethics review recommendations</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available within 6 months of study completion</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

