<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04271306</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VAC082</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04271306</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Immunogenicity and ex Vivo Efficacy of Pfs25-IMX313/Matrix-M in Healthy Volunteers in Bagamoyo, Tanzania.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase Ib Age De-escalation and Dose Escalation Open Label Clinical Trial of the Safety, Immunogenicity and ex Vivo Efficacy of a Candidate Malaria Vaccine Pfs25-IMX313/Matrix-M Administered Intramuscularly in Healthy Adults and Young Children in Tanzania.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ifakara Health Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A phase Ib age de-escalation and dose escalation open label clinical trial of the safety,
      immunogenicity and ex-vivo efficacy of a candidate malaria vaccine Pfs25-IMX313/Matrix-M
      administered intramuscularly in healthy adults and young children in Tanzania
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to evaluate safety, immunogenicity, and transmission blocking activity of
      Pfs25IMX313-Matrix-M in healthy Tanzanian adults and children naturally exposed to malaria in
      Bagamoyo district, Tanzania. The study will enrol 45 volunteers comprising of 13 adults
      (18-45 years) and 32 children (5-12 years).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety of Pfs25IMX313-Matrix-M in healthy Tanzanian adults and children naturally exposed to malaria.</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of solicited symptoms in the first 7 days post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of solicited symptoms after each vaccination during a 7-day surveillance period (day of vaccination and days 1, 2, 3 and 7 after vaccination).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety of Pfs25IMX313-Matrix-M in healthy Tanzanian adults and children naturally exposed to malaria.</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of unsolicited symptoms in the first 30 days post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of unsolicited symptoms after each vaccination during a 30-day surveillance period (day of vaccination and 30 subsequent days).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety of Pfs25IMX313-Matrix-M in healthy Tanzanian adults and children naturally exposed to malaria.</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of SAEs until the end of the study (approx 2 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of serious adverse events throughout the study period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the Pfs25 specific antibody responses following immunization with different vaccination regimens in healthy Tanzanian adults and children.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study (approx 2 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Pfs25 antibody levels elicited by Pfs25IMX313-Matrix-M as measured by ELISA at each time point where serology samples are analysed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the transmission blocking activity of Pfs25 specific antibodies elicited by the different vaccination regimens in healthy Tanzanian adults and children using Standard Membrane Feeding Assay (SMFA) and Direct Membrane feeding assay (DMFA).</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study (approx 2 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Transmission blocking activity (TBA) of induced antibody as measured in standard membrane feeding assays (SMFA) and Direct Membrane feeding assays (DMFA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the transmission blocking activity of Pfs25 specific antibodies elicited by the different vaccination regimens in healthy Tanzanian adults and children using Standard Membrane Feeding Assay (SMFA) and Direct Membrane feeding assay (DMFA).</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study (approx 2 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of TBA with antibody levels at each time point where the membrane feeding assays are conducted.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Select the best vaccination regimen based on the peak Pfs25 specific antibodies after final immunization, their duration and transmission blocking activity by standard membrane feeding assay (SMFA) and direct membrane feeding assay (DMFA).</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study (approx 2 years)</time_frame>
    <description>The vaccination schedule that lead to the highest peak and duration of anti-Pfs25 antibody response post vaccination, and the highest transmission blocking activity (TBA) as measured by standard membrane feeding assay (SMFA) and direct membrane feeding assay (DMFA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria,Falciparum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers (aged 18-45 years) will receive 3 doses of Pfs25-IMX313(10µg)/Matrix-M (50µg) intramuscularly at months 0, 1 and 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers (aged 18-45 years) will receive 3 doses of Pfs25-IMX313(50µg)/Matrix-M (50µg) intramuscularlyat months 0, 1 and 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers (aged 5 - 12 years) will receive 3 doses of Pfs25-IMX313(10µg)/Matrix-M (25µg) intramuscularly at months 0, 1 and 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers (aged 5 - 12 years) will receive 3 doses of Pfs25-IMX313(10µg)/Matrix-M (25µg) intramuscularly at months 0, 1 and 6.5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers (aged 5 - 12 years) will receive 3 doses of Pfs25-IMX313(50µg)/Matrix-M (25µg) intramuscularly at months 0, 1 and 6.5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers (aged 5 - 12 years) will receive 2 doses of Pfs25-IMX313(50µg)/Matrix-M (25µg) intramuscularly at months 0 and 1 and a dose of Pfs25-IMX313(10µg)/Matrix-M (25µg) intracmuscularly at month 6.5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pfs25-IMX313/Matrix-M</intervention_name>
    <description>3 doses of Pfs25-IMX313/Matrix-M at different concentrations: Pfs25-IMX313(10µg)/Matrix-M (50µg) Pfs25-IMX313(50µg)/ Matrix-M (50µg) Pfs25-IMX313(10µg)/ Matrix-M (25µg) Pfs25-IMX313(50µg)/ Matrix-M (25µg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2D</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy adult aged 18 to 45 years or children aged 5-12 years.

          2. Planned long-term (at least 30 months from the date of recruitment) or permanent
             residence in Bagamoyo town.

          3. Adults with a Body Mass Index (BMI) 18 to 30 Kg/m2; or children (5-12 years) with the
             BMI between 13 and 25 Kg/m2.

          4. Able and willing (in the Investigator's opinion) to comply with all study
             requirements.

          5. Agreement to refrain from blood donation for the duration of the study

          6. Written informed consent to participate in the trial.

          7. Women only: Must practice continuous effective contraception* for the duration of the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Use of immunoglobulins or blood products (e.g., blood transfusion) at any time in the
             past.

          2. Receipt of any vaccine in the 14 days preceding enrolment, or planned receipt of any
             other vaccine within 14 days following each vaccination.

          3. Receipt of an investigational product in the 30 days preceding enrolment, or planned
             receipt during the study period.

          4. Concurrent involvement in another clinical trial or planned involvement during the
             study period

          5. Prior receipt of an investigational vaccine likely to impact on interpretation of the
             trial data, as assessed by the Investigator

          6. Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient state, including HIV
             infection; asplenia; recurrent, severe infections and chronic (more than 14 days)
             immunosuppressant medication within the past 6 months (inhaled and topical steroids
             are allowed).

          7. History of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by any component of
             the vaccine (e.g. egg products)

          8. Any history of anaphylaxis in reaction to vaccinations

          9. Pregnancy, lactation or intention to become pregnant during the study.

         10. History of cancer (except basal cell carcinoma of the skin and cervical carcinoma in
             situ).

         11. History of serious psychiatric condition that may affect participation in the study.

         12. Any other serious chronic illness requiring hospital specialist supervision.

         13. Suspected or known injecting drug abuse in the 5 years preceding enrolment.

         14. Seropositive for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or hepatitis C (HCV IgG).

         15. Volunteers unable to be closely followed for social, geographic or psychological
             reasons.

         16. Any clinically significant abnormal finding on biochemistry or haematology blood
             tests, urinalysis or clinical examination. In the event of clinically significant
             abnormal test results, confirmatory repeat tests will be requested. Procedures for
             identifying laboratory values meeting exclusion criteria will be described in a study
             specific SOP.

         17. Any other significant disease, disorder, or finding which may significantly increase
             the risk to the volunteer because of participation in the study, affect the ability of
             the volunteer to participate in the study or impair interpretation of the study data.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela Minassian</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Angela Minassian</last_name>
    <phone>+44865611425</phone>
    <email>angela.minassian@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ally Olotu</last_name>
    <phone>+255718927104</phone>
    <email>aolotu@ihi.or.tz</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ifakara Health Institute Clinical Trial Facility</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bagamoyo</city>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

