<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04278690</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-01294</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04278690</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Supporting Safe Use of Medications by Parents After Infant Discharge From the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled Study of a Health Literacy-informed Technology-based Approach to Support Safe Medication Use by Parents After Discharge of Infants From the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NYU Langone Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled study of parents of children to be discharged from the
      neonatal intensive care unit at Bellevue and Elmhurst hospitals. A total of 425 subjects will
      be recruited across two sites over preparatory phases and two primary study phases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our overarching goal is to promote safe medication use/adherence for high-risk infants, by
      leveraging health literacy approaches and mobile technology to reinforce provider counseling
      and support parent medication management after discharge from the NICU. We will
      adapt/integrate evidence-based strategies studied in less complex populations, for this
      vulnerable group. The HELPix (Health Education and Literacy for Parents) pictogram-based
      intervention, developed by our team, incorporates these strategies, with sizeable
      improvements found in medication knowledge, dosing errors, and adherence in outpatient
      general pediatric settings, but to date, HELPix has not been studied in NICU settings
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in Dosing with HELPix+TECH and HELPix in comparison to usual care.</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 3 (Day 30)</time_frame>
    <description>HELPix (health literacy-informed written materials and verbal counseling in addition to usual care) and HELPix+TECH (a health literacy-informed web application in addition to HELPix and usual care) will result in improved dosing compared to usual care alone. This will be assessed by the percentage of observed dosing error (whether clinically meaningful errors of &gt;20% deviation and/or large error of &gt;40% deviation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in medication adherence with HELPix+TECH and HELPix in comparison to usual care</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 3 (Day 30)</time_frame>
    <description>HELPix (health literacy-informed written materials and verbal counseling in addition to usual care) and HELPix+TECH (a health literacy-informed web application in addition to HELPix and usual care) will result in improved medication adherence compared to usual care alone. This will be assessed by the percentage of poor medication adherence (&gt;20% deviation from # prescribed doses).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Medication Administered in Error</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Current usual care includes standard discharge counseling by a nurse, with or without additional MD counseling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HELPix</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HELPix parents will receive usual care as above, after which trained staff will generate HELPix patient-/regimen-specific medication instruction sheets and review them with the parent.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HELPix+Tech</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After parent receives usual care and HELPix (as above), trained staff will walk parent through the app on-boarding process to overcome initial barriers to use. Steps: 1) Parent texted link to personalized on-line instructions. 2) Parent clicks link to app</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HELPix</intervention_name>
    <description>HELPix parents will receive usual care as above, after which trained staff will generate HELPix patient-/regimen-specific medication instruction sheets and review them with the parent. Instruction sheets include optimized instructions (mL-only, doses appropriately rounded, visuals of recommended tool (e.g. 1-mL syringe best for doses of &lt;1 mL), explicit frequency information (e.g. 'morning and night' instead of '2x/day') reinforced by pictograms (e.g. sun/moon icons)). For each medication, staff will: 1) review the dose (refer to the pictographic dose diagram, which illustrates optimal dosing tool filled to correct amount), 2) demonstrate the dose using optimal dosing tool, 3) ask parent to 'teachback'/'showback' dose (e.g. parent shows provider how much they would give by pulling back plunger on syringe to right level), 4) provide optimal dosing tool for the parent to take home. We anticipate this process will take ~5-10 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HELPix</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HELPix+Tech</intervention_name>
    <description>After parent receives usual care and HELPix , trained staff will walk parent through the app on-boarding process to overcome initial barriers to use. Steps: 1) Parent texted link to personalized on-line instructions. 2) Parent clicks link to app. For each medicine: A. Dosing module with optimized instructions (c/w HELPix); parent teachback/showback of dose B. Frequency module supports simplified, explicit intervals (e.g. 'morning and night'), parent chooses convenient times (text reminders sent based on preferences). Time for TECH depends on # medicines and parent baseline knowledge; structured protocol used to see # teachback rounds needed .</description>
    <arm_group_label>HELPix+Tech</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. English or Spanish-speaking

          2. 18 years of age and older

          3. Child discharged home with a Rx for &gt;1 daily liquid medication (other than
             multivitamin)

          4. Primary person who will administers child's medications.

          5. Willingness and ability to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Does not have a working phone number

          2. Does not have access to internet (via computer/smartphone)

          3. Does not have a mobile phone that receives texts.

          4. Not able to return to the hospital for their child's follow-up visit

          5. Visual acuity worse than 20/50 according to the Rosenbaum Pocket Screener

          6. Uncorrectable hearing impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hsiang Sharon Yin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hsiang Shonna Yin</last_name>
    <phone>646-501-4284</phone>
    <email>hsiang.yin@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jessica Velazquez</last_name>
    <phone>212-562-2821</phone>
    <email>jessica.velazquez@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 9 months and ending 36 months following article publication or as required by a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The investigator who proposed to use the data. Upon reasonable request</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

