<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04276610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRIR-1284-1217</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04276610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Words on the Brain: Can Reading Rehabilitation for Age-Related Vision Impairment Improve Cognitive Functioning?</brief_title>
  <acronym>WOTB</acronym>
  <official_title>Words on the Brain: Can Reading Rehabilitation for Age-Related Vision Impairment Improve Cognitive Functioning?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fonds de la Recherche en Santé du Québec</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université de Montréal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Age-related vision impairment and dementia both become more prevalent with increasing age.
      Research into the mechanisms of these conditions has proposed that some of their causes
      (e.g., macular degeneration/glaucoma and Alzheimer's disease) could be symptoms of an
      underlying common cause, or may be equally linked to a multifactorial context in frailty and
      aging. Research into sensory-cognitive aging has provided preliminary data that sensory
      decline may be linked to the progression of dementia through the concept of sensory
      deprivation. Preliminary data in hearing loss rehabilitation support the idea that improved
      hearing may have a beneficial effect on cognitive functioning; however, there are to date no
      data available to examine whether low vision rehabilitation, specifically for reading, could
      have an equally protective or beneficial effect on cognitive health. The present proposal
      aims to fill this gap.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The research questions are the following:

        1. Does low vision rehabilitation reduce reading effort?

        2. If so, does reduced reading effort increase reading activity,

        3. If so, does increased reading activity improve cognitive (memory) functioning?

      The objectives are to:

        -  Evaluate cognitive functioning and memory before, and 6 and 12 months after low vision
           reading rehabilitation using magnification in patients with age-related macular
           degeneration or glaucoma, compared to age-matched visually impaired controls who undergo
           rehabilitation that is NOT related to reading (e.g., mobility)

        -  Correlate participant characteristics with all cognitive outcome variables in order to
           identify potential mediators, moderators or confounders

      Hypotheses:

        -  Measures of reading (subjective and objective effort) will be statistically
           significantly reduced after participants have received strategies and tools to
           facilitate reading.

        -  Measures of reading behaviour will be negatively correlated with measures of reading
           effort (e.g., participants who report less effort will read more, more frequently and
           for longer)

        -  Individuals that demonstrate reduced reading effort/improved reading behaviour will
           demonstrate improved scores on cognitive tests after 6 months of having received
           rehabilitation strategies and tools, compared to those whose reading effort remains high
           or whose reading behaviour remains unchanged. These beneficial effects will be
           maintained after 12 months.

      Methodology

      Study Design: The study utilizes a quasi-experimental approach (nonrandomized, pre-post
      intervention study), an approach frequently used during the evaluation of health
      interventions. Specifically, a 2x3 design (2 groups x 3 time points) will allow for the
      examination of whether cognitive performance will change before and after 6 and 12 months of
      a low vision reading intervention, when comparing low vision patients to age-matched
      controls. Participants will also be audio-recorded throughout several of the tasks to not
      only ensure the highest level of precision when inputting and analyzing data, but will also
      help reduce the overall testing time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 16, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 16, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are verbally presented with a list of 15 words that they are asked to repeat and memorize, then recall immediately, and again recall them 15 minutes later. The score is the number of items recalled from 0 to 15, with higher scores indicating better recall.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Letter Number Sequencing task</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are asked to speak out loud the first 13 letters of the alphabet and alternate them with consecutive numbers (e.g., 1 - A - 2 - B 3 -C ...). The score is the number of correct alternations between numbers and letter, from 0 to 26, with higher scores indicating better performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal Cognitive Assessment - full or blind version</measure>
    <time_frame>4 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are asked to complete the visual and auditory items of this cognitive screening measure. The Blind versions (no visual items is utilized for persons whose vision is too impaired to see the pictograms). The score is the total number of items completed correctly, ranging from 0 to 30 for the full version, and 0 to 22 for the Blind version, with higher scores indicating better outcomes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1-n-back task</measure>
    <time_frame>3 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are asked to verbally repeat a string of numbers presented orally, while naming the previous item to the one just presented. The score is the total number of correct recalls, ranging from 0 to 25, with higher scores indicating better performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minnesota Reading Test (MNRead)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are asked to read individual sentences on an eye chart. The log score indicates reading acuity ranging from -0.1 to 1.0 with higher numbers indicating poorer acuity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>A 21-item questionnaire that measures the self-reported perception of depression, anxiety and stress on its three sub-scales, respectively. Scores for each item are from 0 to 3. Higher scores indicate higher levels of perceived depression, anxiety and stress, ranging each from 0 to 21 for each sub-scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Canadian Digit Triplet Test</measure>
    <time_frame>4 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>A test measuring speech-in-noise perception. Participants are presented with three spoken digits through a head-set, and are asked to then enter them on a keyboard. Correct repetition will increase background noise, while incorrect answers will decrease background noise. The outcome measure is the estimated threshold for the signal-to-noise ratio where a participant can still comprehend the spoken digits. More negative score ratios indicate more tolerance to noise, therefore indicating better performance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) - for subset of participants</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Cortical invasive scan to measure structure and volume of brain regions involved in reading and sensory processing. Participants will placed in a Magnetic Resonance Imaging scanner in order to obtain structural measurement of their cortical architecture. Participants are asked to remain still a possible during these scans; however, they are not required to be otherwise engaged in any activity or decision-making. Higher volume measures indicate that more cortical volume is allocated to specific brain regions. This does not necessarily imply a functional judgment on its capacity, but is an anatomical measure only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Age-related Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Low Vision</condition>
  <condition>Low Vision Aids</condition>
  <condition>Hearing Loss</condition>
  <condition>Reading Problem</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Control Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Older adults (65+) without impairments in vision or hearing. This groups will simply be followed for the study period (1 year), measured at 6 months intervals, to provide control comparison data for all outcome measures</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Vision Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Older adults (65+) with impairments in vision but without hearing impairment. This groups will receive regular standard of low vision rehabilitation care and will be followed for the study period (1 year), measured at 6 months intervals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dual Sensory Impairment Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Older adults (65+) with impairments in both vision hearing hearing. This groups will receive regular standard of low vision rehabilitation care and will be followed for the study period (1 year), measured at 6 months intervals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Vision Reading Rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>Following Time 1, participants will receive the full complement of vision rehabilitation services available and deemed suitable by their clinical staff and rehabilitation professionals of either rehabilitation centre, according to the provision of assistive devices and services regulated by the Quebec Health Insurance (RAMQ). These services are include but are not limited to: a full optometric exam to determine functional vision, including refraction and the prescription of appropriate near and distance glasses and optical devices, an assessment by a low vision therapist and/or occupational therapist, the loan provision of hand-held optical magnification devices, electronic non-optical magnification devices (e.g., portable or table-top closed-circuit televisions), or computer software for screen content magnification (e.g., ZoomText), with appropriate training and follow-up sessions in the home, if required.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dual Sensory Impairment Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Vision Participants</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Use of magnification devices</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able to communicate in either English or French

          2. Impairment of central vision, affecting acuity due to any diagnosis

          3. Visual acuity in the better eye with best standard correction of 20/60 or less

          4. Potential benefit from magnification or other reading rehabilitation interventions, as
             determined by rehabilitation professional.

          5. Client dossier with one of the partnering rehabilitation agencies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Complete blindness

          2. Inability to communicate verbally

          3. Inability to independently give informed written consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Walter Wittich, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Walter Wittich, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>15143437962</phone>
    <email>walter.wittich@umontreal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Natalie Phillips, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>15148482424</phone>
    <phone_ext>2218</phone_ext>
    <email>Natalie.Phillips@concordia.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Nazareth et Louis-Braille du CISSS de la Montérégie-Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Longueuil</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J4K 5G4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Genevieve Lizé, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>450 463-1710</phone>
      <email>genevieve.lize.inlb@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de réadaptation Lethbridge-Layton-Mackay du CIUSSS du Centre-Ouest-de-l'Île-de-Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4B 1R3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chantal Robillard, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>15144885552</phone>
      <email>chantal.robillard.mab@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Serge Maynard, M.A.</last_name>
      <phone>15144885552</phone>
      <email>serge.maynard.ccomtl@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 17, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université de Montréal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Walter Wittich</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vision, Low</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 16, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/10/NCT04276610/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 7, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/10/NCT04276610/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

