<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04272944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MSB2311-CSP-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04272944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of MSB2311 in Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial on the Tolerance and Pharmacokinetics of Recombinant Humanized Anti-PD-L1 Monoclonal Antibody MSB2311 Injection in the Treatment of Advanced Solid Tumor on Phase I</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mabspace Biosciences (Suzhou) Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mabspace Biosciences (Suzhou) Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a first-in-human (FIH), open-label, Phase 1 dose-Escalation Study of MSB2311, a
      humanized anti-PD-L1 monoclonal antibody, in subjects with advanced solid tumors. Qualified
      subjects will be enrolled to receive their assigned dose regimen of MSB2311 until disease
      progression or intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of consent, or end of study, whichever occurs
      first. The maximum treatment duration is 2 years. During the study, subjects will be
      evaluated for safety and toxicity, PK/PD, immunogenicity and anti-tumor activity of MSB2311.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of MSB2311</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number adverse events that are related to treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose(MTD) or recommended phase2 dose（RP2D）</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of subjects experiencing DLT in each escalation cohort</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) for MSB2311</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following the last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in AUC over time in subjects with MSB2311</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Plasma concentration (Cmax)for MSB2311</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following the last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax is the maximum observed plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to the Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following the last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax is the time in hours/days to reach Cmax following dosing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination half-life (t1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following the last dose</time_frame>
    <description>The time required for the plasma level of the study drug to decrease by one-half during the terminal elimination phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) as measured by RESISTv1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR) as measured by RESISTv1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS) as measured by RESISTv1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best overall response as measured by RESISTv1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) as measured by RESISTv1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days following the last dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSB2311 Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MSB2311 will be administered as an IV infusion once every 3 weeks (Q3W). The planned doses starts at 3 mg/kg to 20 mg/kg, but dose levels or the dosing interval may be adjusted during the study based on emerging data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSB2311 Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>An intravenous infusion with concentration from 3 mg/kg to 20 mg/kg every 3 weeks (Q3W)or every 2 weeks(Q2W).</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSB2311 Injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Voluntary informed consent, knowledge of the study and willingness to follow and has
             ability to complete all trial procedures

          -  There is a histologically or cytologically confirmed, locally advanced or metastatic
             tumor that is not resectable

               -  b period participants shall provide the archive paraffin embedding tumor tissue
                  samples

          -  The eastern United States cooperative tumor group (ECOG) score was 0 or 1

          -  Expect to survive at least 3 months

          -  Subjects must have measurable lesions (at least 1 lesion) and minimum tumor-specific
             antigen levels where applicable

          -  If you have received antitumor therapy, you need to meet certain conditions

          -  There are suitable organs and hematopoietic functions

          -  Male subjects and female subjects of child-bearing age shall agree to take effective,
             investigator-approved contraceptive measures from the date of signing the informed
             consent until 3 months after the last administration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient has had a malignant tumor other than the tumor treated in this study
             within 5 years prior to the first administration, unless the medical examiner of the
             study group and sponsor agrees that the old tumor has been cured or will not
             metastasise or cause death in this study

          -  Adverse reactions to previous treatments did not return to CTCAE v4.03 rating ≤ 1,
             except for residual alopecia effect

          -  Patients who had been treated with anti-pd-1 or pd-l1 antibodies, or who had been
             treated with antibodies/drugs that target any other t-cell co-regulatory proteins
             within 12 weeks of the first administration of the drug in this study

          -  Patients with primary CNS tumors or CNS metastases known or identified during
             screening

          -  Subjects with active or pre-existing autoimmune disease that may recur or patients at
             high risk

          -  Patients who had major surgery in the first 4 weeks of screening and who were expected
             to have major surgery during the study period including a 28-day screening period

          -  Subjects who require systemic treatment with corticosteroids or other
             immunosuppressive drugs within 14 days prior to enrollment or during the study period

          -  Sudden pulmonary disease, interstitial pulmonary disease or pneumonia, or other
             uncontrolled systemic disease, including diabetes, pulmonary fibrosis, acute pulmonary
             disease, cardiovascular disease, including hypertension, except local interstitial
             pneumonia induced by radiotherapy

          -  A history of human immunodeficiency virus infection, or other acquired or congenital
             immunodeficiency, or a history of organ transplantation, or stem cell transplantation

          -  Had a history of tuberculosis, or had tuberculosis disease at the time of screening

          -  Patients with chronic hepatitis b or active hepatitis c.Hepatitis b carriers, stable
             hepatitis b after drug treatment and cured hepatitis c patients can be included in the
             group

          -  Patients who have been seriously infected within 4 weeks prior to first
             administration, or who have developed signs or symptoms of any active infection within
             the previous 2 weeks, or who require antibiotic treatment within the previous 2
             weeks;Unexplained fever occurred before the first administration and the body
             temperature exceeded 38.5℃

          -  Subjects who have previously been known to have a severe allergic reaction to a
             macromolecular protein preparation/monoclonal antibody or to any component of the test
             drug

          -  Immune-related adverse events (irAE) grade ≥3 occurred after receiving immunotherapy

          -  Participated in clinical trials of other drugs within 4 weeks before enrollment

          -  A history of alcohol, drug or substance abuse within the last 1 year

          -  Has a clear history of neurological or psychiatric disorders, such as epilepsy,
             dementia, poor compliance

          -  A woman who is pregnant or breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mengde Wang</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Mabspace Biosciences (Suzhou) Co., Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ling Sun</last_name>
    <phone>+86-512-67079200</phone>
    <phone_ext>8009</phone_ext>
    <email>ling.sun@transcenta.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ming Yue</last_name>
    <phone>+86-512-67079200</phone>
    <phone_ext>8009</phone_ext>
    <email>ming.yue@transcenta.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mabspace Biosciences (Suzhou) Co., Ltd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>215123</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mengde Wang</last_name>
      <phone>+86-512-67079200</phone>
      <phone_ext>8009</phone_ext>
      <email>mengde.wang@transcenta.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lin Shen</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xi Chun Hu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

