<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04275011</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>41153</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04275011</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bone Response to Exercise in Women on Antiresorptive Medications</brief_title>
  <acronym>BRRIE</acronym>
  <official_title>Bone Response to Resistance and Impact Exercise (BRRIE) in Women on Antiresorptive Medications: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Waterloo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Waterloo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Performing resistance training and impact exercise at a moderate to high intensity may help
      prevent bone loss. However, medications used to treat bone diseases such as osteoporosis
      reduce the activity of bone cells. The investigators are unsure whether bone cells will still
      respond to exercise in people on osteoporosis medications. Therefore, investigators have
      designed a study to compare bone response to moderate-high intensity exercise that involves
      resistance training and impact exercise versus posture and low intensity balance exercises.
      Women taking osteoporosis medication will be equally and randomly assigned to one of the
      exercise groups. There will be 23 participants per group and both exercise programs will be
      performed over a span of 6 months, twice weekly, for approximately 30-45 minutes per session.
      Investigators will measure sclerostin, a bone-related protein found in the blood, to see if
      there are any changes after 3 months of training. Higher levels of sclerostin may result in
      greater bone breakdown. It is expected that the moderate-high intensity exercise program will
      decrease sclerostin levels more than low intensity training. Further, changes in sclerostin
      levels during the 6-month exercise intervention will be explored. The effects of the exercise
      program on other bone markers in the blood, physical ability, and quality of life will be
      reported. The willingness of the participants to perform the exercise program and the safety
      of the exercises provided will also be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pharmacological and exercise interventions aimed to treat osteoporosis are typically examined
      separately. A common pharmacological treatment for osteoporosis involves antiresorptive
      medications, which has been previously shown to blunt the bone response to exercise. Many
      studies have shown that moderate-high intensity progressive resistance training (PRT) and
      impact exercise is required to stimulate bone. There are only two RCT studies that examined
      the effect of progressive resistance training or impact exercise on bone response in
      participants taking antiresorptive medications. One study showed that the combination of
      antiresorptive medications and resistance training did not increase bone mineral density
      (BMD) to a greater extent than medications alone in postmenopausal women. Another study
      demonstrated no additive effect of antiresorptive medications and progressive impact exercise
      on reducing bone turn over markers (BTMs) in postmenopausal women. However, there are
      currently no available studies that examine the effect of both progressive resistance
      training along with impact exercise on the bone response in women taking antiresorptive
      medications. Most exercise studies exclude people taking medications that affect bone, or are
      heterogeneous with respect to antiresorptive medication use. Further, there is little data on
      the safety of moderate-high intensity PRT and impact exercise in individuals at moderate or
      high risk for fracture.

      The bone response to medications and exercise can be measured via the assessment of bone
      biomarkers present in the blood. For instance, sclerostin is a protein secreted by osteocytes
      and it can influence the bone remodeling process by inhibiting bone formation. Human genetic
      disorders deficient in sclerostin, such as sclerosteosis and Van Buchem's disease, have been
      associated with significant increases in bone mass. Therefore, decreasing sclerostin levels
      may be a potential treatment for people with low bone mass conditions. A case-control study
      demonstrated that postmenopausal women who adequately responded to bisphosphonates (e.g., did
      not experience a fracture while on treatment) had significantly lower serum sclerostin
      concentrations than those who experienced a fracture while taking bisphosphonates. There is
      also a link between sclerostin and exercise as a previous cross-sectional study reported an
      association between low serum sclerostin levels and increased physical activity duration. In
      addition, PRT and high impact exercise interventions have been shown to decrease sclerostin
      levels in healthy pre-menopausal women and thus may eventually increase bone mass or prevent
      bone loss. Therefore, changes in serum sclerostin levels can be used to provide insight
      regarding the bone response to antiresorptive medications as well as exercise.

      Investigators plan to conduct a single-blinded parallel-group randomized controlled trial
      (RCT) with 1:1 allocation ratio to determine whether participants with low bone mass are able
      to adhere and safely perform PRT and impact exercises at an intensity that is hypothesized to
      stimulate bone. Specifically, the primary aim will be to determine the effects of
      moderate-high PRT and impact training on sclerostin in women on antiresorptive medication.
      The secondary aims are: a) to explore the effects of moderate-high PRT and impact training on
      BTMs [serum N-terminal procollagen of type I collagen (P1NP), C-terminal cross-linked of type
      I collagen (CTX), parathyroid hormone (PTH), Vitamin D and serum calcium], physical function
      and quality of life and body composition; b) to determine the feasibility of the intervention
      by assessing adherence, participant satisfaction with the intervention, and the acceptability
      of the attention control group; and c) to determine if there are any adverse events,
      including falls, fractures, or other adverse health outcomes attributable to the exercise
      intervention.

      Investigators hypothesize that a moderate-to high PRT and impact exercise program will
      decrease sclerostin levels to a greater extent than the posture and balance exercise program.
      Further, it is hypothesized that PRT and impact exercise will result in more favourable
      improvements in other bone biomarkers, physical function, mobility, quality of life and body
      composition than the control group. Investigators hypothesize a low drop-out rate since both
      groups will be receiving the same level of attention throughout the study. Further, no
      adverse events attributable to exercise are expected. Kinesiologists who are Certified
      Exercise Physiologists will provide coaching on proper form, and will use appropriate
      progression of exercise intensity and volume.

      Sample Size Estimation:

      The sample size estimation was determined using data from a cross-sectional study that
      reported an association between low physical activity duration and high serum sclerostin
      levels. Women who engaged in less than 30 minutes of exercise per week had statistically
      significantly higher serum sclerostin levels than women who engaged in 60-120 minutes of
      physical activity per week (27.84 +/- 4.98 pmol/L vs. 21.64 +/- 6.21 pmol/L; p&lt;0.0001,
      respectively). The study described used a manual ELISA® kit to assess sclerostin which is
      consistent with the current study protocol. Based on the study findings, to detect a
      difference in serum sclerostin of 6.2 pmol/L with a standard deviation of 1.23 pmol/L
      investigators will need 38 participants using an alpha level of 0.05 and a power of 90%.
      Investigators assumed a 20% attrition rate for the current study therefore the estimated
      sample size was increased to 46 participants.

      Analyses:

      The study protocol was prepared according to the Standard Protocol Items: Recommendations for
      Interventional Trial (SPIRIT) guidelines. Reporting will be consistent with Consolidated
      Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) non-pharmacological trials extension. The proposed
      study protocol is summarized. Participant characteristics and outcomes that are considered
      continuous variables will be reported as mean +/- standard deviation or median and
      interquartile range. Categorical data will be reported as number (%). Analyses of the
      feasibility and safety of the exercise intervention will be descriptive. A participant flow
      diagram will be used to demonstrate the number of participants who were randomly assigned to
      each group, who completed the exercise training program and who were analyzed for each
      outcome. For each group, losses or exclusions after randomization will be recorded along with
      reasons. Intention-to-treat analysis will be performed and thus all participants will be
      included in the analysis and analysed according to the group to which they were randomized.
      Differences in outcome measures will be assessed using analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) while
      adjusting for baseline demographic and clinical characteristics (e.g., age, smoking status,
      physical activity level, dietary intake). Investigators will also perform sensitivity
      analysis to determine if participants with ≥80% adherence criteria to the exercise
      intervention experience greater benefits. At the end of the study, investigators will assess
      whether allocation concealment was maintained among the blinded research staff and whether
      participants were aware of the study hypothesis. Statistical significance will be set at p &lt;
      or equal to 0.05. All data analysis will be conducted using the IBM Corporation Statistical
      Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) version 24.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a single-blinded RCT comparing moderate-high progressive resistance training and impact exercise to an attention control who will be performing static posture and balance exercises.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Using a computer-generated random selection process, participants will be randomized in a 1:1 allocation ratio in blocks which will be randomly determined. Allocation will be concealed from all but the person performing the randomization, the participants, and the exercise trainers. Although the participants cannot be blinded to the assigned exercise group, they will simply be informed that the purpose of the study is to compare two different exercise programs with no indication regarding the study hypothesis. Research staff blinded to group allocation will have access to the assessment forms. An alternate research staff member will collect or enter data that may cause unblinding (e.g., randomization, exercise adherence logs). Exercise trainers who are unblinded to group allocation will have access to the exercise training manual. Completed outcome assessments and exercise training data will be stored in separate password protected files to avoid exposing group allocation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Serum Sclerostin at 3 months and 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure will be serum sclerostin. Venous blood samples will be taken by experienced phlebotomists between 8:00 and 10:00 am, after an overnight fast (8-12 hours). Participants will also be instructed to refrain from exercise for 48 hours prior to blood collection. An assessor who is blind to group allocation will measure sclerostin using ab221836 Human SOST SimpleStep ELISA® (Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay) supplied by Abcam (Abcam Inc., Toronto, Ontario, Canada).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Data - Demographic information</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will collect data such as demographic information including date of birth, race, formal education and marital status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Data - Medical History</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Current and past medical history (including family history) will be collected including recent/past drug therapies and bone-related medications, reproductive history (e.g. age at menarche or menopause), past surgical history, falls risk (e.g. number of falls within the last 12 months) and fracture history, as well as current alcohol consumption and smoking status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Data - Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline physical activity will be assessed using a Bone-specific Physical activity Questionnaire (BPAQ), and by asking participants to wear accelerometers for one week prior to participating in the exercise program.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive Data - Dietary Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-months, and 6-months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess dietary energy, calcium and protein intake, participants will be asked to complete an Automated Self-Administered 24-hour (ASA24®) Dietary Assessment Tool (Canada Version).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other bone biomarkers - Serum P1NP</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum P1NP will be be measured by the same single blinded assessor. P1NP will be measured using Human Total Procollagen Type I Intact N-Terminal Propeptide (TP1NP) ELISA Kit supplied by MyBioSource (MyBioSource Inc., San Diego, California, USA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other bone biomarkers - CTX</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>CTX will be measured in the blood by the same single blinded assessor. Beta-crosslaps CTX will be measured using Human beta-crosslaps (bCTx) ELISA Kit supplied by Cusabio (Cusabio Technology LLC, Houston, Texas, USA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other bone biomarkers - Parathyroid Hormone</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>PTH will be measured in the blood by the same single blinded assessor. Parathyroid hormone will be measured using ab230931 Human PTH SimpleStep ELISA® Kit supplied by Abcam (Abcam Inc., Toronto, Ontario, Canada).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other bone biomarkers - Vitamin D</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Vitamin D will be measured in the blood by the same single blinded assessor. Vitamin D will be measured using Human 25-Hydroxyvitamin D-1 Aplha Hydroxylase Mitochondrial (CYPB27B1) ELISA® Kit supplied by Cusabio (Cusabio Technology LLC, Houston, Texas, USA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other bone biomarkers - Calcium</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Calcium will be measured in the blood by the same single blinded assessor. Calcium will be measured using ab112115 Calcium Quantification Kit - Red Fluorescence supplied by Abcam (Abcam Inc., Toronto, Ontario, Canada).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical function and mobility - 40 metre Fast-paced Walk</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Physical function and mobility will be assessed using the 40 m fast-paced walk test. Time to complete test will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical function and mobility - 30-second Sit-to-Stand Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Physical function and mobility will be assessed using the 30-second sit-to-stand test. Number of sit-to-stand repetitions performed in 30 seconds will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical function and mobility - 4-square Step Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Physical function and mobility will be assessed using the 4-square step test. Time to complete test will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical function and mobility - Stair Climb Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Physical function and mobility will be assessed using the stair climb test. Time to complete test will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life - EQ-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>The 5 level EuroQol EQ-5D instrument (EQ-5D-5L) will be used to assess the quality of life of the participants. The EQ-5D-5L instrument includes a descriptive system that is comprised of five dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Scores are coded from 11111 (no problems in all dimensions) to 55555 (extreme problems in all dimensions). A lower score is better. There is also a visual analogue scale that is used to measure the individuals self-rated overall health on a particular day. The visual analogue scale is scored from 0 (worst health imaginable) to 100 (best health imaginable).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life - QUALEFFO-41</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-month and 6-month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>The Quality of Life Questionnaire of the European Foundation for Osteoporosis (QUALEFFO-41) questionnaire will be used to assess quality of life of the participants. The QUALEFFO-41 questionnaire is specific to people with osteoporosis and includes the following domains: pain, activities of daily living, mobility, leisure and social activity, general health perception, and mental function. Scores range from 0-100, lower is better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone Mineral Density</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Certified technologists, blind to group allocation, will assess bone mineral density (g/cm2) at the spine (L1-L4) and femoral neck using a dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan (Hologic Inc, Bedford, MA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Certified technologists, blind to group allocation, will assess body mass (kg) and use this to determine whole body fat- and bone-free lean mass (FBFM, in kg) and appendicular lean mass (ALM, in kg) and its index (ALMI) using a dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan (Hologic Inc, Bedford, MA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility (Number of participants retained)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility outcomes will include a record of the number of participants recruited and retained, and the acceptability of the attention control group (e.g., low dropout rate after randomization).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility (Adherence)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study, 6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The exercise trainers will be provided with an attendance sheet at every exercise session to monitor the number of exercise sessions participants attend to determine adherence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility (Acceptability)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>We will conduct one exit interview to determine the participants' perspective on the intervention and control groups, and if they understood the purpose of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study, up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Falls will be recorded using a prospective notification system to assess the number of falls, the number of fallers/non-fallers/frequent fallers and the fall rate. Participants will be asked weekly to report any falls that occurred outside of, and during, the exercise training program. Participants will be instructed to provide their weekly assessments to the exercise trainers when they attend their scheduled exercise sessions. Exercise trainers will check to ensure completion, confirm the date, injuries and hospitalization after a fall has been reported, and will follow-up with participants who have missing assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fractures</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study, up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will also be asked to report any new fractures or injuries, related or unrelated to the exercise training. Exercise trainers will complete an adverse event report to ascertain the cause and timing of any injuries. To verify fracture details, written consent will be obtained to abstract data from medical records.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study, up to 6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>According to Health Canada a serious adverse event is defined as &quot;. . . an event (experience) or reaction is any untoward medical occurrence that at any dose (a) results in death, (b) is life-threatening, (c) requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, (d) results in persistent or significant disability/ incapacity, or (e) is a congenital anomaly/birth defect&quot;. Whereas a non-serious adverse event includes bone/limb pain, myalgia or muscle cramps (e.g. pain, cramps or aches), and injuries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoporosis</condition>
  <condition>Bone Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Static Posture and Balance Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive equal attention through a static posture and balance exercise class two times per week, in a small group setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Resistance and Impact Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The exercise program will include two progressive resistance and impact exercise training sessions per week in a small group setting. Exercises will be individually tailored to the participants' abilities and designed to achieve a maximum 80-85% 1RM.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progressive Resistance and Impact Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Full body resistance and impact exercises will be performed twice a week for 30-45 minutes over a 6 month period. There will be at least one day of rest between scheduled exercise sessions. Participants will be individually prescribed variations of push, pull, squat, lift and carry movements targeting major muscle groups that they can safely complete, and accessory exercises to help develop movement patterns. Exercises will challenge both the upper and lower body using functional movement patterns. Each muscle group will be trained twice a week. During the first month, participants will focus on completing exercises with good form at a low intensity. Once form is mastered, exercises will be progressed (by increasing load, or challenge of the movement) to a moderate to high exercise intensity (80-85% 1RM) so that the participant can complete a maximum of 8 (~80% 1RM) or 6 (~85% 1RM) repetitions with 1-2 repetitions in reserve for 3 sets at a rating of perceived exertion (RPE) of 8-9.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Resistance and Impact Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Static Balance and Postural Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the attention control group will perform static posture and balance exercises (e.g., low intensity yoga poses) and will be given the same attention as the participants in the intervention group. The small group exercises will be performed twice a week, 30-45 minutes per session, over 6 months, with at least one day of rest between each session. The exercise program will be supervised by a certified personal trainer and yoga instructor who is BoneFit trained.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Static Posture and Balance Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women over 18 years of age AND

          -  Taking anti-resorptive medications for at least 12 months eg. risedronate (Actonel),
             alendronate (Fosamax, Fosavance), etidronate (Didronel, Didrocal), zoledronic acid
             (Aclasta, Reclast, Zometa), pamidronate (Aredia) and denosumab (Prolia, Xgeva).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not able to communicate in English

          -  Already participating in structured progressive resistance exercise or impact training
             exercise program; presence of any progressive neurological disorders that can possibly
             prevent study completion; unable to stand or walk 10 m with or without gait aid; does
             not have the mental capacity to provide informed consent; have any contraindications
             to exercise as determined by a physician.

          -  Individuals that have had a fracture in the last 6 months need to have completed any
             immobilization (eg. casting) and post-fracture rehabilitation, and will need physician
             consent to participate in the study. Individuals with previous fractures (&gt; 6 months
             ago) will not be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lora M Giangregorio, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Waterloo, Schlegel-UW Research Institute for Aging</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Waterloo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N2L 3G1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rasha El-Kotob, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>519-888-4567</phone>
      <phone_ext>38779</phone_ext>
      <email>relkotob@uwaterloo.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lora M Giangregorio, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swift JM, Nilsson MI, Hogan HA, Sumner LR, Bloomfield SA. Simulated resistance training during hindlimb unloading abolishes disuse bone loss and maintains muscle strength. J Bone Miner Res. 2010 Mar;25(3):564-74. doi: 10.1359/jbmr.090811.</citation>
    <PMID>19653816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chilibeck PD, Davison KS, Whiting SJ, Suzuki Y, Janzen CL, Peloso P. The effect of strength training combined with bisphosphonate (etidronate) therapy on bone mineral, lean tissue, and fat mass in postmenopausal women. Can J Physiol Pharmacol. 2002 Oct;80(10):941-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12450060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uusi-Rasi K, Kannus P, Cheng S, Sievänen H, Pasanen M, Heinonen A, Nenonen A, Halleen J, Fuerst T, Genant H, Vuori I. Effect of alendronate and exercise on bone and physical performance of postmenopausal women: a randomized controlled trial. Bone. 2003 Jul;33(1):132-43.</citation>
    <PMID>12919708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martyn-St James M, Carroll S. A meta-analysis of impact exercise on postmenopausal bone loss: the case for mixed loading exercise programmes. Br J Sports Med. 2009 Dec;43(12):898-908. doi: 10.1136/bjsm.2008.052704. Epub 2008 Nov 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18981037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basat H, Esmaeilzadeh S, Eskiyurt N. The effects of strengthening and high-impact exercises on bone metabolism and quality of life in postmenopausal women: a randomized controlled trial. J Back Musculoskelet Rehabil. 2013;26(4):427-35. doi: 10.3233/BMR-130402.</citation>
    <PMID>23948830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erickson CR, Vukovich MD. Osteogenic index and changes in bone markers during a jump training program: a pilot study. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2010 Aug;42(8):1485-92. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e3181d0fa7a. Erratum in: Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2012 Apr;44(4):770.</citation>
    <PMID>20139789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watson S, Weeks B, Weis L, Harding A, Horan S, Beck B. High-Intensity Resistance and Impact Training Improves Bone Mineral Density and Physical Function in Postmenopausal Women With Osteopenia and Osteoporosis: The LIFTMOR Randomized Controlled Trial. J Bone Miner Res. 2019 Mar;34(3):572. doi: 10.1002/jbmr.3659. Epub 2019 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>30861219</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watson SL, Weeks BK, Weis LJ, Horan SA, Beck BR. Heavy resistance training is safe and improves bone, function, and stature in postmenopausal women with low to very low bone mass: novel early findings from the LIFTMOR trial. Osteoporos Int. 2015 Dec;26(12):2889-94. doi: 10.1007/s00198-015-3263-2. Epub 2015 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26243363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamilton CJ, Swan VJ, Jamal SA. The effects of exercise and physical activity participation on bone mass and geometry in postmenopausal women: a systematic review of pQCT studies. Osteoporos Int. 2010 Jan;21(1):11-23. doi: 10.1007/s00198-009-0967-1. Epub 2009 Jun 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19504035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beck BR, Daly RM, Singh MAF, Taaffe DR. Exercise and Sports Science Australia (ESSA) position statement on exercise prescription for the prevention and management of osteoporosis. J Sci Med Sport [Internet]. 2017;20(5):438-45. Available from: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jsams.2016.10.001</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaastad TS, Nordsletten L, Narum S, Madsen JE, Haug E, Reikerås O. Training increases the in vivo fracture strength in osteoporotic bone. Protection by muscle contraction examined in rat tibiae. Acta Orthop Scand. 1996 Aug;67(4):371-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8792742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howe TE, Shea B, Dawson LJ, Downie F, Murray A, Ross C, Harbour RT, Caldwell LM, Creed G. Exercise for preventing and treating osteoporosis in postmenopausal women. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011 Jul 6;(7):CD000333. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000333.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21735380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baron R, Rawadi G. Targeting the Wnt/beta-catenin pathway to regulate bone formation in the adult skeleton. Endocrinology. 2007 Jun;148(6):2635-43. Epub 2007 Mar 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17395698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Bezooijen RL, ten Dijke P, Papapoulos SE, Löwik CW. SOST/sclerostin, an osteocyte-derived negative regulator of bone formation. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 2005 Jun;16(3):319-27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15869900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moester MJ, Papapoulos SE, Löwik CW, van Bezooijen RL. Sclerostin: current knowledge and future perspectives. Calcif Tissue Int. 2010 Aug;87(2):99-107. doi: 10.1007/s00223-010-9372-1. Epub 2010 May 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20473488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morales-Santana S, Díez-Pérez A, Olmos JM, Nogués X, Sosa M, Díaz-Curiel M, Pérez-Castrillón JL, Pérez-Cano R, Torrijos A, Jodar E, Rio LD, Caeiro-Rey JR, Reyes-García R, García-Fontana B, González-Macías J, Muñoz-Torres M. Circulating sclerostin and estradiol levels are associated with inadequate response to bisphosphonates in postmenopausal women with osteoporosis. Maturitas. 2015 Dec;82(4):402-10. doi: 10.1016/j.maturitas.2015.08.007. Epub 2015 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26358930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ardawi MS, Rouzi AA, Qari MH. Physical activity in relation to serum sclerostin, insulin-like growth factor-1, and bone turnover markers in healthy premenopausal women: a cross-sectional and a longitudinal study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Oct;97(10):3691-9. doi: 10.1210/jc.2011-3361. Epub 2012 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22865898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vainionpää A, Korpelainen R, Väänänen HK, Haapalahti J, Jämsä T, Leppäluoto J. Effect of impact exercise on bone metabolism. Osteoporos Int. 2009 Oct;20(10):1725-33. doi: 10.1007/s00198-009-0881-6. Epub 2009 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>19262975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Progressive Resistance Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Impact Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-resorptive medication</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

