<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04277858</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MP-37-2018-3443</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04277858</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy and Transoral Robotic Surgery for Oropharyngeal Cancer.</brief_title>
  <acronym>NECTORS</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Study: Induction Chemotherapy Followed by Transoral Robotic Surgery and Neck Dissection for Definitive Management of Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma. (NECTORS Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nader Sadeghi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this trial is to study the efficacy of treatment of human papilloma virus
      (HPV) related oropharyngeal cancer with chemotherapy followed by Transoral Robotic Surgery
      (TORS) as definitive treatment. Current treatment of oropharyngeal cancer are
      chemo-radiotherapy. There is significant lifelong side effects associated with this approach
      related to tissue effects of radiotherapy. The side effects results in significant quality of
      life deterioration among the patients. Overall there is 20% failure rate with this treatment
      approach. The study hypothesis is that treatment with upfront (neoadjuvant) chemotherapy
      followed by transoral surgery and neck dissection is highly effective treatment allowing
      competitive cure rate compared to chemo-radiotherapy with less than 10% failure rate, while
      avoiding radiotherapy in majority of cases. It is also hypothesized that better functional
      and quality of life outcome maybe achieved with this approach.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current standard of care for advanced (AJCC-7 edition stage III and IV) oropharyngeal
      squamous cell carcinoma are concomitant chemoradiation, or surgery followed by adjuvant
      radiation therapy with or without concomitant chemotherapy. These approaches have persistent
      and significant lifelong side effects and sequelae related to treatment, and in particular
      related to radiotherapy. The side effects of radiotherapy (augmented with concomitant
      chemotherapy) include soft tissue fibrosis, loss of salivary function, dry mouth, life long
      disturbed taste function, poor dental health with rapidly decaying teeth, dysfunction of
      swallowing, significant loss of the mobility of the base of tongue and pharyngeal
      constrictors, loss of laryngeal elevation, esophageal stricture, and at times severe side
      effects such as soft tissue necrosis or osteoradionecrosis of the mandible. About 10% of the
      patients undergoing chemoradiation for oropharyngeal cancer develop long term swallowing
      dysfunction with feeding tube dependency. As a result , patient's quality of life (QOL) is
      adversely affected. Improvements in the side effect profile of treatment, the functional
      outcome, and the QOL remain very important areas of advancement in treating this patient
      population. Improvements in functional outcome need to be achieved while maintaining or
      improving the oncologic outcome and cure rates for cancer, compared to the standard of care.

      Use of Taxane based chemotherapy along with Platinum drugs (Cisplatin and Carboplatin) in
      high dose neoadjuvant setting, coupled with Transoral Laser Microsurgery (TLM) or Transoral
      Robotic Assisted Surgery (TORS), allows potential for improved oncologic outcome as well as
      avoidance of long term sequelae of high dose radiation therapy to head and neck. These
      transoral surgical approaches (TLM and TORS) provide improved functional outcome compared
      with traditional open composite resections and complex reconstructive algorithms for
      oropharynx. TLM and TORS are currently in clinical use for early (stage T1 and T2 with N0 or
      N+ve) oropharyngeal cancer.

      De-escalation treatment strategies of TORS followed by adjuvant radiotherapy are being
      investigated currently. However even without de-escalation there is overall 18-20% rate of
      treatment failure and half of failures are due to distant metastasis in the absence of
      loco-regional recurrence. In this study the investigators propose systemic escalation of
      treatment with neoadjuvant chemotherapy (docetaxel and cisplatin) followed by de-escalated
      locoregional treatment with transoral surgery and neck dissection reserving radiotherapy for
      salvage.

      This approach has the potential for improved functional outcome by avoiding short and more
      importantly long term and permanent sequelae of radiation therapy in oropharyngeal cancer
      treatment. This approach is a new paradigm in treatment of oropharyngeal cancer, and can
      significantly improve the functional outcome of cancer treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>neoadjuvant Docetaxel and Cisplatin and transoral surgery</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary outcome: progression free survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be evaluated for cancer recurrence or persistence. Index cancer recurrence or persistence following completion of treatment at any site will be recorded as an event. Progression free survival will be calculated at 2 years according to the Kaplan Meier methods.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Specific Survival (DSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The trial subjects will be followed for vital statistics (dead or alive) from the time enrolled in the trial. Any deaths that is caused by the index cancer will count as an event. DSS will be calculated with intention to treat analysis according to the Kaplan Meier methods at 5 years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The trial subjects will be followed for vital statistics (dead or alive) from the time of enrolment. Death from any cause will be counted as an event. Overall survival will be calculated according to the Kaplan Meier methods at years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General Quality of Life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported general quality of life outcome will be measured according to The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) general quality of life questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) at 3 month, 6 months, and 12 months following the completion of treatment. These questionnaires are validated and an integrated system for assessing the quality of life (QoL) of cancer patients participating in clinical trials. Outcome score for functional scales at 12 months will be compared to pretreatment levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Head and Neck Specific Quality of Life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported quality of life outcome will be measured according to EORTC head and neck specific questionnaire (QLQ-H&amp;N35) prior to trial treatment (baseline), at 3 month, 6 months, and 12 months following the completion of treatment. These questionnaires are validated and an integrated system for assessing the quality of life (QoL) of head and neck cancer patients participating in clinical trials. Outcomes for symptom scales in H&amp;N-35 at 12 months will be compared to pretreatment levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Oropharynx Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Tonsil Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Throat Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Base of the Tongue Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel and Cisplatin x 3 cycles followed by Transoral robotic surgery and neck dissection.
Carboplatin may be used instead of Cisplatin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be treated with neoadjuvant docetaxel and cisplatin for 3 cycles. This is followed by transoral robotic surgery (TORS) and neck dissection as definitive treatment, reserving radiotherapy for salvage.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy and surgery</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cisplatin, Transoral robotic surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Squamous cell cancer of oropharynx, p 16 positive

          -  American Joint Commission on Cancer version-7 (AJCC-7) Stage III (T1N1, T2N1, T3N0,
             T3N1) and stage IVa (T1N2, T2N2, T3N2)

          -  Treatment Naive

          -  No evidence of distant metastatic disease

          -  Fit for surgery, and primary tumor assessed surgically resectable with negative
             margins via transoral approach

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Karnofsky performance status &gt; 60% or Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) &lt; 2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 2,000, platelets &gt; 100,000 and calculated creatinine
             clearance &gt; 50 cc/min

          -  Signed study specific consent form

          -  No other malignancies except cutaneous basal cell carcinoma (BCC) or squamous cell
             carcinoma (SCC) within the last 5 years

          -  Agree to use effective contraception while on the study. Women of child bearing
             potential must have a negative pregnancy test, and not be lactating.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with advanced T4 cancer unresectable without organ preservation

          -  P16 negative tumor

          -  N3 disease (Stage IVB AJCC-7)

          -  5 or more positive cervical lymph nodes at presentation

          -  Distant metastatic disease (Stage IVC)

          -  Radiological evidence of gross extracapsular nodal tumor invasion

          -  Anatomy not allowing transoral access and exposure

          -  Prior head and neck cancer at any time (Other than BCC or SCC of skin)

          -  Coexistent second malignancy or history within 5 years of prior malignancy (other than
             BCC or early SCC skin or curatively treated Stage I carcinoma of cervix)

          -  Peripheral neuropathy &gt;/= grade 1

          -  Have had prior Taxanes or Cisplatin

          -  Concurrent infection

          -  Coexisting medical illness of a severity that might interfere with treatment or
             follow-up, or who do not have the ability to give informed consent.

          -  Receiving any other investigational agent while on the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nader Sadeghi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nader Sadeghi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
    <phone_ext>34974</phone_ext>
    <email>nader.sadeghi@mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Beaubien</last_name>
    <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
    <phone_ext>34974</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McGill University Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4A 3J1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nader Sadeghi</last_name>
      <phone>5149341934</phone>
      <phone_ext>34974</phone_ext>
      <email>nader.sadeghi@mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Beaaubien</last_name>
      <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>34974</phone_ext>
      <email>elizabeth.beaubien@muhc.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University Health Centre/Research Institute of the McGill University Health Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nader Sadeghi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oropharynx cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>throat cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>HPV related throat cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>tonsil cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>base of tongue cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tonsillar Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

