<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04272333</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PBI-CEL-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04272333</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intratumoral Microdosing of Motolimod in HNSCC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 0 Study Using the CIVO® Platform to Evaluate Intratumoral Microdoses of Motolimod Singly and in Combination With Nivolumab in Patients With Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Presage Biosciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Presage Biosciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, single arm, open-label, multi-agent, localized pharmacodynamic
      biomarker Phase 0 trial designed to study the biological effects within the tumor
      microenvironment of motolimod and motolimod combined with nivolumab when administered
      intratumorally in microdose quantities via the CIVO device in patients with head and neck
      squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC). CIVO stands for comparative in vivo oncology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CIVO is a research tool composed of a hand-held single-use sterile injector coupled with
      fluorescent tracking microspheres called CIVO GLO that mark the sites of drug microdose
      injection, enabling rapid assessment of multiple oncology drugs or drug combinations
      simultaneously within a patient's tumor. In this Phase 0 intratumoral microdosing study in
      human patients with pathologic diagnosis of HNSCC with at least one lesion (primary,
      recurrent, or effaced metastatic lymph nodes) for which there is a planned surgical
      intervention, we will evaluate motolimod's ability to activate immune effector cells within
      the local tumor microenvironment. Additionally, this study will examine motolimod in
      combination with nivolumab to study whether motolimod enhances the localized immune responses
      compared to those of either immunotherapy alone. Motolimod singly and in combination with
      nivolumab will be delivered intratumorally in subtherapeutic microdose quantities via CIVO.

      The CIVO device percutaneously penetrates solid tumors and delivers subtherapeutic microdoses
      of up to eight anti-cancer agents or combinations of anti-cancer agents co-injected with CIVO
      GLO into discrete regions of the tumor. At the time of the planned surgical intervention (at
      least four hours to up to four days after the CIVO microdose injection), the injected tumor
      tissue is then excised and tumor responses are assessed via histological staining of tumor
      cross-sections sampled perpendicular to each injection column. Co-injection with CIVO GLO
      enables identification of each injection site during resection as well as in tissues stained
      for analysis. Because the platform delivers microdose amounts of each test agent or
      combination directly into the patient's tumor tissue, hypotheses can be tested earlier in the
      drug development process, consistent with the goals of the 2006 FDA Exploratory IND Guidance
      for Industry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantification of Cell Death and Immune Cell Biomarkers by Immunohistochemistry (IHC) and In-Situ Hybridization (ISH) in Resected Tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours-4 days after microdose injection</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification of biomarker-positive and biomarker-negative cells will be performed within the tumor microenvironment around each of the injection sites of each resected patient sample by IHC and ISH. An aggregate analysis of this quantification may be done across patient samples to evaluate trends in tumor response. List of biomarkers evaluated may include biomarkers for cell death (e.g. cleaved caspase 3), T-cells (e.g. CD3, CD8/Granzyme B), and natural killer (NK)/myeloid cells (e.g. CD56/Granzyme B, CD86, CD68, CD163).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days after microdose injection</time_frame>
    <description>Relationship of AE to study drug or CIVO device will be determined using an AE Relatedness Grading System.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>HNSCC</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CIVO Microdose Injection of Motolimod and Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who are scheduled for surgical biopsy or tumor resection surgery will be injected at least four hours to up to four days prior to surgery using the CIVO device. Each needle of the CIVO device will deliver up to 8.3 microliters of solution, including a vehicle control (sterile saline) or subtherapeutic microdoses of motolimod, nivolumab, or motolimod combined with nivolumab. Each microdose is simultaneously and percutaneously injected in a columnar fashion through each of 8, 5, or 3 needles (in a device configuration determined by tumor dimensions) into a single solid tumor or effaced metastatic lymph node.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motolimod</intervention_name>
    <description>Intratumoral microdose injection by the CIVO device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CIVO Microdose Injection of Motolimod and Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VTX2337</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Intratumoral microdose injection by the CIVO device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CIVO Microdose Injection of Motolimod and Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motolimod + Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Intratumoral microdose injection by the CIVO device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CIVO Microdose Injection of Motolimod and Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Ability and willingness to comply with the study's visit and assessment schedule.

          2. Male or female ≥ 18 years of age at Visit 1 (Screening).

          3. Pathologic diagnosis of HNSCC.

          4. Ability and willingness to provide written informed consent. Voluntary written consent
             must be given before performance of any study related procedure not part of standard
             medical care, with the understanding that consent may be withdrawn by the patient at
             any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          5. At least one lesion (primary or recurrent tumor) ≥ 2 cm in the shortest diameter that
             is accessible for ultrasound-guided percutaneous CIVO injection and for which there is
             a planned surgical intervention. An effaced metastatic lymph node may only be selected
             with prior Sponsor approval. Treatment plan may include adjuvant radiation or
             chemotherapy, and subjects should have no medical contraindication to surgery.

          6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2.

          7. Female patients who :

               -  Are postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., have not had menses
                  at any time during the preceding 24 consecutive months), OR

               -  Are surgically sterile, OR

               -  Are of childbearing potential (FCBP) who agree to true abstinence from
                  heterosexual intercourse (which must be source documented) or to use a highly
                  effective contraceptive method (e.g., combined [containing estrogen and
                  progestogen] or progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with
                  inhibition of ovulation [oral, injectable, intravaginal, patch, or implantable];
                  bilateral tubal ligation; intrauterine device; intrauterine hormone-releasing
                  system; or vasectomized partner sterilization [note that vasectomized partner is
                  a highly effective birth control method provided that partner is the sole sexual
                  partner of the FCBP trial participant and that the vasectomized partner has
                  received medical assessment of the surgical success]) from the time of signing
                  the Informed Consent Form (ICF) and during study participation.

               -  Agree to refrain from donating ova during study participation.

        Male patients who:

          -  Agree to practice true abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or agree to use a
             condom (a latex condom is recommended) during sexual contact with a pregnant female or
             a FCBP from the time of signing the ICF and while participating in the study, even if
             he has undergone a successful vasectomy.

          -  Agree to refrain from donating sperm during study participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Tumors or effaced nodes that are anticipated by the Investigator to lack a sufficient
             volume of viable tumor tissue (based on available pre-operative imaging, pre-injection
             ultrasound imaging, or pathology reports) for CIVO injection due to size, location,
             necrosis, cysts, excessive stroma, fibrosis, or treatment-induced tissue changes.
             Lesions that have received neoadjuvant radiation therapy may lack sufficient viable
             tumor tissue for CIVO injection procedures.

          2. Tumors near or involving critical structures for which, in the opinion of the treating
             clinician, injection would pose undue risk to the patient.

          3. Patients with a diagnosis of nasopharyngeal carcinoma.

          4. Female patients who are:

               -  Both lactating and breastfeeding, OR

               -  Have a positive urine β-subunit of human chorionic gonadotropin (β-hCG) pregnancy
                  test at screening verified by the Investigator.

          5. Any uncontrolled intercurrent illness, condition, serious medical or psychiatric
             illness, or circumstance that, in the opinion of the Investigator, could interfere
             with adherence to the study's procedures or requirements, or otherwise compromise the
             study's objectives.

          6. Patients with a history of concurrent second cancers requiring active, ongoing
             systemic treatment.

          7. Patients with active autoimmune diseases requiring treatment.

          8. Patients with known human immunodeficiency virus/acquired immune deficiency syndrome
             (HIV/AIDS) with uncontrolled viral load and CD4 less than 200, or known chronic
             hepatitis B/C.

          9. Patients that have received a live vaccine within 4 weeks of the baseline/screening
             visit.

         10. Use of any of the following ≤ 2 weeks prior to CIVO injection :

               1. Chronic systemic immunosuppressive therapy or corticosteroids (e.g., prednisone
                  or equivalent exceeding a total dose of 140 mg over the last 14 days).
                  Intranasal, inhaled, topical, or local corticosteroid injections (e.g.,
                  intra-articular injection), or steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity
                  reactions (e.g., computed tomography [CT] scan premedication) are exceptions to
                  this criterion.

               2. Biological response modifiers for treatment of active autoimmune disease.

               3. Hematopoietic growth factors.

               4. Anticoagulants such as warfarin or low-molecular-weight heparin.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Presage Biosciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Presage Biosciences</last_name>
    <phone>800-530-5404</phone>
    <email>clinops@presagebio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://presagebio.com/</url>
    <description>Presage Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klinghoffer RA, Bahrami SB, Hatton BA, Frazier JP, Moreno-Gonzalez A, Strand AD, Kerwin WS, Casalini JR, Thirstrup DJ, You S, Morris SM, Watts KL, Veiseh M, Grenley MO, Tretyak I, Dey J, Carleton M, Beirne E, Pedro KD, Ditzler SH, Girard EJ, Deckwerth TL, Bertout JA, Meleo KA, Filvaroff EH, Chopra R, Press OW, Olson JM. A technology platform to assess multiple cancer agents simultaneously within a patient's tumor. Sci Transl Med. 2015 Apr 22;7(284):284ra58. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.aaa7489.</citation>
    <PMID>25904742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frazier JP, Bertout JA, Kerwin WS, Moreno-Gonzalez A, Casalini JR, Grenley MO, Beirne E, Watts KL, Keener A, Thirstrup DJ, Tretyak I, Ditzler SH, Tripp CD, Choy K, Gillings S, Breit MN, Meleo KA, Rizzo V, Herrera CL, Perry JA, Amaravadi RK, Olson JM, Klinghoffer RA. Multidrug Analyses in Patients Distinguish Efficacious Cancer Agents Based on Both Tumor Cell Killing and Immunomodulation. Cancer Res. 2017 Jun 1;77(11):2869-2880. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-17-0084. Epub 2017 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28364003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dey J, Kerwin WS, Grenley MO, Casalini JR, Tretyak I, Ditzler SH, Thirstrup DJ, Frazier JP, Pierce DW, Carleton M, Klinghoffer RA. A Platform for Rapid, Quantitative Assessment of Multiple Drug Combinations Simultaneously in Solid Tumors In Vivo. PLoS One. 2016 Jun 30;11(6):e0158617. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0158617. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27359113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno-Gonzalez A, Olson JM, Klinghoffer RA. Predicting responses to chemotherapy in the context that matters - the patient. Mol Cell Oncol. 2015 Jun 10;3(1):e1057315. doi: 10.1080/23723556.2015.1057315. eCollection 2016 Jan.</citation>
    <PMID>27308571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>precision oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>intratumoral microdosing</keyword>
  <keyword>microdose injection</keyword>
  <keyword>microdosing</keyword>
  <keyword>in vivo oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>in vivo drug sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>tumor microenvironment</keyword>
  <keyword>multiplexed immunohistochemistry</keyword>
  <keyword>head and neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>SCCHN</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacodynamic biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>CIVO</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Head and Neck</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

