<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04429321</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>843082</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04429321</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nivolumab + Ipilimumab With Immunostimulatory Embolization for Stage 4 Renal Cell Carcinoma With Unresected Primary</brief_title>
  <official_title>UPCC06820 Phase 1 Trial of Nivolumab + Ipilimumab With Immunostimulatory Embolization for Stage 4 Renal Cell Carcinoma With Unresected Primary</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This single center phase 1 trial will study the combination of nivolumab+ipilimumab with
      embolization in participants with renal cell carcinoma. The study will evaluate the safety of
      embolotherapy in patients with metastatic RCC receiving nivolumab+ipilimumab. The hypothesis
      is that the number of serious adverse events will be no greater than the number of serious
      adverse events for both therapies combined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previously untreated subjects with stage 4 RCC and unresected primary tumor will undergo two
      cycles of combination immune checkpoint inhibition (ICI) therapy, embolization of the primary
      tumor, then resume ICI therapy. Study ends with safety and efficacy assessment at 6 months.
      Correlative blood and tissue specimens will be obtained.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Serious adverse events will be recorded from time of informed to consent to 100 days after the end of study intervention</time_frame>
    <description>SAE rate following embolization in patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from baseline to 6 months post initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate by RECIST 1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 12 weeks post initiation of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Characterization of tumor-infiltrating leukocytes in primary and metastatic lesions before and after embolotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD-L1</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 12 weeks post initiation of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of PD-L1 stain positivity in the primary tumor biopsy of participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma Stage IV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab +Nivolumab with Embolization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ICI therapy with Nivolumab 3 mg/kg + ipilimumab 1/mg/kg IV every 3 weeks x 4 cycles, followed by nivolumab 3 mg/kg IV every four weeks for a total of 6 months of therapy unless stopped for confirmed progression or intolerable toxicities.
Patients will receive 2 cycles of systemic therapy followed by Lipiodol:ethanol embolization of their primary tumor and continue systemic therapy subsequently.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Nivolumab 3 mg/kg IV every four weeks, first in combination with capecitabine then alone</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab +Nivolumab with Embolization</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>ipilimumab 1/mg/kg IV every 3 weeks x 4 cycles, in combination with Nivolumab</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab +Nivolumab with Embolization</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yervoy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bland embolization</intervention_name>
    <description>Lipiodol:ethanol embolization of their primary tumor</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab +Nivolumab with Embolization</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>trans-arterial embolization</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Metastatic renal cell carcinoma with unresected primary tumor

          2. No prior immune checkpoint therapy

          3. Primary tumor amenable to percutaneous embolization

          4. Additional metastatic site &gt; 1 cm assessable for response by RECIST 1.1

          5. Adequate organ function by screening laboratory studies within 30 days of embolization

               -  platelets &gt; 50K, correctable by transfusion

               -  INR &lt; 1.5, correctable by transfusion

               -  creatinine &lt; 2.0

          6. ECOG performance status 0-2

          7. Age ≥ 18 years

          8. Have signed the current approved informed consent form and be willing and able to
             comply with this protocol

          9. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must use appropriate method(s) of
             contraception. WOCBP should use an adequate method to avoid pregnancy for 5 months
             after the last dose of study drug

         10. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test

         11. Men who are sexually active with WOCBP must use any contraceptive method with a
             failure rate of less than 1% per year Men receiving nivolumab and who are sexually
             active with WOCBP will be instructed to adhere to contraception for a period of 7
             months after the last dose

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. CNS metastasis

          2. Autoimmune disorder; subjects are permitted to enroll if they have vitiligo, type I
             diabetes mellitus, residual hypothyroidism due to autoimmune condition only requiring
             hormone replacement, psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment

          3. Immunodeficiency syndrome

          4. Glucocorticoid (&gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents) or immunosuppressant therapy

          5. Active infection requiring systemic therapy

          6. Any other medical or personal condition that, in the opinion of the site investigator,
             may potentially compromise the safety or compliance of the patient, or may preclude
             the patient's successful completion of the clinical trial.

          7. Positive test for hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBV sAg) or hepatitis C virus
             ribonucleic acid (HCV antibody) indicating acute or chronic infection

          8. Known history of testing positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or known
             acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)

          9. Contrast allergy not mitigated by usual prophylaxis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michale Soulen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Soulen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>855-216-0098</phone>
    <email>michael.soulen@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motzer RJ, Tannir NM, McDermott DF, Arén Frontera O, Melichar B, Choueiri TK, Plimack ER, Barthélémy P, Porta C, George S, Powles T, Donskov F, Neiman V, Kollmannsberger CK, Salman P, Gurney H, Hawkins R, Ravaud A, Grimm MO, Bracarda S, Barrios CH, Tomita Y, Castellano D, Rini BI, Chen AC, Mekan S, McHenry MB, Wind-Rotolo M, Doan J, Sharma P, Hammers HJ, Escudier B; CheckMate 214 Investigators. Nivolumab plus Ipilimumab versus Sunitinib in Advanced Renal-Cell Carcinoma. N Engl J Med. 2018 Apr 5;378(14):1277-1290. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1712126. Epub 2018 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29562145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zielinski H, Szmigielski S, Petrovich Z. Comparison of preoperative embolization followed by radical nephrectomy with radical nephrectomy alone for renal cell carcinoma. Am J Clin Oncol. 2000 Feb;23(1):6-12.</citation>
    <PMID>10683065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swanson DA, Wallace S. Surgery of metastatic renal cell carcinoma and use of renal infarction. Semin Surg Oncol. 1988;4(2):124-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3293153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sabel MS. Cryo-immunology: a review of the literature and proposed mechanisms for stimulatory versus suppressive immune responses. Cryobiology. 2009 Feb;58(1):1-11. doi: 10.1016/j.cryobiol.2008.10.126. Epub 2008 Oct 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19007768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>den Brok MH, Sutmuller RP, Nierkens S, Bennink EJ, Frielink C, Toonen LW, Boerman OC, Figdor CG, Ruers TJ, Adema GJ. Efficient loading of dendritic cells following cryo and radiofrequency ablation in combination with immune modulation induces anti-tumour immunity. Br J Cancer. 2006 Oct 9;95(7):896-905. Epub 2006 Sep 5.</citation>
    <PMID>16953240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehta A, Oklu R, Sheth RA. Thermal Ablative Therapies and Immune Checkpoint Modulation: Can Locoregional Approaches Effect a Systemic Response? Gastroenterol Res Pract. 2016;2016:9251375. doi: 10.1155/2016/9251375. Epub 2016 Mar 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27051417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kato T, Iwasaki T, Uemura M, Nagahara A, Higashihara H, Osuga K, Ikeda Y, Kiyotani K, Park JH, Nonomura N, Nakamura Y. Characterization of the cryoablation-induced immune response in kidney cancer patients. Oncoimmunology. 2017 May 16;6(7):e1326441. doi: 10.1080/2162402X.2017.1326441. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28811963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ipilimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

