<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04420949</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-0632</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>A176000</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EDUC/KINESIOLOGY</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Protocol Version 5/1/2020</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04420949</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sensory Training for Visual Motion Sickness</brief_title>
  <official_title>High-precision Immersive Robotic Environment for Sensorimotor Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a preliminary study to determine the reliability and validity of new tests of
      orientation and balance, as well as to test the effects of a new treatment for visually
      induced dizziness. Tests involve determining vertical alignment. The treatment is task-based
      and involves focusing attention on internal body sensations to help improve the sense of
      upright. Testing is done twice before and twice after treatment, which is provided
      twice-weekly during a three-week period between testing. The total time participants are
      involved in the study is approximately six weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Falls are a major concern for people living in countries all over the world. Tens of millions
      of people who fall are seriously injured and hundreds of thousands of people who fall die
      every year. People who are dizzy are far more likely to fall. The investigators are
      particularly interested in working with people who have dizziness that is caused by watching
      motion or looking at complex patterns (e.g. checkerboard patterns, walking through grocery
      store aisles, riding in vehicles, or watching movies).

      This type of dizziness or vertigo is typically described as motion sickness or, more
      specifically, visually-induced dizziness. This problem affects adults who are healthy and
      adults who have a variety of health conditions. No diagnostic tests for this condition exist
      at this time and the treatments currently being used may result in worsening dizziness for
      some patients.

      New tests were created for orientation and balance, as well as a new treatment for
      visually-induced dizziness. This is a preliminary study of the reliability and validity of
      the tests we developed, as well as whether the new treatment created results in reduced
      dizziness, improved balance, and changes in daily functioning.

      It is not known whether the new tests of orientation and balance are better, worse, or the
      same as existing tests in the ability to detect problems, nor is it known if the new
      treatment technique is any better, worse, or the same as existing treatments for dizziness
      and imbalance. It is hypothesized that the new tests will be accurate and able to detect
      problems in impaired adults. Additionally, that the treatment will result in less dizziness,
      better balance, and reduced risk of falling.

      The plan is to enroll a total of 30 people in this study, 15 who are healthy and 15 who have
      visually-induced dizziness due to a vestibular (inner ear) problem. Each participant will
      complete several questionnaires and tests of balance performance before and after undergoing
      the treatment. Participants attend 8 visits over 6 weeks. Each study visit lasts
      approximately 60 minutes.

      During visits 1 and 2, which is a double baseline phase, the reliability and validity of the
      new testing procedures will be assessed. All participants will then enter the treatment phase
      (visits 2 through 7) and will attend twice-weekly appointments for three consecutive weeks.
      Following the treatment phase, participants will be re-assessed twice, immediately after
      (visit 7) and one week after (visit 8) completing treatment. During this phase, the
      short-term effectiveness of the treatment will be assessed.

      Participants will complete questionnaires that measure the intensity of visually-induced
      dizziness, perceived handicap due to dizziness, and the impact of dizziness on daily
      functioning. Performance measures include the ability to determine what is upright based on
      the internal sense of gravity (verticality), standing upright, and walking-related balance
      tasks. The verticality tests are performed while the participant is secured in a harness and
      are either standing upright or tilted to the left or to the right. The testing task is to
      determine upright based on using internal body sensations. The standing balance test is
      performed on a platform that measures balance. The verticality tests and the standing balance
      test are experimental.

      The treatment is task-based and is performed while the participant is supported in a harness
      and wearing virtual reality goggles. During the treatment, participants are either standing
      upright or tilted to the left or to the right. The treatment involves focusing attention on
      internal body sensations to help determine whether an image that is presented in an otherwise
      black virtual environment is aligned with gravity. Other visual and sound cues will be
      eliminated to prevent the use of these cues from influencing decisions about what is upright.
      As the participant becomes more successful at determining what is upright, the difficulty of
      the treatment task is gradually increased.

      Participants symptoms will be monitored throughout the testing and treatment. Participants
      are given regular rest breaks and may request to rest at any time. Participation is voluntary
      and may be discontinued at any time.

      The investigators anticipate only mild and infrequent side effects related to testing and
      treatment. The results of this study may influence how orientation and balance are assessed
      and how visually-induced dizziness is treated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study will be conducted in three phases. The first phase is for baseline testing. The second phase is when treatment occurs. The third phase is for follow up testing. Participants will be tested twice during the baseline and follow up phases. Six treatment sessions will occur during the treatment phase.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>It is not possible to mask this behavioral intervention. The study team small; thus, masking of the study team is also not possible.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Rod and Disk Test (RDT) Mean Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>An image of a rod will be shown in the central portion of the visual field. The surrounding virtual environment will be void. A batch of rod angles will be predetermined. This assessment will be completed using an Oculus Rift and without any reference to external visual cues. Only binocular testing will be completed. The average value for performance in each position will be used in data analysis. The mean of absolute value of the error in rod alignment measured in degrees for each body position tested will be used as the measurement variable for this outcome. Mean performance in this population is 0.39 (sd 0.8). Higher scores indicate subjective visual vertical alignment that is farther away from earth vertical.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Multisensory Balance Evaluation (MBE) as measured by the Intersection Point Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>This test is designed to assess balance during quiet standing in different sensory conditions. Participants perform one trial (lasting 50 seconds) of each condition. All trials are performed while standing on a force plate with the feet in a self-selected, comfortable position. The force plate samples center of pressure and direction of ground reaction force. The visual environment is controlled using an Oculus Rift. The surface conditions are either non-compliant or compliant. The frequency-dependent height of the Intersection Point (IP) of the ground reaction force is the main outcome. The behavior and shape of the IP curvature will be studied in each test trial. The IP curvature for certain conditions will be compared versus others in order to assess the impact of manipulating specific sensory inputs on the behavior of the IP. The height of the IP at a specific frequency represents how stable a person is during a given test trial. Lower IP height suggests greater stability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Subjective Visual Vertical (SVV) Mean Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>An image of a rod will be shown in the central portion of the visual field. The surrounding virtual environment will be void. A batch of rod angles will be predetermined. This assessment will be completed using an Oculus Rift and without any reference to external visual cues. Only binocular testing will be completed. The average value for performance in each position will be used in data analysis. The mean of absolute value of the error in rod alignment measured in degrees for each body position tested will be used as the measurement variable for this outcome. Mean performance in this population is 0.39 (sd 0.8). Higher scores indicate subjective visual vertical alignment that is farther away from earth vertical.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Rod and Frame Test (RFT) Mean Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>An image of a rod will be projected inside a tilted frame within the central portion of the visual field. The surrounding virtual environment will be void. The frame will be tilted by +/- 20° in the frontal plane. A batch of rod angles will be predetermined. This assessment will be completed using an Oculus Rift and without reference to external visual cues. Only binocular testing will be completed. The average value for performance in each position will be used in data analysis. The mean of absolute value of the error in rod alignment measured in degrees for each body position tested will be used as the measurement variable for this outcome. Mean performance in this population is 6.51 (sd 7.8). Higher values indicate greater deviations of perceived vertical from earth vertical.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Vision-related Dizziness Questionnaire (VRDQ) Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>The VRDQ is used to quantify vision-related dizziness. This outcome measure consists of 25 questions comprising two subscales [frequency and severity of symptoms]. The maximum score for each sub-scale is 100 points. The total score is the average of both sub-scales. Higher scores represent greater frequency and severity of symptoms. Test-retest reliability for the VRDQ is well above the good performance level and convergent validity for the VRDQ was demonstrated with the Dizziness Handicap Inventory (DHI). Spearman correlation coefficients are 0.75 between the DHI and VRDQ frequency scale and 0.76 between the DHI and VRDQ severity scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Dizziness Handicap Inventory (DHI) Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>The DHI is used to assess the severity of self-perceived disability secondary to dizziness. The tool is comprised of 25 questions which are score as yes = 4 points, sometimes = 2 points, and no = 0 points. The total score has a range of 0 to 100 points. The reliability and validity of the DHI have been established.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Activities-specific Balance Confidence Scale (ABCS) Average Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>The ABCS is a measure of balance-related confidence. The scale is made up of 16 questions for which respondents rate their level of perceived confidence in not becoming unsteady or falling. The average score ranges from 0 to 100%. The reliability and validity of the ABCS has been established in adults with and without a history of falling.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Vestibular Activities and Participation Measure (VAPM) Average Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>The VAPM is a 34-item questionnaire that is used to assess the impact of vestibular dysfunction on daily activities and participation in various life roles. The psychometrics for this tool have been established for adults with vestibular disorders. The average score ranges from 0 to 4.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The Vestibular Rehabilitation Benefits Questionnaire (VRBQ) Total Score at the end of the trial</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>The VRBQ was developed to assess outcomes from vestibular rehabilitation. The 22 questions are based on a literature review, participant interviews, and items from other measures. These questions are divided into three sub-scales: dizziness and anxiety (6), motion provoked dizziness (5), and quality of life (11). The total score ranges from 0%-100% and scores &gt; 0% indicate the presence of symptoms, functional loss, or decreased quality of life. See http://www.isvr.soton.ac.uk/audiology/vrbq.htm for more information regarding the scoring methodology. It has been validated against other measures. The VRBQ is designed to measure the difference between the participant's current state of symptoms and quality of life compared to a state that is normal for the individual.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Functional Gait Assessment (FGA) Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>The FGA is a 10-item, observational, test of walking. Score for each item range from 0 to 3 and, thus, the total score ranges from 0 to 30. Use of an assistive device is permitted. Higher scores indicate greater stability during walking. The psychometrics of the FGA have been established for adults with balance disorders.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Walking Speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1 (Week 1), Visit 2 (Week 2), Visit 7 (Week 4), and Visit 8 (Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>Gait speed has been shown to be a reliable and valid measure of functional balance in adults. Gait speed will be recorded during a 10-meter walk test. Participants will walk for 2-meters before entering and after exiting the 6-meter long recording section. A stopwatch will be used for timing.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Dizziness</condition>
  <condition>Vertigo</condition>
  <condition>Motion Sickness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy adults with visually-induced dizziness with undergo the testing and treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vestibular-impaired</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adults with unilateral or bilateral, peripheral vestibular loss who also have visually-induced dizziness with undergo the testing and treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensory re-weighting</intervention_name>
    <description>During training, sensory re-weighting is driven by priming upregulation of somatosensory cues. Two rounds of training, each lasting 15 minutes and block-randomized in sets of 10 trials, are conducted per training visit. In each training trial, participants must determine the direction of gravity and then indicate if the rod being displayed is aligned with gravity or if it needs to rotate clockwise or counterclockwise for that to be so. Participants will be instructed to pay attention to what they feel from their feet, legs, and gut during training and to use that pressure, stretch, movement, and muscle tension feedback to help them sense gravity. Immediate auditory and non-orienting, visual feedback is provided after each trial. A staircase method is used to adapt the level of difficulty based on response accuracy. After two consecutive correct responses, the difficulty increases. After each incorrect response, the difficulty decreases. This process is repeated in each round.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vestibular-impaired</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Healthy Participants:

        Inclusion Criteria: Participants must

          -  have normal self-reported cognitive function

          -  speak English fluently

          -  weigh less than 225 pounds and be less than 6'4&quot;

          -  be able to support their body weight in an upright posture for 15 minutes at a time

          -  be able to follow the guidelines regarding permitted and prohibited additional
             treatments outlined in this protocol

        Exclusion Criteria: Participants must not

          -  be pregnant or planning to become pregnant while in &quot;on study&quot; status

          -  have best-corrected visual acuity &gt; 20/70

          -  have a self-reported, uncompensated, binocular vision abnormality, such as strabismus,
             amblyopia, or diplopia

          -  have peripheral neuropathy

          -  have a self-reported history of frequent syncope (&gt;1/month)

        Participants with Visually-induced Dizziness:

        Inclusion Criteria: Participants must

          -  have self-reported symptoms of visually-induced dizziness

          -  have normal self-reported cognitive function

          -  speak English fluently

          -  weigh less than 225 pounds and be less than 6'4&quot;

          -  be able to support their body weight in an upright posture for 15 minutes at a time

          -  be able to follow the guidelines regarding permitted and prohibited additional
             treatments outlined in this protocol

        Exclusion Criteria: Participants must not

          -  be participating in vestibular and balance rehabilitation therapy and/or be pregnant
             or planning to become pregnant while in &quot;on study&quot; status

          -  have best-corrected visual acuity &gt; 20/70

          -  have a self-reported, uncompensated, binocular vision abnormality, such as strabismus,
             amblyopia, or diplopia

          -  have peripheral neuropathy, and/or 5) have a self-reported history of frequent syncope
             (&gt;1/month)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Colin R Grove, DPT</last_name>
    <phone>6082638412</phone>
    <email>crgrove@wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kreg G Gruben, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6082622711</phone>
    <email>kreg.g.gruben@wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Colin R Grove, DPT</last_name>
      <phone>608-263-8412</phone>
      <email>crgrove@wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kreg G Gruben, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>6082622711</phone>
      <email>kreg.g.gruben@wisc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kreg G Gruben, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colin R Grove, DPT</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>G M Pyle, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bryan C Heiderscheit, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ari Rosenberg, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan L Whitney, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>verticality</keyword>
  <keyword>postural balance</keyword>
  <keyword>visual dependence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vertigo</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dizziness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motion Sickness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is not plan to share individual participant data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

