<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04427150</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HKBU 12604418</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04427150</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Affective Prosody Recognition and Auditory Intervention for Children With Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Examining Affective Prosody Recognition Among Children With Autism Spectrum Disorders and the Effectiveness of an Auditory Intervention Using a Mobile App</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hong Kong Baptist University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Education University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hong Kong Baptist University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study aims to examine the abilities of children with ASD to recognize emotional
      tones of voice - also known as affective prosody - as compared to typically developing (TD)
      children. Past findings are mixed, and although some studies have found intact performance
      among individuals with ASD, it is possible that they rely on different underlying mechanisms
      in processing affective prosody compared to TD children. Our second objective is therefore to
      examine whether children with ASD have a stronger reliance on psychoacoustic abilities -
      including rapid auditory processing and pitch direction recognition - to identify emotional
      stimuli, as compared to TD children. Lastly, the investigators will study whether auditory
      training targeting psychoacoustic abilities would improve affective prosody recognition among
      children with ASD. Forty children with ASD and 40 TD children between 10 to 12 years old will
      be recruited. Participants' psychoacoustic abilities and affective prosody recognition will
      be assessed in the pretest. The investigators hypothesize that psychoacoustic abilities are
      stronger predictors of affective prosody recognition among children with ASD than among TD
      children. The ASD children will then be randomly assigned to two groups: one group will
      receive auditory training; the other will be an active control group that receives
      non-auditory training. Both groups will receive 12 hours of training via a mobile app. The
      children will be assessed again in the posttest.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will sign an informed consent statement prior to arriving at the lab.
      Participants with ASD will be randomly assigned into either the auditory training group
      (Group 1) or the active control group (Group 2). Participants without ASD will be assigned to
      the typically developed group (Group 3). Groups 1 and 2 will complete all stages of the
      study, whereas Group 3 will only complete the pre-test stage.

      Pre-test: Researchers will assess participants' affective prosody recognition ability and
      psychoacoustic ability. The tests will be conducted in a sound attenuated lab located at Hong
      Kong Baptist University. The tests include an affective prosody recognition test, a pitch
      discrimination recognition test, a rapid auditory processing test, and a theory of mind test.

      Intervention Training: Participants will be required to partake in an intervention training
      program. The program will adopt training exercises provided by Posit Science - BrainHQ. The
      participants will be asked to complete a training session of 15-30 minutes each day for 8-12
      weeks, arriving at a total of at least 12 hours of training. The progress of intervention
      training will be closely monitored by the research team.

      Post-test: Participant will be asked to return to the lab for post-test assessment of the
      same tests, and complete an autism assessment (ADOS-2) conducted by a clinical psychologist
      and a non-verbal Intelligence test conducted by a trained researcher.

      Note: For ethical and fairness purposes, participants from Group 2 will be allowed to access
      the intervention training after Post-test.

      To encourage completion of the intervention training program, participants who successfully
      complete 12 hours of training will be offered a monetary reward as a token of appreciation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>60 participants (40 children with autism spectrum disorder and 20 typically developed children) will form three groups: Group 1 will contain 20 children with autism spectrum disorder (randomly selected) whom will partake in psychoacoustic intervention training. Group 2 will contain 20 children with autism spectrum disorder (randomly selected) whom will partake in non-psychoacoustic intervention training. Group 3 will contain 20 typically developed children whom will not partake in any training.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Accuracy of Affective Prosody Recognition</measure>
    <time_frame>Before &amp; after 8-week intervention program</time_frame>
    <description>Measures the change in the participants' ability in identifying emotional tone of words or sentences (sound stimuli). The participant will be tested before intervention and after intervention. For each test, participants will listen to word or sentences, which are pre-recorded by voice actors, then identify the emotional tone (happy, anger, fear, sad, or neutral) of the stimuli by pressing the corresponding keys on the keyboard. The accuracy of response will be used to assess the participants' ability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Ability in Discriminating Pitch Differences</measure>
    <time_frame>Before &amp; after 8-week intervention program</time_frame>
    <description>Measures the change the participants' ability in discriminating the pitch between two tones using the Pitch Discrimination Recognition task. The participant will be tested before intervention and after intervention. For each test, participants will listen to two tones and will be required to identify which tone has the higher pitch. The pitch difference between the two tones will change using a &quot;two-down one-up&quot; mechanism with a step-wise adjustment, which means the pitch difference will decrease every two consecutive correct responses or increase for every incorrect response. For every reversal (change from decrease to increase or vice versa) of stimuli, the latest pitch difference will be recorded. The average pitch difference of the final 8 reversals will be used to assess the participants' pitch discrimination ability. Lesser difference indicate stronger ability in discriminating the pitch between two tones.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Accuracy in Processing Rapid Presentation of Two Tones</measure>
    <time_frame>Before &amp; after 8-week intervention program</time_frame>
    <description>Measures the change in the participants' ability in processing two rapid tones using the Rapid Auditory Processing task. The participant will be tested before intervention and after intervention. Two complex tones with fundamental frequency of 100Hz (Low tone) and 305Hz (High tone), each 75ms in duration, will be used throughout the entire test. For each trial, the participant will listen to two tones at ISI of 4ms, 8ms, or 30ms. The participants will be required to replicate the sequence of High or Low tones in each trial as quickly as possible. The accuracy of replicating the sequence will be used to assess the participants' ability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Training Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 hours of psychoacoustic training over 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Other Training Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 hours of non-psychoacoustic training over 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TD Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Auditory Training</intervention_name>
    <description>A series of psychoacoustic training exercises through Posit Science - BrainHQ (mobile app or web-browser version). Each training is approximately 2 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Auditory Training Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-auditory training</intervention_name>
    <description>A series of non-psychoacoustic training exercises through Posit Science - BrainHQ (mobile app or web-browser version). Each training is approximately 2 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Other Training Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cantonese as mother language

          -  IQ &gt; 70

          -  Children with autism spectrum disorder

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children diagnosed with dyslexia

          -  Prior diagnosis of mental disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann M Lui, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hong Kong Baptist University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ann M Lui, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+85234115793</phone>
    <email>annlui@hkbu.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashwin C, Baron-Cohen S, Wheelwright S, O'Riordan M, Bullmore ET. Differential activation of the amygdala and the 'social brain' during fearful face-processing in Asperger Syndrome. Neuropsychologia. 2007 Jan 7;45(1):2-14. Epub 2006 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>16806312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baron-Cohen S, Leslie AM, Frith U. Does the autistic child have a &quot;theory of mind&quot;? Cognition. 1985 Oct;21(1):37-46.</citation>
    <PMID>2934210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonnel A, Mottron L, Peretz I, Trudel M, Gallun E, Bonnel AM. Enhanced pitch sensitivity in individuals with autism: a signal detection analysis. J Cogn Neurosci. 2003 Feb 15;15(2):226-35.</citation>
    <PMID>12676060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boucher J, Lewis V, Collis GM. Voice processing abilities in children with autism, children with specific language impairments, and young typically developing children. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2000 Oct;41(7):847-57.</citation>
    <PMID>11079427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oram Cardy JE, Flagg EJ, Roberts W, Brian J, Roberts TP. Magnetoencephalography identifies rapid temporal processing deficit in autism and language impairment. Neuroreport. 2005 Mar 15;16(4):329-32.</citation>
    <PMID>15729132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castelli F, Happé F, Frith U, Frith C. Movement and mind: a functional imaging study of perception and interpretation of complex intentional movement patterns. Neuroimage. 2000 Sep;12(3):314-25.</citation>
    <PMID>10944414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demopoulos C, Hopkins J, Kopald BE, Paulson K, Doyle L, Andrews WE, Lewine JD. Deficits in auditory processing contribute to impairments in vocal affect recognition in autism spectrum disorders: A MEG study. Neuropsychology. 2015 Nov;29(6):895-908. doi: 10.1037/neu0000209. Epub 2015 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26011112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demopoulos C, Lewine JD. Audiometric Profiles in Autism Spectrum Disorders: Does Subclinical Hearing Loss Impact Communication? Autism Res. 2016 Jan;9(1):107-20. doi: 10.1002/aur.1495. Epub 2015 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25962745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devine RT, Hughes C. Silent films and strange stories: theory of mind, gender, and social experiences in middle childhood. Child Dev. 2013 May-Jun;84(3):989-1003. doi: 10.1111/cdev.12017. Epub 2012 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23199139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaab N, Gabrieli JD, Deutsch GK, Tallal P, Temple E. Neural correlates of rapid auditory processing are disrupted in children with developmental dyslexia and ameliorated with training: an fMRI study. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2007;25(3-4):295-310.</citation>
    <PMID>17943007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gebauer L, Skewes J, Hørlyck L, Vuust P. Atypical perception of affective prosody in Autism Spectrum Disorder. Neuroimage Clin. 2014 Oct 5;6:370-8. doi: 10.1016/j.nicl.2014.08.025. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25379450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Globerson E, Amir N, Kishon-Rabin L, Golan O. Prosody recognition in adults with high-functioning autism spectrum disorders: from psychoacoustics to cognition. Autism Res. 2015 Apr;8(2):153-63. doi: 10.1002/aur.1432. Epub 2014 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25428545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Golan O, Baron-Cohen S, Hill JJ, Golan Y. The &quot;reading the mind in films&quot; task: complex emotion recognition in adults with and without autism spectrum conditions. Soc Neurosci. 2006;1(2):111-23. doi: 10.1080/17470910600980986.</citation>
    <PMID>18633780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grossman RB, Tager-Flusberg H. &quot;Who said that?&quot; Matching of low- and high-intensity emotional prosody to facial expressions by adolescents with ASD. J Autism Dev Disord. 2012 Dec;42(12):2546-57. doi: 10.1007/s10803-012-1511-2.</citation>
    <PMID>22450703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hudepohl MB, Robins DL, King TZ, Henrich CC. The role of emotion perception in adaptive functioning of people with autism spectrum disorders. Autism. 2015 Jan;19(1):107-12. doi: 10.1177/1362361313512725. Epub 2013 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24335115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones CR, Happé F, Baird G, Simonoff E, Marsden AJ, Tregay J, Phillips RJ, Goswami U, Thomson JM, Charman T. Auditory discrimination and auditory sensory behaviours in autism spectrum disorders. Neuropsychologia. 2009 Nov;47(13):2850-8. doi: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2009.06.015. Epub 2009 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19545576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamio Y, Inada N, Koyama T. A nationwide survey on quality of life and associated factors of adults with high-functioning autism spectrum disorders. Autism. 2013 Jan;17(1):15-26. doi: 10.1177/1362361312436848. Epub 2012 Mar 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22399449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones CR, Pickles A, Falcaro M, Marsden AJ, Happé F, Scott SK, Sauter D, Tregay J, Phillips RJ, Baird G, Simonoff E, Charman T. A multimodal approach to emotion recognition ability in autism spectrum disorders. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2011 Mar;52(3):275-85. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02328.x. Epub 2010 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>20955187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kargas N, López B, Reddy V, Morris P. The relationship between auditory processing and restricted, repetitive behaviors in adults with autism spectrum disorders. J Autism Dev Disord. 2015 Mar;45(3):658-68. doi: 10.1007/s10803-014-2219-2.</citation>
    <PMID>25178987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>LaCava PG, Rankin A, Mahlios E, Cook K, Simpson RL. A single case design evaluation of a software and tutor intervention addressing emotion recognition and social interaction in four boys with ASD. Autism. 2010 May;14(3):161-78. doi: 10.1177/1362361310362085. Epub 2010 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20488823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lerner MD, McPartland JC, Morris JP. Multimodal emotion processing in autism spectrum disorders: an event-related potential study. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2013 Jan;3:11-21. doi: 10.1016/j.dcn.2012.08.005. Epub 2012 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23245216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levitt H. Transformed up-down methods in psychoacoustics. J Acoust Soc Am. 1971 Feb;49(2):Suppl 2:467+.</citation>
    <PMID>5541744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindner JL, Rosén LA. Decoding of emotion through facial expression, prosody and verbal content in children and adolescents with Asperger's syndrome. J Autism Dev Disord. 2006 Aug;36(6):769-77.</citation>
    <PMID>16639533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lyons M, Schoen Simmons E, Paul R. Prosodic development in middle childhood and adolescence in high-functioning autism. Autism Res. 2014 Apr;7(2):181-96. doi: 10.1002/aur.1355. Epub 2014 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24634421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marshall CM, Snowling MJ, Bailey PJ. Rapid auditory processing and phonological ability in normal readers and readers with dyslexia. J Speech Lang Hear Res. 2001 Aug;44(4):925-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11521783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moors A, De Houwer J. Automaticity: a theoretical and conceptual analysis. Psychol Bull. 2006 Mar;132(2):297-326.</citation>
    <PMID>16536645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramdoss S, Machalicek W, Rispoli M, Mulloy A, Lang R, O'Reilly M. Computer-based interventions to improve social and emotional skills in individuals with autism spectrum disorders: a systematic review. Dev Neurorehabil. 2012;15(2):119-35. doi: 10.3109/17518423.2011.651655. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22494084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor LJ, Maybery MT, Grayndler L, Whitehouse AJ. Evidence for shared deficits in identifying emotions from faces and from voices in autism spectrum disorders and specific language impairment. Int J Lang Commun Disord. 2015 Jul;50(4):452-66. doi: 10.1111/1460-6984.12146. Epub 2015 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25588870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rutherford MD, Baron-Cohen S, Wheelwright S. Reading the mind in the voice: a study with normal adults and adults with Asperger syndrome and high functioning autism. J Autism Dev Disord. 2002 Jun;32(3):189-94.</citation>
    <PMID>12108620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santos A, Joly-Pottuz B, Moreno S, Habib M, Besson M. Behavioural and event-related potentials evidence for pitch discrimination deficits in dyslexic children: improvement after intensive phonic intervention. Neuropsychologia. 2007 Mar 14;45(5):1080-90. Epub 2006 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>17140611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schirmer A, Kotz SA. Beyond the right hemisphere: brain mechanisms mediating vocal emotional processing. Trends Cogn Sci. 2006 Jan;10(1):24-30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16321562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart ME, McAdam C, Ota M, Peppé S, Cleland J. Emotional recognition in autism spectrum conditions from voices and faces. Autism. 2013 Jan;17(1):6-14. doi: 10.1177/1362361311424572. Epub 2012 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23045218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiethoff S, Wildgruber D, Kreifelts B, Becker H, Herbert C, Grodd W, Ethofer T. Cerebral processing of emotional prosody--influence of acoustic parameters and arousal. Neuroimage. 2008 Jan 15;39(2):885-93. Epub 2007 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>17964813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hong Kong Baptist University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ming Lui</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymous individual participant data will be uploaded to an publicly accessible database should the results were published as a journal article.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be provided when a journal article is published for indefinite time</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access to the data will be made public. The link to the database will be provided in the journal article.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

