<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04426812</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RHINO ID 2019-0651</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01AT010402-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04426812</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Measuring Chronic Pain Impact: Measurement Enhancement for Chronic Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Measuring Chronic Pain Impact</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RAND</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RAND</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many complementary and integrative health approaches have been shown to be effective for
      chronic pain and included in guidelines. This evidence of effectiveness is built on hundreds
      of studies representing millions of research dollars, and the ability to analyze and better
      compare results across these studies is essential to obtain the full value of this
      investment. However, useful across-study comparisons which would allow better understanding
      and targeting of these interventions are hampered by at least two challenges: the lack of
      common outcome measures and the inability to meaningfully stratify or classify patients.

      The first two Aims of this study each address one of these two challenges. The last Aim takes
      advantage of this study to further test the viability of MTurk as a data collection platform.

      Specific Aim 1 addresses the lack of common outcome measures. This Aim is to develop and
      evaluate links or crosswalks between the PROMIS-29 and other common (legacy) measures used
      for chronic pain so that the results of studies using different measures can be compared. Our
      hypothesis here is that we will be able to create some sort of linkage between PROMIS and
      legacy measures that will allow for each pair estimates of one to be made from the other.

      Specific Aim 2 addresses the inability to meaningfully stratify or subclassify chronic pain
      patients. This Aim is to evaluate and refine the chronic pain impact stratification scheme
      (ISS) proposes by the NIH Research Task Force on chronic low back pain, which is based on 9
      PROMIS-29 items. Our hypothesis here is that the ISS can be refined so that it can identify
      subgroups of chronic pain patients with different levels of morbidity and different needs for
      treatment.

      Specific Aim 3 addresses the potential for more efficient data collection using the MTurk
      platform. This Aim is to evaluate MTurk as a cost- and time-efficient method to collect
      quality data on individuals with chronic pain. Our hypothesis here is that we find that MTurk
      produces data of sufficient quality to be of use to future research projects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While there is an extensive literature on the effectiveness of pharmaceutical and
      nonpharmacologic interventions for chronic low back pain (CLBP), it is challenging to
      synthesize the findings because of differences in the CLBP samples and in the outcome
      measures used. The NIH Research Task Force (RTF) on CLBP noted that these differences make it
      &quot;difficult to compare epidemiologic data and studies of similar or competing interventions,
      replicate findings, pool data from multiple studies, resolve conflicting conclusions, develop
      multidisciplinary consensus, or even achieve consensus within a discipline regarding
      interpretation of findings.&quot; To this list we would add that these differences also prevent
      the use of the results to answer questions such as 'Which therapies work best? And for whom?'
      This project tackles two things that are needed to address these differences and allow for
      better cross-study comparisons: we will develop empirical links between different outcome
      measures to allow their expression in similar units (Aim 1), and we will refine the RTF's
      proposed stratification (subgrouping) of patients by the impact of their CLBP (Aim 2).

      To address the first challenge, in Aim 1 this study will develop and evaluate crosswalks or
      links between components of the 29-item Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information
      System (PROMIS®) short form (PROMIS-29) and common legacy measures used for chronic pain. The
      purpose of these crosswalks or links is to allow researchers who measured outcomes using one
      instrument to estimate what the outcome would be if it had been measured using the other
      instrument. In particular, we will create crosswalks/links for the two most commonly used
      instruments used to measure outcomes for CLBP: the Roland-Morris Disability Questionnaire
      (RMDQ) and the Oswestry Disability Index (ODI). In addition, depending on data availability
      and input from our Advisory Council we will create at least two other crosswalks/links
      between the PROMIS-29 and other legacy measures for CLBP (e.g., the Back Pain Functional
      Scale) or legacy measures for other types of chronic pain (e.g., the Neck Disability Index
      for chronic neck pain).

      To address the second challenge, in Aim 2 we will evaluate and refine the chronic pain impact
      stratification scheme proposed by the NIH Research Task Force on chronic low back pain. The
      proposed scheme uses the Impact Stratification Score (ISS) which is calculated using 9 items
      from the PROMIS-29. This ISS was intended to identify and categorize patients with chronic
      pain into groups based on the severity of their condition so that treatment can be better
      targeted. We will first evaluate the ISS and its properties to determine whether they are
      stable across different samples and determine whether they can be improved. After we have
      finalized the components and calculation of the ISS, we will examine its effect on the
      impacts of chronic pain (e.g., health-related quality of life, healthcare utilization, worker
      productivity) to identify meaningful cut-points to use to stratify chronic pain patients into
      subgroups who exhibit different levels of chronic pain impact.

      Three types of data will be used in the analyses to address Aims 1 and 2: data from existing
      datasets built during other studies, data collected from an anonymous national convenience
      sample using Amazon's Mechanical Turk (MTurk) crowdsourcing platform, and data from members
      of the probability-based nationally representative KnowledgePanel. Aim 3 will evaluate
      whether MTurk is a reliable, efficient method to collect data on individuals with chronic
      pain. One part of this evaluation will involve comparison of the results from MTurk to what
      was found using KnowledgePanel.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oswestry Disability Index (ODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline only</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of function for those with chronic back pain; range 0-100; higher is worse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Roland-Morris Disability Questionnaire (RMDQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline only</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of function for those with chronic back pain; range 0-100; higher is worse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact Stratification Score (ISS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline only</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of the level of impact chronic pain has on individual's lives; range 8-50; higher is worse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline only</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of pain intensity; range 0-10; higher is worse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS pain interference</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline only</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of the amount of interference pain causes in life; range 4-20; higher is worse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS physical function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline only</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of the impact of a condition on physical function; range 4-20; higher is worse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Impact Stratification Score (ISS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of the change in the level of impact chronic pain has on individual's lives; range -42 to +42; positive values are a worsening of impact</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MTurk sample</arm_group_label>
    <description>Data collected from a sample of participants in an online convenience platform called MTurk who self-identify as having chronic pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>KnowledgePanel</arm_group_label>
    <description>Data collected from a sample of panel members in an online representative panel called KnowledgePanel who self-identify as having chronic pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention; just data collection</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention; just data collection</description>
    <arm_group_label>KnowledgePanel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MTurk sample</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We have two cohorts. Both will have similar inclusion and exclusion criteria. The first
        from MTurk is a non-probability sample, and the second is from KnowledgePanel and is a
        probability-based sample, but one that has been established by the group who owns this
        panel.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adult

          -  self-described chronic pain

          -  member of one of the panels (MTurk or KnowledgePanel) we are using for data collection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unwillingness to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia M Herman, ND, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>RAND</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patricia M Herman, ND, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>310-393-0411</phone>
    <phone_ext>7129</phone_ext>
    <email>pherman@rand.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ron D Hays, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>310.794.2294</phone>
    <email>drhays@ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We have 3 types of data in this study. The first is using data from existing datasets gathered in other studies. We don't know whether we will be able to get permission to share those data. The second source is the MTurk sample. We hope to share those data and those of the third source KnowledgePanel. However, in each case we are limited by the regulations of those data collection platforms.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

