<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04420481</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Protocol 2003-03-26</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04420481</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Growth Hormone in Ischemic Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Growth Hormone Treatment in Patients With Ischemic Heart Failure and Circulating Levels of NT-proBNP</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Göteborg University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Göteborg University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, we randomly assigned 37 patients (mean age 66
      years; 95% male) with ischemic heart failure (HF) (ejection fraction (EF) &lt; 40%) to a 9-month
      treatment with either recombinant human GH (1.4 mg every other day) or placebo, with
      subsequent 3-month treatment-free follow-up. The primary outcome was change in left
      ventricular (LV) end-systolic volume measured by cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR). Secondary
      outcomes comprised changes in cardiac structure and EF. Prespecified tertiary outcomes
      included changes in New York Heat Association (NYHA) functional class and quality of life
      (QoL), as well as levels of insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) and N-terminal pro-brain
      natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TITLE: GROWTH HORMONE IN HEART FAILURE Addition of recombinant human growth hormone to
      standard heart failure therapy in patients with congestive heart failure due to ischaemic
      heart disease.

      A 12 month study, consisting of a 9 month double-blind, placebo-controlled randomised growth
      hormone treatment phase followed by a 3 month growth hormone treatment-free period.

      STUDY PHASE: III

      COORDINATING CENTRE:

      Endocrine Cardiac Unit (ECU) Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sahlgrenska S-413 45 Göteborg
      Sweden

      STUDY PRODUCT:

      Somatropin, recombinant human growth hormone (rhGH), Saizen® 8 mg (24 IE).

      CONTROL PRODUCT:

      Placebo for Saizen®

      DOSAGE OF STUDY PRODUCT:

      1,4 mg (4,2 IE) every other day.

      DOSAGE:

      9 month treatment period and a 3 month follow-up period. ROUTE OF ADMINISTRATION One
      subcutaneous injection of Saizen® of study product, or corresponding placebo in the thigh or
      abdomen given in the evening given every other day.

      STUDY DESIGN:

      Double-blind (regarding treatment), parallel, placebo-controlled, randomised.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      Female and male patients 75 years of age or below with congestive heart failure (NYHA class
      II or III) due to ischemic heart disease.

      NUMBER OF PATIENTs:

      54 evaluable patients. MULTICENTRE: Yes. NUMBER OF CENTRES: Four

      ALLOCATION OF TREATMENT:

      Randomisation to treatment if all inclusion/exclusion criteria are met.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      To investigate the effect of subcutaneously administered Saizen® compared with placebo on
      left ventricular endsystolic volume by MRI in patients with congestive heart failure due to
      ischaemic heart disease.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVE:

      To determine the effect of Saizen® on enddiastolic volume, left ventricular mass and left
      ventricular ejection fraction

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      To determine the effect of Saizen® on change in NYHA class after 9 months of follow up.

      To determine the effect of Saizen® on circulating levels of IGF-I and IGFBP-3 and to evaluate
      the correlation between changes in IGF-I and the respective changes in left ventricular
      ejection fraction, wall stress and left ventricular mass.

      To evaluate the effect of Saizen® on quality of life by using two different questionnaires
      (Minnesota - Living with Heart Failure and Cardiac Health Profile).

      To determine the effect of Saizen® on neurohormonal activation by measuring NT-proBNP

      SAFETY VARIABLES:

      Hospitalization, morbidity and mortality.

        -  Clinical events, including tendency to fluid retention, glucose intolerance, arrhythmias
           and worsening heart failure.

        -  Electrolytes, haematology, prothrombin complex, parameters for renal and hepatic
           function.

      ADVERSE EVENTS:

      Spontaneously reported from patients and asked for. To be recorded in Case Report Forms
      (CRFs) and on separate Adverse Event form if serious Adverse Event.

      STATISTICS AND DATABASE MANAGEMENT:

      Data management will be performed by Scandinavian Contract Research Institute and when clean
      file is declared data will be made available to the statistician for the analysis. The
      analysis will be performed according to the intention to treat principle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 28, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 25, 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 25, 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A 12 month study, consisting of a 9 months' double-blind, placebo-controlled randomised growth hormone treatment phase followed by a 3 months' growth hormone treatment-free period.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>All care providers and patients were masked with respect to the study drug during the study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left ventricular endsystolic volume</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by CMR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in enddiastolic volume</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by CMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left ventricular mass</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by CMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left ventricular ejection fraction</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by CMR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in QoL Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in NT-proBNP level</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>blood sample</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure, Systolic</condition>
  <condition>Ischemic Heart Disease Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Growth hormon group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 12 month study, consisting of a 9 months growth hormone treatment phase followed by a 3 month growth hormone treatment-free period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 12 month study, consisting of a 9 month placebo treatment phase followed by a 3 month treatment-free period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Somatropin</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose: 1,4 mg (4,2 IE) every other day Dosage: 9 month treatment period and a 3 month follow-up period Administration: One subcutaneous injection of somatropin or corresponding placebo in the thigh or abdomen given in the evening given every other day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Growth hormon group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ejection fraction at rest less than 40% at the screening visit as measured by
             echocardiography and a left ventricular enddiastolic diameter &gt; 32 mm/m2

          -  Stable, optimised therapy for heart failure for at least 4 weeks prior to
             randomisation including Angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors, or if not tolerated,
             angiotensin II blockers and/or digitalis. If tolerated patients should receive
             beta-blockers for heart failure provided they have had a stable dose for at least 3
             months prior to randomisation. The dose of diuretics may vary within a given
             dose-range considered normal for that patient as determined by the investigator.

          -  Written informed consent obtained

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension, treated or not treated with a diastolic blood pressure &gt;105
             mm Hg

          -  Haemodynamic clinically significant primary valvular disease or significant congenital
             heart disease

          -  Hypertrophic or idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy

          -  Acute pericarditis/myocarditis

          -  Echocardiography findings such as mobile thrombus, significant pericardial effusion
             and significant left ventricular aneurysm

          -  Symptomatic or sustained ventricular arrhythmias within the last 3 months not
             adequately treated with antiarrhythmic drugs or internal cardiovertor defibrillator
             (ICD)

          -  Unstable angina pectoris, or myocardial infarction within last 3 months

          -  percutaneous coronary intervention performed within 6 months prior to randomization

          -  Planned percutaneous coronary intervention, heart transplantation, other cardiac
             surgery or other major surgery

          -  Atrial fibrillation, if a frequency &gt; 100/min or a large frequency variation,
             according to clinical judgment

          -  Diabetes mellitus, insulin treated

          -  Severe liver disease (alanine aminotransferase and/or alanine aminotransferase three
             times upper limit of normal range laboratory values)

          -  Severely reduced renal function (S-Creatinine above 250 micromol/l) or suspected
             significant renal artery stenosis

          -  Uncontrolled endocrine disorders

          -  Ongoing treatment with calcium antagonist

          -  Pregnancy or lactation or females of childbearing potential taking inadequate measures
             to prevent pregnancy

          -  History of or ongoing malignant disease

          -  Previous treatment with growth hormone

          -  Patients in a catabolic state

          -  Known drug and/or alcohol abuse

          -  Inability to cooperate or administer the study drug

          -  Patients participating in any other clinical study, within 30 days prior to screening
             visit and/or during this particular study period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart Failure, Systolic</keyword>
  <keyword>Ischemic Heart Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth Hormone Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin Growth Factor I Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormone Disturbance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure, Systolic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be share upon reasonable request</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>3 months</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>A researcher that can show previous scientific merits that can be validated</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

