<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02562456</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RECART</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02562456</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cost-efficacy Between ART and Composite Resin Restorations in Primary Molars</brief_title>
  <official_title>Difference of Cost-efficacy Between Atraumatic Restoration Treatment (ART) and Composite Resin Restorations in Primary Molars: A Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized clinical trial study is to compare the longevity of Atraumatic
      Restorative Treatment (ART) using high viscosity GIC and Conventional Treatment using
      composite resin under rubber dam isolation and local anesthesia (CT) in primary molars. As
      secondary outcomes, cost-efficacy, self-reported discomfort and cooperation will also be
      tested. Children aging between 3 to 6 years old presenting at least one occlusal and/or
      occlusoproximal cavity will be randomly assigned to one of two groups according to the dental
      treatment: ART (experimental group) or CT (control group). The dental treatment will be
      performed at a dental care trailer located in a Public School in Barueri (São Paulo, Brazil).
      The unit of analysis for randomization will be the child. A number of 204 teeth presenting
      occlusal cavities and 240 teeth presenting occlusoproximal cavities were set after sample
      size calculation. The primary outcome will be the restorations' longevity, which will be
      assessed after 6, 12, 18 and 24 months by two evaluators through clinical examination
      according to Frencken et al. (1998) criteria for occlusal restorations and Roeleveld et al.
      (2006) criteria for occlusoproximal restorations. The time spent during the dental treatment
      and all materials used will be considered for estimating the cost-efficacy of each treatment.
      The individual's discomfort will be also measured after each dental procedure using the
      Facial Scale of Wong-Baker. Cooperation will be assessed by the operator using a 5-point
      scale.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research setting

      The study will be performed in a dental care trailer which simulated a regular dental office
      and it is located inside a public school of the city Barueri (São Paulo, Brazil).

      Sample size calculation

      For sample size calculation, data regarding longevity of CT in occlusal and occlusoproximal
      restorations after 2 years were extracted from the literature as 86% for occlusal and 60% for
      occlusoproximal restorations. A difference of 15% and 20% between the longevity of CT and ART
      was set as non-inferiority limit. Considering the level of significance as 5%, power as 80%
      and adding 40% due to the study design (cluster per child), a number of 204 occlusal
      restorations and 240 occlusoproximal restorations will be needed.

      Randomization

      The child will be the unit of randomization which means that all eligible teeth of a
      participant will be treated according the same restorative approach. Randomization list will
      be obtained using blocks of 4, 6 and 8 generated by software Sealed Envelope Ltd. Opaque,
      sealed and sequentially numbered envelopes will be used for randomizing all participants
      immediately before restorative treatments' beginning.

      Allocation concealment

      To assure allocation concealment, the participant will be randomized immediately before the
      treatment. When two or more cavities is available, preventing the finalization of the
      treatment in only one session, breach of allocation concealment will be signalized in the
      participants' record.

      Blinding

      Due to differences between the techniques, it will be not possible to blind operators,
      participants and evaluators.

      Operators

      All operators will be masters or PhD students from the Pediatric Dentistry Department,
      Faculty of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, previously trained. All procedures will be
      performed with the assistance of a dental student previously trained to manipulate all
      restorative materials.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 10, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 10, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The restoration survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The treatments will be classified as successful when they present a clinical satisfactory aspect. Otherwise, &quot;minor failures&quot; will be analyzed. &quot;Minor failures&quot; are those in which there is a defect in the restoration/crown, but it does not interfere with the tooth health.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-efficacy assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment costs = professional costs + procedure costs.
Professional cost: the time spent in each session will be converted in hours and multiplied not only by the medium income of the dentist per hour added 40% of dangerousness but also by the medium income of a dental assistant added 20% of insalubrity
Procedure cost: variable cost (equipment &amp; instruments depreciation and electricity) and and materials cost. To calculate the equipments' and instruments' depreciation, we will consider their price, the lifespan of 5 and 3 years respectively and a monthly use of 160 hours. To calculate materials' costs, all materials used in each procedure will have their specifications and quantity registered. Prices will be inferences from the market value converted in US Dollars obtained by the medium of the values from different places that commercialized the referred products.
If the restorative treatment requires repairs, the additional cost of it will also be considered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child self-reported discomfort</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The acceptability of each type of treatment will be evaluated using the Facial scale of Wong-Baker (Wong; Baker, 1998). This scale indicates the discomfort of an individual who has to choose among six faces, each one expressing different facial countenance. The first image is a smiling happy face, indicating no discomfort, followed by gradually less cheerful expressions, up to the last one which is a very sad face covered by tears, indicating great discomfort. The participant will be asked to choose the face that is more similar to how he or she felt during the treatment. This answer should be given solely by the child, which means, no parental or professional interferences. The facial scale of Wong-Baker will be applied right after the end of each restorative treatment session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cooperation</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Cooperation will be evaluated by the operator immediately after the end of the treatment using a 5-point scale: 1- Good behaviour, 2- Reasonable behaviour, 3- Indiferent, 4- Bad behaviour, 5- Really bad behaviour.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">428</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Caries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Occlusal and occlusoproximal composite resin restorations in primary molars (rubber dam isolation + Adhesive system + composite resin Filtek z350)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ART using Fuji IX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Occlusal and occlusoproximal ART restorations in primary molars with GIC Fuji IX</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ART using Fuji IX</intervention_name>
    <description>Occlusal and occlusoproximal ART restorations in primary molars using the high viscosity GIC Fuji IX will be performed under relative isolation. No local anesthesia will be used. Infected carious tissue will be removed with hand instruments, and the cavities restored with GIC. After the press-finger technique, the excess of material will be removed and occlusion will be checked. For occlusoproximal restoration, an adapted matrix strip with a wooden wedge will be used to assure appropriate contour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ART using Fuji IX</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Occlusal and occlusoproximal composite resin restorations in primary molars using the Scotchbond Multi-purpose adhesive system and the Filtek Z-350 composite resin wil be performed. Local anesthesia will be used. Absolute isolation will be performed using rubber dam and clamp. Removal of unsupported enamel will be performed using a round bur. Infected carious tissue will be removed with hand instruments. The cavity will be etched using 37% phosphoric acid for 15 seconds followed by rising and drying for the same amount of time. The cavity will be restored with composite resin. Occlusion will be checked. an adapted matrix strip with a wooden wedge will be used to assure appropriate contour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children aging between 3 and 6 years

          -  presenting good health conditions

          -  whose parents or legal guardians accept and sign the consent form

          -  with at least one occlusal or occlusal proximal caries lesion in primary molars

          -  only occlusal and/or occlusal-proximal surfaces with caries lesions with dentin
             involvement

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  severe behavioral issues

          -  presence of fistula or abscess near the selected tooth

          -  presence of pulp exposure in the selected tooth

          -  presence of mobility in the selected tooth
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniela P Raggio, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complexo Educacional Carlos Osmarinho de Lima - Trailer USP</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barueri</city>
        <state>São Paulo</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniela Prócida Raggio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Pediatric Dentistry Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dental Atraumatic Restorative Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Composite Resins</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Teeth</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cost Analysis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

