<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04290468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ultrasound in shoulder</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04290468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dynamic Ultrasound in Shoulder Impingement</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Ultrasound in Shoulder Impingement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  To evaluate the role of dynamic ultrasound in evaluation patient with clinically
           suspected shoulder joint impingement.

        -  To assess the added value of dynamic ultrasonography to the static examination of
           patients with clinically suspected impingement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Shoulder impingement syndromes and degenerative rotator cuff (RC) disease represent the main
      causes of shoulder pain . Impingement is classified into four types, depending on the site of
      soft-tissue entrapment: sub acromial, sub coracoid, poster superior inner and anterosuperior
      inner impingement. The sub acromial impingement syndrome is by far the most common in
      practice. . The clinical symptoms of sub acromial impingement include nocturnal pain and
      progressive, limited range of motion. At clinical examination, there is a painful area at
      80-120° elevation, which is worsened during downward movements Osteophytes, or an abnormal
      shape of the acromion, sub acromial spurs, and the acromioclavicular joint, are common causes
      of compression at the rotator cuff and the overlying subacromial-subdeltoid bursa .
      Ultrasonography (US) is a commonly performed examination for shoulder impingement,
      recommended by experts as the first-choice technique to evaluate various shoulder diseases.
      Shoulder impingement is the most common and well-recognized indication for dynamic US in the
      shoulder.

      Dynamic evaluation can be done by shoulder abduction or flexion with the probe placed at the
      end of the acromion in the coronal plane or in the sagittal plane. The two important points
      to be checked for shoulder impingement are the humeral head depression and tendon/bursal
      impingement . Because humeral head depression is essential to make enough space for the
      rotator cuff to slide beneath the acromion, the center of the humeral head normally moves
      inferiorly in the latter half of the cycle during shoulder abduction. When the humeral head
      does not move inferiorly or abnormally moves superiorly, the space for the rotator cuffs and
      the subacromial-subdeltoid bursa decreases and subacromial impingement can occur .

      Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is currently considered the reference standard for imaging
      of shoulder disorders. The strength of MRI lies in its ability to assess sonographically
      inaccessible areas such as labrum, deep parts of various ligaments, capsule, and areas
      obscured by bone . MRI is the imaging study of choice for classifying tendon retraction and
      assessing the shoulder musculature. Its main disadvantage is being a static evaluation of the
      shoulder joint . There are several advantages of Ultrasonography over MRI. Ultrasonography
      has the benefit of being a dynamic form of imaging as compared to the static MRI.
      Ultrasonography is portable, quick, and a more cost-effective method. It is also better
      tolerated by the patient and allows interaction with the patient, who can point at the
      symptomatic area, thus optimizing the diagnostic yield.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of dynamic ultrasound findings with MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the role of dynamic shoulder ultrasound in evaluation of patients with clinically suspected shoulder impingement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Shoulder Impingement</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dynamic ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>The ultrasound examination will be carried out blinded to the results of MRI using the Affiniti 70 ultrasound machine by Philips (USA) via a 5-12MHz linear transducer.
MRI was performed on a high field system (1.5 Tesla) magnet units (Philips Acheiva).</description>
    <other_name>MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        sample size was determined by using G*power version 3.1.9.2 for windows for power analysis
        .we estimated 37 patients to be included in the study with statistically power 95% and 0.05
        as an alpha error
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  All patients referred to the Radiology department with clinically suspected shoulder
             impingement. Inclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The following categories of patient will be excluded from the study.

               1. History of previous shoulder surgery.

               2. History of joint dislocation.

               3. Fracture to the shoulder girdle.

               4. Patient with contraindication to MRI.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marwa Mohammed</last_name>
    <phone>01012561056</phone>
    <email>mrwaismail90@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Noha Attia</last_name>
    <phone>01065742341</phone>
    <email>nohamohamedali@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowbotham EL, Grainger AJ. VIDEO: Ultrasound Evaluation of External Shoulder Impingement. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2018 Aug;211(2):W122. doi: 10.2214/AJR.18.19534. Epub 2018 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29927333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coats-Thomas MS, Massimini DF, Warner JJP, Seitz AL. In Vivo Evaluation of Subacromial and Internal Impingement Risk in Asymptomatic Individuals. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2018 Sep;97(9):659-665. doi: 10.1097/PHM.0000000000000940.</citation>
    <PMID>29613881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pesquer L, Borghol S, Meyer P, Ropars M, Dallaudière B, Abadie P. Multimodality imaging of subacromial impingement syndrome. Skeletal Radiol. 2018 Jul;47(7):923-937. doi: 10.1007/s00256-018-2875-y. Epub 2018 Feb 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29445933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soker G, Gulek B, Soker E, Kaya O, Inan I, Arslan M, Esen K, Memis D, Yilmaz C. Sonographic assessment of subacromial bursa distension during arm abduction: establishing a threshold value in the diagnosis of subacromial impingement syndrome. J Med Ultrason (2001). 2018 Apr;45(2):287-294. doi: 10.1007/s10396-017-0839-9. Epub 2017 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>29075914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Do HK, Lim JY. Ultrasonographic Evaluation and Feasibility of Posterosuperior Internal Impingement Syndrome: A Case Series. PM R. 2017 Jan;9(1):88-94. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2016.06.008. Epub 2016 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>27317919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daghir AA, Sookur PA, Shah S, Watson M. Dynamic ultrasound of the subacromial-subdeltoid bursa in patients with shoulder impingement: a comparison with normal volunteers. Skeletal Radiol. 2012 Sep;41(9):1047-53. doi: 10.1007/s00256-011-1295-z. Epub 2011 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21997670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michener LA, Subasi Yesilyaprak SS, Seitz AL, Timmons MK, Walsworth MK. Supraspinatus tendon and subacromial space parameters measured on ultrasonographic imaging in subacromial impingement syndrome. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 2015 Feb;23(2):363-9. doi: 10.1007/s00167-013-2542-8. Epub 2013 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23736252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marwa Ismail Ahmed Mohammed</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Impingement Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

