<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04290689</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RL1 777</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04290689</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can Gait Analysis and Ultrasound Detect a Change in Calf Musculature in Children With Cerebral Palsy?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can Gait Analysis and Imaging Methods Detect Change in the Calf Musculature in Children With Cerebral Palsy? Comparison Study of Toe Walking Patients Following Serial Casting, Botulinum Toxin-A and Typically Developing Controls.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Robert Jones and Agnes Hunt Orthopaedic and District NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Robert Jones and Agnes Hunt Orthopaedic and District NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      ORLAU is a clinical department of the Robert Jones and Agnes Hunt Orthopaedic Hospital. We
      treat patients with a wide range of movement disorders affecting their walking or arm
      function. One of the most common gait issues we see is toe-walking, this is most prevalent in
      those patients with cerebral palsy (CP). Toe-walking in CP children arises mostly from
      problems in the calf muscle, we currently use gait analysis to help guide treatment
      management plans. Two standard interventions for such cases are serial casting and Botulinum
      Toxin-A injections. Using gait analysis we will be able to see changes to the gait pattern
      before and after the interventions, however, we want to obtain a whole clinical picture,
      using B-mode ultrasound, elastography and electromyography (EMG) we will be able to achieve
      this. These measurements will provide us with information about the muscle architecture and
      properties including activation. This will help us to determine the effects of the
      interventions. Elastography is a fairly new clinical technique that uses shear waves
      generated by the ultrasound probe to map the stiffness of a muscle. Stiffness of muscle is a
      good indication of myopathies. The additional examinations we want to carry out are all
      non-invasive, they will be carried out in two sessions, one before the intervention and one
      after. We will compare the data we collect from the children with CP to our normal database
      with ORLAU has ethical approval for. The final stage of this study will be to use the muscle
      parameters obtained by ultrasound to set parameters in a computer musculoskeletal model.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the impact on gait and morphology of the calf muscle
      in children with Cerebral Palsy with equinus gait pattern following serial casting and
      Botulinum toxin (Btx) interventions.

      Toe walking is a common feature of a number of orthopaedic and neurological problems (e.g.
      cerebral palsy, idiopathic toe walking and stroke). Patients who toe walk often develop
      contractures in their calf muscles and in the longer term may suffer from foot or calf pain
      and foot deformities. Toe walking also causes difficulties with balance and leads to
      secondary compensations and deformities. The causes of toe walking are not always clear for
      individual patients. Current interventions target the perceived causes (e.g. surgery,
      stretching or orthotics for contracture or botulinum toxin injections for excessive activity)
      but the relationship between toe walking and the impairment in muscle morphology and control
      is not fully understood. Clinical movement analysis is used to quantify joint motion and
      loading during gait. This is done according to established local departmental protocol and is
      part of routine clinical practice. This is done using the Video Based Motion Analysis System
      Ltd (VICON), which is a 3D movement analysis modality which makes use of small, spherical
      reflective markers, between 5mm and 25mm in diameter that are attached to the skin over key
      anatomical landmarks (located during the clinical examination). Special infrared cameras are
      used to track the movements of reflective markers in three dimensions. This is combined with
      AMTI force plates; which together give the kinematics and kinetics of the subject.
      Electromyography (EMG) of the Triceps Surae and Tibialis Anterior enables observation of
      muscle activity in conjunction with the gait cycle during different movements. After
      obtaining participant consent and ensuring that the participant fully understands the scope
      of the tasks, the session is undertaken. In brief, using local ORLAU department protocol, a
      clinician places reflective markers on the subject and anthropometric measurements are taken.
      After the subject is prepared, they are asked to walk along a 10-metre walkway at a self
      selected speed and a minimum of 6 trials are collected with adequate strikes with each foot
      landing on the force plate to obtain desired kinematic and kinetic data. EMG recordings are
      performed simultaneously on the Medial &amp; Lateral Gastrocnemius, Soleus, and Tibialis Anterior
      to record muscle activity during the movement.

      To obtain information about the morphology, the modality of B-mode ultrasound evaluated the
      muscle morphology and obtains key information such as muscle fibre length, fibre orientation,
      pennation angle, cross sectional area, and muscle thickness. After obtaining consent and
      ensuring that the participant understands fully the scope of the session, they are asked to
      lie prone on the plinth with lower legs exposed so that the assessor has access to the calf
      muscles. The assessor then uses the b-mode ultrasound protocol to obtain the key parameters
      of the calf muscle. Muscle lengths are measured using a Vernier caliper.

      In addition, the imaging modality elastography is used. This uses mechanical force, from
      manual pressure or through a shear wave impulse generated within the ultrasound probe, to
      detect the change in deformation of the examined tissue and therefore to determine the
      stiffness. The stiffness of soft tissues can be an indication of pathology. Elastography uses
      harmless ultrasound waves and allows for the visualisation of strain across a tissue, by
      superimposing the colour coded elasticity map onto a conventional B-mode image. The colours
      represent the stiffness of the tissue ranging from red to green to blue, with the exact scale
      varying between vendors. Shear wave elastography has the added advantage of being able to
      provide velocity measurements within a defined region of interest, thus quantifying tissue
      stiffness.

      Prior to beginning the session, consent from the subject is obtained and the scope of the
      session is explained. After consent from the participant, the subject is asked to lie prone
      on the plinth with their lower legs exposed. The consultant radiologist undertakes
      elastography measures on the calf muscles (medial, lateral gastrocnemius, soleus) in
      longitudinal and transverse planes according to the protocol. These are then saved after the
      key information is obtained and analysed after the session.

      Computer modelling can estimate muscle forces during gait, and it is used to study a wide
      range of conditions such as spastic paresis and crouch gait. Ultrasound can provide
      information about muscle parameters such as volume, length, anatomical cross-sectional area
      and pennation angle. This information can be used to adjust the parameters of the
      musculoskeletal model to fit the characteristics of each patient. The musculoskeletal model
      can then estimate personalised muscle forces and help understand the individual impairments
      which lead to toe walking. Future prospects Clinical- The computer models will assist with
      the precise identification of impairments (eg muscle atrophy, contracture and spasticity) and
      hence allow more objective specification and targeting of interventions. Combining the data
      collected from B mode ultrasound, elastography and gait analysis, the effects of clinical
      interventions in muscle properties can be observed. This can be applied to other
      interventions, including orthopaedic surgery and orthotic devices. Elastography can also be a
      vital tool in understanding the elastic muscle properties associated with myopathies and can
      help optimise and personalise care by selecting the most effective intervention based on an
      individual's baseline features.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there gait (kinetic) differences pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Kinetics (joint forces) will be measured (using gait analysis modality) pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects. The intervention will be determined by the consultant Orthopedic Surgeon in clinic.Units of measure:measured in Nm/kg</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there gait (kinematic) differences pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Kinematics (joint angles) will be measured (using gait analysis modality) pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects. The intervention will be determined by the consultant Orthopedic Surgeon in clinic.Units of measure: measured in degrees (angle).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Triceps Surae muscle activation during the gait cycle (Electromyography)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Electromyography (EMG) measurement - is the muscle activated or deactivated pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects? Measured in uV</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there morphological differences in the calf muscle pre and post serial casting/botulinum toxin-A intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>B-mode ultrasound modality will be used pre and post intervention to measure muscle morphology parameter - muscle thickness. Measured in millimeter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there morphological differences in the calf muscle pre and post serial casting/botulinum toxin-A intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>B-mode ultrasound modality will be used pre and post intervention to measure muscle morphology parameter - muscle fibre length; measured in millimeter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there morphological differences in the calf muscle pre and post serial casting/botulinum toxin-A intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>B-mode ultrasound modality will be used pre and post intervention to measure muscle morphology parameter - muscle length; measured in millimeter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there morphological differences in the calf muscle pre and post serial casting/botulinum toxin-A intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>B-mode ultrasound modality will be used pre and post intervention to measure muscle morphology parameter - pennation angle; measured in degrees.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Are there morphological differences in the calf muscle pre and post serial casting/botulinum toxin-A intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>B-mode ultrasound modality will be used pre and post intervention to measure muscle morphology parameter - Cross sectional area; measured in cm^2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the muscle stiffness values (using elastography) in the calf muscle pre and post intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine, using elastography modality, if there is a difference in muscle stiffness values pre and post intervention for toe walking cerebral palsy children. Units of measure: m/s velocity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Are there gait (kinetic and kinematic) differences pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The temporospatial parameter during the gait analysis will be measured pre and post intervention: walking speed; units of measure:m/s</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Are there gait (kinetic and kinematic) differences pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The temporospatial parameter during the gait analysis will be measured pre and post intervention: cadence; units of measure: steps/min</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Are there gait (kinetic and kinematic) differences pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The temporospatial parameter during the gait analysis will be measured pre and post intervention: single/double support ; units of measure: single/double</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Are there gait (kinetic and kinematic) differences pre and post intervention in toe walking cerebral palsy subjects?</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The temporospatial parameter during the gait analysis will be measured pre and post intervention:step width; units of measure: meter</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin-A injection treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Toe walking Cerebral Palsy subject who are subject to Botulinum toxin-A injection treatment. The dosage will be determined by the Orthopaedic Consultant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Serial casting stretching treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Toe walking Cerebral Palsy subject who are subject to serial casting stretching treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Botulinum Toxin-A injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Botulinum Toxin-A injection to be administered by the surgeon to the subject's calf muscle as per normal clinical protocol to help improve muscle tone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin-A injection treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;Botox&quot;</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Serial casting stretching</intervention_name>
    <description>Stretching cast intervention to be carried out in clinic as per normal clinical protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Serial casting stretching treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>serial cast</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Potential participants will be screened by the research team at weekly review meeting
        (involving the Medical Director and orthopaedic consultants). Participants will be
        identified in the Childrens outpatient's clinics at Trust Hospital (RJAH).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be diagnosed with Cerebral Palsy and have a planned intervention of
             serial casting or botulinum toxin calf injection or serial casting and botulinum toxin
             injection.

          -  Participants must be able to walk 10 metres barefoot.

          -  Participants must be between the ages of 4 and 16.

          -  Participants must have a gait pattern showing persistent toe walking or premature heel
             rise.

          -  Participants should be able to comply with requests to walk in the gait laboratory.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have had Botulinum toxin-A calf injections or previous serial casting
             within the last 6 months.

          -  Participants should not have fixed foot equinus.

          -  Participants must not have any learning difficulties which would prevent compliance
             with the standard protocols.

          -  Participants must not have had any previous surgical interventions of the lower limbs
             within one year of taking of taking part.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ORLAU, RJAH Orthopaedic Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oswestry</city>
        <state>Shropshire</state>
        <zip>SY10 7AG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Caroline Stewart, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 1691 404666</phone>
      <email>caroline.stewart9@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Claire Wright</last_name>
      <phone>0044 1691 404139</phone>
      <email>clairewright8@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armand S, Decoulon G, Bonnefoy-Mazure A. Gait analysis in children with cerebral palsy. EFORT Open Rev. 2016 Dec 22;1(12):448-460. doi: 10.1302/2058-5241.1.000052. eCollection 2016 Dec.</citation>
    <PMID>28698802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barber L, Barrett R, Lichtwark G. Passive muscle mechanical properties of the medial gastrocnemius in young adults with spastic cerebral palsy. J Biomech. 2011 Sep 2;44(13):2496-500. doi: 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2011.06.008. Epub 2011 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21762920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blemker SS, Asakawa DS, Gold GE, Delp SL. Image-based musculoskeletal modeling: applications, advances, and future opportunities. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2007 Feb;25(2):441-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17260405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart C, Shortland AP. The biomechanics of pathological gait - from muscle to movement. Acta Bioeng Biomech. 2010;12(3):3-12.</citation>
    <PMID>21247058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalsi G, Fry NR, Shortland AP. Gastrocnemius muscle-tendon interaction during walking in typically-developing adults and children, and in children with spastic cerebral palsy. J Biomech. 2016 Oct 3;49(14):3194-3199. doi: 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2016.07.038. Epub 2016 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27545082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cerebral palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>b-mode ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>gait analysis</keyword>
  <keyword>EMG</keyword>
  <keyword>elastography</keyword>
  <keyword>musculoskeletal modelling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>abobotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Study is still recruiting and collecting data. sharing will depend on the quality and quantity of data collected.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

