<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04290312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MASTIHA OIL-BIO-GR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04290312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Absorption and Bioavailability of Major Monoterpenes in Mastiha Oil; a Kinetic Study in Humans.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Absorption and Bioavailability of Major Monoterpenes in Mastiha Oil; a Kinetic Study in Humans.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Harokopio University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Harokopio University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Plant derived foods contain large quantities of non-nutrient phytochemicals that have been
      extensively studied for their beneficial health effects on the prevention of chronic
      diseases. Although research on their health effects is abundant, our knowledge on absorption
      and bioavailability is yet narrow and in some cases zero. The concept of bioavailability
      involves the identification of the fraction of administered compounds that can reach plasma
      and body tissues in an unchanged form. The bioactivity of components in foods that are part
      of our nutrition, either as parent foods or as food supplements, is directly related to
      bioavailability, the latter being a necessary step to prove efficacy.

      Mastiha Oil (MO) is extracted from the resin of Pistacia Lentiscus var. Chia (of the
      Anacardiaceae family), a concentrated source of monoterpenes (e.g., α-pinene, β-pinene,
      β-myrcene) and triterpenes (e.g., mastihadienonic acid, isomastihadienonic acid), and to a
      lesser extent of plant sterols, simple phenols and approximately 10% MO (Assimopoulou, &amp;
      Papageorgiou, 2005, Paraschos et al, 2007, Kaliora, Mylona, Chiou, Petsios, &amp; Andrikopoulos,
      2004). MO is a 100% natural product used as a food additive and flavoring and it is
      manufactured according to the legal standards that make it suitable for human consumption.
      Its nutritional analysis is presented in Supplementary Table 1. A total of 90 components have
      been detected in MO (50% monoterpene hydrocarbons, 20% oxygenated monoterpenes, 25%
      sesquiterpenes). Monoterpenes seem to exhibit beneficial health effects contributing to
      mechanisms of inflammation and oxidative stress (Subramaniyan, 2017; Madhuri, &amp; Naik, 2017).

      Research upon the bioavailability of monoterpenes in humans is limited. Herein, we aimed at
      investigating the bioavailability of the main monoterpenes of MO in humans for the first
      time. To this end, a novel GC-MS-MS method was employed, since the tandem MS technique can
      help overcome matrix difficulties. Additionally, based on the existing data regarding the
      antioxidant activity of monoterpenes, the effect on human antioxidant capacity was evaluated
      applying the serum oxidisabilty assay.

      .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After enrolment, the volunteers will undergo a medical and dietary assessment and their
      health status will be evaluated through a complete blood count. On the day of the experiment
      and after overnight fasting, the volunteers will consume g of mastiha oil (1ml) and blood
      samples will be obtained on timepoints 0.5h, 1h, 2h, 4h, 6h and 24h after intake. Until
      timepoint 6h, they will be allowed to consume only water. After collection, the monoterpenes
      will be identified in plasma samples applying a GC-MS-MS technique. Additionally, oxidative
      stress will be evaluated through the CuSO4 technique in serum samples.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 24, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 24, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of monoterpenes</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The monoterpenes will be identified and quantified in plasma samples applying GC-MS-MS. Data will be presented through study completion in plasma concentration (μg/L).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Absorption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mastiha oil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>As a control to the experimental design, timepoint 0 was considered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mastiha oil</intervention_name>
    <description>After overnight fasting, the authorized study staff inserted a plastic cannula in an arm vein of the volunteers in order to minimize discomfort during consecutive blood sampling. A blood sample was collected on time point 0h and then the volunteers consumed 1mL of MO. The dose selection was based on the study of Papada et al. (2017) who administered healthy volunteers with 10g of Mastiha (containing ~10% MO). Afterwards blood samples were collected on time points 0.5h, 1h, 2h, 4h, 6h and 24h after MO intake, and were centrifuged at 3000rpm for 10 minutes at 4◦C for plasma and serum isolation. All samples were stored at -80◦C until further analysis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mastiha oil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 20-40 years old

          -  BMI: 18.5-24.9 kg/m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Obesity

          -  Alcohol or drug abuse

          -  Medication, vitamin or inorganic supplements

          -  Vegan or macrobiotic diet before and during the study

          -  Gastrointestinal diseases, such as atrophic gastritis, Inflammatory Bowel Disease,
             peptic ulcer or gastrointestinal cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andriana Kaliora, Ass. Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Harokopio University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harokopio University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Attica</state>
        <zip>17671</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Papada E, Gioxari A, Brieudes V, Amerikanou C, Halabalaki M, Skaltsounis AL, Smyrnioudis I, Kaliora AC. Bioavailability of Terpenes and Postprandial Effect on Human Antioxidant Potential. An Open-Label Study in Healthy Subjects. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2018 Feb;62(3). doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201700751. Epub 2017 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>29171157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abidi A, Aissani N, Sebai H, Serairi R, Kourda N, Ben Khamsa S. Protective Effect of Pistacia lentiscus Oil Against Bleomycin-Induced Lung Fibrosis and Oxidative Stress in Rat. Nutr Cancer. 2017 Apr;69(3):490-497. doi: 10.1080/01635581.2017.1283423. Epub 2017 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28287322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>J C Furtado NA, Pirson L, Edelberg H, M Miranda L, Loira-Pastoriza C, Preat V, Larondelle Y, André CM. Pentacyclic Triterpene Bioavailability: An Overview of In Vitro and In Vivo Studies. Molecules. 2017 Mar 4;22(3). pii: E400. doi: 10.3390/molecules22030400. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28273859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-Villalba R, Larrosa M, Possemiers S, Tomás-Barberán FA, Espín JC. Bioavailability of phenolics from an oleuropein-rich olive (Olea europaea) leaf extract and its acute effect on plasma antioxidant status: comparison between pre- and postmenopausal women. Eur J Nutr. 2014 Jun;53(4):1015-27. doi: 10.1007/s00394-013-0604-9. Epub 2013 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24158653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanellos PT, Kaliora AC, Gioxari A, Christopoulou GO, Kalogeropoulos N, Karathanos VT. Absorption and bioavailability of antioxidant phytochemicals and increase of serum oxidation resistance in healthy subjects following supplementation with raisins. Plant Foods Hum Nutr. 2013 Dec;68(4):411-5. doi: 10.1007/s11130-013-0389-2.</citation>
    <PMID>24114059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Subramaniyan SD, Natarajan AK. Citral, A Monoterpene Protect Against High Glucose Induced Oxidative Injury in HepG2 Cell In Vitro-An Experimental Study. J Clin Diagn Res. 2017 Aug;11(8):BC10-BC15. doi: 10.7860/JCDR/2017/28470.10377. Epub 2017 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>28969111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saidi SA, Ncir M, Chaaben R, Jamoussi K, van Pelt J, Elfeki A. Liver injury following small intestinal ischemia reperfusion in rats is attenuated by Pistacia lentiscus oil: antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects. Arch Physiol Biochem. 2017 Oct;123(4):199-205. doi: 10.1080/13813455.2017.1302961. Epub 2017 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>28338348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Harokopio University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andriana C Kaliora</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor in Foods and Human Nutrition</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mastiha oil, bioavailability</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

