<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04296565</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E3143-R</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1I01RX003143-01A2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04296565</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Water-based Activity to Enhance Recall in Veterans: A Randomized Clinical Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>WATER-Vet</acronym>
  <official_title>Water-based Activity to Enhance Recall in Veterans: A Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This four-year study will evaluate the efficacy of an exercise training augmentation for
      cognitive training intervention to improve memory performance in Veterans with a diagnosis of
      amnestic Mild Cognitive Impairment (aMCI). This is a two-phased trial: 1) an exercise phase
      and 2) a cognitive training program. The exercise phase will be an aquatic based exercise
      program. A combination of exercise and cognitive training programs designed for persons
      without cognitive impairment have significantly improved memory more than other single
      intervention groups (exercise only, cognitive training only) and given the success of
      combination training programs with healthy older adults, it is important to adapt these
      programs for persons beginning to exhibit clinically significant memory problems, such as
      those with aMCI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary research question of the proposed study is this: Is a water-based exercise plus
      cognitive training intervention efficacious in improving cognitive outcomes for Veterans with
      Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI)? The investigators address the need to improve cognitive
      function in this vulnerable population through a novel multi-component training program that
      will combine two interventions: water-based exercise and cognitive training. The proposed
      four-year randomized controlled trial will compare water-based exercise + cognitive training
      (WATER+CT) to a Usual Care Control Condition (UC). The primary aim of the proposed research
      is to evaluate the efficacy of WATER+CT to improve cognitive function in Veterans with MCI.
      Secondary aims of the proposed research are: 1) to evaluate the efficacy of WATER+CT to
      improve peak oxygen consumption and 2) to evaluate the durability of the cognitive benefits
      derived from WATER+CT. Exploratory aims of the proposed research are to evaluate moderators
      and mediators of treatment response.

      These aims will be tested in a single-blind randomized controlled trial that will compare the
      efficacy of WATER+CT to UC. This trial will include 130 Veterans meeting criteria for MCI age
      50-90 with half randomized to WATER+CT and half randomized to UC. For the WATER+CT condition,
      the exercise training (i.e., WATER) consists of a six-month long individualized exercise
      program of water-based exercises. During this phase, Veterans will come to thrice-weekly
      group sessions at Aquatic Therapy Center at the VA Palo Alto Health Care System (VAPAHCS).
      After completion of the exercise program, Veterans will begin classroom-based cognitive
      training at the VAPAHCS for up to two months. The CT is based on an efficacious training
      program that is structured around two components, pre-training and mnemonic training, both of
      which have been used successfully in persons with MCI. Veterans randomized to the UC control
      condition will receive educational materials about brain health in addition to their usual
      care, which is the care they would typically receive in the VA. After completion of the
      active treatment phase, Veterans will transition to the six-month long follow-up phase. At
      the end of the six-month long follow-up phase, participants will return to the VA for a final
      follow-up visit.

      Participants will complete a variety of neuropsychological measures taping into areas of
      cognition such as attention, executive functioning, and memory. Participants will also
      undergo physical fitness assessments including a 6-minute walk test and an exercise treadmill
      test. To study possible predictors of response to treatment, the investigators will also
      collect biological (cardiovascular functioning and BDNF plasma levels) and genetic data (APOE
      and BDNF genotypes) from these participants. The investigators hope to provide evidence of
      the efficacy of an exercise training augmentation for cognitive training thus laying the
      groundwork for future VA health care system wide deployment of a lifestyle intervention to
      prevent Alzheimer's disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Function Composite Score (ADAS-Cog-Exe)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The ADAS-Cog is a structured scale that evaluates multiple cognitive domains including: orientation, memory, reasoning, language, and praxis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak VO2</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Peak VO2, or VO2Max, is defined as the minute volume of O2 utilization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual Care condition involves receipt of educational materials about brain health and healthy lifestyles as well as regular contact with study staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>WATER+CT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an 8 month long two phase intervention. The first phase consists of 6 months of thrice weekly pool based physical activity occurring at the Palo Alto VA Health Care System. After completion of the 6 month long water based physical activity, participants transition to a ten session cognitive training program at the Palo Alto VA. The cognitive training classes are approximately two hours in length and will be spread over ten sessions across 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual Care condition involves receipt of educational materials about brain health and healthy lifestyles as well as regular contact with study staff</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WATER+CT</intervention_name>
    <description>This is an 8 month long two phase intervention. The first phase consists of 6 months of thrice weekly pool based physical activity occurring at the Palo Alto VA Health Care System. After completion of the 6 month long water based physical activity, participants transition to a ten session cognitive training program at the Palo Alto VA. The cognitive training classes are approximately two hours in length and will be spread over ten sessions across 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>WATER+CT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans, aged 50 to 90, of any racial or ethnic group

          -  Diagnosis of single or multi-domain amnestic MCI using criteria per National Institute
             on Aging/Alzheimer's Association Guidelines

          -  Available informant for completion of the Clinical Dementia Rating Scale

          -  Visual and auditory acuity to allow neuropsychological testing

          -  Willingness to participate in clinical trial for 14 months (8-month treatment phase,
             6-month no-contact follow-up phase)

          -  Musculoskeletal illness or injury (i.e., osteoporosis, degenerative disc or joint
             disease, arthritis, obesity)

          -  Approval by Primary Care Provider to participate in water-based physical exercise

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Psychiatric Exclusions

          -  Current, uncontrolled severe psychiatric disorder, such as Bipolar I, Schizophrenia,
             or Major Depressive Disorder as determined by the Mini International Neuropsychiatric
             Interview (MINI)

          -  Diagnosis of dementia, Clinical Dementia Rating Scale (CDR) &gt; 0.5; modified Hachinksi
             score 4; or delirium. Those Veterans with scores indicative of dementia (CDR &gt; 0.5,
             modified Hachinksi 4) will be referred to the Memory Disorders Clinic at VAPAHCS for a
             full diagnostic work-up

        Medical Exclusions

          -  History of neurological (e.g., multiple sclerosis, seizure disorder, stroke,) or
             system illness affecting CNS function (e.g., liver failure, kidney failure, congestive
             heart failure, systemic cancer)

          -  Acute illness or unstable chronic illness, e.g., history of severe liver disease
             (cirrhosis, esophageal varices, ascites, portal hypertension, hepatic encephalopathy)

          -  Current severe cardiac disease (e.g., uncontrolled atrial fibrillation, defined as
             mean 24 hour heart rate &gt;85 beats/min, or 24 hour maximal ventricular rate &gt;150
             beats/min; uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, defined as recurrent ventricular
             tachycardia &gt;3 beats in succession, or 24 hour PVC count &gt;20%; active pericarditis or
             myocarditis; Class III/IV heart failure and / or ejection fraction &lt; 20%;
             thrombophlebitis; pulmonary disease with a drop in O2 Sat with exercise to 90% without
             oxygen; embolism within past 6 months)

          -  Inability to participate in an exercise stress test

          -  Inability to read, verbalize understanding and voluntarily sign the Informed Consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Kaci Fairchild, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer K Fairchild, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(650) 439-5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>63432</phone_ext>
    <email>JenniferKaci.Fairchild@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304-1290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer K Fairchild, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(650) 439-5000</phone>
      <phone_ext>63432</phone_ext>
      <email>JenniferKaci.Fairchild@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Kaci Fairchild, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mild Cognitive Impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

