<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04299802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>111111</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04299802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy Versus Platelet Rich Plasma for Gluteal Tendinopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Comparison Study on the Effects of Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy Versus Leukocyte-Rich Platelet Rich Plasma for Refractory Gluteal Tendinopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Andrews Research &amp; Education Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Andrews Research &amp; Education Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate safety and effectiveness of both a single
      percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy or a single injection of LR-PRP in gluteal tendinopathy.
      Effectiveness will be demonstrated in a superiority trial design by comparing improvement in
      pain and function after a single percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy versus a single injection
      of LR-PRP in refractory gluteal tendinopathy that has failed conservative management. The
      investigators hypothesize that both procedures will show improvement to pain and function
      from baseline to 24 weeks and improvement will remain at 48 weeks follow-up. The
      investigators propose to test this hypothesis with a series of randomized cases of gluteal
      tendinopathy treated with one of the proposed treatment arms and evaluate at specified
      intervals with validated clinical outcome measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the Study:

      To investigate the safety and effectiveness of a single percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy
      procedure versus a single injection of autologous leukocyte-rich platelet rich plasma
      (LR-PRP) in subjects with symptomatic gluteal tendinopathy which has been refractory to
      conservative treatment

      Hypothesis of the Study:

      The hypothesis of this study is that subjects with symptomatic gluteal tendinopathy (defined
      as &lt;50% partial-thickness tear of either the gluteus medius or gluteus minimus tendons on MRI
      or US) who receive either a single percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy or a single injection of
      LR-PRP will demonstrate less pain and improved hip function compared to pre-treatment
      baseline.

      Primary Objective:

      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate safety and effectiveness of both a single
      percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy or a single injection of LR-PRP in gluteal tendinopathy.
      Effectiveness will be demonstrated in a superiority trial design by comparing improvement in
      pain and function after a single percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy versus a single injection
      of LR-PRP in refractory gluteal tendinopathy that has failed conservative management.

      Randomization:

      Subjects will be randomly assigned to the single percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy procedure
      or single injection of LR-PRP arms in a 1:1 ratio.

      Enrollment:

      The providers from the Andrews Institute will enroll subjects into the study. 60 subjects
      assigned to two randomization arms will be enrolled: a single percutaneous ultrasonic
      tenotomy procedure arm and a single LR-PRP injection arm.

      Study Duration:

      Estimated Subject Enrollment Period: 36 weeks Treatment and Follow-up Period per Subject: 48
      weeks

      Follow-up Schedule:

      Follow-up visits will occur at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks and 48 weeks
      post-procedure. Visits will include physical examinations, patient-reported outcome
      questionnaires, medication usage, adverse event monitoring and MRIs. Follow-up phone calls
      will occur at 24 and 48 weeks post-procedure. Phone calls will include patient-reported
      outcome questionnaires, medication usage, and adverse event monitoring.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 9, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Clinical Trial tracking Platelet-Rich Plasma injection vs. Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy for up to 1 year</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Unable to blind procedures as they require different types of devices, procedures and settings.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Numeric Pain Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks post treatment, 48 weeks post treatment, 1 year post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Pain rating scale with a minimum score of 0 (No pain) and a maximum score of 10 (worst pain imaginable).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Victorian Institute for Sport Assessment for Gluteal Tendinopathy Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks post treatment, 48 weeks post treatment, 1 year post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Scores range from 0-100. Higher scores indicate less pain and better function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hip Disability and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks post treatment, 48 weeks post treatment, 1 year post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Scores range from 0-100. 0 indicating the worst possible hip symptoms and 100 indicating no hip symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gluteal Muscle Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks post treatment, 48 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Manual muscle strength will be assessed by an investigator. The scale used will range from 0-5. Lower scores indicate less strength.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Visual Analog Scale for Procedure Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 24 weeks post treatment, 48 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>A VAS for satisfaction is a horizontal line of 100-mm long. At the beginning and at the end, there are two descriptors representing extremes of satisfaction (i.e. no satisfaction and extreme satisfaction). The patient will make a vertical mark on the 100-mm line. The measurement in millimetres will be converted to the same number of points ranging from 0 to 100 points.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Gluteal Tendinitis</condition>
  <condition>Trochanteric Bursitis</condition>
  <condition>Tendinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leukocyte-Rich Platelet-Rich Plasma (LR-PRP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>LR-PRP will be administered via usual protocol with venous blood draw and concentration via centrifugation. The LR-PRP will be injected under ultrasound guidance into the gluteus minimus and gluteus medius tendons, enthesis and surrounding bursae.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy will be administered via usual protocol within an outpatient surgical setting or in-office procedure. Patient will be anesthetized with local anesthetic and a &lt;5mm incision will be made along the lateral hip with an #11 scalpel. A 14-G angiocath will be introduced through the defective area of the tendon down to the enthesis. Multiple passes will be made and then the percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy device will be introduced to the defective area. No more than 5 minutes of energy cutting time will be used to address the defective area down to the enthesis, which will debride abnormal tissue but leave normal healthy tissue intact.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leukocyte-Rich Platelet-Rich Plasma</intervention_name>
    <description>LR-PRP will be a concentration of PRP with the addition of leukocytes. Studies have shown that LR-PRP is more effective in treating tendinopathy than leukocyte-poor platelet-rich plasma.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Leukocyte-Rich Platelet-Rich Plasma (LR-PRP)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LR-PRP</other_name>
    <other_name>PRP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Discussed in Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy Arm section</description>
    <arm_group_label>Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TENEX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and Females 18 - 70 years of age (inclusive)

          -  Clinical symptoms for a minimum of three months

          -  Subjects have a baseline pain score of &gt; 3

          -  Partial-thickness gluteal tendon tear (gluteus medius or gluteus minimus) defined as
             &lt;50% partial-thickness tear of either tendon or imaging abnormalities consistent with
             tendinosis on a 3 Tesla MRI or diagnostic ultrasound within the last 3 months, as
             determined by the Investigator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 or &gt; 70

          -  Corticosteroid injection in the index gluteal bursae within the last 3 months

          -  Subjects who have received more than one (1) previous corticosteroid injections or
             percutaneous tenotomy procedure or any biologic treatment in the index gluteal bursae
             at any point in the past.

          -  Severe arthrosis of the femoral-acetabular joint

          -  A high-grade gluteal tendon tear (&gt;50% partial-thickness tear)

          -  Previous hip surgery on the affected side

          -  Previous or current history of labral pathology on the affected side

          -  Lumbar radiculopathy impacting the index hip

          -  History of systemic malignant neoplasms within the last 5 years

          -  Malignant or local neoplasm within the last 6 months or any history of local neoplasm
             at the site of administration (on the affected side)

          -  Receiving immunosuppressive therapy

          -  Active regimen of chemotherapy or radiation-based treatment

          -  Allergy to sodium citrate or any &quot;caine&quot; type of local anesthetic

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Subject is currently participating in another clinical trial that has not yet
             completed its primary endpoint. (Non-interventional observational studies are not
             exclusionary.)

          -  Active workman's compensation case in progress
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Andrews, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Andrews Research &amp; Education Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Todd R Hayano, DO</last_name>
    <phone>9253668012</phone>
    <email>toddhayano@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hillary Plummer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>850-916-8796</phone>
    <email>hillary.plummer@andrewsref.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jacobson JA, Yablon CM, Henning PT, Kazmers IS, Urquhart A, Hallstrom B, Bedi A, Parameswaran A. Greater Trochanteric Pain Syndrome: Percutaneous Tendon Fenestration Versus Platelet-Rich Plasma Injection for Treatment of Gluteal Tendinosis. J Ultrasound Med. 2016 Nov;35(11):2413-2420. Epub 2016 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>27663654</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Borg-Stein J, Osoria HL, Hayano T. Regenerative Sports Medicine: Past, Present, and Future (Adapted From the PASSOR Legacy Award Presentation; AAPMR; October 2016). PM R. 2018 Oct;10(10):1083-1105. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2018.07.003. Epub 2018 Jul 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30031963</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu PI, Diaz R, Borg-Stein J. Platelet-Rich Plasma. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2016 Nov;27(4):825-853. doi: 10.1016/j.pmr.2016.06.002. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27788903</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fitzpatrick J, Bulsara MK, O'Donnell J, McCrory PR, Zheng MH. The Effectiveness of Platelet-Rich Plasma Injections in Gluteal Tendinopathy: A Randomized, Double-Blind Controlled Trial Comparing a Single Platelet-Rich Plasma Injection With a Single Corticosteroid Injection. Am J Sports Med. 2018 Mar;46(4):933-939. doi: 10.1177/0363546517745525. Epub 2018 Jan 2.</citation>
    <PMID>29293361</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fitzpatrick J, Bulsara M, Zheng MH. The Effectiveness of Platelet-Rich Plasma in the Treatment of Tendinopathy: A Meta-analysis of Randomized Controlled Clinical Trials. Am J Sports Med. 2017 Jan;45(1):226-233. doi: 10.1177/0363546516643716. Epub 2016 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>27268111</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee JJ, Harrison JR, Boachie-Adjei K, Vargas E, Moley PJ. Platelet-Rich Plasma Injections With Needle Tenotomy for Gluteus Medius Tendinopathy: A Registry Study With Prospective Follow-up. Orthop J Sports Med. 2016 Nov 9;4(11):2325967116671692. eCollection 2016 Nov.</citation>
    <PMID>27868077</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Neph A, Onishi K, Wang JH. Myths and Facts of In-Office Regenerative Procedures for Tendinopathy. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2019 Jun;98(6):500-511. doi: 10.1097/PHM.0000000000001097. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30433886</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Morrey BF. Total elbow arthroplasty did not differ from open reduction and internal fixation with regard to reoperation rates. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009 Aug;91(8):2010. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.9108.ebo443.</citation>
    <PMID>19651961</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barnes DE, Beckley JM, Smith J. Percutaneous ultrasonic tenotomy for chronic elbow tendinosis: a prospective study. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2015 Jan;24(1):67-73. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2014.07.017. Epub 2014 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>25306494</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Andrews Research &amp; Education Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Todd Hayano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Primary Care Sports Medicine Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gluteal Tendinopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Trochanteric Bursitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet-Rich Plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Ultrasonic Tenotomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Orthobiologics</keyword>
  <keyword>Lateral Hip Pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tendinopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bursitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No HPI will be disclosed to anyone not involved with the study. The data will be published at the completion of the study and will be publicly available for consumption.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

