<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04294875</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JO201901-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04294875</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I, FIH, MTD for MPT0B640</brief_title>
  <acronym>MPT0B64</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase l, First in Human, Multi-centre, Open-label, Clinical Trial of MPT0B640 in Subject With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Solid Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joseah Bio</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Joseah Bio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase l, First in Human, Multi-centre, Open-label, Clinical Trial of MPT0B640 in Subject with
      Locally Advanced or Metastatic Solid Malignancies

      Phase I. Advanced or metastatic solid malignancy First in Human. HSP90 inhibitor Multi-center
      clinical trials. Open label.

      To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) or maximum feasible dose (MFD) of MPT0B640
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of the dose of MPT0B640</measure>
    <time_frame>28days(+/-2days)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Solid Tumor</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MPT0B640</intervention_name>
    <description>PO, every 3 days. dose escalation per MTD</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed, locally advanced or metastatic solid
             malignancies, such as non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), breast cancer,
             hepatocellular carcinoma, colorectal, prostate and pancreatic cancer who is not
             suitable for surgery or radiotherapy.

          2. Subjects must have received prior systemic treatment and disease progression occurred.

          3. Radiological documentation of disease progression while on a previous treatment.

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0 ~ 1

          5. 18 years and older of age (Adult)

          6. Measurable disease by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST 1.1)

          7. Laboratory values:

               1. Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5× upper limit of normal (ULN) or if higher than normal
                  range, calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) must be ≥ 50mL/min/1.73m2 (by
                  Cockroft-Gault formula); actual body weight must be used for CrCl unless body
                  mass index (BMI) &gt; 30kg/m2 then lean body weight must be used

               2. Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5×ULN unless prior history of Gilbert's syndrome.

               3. Aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) ≤ 2.5×ULN, or ≤ 5×ULN
                  if due to liver involvement by tumour.

               4. Haemoglobin ≥ 9.0g/dL.

               5. Platelets ≥ 100×109cells/L.

               6. Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5×109cells/L.

          8. Subjects signed informed contents form

          9. Expected lifespan ≥ 3 months

         10. Female should be using adequate contraceptive measures, should not breast feeding and
             must have a negative pregnancy test prior to start of dosing if of child-bearing
             potential or must have evidence of non-child-bearing potential by fulfilling one of
             the following criteria at screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) metastases which are neurologically unstable
             or requiring increasing doses of steroids within the 28 days prior to study entry to
             control their CNS disease

          2. Systemic anticancer treatment 14 days prior to the first dose of study drug on Visit 1

          3. Subjects who have undergone any major surgery* (as judged by the investigator,
             excluding placement of vascular access) ≤ 28 days of the first dose of study drug on
             Visit 1 or who have not recovered from side effects of such therapy

             *Major surgery defined as a surgical operation within or upon the contents of the
             abdominal, pelvic, cranial or thoracic cavities and a procedure which given the
             locality, condition of patient, constitutes a hazard to life or function of an organ
             or tissue. or given the locality, condition of patient, level of difficulty or length
             of time to perform, constitutes a hazard to life or function of an organ or tissue.
             Major surgery usually requires general anesthesia, a period of hospitalization of
             varying length (often a week) and may be performed by a
             general-board-certified-surgeon in a secondary care hospital, or by a surgical
             subspecialist in a tertiary care hospital.

          4. Limited-field radiotherapy ≤ 7 days or extended-field thoracic radiotherapy &lt; 28 days
             of study drug on Visit 1

          5. Subjects who had a prior history of another malignancy over the last 5 years

          6. Subjects able to swallow and retain orally administered medication and does not have
             any clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may alter absorption
             such as malabsorption syndrome or major restriction of the stomach or bowels

          7. Subjects with active human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or hepatitis B or C infection

          8. Subjects who were administered another investigational product within 3 weeks prior to
             screening

          9. Subjects with any unresolved toxicity of Grade ≥ 2 from previous anti-cancer
             treatment, except for alopecia and skin pigmentation.

         10. Subjects with any clinically significant abnormal intestinal findings that may
             interfere with the administration, passage, or absorption of the investigational
             product, which makes the subjects unable to orally take the suspension form of drugs.

         11. Abuse of drugs and medical, psychological or social conditions in subjects may
             interfere with participating in the study or assessment of the results of the study.

         12. Subjects with any condition or illness might compromise subject safety or interfere
             with the evaluation of the safety of the drug by investigator`s decision

         13. Males and females of reproductive potential who are not using an effective method of
             birth control and females who are pregnant or breastfeeding or have a positive (urine
             or serum) pregnancy test prior to study entry

         14. According to investigator's judgement, protocols cannot be followed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haein Kim</last_name>
    <phone>82-10-9930-7387</phone>
    <email>haein.kim@honorem-apac.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

