<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04296708</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EK 2019-N-161</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04296708</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ExerCube Training on Executive Functions in Young Athletes</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Influence of a Ten-week ExerCube Training on Executive Functions as Well as on Training Motivation, Enjoyment and Mental Well-being in Young Athletes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Swiss Federal Institute of Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Swiss Federal Institute of Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Competitive game sports require the existence of several sport-specific skills. In
      particular, game sport athletes need a good set of skills in order to perform well on the
      field. Therefore, it is important for athletes, especially young athletes, not only perform
      their sport, but also perform variable trainings, which differently train/trigger
      sport-specific skills. One skill set that is important in competitive game sports are
      so-called executive functions. Executive functions are needed for action planning and
      adaptation to the individual environmental situation, e.g. inhibition, flexibility and
      divided attention. A form of training that is very promising in this respect is exergaming as
      nowadays coaches are using virtual reality simulations to create realistic training
      environments. An exergame that combines this cognitive stimulation with whole-body movements
      in a motivating training environment is the ExerCube. Until now, however, evidence is lacking
      how an additional holistic exergame training can influence executive functioning in young
      athletes. Therefore, this study aims to get preliminary insight into the effects of the
      ExerCube performance on the executive function in young athletes (primary objective). The
      participants will be allocated into either the intervention group (ExerCube training) or the
      control group (no additional ExerCube training). The intervention group will train 2 times
      per week for about 30 minutes over a time frame of 10 weeks. Additionally, to consider the
      effects of the training environment, the secondary objectives include training motivation,
      enjoyment and flow as well as mental well-being.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 17, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 17, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FitLight</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the intervention, within two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>FitLight Trainer™ (Sports Corp. Ontario, Canada) is a commercially available product and consists of eight LED powered lights controlled by a wireless connection via a tablet. The tablet is running on android version 4.2.2 and has in advance a FitLight Trainer™ software to interact with the lights. With this software, it is possible to generate new specific light sequences.The FitLight allow the testing of executive functions depending on the programmed sequences. The participants use whole-body movements of arms and legs to solve the programmes sequences. Before the participants execute the main test, they perform a pre-test to minimize the learning effect and to get familiar with the test environment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Test for Attentional Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the intervention, within two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Initially the TAP (D-TAP 2.3 VL, PSYTEST, Psychologische Testsysteme, Herzogenrath, Germany) was developed to assess attentional deficits in a cerebral impaired population. The participants perform a simple reaction task.The stimuli are presented on a screen of a personal computer. Before the participants execute the main test, they perform a pre-test to minimize the learning effect and to get familiar with the test environment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Situation Motivation Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the intervention, within two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Situation Motivation Scale was designed to assess the constructs of intrinsic motivation, identified regulation, external regulation and amotivation in field and laboratory settings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Flow Short Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the intervention, within two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The first 10 items of the 7-point Likert scale measure the components of Flow-Experience as first described by Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi 1975. The items 11 - 13 measure Worry someone may have in the situation the measurement is made.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the intervention, within two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale was developed to measure physical activity enjoyment using college-aged students. The scale is a reliable and valid measure of enjoyment in physical activity environments. The PACES consist of 18 bipolar statements and a 7-point continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after the intervention, within two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This mental well-being scale is a valid measurement at a population and on an individual level. The questionnaire consists of 14 items and covers following aspects of mental health: positive affect (feelings of optimism, cheerfulness, and relaxation), satisfying interpersonal relationships, positive functioning (energy, clear thinking, self-acceptance, personal development, competence and autonomy). The higher the score is, the higher the level of mental well-being.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Effects of Exergaming on Cognitive Functions in Young Athleten</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ExerCube group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The ExerCube is an immersive fitness game setting that combines innovative soft- and hardware designs with state of-the-art training concepts. The ExerCube has three walls which serve as virtual reality projection screens and haptic interfaces. The ExerCube is a playful physical-cognitive exergame training. The user navigates a virtual environment/reality via whole body exercise. The video game navigates the user and triggers various cognitive functions. The used physical exercises are functionally and elicit the improvement of endurance and strength components. Via different monitoring systems (points and heart rate), the game adapts to the individual abilities and training level to tailor workout intensity. The ExerCube training consists of two sessions a week each session will last about 30 minutes of which 25 minutes will be pure playtime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group does not have any additional ExerCube training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exergame Training</intervention_name>
    <description>An exergame combines exercise and gaming in a holistic approach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ExerCube group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female and male

          -  Age between 15 to 20 years

          -  Young athletes (game sports)

          -  Healthy (self-reported)

          -  Able to provide written informed consent and understand instructions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of cardiovascular issue that would prevent training participation

          -  Asthma (not controllable)

          -  Musculosceletal injuries that would prevent training participation

          -  Pain that would be reinforced by sportive activities

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Human Movement Sciences and Sport, ETH Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8093</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exergaming</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Functions</keyword>
  <keyword>Young athletes</keyword>
  <keyword>Training</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

