<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04296032</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TMU-JIRB N201912049</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04296032</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Virtual Reality Game on Upper Extremity Function for Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Wearable Sensor Based Virtual Reality Game on Upper Extremity Function for Patients With Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Taipei Medical University Shuang Ho Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Taipei Medical University Shuang Ho Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Virtual reality training had already been used in stroke rehabilitation, and previous studies
      supported that it could improve upper extremity ability and increase motivation and pleasure
      than conventional methods. Pablo is a new VR game combined with motion sensor system which
      can detect subject's activities. Unlike commercial camera systems such as Kinect or XBOX, the
      systems require a continuous sightline or enough active range of motion which may increase
      risk of compensatory movement. Few of studies had investigated the rehabilitation effects on
      upper extremity with Pablo for patients with stroke.The purpose of this study is to
      investigate the effects of virtual reality upper extremity training through Pablo system in
      patients with chronic stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PURPOSE: The purpose of this study is to investigate the effects of virtual reality upper
      extremity training through Pablo system in patients with chronic stroke.

      METHODS:Patients with mild to moderate motor deficits were recruited and randomly assigned to
      &quot;VR plus standard rehabilitation group&quot;(n=19), and &quot;standard rehabilitation group&quot; (n=19).
      After 12 training sessions (60 minutes a time, 2 times a week), the performance was assessed
      by a blinded assessor. The outcome measures included Fugl-Meyer Assessment-Upper Limb
      section(FMAUE), Box and block test(BBT), Dynanometer, active range of motion of shoulder and
      elbow,and Stroke Impact Scale.Modified Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale and adverse effect
      were recorded after each sessions.Collected data will be analyzed with sample T test by SPSS
      version 20.0, and alpha level was set at 0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 25, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 25, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugl-Meyer Assessment-upper extremity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Fugl-Meyer Assessment-upper extremity (FMA-UE) measures motor impairment in the upper extremity. The assessment consists of 33 items, including movement, reflex, grasp, and coordination, and a total score of 66.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Box and block test</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Box and block test (BBT) measures unilateral gross manual dexterity. The BBT score denotes the number of blocks transferred within 60 s.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dynanometer</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The grip dynamometer was used to measure the maximum isometric strength of the hand and forearm muscles. The mean score of 3 trials was calculated. For this measurement, the elbow was placed at 90° and the forearm was placed in mid-position.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Active range of motion of shoulder and elbow</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The active range of motion of shoulder and elbow were measured through pablo system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale (SIS) is a quality of life measure designed specifically for patients with stroke. The instrument is a self-report questionnaire assessing eight domains: strength, hand function, activities of daily living (ADL)/instrumental ADL (IADL), mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, and social participation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Every training session during 18 sessions, total sessions continued to 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It is an scale that assesses enjoyment for physical activity by asking participants to rate &quot;how you feel at the moment about the physical activity you have been doing&quot; using a 7-point bipolar Likert scale, from 1 (I enjoy it) to 7 (I hate it).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse effect times</measure>
    <time_frame>Every training session during 18 sessions, total sessions continued to 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To record the adverse effect times during the therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>virtual reality group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard treatment 30 minutes plus virtual reality game 30 minutes, twice a week for 9 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>standard treatment group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard treatment 60 minutes, twice a week for 9 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>virtual reality game traning</intervention_name>
    <description>The controllers were attached to upper extremity to control the game. The game could train the shoulder, elbow, and wrist control.</description>
    <arm_group_label>virtual reality group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>standard treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>The program included bilateral hand, grasp/release, and pinch activities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>standard treatment group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>virtual reality group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  First stroke with hemiplegia,

          -  Chronicity of &gt;6 months

          -  Could understand instructions

          -  Brunnstrom stage of UE ≥IV.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who were aged &lt;20 years and &gt;75 years

          -  Patients with visual or auditory impairment who were unable to see or hear the
             feedback from the device clearly

          -  Montreal Cognitive Assessment &lt;16

          -  Modified Ashworth Scale score of &gt;2

          -  Patients with other medical symptoms that can affect movement were excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hsinchieh Lee</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Taipei Medical University, Taiwan, R.O.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hsinchieh Lee, master</last_name>
    <phone>+88622490088</phone>
    <phone_ext>1624</phone_ext>
    <email>09549@s.tmu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hatano S. Experience from a multicentre stroke register: a preliminary report. Bull World Health Organ. 1976;54(5):541-53.</citation>
    <PMID>1088404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carod-Artal J, Egido JA, González JL, Varela de Seijas E. Quality of life among stroke survivors evaluated 1 year after stroke: experience of a stroke unit. Stroke. 2000 Dec;31(12):2995-3000.</citation>
    <PMID>11108762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiu L, Shyu WC, Liu YH. Comparisons of the cost-effectiveness among hospital chronic care, nursing home placement, home nursing care and family care for severe stroke patients. J Adv Nurs. 2001 Feb;33(3):380-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11251725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nordin N, Xie SQ, Wünsche B. Assessment of movement quality in robot- assisted upper limb rehabilitation after stroke: a review. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2014 Sep 12;11:137. doi: 10.1186/1743-0003-11-137. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25217124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jang SH. The recovery of walking in stroke patients: a review. Int J Rehabil Res. 2010 Dec;33(4):285-9. doi: 10.1097/MRR.0b013e32833f0500. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20805757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kopp B, Kunkel A, Mühlnickel W, Villringer K, Taub E, Flor H. Plasticity in the motor system related to therapy-induced improvement of movement after stroke. Neuroreport. 1999 Mar 17;10(4):807-10.</citation>
    <PMID>10208552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basteris A, Nijenhuis SM, Stienen AH, Buurke JH, Prange GB, Amirabdollahian F. Training modalities in robot-mediated upper limb rehabilitation in stroke: a framework for classification based on a systematic review. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2014 Jul 10;11:111. doi: 10.1186/1743-0003-11-111. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25012864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Correction to: Guidelines for Adult Stroke Rehabilitation and Recovery: A Guideline for Healthcare Professionals From the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2017 Dec;48(12):e369. doi: 10.1161/STR.0000000000000156.</citation>
    <PMID>29180589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Susanto EA, Tong RK, Ockenfeld C, Ho NS. Efficacy of robot-assisted fingers training in chronic stroke survivors: a pilot randomized-controlled trial. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2015 Apr 25;12:42. doi: 10.1186/s12984-015-0033-5.</citation>
    <PMID>25906983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laver KE, George S, Thomas S, Deutsch JE, Crotty M. Virtual reality for stroke rehabilitation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 Feb 12;(2):CD008349. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008349.pub3. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 Nov 20;11:CD008349.</citation>
    <PMID>25927099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith, C., et al., Can non-immersive virtual reality improve physical outcomes of rehabilitation? Physical Therapy Reviews, 2012. 17(1): p. 1-15.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters DM, McPherson AK, Fletcher B, McClenaghan BA, Fritz SL. Counting repetitions: an observational study of video game play in people with chronic poststroke hemiparesis. J Neurol Phys Ther. 2013 Sep;37(3):105-11. doi: 10.1097/NPT.0b013e31829ee9bc.</citation>
    <PMID>23872681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laver, K.E., et al., Virtual reality for stroke rehabilitation. Stroke, 2018. 49(4): p. e160-e161.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin LF, Lin YJ, Lin ZH, Chuang LY, Hsu WC, Lin YH. Feasibility and efficacy of wearable devices for upper limb rehabilitation in patients with chronic stroke: a randomized controlled pilot study. Eur J Phys Rehabil Med. 2018 Jun;54(3):388-396. doi: 10.23736/S1973-9087.17.04691-3. Epub 2017 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>28627862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen HM, Chen CC, Hsueh IP, Huang SL, Hsieh CL. Test-retest reproducibility and smallest real difference of 5 hand function tests in patients with stroke. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2009 Jun;23(5):435-40. doi: 10.1177/1545968308331146. Epub 2009 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19261767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

