<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04294511</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OBU-STS-II-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04294511</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Camrelizumab in Combination With Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy in the Treatment of Osteosarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase Ⅱ ,Open-label ,Single Institution Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Camrelizumab in Combination With Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy in the Treatment of Locally , Resectable Osteosarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sun Yat-sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jiangsu HengRui Medicine Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sun Yat-sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a open-lable, , single center, phase II clinical study. Target population is
      patients with locally resectable osteosarcoma. Study objective is to compare the efficacy and
      safety of camrelizumab in combination with adriamycin, cisplatin, ifosfamide and methotrexate
      in study population in China. Camrelizumab is a humanized anti-PD1 IgG4 monoclonal antibody.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study, eligible subject will be enrolled into study arm to accept study treatment.
      Treatment cycles of chemotherapy will be at most 9 cycles which will be decided by
      investigators. The percentage of the patient with tumor cell necrosis rate ＞90% determined by
      the Independent Review Committee (IRC) will be the primary outcome measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 16, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 16, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>tumor cell necrosis rate (TCNR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2 years Overall Survival (OS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients overall survival in 2 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2 years Progression-free survival (PFS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients Progression-free survival in 2 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse event/Serious adverse event that occurred during the study period according to CTCAE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>camrelizumab in combination with adriamycin, cisplatin, ifosfamide and methotrexate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Camrelizumab in Combination With Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>camrelizumab in combination with adriamycin, cisplatin, ifosfamide and methotrexate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PD-1 inhibitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 14 to 65 year old

          2. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 0-1

          3. Histopathologically diagnosed osteosarcomas (except for paraspesarcomas ), have been
             evaluated in patients have achieved normative resection with neoadjuvant chemotherapy

          4. Having measurable lesion according to RECIST 1.1

          5. Life expectancy &gt;3 months

          6. Patients must have adequate organ function

          7. Fertile men and women of childbearing potential must agree to use an effective method
             of birth control from providing signed consent and for 120 days after last study drug
             administration. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test ≤
             72 hours prior to Day 1 of study

          8. Voluntary informed consent , joining the study with good compliance

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. pregnant or lactating women

          2. Known history of hypersensitivity to any components of the camrelizumab formulation,
             or other antibody formulation.

          3. Active central nervous system (CNS) metastases with clinical symptoms , including
             cerebral edema, steroid requirement, or progressive disease.

          4. Patients with other malignant tumor within 5 years , except cured skin basal cell
             carcinoma, cervical carcinoma and Papillary carcinoma of thyroid.

          5. Clinically significant cardiovascular diseases

          6. Patients have had prior treatment with PD-1/PD-L1 or CTLA-4 antagonists.Received any
             study drug within 4 weeks prior to the first study drug administration. Enroll in
             another clinical study, unless it is an observational (non-interventional) clinical
             study or an intervention follow-up study. Concurrent medical condition requiring the
             use of immunosuppressive medications, or immunosuppressive doses of systemic or
             absorbable topical corticosteroids. Doses &gt; 10 mg/day prednisone or equivalent are
             prohibited within 2 weeks before study drug administration. Note: corticosteroids used
             for the allergy and nausea, vomiting are allowed. Inhaled or topical use of steroids
             and adrenocorticosteroid replacement in doses greater than 10mg/ day is permitted in
             the absence of active autoimmune disease.Patients who have received a live vaccine
             within 30 days prior to the first study drug administration.Major surgery or major
             trauma within 4 weeks of first study drug administration. Left ventricular ejection
             fraction (LVEF) is more than 60% .

        (7)Severe infection occurred within 4 weeks before the first first study drug
        administration (CTC AE &gt; grade 2) (8)Patients with any active autoimmune disease or history
        of autoimmune disease, including but not limited to the following: hepatitis, pneumonitis,
        uveitis, colitis (inflammatory bowel disease), hypophysitis, vasculitis, nephritis,
        hyperthyroidism, and hypothyroidism except for subjects with vitiligo or resolved childhood
        asthma/atopy. Asthma that requires intermittent use of bronchodilators or other medical
        intervention should also be excluded. Stable dose of insulin for type 1 diabetes.

        (9)History of immunodeficiency including seropositivity for human immunodeficiency virus
        (HIV), or other acquired or congenital immune-deficient disease, or organ transplantation
        and bone marrow transplantation.

        (10)Objective evidence of previous or current pulmonary fibrosis history, interstitial
        pneumonia, pneumoconiosis, radiation pneumonitis, drug-related pneumonia, pulmonary
        function damaged seriously etc.

        (11)History of active pulmonary tuberculosis infection, or with a history of active
        pulmonary tuberculosis infection within 1 year prior to enrollment, or with a history of
        active pulmonary tuberculosis infection prior to 1 year but without formal treatment.

        (12)Active hepatitis (transaminase does not meet the inclusion, hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA
        ≥10⁴ /ml or hepatitis C virus (HCV) RNA≥103 /ml or higher); Chronic hepatitis B virus
        carriers who HBV DNA＜2000 IU/ml(&lt;104/ml), must receive anti-viral treatment throughout the
        study.

        (13)Known history of psychotropic substance abuse, alcohol abuse and drug abuse.

        (14)The investigators did not think the participants were suitable for inclusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jin WANG, MD</last_name>
    <phone>020-87343910</phone>
    <email>wangjinr@sysucc.org.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Center of Sun-Yat Sen University (CCSYSU)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510060</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jin Wang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>020-87343910</phone>
      <email>wangjinr@sysucc.org.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jin Wang,MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of bone and soft tissue</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

