<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04296201</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LUM-ABU-DMA-20-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04296201</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Immediate Effect and Safety of DMA™ Novel Muscle Stimulation Technology</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Immediate Effect and Safety of DMA™ Novel Muscle Stimulation Technology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lumenis Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lumenis Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A total of at least 15 and up to 17 healthy subjects at a single site, aged 25-45 years old,
      who wish to receive a lifting effect and improved muscle definition, will be included in the
      study.

      The procedure will include treatments with the Legend Pro™ DMA™ technology. Photos will be
      obtained at pre-defined time points throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Single center, prospective, open Label with Before &amp; After Study Design. This study is
      designed to evaluate the immediate efficacy and safety of Legend Pro™'s DMA™ muscle
      stimulation technology. Treatment areas will include the face, buttocks, or abdominal region.
      Each subject will receive 1 treatment with no follow-up visits required. Interim assessment
      will be held after half of the study population has received treatment.

      The study population will be divided into three arms as follows:

        -  5 female subjects will receive treatment in the face area

        -  5 female subjects will receive treatment in the buttocks area

        -  5 male subjects will receive treatment in the abdominal region
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 10, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the immediate effects and safety of DMATM novel muscle stimulation technology on the face, buttocks, and abdominal regions: GAI scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy of the treatment will be based on before and after photography. Efficacy will be established by the Global Aesthetic Improvement scale (GAI) completed by the Principal investigator. Success is defined as an improvement of at least 1 point on the GAI scale assessed by the investigator, as compared to baseline.
Global Aesthetic Improvement (GAI) Scale:
Worse (0), No change (1), Somewhat improved (2), Moderately improved (3), Very Much Improved (4)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate procedure-related skin safety, subject discomfort, and subject satisfaction: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary endpoint will be assessed by the following:
• Subject satisfaction questionnaire
Safety End-Points:
Immediate skin response (erythema, edema, etc.) following each treatment as evaluated by the investigator.
Subject assessment of pain and discomfort associated with treatments using a Pain Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), were 0 is &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 is &quot;intolerable pain&quot;
Skin safety throughout the study as determined by the investigator by examining the post-treatment occurrences of complications and adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Skin Laxity</condition>
  <condition>Muscle Contracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment in the face area</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 female subjects will receive treatment in the face area</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment in the buttocks area</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 female subjects will receive treatment in the buttocks area</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment in the abdominal region</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 male subjects will receive treatment in the abdominal region</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DMA treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Each arm will receive the DMA treatment in a specific area on the body to observe immediate effect.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment in the abdominal region</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment in the buttocks area</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment in the face area</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject read, understood and signed the Consent Form

          2. Healthy male or female aged 25-45 years,

          3. Fitzpatrick skin type 1-6

          4. Subject is capable of reading, understanding and following instructions of the
             procedure to be applied.

          5. Subject is able and willing to comply with the treatment.

          6. Women of child-bearing potential are required to use two forms of reliable methods of
             birth control (such as an intrauterine device, birth control pills, condom with
             spermicidal, NuvaRing, partner with vasectomy, Implanon or other FDA-approved devices,
             or abstinence) during the course of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        General

          1. Subject is female who is pregnant, lactating, or plans to become pregnant during the
             study period or had given birth less than 6 months ago.

          2. Concurrent participation in any other study.

             Specific to the treatment and treatment area

          3. Subject has a pacemaker or internal defibrillator, implanted neurostimulators or any
             other internal electric device or patient who had an implant in the past.

          4. Subject has metal or other implants in the treatment area (Not including dental
             fillings, implants and crowns).

          5. Subject has significant concurrent skin conditions affecting areas to be treated such
             as sores, bleeding, skin fragility, eczema or psoriasis.

          6. Subject has burned, blistered, irritated, or sensitive skin due to excessive fresh
             tanning in areas to be treated or is unlikely to refrain from excessive tanning during
             the study.

             Other treatments

          7. Subject has used oral isotretinoin (Accutane or Roaccutan®) within 6 months prior to
             study enrollment or plans use during the course of the study.

          8. Subject has used topical retinoids in past 1 month

             Medical conditions/ use of medication

          9. Subject has current or history of systemic cancer; premalignant skin lesion or skin
             concern treatment area.

         10. Subject has severe concurrent conditions such as epilepsy, autoimmune, pulmonary or
             cardiac disorders.

         11. Subject has poorly controlled endocrine disorders such as diabetes.

         12. Subject has an impaired immune system due to immunosuppressive diseases such as HIV or
             AIDS, or use of immunosuppressive medications.

         13. Subject has history of collagen disorders, keloid formation or abnormal wound healing.

         14. Subject takes or has taken medications, herbal preparations, food supplements or
             vitamins that might cause fragile skin or impaired skin healing

         15. Subject has used oral steroids in past 6 months

         16. Subject has used topical steroids in past 3 months

         17. Subject has history of bleeding coagulopathies or use of anticoagulants.

         18. Use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS, e.g. ibuprofen containing
             agents) one week before and after each treatment session prior to treatment

         19. Subject has mental disorders that in the opinion of the Investigator would be
             interfere with ability to comply with the study requirements.

         20. Subject has any other medical condition that in the opinion of the Investigator
             warrants exclusion from this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dermatology, Laser, and Vein Specialists of the Carolinas, PLLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Razia Ludin, MHA, BSc, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>704-973-3687</phone>
      <email>RaziaL@carolinaskin.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Girish (Gilly) Munavalli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Contracture</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

