<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04292275</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20180096</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04292275</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heart Failure Study to Evaluate Vital Signs and Overcome Low Use of Guideline-Directed Therapy by Remote Monitoring</brief_title>
  <acronym>HF-eVOLUTION</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-Label, Standard-of-Care-Controlled, Multicenter Study to Evaluate Digital Health Data Use in Managing Guideline-Directed Heart Failure Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A study evaluating the impact of remotely collected data, measured using digital
      technologies, on the use of guideline-recommended heart failure therapy in adult participants
      with heart failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 26, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 26, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Change or Decision That Heart Failure Therapy is Optimal</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the curve (AUC) will be calculated for a daily dose-related medication score for beta-blocker, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor/angiotensin II receptor blocker/angiotensin neprilysin inhibitor, and aldosterone antagonist therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to change or decision that heart failure therapy is optimal</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the curve (AUC) will be calculated for a daily dose-related medication score for beta-blocker, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor/angiotensin II receptor blocker/angiotensin neprilysin inhibitor, and aldosterone antagonist therapy, time to change or decision that dose is optimal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numerical Health Information Technology Usability Evaluation Scale for Healthcare Provider Scores (Health-ITUES-HCP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Health-ITUES-HCP will be used to assess the healthcare provider's experience with the digital health tool(s) and data presentation. The scale consists of 36 items. A higher score indicated higher perceived usability of the technology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numerical Health Information Technology Usability Evaluation Scale for Participants (Health-ITUES-Subject) Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Health-ITUES-Subject will be used to assess the participant's experience with the digital health tool(s). The scale consists of 36 items. A higher score indicated higher perceived usability of the technology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Numerical Rating of Subject Satisfaction with Heart Failure Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a subject satisfaction survey (5 point Likert scale format) ranging from very satisfied to very dissatisfied.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ-23) Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The KCCQ-23 is a 23-item questionnaire to measure the participant's perception of their health status, which includes heart failure symptoms, impact on physical and social function, and how their heart failure impacts their quality of life. All items are measured on a Likert scale with 5-7 response options. Scores for each item are standardized to range from 0 to 100 with higher scores indicating better health status, fewer symptoms, and greater disease-specific health-related quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Digital Health Tools + Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biobeat Wrist Watch</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care procedures and therapies for managing heart failure will be carried out according to each investigator's standard procedures. In addition, participants will be provided with a Biobeat wrist watch for continuous measurement and reporting of blood pressure data and with a smartphone to report weight.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Digital Health Tools + Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care procedures and therapies for managing heart failure will be carried out according to each investigator's standard procedures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Digital Health Tools + Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  History of chronic heart failure.

          -  Ejection fraction equal to or below 40%.

          -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II to class III.

          -  Enrollment during or within 30 days after a hospitalization, emergency department, or
             urgent, unscheduled clinic/office visit with primary diagnosis of heart failure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has received a major organ transplant (e.g., lung, liver, heart, bone marrow, kidney).

          -  Currently in an investigational device or drug study.

          -  Unwilling or unable to wear a digital wrist watch device for measuring blood pressure
             and other parameters during waking hours.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amgen Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>866-572-6436</phone>
    <email>medinfo@amgen.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>50702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tullahoma</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37388</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Digital health</keyword>
  <keyword>Remote monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Wearable device</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual patient data for variables necessary to address the specific research question in an approved data sharing request</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data sharing requests relating to this study will be considered beginning 18 months after the study has ended. There is no end date for eligibility to submit a data sharing request for this study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Qualified researchers may submit a request containing the research objectives, the Amgen study/studies in scope, endpoints/outcomes of interest, statistical analysis plan, data requirements, publication plan, and qualifications of the researcher(s). Requests are reviewed by a committee of internal advisors. If not approved, a Data Sharing Independent Review Panel will arbitrate and make the final decision. Upon approval, information necessary to address the research question will be provided under the terms of a data sharing agreement. This may include anonymized individual patient data and/or available supporting documents, containing fragments of analysis code where provided in analysis specifications. Further details are available at the URL below.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.amgen.com/datasharing</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

