<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04292288</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-19010297</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04292288</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypercalcemia After Paraffin Oil Injection</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hypercalcemia After Paraffin Oil Injection: Aetiology, Pathogenesis and Possible Treatment Options</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Martin Blomberg Jensen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Herlev Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Today, there is an increased use of non-medical, invasive cosmetic treatments globally
      without sufficient awareness of possible health risks. A particular problem is young men
      injecting large amounts of paraffin oil into skeletal muscles especially on upper arms and
      chest to increase the visible size of the muscles. Several case reports have suggested that
      intramuscular injection of paraffin oil induces foreign body reaction and granuloma formation
      and subsequently hypercalcemia. Our hypothesis is that increased generation of activated
      vitamin D (1,25(OH)2D3) in the marcrophages may be responsible for the persistent
      hypercalcemia. Now trhe investigators want to include a large group of men who injected
      100-10.000 ml paraffin oil to identify risk factors for developing hypercalcemia and try to
      understand the pathogenesis of the disease. Additionally, granuloma tissue from selected
      patients will be cultured ex vivo to investigate whether they produce 1,25(OH)2D3 or PTHrP
      and to test which drugs can most effectively be used to lower calcium levels in these men.
      Subsequently, we will try to stratify the men according to the severity of the changes in
      calcium homeostasis as we suggest that this stratification will be the basis for future
      intervention trials
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Today, there is an increased use of non-medical, invasive cosmetic treatments globally
      without sufficient awareness of possible health risks. A particular problem is young men
      injecting large amounts of paraffin oil into skeletal muscles especially on upper arms and
      chest to increase the visible size of the muscles. Several case reports have suggested that
      intramuscular injection of paraffin oil induces foreign body reaction and granuloma
      formation. The formation of granuloma probably precedes the marked hypercalcemia that often
      develops and appears to be difficult to treat. The largest study to date included 14 men and
      showed that practically all men developed serious hypercalcemia, but the etiology was
      unclear. Foreign body granulomas are like other granulomatous diseases such as Tuberculosis
      or sarcoidosis rich in macrophages, (ref) and it has been proposed that increased generation
      of activated vitamin D (1,25(OH)2D3) in the marcrophages may be responsible for the
      persistent hypercalcemia.

      Calcium homeostasis is tightly regulated primarily by vitamin D, Parathyroid hormone (PTH)
      and Fibroblast growth factor 23 (FGF23) that rapidly modifies intestinal absorption, renal
      excretion and calcium mobilization from the skeletal compartment in response to immediate
      changes in serum calcium (ref). Vitamin D (cholecalciferol) is normally formed by UV-B
      radiation of the skin and requires two enzymatic reactions before it can bind and activate
      the vitamin D receptor (VDR). Conversion of cholecalciferol to 25-hydroxydvitamin (25OHD) is
      the first activation step; it is un-regulated and generally exerted by the hepatic CYP2R1.
      25OHD is not biologically active and must undergo 1-alpha hydroxylation by renal CYP27B1 to
      form the active metabolite 1,25(OH)2D3. The main actions of 1,25(OH)2D3 is to promote calcium
      and phosphate absorption and decrease calcium excretion until inactivated by CYP24A1.
      1,25(OH)2D3 is also a powerful inhibitor of PTH and inducer of FGF23, which ensures an
      important feedback-loop to maintain an adequate vitamin D status (ref). PTH which is a potent
      inducer of CYP27B1, mobilizes calcium and phosphate from the skeleton and increases phosphate
      excretion. In contrast, FGF23 that inhibits CYP27B1, induces the in-activating CYP24A1 and
      promotes phosphate excretion. Almost all organs has the ability to activate, respond to, and
      inactivate vitamin D because CYP27B1, VDR and CYP24A1 are expressed also in most non-renal
      tissues. However, regulation of CYP27B1 and CYP24A1 is strikingly different in these organs
      where high intracellular levels of 1,25(OH)2D3 activates VDR that induces transcription of
      CYP24A1 and thereby increases in-activation to restore normal intracellular levels of all
      vitamin D metabolites. This autoregulatory control of vitamin D metabolites secures under
      normal circumstances that high concentrations of 1,25(OH)2D3 are not released into
      circulation. Regulation of vitamin D homeostasis is different in the macrophages present in
      granulomas because they retain a splice variant of CYP24A1 that is not upregulated in
      response to high 1,25(OH)2D3 levels, which in part explains the increased release of
      1,25(OH)2D3 in granulomatosis disease. Another important issue is aberrant regulation of
      CYP27B1 in macrophages, which is induced by inflammatory signals such as interleukin-2 and
      TNF-alpha rather than PTH. Previous case reports have detected CYP27B1 expression in
      granuloma tissue by immunohistochemistry. However, these findings have to our knowledge never
      been corroborated by a more comprehensive analysis of enzyme activity and a recent study
      questioned the etiology because most men with granulomas had normal levels of 1,25(OH)2D3 in
      serum (ref).

      In the present study the investigators want to include a large group of men who injected
      100-10.000 ml paraffin oil to identify risk factors for developing hypercalcemia and try to
      understand the pathogenesis of the disease. Additionally, granuloma tissue from selected
      patients will be cultured ex vivo to investigate whether they produce 1,25(OH)2D3 or PTHrP
      and to test which drugs can most effectively be used to lower calcium levels in these men.
      Subsequently, elucidate whether it is possible to stratify the men according to the severity
      of the changes in calcium homeostasis as such a stratification may be required prior to and
      form the basis for future intervention trials
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypercalcemia</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>the number of men with elevated ionized calcium (above 1.32 mmol/l)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>production of 1,25OHD3</measure>
    <time_frame>ex vivo culture experiments of human granuloma tissue for 48 to 72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>production of 1,25OHD3 determined in media from granuloma tissue culture compared with kidney culture by ELISA platform</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hypercalciuria</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection</time_frame>
    <description>calcium excretion determined by spot or 24 hour urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in serum 1,25OH2D3</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>differences in calcitriol production or conversion rate 1,25OH2D3/25OHD that reflects how active the enzyme is</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>nephrolithiasis</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>obtained by interview -anamnesis and preferably supported by jorunal of CT report on nephrolithiasis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall change in calcium homeostasis</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>changes in calcium, PTH, alkaline phosphatase and 1,25OHD depending on oil injected, varm/cold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>inflammatory response</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>changes in inflammatory markers IL2R, ferritin, ACE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone formation and resorption</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Serum levels of alkaline phosphatase, C-terminal telopeptide of type I collagen (CTX-I) and N-terminal propeptide of type I procollagen (PINP)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>renal function</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>change in GFR, creatinine, Urea</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>calciphylaxis</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>risk determined by Calcium - phosphate product</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Suppressed PTH</measure>
    <time_frame>determined 2-10 years after paraffin oil injection (first visit)</time_frame>
    <description>PTH lower than lower reference (2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>suppression of 1,25OHD3 production</measure>
    <time_frame>ex vivo culture experiments of human granuloma tissue exposed to treatments for 48 and 72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>production of 1,25OHD3 released into the media from granuloma culture suppressed by different treatments in vitro</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>production of PTHrP</measure>
    <time_frame>ex vivo culture experiments of human granuloma tissue for 48 and 72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>PTHrP production in granuloma determined by ELISA platform</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypercalcemia</condition>
  <condition>Granuloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Foreign body granuloma</arm_group_label>
    <description>men injecting paraffin oil</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biochemical observational</intervention_name>
    <description>no intervention - observational</description>
    <arm_group_label>Foreign body granuloma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Up to 200 people (predominantly men) &lt;80 years will be included. Inclusion takes place at
        Endocrinological Section, Medical Department O, Herlev Hospital in connection with an
        outpatient visit. After initial discussions, reflection time and acceptance of
        participation in the study, extended blood tests are taken in connection with the
        pre-planned outpatient visits.

        In the outpatient course, a DXA scan of the person's bones in the spine and femur will be
        performed. It is part of the routine examination of these individuals
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: • previous injection of oil into the body

        -

        Exclusion Criteria: inability to walk, inability to undertand the consequences of inclusion
        or incurable cancer disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>no females</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ebbe Eldrup</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Herlev</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Blomberg Jensen</last_name>
    <phone>+4535453545</phone>
    <email>blombergjensen@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ebbe Eldrup</last_name>
    <phone>+4538683868</phone>
    <email>Ebbe.Eldrup@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herlev Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herlev</city>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ebbe Eldrup</last_name>
      <phone>+4538683868</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Blomberg Jensen</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Martin Blomberg Jensen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Group leader</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Granuloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypercalcemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

