<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04295954</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DISMYOGA01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04295954</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Semi-Presence Yoga Program on Primary Dysmenorrhea</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of a Semi-Presence Yoga Program, With Virtual Tutorized Home Tracking, on Dysmenorrhea in University Students: Randomized an Controlled Clinical Trial Protocol.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Huelva</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Huelva</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of a yoga program on menstrual pain,
      symptomatology and other associated problems.

      Half of the women involved will receive a yoga intervention for dysmenorrhea for 12 weeks,
      while the other half will continue with their conventional treatment during the same period.
      The results of the evaluations carried out prior, to the month, 3 months, 6 and 12 months of
      the intervention will be compared.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dysmenorrhea affects between 50% and 90% of women of childbearing age worldwide, the figure
      is estimated to be 74.8% in Spain. In addition to pain, other menstrual symptoms affect the
      normality of those with it, and it is found to cause absenteeism at work and school and
      influence academic performance. Self-medication with painkillers is one of the most used
      self-care measures by women with dysmenorrhea despite not being the most appropriate. So, in
      recent decades new lines are being investigated that can help reduce the impact of the
      problem on women with dysmenorrhea.

      According to several studies, physical exercise is an effective supportive therapy in
      dysmenorrhea, and in particular through yoga has been found relief from menstrual symptoms
      and associated anguish, and improvement in pain and quality of life. The practice of yoga has
      shown physical, emotional and general well-being improvements. But it is advisable to
      continue to investigate because of the heterogeneity if the interventions it is difficult to
      reach consensus as to the time and frequency of the sessions, program duration or type of
      yoga program and the most appropriate postures. It is therefore recommended to unify the
      characteristics of the participants, describe the programs in detail, extend the duration of
      clinical trials, and carry them out with greater methodological rigor.

      A novel aspect of this specific yoga program for dysmenorrhea is the semi-presence and home
      virtual tutoring of the intervention that will make it easier for women to practice at home
      according to their time possibilities or their health status, being guided by experts and
      supported with validated material for the intervention. Online tutoring and monitoring can
      promote adherence, compliance with intervention more rigorously, and even use of more
      advisable self-care measures, as evidenced by previous studies with patients with other
      health problems.

      So, this clinical trial is intended to analyse the effects of a 12-week tutored semi-presence
      yoga and meditation program in a group of nursing students from Andalusian province,
      comparing the results with a group of similar characteristics who does not receive the
      intervention and will continue with their conventional treatment. They will be evaluated in
      advance, within a month, 3 months, 6 months and one year after receiving the intervention.
      The project has been approved by the Andalusian Ethics and Research Committee.

      The yoga program has been designed according to previous studies for dysmenorrhea and the
      Guidelines for Developing Yoga Interventions for Randomized Trials. It is a Hatha Yoga
      Intervention for dysmenorrhea, i.e. body, respiratory and mental work led by teachers with
      more than 600 hours of accredited training and at least 300 hours of experience with adults
      with varied chronic health conditions. The program has been triangulated by experts and
      piloted after. It will be held at the Centre of Physical and Sports Activities of the El
      Carmen University Campus of the University of Huelva. The intervention consists of three
      weekly 30-minute yoga sessions for 12 weeks. The first 4 weeks 1 face to face session and 2
      home yoga sessions guided by the yoga teacher will be taught weekly in all cases. At home,
      the participants will also have a video and a diptych of the same yoga series designed for
      this trial. There will be a virtual platform to project participants by the yoga teacher and
      researchers. After the first 4 weeks they will continue with 3 weekly sessions of 30 minutes
      each, of directed home yoga also. At six weeks there will be a new face to face session to
      assess achievements or difficulties, and gather information, if it is necessary. Each session
      consists of physical postures or preparation asanas, and they are a means to reach the
      central asanas &quot;cobra, cat and fish&quot;. Followed by asanas of compensation, relaxation and
      meditation.

      Our hypothesis is that compared to the group that continues with its conventional treatment
      and has not made changes to its lifestyle, participation in the yoga program will be
      associated with improvements in pain intensity (VAS) and symptomatology associated with
      dysmenorrhea, absenteeism, academic performance, daytime tiredness, stress and well-being,
      among other secondary outcomes
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two groups will be formed with women who meet the inclusion criteria. Each participant will be randomly assigned to each group, receiving different treatment depending on the group in which it has been assigned: the intervention group will receive yoga intervention and the control group will continue with its conventional treatment for the dysmenorrhea.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The assignment to groups will be blind. A random number computer application will be awarded each participant to a group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Pain Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline pain intensity at 1 month; Change from baseline pain intensity at 3 months; Change from baseline pain intensity at 6 months; Change from baseline pain intensity at 12 months;</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity will be assessed with the Visual Analog Pain Scale (VAS): Is a continuous scale consisting of a horizontal line of 10 centimeters (100 mm) in length, ranging &quot;painless&quot; (score of 0) to &quot;pain as severe as it could be&quot; or &quot;worst imaginable pain&quot; (score of 100).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Satisfaction and Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline Quality of Life at 1 month; Changes from baseline Quality of Life at 3 months; Changes from baseline Quality of Life at 6 months; Changes from baseline Quality of Life at 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be evaluated with the SF-12 Abbreviated Quality of Life Questionnaire, with consists of 12 quality of life items measured o a Likert scale between 0 and 6. Explore multidimensional health and self-administer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline,1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality will be measured with the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). It is a self-report scale that is completed in 5 minutes; it consists of 19 items and contains seven subscales each weighted equally on a scale of 0 to 3, with higher scores indicating a lower sleep quality rating. The total sum ranging from 0 (good sleep quality) to 21 (poor sleep quality) reflects poor sleep if it is ≥ 5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of drowsiness</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Degree of drowsiness will be measured with the Epworth Sleepiness Questionnaire (ESE), a self-applicable instrument for assessing the propensity to fall asleep in eight situations. Each is evaluated on a scale of 0-3, where 0 means zero probability of falling asleep and 3 high probability. The sum of the grades results: 0-24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety State</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety as a state, will be measured using the STAI Status Scale, Spielberger. Will assesse how an individual feels at a given time. The scale include 20 items using a 4-points Likert scale (20 to 80). Higher scores indicate an increase in anxiety levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety Traits</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety as a trait, will be measured using the STAI Spielberger Trait. Anxiety traits will assesse how an individual feels in general. Include 20 items using a 4-points Likert scale (20 to 80). Higher scores indicate an increase in anxiety levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Stress will be measured with the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS), is a self-reporting instrument that assesses the perceived stress level over the last month, consists of 14 items ith a five points scale response format (0= never, 1= almost never, 2= from time to time, 3= often, 4= very often). The highest score corresponds to a higher level of perceived stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of change</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The perception of degree of change on the overall state will be measured with the Grade of Change Perception Scale (GAC), with the following gradation &quot;Much worse/ worse /a little better / same / a little better/ better&quot; until &quot;much better&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Well-being will be measured by the Spanish version of the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Welfare Scale (EBMWE). The questionnaire has 14 items, with 5 answer options (from 1 to 5). Higher scores indicate better mental well-being.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Menstrual symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>It will be evaluated with 13 closed dichotomous questions, about presence or absence of vomiting, dizziness, headaches, irritability, edema, headaches, constipation, diarrhea, tiredness, anxiety among others.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Menstrual Attitude</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>It will be evaluated using the MAQ (Brooks-Gunn &amp; Ruble 1980) Menstrual Attitude Questionnaire. The Mentrual Attitude Questionnaire is a useful tool for evaluating menstrual attitudes among high school and college students. It consists of 7 answer options, in which 1 means &quot;totally disagree&quot; and 7 &quot;totally agree&quot;. It is self-administered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Dysmenorrhea Primary</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Menstrual</condition>
  <condition>Yoga</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Yoga Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive the Yoga Intervention for dysmenorrhea that will consist of 3 yoga sessions a week of 30 minutes each, for 12 weeks. The first 4 weeks 1 of the sessions will be face to face and the other 2 home sessions guided by a vieo and a brochure, and tutored from the virtual platform by the yoga teacher and researchers. This space will also serve for participants to share experiences.
After the first 4 weeks, participants will continue with the virtually tutored home yoga program, consisting of 3 weekly sessions of 30 minutes until completing the 12 weeks. They will be protected in all cases by the teacher and researchers.
After 6 weeks there will be a face to face session where progress or difficulties will be assessed.
They will be evaluated before the start of the yoga program per month, 3 months, 6 months and a year after the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group without intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the comparison group without intervention will not receive yoga intervention, will follow their conventional treatment and their usual daily activities. They will be told not to do yoga. They will be evaluated in advance, per a month, 3 months, 6 months and a year after the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Yoga Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>It is an intervention based on Hatha yoga designed specifically to improve dysmenorrhea. This intervention consists of physical postures, also called asanas; meditation and breathing. It begins with a progression of various asanas until reaching the three central postures: &quot;cat, cobra and fish&quot;. The compensation asanas of these central postures are then performed, and it is closed with a relaxation. The program and Yoga Intervention have been triangulated by experts and piloted afterwards.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Yoga Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Nulliparous women who exhibit moderate-severe pain, 4-10 according to VAS, associated
        with menstruation in their last cycle, have no history of diagnosed gynecological
        pathology, and have an internet access device (mobile, computer or table).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Those who do not meet the criteria for inclusion or do not wish to participated
        voluntarily, suffer from any other illnesses associated with pain or limiting physical
        exercise, as well as exclude women who already perform yoga.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>female, nulliparous</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ana Abreu Sánchez, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad de Huelva, Facultad de Enfermería</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ana Abreu Sánchez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34-680-507-555</phone>
    <phone_ext>88335</phone_ext>
    <email>abreu@uhu.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elia Fernández Martínez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34-959-218-310</phone>
    <phone_ext>88310</phone_ext>
    <email>elia.fernandez@denf.uhu.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iacovides S, Avidon I, Baker FC. What we know about primary dysmenorrhea today: a critical review. Hum Reprod Update. 2015 Nov-Dec;21(6):762-78. doi: 10.1093/humupd/dmv039. Epub 2015 Sep 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26346058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Martínez E, Onieva-Zafra MD, Parra-Fernández ML. Lifestyle and prevalence of dysmenorrhea among Spanish female university students. PLoS One. 2018 Aug 10;13(8):e0201894. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0201894. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30096156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGovern CE, Cheung C. Yoga and Quality of Life in Women with Primary Dysmenorrhea: A Systematic Review. J Midwifery Womens Health. 2018 Jul;63(4):470-482. doi: 10.1111/jmwh.12729. Epub 2018 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29902363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Martínez E, Onieva-Zafra MD, Parra-Fernández ML. The Impact of Dysmenorrhea on Quality of Life Among Spanish Female University Students. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019 Feb 27;16(5). pii: E713. doi: 10.3390/ijerph16050713.</citation>
    <PMID>30818861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armour M, Smith CA, Steel KA, Macmillan F. The effectiveness of self-care and lifestyle interventions in primary dysmenorrhea: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2019 Jan 17;19(1):22. doi: 10.1186/s12906-019-2433-8.</citation>
    <PMID>30654775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armour M, Ee CC, Naidoo D, Ayati Z, Chalmers KJ, Steel KA, de Manincor MJ, Delshad E. Exercise for dysmenorrhoea. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2019 Sep 20;9:CD004142. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004142.pub4.</citation>
    <PMID>31538328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross A, Thomas S. The health benefits of yoga and exercise: a review of comparison studies. J Altern Complement Med. 2010 Jan;16(1):3-12. doi: 10.1089/acm.2009.0044. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20105062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cramer H, Lauche R, Anheyer D, Pilkington K, de Manincor M, Dobos G, Ward L. Yoga for anxiety: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Depress Anxiety. 2018 Sep;35(9):830-843. doi: 10.1002/da.22762. Epub 2018 Apr 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29697885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCall MC, Ward A, Roberts NW, Heneghan C. Overview of systematic reviews: yoga as a therapeutic intervention for adults with acute and chronic health conditions. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2013;2013:945895. doi: 10.1155/2013/945895. Epub 2013 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23762174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dodich A, Zollo M, Crespi C, Cappa SF, Laureiro Martinez D, Falini A, Canessa N. Short-term Sahaja Yoga meditation training modulates brain structure and spontaneous activity in the executive control network. Brain Behav. 2019 Jan;9(1):e01159. doi: 10.1002/brb3.1159. Epub 2018 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30485713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SD. Yoga for menstrual pain in primary dysmenorrhea: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2019 Aug;36:94-99. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2019.06.006. Epub 2019 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>31383452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yonglitthipagon P, Muansiangsai S, Wongkhumngern W, Donpunha W, Chanavirut R, Siritaratiwat W, Mato L, Eungpinichpong W, Janyacharoen T. Effect of yoga on the menstrual pain, physical fitness, and quality of life of young women with primary dysmenorrhea. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2017 Oct;21(4):840-846. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2017.01.014. Epub 2017 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>29037637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armour M, Parry K, Al-Dabbas MA, Curry C, Holmes K, MacMillan F, Ferfolja T, Smith CA. Self-care strategies and sources of knowledge on menstruation in 12,526 young women with dysmenorrhea: A systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2019 Jul 24;14(7):e0220103. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0220103. eCollection 2019.</citation>
    <PMID>31339951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collins SL, Moore RA, McQuay HJ. The visual analogue pain intensity scale: what is moderate pain in millimetres? Pain. 1997 Aug;72(1-2):95-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9272792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherman KJ. Guidelines for developing yoga interventions for randomized trials. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2012;2012:143271. doi: 10.1155/2012/143271. Epub 2012 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23082079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeter PE, Slutsky J, Singh N, Khalsa SB. Yoga as a Therapeutic Intervention: A Bibliometric Analysis of Published Research Studies from 1967 to 2013. J Altern Complement Med. 2015 Oct;21(10):586-92. doi: 10.1089/acm.2015.0057. Epub 2015 Jul 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26196166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ware J Jr, Kosinski M, Keller SD. A 12-Item Short-Form Health Survey: construction of scales and preliminary tests of reliability and validity. Med Care. 1996 Mar;34(3):220-33.</citation>
    <PMID>8628042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF 3rd, Monk TH, Berman SR, Kupfer DJ. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res. 1989 May;28(2):193-213.</citation>
    <PMID>2748771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johns MW. A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale. Sleep. 1991 Dec;14(6):540-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1798888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrer M, Vilagut G, Monasterio C, Montserrat JM, Mayos M, Alonso J. [Measurement of the perceived impact of sleep problems: the Spanish version of the functional outcomes sleep questionnaire and the Epworth sleepiness scale]. Med Clin (Barc). 1999 Sep 11;113(7):250-5. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>10544379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983 Dec;24(4):385-96.</citation>
    <PMID>6668417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>López MA, Gabilondo A, Codony M, García-Forero C, Vilagut G, Castellví P, Ferrer M, Alonso J. Adaptation into Spanish of the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (WEMWBS) and preliminary validation in a student sample. Qual Life Res. 2013 Jun;22(5):1099-104. doi: 10.1007/s11136-012-0238-z. Epub 2012 Jul 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22836376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castellví P, Forero CG, Codony M, Vilagut G, Brugulat P, Medina A, Gabilondo A, Mompart A, Colom J, Tresserras R, Ferrer M, Stewart-Brown S, Alonso J. The Spanish version of the Warwick-Edinburgh mental well-being scale (WEMWBS) is valid for use in the general population. Qual Life Res. 2014 Apr;23(3):857-68. doi: 10.1007/s11136-013-0513-7. Epub 2013 Sep 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24005886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cramer H, Ward L, Saper R, Fishbein D, Dobos G, Lauche R. The Safety of Yoga: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials. Am J Epidemiol. 2015 Aug 15;182(4):281-93. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwv071. Epub 2015 Jun 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26116216</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matthewman G, Lee A, Kaur JG, Daley AJ. Physical activity for primary dysmenorrhea: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2018 Sep;219(3):255.e1-255.e20. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2018.04.001. Epub 2018 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>29630882</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Huelva</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ana Abreu Sánchez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Teacher and Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>clinical trial protocol</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise movements technique</keyword>
  <keyword>female</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dysmenorrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

