<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04297423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCB/2019/0872</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04297423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Two Low Volume Regimens for Colorectal Cancer Screening Colonoscopy</brief_title>
  <acronym>LOWOL</acronym>
  <official_title>Eficacia y Tolerabilidad de Dos Productos de Volumen Reducido Para la Colonoscopia de Cribado: Ensayo Comparativo Paralelo Aleatorizado</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Casen Recordati S.L.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundacion Clinic per a la Recerca Biomédica</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer is the first neoplasm most commonly diagnosed in both sexes and the second
      leading cause of cancer death in Spain. Colorectal cancer screening Program in Barcelona was
      implanted in 2009 and approximately 1,500 colorectal cancer screening colonoscopies are
      performed annually at Hospital Clínic de Barcelona. Adequate colon preparation (anterograde
      cleansing with laxatives) improves polyp detection, decreases examination time, and
      complications. There are both low and high volume intestinal regimens with polyethylene
      glycol (PEG) as the main active ingredient or without it.

      Hypothesis: Two low volumen regimens, 1L PEG plus ascorbate and magnesium citrate plus
      picosulphate, at starting doses have the same Adenoma Detection Rate as cleansing solutions
      in preparation for screening colonoscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to compare the clinical efficacy (by comparing the
      adenoma detection rate) of 1L PEG plus ascorbate versus magnesium citrate plus picosulphate
      in subjects undergoing colonoscopy in a colorectal cancer screening programme. We also will
      compare the Lesion Detection Rate, the quality of colon cleansing (Boston classification)
      overall and by segments, the tolerability and satisfaction and the rate of adverse effects
      experienced with intake of these products.

      Methodology: A comparative, parallel, randomized, single-centre, low-intervention clinical
      trial to be conducted at the CCR screening unit of Hospital Clínic de Barcelona that will
      include 1,002 participants.

      Subjects will complete a Tolerability and Satisfaction Questionnaire after completing the
      bowel preparation. Findings (polyps, CRC, or other lesions) and quality of bowel cleansing
      will be collected from the colonoscopy report.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 17, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A comparative, parallel, randomized, non-inferiority, non-blinded, single-centre and low-intervention clinical trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adenoma detection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients with at least one adenoma in relation to the total subjects in each group of study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Colonoscopy quality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Colonoscopy quality is assess with Boston Bowel Preparation Scale (BBPS) in which each colon segment (right colon, transverse colon, and left colon) is scored from 0 to 3 (0=poor, 1=fair, 2=good, 3=excellent). It will be considered adequate when each segment is scored ≥2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lesion detection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients with at least one polyp in relation to the total subjects in each group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caecal intubation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>If the caecum has been reached in the colonoscopy, it will be considered complete; otherwise, it will be considered incomplete</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of adverse events related to the administration of the preparation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated with the Tolerability and Satisfaction Questionnaire including symptoms such as nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, bloating, headache, chills, dizziness, and dry mouth</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability and satisfaction with preparation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by completing a tolerability and satisfaction questionnaire that has been prepared from the validated questionnaire Mayo Clinic Bowel Prep Tolerability Questionnaire (Patel M, Staggs E, Thomas CS, Lukens F, Wallace M, Almansa C. Development and validation of the Mayo Clinic Bowel Prep Tolerability Questionnaire. Dig Liver Dis. 2014 Sep; 46(9):808-12.doi: 10.1016/j.dld.2014.05.020. Epub 2014 Jun 19. PubMed PMID: 24953203) and which has been adapted and translated into Spanish</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1002</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plenvu</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Plenvu split dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Citrafleet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>citrafleet in split dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plenvu</intervention_name>
    <description>randomization 1:1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Citrafleet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Plenvu</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>citrafleet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women aged 50 to 69 years who have participated in the early detection
             programme for colon and rectal cancer (PDPCCR) in Barcelona, who have obtained a
             positive result in the faecal occult blood test (≥20 μg Hb/g faeces) and who are
             scheduled for a screening colonoscopy at Hospital Clínic de Barcelona.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  People who do not agree to participate in the study.

          -  People with known severe renal failure (grade IV or V) and grade III and IV heart
             failure according to the New York Heart Association (NYHA) Scale of Functional
             Assessment of Heart Failure

          -  Individuals who have undergone a colonoscopy in the past year.

          -  Subjects meeting the Rome IV Criteria for the diagnosis of functional constipation

          -  Subjects with mental disabilities or with a severe mental disorder (schizophrenia and
             other psychotic disorders, recurrent severe major depressive disorders, severe
             obsessive-compulsive disorder, severe personality disorders and bipolar disorders).

          -  Individuals who do not understand Catalan or Spanish verbally and in writing.

          -  Individuals with partial or total colon resection.

          -  Individuals with a personal history of CRC or colorectal disease amenable to specific
             follow-up (ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease, or colorectal adenomas).

          -  Individuals with terminal illness or severe illness/disability that contraindicates
             further study of the colon.

          -  People with gastrointestinal disorders that contraindicate the use of the study
             products (gastric emptying disorders, perforation or gastrointestinal obstruction,
             ileus, toxic megacolon).

          -  People with congestive heart failure

          -  Hypermagnesemia

          -  Rhabdomyolysis

          -  Phenylketourine

          -  Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency

          -  People with hypersensitivity to the active ingredients of excipients

          -  People with severe renal impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>María Pellisé, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 932275400</phone>
    <phone_ext>2675</phone_ext>
    <email>mpellise@clinic.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://seom.org/ultimas-noticias/106525-las-cifras-del-cancer-en-espana-2018.</url>
    <description>Las cifras del cáncer en España 2018 - SEOM: Sociedad Española de Oncología Médica © 2019</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.aegastro.es/publicaciones/publicaciones-aeg/guias-de-practica-clinica/guia-clinica-de-calidad-en-la-colonoscopia-de-cribado-del-cancer-colorrectal</url>
    <description>Guía clínica de Calidad en la Colonoscopia de Cribado del CCR</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hautefeuille G, Lapuelle J, Chaussade S, Ponchon T, Molard BR, Coulom P, Laugier R, Henri F, Cadiot G. Factors related to bowel cleansing failure before colonoscopy: Results of the PACOME study. United European Gastroenterol J. 2014 Feb;2(1):22-9. doi: 10.1177/2050640613518200.</citation>
    <PMID>24918005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schreiber S, Baumgart DC, Drenth JPH, Filip RS, Clayton LB, Hylands K, Repici A, Hassan C; DAYB Study Group. Colon cleansing efficacy and safety with 1 L NER1006 versus sodium picosulfate with magnesium citrate: a randomized phase 3 trial. Endoscopy. 2019 Jan;51(1):73-84. doi: 10.1055/a-0639-5070. Epub 2018 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>30025415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bisschops R, Manning J, Clayton LB, Ng Kwet Shing R, Álvarez-González M; MORA Study Group. Colon cleansing efficacy and safety with 1 L NER1006 versus 2 L polyethylene glycol + ascorbate: a randomized phase 3 trial. Endoscopy. 2019 Jan;51(1):60-72. doi: 10.1055/a-0638-8125. Epub 2018 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>30025414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeMicco MP, Clayton LB, Pilot J, Epstein MS; NOCT Study Group. Novel 1 L polyethylene glycol-based bowel preparation NER1006 for overall and right-sided colon cleansing: a randomized controlled phase 3 trial versus trisulfate. Gastrointest Endosc. 2018 Mar;87(3):677-687.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2017.07.047. Epub 2017 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>28803744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seo SI, Kang JG, Kim HS, Jang MK, Kim HY, Shin WG. Efficacy and tolerability of 2-L polyethylene glycol with ascorbic acid versus sodium picosulfate with magnesium citrate: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Colorectal Dis. 2018 May;33(5):541-548. doi: 10.1007/s00384-018-2989-7. Epub 2018 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29497812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SW, Bang CS, Park TY, Suk KT, Baik GH, Kim DJ. Split-dose Bowel Preparation for Colonoscopy: 2 Liters Polyethylene Glycol with Ascorbic Acid versus Sodium Picosulfate versus Oral Sodium Phosphate Tablets. Korean J Gastroenterol. 2017 Aug 25;70(2):89-95. doi: 10.4166/kjg.2017.70.2.89.</citation>
    <PMID>28830134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai EJ, Calderwood AH, Doros G, Fix OK, Jacobson BC. The Boston bowel preparation scale: a valid and reliable instrument for colonoscopy-oriented research. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Mar;69(3 Pt 2):620-5. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.05.057. Epub 2009 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19136102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel M, Staggs E, Thomas CS, Lukens F, Wallace M, Almansa C. Development and validation of the Mayo Clinic Bowel Prep Tolerability Questionnaire. Dig Liver Dis. 2014 Sep;46(9):808-12. doi: 10.1016/j.dld.2014.05.020. Epub 2014 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24953203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guillaumes S, O'Callaghan CA. [Spanish adaptation of the free OxMaR software for minimization and randomization of clinical studies]. Gac Sanit. 2019 Jul - Aug;33(4):395-397. doi: 10.1016/j.gaceta.2018.07.013. Epub 2018 Nov 1. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>30390995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>María Pellisé</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator. Attending physician Gastroenterology department.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bowel Preparation Solutions</keyword>
  <keyword>Screening colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenoma detection rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>1L PEG plus ascorbate</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnesium citrate plus picosulphate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

