<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04299542</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VIR-19-11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04299542</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Percutaneous Lung Biopsy Using Cone Beam CT With Virtual Guidance: a Randomized Control Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Percutaneous Lung Biopsy Using Cone Beam CT With Virtual Guidance: a Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Image-guided percutaneous lung biopsy is an essential procedure in lung cancer management,
      where it is integral to confirming the diagnosis and determining tumour histology. An ideal
      percutaneous lung biopsy also needs to have a short procedure time with accurate needle
      placement to minimize the inherent risk of the procedure.

      Since the 1970s, conventional Multi-detector CT (MDCT) has been the modality of choice in
      percutaneous lung biopsy. Recent research has proposed CT fluoroscopy and cone-beam CT (CBCT)
      as alternative methods.

      Virtual guidance has been developed to improve target visibility and access for these complex
      cases. More specifically, it plans a potential computed 3D needle path before the procedure,
      using the CBCT images. This 3D path can be transposed onto real time fluoroscopic images to
      guide the biopsy, thus potentially improves patients' safety due to more accurate needle
      placement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Image-guided percutaneous lung biopsy is an essential procedure in lung cancer management,
      where it is integral to confirming the diagnosis and determining tumour histology. In this
      era of personalized medicine where knowledge of specific cellular pathways and molecular
      characterization relies on obtaining optimal tissue sampling, the critical question is how to
      obtain a high-quality biopsy tissue sample that could be processed for various pathological
      assessment from a single, minimally invasive percutaneous image-guided approach.

      An ideal percutaneous lung biopsy also needs to have a short procedure time with accurate
      needle placement to minimize the inherent risk of the procedure, including the stochastic
      effect of radiation, and injuries to structures resulting in pneumothorax, pulmonary
      hemorrhage, and air embolism, which could all be potentially life threatening. Previous
      studies have also shown that post-biopsy haemorrhage or pneumothorax requiring chest tubes
      insertion had worse outcome, increased length of hospital stays, and respiratory failure.

      Since the 1970s, conventional Multi-detector CT (MDCT) has been the modality of choice in
      percutaneous lung biopsy, which requires repeated scanning of the target lesion during the
      procedure and the interventional radiologist entering and leaving the CT suite after each
      needle adjustment. Recent research has proposed CT fluoroscopy and cone-beam CT (CBCT) as
      alternative methods.

      Virtual guidance has been developed to improve target visibility and access for these complex
      cases. This involves image registration where the real-time imaging dataset is matched to a
      reference dataset, where the position of a device is displayed on the current imaging dataset
      in real time. Syngo iGuideTM is a novel navigational software which has the potential for
      accurate needle guidance in percutaneous biopsy. More specifically, it plans a potential
      computed 3D needle path before the procedure, using the CBCT images. An integrated laser
      crosshair is also projected onto the patient's skin to indicate the entry point and angle of
      the needle at no additional radiation dose to the patient and staff. This 3D path can be
      transposed onto real time fluoroscopic images to guide the biopsy, thus potentially improves
      patients' safety due to more accurate needle placement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of needle repositioning to reach the target</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after completion of procedure</time_frame>
    <description>This will be recorded during procedure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>procedure time</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after completion of procedure</time_frame>
    <description>This will be recorded throughout procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>radiation dose</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after completion of procedure</time_frame>
    <description>This will be recorded throughout procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after completion of procedure</time_frame>
    <description>observation during and after procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional Multi-detector CT (MDCT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Percutaneous lung biopsy using MDCT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cone-beam CT (CBCT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Percutaneous lung biopsy using CBCT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous lung biopsy using conventional MDCT</intervention_name>
    <description>Conventional CT biopsy will be performed using a 64 slice CT scanner. A preliminary plain CT is acquired covering the entire target lesion with a skin marker, and the interventional radiologist would decide on the skin puncture site and the needle pathway. A post-procedural CT scan will be made to detect pneumothorax or pulmonary haemorrhage. All images will be archived in the picture achieving and communication system (PACS).</description>
    <arm_group_label>conventional Multi-detector CT (MDCT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous lung biopsy CBCT</intervention_name>
    <description>CBCT guided biopsy will be performed in the angiography suite. A preliminary CBCT (DynaCT) is acquired covering the entire target lesion is first performed. Image data will be displayed and processed using Syngo iGuide system. A potential needle trajectory will be drawn from skin to lesion. Integration of the cross-sectional images and real time fluoroscopy will result in three system positions: one bull's eye view and two progression views. During fluoroscopy, the planned needle trajectory and target will be overlaid on the real time fluoroscopy image. After the needle reaches the target, another CBCT will be performed to confirm needle position. Biopsy using coaxial system and post-procedural CT scans will be performed in similar fashion as the conventional CT group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>cone-beam CT (CBCT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Solitary or multiple lung lesions (solid or subsolid nodule, pulmonary infiltrate)
             ≥1cm

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient &lt;18 years old

          -  Patient not able to give informed consent

          -  Uncooperative patient who is unable to hold still or hold their breath for safe biopsy

          -  Lesions &lt;1cm

          -  Lesions within 1cm of vital thoracic structures such as the great vessels and the
             mediastinum

          -  Peripheral lesions accessible to biopsy with ultrasound guidance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon Yu, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DIIR, CUHK, Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carmen Wong</last_name>
    <phone>(852) 35053210</phone>
    <email>carmenwongsp@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pui Man Chong</last_name>
    <phone>(852) 35054094</phone>
    <email>siuman@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Imaging and Interventional Radiology, Prince of Wales Hospital, The Chinese University of Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Simon Yu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

