<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04299763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DOCNUTAL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04299763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oat Beta-glucan as a Supplement in Chilean Type 2 Diabetics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Oat β-glucans as a Supplement in Chilean Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes for Metabolic Control</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro de Estudios en Alimentación y Nutrición, Chile</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro de Estudios en Alimentación y Nutrición, Chile</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To evaluate the effect of oat β-glucans on the satiety perception, metabolic
      control and intestinal microbiota of type 2 diabetics from Talca, Chile. Methodology:
      Clinical trial, controlled, randomized, double blind and parallel design. The recruited (40
      subjects) were randomized into two groups, placebo (PL) and ß-glucan (BG). 5 gr of oat
      ß-glucan or placebo were delivered for 12 weeks to be added in breakfast. Blood and stool
      samples were requested at the beginning and at the end of the intervention. The investigators
      quantify: HbA1c in whole blood, fasting blood glucose, basal insulin, C-peptide, tumor
      necrosis factor alpha (TNF-a), interleukin (IL) 6, IL-8, IL-10, IL1β, cortisol, ghrelin,
      glucagon-like peptide type 1 (GLP -1), YY peptide (PYY), Resistin, Leptin and serum Lipid
      Profile. The subjective perception of hunger / satiety were established through an analogous
      visual survey. Calorie intake was determined by 24-hour recall survey. Were analyzed the
      phylum: Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes and Verrucomicrobia, and the populations of Bifidobacteria
      spp, Lactobacillus spp, butyrate producing bacteria, Akkermansia Muciniphila and total
      bacteria of fecal microbiota, using quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) with
      specific primers. All participants were instructed not to make changes in their usual eating
      habits, physical activity and pharmacological treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 18, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 10, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two groups were used: experimental (n 17): they received oat beta-glucan supplement to be added to breakfast (5 g). Control group: they received a placebo supplement (microcrystalline cellulose). Both groups received a container with the product and a dosing measure (5 g). The intervention was developed for 12 weeks. Blood samples and stools were taken at the beginning and end of the intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of Glycated Hemoglobin A</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Type2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Beta-Glucan (BETA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>experimental group, received a supplement of oats beta-glucan (5 g) for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (CN)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo group, received a supplement of cellulose microcrystalline (5g) for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oat Beta-glucan as a Supplement in Type 2 Diabetics</intervention_name>
    <description>44 subjects were randomized into two groups, placebo (PL) and β-glucan (BG). Each person received a package with a supplement sufficient for 12 weeks, adding 5 g of supplement to breakfast, which could contain beta-glucan or not. Blood and stool samples were requested at the beginning and at the end of the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Beta-Glucan (BETA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control (CN)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus

          -  Use of oral hypoglycemic agents (Metformin)

          -  30 to 45 years

          -  More than one year and less than 10 diabetes

          -  no major chronic complications

          -  Hb A1c between 7 to 9%

          -  BMI between 30-35 Kg / mt2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Acute and / or chronic intestinal pathologies (malabsorption syndrome, celiac disease,
             chronic inflammatory bowel diseases, among others.),

          -  Drugs that interfere with the microbiota (antibiotics, anti-inflammatories, laxatives,
             prokinetics),

          -  Organic insufficiencies (cardiac, hepatic, renal, respiratory), or with
             immunodeficiencies (HIV, chemotherapy, radiotherapy, transplanted).

          -  Presence of smoking habit.

          -  Regular probiotic or prebiotic intake (more than 2 months)

          -  Dipeptidyl peptidase 4 inhibitors (DPP4) and α-amylase inhibitor drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Estudios en Alimentación y Nutrición</name>
      <address>
        <city>Talca</city>
        <state>Maule</state>
        <zip>3480428</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Francelino Andrade E, Vieira Lobato R, Vasques Araújo T, Gilberto Zangerônimo M, Vicente Sousa R, José Pereira L. Effect of beta-glucans in the control of blood glucose levels of diabetic patients: a systematic review. Nutr Hosp. 2014 Jan 1;31(1):170-7. doi: 10.3305/nh.2015.31.1.7597. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25561108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abbasi NN, Purslow PP, Tosh SM, Bakovic M. Oat β-glucan depresses SGLT1- and GLUT2-mediated glucose transport in intestinal epithelial cells (IEC-6). Nutr Res. 2016 Jun;36(6):541-52. doi: 10.1016/j.nutres.2016.02.004. Epub 2016 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>27188900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beck EJ, Tosh SM, Batterham MJ, Tapsell LC, Huang XF. Oat beta-glucan increases postprandial cholecystokinin levels, decreases insulin response and extends subjective satiety in overweight subjects. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2009 Oct;53(10):1343-51. doi: 10.1002/mnfr.200800343.</citation>
    <PMID>19753601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dong J, Cai F, Shen R, Liu Y. Hypoglycaemic effects and inhibitory effect on intestinal disaccharidases of oat beta-glucan in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice. Food Chem. 2011 Dec 1;129(3):1066-71. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.05.076. Epub 2011 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25212338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pentikäinen S, Karhunen L, Flander L, Katina K, Meynier A, Aymard P, Vinoy S, Poutanen K. Enrichment of biscuits and juice with oat β-glucan enhances postprandial satiety. Appetite. 2014 Apr;75:150-6. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2014.01.002. Epub 2014 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24434584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shen XL, Zhao T, Zhou Y, Shi X, Zou Y, Zhao G. Effect of Oat β-Glucan Intake on Glycaemic Control and Insulin Sensitivity of Diabetic Patients: A Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials. Nutrients. 2016 Jan 13;8(1). pii: E39. doi: 10.3390/nu8010039. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26771637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Chile</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>José Luis Pino Villalón</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Nutritionist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>beta-Glucans</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Chile</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

