<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04297033</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AVM-lovastatin</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04297033</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lovastatin for Treatment of Brain Arteriovenous Malformations</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lovastatin for Treatment of Brain Arteriovenous Malformations:a Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this pilot study is to evaluate the disease-modifying efficacy of lovastatin
      in patients with brain arteriovenous malformation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Brain arteriovenous malformations are lesions that consist of multiple arteries and veins,
      connecting as a fistula without intervening normal capillary bed. As the disease progresses,
      the lesion may cause several adverse clinical events including stroke, seizure or even death.
      For patients with BAVM deemed unsuitable for invasive treatment or who has elected to defer
      invasive treatment, it is essential to take effective medical management.

      Lovastatin possesses antiinflammatory and antiproliferative actions in human endothelial and
      vascular smooth muscle cells independent of its lipid-lowing action. These findings suggest
      that lovastatin may be beneficial for maintaining vascular stability, which may contribute to
      slowing down the progression of the disease and reducing the incidence of adverse clinical
      events.

      The purpose of this pilot study is to evaluate the safety and disease-modifying efficacy of
      lovastatin in patients with BAVMs. Participants will be randomly assigned to receive either
      combination of lovastatin and symptomatic treatment drugs or combination of placebo and
      symptomatic treatment drugs. Patients will have post-dose safety follow-up visit at 1, 3, 6,
      and 12 months after the study begins. The changes in clinical outcomes, including lesion
      volume changes and the rate of stroke, seizure or death, will be evaluated in a period of 2
      years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the incidence of stroke between two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Stroke is defined as a clinically symptomatic event (any new focal neurological deficit, seizure, or new-onset headache) that is associated with imaging findings of haemorrhage or infarction. Haemorrhage is defined as fresh intracranial blood on head CT or MRI, or in the cerebrospinal fluid. Infarction is defined as a new ischaemic lesion on cranial CT or MRI (diffusion-weighted, T2-weighted, or fluid-attenuated inversion recovery MRI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in AVM volume from baseline MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months, 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The volume of arteriovenous malformations will be measured by using MRIcron. The brain arteriovenous malformations will be traced directly on the brain MRIs using MRIcron. Masks of the brain arteriovenous malformations will be drawn on each patient's T1 image in native space by board-certified neurosurgeons, who are blinded to the patients' clinical information. Then, the volume of arteriovenous malformations can be calculated by MRIcron.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the incidence of seizures and death between two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Seizures and death are caused by lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1244</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Arteriovenous Malformation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lovastatin intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>combination of 40mg/d 12m lovastatin and symptomatic treatment drugs as a treatment strategy for BAVM .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>combination of placebo and symptomatic treatment drugs as a treatment strategy for BAVM</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lovastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>lovastatin 40mg/d 12m</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lovastatin intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient must have BAVM diagnosed by MRI/MRA, CTA and/or angiogram

          2. BAVM deemed unsuitable for invasive treatment OR patient has elected to defer invasive
             treatment

          3. Patient must be 18 years of age or older

          4. Sign the informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient has received prior BAVM interventional therapy (endovascular, surgical,
             radiotherapy)

          2. Patient has multiple-foci BAVMs

          3. Patient has any form of arteriovenous or spinal fistulas

             Previous diagnosis of any of the following -

          4. Patient was diagnosed with Vein of Galen type malformation

          5. Patient was diagnosed with cavernous malformation

          6. Patient was diagnosed with dural arteriovenous fistula

          7. Patient was diagnosed with venous malformation

          8. Patient was diagnosed with neurocutaneous syndrome such as cerebro-retinal
             angiomatosis (von Hippel-Lindau), encephalo-trigeminal syndrome (Sturge-Weber), or
             Wyburn-Mason syndrome

          9. Patient was diagnosed with BAVMs in context of moya-moya-type changes

         10. Patient was diagnosed with hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia (Rendu-Osler-Weber)

         11. Contraindication to an HMG-coA-reductase inhibitor

         12. History of adverse reaction to HMG-coA-reductase inhibitors (rhabdomyolysis,
             hepatitis)

         13. Use of any cholesterol lowering medication in the previous 12 weeks

             Uncontrolled medical conditions that could potentially increase the risk of toxicities
             or complications of this treatment

         14. Impaired liver function with aspartate transaminase (AST) or alanine transaminase
             (ALT) is more than twice limit of normal.

         15. Creatine kinase (CK) is more than twice limit of normal.

         16. Medications that interfere with the metabolism of lovastatin

         17. Gastrointestinal disease that would affect the ability to swallow or take oral
             medications or absorb them.

         18. End stage renal disease (creatinine clearance eGFR &lt;30 mL/min) or history of severe
             cardiac disease (angina, myocardial infarction or cardiac surgery in preceding two
             years)

         19. Patient has a history of chronic alcohol or drug abuse within 2 years prior to being
             recruited

         20. Patient has known allergy against iodine contrast agents

         21. Patient is pregnant or lactating

         22. Inability to provide informed consent.

         23. Participation in any clinical investigation within 2 months prior to dosing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yong Cao, MD</last_name>
    <phone>861067096510</phone>
    <phone_ext>100050</phone_ext>
    <email>caoyong6@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Tiantan Hospital Affiliated to Capital Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100050</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yong Cao, MD</last_name>
      <phone>861067096510</phone>
      <phone_ext>100050</phone_ext>
      <email>caoyong6@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Yong Cao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cerebral Arteriovenous Malformation, Lovastatin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemangioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Arteriovenous Malformations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arteriovenous Malformations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lovastatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>L 647318</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dihydromevinolin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

