<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04291989</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Edge I.D - 90666</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04291989</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimal Blood Sampling Site for Point of Care Lactate Assessment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimal Blood Sampling Site for Point of Care Lactate Assessment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospitals, Leicester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospitals, Leicester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study was to compare blood Lactate levels between ear lobe and finger against venous
      forearm blood sample using the electronic hand held lactate device in hip fracture patients
      with good cognitive function (AMT &gt;/= 7)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Following a hip fracture, surgical treatment is advocated to improve pain and mobility. Most
      patients are elderly and a majority of them are frail. Current best practice tariff and
      National Institute for health and care excellence guidelines recommends that all those
      patients who undergo an operation should be performed within 36 hours from the time of injury
      to optimise recovery and function. The patients need to be medically optimised to undergo a
      major operation to have their hip fracture fixed. The adequacy of resuscitation is monitored
      by several clinical and biochemical markers. One of the important markers of resuscitation is
      serum lactate levels. This is used routinely in polytrauma patients. (Moran and Forward,
      2012) The initial interest in lactate in hip fracture patients was based on the philosophy
      that a hip fracture in a frail elderly patient may be equivalent to a polytrauma in a young
      fit patient. Subsequently, high serum lactate levels on admission in hip fracture patients
      have been shown to be associated with higher mortality1. However, at present, this is not
      routinely monitored in hip fracture patients. Measurement of serum lactate levels presents
      logistics difficulties, as the blood sample has to be taken to an analyser and analysed
      within 20 minutes. Hence the investigators want to use a point of care electronic hand held
      device - the Lactate Pro 2. The investigators have already tested this device against the
      laboratory analysers and it has been proven to be accurate. However in preliminary testing
      the investigators found a significant difference between fingertip and earlobe samples in
      volunteers. The volunteers do not represent our population of interest, which are hip
      fracture patients. The investigators aim is to determine which sample site; earlobe or
      fingertip, for Lactate Pro 2 testing best matches venous forearm samples upon which the
      association of higher mortality with high lactate was based.

      Any risk to the patients participating in this study would be very small. The inclusion
      criteria to participate in this research study is a patient who has had a recent hip fracture
      awaiting surgery with a Mental Test score of 7/10 or above and is able to consent.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study aims to compare lactate levels from the same patient at the same time with blood samples taken from three locations - fingertip, earlobe and forearm venepuncture</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Finger prick blood sample and earlobe prick blood sample compared to forearm venepuncture blood sample to measure blood Lactate levels in mmol/l using the point of care Lactate-Pro2 device</measure>
    <time_frame>The investigators aim to recruit 50 acute hip fracture patients over a time period of upto 6 months for our study. The outcome will be measured only once and recorded at the point of care for each patient.</time_frame>
    <description>Which of the two sample sites - finger or earlobe most closely matches the forearm venepuncture blood sample for measuring blood lactate levels?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Lactic Acid Increased</condition>
  <condition>Hip Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Earlobe and Finger Prick versus venous blood lactate sampling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Compare blood Lactate levels between ear lobe and finger against venous forearm blood sample using the electronic hand held lactate device in hip fracture patients with good cognitive function (AMT &gt;/= 7)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Optimal Blood Sampling Site for Point of Care Lactate Assessment using the handled Lactate-Pro 2 device</intervention_name>
    <description>This study aims to compare lactate levels using the Lactate Pro 2 device from the same patient at the same time with blood samples taken from three locations - fingertip, earlobe and forearm venepuncture</description>
    <arm_group_label>Earlobe and Finger Prick versus venous blood lactate sampling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female, aged 18 years or above.

          -  Diagnosed with an acute hip fracture.

          -  Have a mental test score of 7/10 or greater on assessment during admission.

          -  Participant is willing to consent to the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The participant will not enter the study if

               1. There are Injuries other than isolated hip fracture

               2. Age &lt;18 years

               3. They are not willing to consent for the study

               4. They have a mental test score less than 7/10 at the time of admission.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GANAPATHY RAMAN R Perianayagam, FRCS (Orth)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals, Leicester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leicester Royal Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <state>Please Select</state>
        <zip>LE1 5WW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BLOOD LACTATE</keyword>
  <keyword>EARLOBE SAMPLE</keyword>
  <keyword>FINGER PRICK SAMPLE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperlactatemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant date for primary outcomes will be made available</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>for 6 months after publication of the study</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access will be reviewed by an external review panel. Requestors will be required to sign a Data Access Agreement form.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

