<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03845998</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017059-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03845998</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Compare the Efficacy of Different Laryngeal Mask Size Selection Methods in General Anesthesia in Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Compare the Efficacy of Different Laryngeal Mask Size Selection Methods in General Anesthesia in Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eye &amp; ENT Hospital of Fudan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eye &amp; ENT Hospital of Fudan University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The laryngeal mask is widely used in general anesthesia in children. Selection of an
      appropriately sized laryngeal mask airway (LMA) is critical to ensure safe and effective use
      of the device. In children, the appropriate size of the LMA to be used is usually determined
      by the patient's weight. Up to now, this is the gold standard method, but the weight-related
      technique is not always possible. The patient's weight is sometimes unknown or medical staff
      do not remember the relationship between weight and size. Moreover, there are no constant
      correlations between laryngeal airways and body indices such as height and weight, so that
      the standard method could cause an inappropriate size of laryngeal mask airway to be chosen.
      Researchers from Spain introduced a new technique to determine the size of the LMA in
      children by choosing the LMA that best matched the combined widths of the patient's index,
      middle and ring fingers, but needs to be formally evaluated in clinical application. In order
      to compare the application effects of two methods (weight-related and three-fingers), we
      designed a research plan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The allocation sequence is generated by computer random number generation, and the allocation
      is placed in sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes by a non-investigator. Enrolment
      and data collection are performed by trained research staff who are not involved in the care
      of the patients. The treating clinicians are not blinded to the assignment group, but all
      other staff involved in both the collection and collation of data are blinded to group
      allocation. The primary measurement is the oropharyngeal leak pressure (OLP) at the
      recommended intracuff pressure. The secondary measurements included insertion time,
      fibreoptic view grade, insufficient ventilation, and the occurrence of complications such as
      postoperative sore throat. The sample size was calculated to be 390 by a statistical software
      based on previous research results. The continuous variables were expressed as means ±
      standard deviation (SD) whereas categorical variables were expressed as frequency and
      percentage for data description. P &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>oropharyngeal leak pressure (OLP)</measure>
    <time_frame>The OLP was measured after the laryngeal mask was successfully inserted and fixed, and the cuff was inflated.</time_frame>
    <description>With the child's head in a neutral position, OLP was measured by closing the expiratory valve of the circle system at a fixed gas flow of 3 l/minute, recording the airway pressure at which equilibrium was reached. Gas leakage was evaluated at the mouth (by detecting an audible sound) and stomach (by epigastric auscultation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>insertion time</measure>
    <time_frame>The time to successful insertion was measured from the time of facemask removal until the time at which bilateral chest expansion was observed.</time_frame>
    <description>The time to successful insertion was measured from the time of facemask removal until the time at which bilateral chest expansion was observed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>grade of fibreoptic view</measure>
    <time_frame>The grade of fibreoptic view was measured after the laryngeal mask was successfully inserted and fixed, and the cuff was inflated.</time_frame>
    <description>The grade of fibreoptic view was assessed by fibreoptic bronchoscopy through the LMA and graded as follows: 1, full view of vocal cords; 2, partial view of vocal cords, including arytenoids; 3, epiglottis only; 4, other (e.g. LMA cuff, pharynx).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative sore throat</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after the patient wakes up and 24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The patient said that he had sore throat after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">392</enrollment>
  <condition>Airway Management</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>three-finger method</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The size of the laryngeal mask airway was determined by choosing the laryngeal mask that best matched the combined widths of the patient's index, middle and ring fingers. That is what we call the three-finger method.
The intervention is to use the three-finger method.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>weight-related method</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The size of the laryngeal mask airway for each patient was determined by the manufacturer's weight-related guidelines. That is what we call the weight-related method.
The intervention is to use the weight-related method.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>use the three-finger method</intervention_name>
    <description>The size of the laryngeal mask airway was determined by choosing the laryngeal mask that best matched the combined widths of the patient's index, middle and ring fingers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>three-finger method</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>use the weight-related method</intervention_name>
    <description>The size of the laryngeal mask airway was determined by the patient's weight.</description>
    <arm_group_label>weight-related method</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  children aged from 3 to 14yr, underwent elective ophthalmic surgery, had an American
             Society of Anesthesiologists physical status rating of I or II

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with lung disease, known airway problems, upper respiratory tract symptoms or
             any condition that may increase the risk of gastro-oesophageal regurgitation, or any
             anatomical abnormalities, especially those related to the head, neck or limbs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jie Jia</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Eye &amp; ENT Hospital of Fudan University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jie Jia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <zip>021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gallart L, Mases A, Martinez J, Montes A, Fernandez-Galinski S, Puig MM. Simple method to determine the size of the laryngeal mask airway in children. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2003 Jul;20(7):570-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12884992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kapila A, Addy EV, Verghese C, Brain AI. The intubating laryngeal mask airway: an initial assessment of performance. Br J Anaesth. 1997 Dec;79(6):710-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9496200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Eye &amp; ENT Hospital of Fudan University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Junming Xia</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Attending physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>airway</keyword>
  <keyword>anaesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>laryngeal mask airway</keyword>
  <keyword>paediatric</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

