<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03841097</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>832046</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03841097</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pulse Wave Velocity, Tacrolimus Time in Therapeutic Range and CV in African American Kidney Transplants</brief_title>
  <acronym>PTAAK</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase IV, Prospective, Randomized, Open-label, Single-center Study of Pulse Wave Velocity, Tacrolimus TTR and CV in African American Kidney Recipients Receiving Immediate Release Tacrolimus or Extended Release Tablets</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roy D. Bloom, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Veloxis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to evaluate the pulse wave velocity and vascular
      compliance measurements at the beginning and the end of the study while the participants are
      taking either extended release tacrolimus tablets (known by brand name Envarsus XR®, and also
      referred to as LCPT in this study) given once-daily each morning after transplantation or
      immediate release tacrolimus capsules (also known by brand name Prograf® or abbreviation
      IR-TAC in this study) that are administered twice-daily 12 hours apart after kidney
      transplantation. Pulse wave velocity and vascular compliance measurements are two
      non-invasive tests that are used to evaluate how well the blood vessels adapt to each
      heartbeat. The secondary purpose is to look at the effectiveness and safety of LCPT given
      once-daily compared to IR-TAC given twice-daily 12 hours apart after kidney transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are several medicines that are given to kidney transplant patients to prevent the
      body's immune system from rejecting (not accepting) the transplanted kidney. Frequently, more
      than one medicine is used at the same time to prevent rejection after kidney transplant. Some
      of the medicines currently used are IR-TAC, Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF), Mycophenolate sodium
      (MPS), and corticosteroids. IR-TAC is currently approved by the Food and Drug Administration
      (FDA) under the trade name of Prograf® or equivalent generic versions to prevent rejection in
      kidney transplant recipients. IR-TAC is taken twice daily (12 hours apart), and the dose is
      adjusted by the transplant provider to keep the level of tacrolimus in the blood from being
      too low or too high.

      LCPT is a tablet containing the same active ingredient that is in IR-TAC but LCPT has been
      designed to release tacrolimus over a longer period of time so that it only has to be taken
      once a day in the morning. The dose of it is also adjusted by the transplant provider to keep
      the level of tacrolimus in the blood from being too low or too high. It has been approved by
      the FDA for prevention of rejection in kidney transplant recipients in combination with other
      medications to prevent rejection after kidney transplant.

      In this study, the participants will be randomly assigned by chance (like flipping a coin) to
      receive either IR-TAC or LCPT from the time of transplant-on. Approximately half (30) of the
      study participants will be given IR-TAC and half will be given LCPT. Both the study
      participants and the transplant providers will know which medication that the participants
      are receiving. The participants will remain in the study for up to 12 months during which
      time they will be seen for monthly clinic visits, and complete labs per the standard of care.

      Additionally, the study investigators will take an additional blood sample to further find
      out how the body absorbs and breaks down the medication tacrolimus. Participants will also
      undergo non-invasive pulse wave velocity and vascular compliance measurements within 3 days
      of post transplant, then 1 month and 12 months after transplant. Pulse wave velocity and
      vascular compliance measurements are two non-invasive tests that are used to evaluate how
      well the blood vessels adapt to each heartbeat. All participants will also be taking either
      Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) or Mycophenolate sodium (MPS) and corticosteroids to prevent
      rejection. These procedures will help the investigators to look at the effectiveness and
      safety of LCPT compared to IR-TAC after kidney transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess Change in Pulse Wave Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and month 12 post transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in PWV measurements (m/sec) from baseline to 12 months after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess Change in Vascular Compliance measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and month 12 post transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in vascular compliance using central blood pressure (mmHg) from baseline to 12 months after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess Change in Vascular Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and month 12 post transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in vascular compliance using Augmentation Index (ratio) from baseline to 12 months after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess Change in Pulse Wave Velocity measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 month post transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in PWV measurements (m/sec) from baseline to 1 month after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess Change in Vascular Compliance measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 month post transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in vascular compliance using central blood pressure (mmHg) from baseline to 1 month after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.
Augmentation Index (ratio) measurements from baseline to 1 month after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess Change in Vascular Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 month post transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in vascular compliance using Augmentation Index (ratio) from baseline to 1 month after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.
Augmentation Index (ratio) measurements from baseline to 1 month after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare Percent of Kidney Recipients with Tacrolimus Time in Therapeutic Range</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To compare % of kidney recipient subjects with Tacrolimus time in therapeutic range (TTR) &lt; 60% or &lt; 75% by 12 months: (TTR will be defined as trough level between 8-12 ug/L between week 1 after transplant-month 5, and 6-9 ug/L between months 6-12 after transplant) in subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the variability of Tacrolimus levels between LCPT and IR-Tac</measure>
    <time_frame>First 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the variability of Tacrolimus levels between LCPT and IR-Tac using coefficient of variation (CV); high Tacrolimus CV will be defined &gt; 40% during the first 12 months after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare steady-state mg/kg Tacrolimus dosing requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To compare steady-state mg/kg Tacrolimus dosing requirements to reach initial therapeutic troughs (defined as 8-12 ug/L) in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac by CYP3A5*1 expressers vs. CYP3A5*1 non-expressers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare Tacrolimus-related medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>at months 1,2,3,6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare Tacrolimus-related medication adherence (measured by patient report of missed doses at transplant nephrology visits) in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare mean systolic and arterial blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare mean systolic and arterial blood pressure in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare anti-hypertensive medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare anti-hypertensive medication use in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare mean diastolic and arterial blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare mean diastolic and arterial blood pressure in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) measured by the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) formula</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months and 12 months post- transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) via Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) 4 calculation in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare hemoglobin A1C values</measure>
    <time_frame>Post- transplant at months 3, 6, and 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the occurrence of a new diagnosis pre-diabetes (as documented in the electronic health record) and hemoglobin A1C values in all non-diabetic kidney transplant subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the incidence of development of donor specific antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>At months 1, 3, 6 and 12 post- transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the incidence of development of donor specific antibodies (DSA) in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the incidence of development of BK virus</measure>
    <time_frame>At months 1, 3, 6, and 12 post- transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the incidence of development of BK virus (defined as BKV &gt; 2.5 log copies/mL) in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the incidence of serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>At months 6 and 12 post- transplant</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the incidence of serious adverse events (SAEs) (including infections resulting in hospitalization, development of biopsy proven cellular and antibody mediated rejection by Banff criteria when biopsy performed for clinical indications, graft loss and patient death) in all kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant; Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extended Release Tacrolimus Tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dosed once daily in the morning and started at a dose of 0.14 mg/kg/day by the first day after kidney transplant (post-operative day 1). This medication will be given with rabbit antithymocyte globulin (rATG) induction, oral mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) and oral steroids to help prevent rejection. These medications will be ordered per standard of care both inpatient and outpatient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Release Tacrolimus Capsules</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dosed twice daily 12 hours apart and started at a dose of 0.1mg/kg/day by the first day after kidney transplant (post-operative day 1). This medication will be given with rabbit antithymocyte globulin (rATG) induction, oral mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) and oral steroids to help prevent rejection. These medications will be ordered per standard of care both inpatient and outpatient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extended Release Tacrolimus Tablets</intervention_name>
    <description>The primary objective is to assess the change in pulse wave velocity (PWV) and vascular compliance measurements from baseline to 12 months after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extended Release Tacrolimus Tablets</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LCPT</other_name>
    <other_name>Envarsus XR®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immediate Release Tacrolimus Capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>The primary objective is to assess the change in pulse wave velocity (PWV) and vascular compliance measurements from baseline to 12 months after transplant in kidney recipient subjects on LCPT compared to those on IR-Tac.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Release Tacrolimus Capsules</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IR-TAC</other_name>
    <other_name>Prograf®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are African American (Self-reported patients of Black African descent who
             live in the United States)

          -  Subjects receiving a first or second deceased donor or living donor kidney transplant
             at the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania

          -  Subjects whose concurrent immunosuppression at the time of transplant will be (generic
             or brand formulation) Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF, CellCept®) or mycophenolic sodium
             (MPS, Myfortic®), prednisone and induction with rabbit-antithymocyte globulin
             (Thymoglobulin®)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who are greater than 75 years old

          -  Subjects who are not self-described as being of Black African descent and living in
             the United States

          -  Subjects who are recipients of organ transplants other than kidney

          -  Subjects who are recipients of third time or more kidney transplants

          -  Subjects who are HIV positive at the time of pre-transplant screening

          -  Subjects with recurrent focal segmental glomerulosclerosis (FSGS)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roy D Bloom, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Trofe-Clark, Pharm D</last_name>
    <phone>215-614-4274</phone>
    <email>Jennifer.Trofe-Clark@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Trofe-Clark, Pharm D</last_name>
      <phone>215-614-4274</phone>
      <email>jennifer.trofe-clark@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Roy D. Bloom, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Professor of Medicine, and Medical Director of the Penn Kidney Transplant Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Renal</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulse wave velocity</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

