<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03843554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>832750</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01DE027637</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UPCC 06319</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03843554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Commensal Oral Microbiota in H&amp;N Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARMOR</acronym>
  <official_title>The ARMOR Trial: Commensal Oral Microbiota as a Trigger of Oral Mucositis Severity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Forsyth Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The ARMOR Trial will test the efficacy of an oral care protocol to treat oral mucositis (OM)
      in patients receiving radiation (RT) or chemoradiation (chemoRT) for head and neck cancer.
      Participants will attend a screening/baseline visit, weekly intervention visits while they
      are undergoing RT or chemoRT, and a visit 3 months after completing RT or chemoRT. At
      intervention visits, samples will be collected (such as saliva, oral swabs) and participants
      will receive their assigned study intervention, either Oral Mucosal Deterging and Dental
      Prophylaxis protocol (OMDP), which includes a dental cleaning and treatment to the oral
      mucosa, or a Standard of Care Oral Hygiene, which includes teeth brushing and no treatment to
      the oral mucosa.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, single blind, two arm, randomized, controlled trial to test the
      efficacy of an oral care protocol to treat oral mucositis (OM) in patients receiving
      radiation (RT) or chemoradiation (chemoRT) for head and neck cancer. This trial will also
      measure salivary proinflammatory cytokines, and evaluate other clinical effects of the
      intervention during cancer therapy. In addition, oral mucosal swabs will be collected for the
      future characterization of changes in the microbiome associated with OM severity.

      Patients will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to two different oral care protocols within 4
      strata defined by type of RT (Proton beam therapy (Protons)) vs intensity-modulated radiation
      therapy (IMRT) and cancer treatment (RT versus chemoRT). Eligible subjects will be assigned
      to receive either the Oral Mucosal Deterging and Dental Prophylaxis protocol (OMDP) or a
      Standard of Care Oral Hygiene protocol (SOC-OH). Prior to randomization, all enrolled
      subjects will receive a baseline dental prophylaxis and fluoride varnish application prior to
      start of RT or chemoRT to ensure that all subjects enter the study with comparable oral
      health. Subjects assigned to OMDP will receive the OMDP Protocol (Oral Mucosal Deterging and
      Dental Prophylaxis) at weekly intervention visits. Subjects randomized to the SOC-OH will
      receive oral health instructions following the American Dental Association Guidelines1 and
      will have their teeth cleaned (brushed) during weekly intervention visits; no treatment to
      the oral mucosa will be provided to this group.

      At each bi-weekly study visit, study assessments will include the collection of saliva and
      oral mucosal swabs, an oral exam and OM assessment, and the completion of questionnaires.
      During the course of the study, subjects will attend one baseline visit, up to 9 intervention
      visits, and a follow-up visit approximately 3 months after completion of RT. Local supportive
      care, including normal saline rinses, topical anesthetics, mixed medication mouthwashes (e.g.
      Magic Mouthwash), feeding tubes, and pain management will be allowed according to each
      recruitment site's standard of care procedures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, single blind, two arm, randomized, controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blinded assessors will grade the oral mucositis.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral mucosal severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Oral mucositis severity as measured by the World Health Organization's Oral Toxicity Scale (WHO OTS); severity is graded 0 through 4, with 4 being the worst. Grade 0 (none), Grade 1 (oral soreness, erythema), Grade 2 (ulceration, solid diet tolerated), Grade 3 (ulceration, liquid diet only), and Grade 4 (nothing by mouth).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlative measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Salivary cytokines: Levels of Th1/Th2-type cytokines IL10, IL8, IL12p70, TNF alpha, IL4, IL1b, IL2, IL13, IL5, and IFN gamma will be assessed, in addition to levels of gp340.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral mucositis assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Mucositis will be assessed using the WHO Oral Toxicity Scale (see above) and the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (grade 1 through 5 with grade 5 being most severe/death)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration and time to onset of severe OM</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>OM severity will be measured by a blinded member of the study team using the WHO OTS (previously described) and the duration and time to onset of severe OM measured in days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary hypofunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in saliva flow rate (mL/minute) will be assessed by a 5 minute stimulated saliva collection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average mouth and throat soreness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Average mouth and throat soreness (MTS) will be assessed using the validated Oral Mucositis and Daily Questionnaire (Stiff et al.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QOL and Function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 3 months post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life and function will be assessed using the validated EORTC-QLQ-C30 for head and neck cancers. This questionnaire assesses general quality of life as well as issues specific to head and neck cancer patients (e.g. difficulty swallowing, pain, dry mouth).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to date of progression or death from any cause, whichever comes first, assessed up to 5 years after completion of RT</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to date of death from any cause, assessed assessed up to 5 years after completion of RT</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Oral Mucositis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Oral Hygiene</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of Care Oral Hygiene group (SOC-OH): Subjects assigned to SOC-OH will attend weekly oral care visits where they will have their teeth brushed with a soft bristled toothbrush by the interventionist. No treatment to the oral mucosa will be provided to this group as part of the intervention. Subjects will receive oral care instructions and will be asked to follow SOC oral hygiene instructions at home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Mucosal Deterging and Dental Prophylaxis (OMDP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral Mucosal Deterging &amp; Dental Prophylaxis (OMDP) protocol: Subjects assigned to OMDP will attend weekly intervention visits during which they will have their teeth cleaned and will receive the OMDP intervention as follows: subjects will receive a professional dental prophylaxis including periodontal surface debridement and deterging of the oral mucosal surfaces. Subjects will be asked to follow OMDP oral hygiene instructions at home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care Oral Hygiene</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care oral hygiene- weekly oral care visits with soft-bristled toothbrushing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Oral Hygiene</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral mucosal deterging and dental prophylaxis</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive a professional dental prophylaxis including periodontal surface debridement [a light-touch, gentle form of instrumentation performed with an ultrasonic instrument to promote plaque removal, to facilitate biofilm disruption and endotoxin flushing, but yet with the preservation of the periodontal cementum] and deterging of the oral mucosal surfaces.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Mucosal Deterging and Dental Prophylaxis (OMDP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Subject Inclusion Criteria

        To participate in this study, an individual must meet all the following criteria:

          1. 18 years of age or older;

          2. Able and willing to provide informed consent prior to initiation of study procedures;

          3. Scheduled to undergo radiation or chemoradiation treatment for head/neck cancer;

          4. Presents with at least one of nine areas of the oral or oropharyngeal mucosa (i.e.,
             upper lip, lower lip, right cheek, left cheek, right ventral and lateral tongue, left
             ventral and lateral tongue, floor of the mouth, and soft palate) expected to receive
             at least 5000 cGy of RT. Patients with cancer located outside of the oral cavity will
             be included when at least 5000 cGy of RT will be administered to the oral cavity in
             addition to the RT targeted at the primary cancer site.

          5. Presents with a minimum of 6 natural teeth.

        Subject Exclusion Criteria

        An individual who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from participation
        in this study:

          1. Pregnant or lactating at the baseline/screening visit;

          2. Participating in another oral health interventional research study at any point during
             their participation in this trial;

          3. Receiving induction chemotherapy or concurrent radiation therapy with cetuximab;

          4. Reports current use of antifungal or antibiotic at the time of enrollment;

          5. Presents with immunocompromised status (defined as an absolute neutrophil count (ANC)
             of less than 1000);

          6. Presents with any of the following conditions, which based on American Dental and
             American College of Cardiology guidelines, require antibiotic prophylaxis prior to
             dental treatment:

               1. prosthetic cardiac valves, including transcatheter-implanted prostheses and
                  homografts;

               2. prosthetic material used for cardiac valve repair, such as annuloplasty rings and
                  chords;

               3. a history of infective endocarditis;

               4. a cardiac transplant with valve regurgitation due to a structurally abnormal
                  valve;

               5. the following congenital (present from birth) heart disease: unrepaired cyanotic
                  congenital heart disease, including palliative shunts and conduits; or any
                  repaired congenital heart defect with residual shunts or valvular regurgitation
                  at the site of or adjacent to the site of a prosthetic patch or a prosthetic
                  device;

          7. Presents with cardiovascular implantable electronic devices (CIEDs) such as
             pacemakers, and implantable cardioverter-defibrillators; unless, a) in the opinion of
             the investigator, the OMDP protocol can be performed with hand scalers (and not with
             an ultrasonic device as per protocol) or upon consult with the treating cardiologist,
             it is determined that the ultrasonic device can be safely used;

          8. Presents with severe periodontal disease for which treatment cannot be completed prior
             to the start of radiation/chemoradiation (at the discretion of the investigator);

          9. Had surgery as part of cancer treatment and is not sufficiently healed to comply with
             study requirements prior to RT initiation;

         10. In the opinion of the investigator, is unable or unlikely to comply fully with the
             study requirements or procedures for any reason (e.g. cognitive or physical
             impairment).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia Corby, DDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex Lin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn Medicine, Perelman Center for Advanced Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michelle Shuster, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>215-573-6243</phone>
    <email>mbs74@upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matt Buczek</last_name>
    <phone>215-578-5599</phone>
    <email>buczekm@upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Patricia Corby, DDS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Dean of Translational Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Neck Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Mucositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemoradiation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mucositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

