<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03847207</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HTL0030310-101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-003169-33</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>QSC200729</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03847207</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study in Healthy Subjects to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, PK and PD of HTL0030310</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Three-Part Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Single Ascending Subcutaneous Doses of HTL0030310 in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Heptares Therapeutics Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Heptares Therapeutics Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Phase 1, first in human, three-part, single centre study to assess the safety,
      tolerability, PK and PD of single ascending subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310 in healthy
      subjects
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a first in human, three part study with the objective to assess the safety,
      tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of single ascending subcutaneous doses of
      HTL0030310 in healthy subjects. Part 1 is a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomised
      study assessing single ascending doses of HTL0030310. Part 2 is a site-blind (sponsor
      unblinded), placebo-controlled, part-randomised, fixed-sequence, single-dose, 4-period study
      assessing the PD of a positive control, pasireotide, following administration of challenge
      agents. Part 3 is a double-blind, placebo-controlled, part-randomised, fixed-sequence,
      single-dose, HTL0030310 proof of pharmacological effect study, where PD effects of HTL0030310
      will be investigated following administration of challenge agents. The challenge agents
      administered in this study will be: oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT), Growth
      hormone-releasing hormone (GHRH), and corticotrophin releasing hormone (CRH) combined with
      desmopressin.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1: Number of treatment related adverse events (as determined by abnormal clinical laboratory tests, vitals signs, ECG parameters, Holter ECG parameters and injection site reactions)</measure>
    <time_frame>Admission up to 8 days post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and Tolerability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2 and Part 3 Area under the effect time curve (EAUC) 1) for insulin, glucose, glucagon, GLP1, C-peptide and GIP level 2) for GH 3) ACTH and cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose up to 4 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacodynamics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2 and Part 3 Maximum observed effect (EMax) 1) for insulin, glucose, glucagon, GLP1, C-peptide and GIP level 2) for GH 3) ACTH and cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose up to 4 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacodynamics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2 and Part 3 Time to reach Maximum observed effect (TEMax) 1) for insulin, glucose, glucagon, GLP1, C-peptide and GIP level 2) for GH 3) ACTH and cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose up to 4 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacodynamics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1 Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of single subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose to 144 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1 Time to reach Maximum observed plasma concentration (Tmax) of single subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose to 144 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 1 Area under the curve (AUC) of single subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose to 144 hours post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2 Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of single subcutaneous doses of pasireotide</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 24 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2 Time to reach Maximum observed plasma concentration (Tmax) of single subcutaneous doses of pasireotide</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 24 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2 Area under the curve (AUC) of single subcutaneous doses of pasireotide</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 24 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 3: Number of treatment related adverse events (as determined by abnormal clinical laboratory tests, vitals signs, ECG parameters and injection site reactions)</measure>
    <time_frame>Admission up to 8 to 10 days post final dose</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and Tolerability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 3 Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of single subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 96 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 3 Time to reach Maximum observed plasma concentration (Tmax) of single subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 96 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 3 Area under the curve (AUC) of single subcutaneous doses of HTL0030310</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 96 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">176</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 Single Ascending Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eight subjects in up to 8 cohorts will be dosed. A single subcutaneous injection of HTL0030310 or placebo will be administered. In each cohort, 6 subjects will receive HTL0030310 and 2 subjects will receive placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 Pasireotide PD Assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sixteen subjects in 2 cohorts (8 subjects per cohort) will be dosed on 4 occasions. Within each cohort, 4 subjects will be randomised to active dosing with CRH with desmopressin, GHRH and OGTT challenge and 4 subjects will be randomised to placebo dosing with CRH with desmopressin, GHRH and OGTT challenge.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 3 Proof of Pharmacological Effect</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Up to 80 subjects in 4 cohorts (up to 20 subjects per cohort) will be dosed in up to 3 study periods. In each period, subjects will receive active drug or placebo with GHRH, OGTT and CRH with desmopressin (optional).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HTL0030310</intervention_name>
    <description>Solution for Subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 Single Ascending Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 3 Proof of Pharmacological Effect</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pasireotide</intervention_name>
    <description>Pasireotide 600 μg for subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 Pasireotide PD Assessment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo Solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 Single Ascending Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 Pasireotide PD Assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 3 Proof of Pharmacological Effect</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Healthy males or healthy WONCBP; a woman is considered of childbearing potential
             unless she is permanently sterile (hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy and bilateral
             oophorectomy) or is postmenopausal (had no menses for 12 months without an alternative
             medical cause and a serum follicle-stimulating hormone [FSH] concentration ≥40 IU/L).

          2. Age 18 to 50 years of age

          3. A BMI of 20.0 to 30.0 kg/m2, with a minimum weight of 45 kg

          4. Must be willing and able to communicate and participate in the whole study

          5. Must provide written informed consent

          6. Must agree to adhere to the contraception requirements defined in the protocol
             (Section 9.4) Inclusion criteria 4 and 6 from the list above will be re-assessed at
             admission/pre-dose.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Subjects who have received any IMP in a clinical research study within the previous 3
             months of screening

          2. Subjects who are study site employees, or immediate family members of a study site or
             sponsor employee

          3. Subjects who have previously been enrolled in this study. Subjects who have taken part
             in Part 1/Part 2 are not permitted to take part in Part 2/Part 3

          4. History of any drug or alcohol abuse in the past 2 years

          5. Regular alcohol consumption in males &gt;21 units per week and females &gt;14 units per week
             (1 unit = ½ pint beer, or a 25 mL shot of 40% spirit, 1.5 to 2 Units = 125 mL glass of
             wine, depending on type)

          6. Current smokers and those who have smoked within the last 12 months. A breath carbon
             monoxide reading of greater than 10 ppm at screening and admission

          7. Current users of e-cigarettes and nicotine replacement products and those who have
             used these products within the last 12 months

          8. Females of childbearing potential. A woman is considered of childbearing potential
             unless she is permanently sterile (hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy and bilateral
             oophorectomy) or is postmenopausal (had no menses for 12 months without an alternative
             medical cause and a serum FSH concentration ≥40 IU/L). All female subjects must have a
             negative urine pregnancy test

          9. Subjects who do not have suitable veins for multiple venepunctures/cannulation as
             assessed by the investigator at screening

         10. Subjects with vital signs outside the normal range for healthy volunteers (HR &lt; 50 or
             &gt;90 bpm; Systolic BP &gt; 140 mmHg; Diastolic BP &gt; 90 mmHg)

         11. Clinically significant abnormal biochemistry, haematology, coagulation or urinalysis
             as judged by the investigator (laboratory parameters are listed in Appendix 1 of the
             protocol)

         12. Fasting blood glucose at screening above the upper limit of normal (3.9 to 5.8 mM)

         13. HbA1c at screening above the upper limit of normal (&gt;6%)

         14. Abnormal renal function - defined as creatinine clearance &lt; 70mL/min using the
             Cockcroft-Gault equation at screening

         15. Abnormal hepatic function - defined as ALT, AST and total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x upper
             limit of normal at screening

         16. Positive drugs of abuse test result (drugs of abuse tests are listed in Appendix 1 of
             the protocol)

         17. Positive hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C virus antibody (HCV Ab) or
             human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) results

         18. History of clinically significant cardiovascular, renal, hepatic, chronic respiratory
             or GI disease, neurological or psychiatric disorder, as judged by the investigator

         19. Family history of long QT syndrome or sudden cardiac death in a young adult where a
             cause of arrhythmia cannot be excluded

         20. QTcF at screening &gt;450 msec in males or &gt;470 msec in females

         21. Serious adverse reaction or serious hypersensitivity to any drug or the formulation
             excipients, including glucose/fructose intolerance for the standard OGTT

         22. Presence or history of clinically significant allergy requiring treatment, as judged
             by the investigator. Hayfever is allowed unless it is active

         23. Donation or loss of greater than 400 mL of blood within the previous 3 months

         24. Subjects who are taking, or have taken, any prescribed or over-the-counter drug (other
             than up to 4 g per day paracetamol) or herbal remedies (including St. John's Wort) in
             the 21 days before IMP administration (See Section 11.4 of protocol). Exceptions may
             apply on a case by case basis, if considered not to interfere with the objectives of
             the study, as agreed by the PI and sponsor's medical monitor

         25. Subjects with tattoos or scars on the abdomen which may interfere with injection site
             assessments or pharmacodynamic measurements, as determined by the PI or delegate at
             screening

         26. Failure to satisfy the investigator of fitness to participate for any other reason
             Exclusion criteria 11, 16, 22, 24 and 26 from the list above will be re-assessed at
             admission/pre-dose.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philip Evans, MBChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Quotient Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claire Swann</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)115 931 5505</phone>
    <email>Claire.Swann@quotientsciences.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Quotient Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nottingham</city>
        <zip>NG11 6JS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philip Evans, MBChB</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>First in Human</keyword>
  <keyword>Single Ascending Dose</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pasireotide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

