<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03843463</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00203667</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03843463</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Escitalopram and Language Intervention for Subacute Aphasia</brief_title>
  <acronym>ELISA</acronym>
  <official_title>Escitalopram and Language Intervention for Subacute Aphasia (ELISA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this project, the investigators will investigate the effects of a selective serotonin
      reuptake inhibitor (SSRI), escitalopram, on augmenting language therapy effectiveness, as
      measured by naming untrained pictures and describing pictures, in individuals with aphasia in
      the acute and subacute post stroke period (i.e., within three months post stroke).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this project, the investigators will investigate the effects of a selective serotonin
      reuptake inhibitor (SSRI), escitalopram, on augmenting language therapy effectiveness, as
      measured by naming untrained pictures and describing pictures, in individuals with aphasia in
      the acute and subacute post stroke period (i.e., within three months post stroke). There has
      been no previous randomized controlled trial (RCT) to evaluate the effect of daily SSRI in
      the first three months after stroke on improvement of language in people undergoing aphasia
      treatment. It is plausible that SSRIs, which elevate synaptic serotonin, might enhance
      recovery by augmenting synaptic plasticity.

      The investigators propose to conduct a Phase 2 multi-center, randomized, double blind,
      placebo-controlled trial of escitalopram for augmenting language intervention in subacute
      stroke. The investigators hypothesize that daily escitalopram for 90 days after stroke
      results in greater improvement (compared to placebo) in naming untrained pictures, as well as
      greater increase in content of picture description and greater improvement in morphosyntactic
      production, when combined with speech and language treatment (SALT). A second aim is to
      evaluate the mechanisms of language recovery in individuals who receive active medical
      treatment and those who receive placebo, using resting state functional magnetic resonance
      imaging (rsfMRI) and genetic testing. The investigators hypothesize that greater improvement
      in language is associated with increased connectivity within the left hemisphere language
      network on rsfMRI in participants who receive escitalopram than in those who receive placebo,
      independently of improvement in depression. The investigators also hypothesize that the
      effects are greatest in individuals with val/val allele of brain-derived neurotrophic factor
      (BDNF) - (consistent with previous studies showing a greater response to treatment and
      greater neuroplasticity in people with the val/val allele than those with one or more met
      alleles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Philadelphia Naming Test accuracy score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 week after computer-delivered naming treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of correctly named items of 175 total items on the computerized picture naming assessment. Scores ranges from 0 to 175 with higher scores meaning better naming ability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Language production as assessed by lexical features of discourse in &quot;Cookie Theft&quot; picture description</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Lexical features, meaning carrying units of language (morphemes), will be counted for each Cookie Theft picture description. There is no maximum number of meaning carrying units, but norms are available to assist in the interpretation of this performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Language production as assessed by content units included in picture description of &quot;Cookie Theft&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Content units are based on a standard scoring template of commonly identified concepts (nouns and verbs) in the left and right regions of the &quot;Cookie Theft&quot; picture. Participants either include or fail to include 30 concepts on the left side of the picture and 23 concepts on the right side of the picture. A ratio of included left content units to included right content units then can be calculated and interpreted as a measure of hemispatial attention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Language production as assessed by rate of syllables per content unit produced in &quot;Cookie Theft&quot; picture description</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Syllables included in the picture description are counted. Content units are based on a standard scoring template of commonly identified concepts (nouns and verbs) in the left and right regions of the &quot;Cookie Theft&quot; picture. Participants either include or fail to include 30 concepts on the left side of the picture and 23 concepts on the right side of the picture. The average rate of syllables per content unit produced can then be calculated and interpreted as a measure of efficiency in producing relevant information in the task.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression as assessed by Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>9 item scale scored 0-3 for each item. PHQ-9 scores of 5, 10, 15, and 20 represent mild, moderate, moderately severe, and severe depression. PHQ-9 &gt;15 or suicidal ideation suggest depression sufficient for exclusion or removal from study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Language production as assessed by Morphosyntactic Generation (MorGen) Test</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>60 item assessment of word morphology (e.g., plurals, possessives) and modifiers (e.g., number, size, color). Each item is scored based on produced accurate descriptors of an image relative to a second reference image (e.g., patients see two trees, one larger than the other, and the phrase &quot;little tree&quot; is elicited). Patients are scored for objects correctly named (nouns) out of 60, instances of correct use of plural marker out of 31, instances of correct use of numbers out of 8, instances of correct modifiers denoting size out of 16, instances of correct modifiers denoting color out of 19, instances of correct modifiers denoting possessive markers out of 17, and instances of correctly named possessing individuals (proper names provided on screen) out of 17. These scores can then be interpreted separately or averaged to interpret a broad morphosyntactic accuracy score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke severity as assessed by NIH Stroke Scale (NIHSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The NIHSS is a 15-item neurologic examination stroke scale used to evaluate the effect of acute cerebral infarction on the levels of consciousness, language, neglect, visual-field loss, extraocular movement, motor strength, ataxia, dysarthria, and sensory loss. A trained observer rates the patient's ability to answer questions and perform activities. Ratings for each item are scored with 3 to 5 grades with 0 as normal, and there is an allowance for untestable items.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-stroke quality of life as assessed by Stroke Impact Scale (SIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>59 item scale scored 1-5 for each item assessing a variety of domains: strength, hand function, activities of daily living, mobility, communication, emotion, memory/thinking, and participation. Scores for each domain can range from 0-100, with 100 indicating the most severe disturbance to the patient's quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-stroke level of disability as assessed by modified Rankin Scale (mRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The mRS is a 6-level scale from &quot;0-No symptoms&quot; to &quot;6-dead&quot; used to evaluate the degree of disability in patients who have suffered a stroke.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke paresis severity as assessed by right arm strength</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Right arm strength assessment by the neurologist (measured via clinical opinion) is a common measure of upper motor paresis associated with left hemisphere ischemic stroke. Strength in the arm is graded from 0 to 5 with 5 being full strength.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Aphasia</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Naming Treatment + Escitalopram</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 mg escitalopram daily for three months (escalating from 5 mg per day for the first week and tapering to 5 mg per day for the last two weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Naming Treatment + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 mg placebo daily for three months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Escitalopram 10mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Escitalopram tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Naming Treatment + Escitalopram</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lexapro</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Sugar pill manufactured to mimic escitalopram 10 mg tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Naming Treatment + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo (for Escitalopram)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computer-delivered naming treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>15 45-minute sessions of computer-delivered naming treatment beginning two months following stroke</description>
    <arm_group_label>Naming Treatment + Escitalopram</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Naming Treatment + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CoDeNT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have sustained an acute ischemic left hemisphere stroke.

          -  Participants must be fluent speakers of English by self-report.

          -  Participants must be capable of giving informed consent or indicating another to
             provide informed consent.

          -  Participants must be age 18 or older but not older than 99 years.

          -  Participants must be within 5 days of onset of stroke.

          -  Participants must have an aphasia diagnosis as confirmed by the Western Aphasia
             Battery-Revised.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous neurological disease affecting the brain including previous symptomatic
             stroke

          -  Diagnosis of schizophrenia, autism, or other psychiatric or neurological condition
             that affects naming/language

          -  Current severe depression, defined as a score of &gt; 15 on the Patient Health
             Questionnaire

          -  Uncorrected visual loss or hearing loss by self-report

          -  Use of any medication approved by the FDA for treatment of depression at the time of
             stroke onset

          -  Concomitant use of any monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) or pimozide, or other
             contraindications to escitalopram that may be identified
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Argye Hillis-Trupe, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Argye Hillis-Trupe, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(410) 614-2381</phone>
    <email>argye@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Argye Hillis, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-614-9807</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhogal SK, Teasell R, Speechley M. Intensity of aphasia therapy, impact on recovery. Stroke. 2003 Apr;34(4):987-93. Epub 2003 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>12649521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brady MC, Kelly H, Godwin J, Enderby P, Campbell P. Speech and language therapy for aphasia following stroke. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016 Jun 1;(6):CD000425. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000425.pub4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27245310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chollet F, Tardy J, Albucher JF, Thalamas C, Berard E, Lamy C, Bejot Y, Deltour S, Jaillard A, Niclot P, Guillon B, Moulin T, Marque P, Pariente J, Arnaud C, Loubinoux I. Fluoxetine for motor recovery after acute ischaemic stroke (FLAME): a randomised placebo-controlled trial. Lancet Neurol. 2011 Feb;10(2):123-30. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(10)70314-8. Epub 2011 Jan 7. Erratum in: Lancet Neurol. 2011 Mar;10(3):205.</citation>
    <PMID>21216670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>FOCUS Trial Collaboration. Effects of fluoxetine on functional outcomes after acute stroke (FOCUS): a pragmatic, double-blind, randomised, controlled trial. Lancet. 2019 Jan 19;393(10168):265-274. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32823-X. Epub 2018 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>30528472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doron R, Lotan D, Versano Z, Benatav L, Franko M, Armoza S, Kately N, Rehavi M. Escitalopram or novel herbal mixture treatments during or following exposure to stress reduce anxiety-like behavior through corticosterone and BDNF modifications. PLoS One. 2014 Apr 1;9(4):e91455. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0091455. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24690945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Enderby P, Broeckx J, Hospers W, Schildermans F, Deberdt W. Effect of piracetam on recovery and rehabilitation after stroke: a double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Clin Neuropharmacol. 1994 Aug;17(4):320-31.</citation>
    <PMID>9316679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fridriksson J, Elm J, Stark BC, Basilakos A, Rorden C, Sen S, George MS, Gottfried M, Bonilha L. BDNF genotype and tDCS interaction in aphasia treatment. Brain Stimul. 2018 Nov - Dec;11(6):1276-1281. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2018.08.009. Epub 2018 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>30150003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gu SC, Wang CD. Early Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors for Recovery after Stroke: A Meta-Analysis and Trial Sequential Analysis. J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis. 2018 May;27(5):1178-1189. doi: 10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2017.11.031. Epub 2017 Dec 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29276014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayasaka Y, Purgato M, Magni LR, Ogawa Y, Takeshima N, Cipriani A, Barbui C, Leucht S, Furukawa TA. Dose equivalents of antidepressants: Evidence-based recommendations from randomized controlled trials. J Affect Disord. 2015 Jul 15;180:179-84. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2015.03.021. Epub 2015 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>25911132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hillis AE. The 'standard' for poststroke aphasia recovery. Stroke. 2010 Jul;41(7):1316-7. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.585364. Epub 2010 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20538691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hillis AE, Beh YY, Sebastian R, Breining B, Tippett DC, Wright A, Saxena S, Rorden C, Bonilha L, Basilakos A, Yourganov G, Fridriksson J. Predicting recovery in acute poststroke aphasia. Ann Neurol. 2018 Mar;83(3):612-622. doi: 10.1002/ana.25184. Epub 2018 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29451321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hillis AE, Tippett DC. Stroke Recovery: Surprising Influences and Residual Consequences. Adv Med. 2014;2014. pii: 378263.</citation>
    <PMID>25844378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huber W, Willmes K, Poeck K, Van Vleymen B, Deberdt W. Piracetam as an adjuvant to language therapy for aphasia: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled pilot study. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1997 Mar;78(3):245-50.</citation>
    <PMID>9084344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jorge RE, Acion L, Moser D, Adams HP Jr, Robinson RG. Escitalopram and enhancement of cognitive recovery following stroke. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2010 Feb;67(2):187-96. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.185.</citation>
    <PMID>20124118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kraglund KL, Mortensen JK, Damsbo AG, Modrau B, Simonsen SA, Iversen HK, Madsen M, Grove EL, Johnsen SP, Andersen G. Neuroregeneration and Vascular Protection by Citalopram in Acute Ischemic Stroke (TALOS). Stroke. 2018 Nov;49(11):2568-2576. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.117.020067.</citation>
    <PMID>30355209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kurland J, Pulvermüller F, Silva N, Burke K, Andrianopoulos M. Constrained versus unconstrained intensive language therapy in two individuals with chronic, moderate-to-severe aphasia and apraxia of speech: behavioral and fMRI outcomes. Am J Speech Lang Pathol. 2012 May;21(2):S65-87. doi: 10.1044/1058-0360(2012/11-0113). Epub 2012 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22294409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lam RW. Antidepressants and QTc prolongation. J Psychiatry Neurosci. 2013 Mar;38(2):E5-6. doi: 10.1503/jpn.120256.</citation>
    <PMID>23422053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lazar RM, Minzer B, Antoniello D, Festa JR, Krakauer JW, Marshall RS. Improvement in aphasia scores after stroke is well predicted by initial severity. Stroke. 2010 Jul;41(7):1485-8. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.109.577338. Epub 2010 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20538700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marangolo P, Fiori V, Sabatini U, De Pasquale G, Razzano C, Caltagirone C, Gili T. Bilateral Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation Language Treatment Enhances Functional Connectivity in the Left Hemisphere: Preliminary Data from Aphasia. J Cogn Neurosci. 2016 May;28(5):724-38. doi: 10.1162/jocn_a_00927. Epub 2016 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26807842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mead GE, Hsieh CF, Lee R, Kutlubaev MA, Claxton A, Hankey GJ, Hackett ML. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) for stroke recovery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Nov 14;11:CD009286. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD009286.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2019 Nov 26;2019(11):.</citation>
    <PMID>23152272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pan XL, Chen HF, Cheng X, Hu CC, Wang JW, Fu YM, Kong HM, Shao HJ. Effects of Paroxetine on Motor and Cognitive Function Recovery in Patients with Non-Depressed Ischemic Stroke: An Open Randomized Controlled Study. Brain Impairment. 2018 May:1-7.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sæterdal I, Pike E, Ringerike T, Gjertsen MK. Efficacy and Safety for the Newer Antidepressants in Adults [Internet]. Oslo, Norway: Knowledge Centre for the Health Services at The Norwegian Institute of Public Health (NIPH); 2007 Jun. Available from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK464856/</citation>
    <PMID>29320072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanchez C, Reines EH, Montgomery SA. A comparative review of escitalopram, paroxetine, and sertraline: Are they all alike? Int Clin Psychopharmacol. 2014 Jul;29(4):185-96. doi: 10.1097/YIC.0000000000000023. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24424469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sebastian R, Saxena S, Tsapkini K, Faria AV, Long C, Wright A, Davis C, Tippett DC, Mourdoukoutas AP, Bikson M, Celnik P, Hillis AE. Cerebellar tDCS: A Novel Approach to Augment Language Treatment Post-stroke. Front Hum Neurosci. 2017 Jan 12;10:695. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2016.00695. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>28127284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang C, Zhang Y, Liu B, Long H, Yu C, Jiang T. Dosage effects of BDNF Val66Met polymorphism on cortical surface area and functional connectivity. J Neurosci. 2014 Feb 12;34(7):2645-51. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3501-13.2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24523553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walker-Batson D, Curtis S, Natarajan R, Ford J, Dronkers N, Salmeron E, Lai J, Unwin DH. A double-blind, placebo-controlled study of the use of amphetamine in the treatment of aphasia. Stroke. 2001 Sep;32(9):2093-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11546902</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aphasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexetimide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Citalopram</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

