<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03841747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>012342QM</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-000188-10</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03841747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paclitaxel Plus Pembrolizumab vs. Paclitaxel Weekly in ER+ Luminal B Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>PELICAN</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Randomized Study of Paclitaxel Weekly Plus Pembrolizumab Versus Paclitaxel Weekly in ER-positive, Luminal B Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen Mary University of London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Institute of Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen Mary University of London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PELICAN is a randomised phase II trial that aims to evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      paclitaxel plus pembrolizumab relative to paclitaxel alone, in patients with locally advanced
      or metastatic ER-positive, HER2-negative, Luminal B breast cancer who have received no prior
      chemotherapy for advanced or metastatic disease.

      Patients will be randomised (2:1) to one of the two treatment arms:

        -  Pembrolizumab plus Paclitaxel

        -  Paclitaxel
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PELICAN is a randomised phase II trial that aims to evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      paclitaxel plus pembrolizumab relative to paclitaxel alone, in patients with locally advanced
      or metastatic ER-positive, HER2-negative, Luminal B breast cancer who have received no prior
      chemotherapy for advanced or metastatic disease.

      Luminal B is defined as high Ki67 (≥20%) and /or histological grade 3 and / or Luminal B
      according to PAM50 assay. This study will include patients irrespective of PD-L1 expression,
      but patients will be stratified by centrally determined PD-L1 expression. The number of
      patients with PD-L1 negative tumours (&lt;1% expression) will be capped at 50% of the total
      study population.

      Patients will be randomised (2:1) to one of the two treatment arms:

        -  Pembrolizumab every 3 weeks (Q3W) plus Paclitaxel on Days 1,8, and 15 every 28 days

        -  Paclitaxel on Days 1,8, and 15 every 28 days Paclitaxel alone

      Randomisation will be stratified by the following two factors:

        -  Centrally assessed PD-L1 expression (&lt;1% PD-L1 expression; ≥1%)

        -  Presence vs non-presence of visceral metastases

      Paclitaxel treatment will be continued for at least 6 cycles unless there is evidence of
      unacceptable toxicity, disease progression, or if the patient requests to stop the treatment.
      If paclitaxel treatment is discontinued prior to disease progression, patients in the
      combination arm should continue pembrolizumab single agent therapy until progression or
      evidence of unacceptable toxicity up to a maximum of 2 years.

      If disease progression is documented (RECIST 1.1) while the patient is on study medication
      (in the pembrolizumab plus paclitaxel arm) it would be standard practice for the patient to
      be taken off study medication. However, in the absence of other discontinuation criteria,
      patients treated with paclitaxel plus pembrolizumab may be continued on study medication if
      in the opinion of the treating physician there is clinical benefit. In this case patients
      must meet all of the following criteria:

        -  Evidence of clinical benefit as assessed by the investigator

        -  Absence of symptoms and signs (including worsening of laboratory values [e.g., new or
           worsening hypercalcemia]) indicating clinically significant progression of disease

        -  No decline in Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status that can be
           attributed to disease progression

        -  Absence of tumour progression at critical anatomical sites (e.g., leptomeningeal
           disease) that cannot be managed by protocol-allowed medical interventions (i.e., pain
           secondary to disease or unmanageable ascites, etc.), as determined by the investigator
           after an integrated assessment of radiographic data, biopsy results (if available), and
           clinical status.

      Pembrolizumab treatment will not exceed 2 years.

      Patients who were randomized to the paclitaxel alone must discontinue study treatment upon
      determination of progressive disease. No crossover is allowed. On completion of study
      treatment in both arms, patients will enter a survival follow-up period during which data on
      cancer therapy, disease status and survival status will be collected. Endocrine maintenance
      therapy is not permitted prior to disease progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of first tumour progression or death, whichever came first, assessed up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival, defined as the time from the date of randomisation to the date of first documented tumour progression (using RECIST 1.1) or death from any cause, whichever occurs first. To be used for both the overall patient population and in patients with PD-L1-positive tumours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of death, assessed up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival is defined as the time from date of randomisation to the date of death due to any cause in all patients. To be used for both the overall patient population and in patients with PD-L1-positive tumours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of first documentation of CR or PR or to the date of first documented tumour progression (using RECIST 1.1) or death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Objective Response Rate is defined as the proportion of the patients in the analysis population who have a CR or PR (using RECIST 1.1). To be used for both the overall patient population and in patients with PD-L1-positive tumours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of first documentation of CR or PR to the date of first documented tumour progression (using RECIST 1.1) or death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of Response is defined as the time from first documentation of CR or PR to the date of first documented tumour progression (using RECIST 1.1) or death from any cause, whichever occurs first. To be used for both the overall patient population and in patients with PD-L1-positive tumours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Benefit Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of first tumour progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed over a minimum of 24 weeks and up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Benefit Rate is defined as the percentage of patients who have achieved at least one CR or PR or met the SD criteria at least once after randomisation for a minimum interval of 24 weeks (using RECIST 1.1). To be used for both the overall patient population and in patients with PD-L1-positive tumours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Clinical Benefit</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of first tumour progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of Clinical Benefit is calculated as time (in months) from randomisation to progression or death from any cause in patients with a clinical benefit. To be used for both the overall patient population and in patients with PD-L1-positive tumours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of paclitaxel plus pembrolizumab versus paclitaxel through review of all AEs and SAEs assessed by CTCAE v4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of all adverse event resolution following discontinuation for any reason or death, assessed up to 30 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence, nature and severity of adverse events with severity determined according to CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life (QoL) as assessed by time to deterioration (TTD) in patient reported outcomes (PROs) in patients treated with paclitaxel plus pembrolizumab versus paclitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of safety visit (125 days after date of discontinuation for any reason)</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the time to deterioration (TTD) in Items 29 and 30 of the EORTC Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 30 (QLQ-C30) and the percentages of patients with a decrease or increase of ≥ 10 points on the global health status/HRQoL scale of the EORTC QLQ-C30, respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life (QoL) as assessed by the global health status/HRQoL scale of the EORTC QLQ-C30 on patient reported outcomes (PROs) in patients treated with paclitaxel plus pembrolizumab versus paclitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomisation to date of safety visit (125 days after date of discontinuation for any reason)</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the percentages of patients with a decrease or increase of ≥ 10 points on the global health status/HRQoL scale of the EORTC QLQ-C30</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">87</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>200 mg Pembrolizumab intravenously (IV) every 3 weeks (Q3W) plus 80 mg/m2 paclitaxel intravenously (IV) on Days 1,8, and 15 of each 28 day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>80 mg/m2 paclitaxel intravenously (IV) on Days 1,8, and 15 of each 28 day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg Pembrolizumab intravenously (IV) every 3 weeks (Q3W).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KEYTRUDA</other_name>
    <other_name>lambrolizumab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>80 mg/m2 paclitaxel intravenously (IV) on Days 1,8, and 15 of each 28 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab + Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Willing and able to provide written informed consent

          2. Ability to comply with the protocol

          3. Female ≥ 18 years of age

          4. Histologically confirmed metastatic or locally advanced breast cancer that is:

               1. ER+ve defined as tumours with ≥1% of tumour cells positive for ER on IHC staining
                  or an IHC score (Allred) of ≥ 3 and

               2. HER-2-ve defined as 0, 1+ or 2+ intensity on IHC and no evidence of amplification
                  of the HER2 gene on ISH and

               3. Luminal B defined as: high Ki67 defined as ≥20% and /or histological grade 3 and
                  / or Luminal B according to PAM50 assay

          5. Patients must have:

               1. at least one lesion, not previously irradiated, that can be measured accurately
                  at baseline as ≥ 10mm in the longest diameter (except lymph nodes which must have
                  short axis ≥ 15mm) with computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging
                  (MRI) which is suitable for accurate repeated measurements, or

               2. lytic or mixed (lytic + sclerotic) bone lesions in the absence of measurable
                  disease as defined above; patients with sclerotic/osteoblastic bone lesions only
                  in the absence of measurable disease are not eligible

          6. Representative formalin-fixed paraffin embedded (FFPE) breast tumour samples with an
             associated pathology report from the primary or recurrent cancer that are determined
             to be available and sufficient for central testing OR tumour accessible for biopsy.

          7. ECOG performance status 0-1

          8. Adequate haematologic and end-organ function within 28 days prior to the first study
             treatment defined by the following:

               1. ANC ≥ 1500 cells/μL (1.5 x 109/L) (without granulocyte colony-stimulating factor
                  support within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1)

               2. WBC &gt; 2500/μL (2.5 x 109/L)

               3. Platelet count ≥ 100,000/μL (100 x 109/L) (without transfusion within 2 weeks
                  prior to Cycle 1, Day 1)

               4. Haemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL (90g/L) (patients may be transfused or receive
                  erythropoietic treatment to meet this criterion).

               5. Serum albumin ≥ 3g/dL

               6. AST or ALT and ALP ≤ 2.5 times the institutional upper limit of normal (ULN),
                  bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN (patients with liver metastases who have AST or ALT ≤ 5 x
                  the institutional ULN may be enrolled, and patients with known Gilbert disease
                  who have serum bilirubin level ≤ 3 × the institutional ULN may be enrolled).

               7. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               8. INR and aPTT ≤ 1.5 × the institutional ULN. This applies only to patients who are
                  not receiving therapeutic anticoagulation; patients receiving therapeutic
                  anticoagulation should be on a stable dose.

          9. Patients of childbearing potential are eligible provided they have a negative serum or
             urine pregnancy test on Day 1 Cycle 1 (within 72 hours) of study treatment, preferably
             as close to the first dose as possible. Patients must agree to use adequate
             contraception, defined as those methods with a failure rate of &lt; 1 % per year, (see
             section 6.13) beginning 14 days before the first dose of study drug and for 3 months
             after the last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Luminal A breast cancer

          2. Prior chemotherapy for advanced or metastatic disease

          3. Prior treatment with paclitaxel in the (neo)adjuvant setting within 12 months from the
             end of paclitaxel treatment and randomisation into this study

          4. Patients with neuropathy ≥ Grade 2

          5. Previous systemic treatment for other neoplasms within 5 years prior to randomisation.

          6. Patients with prior allogeneic stem cell or solid organ transplantation.

          7. Prior treatment with CD137 agonists, AKT inhibitors, anti-CTLA-4, anti-OX-40,
             anti−programmed death−1 (PD-1), or anti−PD-L1 therapeutic antibody or
             pathway-targeting agents.

          8. Patients must not have a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving chronic
             systemic steroid therapy (in dosing exceeding 10 mg daily of prednisone equivalent),
             or had oral or IV steroids for 7 days prior to the first dose of study drug; the use
             of inhaled corticosteroids, physiologic replacement doses of glucocorticoids (i.e. for
             adrenal insufficiency) and mineralocorticoids (e.g. fludrocortisone) is allowed.

          9. Received therapeutic oral or intravenous antibiotics within 14 days prior to
             randomisation (Patients receiving prophylactic antibiotics (e.g., for prevention of a
             urinary tract infection or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease) are eligible).

         10. Administration of a live vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of study drug.
             Examples of live vaccines include, but are not limited to, the following: measles,
             mumps, rubella, varicella/zoster (chicken pox), yellow fever, rabies, Bacillus
             Calmette-Guérin (BCG), and typhoid vaccine. Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection
             are generally killed virus vaccines and are allowed; however, intranasal influenza
             vaccines (eg, FluMist®) are live attenuated vaccines and are not allowed.

         11. Treatment with systemic immunostimulatory agents (including but not limited to
             interferons or interleukin [IL] −2) within 28days or five half-lives of the drug,
             whichever is shorter, prior to randomisation.

         12. History of autoimmune disease including but not limited to myasthenia gravis,
             myositis, autoimmune hepatitis, systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis,
             inflammatory bowel disease, vascular thrombosis associated with antiphospholipid
             syndrome, Wegener's granulomatosis, Sjögren's syndrome, Guillain-Barré syndrome,
             multiple sclerosis, vasculitis, or glomerulonephritis. Patients with
             autoimmune-related hypothyroidism on a stable dose of thyroid replacement therapy may
             be eligible for the study following discussion with the medical monitor.

         13. History of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (including pneumonitis or interstitial lung
             disease), drug-induced pneumonitis, organizing pneumonia (i.e., bronchiolitis
             obliterans, cryptogenic organizing pneumonia) requiring steroids, or evidence of
             active pneumonitis on screening chest CT scan (History of radiation pneumonitis in the
             radiation field (fibrosis) is permitted).

         14. Active infection requiring systemic therapy.

         15. History of HIV infection

         16. Known active hepatitis infection (defined as having a positive hepatitis B surface
             antigen [HBsAg] test at screening) or hepatitis C. Patients with past hepatitis B
             virus (HBV) infection or resolved HBV infection (defined as having a negative HBsAg
             test and a positive antibody to hepatitis B core antigen [anti-HBc] antibody test) are
             eligible. Patients positive for hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody are eligible only if
             polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is negative for HCV RNA.

         17. Known history of active tuberculosis

         18. Any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding that, in the investigator's opinion, gives reasonable suspicion of
             a disease or condition that contraindicates the use of an investigational drug, may
             affect the interpretation of the results, render the patient at high risk from
             treatment complications or interferes with obtaining informed consent.

         19. Psychological, familial, sociological or geographical conditions that do not permit
             compliance with the study protocol.

         20. Concurrent treatment with other experimental drugs or participation in another
             clinical trial with therapeutic intent within 28 days prior to randomisation.

         21. Pregnant and lactating female patients.

         22. Major surgical procedure within 4 weeks prior to randomisation or anticipation of need
             for a major surgical procedure during the course of the study other than for
             diagnosis.

         23. Malignancies other than breast cancer within 5 years prior to Cycle 1, Day 1, with the
             exception of those with a negligible risk of metastasis or death and treated with
             expected curative outcome (such as adequately treated carcinoma in situ of the cervix,
             basal or squamous cell skin cancer, or ductal carcinoma in situ treated surgically
             with curative intent)

         24. Severe infections within 28 days prior to randomisation in the study including but not
             limited to hospitalization for complications of infection, bacteraemia, or severe
             pneumonia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Schmid, MD PhD FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen Mary University of London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>PELICAN Coordinator</last_name>
    <phone>020 7882 8487</phone>
    <email>bci-pelican@qmul.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charlotte Tyson</last_name>
    <phone>020 7882 8497</phone>
    <email>c.tyson@qmul.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ER-positive</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Locally Advanced</keyword>
  <keyword>Ki67</keyword>
  <keyword>PAM50</keyword>
  <keyword>Pembrolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Paclitaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>HER2-negative</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

