<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03847636</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00163804</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03847636</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CryoBalloon Ablation for Treatment of Duodenal Adenomas</brief_title>
  <acronym>C2D2</acronym>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of Cryoballoon Ablation for Treatment of Sporadic and Familial Nonampullary Nonpolypoid Duodenal Adenomas (the C2D2 Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pentax Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This multicenter prospective non-randomized interventional study (clinical trial) that will
      assess the safety and efficacy of cryoballoon ablation treatment using the C2 Cryoballoon
      device (Pentax Medical Corporation) as an alternative primary treatment modality for sporadic
      and familial nonampullary nonpolypoid (flat) duodenal adenomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Duodenal adenomas are precursors to adenocarcinoma. Treatment with endoscopic polypectomy is
      technically challenging problematic and associated with a high rate of complication - overall
      26%, with bleeding 22-40%, higher with larger polyps. Surgery to remove these benign polyps
      would be a Whipple operation, which has a high morbidity and 1-4% mortality rate. Medical
      therapies like celecoxib decrease the number of polyps but do not prevent cancer.

      This multicenter prospective cohort study will assess the safety and efficacy of cryoablation
      treatment as an alternative primary treatment modality for sporadic and familial nonampullary
      nonpolypoid (flat) duodenal adenomas

      Prospective studies have demonstrated the safety and efficacy of nitrous oxide focal
      cryoballoon ablation for complete eradication of Barrett's esophagus (including a clinical
      trial published by the Principal Investigator), which is intestinal metaplasia, which is
      histologically similar to normal duodenal mucosa.

      When inflated, the cryoballoon flattens the duodenal folds allowing improved visibility of
      the duodenal lesions. The focal ablation allows precise targeting and avoidance of the
      ampulla to minimize pancreatitis risk.

      Two cases at Johns Hopkins Hospital have been treated successfully and safely using cryogen
      dose of 10 seconds. The procedures were easy and short, with excellent views of the lesion
      with balloon inflation and high definition endoscope. No major adverse events, pain requiring
      treatment, or bleeding were noted. Minor adverse events included transient abdominal bloating
      lasting for &lt; 3 days in 1 patient. In one patient with sporadic laterally spreading large
      Paris 2A polyp who declined standard treatments, complete eradication was achieved with 2
      ablation sessions.

      In the other patient with familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP) who had 2 hospitalizations for
      post-polypectomy bleeding after duodenal EMR, complete eradication was noted after 1
      treatment of 3 Paris 2A and 2B adjacent polyps.

      Follow-up of these two patients shows no recurrence &gt; 1 year and at the most recent follow-up
      procedures. Clinical and endoscopic surveillance continues.

      In addition, another physician at the University of Texas Health Science Center at San
      Antonio (UTHSCSA) reported another two patients with duodenal adenomas in her practice
      treated successfully with cryoballoon ablation without complications. Two other collaborating
      physicians at Memorial Hermann Texas Medical Center in Houston, Texas, and Geisinger Medical
      Center in Pennsylvania have also reported favorable response of these challenging neoplasms
      to endoscopic cryoballoon ablation. The group is currently preparing a case series report and
      a separate Institutional Review Board application is being submitted.

      This study may impact on the management of patients with duodenal adenomas by demonstrating
      the potential for safe and effective non-operative eradication using cryoballoon ablation.
      The safety profile of endoscopic cryoballoon ablation is likely to be better than endoscopic
      resection based on a large clinical and research experience in Barrett's esophagus patients
      (&gt;250) and small clinical experience in duodenal adenoma patients, with &lt;=5% bleeding, no
      perforation, and transient, mild post-treatment discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Non-randomized pilot study of highly selected patients</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of cryoBalloon ablation in treating non-ampullary non-polypoid duodenal adenomas (DAs) as assessed by the incidence of adverse events in all treated patients</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To assess incidence of treatment-related adverse events following cryoablation using the C2 cryoballoon system, defined by frequency or number of adverse events in all treated patients (per patient analysis).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of cryoBalloon ablation in treating non-ampullary non-polypoid duodenal adenomas (DAs) as assessed by the incidence of adverse events in all treatment procedures</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To assess incidence of treatment-related adverse events following cryoablation using the C2 cryoballoon system, defined by frequency or number of adverse events in all treatment procedures (per procedure analysis).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete eradication rate of DAs</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Complete eradication (CE) rate of DAs as assessed by a combination of endoscopic and pathologic absence of adenomatous tissue in treated areas.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in the treated duodenal adenoma size</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Endoscopic assessment: percent change in adenoma size by blinded review by 3-person expert panel of still images with region of interest marked by tattoo - per lesion analysis and per patient analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical failure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Technical failure rate is the proportion of treatment procedures with cryoballoon ablation that did not complete delivery of cryogen to all targeted sites.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spigelman class score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in Spigelman classification for polyp burden in FAP patients from baseline to 1 year after treatment is completed. The Spigelman classification assigns points based upon polyp number, polyp size, histology and dysplasia grade, where Stage 0 = 0 points, Stage I = 1-4 points, Stage II = 5-6 points, Stage III = 7-8 points, and Stage IV = 9-12 points. The higher the score, the more severe or advanced the FAP disease in the duodenum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression rate to high grade dysplasia or duodenal cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression rate: percentage of patients with progression of dysplasia grade to high grade dysplasia or invasive cancer, compared to baseline biopsies, at any time during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to complete eradication of DAs in each patient</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to complete eradication (in months) of all duodenal adenomas in each patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to complete eradication of each treated DA lesion</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to complete eradication (in months) of each treated DA lesion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median number of CryoBalloon treatments to complete eradication.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Median number of cryoballoon ablation treatments to achieve complete eradication.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Duodenal Adenomas</condition>
  <condition>Familial Adenomatous Polyposis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Familial Adenomatous Polyposis (FAP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals with duodenal adenomas (DAs) and FAP with Spigelman class 2,3 or 4, treated with cryoballoon ablation (intervention)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sporadic duodenal adenomas</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals with at least 1 sporadic duodenal adenoma (DA) between 1-5 cm in maximum diameter, treated with cryoballoon ablation (intervention)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CryoBalloon ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>Endoscopic cryoablation (cryogen is contained nitrous) using a CryoBalloon catheter to ablate up to 4 separate DA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Familial Adenomatous Polyposis (FAP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sporadic duodenal adenomas</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Sporadic duodenal adenomas between 1 to 5 cm in widest diameter

          -  FAP patient with Spigelman class 2, 3 or 4 (see definition below)

          -  Polyp characteristics: Non-polypoid lesions Paris 2A and 2B, or

          -  Sessile adenomas, occupying no more than 50% circumference of duodenum, and no more
             than 3 duodenal folds

          -  Individuals must be considered high risk for surgery or endoscopic resection, due to
             complication risk, or declined standard therapies.

          -  Prior endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR) or saline-assisted polypectomy allowed if
             polyp characteristics meet inclusion criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Suspected or proven duodenal carcinoma

          -  Paris 1p pedunculated, Paris 2c, or 3 lesions

          -  Paris 1s lesion &gt; 4 mm thick (estimated with closed biopsy forceps)

          -  Ampullary lesion or lesion involving the ampulla

          -  Prior failed ablative treatment with Argon Plasma Coagulation, laser, or cryotherapy

          -  Pre-existing esophageal, gastric, pyloric, or duodenal stenosis/stricture preventing
             advancement of a therapeutic endoscope during screening/baseline
             esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD.) Subjects are eligible if the stenosis/stricture is
             dilated to at least 15mm, but baseline treatment may need to be delayed.

          -  Any endoscopically-visualized abnormalities such as ulcers, masses or nodules during
             screening/baseline EGD within 3 cm of the treatment area.

          -  Subjects with nodular polyps or suspicion of invasive cancer by white light endoscopy
             /enhanced imaging/biopsy identified during screening/baseline EGD

          -  Suspicion of malignancy by abdominal or endoscopic ultrasound imaging based on
             malignant lymph nodes, invasion of lesion beyond mucosa.

          -  EMR or polypectomy &lt; 6 weeks prior to baseline treatment.

          -  Untreated invasive esophageal malignancy, including margin-positive EMR.

          -  Active duodenitis in treatment zone during screening/baseline EGD.

          -  Severe medical comorbidities precluding endoscopy, or limiting life expectancy to less
             than 2 years in the judgment of the endoscopist.

          -  Uncontrolled coagulopathy or inability to be off anticoagulation or anti-platelet
             medication (ASA, Plavix) for 1 week prior to and 2 weeks after each endoscopy.

          -  Known portal hypertension, visible esophageal, gastric, or duodenal varices, or
             history of varices.

          -  General poor health, multiple co-morbidities placing the patient at risk, or otherwise
             unsuitable for trial participation.

          -  Pregnant or planning to become pregnant during period of study participation.

          -  Patient refuses or is unable to provide written informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcia I. Canto, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwell Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhasset</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geisinger Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danville</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist Dallas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Hermann Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenomatous Polyposis Coli</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Submit request to P.I. and study team with study goal.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>4 years</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Submit request to P.I. and study team with study goal.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

