<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03849573</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00206180</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03849573</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Web-Based Tool to Improve Breast Cancer Survivorship</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Mindfulness-Based e-Health Intervention to Improve Medication Adherence Among Breast Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the efficacy of a psychosocial eHealth intervention
      on the proposed primary outcomes, hormone therapy adherence and health related quality of
      life (HRQoL), in breast cancer survivors.

      The intervention components include mindfulness-based stress reduction, breast cancer
      knowledge, stress awareness and management, social support, and enhanced communication. The
      intervention will be delivered via an online application over an 8-week period.

      Participants are randomized into either an intervention application (described above) or a
      control application (health information and general health promotion strategies). Aside from
      having access to the online application for the recommended 8 weeks with weekly online focus
      groups, participation in this study includes four assessments: baseline (at the beginning of
      the research study), post-intervention (8 weeks after baseline), a 6-month follow-up and a
      12-month follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is the most commonly diagnosed cancer among women in the U.S. Approximately 75%
      to 80% of breast cancer survivors are prescribed HT (hormone therapy) medication for 5 to 10
      years following primary treatment. Five years of adjuvant HT among women with non-metastatic
      cancer reduces the risk of recurrences by 50%. Adherence to HT is also an independent
      predictor of breast cancer mortality, reducing the risk by up to 28%. HT-side effects,
      however, are not only a major source of distress but also among the most robust predictors of
      non-adherence to HT. Therefore, effective management and ability to reduce the burden of
      these side effects are critically important to achieve optimal HT adherence. Because HT side
      effects may persist for years and are not easily managed, MBSR's mind-body approach and
      emphasis on non-judgmental attitudes, acceptance, and uncertainty tolerance may be an
      especially beneficial approach to helping cancer survivors cope with the burdensome
      medication-related side effects, thus improving adherence to medication. The investigators
      propose that a mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) intervention that has been
      efficacious in reducing HT side effects and improving HRQoL in cancer patients may also prove
      beneficial in improving HT adherence. After developing a web-based MBSR intervention and
      refining it via a usability trial, this study will establish the feasibility of a
      web-delivered, group based MBSR intervention to improve HT medication adherence and HRQoL in
      patients being treated for breast cancer. It is hypothesized that participants assigned to
      the MBSR intervention will have better primary outcomes than participants in the control
      group, which receives standard health information.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Reported Adherence to Hormone Therapy will be evaluated with the ARMS questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The ARMS (Adherence to Refills and Medications Scale) survey is a previously validated patient-report measure of barriers to medication adherence and adherence-related behavior.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health Related Quality of Life will be evaluated with The Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Endocrine (FACT-ES)</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The FACT-ES has been used extensively to measure HRQoL. It assesses participant's wellbeing in physical, emotional, social, functional, and concerns specific to endocrine therapy in the last seven days using a five-point response scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Electronically Verified Hormone Therapy Adherence will be measured using medication event monitoring systems (MEMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>MEMS data will be collected continuously during study participation from T1 (prior to starting intervention) to T4 (12 months post-intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>A MEMS cap is an electronic bottle cap that tracks when participants open their medication bottle. MEMS cap data will be collected continuously during the duration of participation in the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacy reported Adherence to Hormone Therapy will be measured using pharmacological records</measure>
    <time_frame>T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacy data will be pulled once at approximately T4 when a participant finishes the study. This data will inform how frequently patients refill their hormone therapy medication.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer-Specific Distress will be evaluated using The Impact of Event Scale (IES)</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The IES is made up of two subscales measuring the frequency of intrusion and avoidance experiences after a stressful event. The IES has been widely used among patients diagnosed with cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast Cancer Related Knowledge will be evaluated with the Knowledge about Breast Cancer Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>This quiestionnaire has been tested and validated with breast cancer patients. It is made up of 16 true and false questions regarding general breast cancer knowledge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast Cancer Related Communication and Attitudinal Self Efficacy will be evaluated using the Communication and Attitudinal Self-Efficacy scale for cancer (CASE-cancer)</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The CASE-cancer questionnaire is made up various subscales measuring breast cancer related communication and attitudinal self-efficacy. Each question asks participants to use a four-point response scale to agree or disagree with statements regarding their level of confidence with different skills.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress Management Skills will be evaluated with the Brief COPE Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief COPE is made up of various subscales measuring different ways of coping. Each question as participants to rate how often they have used each coping mechanism in response to their breast cancer experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived benefits and cost barriers to using hormone therapy will be assessed using a Beliefs about Medicines scale</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The 11 point Beliefs about Medicines questionnaire assesses patients' beliefs about the efficacy of their treatment as well as their beliefs about how the benefits and side affects of hormone therapy affect their life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Reported Negative Mood is measured with the Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Depression questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The PROMIS Depression questionnaire is a computer adaptive assessment that measures patients' self-reported level of negative mood within the past 7 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotional Social Support is assessed using the emotional subscale portion of the Medical Outcomes Study - Social Support Survey Instrument (MOS-SSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The 8 question MOS-SSS scale was developed by RAND Healthcare to assess the degree of companionship, assistance, or other types of social support that participants have access to. This study will use the 8 question emotional-informational support subsection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Self-Efficacy in managing side effects is measured using the PROMIS Self Efficacy for Managing Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The PROMIS Self Efficacy for Managing Symptoms survey is a validated, computer adaptive survey to assess how confident participants are in their ability to manage their symptoms and side effects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mindfulness will be assessed using questionnaires tailored to MBSR treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The Intolerance of Uncertainty, Rumination and Reassure Me survey assesses participants' development in MBSR intervention targets, which will help isolate and assess the effect of MBSR treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concerns about cancer recurrence will be measured using the Concerns about Recurrence scale</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (prior to starting intervention), T2 (8 weeks post intervention), T3 (6 months post-intervention), T4 (12 months post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>The Concerns about Recurrence scale is a 4 question scale that assesses the frequency and intensity of patients' concerns about cancer recurrence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Hormone Dependent Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Adherence to Hormone Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-based stress reduction + Hormone Therapy Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hormone Therapy Education + Overall Health Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>&quot;OncoTool&quot; Intervention (MBSR + HT education)</intervention_name>
    <description>OncoTool is a website intended to improve self-management practices for helping cancer patients cope with stress and improve health-related quality of life. OncoTool provides mindfulness-based education and management for dealing with the numerous physical and mental side effects associated with hormone therapy (e.g., muscle and joint pain, vaginal dryness, depressive symptoms). OncoTool is a website designed to improve hormone therapy adherence by improving quality of life, and hormone therapy associated symptom burden. Both intervention and active comparator conditions are administered to participants for 8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-based stress reduction + Hormone Therapy Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>&quot;Oncotool&quot; Control (health +HT education)</intervention_name>
    <description>OncoTool is a health promotion website with health education on subjects like nutrition and exercise specific to breast cancer survivors, as well as general advice on lifestyle choices and prevention. The Oncotool control has similar HT education content as the experimental content but without the CBT and MBSR state. Both intervention and active comparator conditions are administered to participants for 8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hormone Therapy Education + Overall Health Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. ≥ 18 years of age

          2. English-speaking (6th grade reading level) as required to complete assessments

          3. medical chart confirmed diagnosis of hormone-receptor positive non-metastatic breast
             cancer

          4. Stages I-IIIa

          5. completion of any combination of surgical, radiation, and chemotherapy treatment

          6. willingness to be randomized into study

          7. have initiated HT within the past 4 months as data in literature indicates that the
             overwhelming majority of women who initiated HT are still adherent within the first 4
             months

          8. first-time diagnosis of breast cancer

          9. access to a computer or tablet with Internet capabilities

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Visual, hearing, voice, or motor impairment that would prevent completion of study
             procedures

          2. diagnosis of an unmanaged psychotic or psychiatric disorder (e.g., clinical
             depression, anxiety, or PTSD), bipolar disorder, dissociative disorder, or other
             diagnosis for which participation in this trial is either inappropriate or dangerous -
             this includes patients who have life-threatening illness (e.g., end-stage kidney
             disease) or diagnosis of a chronic disease that is associated with a major functional
             impairment (e.g., chronic severe pain, fibromyalgia)

          3. Alzheimer's, dementia or history of stroke
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Betina Yanez, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Diana Buitrago</last_name>
    <phone>3125032866</phone>
    <email>diana.buitrago@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Betina Yanez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3125035341</phone>
    <email>betina.yanez@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diana Buitrago</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-2866</phone>
      <email>diana.buitrago@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Betina Yanez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>eHealth</keyword>
  <keyword>Adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Related Quality of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptom Burden</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Hormone-Dependent</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data (IPD) will not be shared with any researchers outside Northwestern.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 8, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT03849573/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

