<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03848312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WIRB® Protocol #20182630</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R56AG058234-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03848312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing Alzheimer's Disease With Cognitive Training</brief_title>
  <acronym>PACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Preventing Alzheimer's Disease With Cognitive Training: The PACT Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of South Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michigan State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of South Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dementia is the most expensive medical condition in the US and increases in prevalence with
      age. More than 5 million Americans have Alzheimer's disease, the most common form of
      dementia. Mild cognitive impairment is a transitional stage between normal cognitive aging
      and Alzheimer's disease or another type of dementia, and is indicative of higher risk for
      dementia. In addition to the obvious health and quality-of-life ramifications of dementia,
      there are high direct (e.g., subsidizing residential care needs) and indirect (e.g., lost
      productivity of family caregivers) economic costs. Implementing interventions to prevent MCI
      and dementia among older adults is of critical importance to health and maintained
      quality-of-life for millions of Americans. Recent data analyses from the Advanced Cognitive
      Training in Vital Elderly study (ACTIVE) indicate that a specific cognitive intervention,
      speed of processing training (SPT), significantly delays the incidence of cognitive
      impairment across 10 years. The primary contribution of the proposed research will be the
      determination of whether this cognitive training technique successfully delays the onset of
      clinically defined MCI or dementia across three years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preventing Alzheimer's Disease with Cognitive Training: The PACT Trial

      The primary objective is to establish the feasibility of the proposed field trial including
      meeting participant enrollment goals. The feasibility of the field trial will be established
      by identifying enrollment sites, hiring and training staff in study protocols and standard
      operating procedures, developing marketing tools, and initiating recruitment. The enrollment
      goal is to accrue 1600 participants within 1 year of starting data collection.

      The secondary objective is to ascertain participants' willingness to enroll in a longitudinal
      clinical trial and to subsequently complete a multispecialty clinical diagnostic evaluation,
      psychometric testing, MRI, PET scan, and genetic testing. Participants' willingness to allow
      access to medicare records will also be determined.

      If the trial is funded and extended into a longitudinal study, the primary goal of the
      subsequent trial will be to ascertain the effectiveness of cognitive speed of processing
      training (SPT) to reduce the incidence of MCI or dementia.

      Design and Outcomes: A pilot randomized clinical trial among 1600 adults 65 years of age and
      older will be completed in order to demonstrate the feasibility of conducting a larger trial
      designed to test the effectiveness of computerized cognitive speed of processing training
      (SPT) to reduce incidence of Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) or dementia.

      Participants will be screened with an inclusion/exclusion questionnaire and those potentially
      eligible will complete brief memory screening, depression screening, and other
      questionnaires. Those eligible will be randomized to either cognitive speed of processing
      training (SPT) or an active control condition (computer games) and will complete at least
      three in-person, supervised training sessions. Additional exercises will be completed at-home
      over the next 3 to 5 months followed by booster sessions 1- and 2-years later. Participants'
      willingness to enroll in a longitudinal trial and to subsequently complete a multispecialty
      clinical diagnostic evaluation, MRI, psychometric testing, PET scan, genetic testing, and to
      allow access to Medicare records will be assessed.

      Participants will initially complete 25 sessions of training and will complete an additional
      10 sessions of booster training 1- and 2- years later. Participants will first be instructed
      to complete 2-3 sessions of training per week until 25 sessions are completed. At 1- year and
      again at 2-years, participants will be instructed to complete an additional 10 sessions of
      training.

      Sample Size and Population: Adults 65 years of age and older (N=1600) will be randomly
      assigned to SPT (n=800) or the control condition (n=800).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants enrolled</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure will be the number of participants enrolled in this pilot trial by one year after start of data collection. The goal is at least 1200 participants successfully enrolled after 1 year of data collection, demonstrating the feasibility of a larger trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence, which will be quantified as percent of participants who completed 20 or more sessions of assigned exercises.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of participant's adherent to complete at least 20 sessions of assigned exercises. The goal is for at least 75% of those randomized to be adherent, demonstrating feasibility of a larger trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demographics of the sample including race, ethnicity, and education levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of data collection</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome is descriptive in nature. The diversity of the enrolled sample will be assessed by quantifying the racial, ethnic, and educational composition of the enrolled study sample. The goal is to approximate characteristics of the US older adult population by obtaining a sample that includes 85% Caucasians, 8.5% African Americans and 3.5% Asian Americans; across whom 7% will be of Hispanic ethnicity. The goal is for &lt;=85% of the sample to have education levels of high school or more and &gt;=15% of the sample with education levels less than high school.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of enrolled participants who are willing to participate in a longitudinal trial</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of enrolled participants who are willing to further participate in a subsequent longitudinal trial will be quantified. This is assessed by one yes/no question. The proportion of participants who answer yes will be quantified. The goal is for at least 80% of the enrolled participants to indicate yes that they are willing to participate in a follow-up study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who are willing to complete planned study measures.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The willingness of participants to complete assessments in a subsequent trial including: clinical diagnostic evaluation, psychometric testing, MRI, PET scan, and genetic testing is assessed. Their willingness to allow access to medicare records will also be determined. This is assessed through a questionnaire with yes/no answers across six items. The percentage who endorse yes to these items will be measured. The goal is for at least 80% of the participants to endorse at least 4 of the questions as yes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1600</enrollment>
  <condition>Age-related Cognitive Decline</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Computerized Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will complete computerized cognitive training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Computerized Cognitive Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will complete cognitively-stimulating computer activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be completing a total of 45 computerized sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Computerized Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computerized Cognitive Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be completing a total of 45 computerized cognitive stimulation sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Computerized Cognitive Stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be age 65 or older at time of consent

          -  Have ability to speak and understand English

          -  Report adequate sensorimotor capacity to perform the computer exercises

          -  Report adequate visual capacity to read from a computer screen at a typical viewing
             distance

          -  Show adequate auditory capacity to understand conversational speech

          -  Show adequate motor capacity to touch a computer screen or control a computer mouse.

          -  Have no evidence of Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) or dementia, as assessed by the
             Montreal Cognitive Assessment score &gt;=26.

          -  Have adequate mental health (no self-reported diagnoses of mental illness that would
             interfere with ability to comply with study procedures or benefit from intervention)

          -  Wiling to complete all study activities

          -  Ability to understand study procedures and comply with them for the length of the
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently enrolled in another randomized clinical trial, treatment trial, or another
             research study that assesses cognition

          -  Previous participation in a USF Cognitive Aging Lab cognitive training study

          -  Self-reported vision, hearing, or motor difficulties that would interfere with the
             ability to complete the study interventions

          -  Self-reported diagnosis of mild cognitive impairment, dementia, stroke, traumatic
             brain injury, brain tumor, or a neurological disorder that affects cognition or would
             interfere with the ability to benefit from the study intervention (e.g., Parkinson
             disease, multiple sclerosis), or any other unstable medical conditions that is
             predisposing to imminent cognitive or functional decline (e.g., congestive heart
             failure, chronic obstructive pulmonary disorder dependent on oxygen, or undergoing
             chemotherapy or radiation).

          -  Self-reported use of medications typically prescribed for dementia such as Namenda,
             Memantine, Namzaric, Donepezil, Aricept, Rivastigmine, Exelon, Razadyne, Galantamine,
             or Reminyl.

          -  Completion of 10 or more hours of a computerized cognitive training program in the
             last 5 years such as: Lumosity, Posit Science Brain Fitness, InSight, or Brain HQ,
             Lace, CogMed, CogniFit, Happy Neuron, or Dakim

          -  Severe depressive symptoms (Geriatric Depression Scale score &gt;=5)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jerri Edwards, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>813.974.8572</phone>
    <email>usftampapact@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alisa Houseknecht, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>813.974.8572</phone>
    <email>usftampapact@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33620</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cognitive Aging Lab</last_name>
      <phone>813-974-8572</phone>
      <email>usftampapact@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jerri Edwards, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ross Andel, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ming Ji, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Lister, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Hudak, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer O'Brien, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michigan State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grand Rapids</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>49503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Baraa Abu-Dalu</last_name>
      <phone>616-234-0952</phone>
      <email>msupact@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kelsey Magolan</last_name>
      <phone>616-234-0952</phone>
      <email>msupact@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dave Morgan, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

