<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03843021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00157335</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03843021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ventricular Assist Device (VAD) Infection Prevention Survey</brief_title>
  <official_title>Understanding and Addressing Variation in Healthcare-Associated Infections After Durable Ventricular Assist Device Therapy: Organizational: Aim 1 Survey</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Annually, more than 250,000 patients in the U.S. with end-stage heart failure stand to
      benefit from ventricular assist device (VAD) therapy. 60% of patients develop a
      healthcare-associated infection (HAI) within 90-days of implantation. The investigators long
      term goal is to develop and subsequently promote wide-scale adoption of evidence-based HAI
      prevention practices following durable VAD implantation.

      This will be done by addressing the following aims:

      Aim 1. Identify determinants of center-level variability in HAI rates. Aim 2. Develop a
      comprehensive understanding of barriers and facilitators for achieving low center HAI rates.

      Aim 3. Develop, iteratively enhance, and disseminate a best practices toolkit for preventing
      HAIs that accommodates various center contexts.

      The investigators will use a focused survey of U.S. VAD centers to identify determinants of
      center variation in 90-day HAI rates:

        -  Process Factors (e.g., intranasal mupirocin),

        -  Provider Factors (e.g., surgeon technique),

        -  Device Factors (e.g., centrifugal vs. axial),

        -  Center Factors (e.g., provider communication).

      Understanding the barriers and facilitators within individual centers for maximizing adoption
      of prevention measures would serve as the foundation for targeted improvement strategies.
      Without this knowledge, evidence-based, action-oriented recommendations will have limited
      local adoption and ultimately effectiveness in preventing HAIs after VAD implantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Annually, more than 250,000 patients in the U.S. with end-stage heart failure stand to
      benefit from ventricular assist device (VAD) therapy. Despite VADs providing long-term
      &quot;durable&quot; support, this therapy is associated with substantial risk (50% mortality at 4
      years) and expense ($179,000 for inpatient services). Additionally, 60% of patients develop a
      healthcare-associated infection (HAI) within 90-days of implantation. Broad adoption of
      durable VAD therapy is hindered in part by HAIs, given associated sequelae (6-fold increased
      risk of 1-year mortality) and costs ($264,000 - $869,000 per patient). It is critical to
      determine how best to prevent HAIs in order to maximize the benefit of VAD therapy. While
      several studies have reported variation in HAI rates across centers after complex cardiac
      surgery, less is known in the setting of durable VADs. The average 90-day HAI rate after VAD
      implantation is as high as 19 events per 100 patient-months and varies (25th - 75th
      percentile, 9-23) across centers. While some argue that centers with lower HAI rates select
      healthier patients, others counter that improved practices (e.g., standardizing empirical and
      targeted antimicrobial therapy) or enhanced provider teamwork are more predictive of improved
      outcomes.

      While evidence-based HAI prevention guidelines and implementation tools (e.g., checklists)
      exist, these approaches are not comprehensive (e.g., neglecting device-specific determinants)
      or customizable to local context, thus limiting usability, adoption, and likelihood of
      significant effectiveness for preventing HAIs. Understanding the barriers and facilitators
      within individual centers for maximizing adoption of prevention measures would serve as the
      foundation for targeted improvement strategies. Without this knowledge, evidence-based,
      action-oriented recommendations will have limited local adoption and ultimately effectiveness
      in preventing HAIs after VAD implantation.

      The investigators long-term goal is to develop and subsequently promote wide-scale adoption
      of evidence-based HAI prevention practices following durable VAD implantation. The objective
      of this proposal is to identify prevention recommendations for the most significant HAIs
      after VAD implantation. To achieve this objective, the investigators will undertake a mixed
      methods study of adult patients receiving VADs in the U.S. from 2009 - 2017 and develop a
      modular toolkit of evidence-based recommendations. To determine best practices for preventing
      HAIs, the investigators will examine center-level differences in HAI rates to identify
      strategies used by centers with low rates, and potential barriers among centers with high
      rates.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>An organization's use of practices associated with center HAI rates.</measure>
    <time_frame>March 2019 - March 2020</time_frame>
    <description>We will use a survey to identify a center's use of practices that may explain their center's HAI rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Healthcare Associated Infection</condition>
  <condition>Ventricular Assist Device</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VAD Healthcare Providers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Adult healthcare providers of VAD therapy recipients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VAD Infection Prevention Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthcare providers caring for VAD Therapy recipients will answer questions regarding processes of care at their institutions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VAD Healthcare Providers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthcare providers involved in the medical management of a Ventricular Assist Device
        (VAD) recipient during the peri-operative period, specifically surgeons, cardiologist, VAD
        coordinators.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthcare providers involved in the medical management of a Ventricular Assist Device
        (VAD) recipient during the peri-operative period, including those with the following roles:
        surgeons, cardiologists and VAD coordinators

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Healthcare providers not caring for VAD recipient patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald S Likosky, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Donald Likosky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cross Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will not be sharing individual participant data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

