<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03845842</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018 5701</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03845842</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Implementation Intentions to Reduce Cannabis Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of a Volitional Help Sheet in Cannabis Users</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manchester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manchester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will recruit frequent users of cannabis (defined at least fortnightly use) and
      randomize them either to: (1) form implementation intentions by linking situations in which
      they are tempted to use cannabis with strategies to avoid using cannabis in those situations
      by using a volitional help sheet, or (2) to consider the situations in which they are tempted
      to use cannabis alongside possible strategies to avoid using it as presented in the
      volitional help sheet but not to form implementation intentions. The effects on self-reported
      cannabis use will be assessed 1 month post-intervention. Predictors of cannabis reduction
      will also be examined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design: This study will use questionnaires to assess participants cannabis habits (frequency
      and amount of use) and then employ planning strategies to help them quit. Follow up
      questionnaires will be used to ascertain the success of planning on reduction in cannabis
      use.

      Sample Size: We plan to recruit a minimum of 60 participants in each condition (120 total)
      but aim to collect data from as many participants as possible.

      Recruitment: To participate in this study a person must be over the age of 18 and a frequent
      user of cannabis. The study will be advertised online on social media platforms.

      Procedure: Potential participants will follow an online link to a briefing sheet that
      provides information about the study. The sheet will also inform participants that they do
      not have to complete the questionnaire and that they can withdraw from the study at any time
      without giving a reason. Once they have read the briefing sheet and generated their personal
      identity code, as instructed, they will complete the questionnaire online. A month after the
      participants have completed the initial questionnaire they will receive a link to a follow-up
      questionnaire via email. Email addresses will be stored separately to study data and will be
      destroyed once the follow up phase has completed and their involvement in the study ends.

      Outcomes and Analysis: The main purpose of this study is to explore the role of planning in
      encouraging people to reduce cannabis use. Quantitative analysis will be conducted to assess
      the effects of planning on cannabis use reduction. The investigators expect to find that
      planning is effective in helping people reduce their use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cannabis use reduction (amount)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported cannabis use -amount of cannabis (weight)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cannabis use reduction (frequency)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported cannabis use - frequency of use (days per week)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self reported habit as measured by the automaticity subscale of the Self-Report Habit Index.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported habit (e.g., &quot;Using cannabis is something I do automatically: strongly agree - strongly disagree).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self reported action control as measured by the scale developed by Sniehotta et al (2011)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported action control (e.g., &quot;During the last week I often had my intention to reduce my cannabis use on my mind: strongly disagree-strongly agree&quot;)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self reported craving as measured by items from the mood and physical symptoms scale (MPSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>self reported craving</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Cannabis Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (volitional help sheet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants read a brief statement designed to encourage them to reduce their cannabis use (&quot;We want you to plan to reduce your cannabis use&quot;). Participants are presented with a table with two columns and twenty rows. Twenty 'high risk' situations (temptations) are presented in the left hand column and 20 appropriate responses (processes of change) are presented in the right hand column (see Armitage, 2008). Participants are told that identifying situations in which they were tempted to use cannabis and identifying ways to overcome those temptations had been shown to help people change their behaviour and are asked to tick critical situations/appropriate responses that might be useful to them.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (volitional help sheet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants read a brief statement designed to encourage them to reduce their cannabis use (&quot;We want you to plan to reduce your cannabis use&quot;). Participants are presented with a table with two columns and twenty rows. Twenty 'high risk' situations (temptations) are presented in the left hand column and 20 appropriate responses (processes of change) are presented in the right hand column (see Armitage, 2008). Participants are told that identifying situations in which they were tempted to use cannabis and identifying ways to overcome those temptations had been shown to help people change their behaviour. Implementation intentions are formed by linking critical situations with appropriate responses by choosing an appropriate response from a drop down menu for each critical situation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Volitional help sheet</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are asked to choose from a list of strategies for avoiding cannabis use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control (volitional help sheet)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (volitional help sheet)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Frequent cannabis user (at least fortnightly)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Younger than 18 years of age

          -  Infrequent / no cannabis use (less than fortnightly)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lynsey Gregg, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Manchester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lynsey Gregg, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01612758486</phone>
    <email>lynsey.gregg@manchester.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chris Armitage, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01613066000</phone>
    <email>chris.armitage@manchester.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Manchester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M13 9PL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lynsey Gregg, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>01612758486</phone>
      <email>lynsey.gregg@manchester.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chris Armitage, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>01613066000</phone>
      <email>chris.armitage@manchester.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sniehotta FF, Nagy G, Scholz U, Schwarzer R. The role of action control in implementing intentions during the first weeks of behaviour change. Br J Soc Psychol. 2006 Mar;45(Pt 1):87-106.</citation>
    <PMID>16573874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gardner B, Abraham C, Lally P, de Bruijn GJ. Towards parsimony in habit measurement: testing the convergent and predictive validity of an automaticity subscale of the Self-Report Habit Index. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2012 Aug 30;9:102. doi: 10.1186/1479-5868-9-102.</citation>
    <PMID>22935297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>West R, Hajek P. Evaluation of the mood and physical symptoms scale (MPSS) to assess cigarette withdrawal. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2004 Dec;177(1-2):195-9. Epub 2004 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>15179542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Manchester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lynsey Gregg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cannabis</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk reduction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Marijuana Abuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

