<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03846999</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SURBCAN Project</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03846999</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comorbidities and Health Care Services Utilisation Among Long-term Breast Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <acronym>SURBCAN</acronym>
  <official_title>Comorbidities and Health Care Services Utilisation Among Long-term Breast Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Parc de Salut Mar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fondo de Investigacion Sanitaria</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Regional Development Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Red de Investigación en Servicios de Salud y Enfermedades Crónicas (REDISSEC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Parc de Salut Mar</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The increased likelihood of survival can be explained by numerous factors, such as
      improvements in breast cancer screening and advances in diagnosis and treatment and aging.
      This phenomenon is associated with comorbidity due to cancer treatment and external factors
      like aging or lifestyle. Little is known about how these women follow-up their disease, their
      pattern of use of health resources and their met and unmet needs. Studying the health needs
      of these women is a cancer-related priority for Cancer Organizations.The project is aimed at:
      1) Describing the comorbidities and patterns of use of primary and specialized care in women
      who have survived a breast cancer for at least five years; 2) Comparing the comorbidities and
      patterns of use of long time breast cancer survivors with women without a cancer diagnosis;
      and 3) Estimating the use of resources in long time survivors of breast cancer adjusted for
      survival-time and comorbidities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The general objective of this study is to analyze the pattern of comorbidities and
      utilization of primary care officers and specialized attention of long-term breast cancer
      survivors and to compare it with women without history of cancer. Long-term breast cancer
      survivors are those women who survived for at least five years since de primary breast cancer
      diagnosis.The use of health care services for long-term breast cancer survivors presents new
      challenges for health systems in terms of defining the role of each health professional and
      each level of care in contact with these women during their follow-up.

      The SURBCAN Project is an observational study that includes a retrospective cohort of women
      from five Spanish areas. The study is based on Real World Data from clinical history and
      tumor registration. Women with a diagnosis of breast cancer and a survival period of ≥ 5
      years were identified, as well as those women without a cancer diagnosis and matched by age
      and area with breast cancer survivors (1:2). N= 21639 women (7241 cases /13,398 controls).
      Sociodemographic and clinical variables were included. The use of primary care and hospital
      attention and the presence of comorbidities were assessed during the follow-up period
      (2012-2016). The basal cohort, the comorbidities and the use of health services were
      described. Factors associated with use were analyzed through multi-level logistic regression
      models.

      Expected results: Nowadays there are no results of cohort analysis that focus specifically in
      long-term breast cancer survivors. The SURBCAN study will provide evidence regarding
      comorbidity patterns and follow-up characteristics. The results will guide the elaboration of
      new recommendations and the decision making by stakeholders concerned to breast cancer
      survivor's follow-up.

      This project combines the experience from experts groups in health services assessment, and
      analysis of comorbidities and chronic diseases, belonging to the REDISSEC network.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years of survival</time_frame>
    <description>Number of comorbidities of each woman at five-year survival from breast cancer. Assessed through ICD10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of visits to healthcare services</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years of survival</time_frame>
    <description>Number of visits to primary care attention or specialised attention done by each women at five-year survival from breast cancer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Main health provider visited</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years of survival</time_frame>
    <description>Leading provider of health services (GP, oncologist, community nurse, oncology nurse, physiotherapist...) of each women at five-year survival from breast cancer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of visits to primary care attention</measure>
    <time_frame>at 5 years of survival</time_frame>
    <description>Number of visits to primary care attention done by each women at five-year survival from breast cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of visits to specialized care attention</measure>
    <time_frame>at 5 years of survival</time_frame>
    <description>Number of visits to specialised attention done by each women at five-year survival from breast cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Annual mammogram frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the percentage of women who have a mammogram every year.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21639</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Long-term breast cancer survivors</arm_group_label>
    <description>Analyze comorbidities and patterns of use of health services. Describe the specific use of health services in primary care vs. specialized care.
Analyze comorbidities and patterns of use of health services by tumor characteristics.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Women without history of cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Analyze comorbidities and patterns of use of health services. Describe the specific use of health services in primary care vs. specialized care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women with a diagnosis of breast cancer (during 2000 until 2006) with a survival period of
        ≥ 5 years that had a visit with the healthcare services during the period from 2012 to 2016
        were identified, as well as those women without a cancer diagnosis and matched by age and
        area with breast cancer survivors.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  &gt;18 years old

          -  Women diagnosed with an incident breast cancer during the period from 01/01/2000 until
             31/12/2006 who survived for at least 5 years.

          -  Women who visited at least once the primary health services during follow-up period
             (01/01/2012 to 31/12/2016).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Unknown diagnostic year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Long-term breast cancer survivors (women who survived at least 5 years from the diagnosis)</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Parc de Salut Mar</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Sala</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Evaluation and Quality, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>comorbidities</keyword>
  <keyword>healthcare services research</keyword>
  <keyword>survival</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

