<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03843190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00100588</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03843190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Me: A Program for Older Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Changes in Weight and Physical Function for Older African American Women in a National, Nonprofit, Community-Based, Peer-Led, Weight Loss Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators approach will be a 12-month cluster randomized trial with a waitlist
      control that recruits 240 older AA women through public housing communities and senior
      centers in North Carolina. The rationale for these aims is that the successful completion is
      expected to provide evidence that a community-based, peer-led weight loss program with a
      national infrastructure can help a vulnerable, underserved population lose weight and improve
      their physical function. For older, obese, frail individuals, this could improve their CVD
      risk factors, quality of life, enhance their health; reduce their healthcare utilization,
      illness, and disability; and decrease their adverse geriatric outcomes. After completing
      these aims, the investigators expect that they will have proven that the community-based,
      peer-led weight loss program can improve both weight and physical function among older, obese
      AA women. This also could help other demographic groups with obesity and poor physical
      function. Eventually, it could help older adults maintain their health and independence in
      the community
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Older African American (AA) women have the highest prevalence of both obesity and frailty. In
      academic, expert-led interventions, obese, frail, older individuals both lost weight and
      improved their physical function. However, because of high personnel costs and nonexistent
      nationwide infrastructure, large-scale implementation of these interventions is impractical.
      The long-term goals are to eliminate the health disparities of obesity and frailty in older
      AA women. This proposal's overall objective is to determine the effects of a low-cost,
      community-based, peer-led weight loss program with a national infrastructure on obesity,
      physical function, and healthcare utilization in older AA women. To treat obesity and frailty
      in older AA women, it is critical to test a weight loss intervention that 1) has preliminary
      evidence of benefit; 2) is acceptable to older AA women; 3) is affordable; and 4) can be
      broadly disseminated. Take Off Pounds Sensibly (TOPS) is a national, nonprofit,
      community-based, peer-led weight loss program that meets these criteria. First, the
      applicant's retrospective database analyses of TOPS showed two important results: 1)
      Participants who renew their annual membership lose and maintain significant weight loss
      (SWL) for up to 7 years; and 2) Compared to their younger counterparts, older women are more
      likely to achieve SWL. Second, the applicant started three TOPS chapters for older AA women
      in a successful pilot study. Though the study ended in 2012, one of the chapters is still
      active almost 6 years later. Third, TOPS is affordable; it only costs $92 annually. Finally,
      TOPS has a nationwide infrastructure with chapters in all 50 states. Since obese, frail,
      older individuals in academic, expert-led weight loss interventions can improve their
      physical function, the central hypothesis is that a low cost, community-based, peer-led
      weight loss program with a national infrastructure can provide SWL, improved physical
      function, and lower healthcare utilization for AA women, an underserved, vulnerable
      population. The rationale for the proposed research is that TOPS and academic, expert-led
      weight loss interventions share components critical to successful weight loss; therefore,
      TOPS can deliver similar outcomes. The central hypothesis will be tested by pursuing the
      following aims in obese, frail, older AA women: Determine the effect of TOPS on 1) weight
      change and cardiovascular disease risk factors; 2) physical function and quality of life; and
      3) healthcare utilization. This project is innovative because it uses a &quot;community to
      academia&quot; approach to treat the health disparities; our study population focuses on older AA
      women with decreased physical function; our outcomes focus on weight, physical function, and
      healthcare utilization; and our unique study settings. The proposed research is significant
      because determining the real-world effectiveness of the TOPS program and its impact on
      weight, physical function, and healthcare utilization in AA women can have a widespread
      impact on the older population at large. Thus, it has the potential to reduce adverse
      geriatric outcomes among all older individuals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight change</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of weight loss over 12 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function as measured by Short physical performance battery (SPPB)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function as measured by 6-minute walk</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function as measured by 8-ft up and go</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function as measured by 30-second chair stands</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function as measured by Isometric hand grip</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Disease (CVD) risk factors as measured by Blood pressure (BP)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Disease (CVD) risk factors as measured by Waist circumference (WC)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Disease (CVD) risk factors as measured by Hemoglobin A1c (HA1c)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Disease (CVD) risk factors as measured by Lipids</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) as measured by 36-item short form survey (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) as measured by Center for Epidemiologic Studies - Depression (CES-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) as measured by Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) as measured by Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization as measured by surveys of inpatient stays and outpatient visits</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Take Off Pounds Sensibly (TOPS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive TOPS intervention at the start of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be the control group for the initial year of the study. Then at the completion of the study they will receive the TOPS intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Take of Pounds Sensibly (TOPS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Peer led</description>
    <arm_group_label>Take Off Pounds Sensibly (TOPS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  African American women aged ≥60

          -  BMI ≥30 kg/m2

          -  decreased physical function (i.e., those who score between 4 and 10 [out of 12] on the
             Short Physical Performance Battery [SPPB])

          -  Stable body weight (± 2 kg for 6 months prior to study)

          -  Sedentary (not exercising more than 1 hour per week)

        Conditional Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants with type 2 diabetes on insulin or sulfonylureas will be allowed to
        participate in the study only if their providers agree to manage the changing medications
        requirements associated with possible weight loss by signing a &quot;Permission to Participate&quot;
        form. It is important to include type 2 diabetics on insulin and sulfonylureas because
        these participants can benefit greatly from weight loss.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 diabetics on insulin or sulfonylureas without provider approval

          -  current cancer diagnosis

          -  use of medications thought to effect metabolism, body weight, energy expenditure, or
             appetite

          -  major psychiatric disorder

          -  current moderate to severe symptoms of depression

          -  dementia

          -  neurological conditions causing functional limitations

          -  unstable medical illness such as unstable angina, recent MI, or congestive heart
             failure class III-IV

          -  terminal medical conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>African-American women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>weight loss</keyword>
  <keyword>african american women</keyword>
  <keyword>physical function</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

