<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03848364</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAQ6052</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2R01NS067443-06</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03848364</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hip Hop Stroke: Statewide Dissemination of a School-based Public Stroke Education Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hip Hop Stroke: Statewide Dissemination of a School-based Public Stroke Education Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to disseminate Hip Hop Stroke 2.0 (HHS2.0) to a more heterogeneous (urban,
      suburban, and rural population) via NYS Stroke Centers through a partnership with the New
      York State Department of Health (NYSDOH) Stroke Designation Program. This digital program is
      a second part to an original Hip Hop Stroke program where study showed effectiveness at
      communicating stroke awareness. In this study, the investigator proposes to intervene in
      school classrooms with the Hip Hop Stroke 2.0 (HHS2.0) digital program, geared towards
      children aged 9 to 11 years.

      Primary Aims:

      Aim 1: To identify contextual factors, such as barriers and facilitators, that influence
      uptake of the HHS program in a new, heterogeneous sample at the Stroke Center and local
      school levels.

      Hypothesis 1: Contextual factors at the Stroke Center and local school levels will lead to
      differential uptake of HHS.

      Aim 2: To determine whether Stroke Center implementation of the HHS program leads to
      increased stroke literacy of local students by cross-validating outcomes with the results of
      our Randomized Clinical Trial.

      Hypothesis 2: Stroke Center implementation will lead to increased stroke literacy of local
      students.

      Secondary Aims:

      Aim 3: To assess the determinants of high performance implementation and effectiveness under
      real world practice conditions.

      Aim 4: To evaluate the costs associated with HHS program implementation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite effective Acute Stroke Treatment, fewer than 10% of patients in the United States
      receive them. The largest barrier to this treatment are pre-hospital delays which include
      limited to no, knowledge of stroke signs and symptoms and the intent seek care. While there
      is abundance of stroke education materials available, studies continue to reveal severe
      deficiencies in stroke literacy (knowledge of symptoms, urgent action, and prevention
      measures).

      A mere 7% of ischemic stroke events in the US receive thrombolysis (t-PA) therapy1 due to
      delayed hospital arrival, most often related to the failure to recognize stroke symptoms and
      to call 911 immediately. Efforts to improve the public's stroke literacy have been driven by
      mass media stroke education campaigns that include public service announcements and print
      advertising. However, these efforts have failed to have an effect on 911 use (the major
      determinant of early hospital arrival) beyond the funding period for the specific media
      campaign. Stroke Centers may represent more sustainable channels for public stroke education
      initiatives promoting the use of ambulance services.

      State Departments of Health and the Joint Commission regulate Stroke Center hospitals through
      an accreditation process that requires the fulfillment of certain stroke care measures.
      Notably, one of these regulatory requirements is community stroke education by the hospital;
      however, these are underdeveloped, and lack guidelines and evaluation metrics. Consequently,
      stroke education efforts by Stroke Centers are often poorly delivered and do not use
      evidence-based approaches.

      The program helps schools fulfill NYS health education requirements through its primordial
      prevention modules. Children are also taught to teach stroke information to their
      parents/caregivers. HHS2.0 has shown to be effective in the real world setting through
      several studies, including an Randomized Clinical Trial (RCT) involving more than 3,000
      predominantly Black and Hispanic urban school children aged 9-11 years. These studies found
      that children can and will: (1) learn how to recognize stroke, including self-efficacy for
      calling 911 when they witness stroke, and retain this knowledge for at least 15 months, (2)
      communicate stroke literacy successfully to their parents and grandparents who retain this
      knowledge for at least 3 months, and (3) actually call 911 when they witness stroke symptoms
      occurring in their homes or community.

      This project is an outgrowth of our previously funded RCT (R01NS067443), in which we
      developed and established the effectiveness of a novel intervention to teach economically
      challenged minority residents of New York City to recognize stroke symptoms and know the
      correct response - call 911 (stroke literacy).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 17, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Stroke Centers who agree to participate will designate a Stroke coordinator who will recruit at least 2 schools from their area with 4th and/or 5th grades. Coordinators will receive a customizable electronic training package to introduce content, and recruit strategies to engage schools. They will in turn coordinate with School Champions (school designated member), who will receive program training, to implement the program. School Champion will be responsible for the distribution of Opt-Out consent forms, scheduling programming (including computer use), and coordinating with the Stroke Champion and research staff. Regarding maintenance, Stroke Coordinators and School Champions will complete and exit survey, and to promote annual implementation in recruited schools.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Stroke Literacy Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at least 3 days from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Investigator will assess stroke literacy among 4th and 5th grade students with the validated Stroke Literacy Action Measure using a pre-post- test design. Literacy will be determined by percentage of questions answered correctly. The greater percentage correct indicates a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average number of barriers influencing program uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at least 1 year from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Investigator will find the average rate of factors influencing program update through the use of the Consolidated Framework for Implementation (CFIR). The CFIR will be measured by the Reach, Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation, and Maintenance (RE-AIM) framework to evaluate these averages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average number of facilitators influencing program uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at least 1 year from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Investigator will find the average rate of factors influencing program update through the use of the Consolidated Framework for Implementation (CFIR). The CFIR will be measured by the Reach, Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation, and Maintenance (RE-AIM) framework to evaluate these averages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average number of determinants yielding high performance implementation and effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from Aim 1 and Aim 2, the Investigator will analyze contextual data from each Stroke Center in relation to the data generated from RE-AIM variables. The Investigator will assess the average number of factors/elements influencing the adoption, implementation, and maintenance of the intervention at the Stroke Center and the local school level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average total cost associated with program implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Investigator will conduct cost analyses from two complementary perspectives: 1) implementing agencies (primary cost analysis) and 2) society as a whole (secondary cost analysis). The Investigator will first estimate costs, and variations therein, based on the experience of participating Stroke Centers and schools (implementing agencies). The Investigator will develop estimates of the total cost of the HHS program, its key components and activities, and costs per participant using the resource cost method and look at the average totals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4700</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hip Hop Stroke 2.0 intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students in 4th and 5th grade will receive the intervention, Hip Hop Stroke 2.0, disseminated and implemented by local Stroke Centers - uses a framework of Child-Mediated Health Communication to make children &quot;stroke literate&quot; and then empower these stroke literate students with the tools required to successfully communicate actionable stroke knowledge (recognition of stroke symptoms and the urgency of calling 911) to their parents and grandparents at home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hip Hop Stroke 2.0</intervention_name>
    <description>HHS2.0 is an innovative, multimedia program, a brief 3-hour (1hr/day for 3 days), school-based intervention designed to educate at-risk populations concerning stroke symptoms and calling 911 immediately in the event they occur (stroke literacy). HHS2.0 is accessed and delivered via a web link online as self-administered, interactive modules that target 4th and 5th grade children in the school system (ages 9-11) using narrative cartoons and multimedia games.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hip Hop Stroke 2.0 intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HHS2.0</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Schools located in the 47 hospital (stroke center) geographic catchment areas

          -  Schools with 4th and/or 5th grade classes and have ascertained the following: student
             bodies have at least 50 students in each of these grades, diverse socio-demographic
             NYS communities, and computer resources / internet access required for the
             implementation of the HHS program.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Special education school with a student body comprised of those with learning
             disabilities.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olajide Williams, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luisa G Gomez, MA</last_name>
    <phone>212-342-3668</phone>
    <email>Lg2033@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Janhavi Mallaiah, MBBS, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>212-342-0715</phone>
    <email>jm4498@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luisa G Chan, MA</last_name>
      <phone>212-342-3668</phone>
      <email>Lg2063@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janhavi Mallaiah, MBBS, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>212-342-0715</phone>
      <email>jm4498@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olajide A Williams, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Olajide Williams</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Education</keyword>
  <keyword>Hip Hop Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Community</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Schools</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke Centers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

