<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03842319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIBER-MEDIMACS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03842319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of MEditerranean Diet, Inflammation and Microbiome After an Acute Coronary Syndrome</brief_title>
  <acronym>MEDIMACS</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of MEditerranean Diet, Inflammation and Microbiome on Plaque Vulnerability and Microvascular Dysfunction After an Acute Coronary Syndrome. A Randomized, Controlled, Mechanistic Clinical Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Consorcio Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red, M.P.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundación para el Fomento de la Investigación Sanitaria y Biomédica de la Comunitat Valenciana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Navarra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tel Aviv University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Göteborg University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Consorcio Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red, M.P.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the MEDIMACS project, the investigators will use a randomized clinical-trial design to
      address the effects of mediterranean diet on atherosclerotic plaque vulnerability and
      coronary endothelial function in order to decipher complex interplays between diet,
      microbiome, immunological and metabolic responses and coronary atherosclerosis. The
      investigators will focus on patients after an episode of acute coronary syndrome and use
      state-of-the-art techniques to address atherosclerotic plaque composition and coronary
      endothelial function. A number of different -omic approaches will be used to address effector
      pathways. The insights provided by this study will allow identifying potential new dietary,
      microbiota and/or metabolic targets for the treatment of atherosclerosis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Coronary atherosclerosis is a leading cause of mortality and disability worldwide. Continuous
      efforts are needed to improve secondary prevention and understand the mechanism underlying
      disease progression. Based on primary prevention trials, a potential benefit of the
      Mediterranean diet after an acute coronary syndrome can be anticipated. The integrated
      microbiome-mediated/ immunologic and metabolic pathways by which the Mediterranean diet
      modifies cardiovascular risk remain mostly unknown. Intestinal and oral dysbiosis is involved
      in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis and microbiome dynamics may account for some of the
      observed benefits of Mediterranean diet. The first objective of the trial is to evaluate the
      effects of a well-controlled Mediterranean diet intervention on atherosclerotic plaque
      vulnerability and coronary endothelial dysfunction after an episode of acute coronary
      syndrome. The second objective is to decipher the interplays among diet, microbiota, immunity
      and metabolism responsible for the observed effects. The investigators propose a randomized
      mechanistic clinical trial, using state-of-the-art efficacy read-outs. The multidisciplinary
      consortium includes highly experienced cardiologists, nutritionists and experts in
      translational research in immunology, microbiomics, genomics, proteomics, metabolomics and
      metagenomics. This study will provide valuable insights to identify potential microbiome
      therapeutic targets for coronary artery disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Intervention Group: High intensity Mediterranean diet in secondary prevention after acute coronary syndrome. Control Group: recommendation of a standard of care, standard Mediterranean diet. Duration of the intervention per participant: 12 months. Follow-up period per participant: 12 months.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Non-intervention or MedDiet intensive intervention group assignment will be made through an automated system. Each patient will be assigned a patient identification number that should appear on all eCRF pages (electronic &quot;case report&quot;), source documents and laboratory data. All researchers involved in the measurement of data, analysis and allocation of results will be blind. The MedDiet intensive intervention will be blind to the evaluation of the endpoints (the research team in charge of the measurement, analysis and awarding of the results will be blind). The samples will be coded and anonymously analyzed by each research team</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fibrous cap thickness change</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the thickness of the fibrous layer of the atheroma plaque in the non-culprit vessel measured by optical coherence tomography at 12 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endothelial dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Vascular endothelial function measured using a Doppler pressure guidewire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intestinal microbiota composition changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline in intestinal microbiota will be analysed using the 16S rRNA target gene sequencing approach at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral microbiota composition changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline in oral microbiota will be analysed using the 16S rRNA target gene sequencing approach at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adaptive immune system status changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of adaptive immune cell lineages will be assessed dynamically using high performance cytometry at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Innate immune system status changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of innate immune cell lineages will be assessed dynamically using high performance cytometry at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood protein profiling changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of host protein-profiles from collected plasma samples will be analyzed for detection of biomarkers at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Faecal protein profiling changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of host protein-profiles from collected faces samples will be analyzed for detection of biomarkers at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine metabolome profiling changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of host metabolome profiles in urine will be analyzed using mass-spectrometry-based at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood metabolome profiling changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of host metabolome profiles in blood will be analyzed using mass-spectrometry-based at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Faecal metabolome profiling changes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline of metabolome profiles in faecal samples will be analyzed using mass-spectrometry-based at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In patients allocated to the control group, the currently used Spanish Mediterranean diet will be recommended as part of a standard high-quality secondary prevention program, where the patient is invited to participate in a single 45 minute nutritional educational group session. Interventions: Microbiota analysis, Immunological analysis, Proteome analysis, Metabolome analysis, Clinical evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients allocated to the interventional group will be individually evaluated by a dietitian and will participate in dedicated individual and group sessions at baseline, and at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months. In the interventional group, a personalized MedDiet will assess chemical and nutritional composition and total energy intake will be adapted to participant's weight, age, and requirements, and the dietitian's tailored advice to his/her individual needs. A 14-item dietary screen for adherence to the Mediterranean diet will be used to personalize the intervention and negotiate dietary changes. Furthermore, free virgin olive oil, recipes, shopping list and designed weekly menus will be provided to maximize the differences between groups. Interventions: MedDiet, Microbiota analysis, Immunological analysis, Proteome analysis, Metabolome analysis, Clinical evaluation, Diet evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microbiota analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>From the feces and oral cavity samples, the DNA of the microbiota will be extracted using specific extraction kits and the microbiome will be analyzed through the study of 16S ribosomal RNA amplicons.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immunological analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>A study of immunological cell populations, inmunogenetics and cytokines will be carried out from fresh blood samples using antibody panels and flow cytometry</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Proteome analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>A study of host and microbiota proteome will be carried out from samples using mass spectrometry</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metabolome analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>A study of host and microbiota metabolome will be carried out from samples using MS-based as well as NMR-based methods</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinical evaluation including hemostasis and biochemical studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>Biochemical analysis and questionaries for diet adherence and exercise registration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MedDiet</intervention_name>
    <description>The high-intensity Mediterranean diet will include the promotion of the following: a) abundant use of olive oil (&gt;40 g/d) for cooking and dressing dishes; b) consumption of &gt;2 daily servings of vegetables; c) &gt;2-3 daily serving of fresh fruits; d) &gt;3 weekly servings of legumes; e) &gt;3 weekly servings of fish or seafood; f) &gt;1 weekly serving of nuts or seeds; g) select white meats instead of red meats or processed meats; and h) cook regularly with tomato, garlic and onion adding or no other aromatic herbs, and dress vegetables, pasta, rice and other dishes with tomato, garlic and onion adding or no other aromatic herbs. Two main meals per day should be eaten (seated at a table, lasting more than 20 minutes). A recommendation to drink a glass of wine per day during meals is given. Limited consumption is advised for cured ham, red meat, chocolate, cured or fatty cheeses</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity MedDiet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients undergoing cardiac catheterization for an acute coronary syndrome.

          -  At least 1 non-causal lesion in a coronary segment with a stenosis diameter between
             40-70% that will not be submitted to intervention during the revascularization
             procedure.

          -  Disposition and possibility to modify the diet.

          -  With the ability to track and answer questionnaires.

          -  Signature of informed consent for the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  TIMI score &lt;3 in the injury

          -  Reference lesion with diameter &lt;2.0 mm

          -  LV ejection fraction (EF) less than 45%.

          -  Active systemic infection

          -  Active periodontal disease

          -  Chronic inflammatory disease

          -  Active treatment with corticosteroids or immunomodulators

          -  Renal insufficiency with glomerular filtration less than 30 mL / min

          -  Severe hepatic insufficiency (liver cirrhosis in Child B or C stages).

          -  Comorbidity with life expectancy of less than one year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francisco Fernández-Avilés, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CIBER, HGUGM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Javier Bermejo, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+3491 586 8279</phone>
    <email>javier.bermejo@salud.madrid.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Javier Bermejo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>91 586 8279</phone>
      <email>javier.bermejo@salud.madrid.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Mediterranean diet</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>immune system</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolome</keyword>
  <keyword>proteome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Consortium Partners involved in data creation and analysis agrees to follow the FAIR data management principles of Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability and Reusability. The Project Management Committee will decide what type and format of data to be stored in the collective database and what type and format of data will be available publicly (as an open-access to research data), as well as how data will be curated and preserved after the end of the project. Sequences, genotypes and protein and immune profiles would be organized and indexed in metadata files following a unique code of assignment that will be submitted for releasing to public database repositories such as GenBank, Gene Expression Omnibus and ClinicalTrials. The International Standards for Genomes and Metagenomes will be followed</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

