<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03842865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CL-PTL-132</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03842865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Expanded Access of Vigil in Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Expanded Access Trial of Vigil (Bi-shRNAfurin and GMCSF Augmented Autologous Tumor Cell Immunotherapy) in Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gradalis, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gradalis, Inc.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, expanded access protocol of intradermal autologous Vigil
      immunotherapy. Subjects meeting expanded access eligibility criteria will receive a minimum
      of 1 immunotherapy dose of Vigil (1 x 10e4, 1 x 10e5, or 1 x 10e6 cells/injection),
      intradermally every 4 weeks as monotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 40 subjects who had tissue procured and Vigil manufactured but fail
      manufacturing release criteria under a previous Gradalis protocol are considered for this
      study.

      Participants will be managed in an outpatient setting. Hematologic function, liver enzymes,
      renal function and electrolytes will be monitored. Blood for immune function analyses in
      response to autologous tumor antigens will be collected at screening, Day 1 (prior to Vigil
      administration) at Cycles 2, 4, and 6, end of treatment (EOT); 3 months after EOT, and every
      6 months thereafter for those in response follow up. For subjects with Ewing's sarcoma, blood
      for ctDNA analysis will be collected at screening, on Day 1 prior to Vigil administration at
      Cycles 2, 3, 4, and 6, and EOT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Temporarily not available</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <expanded_access_info>
    <expanded_access_type_intermediate>Yes</expanded_access_type_intermediate>
  </expanded_access_info>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Ewing Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Ewing's Tumor Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Ewing's Sarcoma Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Gynecological Cancers</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Uterine Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vigil</intervention_name>
    <description>Vigil is composed of autologous tumor cells harvested from the patient at the time of initial de-bulking surgery which are then transfected extracorporeally, with a plasmid encoding for the gene for GM-CSF, an immune-stimulatory cytokine, and a bifunctional, short hairpin RNA which specifically knocks down the expression of furin, the critical convertase responsible for production of the two TGβ isoforms (TGFβ-1 and TGFβ-2).</description>
    <other_name>Engineered Autologous Tumor Cell Immunotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>FANG</other_name>
    <other_name>IND 14205</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Study Enrollment Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed advanced or metastatic non-curable solid tumor.

          2. Completed manufacture of at least 1 vial of Vigil, but failure of one or more
             manufacturing release criteria.

          3. ECOG performance status (PS) 0-1 or Karnofsky performance status (KPS) / Lansky
             performance status (LS)≥ 70%.

          4. Normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

             Absolute granulocyte count ≥1,000/mm3, Absolute lymphocyte count ≥400/mm3, Platelets
             ≥75,000/mm3, Hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 mg/dL, Total bilirubin ≤ institutional upper limit of
             normal*, AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤2x institutional upper limit of normal, Creatinine &lt;1.5
             mg/dL

             *documented Gilbert's syndrome may be considered after medical monitor review

          5. No systemic therapy, immunologic therapy or investigational therapy within 2 weeks and
             no radiation therapy within 1 week prior to enrollment.

          6. Subject has recovered to CTCAE Grade 1 (except for parameters noted in Item 4, above)
             or better from all adverse events associated with prior therapy or surgery.
             Pre-existing motor, sensory neurologic pathology or symptoms, or dermatologic
             toxicities must be recovered to CTCAE Grade 2 or better.

          7. If female of childbearing potential, has a negative urine or serum pregnancy test. If
             the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a negative serum test
             will be required for study entry.

          8. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed protocol specific
             consent or a parental/guardian informed consent and pediatric assent when appropriate.

        Study Enrollment Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Medical condition requiring any form of chronic systemic immunosuppressive therapy
             (steroid or other) except physiologic replacement doses of hydrocortisone or
             equivalent (no more than 30 mg hydrocortisone or 10 mg prednisone equivalent daily)
             for &lt; 30 days duration.

          2. Known history of other malignancy unless having undergone curative intent therapy
             without evidence of that disease for ≥ 3 years except cutaneous squamous cell and
             basal cell skin cancer, superficial bladder cancer, in situ cervical cancer or other
             in situ cancers are allowed if definitively resected.

          3. Receipt of greater than 2 lines of systemic treatment between Vigil manufacture and
             screening for this protocol.

          4. Live vaccine used for the prevention of infectious disease administered &lt; 30 days
             prior to the start of study therapy.

          5. Post-surgery complication that in the opinion of the treating investigator would
             interfere with the subject's study participation or make it not in the best interest
             of the patient to participate.

          6. Brain metastases unless treated with curative intent (gamma knife or surgical
             resection) and without evidence of progression for ≥ 2 months.

          7. Any documented history of autoimmune disease with exception of Type 1 diabetes on
             stable insulin regimen, hypothyroidism on stable dose of replacement thyroid
             medication, vitiligo, or asthma not requiring systemic steroids.

          8. Known HIV or chronic Hepatitis B or C infection.

          9. Known history of allergies or sensitivities to gentamicin.

         10. History of or current evidence of any condition (including medical, psychiatric or
             substance abuse disorder), therapy, or laboratory abnormality that might confound the
             results of the study, interfere with the patient's participation for the full duration
             of the study, or is not in the best interest of the patient to participate, in the
             opinion of the treating Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luisa Manning, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Gradalis, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Oncology - Pediatrics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghisoli M, Rutledge M, Stephens PJ, Mennel R, Barve M, Manley M, Oliai BR, Murphy KM, Manning L, Gutierrez B, Rangadass P, Walker A, Wang Z, Rao D, Adams N, Wallraven G, Senzer N, Nemunaitis J. Case Report: Immune-mediated Complete Response in a Patient With Recurrent Advanced Ewing Sarcoma (EWS) After Vigil Immunotherapy. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2017 May;39(4):e183-e186. doi: 10.1097/MPH.0000000000000822.</citation>
    <PMID>28338569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oh J, Barve M, Matthews CM, Koon EC, Heffernan TP, Fine B, Grosen E, Bergman MK, Fleming EL, DeMars LR, West L, Spitz DL, Goodman H, Hancock KC, Wallraven G, Kumar P, Bognar E, Manning L, Pappen BO, Adams N, Senzer N, Nemunaitis J. Phase II study of Vigil® DNA engineered immunotherapy as maintenance in advanced stage ovarian cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2016 Dec;143(3):504-510. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2016.09.018. Epub 2016 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27678295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Senzer N, Barve M, Kuhn J, Melnyk A, Beitsch P, Lazar M, Lifshitz S, Magee M, Oh J, Mill SW, Bedell C, Higgs C, Kumar P, Yu Y, Norvell F, Phalon C, Taquet N, Rao DD, Wang Z, Jay CM, Pappen BO, Wallraven G, Brunicardi FC, Shanahan DM, Maples PB, Nemunaitis J. Phase I trial of &quot;bi-shRNAi(furin)/GMCSF DNA/autologous tumor cell&quot; vaccine (FANG) in advanced cancer. Mol Ther. 2012 Mar;20(3):679-86. doi: 10.1038/mt.2011.269. Epub 2011 Dec 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22186789</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ghisoli M, Barve M, Mennel R, Lenarsky C, Horvath S, Wallraven G, Pappen BO, Whiting S, Rao D, Senzer N, Nemunaitis J. Three-year Follow up of GMCSF/bi-shRNA(furin) DNA-transfected Autologous Tumor Immunotherapy (Vigil) in Metastatic Advanced Ewing's Sarcoma. Mol Ther. 2016 Aug;24(8):1478-83. doi: 10.1038/mt.2016.86. Epub 2016 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27109631</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ghisoli M, Barve M, Schneider R, Mennel R, Lenarsky C, Wallraven G, Pappen BO, LaNoue J, Kumar P, Nemunaitis D, Roth A, Nemunaitis J, Whiting S, Senzer N, Fletcher FA, Nemunaitis J. Pilot Trial of FANG Immunotherapy in Ewing's Sarcoma. Mol Ther. 2015 Jun;23(6):1103-1109. doi: 10.1038/mt.2015.43. Epub 2015 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25917459</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Ewing</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

