<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03842722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL64824.058.18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03842722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Insufficient Oxygenation in Septic Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>INOX-SEPSIS</acronym>
  <official_title>Insufficient Oxygenation in Septic Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanquin-LUMC J.J van Rood Center for Clinical Transfusion Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanquin-LUMC J.J van Rood Center for Clinical Transfusion Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will describe the change of mitochondrial oxygen tension (mitoPO2) compared to
      traditional parameters of oxygenation and oxygen balance in the first 24 hours of septic
      patients admitted to the intensive care unit of an academic hospital. The mitoPO2 will be
      measured on prespecified measurement moments in the ICU. With each measurement moment,
      arterial and central venous blood gasses will be taken too.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Evidence is increasing that there is no clear parameter for tissue oxygenation in critically
      ill septic patients to guide resuscitation. New studies have shown the potential of
      protoporphyrin IX-triple state lifetime technique to measure mitochondrial oxygenation
      tension (mitoPO2) in vivo, which possibly is an early indicator of oxygen disbalance in the
      cell and therefore a physiological trigger for fluid therapy.

      Objectives: 1. To describe mitoPO2 measurements in patients with sepsis who are about to
      receive fluid therapy 2. To describe the effects of fluid therapy and the associated change
      in mitoPO2 and change in other physiologic measures of tissue oxygenation and oxygen balance
      3.To describe the association between mitoPO2 and vital organ (dis)functions and change of
      SOFA (Sequential organ failure assessment) score after 24hrs 5. To describe the
      microcirculatory, cellular and mitochondrial function during the first 24 hours of septic
      patients.

      Study population: critically ill patients with sepsis which are admitted to the intensive
      care unit through the emergency department or hospital ward and in whom fluid therapy
      (crystalloid, albumin and red cell transfusion) is planned.

      Main study endpoints

      Primary endpoint: Change in mitoPO2 after fluid therapy. This will be compared to traditional
      parameters used to measure oxygenation and oxygen balance

      Secondary endpoints:

        -  Association of mitoPO2 trend with separate (ischemic) organ (dis)function. The SOFA
           score after 24 hours will also be assessed.

        -  Safety of mitoPO2 measurements in critically ill septic patients.

        -  Description of the association of sepsis with microcirculatory function, cellular
           function and mitochondrial function.

        -  Description of the association between mitoPO2 change and clinical outcomes , like
           length of stay(both ICU and in-hospital) and mortality (both ICU and in-hospital).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of mitoPO2 during first 24 hours of a septic patient</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the change of mitoPO2(mitochondrial oxygenation) before and after fluid therapy in patients with sepsis. This will be compared to traditional parameters used to measure tissue oxygenation and oxygen balance (central venous oxygen saturation, mean arterial pressure and lactate).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SOFA (sequential organ failure assessment) score after 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The association of mitoPO2 change in 24 hours with the Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score after 24 hours will be assessed. With the help of this information, more insight can be given in how much information the cutaneous mitoPO2 measurement gives about the organs separately and together.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ (dis)function</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the association between mitoPO2 change and separate organ functions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of mitoPO2 measurement with blood based biomarkers of cellular function</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Cellular function will be assessed with blood-based biomarkers mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP), presence of cellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) molecules and glutathione (GSH) activity. Mitochondrial function will be assessed with mitoPO2 measurements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety (incidence of adverse and serious adverse events)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The adverse and serious adverse events of the mitoPO2 measurements will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of ICU stay</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Association of mitoPO2 change and length of intensive care unit-stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Association of mitoPO2 change and length of hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Association of mitoPO2 change and intensive care unit mortality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Association of mitoPO2 change and in-hospital mortality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Sepsis</condition>
  <condition>Critical Care</condition>
  <condition>Mitochondria</condition>
  <condition>Oxygen</condition>
  <condition>Fluid Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Critically ill septic patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cohort: patients admitted via the emergency department or hospital ward to the intensive care unit of Leiden University Medical Center with the diagnosis sepsis or septic shock, who receive fluid therapy (either colloid, crystalloid and/or red blood cell) in their first day of admission to the ICU.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protoporphyrin IX - Triplet State Lifetime Technique</intervention_name>
    <description>Protoporphyrin IX - Triplet State Lifetime Technique is a way to measure mitochondrial oxygen tension in a non-invasive way at bedside.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Critically ill septic patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples will be taken for measurement of: creatinine, hemoglobin, lactate, central
      venous oxygen saturation, arterial saturation, arterial oxygen tension, venous oxygen
      tension, central venous-to-arterial carbon dioxide partial pressure difference. Furthermore,
      blood based cellular function will be assessed (presence of reactive oxygen species
      molecules, mitochondrial membrane potential and glutathione activity).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients in the emergency department or hospital ward admitted to the Intensive Care Unit
        of the Leiden University Medical Center with (the suspicion of) sepsis will be the source
        population of the study. Leiden Univesity Medical Center is an academic hospital.

        Septic patients are identified as specified in the Dutch protocol of sepsis identification
        and management in the emergency department. It consists of having clinical suspicion of
        sepsis in combination with the at least 2 of the following symptoms: ≥ 20 breaths per
        minute, heart frequency &gt; 90 beats per minute, leukocytes &gt; 12x109 or leukocytes &lt; 4x10^9,
        and/or temperature &gt; 38 °C or &lt;36 °C
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age of patient is at least 18 years

          -  Patients diagnosed with sepsis in the emergency department or hospital ward

          -  Patients are admitted to the ICU via the hospital ward or emergency department

          -  Informed consent is given either by the patient or if the patient is too ill to give
             informed consent, by his or her legal representative.

          -  Patients have an arterial catheter in situ, since blood samples will be taken for the
             study. Most patients admitted to the ICU have an arterial catheter in place since it
             is part of standard care.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients younger than 18 years

          -  Patients with sepsis discharged after emergency department visit

          -  Patients admitted to a hospital ward other than the ICU after emergency department
             visit

          -  Patients who cannot give informed consent themselves and without a legal
             representative will be excluded since no informed consent can be obtained

          -  Patients known with porphyria and/or photodermatosis will be excluded, since the risk
             of phototoxicity

          -  Patients with hypersensitivity to the active substance or to the plaster material of
             ALA (5-aminolevulinic acid)

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding women since there is no adequate data form the use of ALA
             in pregnant or breast feeding women

          -  Insufficient comprehensibility of the Dutch language
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johanna G van der Bom, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Leiden University Medical Center and Sanquin Research Leiden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>M S Arbous, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Leiden University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meryem Baysan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+31715297274</phone>
    <email>m.baysan@lumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Johanna G van der Bom, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31715268871</phone>
    <email>J.G.van_der_Bom@lumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <zip>2333 ZA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meryem Baysan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+31715297274</phone>
      <email>m.baysan@lumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Protoporphyrin IX</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

