<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03844009</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RNN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03844009</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Computer Debriefing and Screen-based Simulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Computer Debriefing During Screen-based Simulation of Neonatal Resuscitation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ilumens</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ilumens</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Debriefing after simulation plays a crucial role in student learning and medical practice.
      This paper focuses on impact of computer debriefing technique on knowledge retention of
      midwives during screen-based simulation of neonatal resuscitation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Simulation, including screen-based simulation, is employed in medicine to enhance competency
      and improve care. It has been practiced for centuries in its primitive form as uses of wax
      Venus or obstetrics dolls to teaching anatomical knowledge or know-how/gestures. Many
      benefits come from simulations as the capacity to practiced procedures without any risk to
      the patient, the possibility of trainees to commit errors and learn from these errors, the
      repeatability of scenario that can be different or presented to learners many times, and then
      the opportunity to improved technical and non-technical skills among learners. Specifically,
      screen-based simulation has many advantages as portability (easy to move), distribution and
      replicability (usable by many learners at differences places in the world), repeatability
      (people not faced frequently in their regular practice), even be remotely usable.
      Screen-based simulation appears in literature to be a complement of mannequin simulation.
      Indeed, since last years the development of computer science has made it possible to create
      new kind of simulators in the medical field for the acquisition of knowledge, know-how and
      technical gestures, more realistic and interactively rich.

      Debriefing is considered as a part of simulation-based training and cannot be separated of
      simulators. Debriefing improve professional practice, clinical skills and competences. It
      exists different debriefing methods: post simulation debriefing, in-simulation debriefing,
      verbal instructor debriefing, video-assisted instructor debriefing, self-debriefing or also
      multimedia debriefing. However, debriefing is considered by many as a communication between
      student/learner and teacher, after a situation (e.g. simulation), and about this experience.
      It is not just a feedback on performance but also a communication process about the impact of
      the experience or performance explanation.

      This study aims to evaluate the impact of a computer integrated debriefing of technical and
      non-technical skills on retention and performance of neonatal resuscitation management by
      trainee's midwives.

      Thirty student in midwifery in fourth year will participate. The study protocol is the
      following:

      Baseline knowledge questionnaire, randomization of the participants. Day one: Tutorial of the
      simulator, First scenario (+/- debriefing depending of the allocation group), second scenario
      (+/- debriefing depending of the allocation group).

      Day two (two month later): knowledge questionnaire, tutorial of the simulator, one scenario
      (+/- debriefing depending of the allocation group).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 7, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized controlled study comparing two groups, one intervention group (debriefing) and one control group (no debriefing)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The outcomes assessor (questionnaire) was blinded of the allocation group of the participant.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>knowledge retention</measure>
    <time_frame>two months</time_frame>
    <description>Knowledge assesment based on a validated questionnaire created from International Liaison Committee On Resuscitation guidelines at T0 (before simulation), T1 (after the first simulation session) and T2 (after the second simulation session, two month later)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-technical skills assesment</measure>
    <time_frame>two months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the Anesthetist Non technical skills score at T1 (first session) and T2 (second session, two month later)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical skills assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>two months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the Modified Neonatal Resuscitation Program Evaluation score at T1 (first session) and T2 (second session, two month later)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Computer Simulation</condition>
  <condition>Neonatal Resuscitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Debriefing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant's of the debriefing group had a computer integrated debriefing at the end of each scenario of the computer-based simulator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No debriefing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant's of the debriefing group had no computer integrated debriefing at the end of each scenario of the computer-based simulator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computer integrated debriefing</intervention_name>
    <description>At the end of each computer-based simulation, the participant had a computer integrated debriefing of his performance during the neonatal resuscitation simulation and a debriefing based on an auto-evaluation of his non-technical skills.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Debriefing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Student in midwifery in fourth year in france (penultimate year of the midwifery
             studies)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antoine Tesnière, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ilumens</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ilumens, Paris Descartes University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75006</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daphné Michelet, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33617861084</phone>
      <email>daphnemichelet@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Heide PA, van Toledo-Eppinga L, van der Heide M, van der Lee JH. Assessment of neonatal resuscitation skills: a reliable and valid scoring system. Resuscitation. 2006 Nov;71(2):212-21. Epub 2006 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16987590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donoghue A, Nishisaki A, Sutton R, Hales R, Boulet J. Reliability and validity of a scoring instrument for clinical performance during Pediatric Advanced Life Support simulation scenarios. Resuscitation. 2010 Mar;81(3):331-6. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2009.11.011. Epub 2010 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>20047787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ilumens</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daphne Michelet</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

