<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03643666</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N-9-2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03643666</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intraperitoneal Dexamethasone vs Dexamethasone Plus Magnesium Sulphate for Pain Relief in Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intraperitoneal Dexamethasone vs Dexamethasone Plus Magnesium Sulphate for Pain Relief in Laparoscopic cholecystectomY</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Laparoscopic cholecystectomy has become a standard technique for gall bladder surgery.
      Benefits in comparison to conventional laparotomy are shorter lived effects on pulmonary
      function and less postoperative pain . However, patients often suffer from considerable pain
      during the first 24 postoperative hours. Pain can prolong hospital stay and lead to increased
      morbidity, which is particularly important now that many centers are performing this
      operation as a day-case procedure. Administration of intraperitoneal local anesthetic, either
      during or after surgery, is used by as a method of reducing postoperative pain. Although a
      number of studies have reported a significant reduction in postoperative pain after the use
      of intraperitoneal analgesia, others have reported no benefit. Several investigations have
      been conducted in order to find the cause of this pain. According to some of these
      investigations, the pain is attributed to peritoneal inflammation due to carbon dioxide
      pneumoperitoneum. Since steroids have been used for reducing inflammation, they may be
      considered as alternatives for relieving pain. Dexamethasone is a strong long acting
      glucocorticoid and it is widely used after surgery. it has been established that steroids are
      effective in relieving postoperative pain in laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Also,
      administration of magnesium sulphate has been shown to have a potential to prevent
      postoperative pain and to reduce intra operative anesthetic and analgesic requirements being
      an antagonist of N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors and its associated ion channels. Some
      studies showed reduction of pain scores if magnesium sulphate was injected intra-articular
      and intraperitoneal with no serious adverse effects. In this study the investigators will use
      intraperitoneal dexamethasone vs dexamethasone plus magnesium sulphate to study their
      analgesic efficacy after laparoscopic cholecystectomy as the investigators assume that the
      combination of both drugs will provide stronger analgesia than dexamethasone alone
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 27, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative pain: VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>first 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative pain scoring using standard Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) pain score of 0-10 (with 0 meaning no pain and 10 meaning the most intense pain ever experienced)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative nausea and vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>first 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative nausea and vomiting using simplified simplified postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) impact scale which is measured through two questions as following:
Q1. Has the patient vomited or had dry-retching? 0. No
Once
Twice
Three or more times Q2. Has the patient experienced a feeling of nausea (an unsettled feeling in the stomach and slight urge to vomit)? If yes, has the feeling of nausea interfered with activities of daily life, such as being able to get out of bed, being able to move about freely in bed, being able to walk normally, or eating and drinking?
0. Not at all
Sometimes
Often or most of the time
All of the time. To calculate the PONV Impact Scale, the numerical responses to questions 1 and 2 will be added. Several vomits or dry-retching events occurring over a short time frame e.g 5 min, will be counted as one vomiting/dry-retching episode.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>first 24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>arterial blood pressure measurement postoperative</measure>
    <time_frame>first 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>systolic and diastolic blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>doses of consumed postoperative analgesics</measure>
    <time_frame>first 24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>this group will include 25 patients receiving intraperitoneal 40 ml of normal saline only at the end of laparoscopic cholecystectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dexamethasone group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>this group will include 25 patients receiving intraperitoneal 16 mg dexamethasone in 40 ml saline at the end of laparoscopic cholecystectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dexamethasone plus magnesium sulphate group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>this group will include 25 patients receiving intraperitoneal 16 mg dexamethasone plus 2 gm magnesium sulphate at the end of laparoscopic cholecystectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>before closure of the laparoscopic entering sites the patients will receive instillation of 40 ml of normal saline containing 16mg dexamethasone</description>
    <arm_group_label>dexamethasone group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>dexamethasone plus magnesium sulphate group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>magnesium sulphate</intervention_name>
    <description>patients will receive instillation of 40 ml of normal saline containing 16mg dexamethasone plus magnesium sulphate 2 gm into the peritoneum at the end of the operation</description>
    <arm_group_label>dexamethasone plus magnesium sulphate group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo (saline)</intervention_name>
    <description>before closure of the laparoscopic entering sites the patients received instillation of 40 ml normal saline into the peritoneum</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age group and gender: between 18 to 60 years both males and females

          2. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status I-II

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 18 years or &gt; 60 years

          2. ASA physical status III or IV

          3. Patients with diabetes

          4. Patient refusal to participate in the study

          5. Chronic respiratory disease

          6. Advanced renal or hepatic diseases

          7. Use of opioids, tranquilizers or steroids

          8. Confusion or psychiatric illness

          9. Acute cholecystectomy

         10. Patients with peritoneal drain after surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kasr Alaini hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>AbdElKhalik Mahmoud Shaban</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Magnesium Sulfate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

