<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03646760</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HFHS iATTEND</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R33HL143099</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03646760</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Improving ATTENDance to Cardiac Rehabilitation Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>iATTEND</acronym>
  <official_title>The Improving ATTENDance to Cardiac Rehabilitation Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henry Ford Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Henry Ford Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The benefits of cardiac rehabilitation are well known. However, despite center based cardiac
      rehabilitation (CBCR) representing guideline-based care for patients with cardiovascular
      disease, most patients do not complete the maximum number of sessions allowed by third party
      insurance payers. As such, many patients may not be receiving the full clinical benefit
      ascribed to CR. This study will assess the efficacy of an innovative approach to CR delivery
      on attendance by combining both center-based and remote- or home-based CR sessions. The
      intervention group combines center-based CR and remote-/home-based CR and is tailored to the
      individual needs of each patient, accomplished with the assistance of an easy-to-access
      telecommunications methodology (telemedicine)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of CR sessions completed within 6 months will be significantly greater in patients randomized to HYCR vs. patients randomized to traditional CBCR (usual care).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of patients completing 36 CR sessions within 6 months will be significantly greater among patients randomized to the HYCR program vs. patients randomized to the CBCR program.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The improvement in exercise capacity, as measured by distance walked during the six min walk (6MW) test, in patients randomized to HYCR will be equivalent (not inferior) to patients randomized to CBCR.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The improvement in exercise capacity, as measured by peak oxygen uptake (VO2), in patients randomized to HYCR will be equivalent (not inferior) to patients randomized to CBCR.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The improvement in quality of life (QOL), as measured by the Short Form Health Survey-12, in patients randomized to HYCR will be equivalent (not inferior) to patients randomized to CBCR.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>At 6 months after completing CR, explore the effect of a HYCR on exercise capacity as measured by peak oxygen uptake (VO2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>At 6 months after completing CR, explore the effect of a HYCR on quality of life (QOL), as measured by the Short Form Health Survey-12.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">270</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Heart Valve Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Event</condition>
  <condition>Angina Pectoris</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation (HYCR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Center Based cardiac Rehabilitation (CBCR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HYCR</intervention_name>
    <description>This group involves a hybrid design, with the frequency of center based cardiac rehabilitation (CBCR) visits and HYCR visits individualized and modified based on the subject's personal preferences and their family, transportation and work constraints. Patients in HYCR will engage in at least one CBCR visit. Patients will have the video app loaded to their smart phone or tablet (or that of a &quot;willing to assist&quot; family member or friend). HYCR patients receive a chest strap/wrist heart rate device to document HR before, during, and/or after exercise during the TM session. Program education for patients in HYCR will be delivered using the twenty-eight, 7-15 min audio PDF's that are free to access from the Health System's web site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hybrid Cardiac Rehabilitation (HYCR)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CBCR</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will attend 2-3 sessions of cardiac rehabilitation per week at the investigator's Detroit location. Program education for patients in CBCR will be delivered during eight. 1 hour education lectures taught by staff (exercise physiologists and registered dieticians).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Center Based cardiac Rehabilitation (CBCR)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Has agreed to participate in CR and has experienced a cardiac event (myocardial
             infraction, coronary revascularization, heart valve surgery, or cardiac transplant in
             the past 6 months; diagnosed with chronic, stable AHA/ACC stage B or C heart failure
             or Canadian class 0-2 stable angina pectoris)

          2. Lives in or plans to remain in the greater Detroit, MI area for the next year

          3. Age 18-85 years of age

          4. Agrees to attend at least one CBCR session

          5. Agrees to scheduling at least 2, up to 3, CR sessions (either CBCR or HYCR)/wk

          6. Has demonstrated to research staff their ability to access and connect to the internet
             via smart phone or tablet and already has access to satisfactory home- or
             community-based exercise equipment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Received a left ventricular assist device, receiving continuous inotropic support
             (e.g., milrinone), or undergoing hemodialysis

          2. Angina at rest or with a low functional capacity (&lt; 2 METs)

          3. Advanced cancer, advanced risk for falling, limiting cognitive impairment, or other
             advanced disorder that limits participation in CR

               1. Advanced risk for falling will be assessed by 5X sit-to-stand test, with a
                  cut-off score of &gt;15 seconds

               2. Cognitive assessment will be completed using the Mini-Cog instrument, with a
                  cut-off score &lt; 3 used to exclude potential subjects.

          4. Severe arrhythmia unless adequately treated (e.g., implantable cardiac defibrillator)

          5. Pregnant or plan to become pregnant in the next year.

          6. Major cardiovascular procedure or hospitalization planned in the next 6 months

          7. Less than 12 month life expectancy

          8. Participation in another clinical trial that interferes with iATTEND participation,
             follow-up, data collection, exercise capacity or quality of life.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Keteyian, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Henry Ford Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Crystal Grimshaw</last_name>
    <phone>313-972-4037</phone>
    <email>cgrimsh1@hfhs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matt Saval</last_name>
    <phone>313-972-4018</phone>
    <email>msaval1@hfhs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Henry Ford Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven J. Keteyian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angina Pectoris</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Valve Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

