<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03646357</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-000590-75</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03646357</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BEtablocker Treatment After Acute Myocardial Infarction in Patients Without Reduced Left Ventricular Systolic Function</brief_title>
  <acronym>BETAMI</acronym>
  <official_title>BEtablocker Treatment After Acute Myocardial Infarction in Patients Without Reduced Left Ventricular Systolic Function (BETAMI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Drammen sykehus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Hospital of Vestfold</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oslo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Helse Stavanger HF</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Olavs Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital of North Norway</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sorlandet Hospital HF</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Feiringklinikken</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oslo University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to investigate whether oral betablocker (BB) therapy is superior to no such
      treatment following an acute myocardial infarction (AMI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, open blinded end-point (PROBE) study. Patients with AMI
      will be randomized 1-8 days following PCI or thrombolysis, and allocated to either
      prescription of a BB or to no such prescription. Subjects will be followed up for at least 2
      years with respect to the primary and secondary endpoints.

      The primary objective is to test whether oral BB therapy reduces the risk of all-cause death
      or non-fatal MI compared to no such therapy, in patients with AMI treated with PCI or
      thrombolysis without reduced LVEF.

      The key secondary objectives are:

        -  To study whether oral BB therapy reduces the risk of each of the components of the
           primary end-point separately, compared to no such therapy

        -  To study whether oral BB therapy reduces the risk of hospitalization for ventricular
           arrhythmias or heart failure compared to no such therapy

        -  To study whether oral BB therapy reduces the risk of cardiovascular death compared to no
           such therapy

        -  To assess clinical outcomes linked BB therapy including outcomes in treatment subgroups
           (i.e. doses), STEMI vs. NSTEMI, betablocker-naive patients vs. those who are not, LVEF
           subgroups (preserved LVEF: ≥50% vs. mid-range LVEF: 40-49%), drug-related side-effects,
           drug adherence, cardiovascular risk factors, quality of life, anxiety, depression,
           symptom burden (angina, dyspnea), sexual dysfunction and sleep disturbance

        -  To study sociodemographic, clinical, and psychosocial characteristics (PROMS and
           clinical data) between the two study arms and in the total sample

        -  To conduct cost-utility analysis in relation to quality of life and a health economic
           evaluation including drug use, health care utilization, employment, income, and benefit
           take-up

        -  To assess study safety

      Exploratory objectives:

        -  To study the proportion and predictors of non-adherence with BB, statins and other
           cardiovascular drugs assessed by direct methods quantifying drug concentrations in blood

        -  Identify pharmacokinetic, pharmacogenetic and pharmacodynamic markers associated with
           side-effects and suboptimal response to treatment with cardiovascular drugs

      Post-trial objective:

      • To perform a joint analysis of the data from this study with that of the REDUCE study
      (Sweden). This analysis will comprise 17000 patients, giving increased power and precision
      for clinical decisions on both primary and secondary endpoints.

      The primary study end-points will be obtained through linkage to the Norwegian Cardiovascular
      Disease Registry and The Norwegian Population Registry (Folkeregisteret)

      Secondary endpoints will be obtained by linkage to the following national registries: The
      Norwegian Population Registry (Folkeregisteret), the Cause of Death Registry, the Norwegian
      Patient Registry, the Norwegian Cardiovascular Disease Registry, the Norwegian Prescription
      Database, the Norwegian registry for income, the FD-Trygd database (social security micro
      data for research) and the Control and payment of reimbursements to health service providers
      (KUHR) database. Further by collecting self-reported questionnaires and a clinical
      examination with blood sample collection.

      Safety endpoints:

      • Rate of ventricular arrhythmias, heart failure, new MI or all-cause death 30 days after
      randomization and rate of new MI or all-cause death after 6 and 18 months

      Safety endpoints will be under the responsibility of the primary investigators at all
      participating centers and collected by:

        -  30 days: direct telephone contact with the patient and from hospital medical records

        -  At 6 and 18 months:, safety assessments at the study visits in addition to linkage to
           the Norwegian Cardiovascular Disease Registry and The Norwegian Population Registry

        -  Continuous surveillance of serious adverse events (SAEs)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>PROBE - prospective, randomized, open blinded end-point</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to the composite of death of any cause and non-fatal myocardial infarction</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years minimum</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of combined endpoint from randomization. Estimated maximal follow-up for each patient for this outcome is 1-3 years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-fatal MI</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years minimum</time_frame>
    <description>Time to non-fatal MI from randomization. Estimated maximal follow-up for each patient for this outcome is 1-3 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause death</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years minimum</time_frame>
    <description>Time to a-cause Death from randomization. Estimated maximal follow-up for each patient for this outcome is 1-3 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ventricular arrhythmia</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years minimum</time_frame>
    <description>Time to ventricular arrhythmia from randomization. Estimated maximal follow-up for each patient for this outcome is 1-3 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization for heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years minimum</time_frame>
    <description>Time to hospitalization for heart failure from randomization. Estimated maximal follow-up for each patient for this outcome is 1-3 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular death</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years minimum</time_frame>
    <description>Time to cardiovascular death from randomization. Estimated maximal follow-up for each patient for this outcome is 1-3 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Non-ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Betablocker</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving a betablocker. Any other treatment or management is to be given as per usual care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Betablocker</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>No betablocker is given to this arm. Any other treatment or management is to be given as per usual care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-betablocker</intervention_name>
    <description>No betablocker will be administered. Patients randomized to no beta-blockade will be discouraged to use beta-blockade as long as there is no other indication than strictly secondary prevention after myocardial infarction. Any other treatment or management is to be given as per usual care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Betablocker</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Betablocker</intervention_name>
    <description>A betablocker will be administered. To reflect contemporary management, for which this study is designed to test, there will not be a defined minimum dosage. The type and dose of BB will be left at the discretion of the PI. Generic drug and accepted dosages will be:
Metoprolol succinate up to a total dose of 200mg daily
Bisoprolol up to a total dose of 10mg daily
Carvedilol up to a total dose of 50mg daily
The treating physician will be encouraged to aim for an equipotent dose of 100 mg metoprolol succinate or higher. Any other treatment or management is to be given as per usual care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Betablocker</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        To be eligible for inclusion in the study, subjects must fulfill the following criteria at
        inclusion:

          -  18 years or older

          -  Diagnosed with an acute MI type I according to the &quot;Universal Definition of MI&quot;
             (Defined as a detection of a rise and/or fall of cardiac biomarker value, preferably
             troponin, with at least one value above the 99th percentile upper reference limit and
             with at least one of the following; a) symptoms of ischemia, b) new or presumed new
             significant ST-segment-T wave changes or new left bundle branch block, c) development
             of pathological Q waves, d) imaging evidence of new loss of viable myocardium or e)
             identification of an intracoronary thrombus by coronary angiogram)

          -  Must have been treated with PCI or thrombolysis during current hospitalization

          -  Signed informed consent and expected cooperation of the patient according to ICH/GCP
             and national/local regulations

          -  Have a national personal identification number and not be expected to emigrate during
             study

        Exclusion Criteria

        Study subjects must not meet any of the following criteria:

          -  Having a condition where betablocker-therapy is required, including but not limited
             to:

               -  Arrhythmias

               -  Hypertension

               -  Cardiomyopathies

               -  Clinical diagnosis of heart failure

               -  LVEF &lt; 40% by echocardiography (by measurement and not only visual assessment for
                  STEMI patients)

               -  Left ventricular akinesia in ≥ 3 segments regardless of the LVEF

          -  Contraindications to betablocker-therapy, including but not limited to:

               -  Bradyarrhythmias

               -  Hypotension

               -  Severe peripheral artery disease

               -  Previously known side-effects causing withdrawal

               -  Severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease

               -  • Women of childbearing potential (a woman is considered of childbearing
                  potential, i.e. fertile, following menarche and until becoming post-menopausal
                  unless permanently sterile)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any ingredient of the IMP

          -  Other, according to the responsible investigator

          -  End-stage somatic disease with short life expectancy, dementia, psychosis and other
             conditions could put the subject at significant risk, confound the study results,
             interfere significantly with the subject participation in the study, or rendering
             informed consent unfeasible

        Previous treatment with a betablocker is not an exclusion criterion for enrollment into the
        BETAMI study. Enrolled patients can participate in any other study that does not directly
        alter the effect betablocker treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dan Atar, MD Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Munkhaugen, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004732803000</phone>
    <email>johmun@vestreviken.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vidar Ruddox, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004733342000</phone>
    <email>vidar.ruddox@siv.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sørlandet Sykehus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arendal</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jarle Jortveit, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Drammen Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Drammen</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Munkhaugen, PhD</last_name>
      <email>John.munkhaugen@betami.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AHUS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lørenskog</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Henrik Schirmer</last_name>
      <phone>PhD</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vestfold hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tønsberg</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vidar Ruddox, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>004733342000</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jan Erik Otterstad, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>004733342662</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dan Atar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-ST Elevated Myocardial Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>Ischemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Ischemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Metoprolol</keyword>
  <keyword>Bisoprolol</keyword>
  <keyword>Betablocker</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Arrhythmia Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiological Effects of Drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Beta-blocker</keyword>
  <keyword>Beta blocker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-ST Elevated Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenergic beta-Antagonists</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>August 6, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/57/NCT03646357/Prot_ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

