<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03648996</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012106</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03648996</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sex-related Differences in Arterial Stiffness in Type 2 Diabetics: Role of Uric Acid</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sex-related Differences in Arterial Stiffness in Type 2 Diabetics: Role of Uric Acid</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Three separate interventions will be undertaken with the primary outcome of improving pulse
      wave velocity. Initially, age and BMI-matched men and post-menopausal women, all with type 2
      diabetes, will be treated with allopurinol (20 men, 20 women) for 6 months, in order to
      reduce serum uric acid (SUA) concentrations relative to placebo (10 men, 10 women). In a
      second intervention, dietary fructose will be restricted for a period of 6 months in type 2
      diabetes (T2D) subjects who will maintain a stable weight (20 men, 20 women). In a third
      intervention, dietary fructose will be restricted for a period of 6 months in type 2 diabetes
      (T2D) subjects who will achieve a caloric deficit and weight reduction (20 men, 20 women). At
      the beginning and end of each of the studies, measures of arterial stiffness will be combined
      with assessments of endothelial function (flow-mediated dilation and insulin stimulated leg
      blood flow), measurements of systemic inflammation and oxidative stress.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sedentary, overweight and obese subjects diagnosed with T2D, ages 40-75 years old, will be
      recruited from the local community, via the University of Missouri's Endocrinology Clinic and
      the primary care clinics. During screening, and after consent, anthropometrics (waist
      circumference and body composition) will be obtained and fasting blood will be drawn for
      serum chemistries, A1c, complete blood count, liver and kidney function. Screening will also
      include completion of an oral glucose tolerance test with measurements of arterial stiffness
      and assessment of endothelial function. Following screening, eligible subjects will be
      assigned to one of the four groups (allopurinol, placebo, fructose restriction/isocaloric, or
      fructose restriction/hypocaloric). Allopurinol will be titrated to achieve a target dose of
      300 mg/day. Along with placebo, this arm of the study is double-blinded. A separate group of
      men and women will be assigned to the isocaloric fructose-restriction study in which dietary
      fructose is replaced by starch and body weight is held constant. Lastly, a separate group of
      men and women will be assigned to the hypocaloric fructose-restriction in which baseline
      caloric intake will be reduced by 500 Calories/day while baseline intakes of protein and fat
      will remain constant. The subjects in these groups will not be blinded to the dietary
      treatment but the staff making measurements will be. Subjects in the four groups will be
      matched for age and BMI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>carotid femoral pulse wave velocity (cfPWV)</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be assessed at baseline, 3 months (interim) and 6 months (final). The goal is to assess changes from baseline when compared to interim and final time point.</time_frame>
    <description>It is the gold standard non-invasive index of arterial stiffness. Transit time between carotid and femoral pressure waves is calculated using the foot-to-foot method. cfPWV is calculated as distance traveled by the pulse wave (i.e., femoral location-sternal notch minus sternal notch-carotid location) divided by pulse transit time. All the measurements will be done by the same blinded technician</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brachial artery flow mediated dilation (FMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months (interim) and 6 months (final). The goal is to assess changes from baseline when compared to interim and final time point.</time_frame>
    <description>Brachial artery FMD will be assessed at baseline and at 12-wk. FMD is a measurement of conduit artery endothelial function. FMD is assessed immediately after each PWV measurement. Shear rate AUC until peak diameter is calculated as stimulus for FMD and used in covariate analysis as described. All measurements will be performed, under co-I supervision by the same blinded technician.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin-stimulated leg blood flow</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months (final). The goal is to assess changes from baseline when compared to interim and final time point.</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be instrumented with EKG for contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEU) measurements. We will perform a hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp to evaluate microvascular perfusion of skeletal muscle via CEU. Insulin will be infused at a constant rate to mimic postprandial insulin concentrations and glucose maintained at fasting values via a variable 20% dextrose infusion. At baseline and in the steady state phase of the insulin clamp, we will assess microvascular perfusion in the vastus lateralis muscle using CEU (IE-33, Philips Ultrasound), via infusion of perflutren lipid microspheres. Microvascular perfusion will be assessed as an A-value. A is the video intensity plateau after complete replenishment reflecting relative microvascular blood volume (MBV).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Hyperuricemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-fructose diet, isocaloric</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects assigned to this arm of the study will consume for 6 months a diet low in fructose while maintaining baseline body weight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allopurinol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects assigned to this arm of the study will be treated for 6 months with allopurinol (max dose 300 mg)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects assigned to this arm will receive placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-fructose diet, hypocaloric</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects assigned to this arm of the study will consume for 6 months a diet low in fructose with a 500 Calorie energy reduction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-fructose diet, isocaloric</intervention_name>
    <description>6 month of consumption a low fructose diet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-fructose diet, isocaloric</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allopurinol</intervention_name>
    <description>6 months of allopurinol treatment with the goal of decreasing uric acid compared to control group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allopurinol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zyloprim</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>6 months of placebo treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-fructose, hypocaloric</intervention_name>
    <description>6 month of consumption a low fructose diet with a 500 Calorie/day energy restriction</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-fructose diet, hypocaloric</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women ages 40-75 years at randomization

          -  BMI between 25.1 and 50 kg/m2.

          -  Type 2 diabetes diagnosed &gt; 3 months ago. Patients with T2D will be classified based
             on physician diagnosis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  serum uric acid &lt; 5.5 mg/dL (for medication/allopurinol and isocaloric low-fructose
             diet arm)

          -  habitual diet containing low amount of sugars &lt; 5% of total energy intake

          -  recent CVD event (stroke, heart failure hospitalization, revascularization or acute
             coronary event in the last 12 months).

          -  abnormal thyroid tests or chronic liver disease

          -  stage IV renal disease (GFR &lt;30)

          -  hyperparathyroidism

          -  use of azathioprine

          -  active cancer

          -  autoimmune diseases

          -  excessive alcohol consumption (&gt;14 drinks/week for men, &gt;7 drinks/week for women)

          -  current tobacco use

          -  bodyweight change ≥10% within the last 6 months

          -  history of gout or uncontrolled hypertension

          -  A1C &gt;10 % (only for medication/placebo arm)

          -  Pregnancy or lactation in women (or women not using contraceptives)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Camila Manrique Acevedo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Camila Manrique Acevedo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>573-8820999</phone>
    <email>manriquec@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Camila Manrique Acevedo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>573-882-0999</phone>
      <email>maniriquec@health.missouri.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Camila Manrique</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>arterial stiffness</keyword>
  <keyword>endothelial dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>type 2 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>hyperuricemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperuricemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Allopurinol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

