<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03640806</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-57</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03640806</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>QOL Efficacy of Adapted Physical Activity for Patients With Fibromyalgia</brief_title>
  <official_title>QOL Efficacy of Adapted Physical Activity for Patients With Fibromyalgia : Single-center, Prospective, Randomized With Biological and Cerebral Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fibromyalgia affects at least 4% of the population. This chronic painful pathology is a
      source of social exclusion with a major impact on professional activity;

      To our knowledge, no study has demonstrated with sufficient evidence the effectiveness of the
      practice of well-defined adapted physical activity (APA) via a reproducible program of
      physical activity that has been the mechanisms of action that underlie this efficacy by
      biology and functional brain imaging (PET CT) in this context.

      In addition, the publications mention recruitment difficulties, a high drop-out rate and a
      difficult maintenance of the benefits of physical activity in the long term, or even a return
      to the initial level after a few months.

      The programs evaluated do not seem to take into account the peculiarities of patients, their
      coping coping strategies, associated with chronic pain and disability . In order to reinforce
      the durability of the benefits of our intervention, we make modulating factors of &quot;coping&quot;
      styles of therapeutic targets in their own right, as well as muscular strength, aerobic
      capacity or flexibility. Thus, cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) procedures validated in the
      treatment of chronic pain are adapted and transposed to our APA program in order to propose
      specific strategies.

      &quot;Fibromy'activ&quot; aims to act upstream and downstream of the formation of health inequalities
      found in the population suffering from fibromyalgia and favored by the natural evolution of
      the disease: These workshops tend to favorably influence the course of life and to define a
      reproducible interdisciplinary protocol.

      It is a question of making accessible and reproducible the practice of adapted physical
      activity (APA), non-medicinal therapeutic recommended by the HAS since 2010 , by the EULAR in
      2016, but not refunded, poorly protocolized therefore not reproducible and little
      implementation. It is part of the spirit of the amended Health Act with the coming into force
      of the application decree since March 2017 &quot;Physical Prescription&quot;.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fibromy'activ, an adapted physical activity program (APA) for patients with fibromyalgia,
      aims to provide lasting symptomatic relief, to favorably influence the life course, to
      identify mechanisms of action and to define a reproducible interdisciplinary protocol.

      Fibromyalgia affects at least 4% of the population. This chronic painful pathology is a
      source of social exclusion with a major impact on professional activity . In France, the
      prevalence of co-morbidities is increased in pain patients . There is a significant impact on
      health care systems. It is very expensive for the society of about € 7,900 / patient / year.

      The fibromyalgia population managed at the Center for Assessment and Treatment of Pain CHU
      Timone (CETD), is characterized as follows: 50 years of average age, 85% of women with
      children in 80% of cases. 60% have a level of education lower than the baccalaureate, less
      than 30% have a professional activity. The duration of the pain before the first consultation
      is on average 8.1 years. The SPICE score is above average which indicates a higher level of
      precariousness. It is associated with dysfunctional pain adjustment strategies, psychological
      distress, low acceptance and poor quality of life. The characteristics are close to European
      studies

      Natural evolution can lead to a total physical, psychological, social deconditioning. A link
      has been established between the severity of this pathology, a provider of precariousness and
      the poor physical condition, related to physical inactivity. The reverse has been described ,
      so the practice of APA brings a significant reduction in symptoms .

      To our knowledge, no study has demonstrated with sufficient evidence the effectiveness of the
      practice of well-defined adapted physical activity (APA) via a reproducible program of
      physical activity that has been the mechanisms of action that underlie this efficacy by
      biology and functional brain imaging (PET CT) in this context.

      In addition, the publications mention recruitment difficulties, a high drop-out rate and a
      difficult maintenance of the benefits of physical activity in the long term, or even a return
      to the initial level after a few months.

      The programs evaluated do not seem to take into account the peculiarities of patients, their
      coping coping strategies, associated with chronic pain and disability . In order to reinforce
      the durability of the benefits of our intervention, we make modulating factors of &quot;coping&quot;
      styles of therapeutic targets in their own right, as well as muscular strength, aerobic
      capacity or flexibility. Thus, cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) procedures validated in the
      treatment of chronic pain are adapted and transposed to our APA program in order to propose
      specific strategies.

      &quot;Fibromy'activ&quot; aims to act upstream and downstream of the formation of health inequalities
      found in the population suffering from fibromyalgia and favored by the natural evolution of
      the disease: These workshops tend to favorably influence the course of life and to define a
      reproducible interdisciplinary protocol.

      It is a question of making accessible and reproducible the practice of adapted physical
      activity (APA), non-medicinal therapeutic recommended by the HAS since 2010 (level of proof
      A), by the EULAR in 2016, but not refunded, poorly protocolized therefore not reproducible
      and little implementation. It is part of the spirit of the amended Health Act with the coming
      into force of the application decree since March 2017 &quot;Physical Prescription&quot;.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>FIQ Questionnaire was developed in 1991 as a specific measuring instrument for assessing the health status of patients with fibromyalgia. The validation of this adaptation and the evaluation of its psychometric properties were carried out by Perrot in 2002.
self-administered, exploring ten dimensions of the impact of pathology on quality of life.
Scale from 0 to 10, a high figure corresponding to a greater disadvantage or handicap. The analysis of the evolution of the FIQ over time, spontaneously or under treatment, is therefore dimension by dimension, in order to maintain a clinical informative value, as well as by an aggregate score ( corresponding to the algebraic sum of the dimensions evaluated, compared to 100 units). A weighting of the aggregate score is expected when the patient can not assess impact on professional activity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PHYSICAL ACTIVITY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard support for 12 months (HAS 2010, EULAR 2016) 3 fibromyactiv workshops per week during the first 6 months, or 72 sessions. Each workshop lasts 2 hours of physical activity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care for 12 months (HAS 2010, EULAR 2016) with Pain Consultation every 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PHYSICAL ACTIVITY</intervention_name>
    <description>3 fibromyactiv workshops per week during the first 6 months, or 72 sessions. Each workshop lasts 2 hours of physical activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PHYSICAL ACTIVITY</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Female or male subject, 18 years of age or older, not pregnant, not breastfeeding, not
        deprived of liberty;

          -  Subject with fibromyalgia meeting the criteria of the American College of Rheumatology
             (ACR)

          -  Subject managed by the Center for Assessment and Pain Management of CHU Timone or
             addressed to it in consultation / day hospital;

          -  Subject free from any general illness or serious psychiatric disorders, and any
             infectious, inflammatory, tumoral, vascular, degenerative or traumatic pathology of
             the central nervous system, determined during the interrogation;

          -  Subject not having a history of alcoholism or drug addiction,

          -  Subject with no contraindication to PET scintigraphy (pregnancy and lactation),

          -  Subject with no indication of physical activity;

          -  Subject whose general state and comprehension of French makes it possible to complete
             a questionnaire;

          -  Topic with average pain&gt; 4/10 at EN

          -  Subject affiliated with Social Security

          -  Subject who has read, understood and signed informed consent after informing and
             accepting protocol rules

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Major subject under legal protection or unable to express their consent: L1121-8 of the
        CSP

          -  Subject presenting a contraindication to the practice of physical activity, to
             scintigraphic scanning by PET,

          -  Subject deprived of liberty following a judicial or administrative decision

          -  Subject with psychiatric illness or Personality Disorder making group work difficult

          -  Subject refusing to participate in the study or not signing the consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>EMILIE GARRIDO PRADALIE</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>APHM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>STEPHANIE RANQUE, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 491385451</phone>
    <email>Stephanie.RANQUE@ap-hm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance Publique Des Hopitaux de Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <state>Paca</state>
        <zip>13354</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>STEPHANIE RANQUE, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 491385451</phone>
      <email>Stephanie.RANQUE@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

