<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03646877</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO00100375</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03646877</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanisms of Ozone-Induced Alterations in Efferocytosis and Phagocytosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanisms of Ozone-Induced Alterations in Efferocytosis and Phagocytosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Robert Tighe, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>East Carolina University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study to understand how environmental and genetic factors may be
      involved in lung function. Healthy Study participants will undergo a 1-day screening that
      includes a blood draw and breathing testing, return for a two-day series of testing to
      include blood draw, and brief breathing test before and after an inhaled challenge with
      either filtered air (FA) or ozone (O3). Participants return the next day for a brief
      breathing test, a blood draw and a procedure called bronchoscopy performed under conscious
      sedation to evaluate the lung after the challenge.

      Participants then return 18 - 20 days later to repeat the two-day series of testing to be
      challenged with the exposure not received on the first series, (FA or O3). Each visit will
      take about 3 - 3.5 hours. Follow-up phone calls from the study team will occur at 24 hours
      after each 2-day test series. Total study duration is about one to one-and a half months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In brief, at V1 subjects will be assessed for baseline spirometry and venous blood analysis
      prior to exposure. The venous blood will be used to obtain PMNs for apoptosis assays, and
      serum for CFH and sCD163 levels. Additionally, this will be used to measure cytokines and
      growth factors. At each visit, if the subject is female, there will be a urine pregnancy test
      performed. Following this initial assessment, subjects will be challenged with FA or O3 and
      then spirometry will be performed, and venous blood will be obtained immediately following
      the exposure (V2). The subjects will then return 20 hours ±4h later for follow up studies
      (V3). There will be spirometry, a venous blood draw and urine pregnancy testing (if female)
      followed by bronchoscopy. At bronchoscopy, vital signs will be determined, including O2 sat.
      Patient then undergo an 18-20 day washout period before they are brought back in for V4 for
      the alternate challenge. This will follow the same protocol as outline above in the initial
      exposure and use the same series of analysis as the first set of visits. Therefore, we will
      fully characterize the biological response to ozone and filtered air in these same subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    COVID 19
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in ozone induced efferocytosis of lung macrophages (ability to clear dead or dying cells)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Efferocytosis is defined by determining the number of apoptotic PMNs phagocytized by alveolar macrophages (BAL cytospins) versus the total number of macrophages ('efferocytic index')</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ozone induced phagocytosis of lung macrophages (ability to clear debris or bacteria)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Bronchoalveolar macrophages are incubated with pHrodo™ dye-labeled particles. Macrophage phagocytosis will be defined by determining the number of macrophages that contain fluorescent particles versus the total macrophages Cell free hemoglobin and soluble CD163 - both are measured by commercial ELISA kit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ozone induced increase in cell free hemoglobin in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid and serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ozone induced increase in soluble CD163 in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid and serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ozone (O3)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The O3 level during the exposures will be 200 ppb, which has previously been used in human exposure studies without short or long term, untoward side effects (and comparable to peak levels attained during the summer in the Raleigh-Durham area of North Carolina) (REF - Bromberg review).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Filtered Air (FA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control will be treadmill walk with filtered room air in chamber.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ozone</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will perform alternating 15 minutes rest with 15 minutes treadmill walk exercise periods for 135 minutes in while breathing Ozone (O3).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ozone (O3)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>O3</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Filtered Air</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will perform alternating 15 minutes rest with 15 minutes treadmill walk exercise periods for 135 minutes in while breathing filtered air.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Filtered Air (FA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        • Individuals between 18-35 yrs. of age (No subject will be excluded from the study on the
        basis of gender or ethnicity)

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Current smokers of tobacco products including e-cigarettes or those with previous
             smoking history within the prior 5 years

          -  Pregnant women and women who are presently lactating.

          -  Subjects that have received antibiotic administration or an upper respiratory
             infection within the previous 4 weeks

          -  College and graduate students or employees who are under direct supervision by any of
             the investigators in this protocol

          -  Alcohol or illicit substance abuse

          -  Chronic cardio/pulmonary respiratory disorders or other medical conditions as
             determined by the investigator

          -  Increased airway hyperresponsiveness at baseline as measured by a positive
             methacholine challenge response (methacholine PC20 FEV1 &lt; 8 mg/ml)

          -  Subjects will be requested to refrain from antihistamines, nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory agents, antioxidants (e.g. beta-carotene, selenium, and lutein) and
             supplemental vitamins (e.g. C and E), for 1 week prior to, and during testing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Tighe, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Tighe, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

