<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03648190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17200237</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03648190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Platelet Glycoproteins in Inherited Thrombocytopathy: Association With Aggregation Studies and Bleeding Severity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Platelet Surface Glycoproteins in Patients With Inherited Thrombocytopathy: Association With Aggregation Studies and Bleeding Severity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Disorders of platelet function are characterized by variable mucocutaneous bleeding
      manifestations and excessive hemorrhage following surgical procedures or trauma. Generally,
      most patients have mild to moderate bleeding manifestations with a prolonged bleeding time.

      Platelet aggregation and secretion studies using platelet-rich plasma (PRP) provide evidence
      for platelet dysfunction but are neither predictive of severity of clinical manifestations
      nor the molecular mechanisms.

      Glanzmann's thrombasthenia (GT) is a rare autosomal recessive genetic bleeding syndrome
      characterized by defects in platelet aggregometry. The clinical phenotype of patients with GT
      is variable. Some suffer from severe bleeding, while others have only mild bleeding. Some
      studies found bleeding severity in GT was influenced by the abundance and functioning of
      platelet receptors involved in aggregation and adhesion.

      In addition to a complete medical history, a GT diagnosis requires a comprehensive laboratory
      workup, including platelet aggregation analysis, and a confirmation by flowcytometry or
      western blotting with monoclonal antibodies that recognize the GPIIb/IIIa complex.

      Platelet flow cytometry is an emerging tool in diagnostic and therapeutic hematology. It is
      eminently suited to study the expression of platelet surface receptors both qualitatively as
      well as quantitatively.

      Aim of the study:-

        -  Determine the role of flowcytometry as a quantitative measurement tool of platelets
           surface glycoproteins in patients with inherited thrombocytopathies and its correlation
           with bleeding severity of these patients.

        -  To compare the efficacy, advantages and disadvantages between platelets flowcytometry
           and aggregometer in diagnosing various inherited thrombocytopathies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a case-control observational study to be done at Clinical pathology department,
      Assiut University hospital, Assiut University, Egypt.

      Patients with inherited qualitative platelets defect with clinical manifestations in the form
      of mucocutaneous bleeding or hemorrhage will be included in the study. Individuals with
      similar age and sex distribution to the patient group will act as controls. Control group
      shouldn't take medications or anti-platelet drugs for the preceding two weeks. They should
      have normal platelet count and morphology. Bleeding patients with acquired bleeding,
      coagulation defects, and those on anti-platelet drugs will be excluded from the study.

      All Patients with inherited platelets function disorders will be subjected to:-

      I - Careful history and clinical examination data collecting including:

      Clinical history of bleeding such as (Sites, Severity and frequency of bleeding, trauma
      related events, history of surgical procedures, history of menorrhagia in females, history of
      packed red cell/ platelets transfusion.

      II - Family history such as consanguinity, bleeding complications in any parents/ siblings.

      III - Grading of bleeding severity: according to World Health Organization (WHO) bleeding
      assessment scale from grade 1 to grade 4.

      The following routine investigations will be done:-

        1. Complete blood count (CBC) analysis.

        2. Prothrombin time, concentration and international normalized ratio (INR) assay.

        3. Activated partial thromboplastin time assay.

        4. Fibrinogen level and thrombin time assay.

      The following specific investigations:-

        1. Platelets aggregation tests by aggregometer using four different agonists (ADP,
           Collagen, Arachidonic acid and ristocetin) on Bio/Data PAP-8E.

        2. Flowcytometry analysis of platelets receptors (CD 41, CD 61 and CD 42b) on BD
           FACSCalibur flowcytometry instrument.

      Data collection and analysis will be done by computer program SPSS version 21 Chicago USA.
      Data expressed as mean ±SD, mean±SE, number and percentage. Using Manwhitny test to determine
      the significance for numeric variable and chisquare to determine the significance for
      non-parametric variable. ROC curve was done to determine the area under curve (AUC),
      sensitivity and specificity for each marker.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Establishment of a protocol for Flowcytometry device to be used in routinely diagnosing cases with inherited platelets function defects.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the ability of flowcytometry to assay (determine the levels of expression of each surface marker in percent) platelets surface glycoproteins (CD 41, CD 61 and CD 42b) using BD FACSCalibur flowcytometry instrument in patients with inherited thrombocytopathies and its correlation with bleeding severity of these patients with establishment of a protocol for it to be used in routinely diagnosing these cases.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Bleeding</condition>
  <condition>Platelet Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inherited qualitative platelets defect</arm_group_label>
    <description>Clinical manifestations in the form of mucocutaneous bleeding or hemorrhage.
Bleeding patients with acquired bleeding disorders, coagulation defects, and those on antiplatelet drugs will be excluded from the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Normal healthy participants, with no manifestations of bleeding disorders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flowcytometry analysis of platelets surface receptors</intervention_name>
    <description>BD FACSCalibur flowcytometry instrument.
Platelet flow cytometry is an emerging tool in diagnostic and therapeutic hematology. It is eminently suited to study the expression of platelet surface receptors both qualitatively as well as quantitatively.
Flow cytometry rapidly measures the specific characteristics of a large number of cells in suspension. Typically, the cells are labeled with fluorescently conjugated monoclonal antibodies (mAbs).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Inherited qualitative platelets defect</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Platelets aggregation tests by aggregometer</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Bleeding patients suffering from inherited qualitative platelets defect, with the exclusion
        of coagulation defects, acquired bleeding disorders and anti-platelet drugs intake. Both
        male and females are eligible with no age limits.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Bleeding patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Coagulation defects, and those on anti-platelet drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hanan Galal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Madleen Adel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eman Nasr-Eldin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohammed Ashraf, M.Sc</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mohammed Ashraf, M.Sc</last_name>
    <phone>+201002867611</phone>
    <email>M1111a1111@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <zip>71515</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mohammed Ashraf, M.Sc</last_name>
      <phone>+201002867611</phone>
      <email>M1111a1111@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou L, Jiang M, Shen H, You T, Ding Z, Cui Q, Ma Z, Yang F, Xie Z, Shi H, Su J, Cao L, Lin J, Yin J, Dai L, Wang H, Wang Z, Yu Z, Ruan C, Xia L. Clinical and molecular insights into Glanzmann's thrombasthenia in China. Clin Genet. 2018 Aug;94(2):213-220. doi: 10.1111/cge.13366. Epub 2018 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>29675921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harrison P. Assessment of platelet function in the laboratory. Hamostaseologie. 2009 Jan;29(1):25-31.</citation>
    <PMID>19151842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saboor M, Moinuddin M, Ilyas S. New horizons in platelets flow cytometry. Malays J Med Sci. 2013 Mar;20(2):62-6.</citation>
    <PMID>23983579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mohammed Ashraf</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GT</keyword>
  <keyword>CD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Blood Platelet Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

