<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03645551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Gresnigt</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03645551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Longevity of Ceramic Laminate Veneers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Longevity of Ceramic Laminate Veneers Bonded to Teeth With and Without Existing Composite Restorations up to 10 Years</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Center Groningen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Center Groningen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Survival rates of teeth with laminate veneers were reported to have more marginal
      caries and discoloration when existing restorations are present. However in these studies no
      conditioning of the existing restorations was performed.

      Objective: This study evaluate the survival rate of ceramic laminate veneers bonded to teeth
      with and without existing composite restorations Study design: Prospectief Cohort research
      Study population: the participants received laminate veneers and older then 18 years.

      Intervention (if applicable): The participants received laminate veneers in the past. No
      intervention.

      Main study parameters/endpoints: Survival and success of laminate veneers with existing
      restorations: Survival (no loss of laminate veneer during follow up time), Success was
      measured using USPHS health criteria.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: The participants are asked to come for a check-up of their restorations, the
      investigators will evaluate the laminate veneers by sight and take some light photo's and a
      patient questionnaire will be given.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The use of ceramic laminate veneers as opposed to metal-ceramic or all-ceramic full-coverage
      crowns is a minimal invasive treatment option in reconstructive dentistry. Since their
      retention relies solely on adhesion, durable adhesion of resin luting cements to both the
      enamel/dentin and the cementation surface of the ceramic is crucial. Luting cements used in
      conjunction with phosphoric acid etching followed by adhesive application on enamel show
      reliable adhesion with mean bond strengths up to 40 MPa. Also, etching the intaglio of glass
      ceramic veneers with hydrofluoric acid followed by silane coupling agent application delivers
      bond strength values similar to or higher than to enamel. Even after long-term water storage
      and thermocycling aging conditions, promising results were reported with resin-ceramic
      adhesion. Ceramic laminates are indicated not only to restore malformed, malpositioned, or
      discolored teeth where mainly the substrate is the enamel and/or dentin but also in
      situations where resin composite restorations are present on the tooth to be restored. In
      case of secondary caries, severe marginal or surface changes, it may be necessary to remove
      such restorations. On the other hand, degradation of polymers in the aggressive oral
      environment may decrease the free radicals available on the resin surface that may eventually
      decrease the adhesion of resin cements to such composites. However, limited information is
      available on the survival of ceramic laminates on such existing composite restorations where
      mainly fractures and marginal defects were reported. Defects were especially noticed at the
      locations where the existing fillings were present. In fact, today, advances in surface
      conditioning methods and adhesion promoters enable durable composite-composite adhesion.
      Among numerous other methods, several studies reported increased composite- composite bond
      strengths after conditioning the composites with alumina or alumina-coated silica particles
      followed by silanization. The process of silanization promotes the wettability of the
      substrates and further reacts with the glass particles present on the composite surface
      forming covalent bonds. Composite- composite bond strength simulating aging after silica
      coating and silanization was reported to deliver significantly higher bond strengths (46-52
      MPa) than conditioning the composite substrate with phosphoric acid and adhesive resin
      application only (16-25 MPa). Unfortunately, the previous clinical studies did not report
      application of any surface conditioning method prior to cementation of ceramic laminates. In
      clinical practice, the clinical dilemma is whether or not to remove the existing composite
      restorations with no indications of caries or acceptable surface degradation that could be
      refinished and repolished. Alternatively, full-coverage crowns are indicated on teeth with
      large composite restorations that require more tissue removal yielding to preparations in
      dentin that is a substrate less favorable to bond onto than enamel. The objective of this
      prospective clinical study is to evaluate the performance of ceramic laminate veneers bonded
      onto either intact teeth or to teeth with existing composite restorations with no indications
      of caries, ditching, or marginal staining. The null hypothesis tested is that the presence of
      existing composite restorations would not decrease the survival rate of ceramic laminate
      veneers compared to those bonded onto intact teeth.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Restorations which survived when applied on the tooth till the last follow up. (survival)</measure>
    <time_frame>june 2007- september 2018</time_frame>
    <description>Caries, debonding, chipping, and fracture are considered as absolute failures. Due to these factors the restorations will be lost and a new one has to be made, that is why these scores are survival and main endpoints.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Succes</measure>
    <time_frame>june 2007 - september 2018</time_frame>
    <description>Both observers evaluate the restorations independently, according to the modified United States Public Health Service (USPHS) criteria on Marginal Adaptation, Color match, Marginal discoloration, Surface roughness, Fracture of the restoration, Fracture of the tooth, wear of the restoration, wear of the antagonist, Caries, Postoperative sensitivity. Patient satisfaction. Above scores are not indications for removal of the restoration but sometimes can be a deterioration of the restoration itself. So the esthetic outcome can be a little less but the survival is still good.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Restoration Failure of Marginal Integrity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>checkup, no test</intervention_name>
    <description>In this study we would like to examine if existing restorations already applied in teeth which we treated with laminate veneers had an effect. We will evaluate the laminate veneers by sight and take pictures and use a questionnaire</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This is an evaluative prospective study where over 450 laminate veneers were made in 110
        patients. All patients will be asked to enrol in the study. Probably 90% will come to an
        evaluation appointment when asked to enrol. 90% seems very high but all patients were
        formerly patients when dr. Gresnigt was still working in a private general dentistry
        office. So reasonably 400 laminate veneers with 100 patients will be expected to be
        evaluated.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients treated with laminate veneers by dr. Gresnigt

          -  at least 18 years old

          -  able to read and sign the informed consent document

          -  physically and psychologically able come for an evaluation as outlined by the
             investigators.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  People not able to return or not willing to come for an evaluation

          -  People died
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marco Cune, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Center Groningen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marco Gresnigt, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>0031647494611</phone>
    <email>marcogresnigt@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peumans M, De Munck J, Fieuws S, Lambrechts P, Vanherle G, Van Meerbeek B. A prospective ten-year clinical trial of porcelain veneers. J Adhes Dent. 2004 Spring;6(1):65-76.</citation>
    <PMID>15119590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gresnigt MMM, Özcan M, Carvalho M, Lazari P, Cune MS, Razavi P, Magne P. Effect of luting agent on the load to failure and accelerated-fatigue resistance of lithium disilicate laminate veneers. Dent Mater. 2017 Dec;33(12):1392-1401. doi: 10.1016/j.dental.2017.09.010. Epub 2017 Nov 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29079354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gresnigt MM, Cune MS, de Roos JG, Özcan M. Effect of immediate and delayed dentin sealing on the fracture strength, failure type and Weilbull characteristics of lithiumdisilicate laminate veneers. Dent Mater. 2016 Apr;32(4):e73-81. doi: 10.1016/j.dental.2016.01.001. Epub 2016 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26856454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gresnigt MM, Kalk W, Ozcan M. Randomized clinical trial of indirect resin composite and ceramic veneers: up to 3-year follow-up. J Adhes Dent. 2013 Apr;15(2):181-90. doi: 10.3290/j.jad.a28883.</citation>
    <PMID>23534025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gresnigt MM, Kalk W, Özcan M. Clinical longevity of ceramic laminate veneers bonded to teeth with and without existing composite restorations up to 40 months. Clin Oral Investig. 2013 Apr;17(3):823-32. doi: 10.1007/s00784-012-0790-5. Epub 2012 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22821429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gresnigt M, Ozcan M, Kalk W. Esthetic rehabilitation of worn anterior teeth with thin porcelain laminate veneers. Eur J Esthet Dent. 2011 Autumn;6(3):298-313.</citation>
    <PMID>21876866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gresnigt MM, Ozcan M, Kalk W, Galhano G. Effect of static and cyclic loading on ceramic laminate veneers adhered to teeth with and without aged composite restorations. J Adhes Dent. 2011 Dec;13(6):569-77. doi: 10.3290/j.jad.a21742.</citation>
    <PMID>21734979</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Center Groningen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marco Gresnigt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>independent investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dentistry</keyword>
  <keyword>laminate veneer</keyword>
  <keyword>existing restoration</keyword>
  <keyword>survival</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This study will focus on laminate veneers bonded to teeth with and without composite restorations. And also will be looked at preparations were more than 50% of dentin was exposed if an immediate dentin sealing would have an benefit.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

