<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03649425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>84939418.6.0000.5342</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03649425</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>COMPARATIVE PROSPECTIVE STUDY OF COMPLICATIONS FOUND IN THE PINS OF EXTERNAL FIXERS COMPARING STEEL PINS AND PINS COATED WITH HYDROXIAPATITA</brief_title>
  <official_title>COMPARATIVE PROSPECTIVE STUDY OF SURFACE AND DEEP COMPLICATIONS FOUND IN THE PINS OF EXTERNAL FIXERS COMPARING STEEL PINS AND PINS COATED WITH HYDROXIAPATITA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Faculdade de Ciências Médicas da Santa Casa de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto de Ortopedia e Traumatologia de Passo Fundo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidade de Passo Fundo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Faculdade de Ciências Médicas da Santa Casa de São Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present study is a prospective non-randomized and comparative study of patients
      undergoing surgical treatment with external fixators of any type, between May 2018 and May
      2020, in the city of Passo Fundo, RS, Brazil, in the São Vicente de Paulo hospitals. A study
      in which we compared infection rates, pin loosening and complications found in external
      fixators made with hydroxyapatite coated pins and uncoated steel pins.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will use as a guide to define the degree of infection and the conduct to be taken in the
      classification of Mas Oxford Nuffield (Table 3), therefore the presence of infection
      occurring in patients classified as Grade 2 - erythema of the skin, serous or purulent
      secretion, pain and sensitivity in soft tissues capable of mobilizing with analgesia. We will
      also send to the culture the tip of two pins removed from each patient to evaluate possible
      colonization and to compare with the degree of classification presented in the pin in
      question, we will do this with a pin without signal of infection and with the pin with the
      highest degree of classification presented in each patient at the time of the external
      fixator removal.

      We will use as a method of insertion of the pin the pre-perforation irrigated before the
      insertion of the pins, to decrease the chances of thermal necrosis and consequent release or
      infection. We will use steel Shanz pins coated with hydroxyapatite or not in size between
      5-6mm. Comorbidities and risk factors such as diabetes mellitus, smoking, immunodepression,
      among others, will be computed for later comparison with the data collected. The degree of
      classification of the fractures, as well as the pathologies that were treated with the
      fixators, as well as the residence time with the external fixator will also be computed for
      later comparison with the data collected.

      For the elaboration of this study, the patients will be prospectively observed, which will be
      submitted to the treatment of several pathologies with external fixators, of any type. The
      occurrence of infection and / or loosening of the pins, as well as the influence of risk
      factors and the cultural examination results of the pins removed at the end of the treatment
      will be recorded. The objectives of the study are to comparatively evaluate the differences
      in complications of infection, pin loosening and microbiological results of cultural
      examinations, between patients submitted to external fixators with uncoated steel pins and
      steel pins coated with hydroxyapatite. The influence of risk factors on outcomes will also be
      observed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 25, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>compare infectious complications</measure>
    <time_frame>April 2018 and December 2019</time_frame>
    <description>To compare superficial and deep infectious complications associated with the presence of external fixation pins. To evaluate the incidence and degree of infection at pin insertion sites, osteomyelitis and wound infection, comparatively between hydroxyapatite and uncoated pins.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the incidence of loosening of the pins</measure>
    <time_frame>April 2018 and December 2019</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the incidence of pin loosening, comparatively between pins coated with hydroxyapatite and uncoated pins, in the external fixators.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>risk factors and comorbities associated</measure>
    <time_frame>April 2018 and December 2019</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the risk factors and comorbidities associated with infectious complications and pin loosening in the patients participating in the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">119</enrollment>
  <condition>External Fixation Pin Site Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>hydroxyapatite coated pins</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients submitted to surgical treatment with external fixators using pins coated with hydroxyapatite.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>uncoated steel pins</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients submitted to surgical treatment with external fixators using uncoated steel pins.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who underwent surgical treatment with external fixators for at least 2 weeks,
        regardless of age, gender and comorbidities.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  We will select for the study patients who agree to participate, signing the commitment
             term for data use, and who underwent surgical treatment with external fixation of any
             type both for fracture treatment and correction of deformities, treatment of
             osteomyelitis and or pseudoarthrosis , for a minimum period of 2 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  We will exclude patients who do not agree to participate in the study, patients who
             have had external fixation for less than 2 weeks, and patients in whom we have lost
             follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cristhopher L Stoffel</last_name>
    <phone>5554981249707</phone>
    <email>cristoffel@outlook.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mauro Salles</last_name>
    <phone>5511985360055</phone>
    <email>salles.infecto@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital São Vicente de Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Passo Fundo</city>
        <state>Rio Grande Do Sul</state>
        <zip>99010-080</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ivânio Tagliari</last_name>
      <phone>5554991173026</phone>
      <email>ivanio.tagliari@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Cristhopher L Stoffel</last_name>
      <phone>5554981249707</phone>
      <email>cristoffel@outlook.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>infection</keyword>
  <keyword>pin site</keyword>
  <keyword>external fixator</keyword>
  <keyword>hydroxyapatite coated</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

