<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03646838</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D17-P16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03646838</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Family Experiences After International Adoption</brief_title>
  <acronym>VF-ADIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Family Experiences After International Adoption</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier St Anne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier St Anne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the types of experiences faced by families in
      France who have adopted a child internationally. In addition, internationally adopted
      adolescents are invited to respond to questions about their own personal experiences.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Microaggressions, or &quot;unintended discrimination&quot; related to adoption have been widely
      investigated in the USA. These microaggressions may relate to both adoptive status and
      country of origin, or both. However, the prevalence and qualitative characteristics of these
      events have been seldom studied in other countries. Differences in cultural norms and
      practices among countries might influence the type and frequency of microaggressions
      experienced by adopted children and their families. Brief anonymous questionnaires devised to
      elicit personal experiences related to microaggressions will be distributed by 4 clinical
      services serving this population (3 pediatric, 1 child psychiatric) and by 2 large adoptive
      family support networks to adoptive parents in France. Frequencies and relations between
      experience of micro-aggressions and other variables will be analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and type of micro-aggressions experienced by French families who have adopted internationally</measure>
    <time_frame>parents respond to a questionnaire at a single time point, regarding their experience. Participation is hence limited to the 30 minutes required to complete the questionnaire.</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will respond to a questionnaire regarding their experiences of micro-aggressions as an adoptive family in France, enumerating the types of discrimination (if any) they have encountered, in what context or environment this occurred, and their feelings in response to these experiences. The types of micro-aggressions could include hearing derogatory comments about adoption in general, their child's country of origin or appearance, etc. Parents may also experience well-meaning but uninformed comments (&quot;how much did she cost?&quot;) which are also experienced as micro-aggressions. Simple frequency statistics enumerating these experiences will be compiled. These will be compared to basic demographic indicators such as the country of origin of the child, the child's age at adoption, the child's current age, the time interval since adoption, etc.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and type of micro-aggressions experienced by internationally adopted adolescents in France</measure>
    <time_frame>Adolescents respond to a questionnaire at a single time point, regarding their experiences as an adopted person in France. Participation is hence limited to the 30 minutes required to complete the questionnaire.</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescents will respond to a questionnaire regarding their experiences of micro-aggressions as adopted individuals in France, enumerating the types of discrimination (if any) they have encountered, in what context or environment this occurred, and their feelings in response to these experiences. The types of micro-aggressions could include hearing derogatory comments about adoption in general, their country of origin or appearance, etc. Adolescents may also experience well-meaning but uninformed comments (&quot;why did your real parents abandon you?&quot;) which are also experienced as micro-aggressions. Simple frequency statistics enumerating these experiences will be compiled. These will be compared to basic demographic indicators such as their country of origin, their age at adoption, their current age, the time interval since adoption, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Discrimination, Racial</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adoptive parents, regardless of the age of their children, as well as adolescents who have
        been adopted internationally, directly.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Parents :

          1. Parents of an internationally adopted child, whose placement occurred at least 6
             months ago

          2. Willing and able to complete a questionnaire

        Adolescents :

          1. Internationally adopted adolescents who were placed at least 6 months ago

          2. Willing and able to complete a questionnaire

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Parents :

        1. Unwilling or unable to complete the questionnaire

        Adolescents :

          1. Parents are unwilling for child to participate

          2. Child is unwilling to participate

          3. Unable to understand the questions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie Odile MD PEROUSE DE MONTCLOS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital SAINTE ANNE</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marie Odile MD PEROUSE DE MONTCLOS</last_name>
    <phone>0145657499</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>perousedemontclos@ch-sainte-anne.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laurie MD MILLER</last_name>
    <phone>0612222628</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Enfants CHU du BOCAGE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-Vital MD DE MONLEON</last_name>
      <email>jvm@chu-dijon.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital SAINTE ANNE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Odile MD PEROUSE DE MONTCLOS</last_name>
      <email>perousedemontclos@ch-sainte-anne.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laurie MD MILLER</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital NECKER</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frédéric MD SORGE</last_name>
      <email>afreds@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital MIGNOT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Versailles</city>
        <zip>78000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne MD DE TRUCHIS</last_name>
      <email>coca.versailles@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frable DE, Wortman C, Joseph J. Predicting self-esteem, well-being, and distress in a cohort of gay men: the importance of cultural stigma, personal visibility, community networks, and positive identity. J Pers. 1997 Sep;65(3):599-624.</citation>
    <PMID>9327589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sue DW, Capodilupo CM, Torino GC, Bucceri JM, Holder AM, Nadal KL, Esquilin M. Racial microaggressions in everyday life: implications for clinical practice. Am Psychol. 2007 May-Jun;62(4):271-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17516773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>International adoption</keyword>
  <keyword>Family experiences</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>France</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

