<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03641976</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2018-0460</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03641976</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Bevacizumab, Infusional Fluorouracil, Leucovorin, Oxaliplatin, and Irinotecan (A-FOLFOXIRI) Compared With Bevacizumab, Infusional Fluorouracil, Leucovorin, and Irinotecan/Oxaliplatin (A-FOLFIRI/FOLFOX) as First-line Treatment for Metastatic Right-sided Colon Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-label, Multicenter Phase II Study of Bevacizumab, Infusional Fluorouracil, Leucovorin, Oxaliplatin, and Irinotecan (A-FOLFOXIRI) Compared With Bevacizumab, Infusional Fluorouracil, Leucovorin, and Irinotecan/Oxaliplatin (A-FOLFIRI/FOLFOX) as First-line Treatment for Metastatic Right-sided Colon Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Recently, the importance of prognosis according to the location of the primary
      tumor in colorectal cancer has been raised. In the CALGB / SWOG 80405 study published in
      2016, the addition of bevacizumab or cetuximab to the first line FOLFIRI / FOLFOX in KRAS
      (codon 12, 13) wild type metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC) patients did not show a
      significant difference between overall survival (OS) and progression free survival (PFS) in
      both groups. Alan P. Venook et al. published a follow-up subgroup analysis on the effect of
      primary tumor location at 2016 ASCO. In the treatment group with cetuximab, the difference in
      treatment effect was significant according to the primary tumor location. The right colon
      cancer showed a poor prognosis for cetuximab treatment. (PFS: 7.8 vs 12.4 months, HR 1.56, p
      &lt;0.0001 / OS: 16.7 vs 36.0months, HR 1.87, P &lt;0.0001).

      Therefore, the investigators propose a phase II trial for the efficacy evaluation of
      bevacizumab-FOLFOXIRI and bevacizumab-FOLFIRI or FOLFOX treatment in patients with poor
      prognosis of unresectable right-sided colorectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter study. Patients are stratified according to ECOG performance
      status (0 vs 1-2), prior adjuvant chemotherapy (yes vs no), and participating center.
      Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      Arm I (A-FOLFOXIRI): Patients receive irinotecan hydrochloride IV over 1 hour, oxaliplatin IV
      over 2 hours, leucovorin calcium IV over 2 hours, and bevacizumab IV on day 1. Patients also
      receive fluorouracil IV continuously over 48 hours beginning on day 1.

      Arm II (A-FOLFOX/FOLFIRI): Patients receive irinotecan hydrochloride IV over 1 hour (or
      oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours), leucovorin calcium IV over 2 hours, fluorouracil IV bolus, and
      bevacizumab IV on day 1. Patients also receive fluorouracil IV continuously over 48 hours
      beginning on day 1.

      In both arms, treatment repeats every 2 weeks for up to 12 courses. After the 12 cycle
      treatment finished, investigator decides whether to keep the study drug. Treatment continues
      in the absence of disease progression, withdrawal consent, or unacceptable toxicity. If
      treatment with oxaliplatin or irinotecan is difficult due to side effects, treatment with
      bevacizumab, fluorouracil, and leucovorin calcium continues in the absence of disease
      progression, withdrawal consent, or unacceptable toxicity.

      Patients undergo serum extraction and blood sample collection periodically for genomic, ctDNA
      and translational study. Patients also undergo collection of tumoral sections from paraffin
      embedded primary and/or metastatic lesions periodically for immunohistochemical analyses.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed every 6 months for survival and
      other treatments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6-month PFS rate (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the 6-month progression free survival (PFS) rate (%) of bevacizumab in combination with oxaliplatin, irinotecan and infusional 5FU/LV (A-FOLFOXIRI regimen) to bevacizumab in combination with oxaliplatin or irinotecan and infusional 5FU/LV (A-FOLFOX/A-FOLFIRI regimen) in not previously treated, unresectable stage IV right-sided colon cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival(OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the overall survival (OS) between treatment arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression free survival(PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the progression free survival (PFS) between treatment arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety profile including long-term adverse events between treatment arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>surrogate markers predictive of survival: ctDNA</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between 6-month PFS rate(%) and change in ctDNA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Unresectable Metastatic Right-sided Colon Cancer Starting First-line Combination Chemotherapy</condition>
  <condition>Unresectable Metastatic Right-sided Colon Cancer, Stage IV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (A-FOLFOXIRI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive irinotecan hydrochloride IV over 1 hour, oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours, leucovorin calcium IV over 2 hours, and bevacizumab IV on day 1. Patients also receive fluorouracil IV continuously over 48 hours beginning on day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (A-FOLFOX/A-FOLFIRI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive irinotecan hydrochloride IV over 1 hour (or oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours), leucovorin calcium IV over 2 hours, fluorouracil IV bolus, and bevacizumab IV on day 1. Patients also receive fluorouracil IV continuously over 48 hours beginning on day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A-FOLFOXIRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm I (A-FOLFOXIRI)
Biological: bevacizumab Given IV
Drug: fluorouracil Given IV
Drug: irinotecan hydrochloride Given IV
Drug: leucovorin calcium Given IV
Drug: oxaliplatin Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (A-FOLFOXIRI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arm II (A-FOLFOX/A-FOLFIRI)</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm II (A-FOLFOX/A-FOLFIRI)
Biological: bevacizumab Given IV
Drug: fluorouracil Given IV
Drug: irinotecan hydrochloride Given IV
Drug: leucovorin calcium Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (A-FOLFOX/A-FOLFIRI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven diagnosis of unresectable recurrent or advanced stage IV
             right-sided colon cancer (The definition of the right colon cancer is confirmed by the
             colonoscopy result, the surgical report, or the image reading paper including CT, MRI,
             and PET CT. (cecum~splenic flexure))

          -  Not previously treated with chemotherapy for metastatic disease

          -  At least one measurable lesion according to RECIST criteria

          -  Age over 19 years old

          -  ECOG 0~2

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          -  Adequate major organ functions

          -  ANC ≥ 1.5 x 109/L

          -  PLT ≥ 100 x 109/L

          -  Hb ≥ 9.0 g/dL (can be corrected by blood transfusion)

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ upper normal limit(UNL) * 1.5

          -  ALT , AST ≤ UNL * 3 (in case of liver metastasis, ALT , AST ≤ UNL * 5), alkaline
             phosphatase ≤ UNL *3 (in case of liver metastasis, ALP ≤ UNL * 5

          -  adequate renal function : corrected creatinine clearance by Cockcroft and Gault
             formula ≥ 30mL/min

          -  Urine dipstick of proteinuria &lt;2+. Patients discovered to have 2+ proteinuria on
             dipstick urinalysis at baseline, should undergo a 24-hour urine collection and must
             demonstrate 1 g of protein/24 hr.

          -  Written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously treated with chemotherapy for metastatic disease

          -  Within 6 months after adjuvant chemotherapy

          -  Major surgical procedure within 28 days prior to study treatment start, or patients
             who have not fully recovered from major surgery

          -  Radiotherapy to target lesion within 4 weeks before the study (A 2-week washout is
             permitted for palliative radiation.)

          -  Has known uncontrolled active CNS metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis

          -  Peripheral neuropathy CTCAE v4.03 ≥ grade 2

          -  Has a known additional malignancy that is progressing or has required active treatment
             within the past 3 years.

        Note: Participants with basal cell carcinoma of skin, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin,
        low grade thyroid cancer or carcinoma in situ (eg, cervical cancer in situ) that have
        undergone potentially curative therapy are not excluded.

          -  Has an active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2
             years. Replacement therapy, such as thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, is not considered a form
             of systemic systemic treatment and is allowed.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension or clinically active cardiovascular disease: for example,
             cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack, unstable angina, myocardial
             infarction within 24 weeks prior to randomization. Have symptomatic congestive heart
             failure (CHF; New York Heart Association II-IV) or symptomatic or poorly controlled
             cardiac arrhythmia.

          -  Have significant bleeding disorders, or evidence of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

          -  Have had a significant bleeding episode from the gastrointestinal (GI) tract or lung

          -  Have a history of GI perforation and/or fistula, or intra-abdominal abscess within 24
             weeks prior to randomization.

          -  Have a history of HNPCC syndrome or polyposis

          -  Have experienced any arterial thromboembolic event or ongoing treatment with
             anticoagulants for therapeutic purpose within 24 weeks prior to randomization.

          -  Has a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection

          -  Are pregnant or breast feeding. Females of childbearing potential must have a negative
             serum or urine pregnancy test within 7 days prior to first dose of study treatment.
             For women of childbearing potential and men, agreement to remain abstinent or use
             contraceptive methods that result in a failure rate of &lt;1% per year during the
             treatment period and for at least 30 days after the last dose of study drugs.
             Postmenopausal women is defined that : 1) must have been amenorrheic for at least 12
             months, &gt; 50 years old or 2) Age ≤ 50 years old and amenorrheic for 12 or more months
             in the absence of chemotherapy, tamoxifen, toremifene, or ovarian suppression and
             follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol in the postmenopausal range (&gt;40
             mIU/mL), 3) prior bilateral oophorectomy

          -  Patients who are hypersensitive reaction to experimental drugs

          -  Patients who are hypersensitive to CHO cell products or other recombinant or humanized
             antibodies

          -  In case of contraindication of experimental drugs

          -  Have any condition (eg, psychological, geographical, or medical) that does not permit
             compliance with the study and follow-up procedures or suggest that the patient is, in
             the investigator's opinion, not an appropriate candidate for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yonsei Cancer Center, Severance Hospital, Yonsei University Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joong Bae Ahn, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2228-8134</phone>
      <email>vvswm513@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

