<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03649698</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S60763</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03649698</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise and Nutrition for Healthy AgeiNg</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENHANce</acronym>
  <official_title>Exercise and Nutrition for Healthy AgeiNg: Anabolic Interventions for Older People With (Pre)Sarcopenia to Improve Physical Functioning, Muscle Mass and Muscle Strength and to Understand the Underlying Mechanisms of Action.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>KU Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VISTA-Life</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nestlé Health Science Belgium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized placebo-controlled 5-arm clinical trial is to evaluate the effect
      of combined anabolic interventions compared to single or placebo interventions on physical
      performance in community-dwelling (pre)sarcopenic elderly (≥ 65 years) and to determine the
      underlying mechanisms of action. Important secondary outcome measures are muscle mass, muscle
      strength, compliance to the interventions (exercise program, protein and omega-3
      supplementation) and functional, cognitive and nutritional status.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized 5-arm clinical trial is to evaluate the effect of combined
      anabolic interventions compared to single or placebo interventions on physical performance in
      community-dwelling (pre)sarcopenic elderly (≥ 65 years) living in Belgium. Physical
      performance will be evaluated using the Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB). Muscle
      mass will be measured using a DXA and/or BIA. Muscle strength will be measured by the Biodex
      (knee-extensor and knee-flexor) and a 1 hand-held dynamometer. The trial will also determine
      the underlying mechanisms of action using blood measures (such as markers of inflammation and
      sarcopenia) and muscle biomarkers. Important secondary outcome measures are compliance to the
      exercise program and to the protein and omega-3 supplementation, as well as functional,
      cognitive and nutritional status and the patients report on benefits and adverse events.

      The study consists of four parts. Part I is the screening phase, which starts from the moment
      the participant has signed the informed consent until the start of the preparations of the
      study. During the screening, participants will be assessed for study eligibility by the study
      coordinator and contributors. If the participant is eligible, he or she will be randomly
      assigned into 1 of 5 intervention groups: Group 1: Exercise intervention; Group 2: Protein
      supplement; Group 3: Exercise intervention + protein supplement; Group 4: Exercise + Protein
      supplement + omega-3 supplement; Group 5: No intervention.

      Part II is the preparation phase, in which the participants starts some of the interventions
      before the start of the study to familiarize patients with e.g. the intake of a protein
      supplement. All the participants will take an oral vitamin D supplement (800 IU
      cholecalciferol) from 4 weeks before the start of the intervention if their vitamin D level
      is above 20 nmol/L. Patients with a vitamin D level &lt; 20 nmol/L will receive repletion
      therapy. A trial diary will be completed by all participants to record PA, falls and intake
      of protein/omega3/placebo and vitamin D products. Participants in the exercise intervention
      (group 1, 3 and 4) will be invited to an information session where the Otago Exercise Program
      (OEP) will be explained and practiced. With respect to the protein supplementation,
      participants will receive an individually adapted protein supplement to achieve the
      recommended total daily intake of 1.5 g protein/kg. This will be realized by adding an
      individualized amount (g) of protein powder during breakfast, lunch, dinner or snack between,
      before or after meals, based on the subjects' food intake assessed by a food diary. The
      protein powder is commercially available and consists of 4.5g protein/ 5g powder. The
      participants in group 2, 3 and 4 will start taking the protein supplement or matched placebo
      5 days before the start of the intervention. Four weeks before the start of the intervention,
      the participants of group 4 will start with the intake of omega-3 (1 capsule providing in
      total 500 mg EPA (eicosapentanoic acid) and 450 mg DHA (docosahexanoic acid)) or matched
      placebo. Placebo will be provided for the participants who are not given a protein and/or
      omega-3 supplement. Participants are blinded to the nutritional interventions.

      The third part of the study, the intervention period, takes 12 weeks. During this period,
      there are 8 contact moments (at baseline, week 1, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, week 10 and
      week 12). All the participants continue with the vitamin D supplementation. Participants in
      the exercise intervention (group 1, 3 and 4) will perform the optimized and personally
      adapted OEP and will also follow a walking plan. The strength exercises of the OEP are
      personalised based on the individual's 1 repetition maximum. Balance exercises of the OEP are
      personalised based on improvements on MiniBESTest scores during the intervention period. The
      nutritional intervention groups (protein supplementation: group 2, 3 and 4 and omega-3
      supplementation: group 4) continue with the protein and/or omega-3 supplements until the last
      visit of the intervention period.

      Part IV is the follow-up period, after the intervention. This phase takes 12 weeks and exists
      of 2 telephone contacts and 2 contact moments. All the participants continue the vitamin D
      supplementation until the last visit of the follow-up. The exercise intervention group (group
      1, 3 and 4) may continue the OEP, but no personal encouragement will be given during this
      period. No protein and/ or omega-3 supplements will be given during the follow-up.

      Several outcomes will be measured during the contact moments of the intervention period and
      follow-up period (part III and part IV). This will be done by questionnaires about
      nutritional status, fall history and use of health care (from baseline until end of
      follow-up), and evaluation of functional and cognitive status. Blood, urine and muscle
      samples will be taken. The physical activity will be measured by wearing a movement tracker.
      All participants will wear a movement tracker 5 days before the intervention period and
      during the first two weeks of the intervention period and last two weeks of the intervention
      period, and during the last 2 weeks of the follow-up period. Participants who receive an
      exercise intervention (group 1, 3 and 4) will be encouraged to wear the movement tracker
      during the complete intervention period. The participants will complete a four-day food diary
      throughout the trial at week 1, week 6, week 12 and week 24. The participants will be asked
      for compliance during the preparation period and intervention period and their fall history
      which can be monitored by using diaries during the intervention period and the follow-up
      period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participant: Yes blinded for protein and omega-3
Investigator: Yes blinded for protein and omega-3
Outcomes Assessor: Yes blinded for protein and omega-3
No blinding for exercise intervention.
Statisticus is blinded for protein, omega-3 and exercise intervention.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, week 12 and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in SPPB score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with change in physical functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, week 12 and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>the percentage of participants with more than 1 or 1 point increase in SPPB score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in muscle mass (after intervention-baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at screening, week 12 and week 24 with DXA or when screening is 6 weeks prior to baseline, DXA will also be performed at baseline. At screening, baseline, week 12 and week 24 with BIA.</time_frame>
    <description>Appendicular lean mass will be measured with a whole-body DXA scan and by BIA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in muscle strength (after intervention-baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>Hand grip measured at screening, baseline, week 12 and week 24. Biodex measured at baseline, week 12 and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle strength of the knee-extensor, knee-flexor and hip abductors will be measured by Biodex and hand grip strength with dynamometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the exercise intervention, subjective</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline untill week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to the Otago program will be assessed by measure of:
- The number of Otago sessions the participant performed divided by the number of Otago sessions the participants needed to perform. Likewise, this will be calculated for the walking program and for the integral exercise intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the exercise intervention, objective</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline untill week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to the Otago program will be assessed by measure of:
- Monitor and diary: Length of exercise session (time). Pattern recognition of exercise groups by algorithm development</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the exercise intervention, subjective, detailed</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline untill week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to the Otago program will be assessed by measure of:
- Diary: the reported intensity of the strength exercises</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the protein supplementation, objective</measure>
    <time_frame>Urine samples at baseline, week 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to protein supplementation:
- The number of nutritional intakes the participant did divided by the number of intakes of nutritional supplement the participant was prescribed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the protein supplementation, subjective</measure>
    <time_frame>Urine samples at baseline, week 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to protein supplementation:
- Count and weight returned powder boxes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the protein supplementation objective</measure>
    <time_frame>Urine samples at baseline, week 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to protein supplementation:
- N content in 8 24h urine samples by the Dumas method (28) to estimate rise in protein intake and Creatinine index to estimate the completion of the urine samples (29, 30)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the omega-3 supplementation, subjective</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to omega-3 supplement
- Count returned capsules and placebo tablets</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance to the omega-3 supplementation, objective</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance to omega-3 supplement
- Compliance to the omega- 3 supplement is assessed by counting the number of capsules during each study visit and by analysis of RBC membrane fatty acid profile</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status: fraitly</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>- Change in physical frailty stage defined by Fried et al (frail (3-5/5), prefrail (1-2/5), robust (0/5))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status: activities of daily living</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in ADL (Barthel-index)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status: balance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in balance (Mini-BESTest)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status: change in physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in PA by the MoveMonitor+ (MM+) (method under development in our research group)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status: health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>- Change in health-related quality of life, according to SF-36 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status: falls</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>- Number of falls and the circumstances, identified using weekly fall calendars + FES-I</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive status: immediate and delayed memory, attention, language and visuospatial skills</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>- The Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS): immediate and delayed memory, attention, language and visuospatial skills;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive status: inhibition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>Stroop test (inhibition)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive status</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>- Maze test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutritional status: malnutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (preparation for food diary), week 6, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>- Changes in numbers of participants with malnutrition, according to Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutritional status: nutriënt intake</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (preparation for food diary), week 6, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>- Changes in nutriënt intake, according to the four day food diary.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported benefits and adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>week 1, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 22, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>Benefits and adverse effects are asked. Participants will describe their thoughts about the study, what they like and don't like.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 1, 4, 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>change in hs-CRP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hemoglobin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in creatinine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ureum</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in ureum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in serum albumin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in serum albumin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in glucose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cholesterol (HDL, LDL, total, Triglycerides)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in cholesterol (HDL, LDL, total, Triglycerides)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in insulin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in IGF-1</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in IGF-1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 25-hydroxy-vitamin D</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in 25-hydroxy-vitamin D</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in creatinine kinase</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in creatinine kinase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in indoxyl sulfate</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in indoxyl sulfate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in IL-6</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in IL-6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in IL-1b</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in IL-1b</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in TNF-alpha</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in TNF-alpha</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in myostatin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in myostatin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in activin A</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 12 and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change in activin A</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcopenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based training program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home-based training program + protein placebo + omega-3 placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-quality protein supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-quality protein supplement + omega-3 placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home-based training program and high quality protein supplement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home-based training program, high-quality protein supplement and omega-3 fatty acids</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo protein powder and omega-3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group: protein placebo + omega-3 placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home-based training program</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise intervention: During the intervention period, the participant will perform the optimized and personally adapted Otago Exercise Program (OEP). The participant is encouraged to perform the resistance exercises three times a week with a rest day in between. The participant is advised to perform the exercises in close temporal proximity to one of the moments of the intake of the protein supplement. The participant will also follow a walking plan in which he or she needs to walk 30 minutes twice a week. These 30 minutes can be broken down to three 10-minute walks throughout the day. During the follow-up period, participants may continue the OEP, but no personal encouragement will be given during this period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based training program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-quality protein supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>The participant will receive an individually adapted protein supplement to achieve the recommend total (usual diet and supplements) daily intake of 1.5 g/protein/kg for frail elderly. This will be realized by adding an individualized amount (g) of protein powder during breakfast, lunch, dinner or snack between meals, or before breakfast or after dinner, based on the subjects' food intake assessed by a food diary. The participant will take the protein supplement from 5 days before the start of the intervention. The protein powder is commercially available and consists of 4.5g protein/5g powder. During the follow-up, no protein supplement is added.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-quality protein supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Omega-3 fatty acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Four weeks before the start of the intervention, the participant will start the intake of 1 omega-3 capsule providing in total 500 mg EPA and 450 mg DHA until the end of the intervention. He or she has to take the supplement once daily at a chosen time. During the follow-up, no omega-3 supplement will be given.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo protein powder</intervention_name>
    <description>Isocaloric maltodextrin powder. Amount based on food diary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based training program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo protein powder and omega-3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo omega-3</intervention_name>
    <description>Peanut oil soft gel capsules. 1g/ capsule. 1 capsule/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 Anabolic interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-quality protein supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based training program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo protein powder and omega-3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female persons with (pre)sarcopenia according to the European Working Group on
             Sarcopenia in Older People (EWGSOP): reduced muscle mass without (presarcopenia) or
             with (sarcopenia) reduced walking speed (≤ 0.8m/s) or muscle strength OR probable,
             confirmed or severe sarcopenia according to EWGSOP2.

          2. 65 years or older;

          3. Community-dwelling elderly or assisted living;

          4. In case of one or more positive answer(s) on the health screen for exercise, subjects
             need approval of their general practitioner to participate in this RCT.

               -  Uncontrolled or unstable health problems

               -  Uncontrolled pain or feeling unwell the day of the exercise

               -  Recently diagnosed cardiovascular events

               -  SBP ≥ 180mmHg and/or DBP ≥ 100 mmHg

               -  Resting tachycardia &gt; 100 bpm

               -  Uncontrolled atrial or ventricular arrhythmias

               -  Unstable or acute heart failure

               -  Lasting, increased pain following a previous session

               -  Suspected acute injury

               -  Recent injurious fall without medical assessment

               -  Severe breathlessness or dizziness

               -  Uncontrolled pulmonary problems

               -  Rheumatoid arthritis flare up or acute systemic illness/infection

               -  Unexplained lethargy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Impairments/diseases that impose problems to participation in the study;

          2. Allergy to milk or soy or peanut;

          3. MMSE &lt; 21;

          4. Terminal illness (prognosis &lt; 6 months);

          5. Persons who followed a physical training program in the last 6 months (twice or
             more/week);

          6. Persons with a daily intake of &gt; 1.5 g protein/kg BW/day;

          7. Diagnosis of severe kidney disease (GFR &lt; 30 ml/min) or diabetes mellitus;

          8. Unable to communicate in Dutch, English or French.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evelien Gielen, Prof MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gerontology and Geriatrics, Department of Public Health and primary care KU Leuven</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lenore Dedeyne, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+32 16 34 01 35</phone>
    <email>lenore.dedeyne@kuleuven.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jolan Dupont</last_name>
    <email>jolan.dupont@uzleuven.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gerontology and Geriatrics, Department of chronic diseases, metabolism and ageing (CHROMETA) KU Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <state>Vlaams-Brabant</state>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lenore Dedeyne, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+32 16 34 01 35</phone>
      <email>Lenore.dedeyne@kuleuven.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evelien Gielen, Prof MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sarcopenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Protein</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin D</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Older people</keyword>
  <keyword>Frailty</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcopenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

