<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03667131</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EEVA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03667131</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enalapril Maleate on Arterial Stiffness in Rheumatoid Arthritis.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Prophylactic Treatment With Enalapril Maleate on Arterial Stiffness in Rheumatoid Arthritis Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Guadalajara</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Guadalajara</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effect in artery stiffness of enalapril maleate in Rheumatoid
      Arthritis women patients. Half of participants will receive 5 mg enalapril maleate every 12
      hrs, while the other half will receive a placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA) is a chronic inflammatory systemic disease considered as an
      independent cardiovascular risk factor that is associated with cumulative inflammatory load
      with an elevation of circulating levels of cytokines, which mediate the mechanism of
      endothelial cells activation by increasing the angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) function
      and generation of vasoconstriction. Enalapril maleate is a prodrug that is hydrolyzed by
      hepatic esterases in enalaprilat, which is a potent inhibitor of ACE. ACE inhibition
      decreases vascular systemic resistance and mean, diastolic and systolic blood pressures in
      several hypertensive states, independently of the mechanism, ACE inhibitors have a widespread
      clinic use for cardiovascular diseases. Therefore, the researchers considered that there
      could be an association between the use of enalapril and the decrease in arterial stiffness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 19, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 8, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, double blind, controlled, parallel groups clinical trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participant, care provider, investigator and outcomes assessor.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pulse Wave Velocity (PWV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>This is a measure of arterial stiffness, or the rate at which pressure waves move down the vessel.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cardio-Ankle Vascular Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>This is calculated from PWV at the origin of the aorta to the ankle portion of the tibial artery, and systolic and diastolic blood pressures measured at the upper brachial artery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enalapril Maleate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Enalapril Maleate 5 mg every 12 hrs for 90 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Substance that lacks in itself therapeutic action.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enalapril Maleate</intervention_name>
    <description>Enalapril Maleate 5 mg tablet, every 12 hrs for 90 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enalapril Maleate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo 5 mg tablet, every 12 hrs for 90 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Inactive drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients classified with RA according to the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) /
             European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) 2010

          -  Patients treated in the outpatient service of the Rheumatology Service of the Hospital
             Civil de Guadalajara &quot;Dr. Juan I Menchaca&quot;.

          -  Sign an Informed Consent Letter

          -  Under treatment with conventional Disease-Modifying Antirheumatic Drugs (DMARDS)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a previous diagnosis of diabetes mellitus, systemic hypertension,
             thyroid, kidney or liver disease

          -  History of acute myocardial infarction, cardiac arrhythmias, cerebral vascular event
             or heart failure

          -  Smoking active patients in the last 6 months

          -  Patients with a desire for close conception, pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Patients with blood pressure &lt;90/60 mmHg

          -  Patients who do not accept to participate in the study

          -  Patients with a BMI greater than ≥40 Kg / m2

          -  Non-palpable carotid and femoral pulses

          -  Unstable psychological state
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monica Vázquez-Del Mercado, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Guadalajara</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Investigación en Reumatología y Sistema Músculo Esquelético</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guadalajara</city>
        <state>Jalisco</state>
        <zip>44340</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gossec L, Dougados M, Dixon W. Patient-reported outcomes as end points in clinical trials in rheumatoid arthritis. RMD Open. 2015 Apr 2;1(1):e000019. doi: 10.1136/rmdopen-2014-000019. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26509052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burmester GR, Feist E, Dörner T. Emerging cell and cytokine targets in rheumatoid arthritis. Nat Rev Rheumatol. 2014 Feb;10(2):77-88. doi: 10.1038/nrrheum.2013.168. Epub 2013 Nov 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24217582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gibofsky A. Overview of epidemiology, pathophysiology, and diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis. Am J Manag Care. 2012 Dec;18(13 Suppl):S295-302.</citation>
    <PMID>23327517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gkaliagkousi E, Gavriilaki E, Doumas M, Petidis K, Aslanidis S, Stella D. Cardiovascular risk in rheumatoid arthritis: pathogenesis, diagnosis, and management. J Clin Rheumatol. 2012 Dec;18(8):422-30. doi: 10.1097/RHU.0b013e31827846b1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23188207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomon DH, Karlson EW, Rimm EB, Cannuscio CC, Mandl LA, Manson JE, Stampfer MJ, Curhan GC. Cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in women diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis. Circulation. 2003 Mar 11;107(9):1303-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12628952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kramer HR, Giles JT. Cardiovascular disease risk in rheumatoid arthritis: progress, debate, and opportunity. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2011 Apr;63(4):484-99. doi: 10.1002/acr.20386. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21452262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crowson CS, Nicola PJ, Kremers HM, O'Fallon WM, Therneau TM, Jacobsen SJ, Roger VL, Ballman KV, Gabriel SE. How much of the increased incidence of heart failure in rheumatoid arthritis is attributable to traditional cardiovascular risk factors and ischemic heart disease? Arthritis Rheum. 2005 Oct;52(10):3039-44.</citation>
    <PMID>16200583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kremers HM, Crowson CS, Therneau TM, Roger VL, Gabriel SE. High ten-year risk of cardiovascular disease in newly diagnosed rheumatoid arthritis patients: a population-based cohort study. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Aug;58(8):2268-74. doi: 10.1002/art.23650.</citation>
    <PMID>18668561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crilly MA, Kumar V, Clark HJ, Scott NW, Macdonald AG, Williams DJ. Arterial stiffness and cumulative inflammatory burden in rheumatoid arthritis: a dose-response relationship independent of established cardiovascular risk factors. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2009 Dec;48(12):1606-12. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/kep305. Epub 2009 Oct 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19858120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klocke R, Cockcroft JR, Taylor GJ, Hall IR, Blake DR. Arterial stiffness and central blood pressure, as determined by pulse wave analysis, in rheumatoid arthritis. Ann Rheum Dis. 2003 May;62(5):414-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12695151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park S, Lakatta EG. Role of inflammation in the pathogenesis of arterial stiffness. Yonsei Med J. 2012 Mar;53(2):258-61. doi: 10.3349/ymj.2012.53.2.258. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22318811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roman MJ, Devereux RB, Schwartz JE, Lockshin MD, Paget SA, Davis A, Crow MK, Sammaritano L, Levine DM, Shankar BA, Moeller E, Salmon JE. Arterial stiffness in chronic inflammatory diseases. Hypertension. 2005 Jul;46(1):194-9. Epub 2005 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>15911740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vázquez-Del Mercado M, Nuñez-Atahualpa L, Figueroa-Sánchez M, Gómez-Bañuelos E, Rocha-Muñoz AD, Martín-Márquez BT, Corona-Sanchez EG, Martínez-García EA, Macias-Reyes H, Gonzalez-Lopez L, Gamez-Nava JI, Navarro-Hernandez RE, Nuñez-Atahualpa MA, Andrade-Garduño J. Serum levels of anticyclic citrullinated peptide antibodies, interleukin-6, tumor necrosis factor-α, and C-reactive protein are associated with increased carotid intima-media thickness: a cross-sectional analysis of a cohort of rheumatoid arthritis patients without cardiovascular risk factors. Biomed Res Int. 2015;2015:342649. doi: 10.1155/2015/342649. Epub 2015 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25821796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wållberg-Jonsson S, Caidahl K, Klintland N, Nyberg G, Rantapää-Dahlqvist S. Increased arterial stiffness and indication of endothelial dysfunction in long-standing rheumatoid arthritis. Scand J Rheumatol. 2008 Jan-Feb;37(1):1-5. doi: 10.1080/03009740701633238.</citation>
    <PMID>18189187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vázquez-Del Mercado M, Gomez-Bañuelos E, Chavarria-Avila E, Cardona-Muñoz E, Ramos-Becerra C, Alanis-Sanchez A, Cardona-Muller D, Grover-Paez F, Perez-Vazquez FJ, Navarro-Hernandez RE, Valadez-Soto JM, Saldaña-Millan AA, Gonzalez-Rosas L, Ramos-Lopez G, Petri MH, Bäck M. Disease duration of rheumatoid arthritis is a predictor of vascular stiffness: a cross-sectional study in patients without known cardiovascular comorbidities: A STROBE-compliant article. Medicine (Baltimore). 2017 Aug;96(33):e7862. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000007862.</citation>
    <PMID>28816989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Guadalajara</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mónica VázquezdelMercadoEspinosa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>arterial stiffness</keyword>
  <keyword>enalapril maleate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Enalapril</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enalaprilat</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enzyme Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data for pulse wave velocity will be available.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available within one year of study completion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access requests will be reviewed by an external independent Review Panel. Requests will be required to sign a Data Access Agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

