<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03662737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRV-CAN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03662737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VRT as a Biomarker of Cerebellar Dysfunction in Chronic Cannabis Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Visuomotor Rotation Task as a Biomarker of Cerebellar Dysfunction in Chronic Cannabis Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic cannabis consumption has been associated with poor psychosocial functioning that
      could be associated to cerebellar dysfunction. The cerebellum has a relevant role in
      adaptation processes and has a high density of cannabinoid 1 receptor (CB1R). Implicit motor
      learning is a cerebellum dependent function that can be measured with a visuomotor rotation
      task (VRT).

      The project aims to identify a sensitive and specific biomarker of cerebellum dysfunction in
      chronic cannabis users. The investigators would like to demonstrate that the visuomotor
      rotation paradigm is valid to measure and quantify such a dysfunction.

      A longitudinal prospective study with a 3 month follow-up is proposed. 3 groups will be
      included: 1) chronic cannabis users; 2) individuals with an alcohol use disorder; and 3)
      healthy controls. All groups will be matched by sex and age. Forty individuals will be
      included in each group. Individuals will be assessed at baseline, at first month and at
      3-months of follow-up. Sociodemographic and clinical data will be recorded. Information on
      cannabis consumption will be registered using an App.

      Participants will do the visuomotor rotation task and answer three questionnaires: the
      Intrinsic Motivation Inventory, the Scale for the assessment and rating of ataxia (SARA) and
      the Harris tests for lateral dominance.

      The biomarker developed by this project will facilitate the detection of cerebellar
      alterations in chronic cannabis users, and will permit to quantify and monitor such
      alteration over time. The team's intention is to patent the proposed model and disseminate it
      in order to use it in clinical practice at both primary and specialized health centres.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The subjects have to realize movements towards a target, at a digitizing tablet, holding a
      digitizing pencil. Visual feedback is projected on a screen surface in front of the subject,
      which hides the sight of actual movements from the latter. In the experimental condition of
      rotation, the experimenter introduces a rotation of 45 grades between the movement realized
      by the subject and the visual feedback that is provided on the screen. Then, the subject is
      provided with a strategy in order to overcome this perturbation: that is, to make the
      movement aiming 45 grades to the opposite direction from the introduced rotation. This
      explicit strategy leads to immediate correction of the error, but as the time passes subjects
      tend to commit more and more errors due to implicit motor adaptation. This happens because
      the motor control system tends to correct the perceived perturbation between the anticipated
      and the actual location of the hand in an automatic and unconscious way. The conflict between
      the implicit and explicit strategies has the surprising consequence of a persistent and
      accumulative deterioration of performance that can only be resolved when the participants
      abandon the explicit strategy. Subjects with cerebellar damage show deficits in implicit
      motor learning and for this reason they do not show this progressive deterioration of
      performance. Given that chronic cannabis abuse can lead to cerebellar damage, the
      investigators hypothesize that subjects from the experimental group 1 (cannabis use) will
      have a significant smaller directional error on the rotation condition than controls. A
      second hypothesis is that this effect will be cannabis-specific, due to the high CB1R
      concentration on the cerebellum, so the alcohol dependence group is expected to perform
      similarly to control group
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in directional error between baseline and after cessation of cannabis use</measure>
    <time_frame>The visuomotor adaptation task duration will not exceed 20 minutes and subjects are expected to realize it at three different time points: baseline, 1 month, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Directional error of hand movement trajectories towards the target object on the rotation condition of the visuomotor rotation task.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Cannabis Use</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 -Chronic cannabis use</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals between 18 and 50 years old who have been using at least 2 joints per day for at least 3 years. They should have used cannabis during the last 24h but not during the 3h prior to participation to the study and they should test positive for cannabis in their urine. Individuals with another substance use or severe mental disorder will be excluded (except tobacco use)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Alcohol dependence</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals between 18 and 50 years old diagnosed with alcohol use disorder according to DSM-V criteria and have been consuming alcohol for at least 3 years. Individuals who are diagnosed with another substance use or severe mental disorder will be excluded (except tobacco use).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals matched in gender and age with the experimental groups and with no diagnosis of substance use or severe mental disorder (except tobacco use)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Visuomotor adaptation task</intervention_name>
    <description>We will measure performance of the subjects of each group on the visuomotor adaptation task, especially in the rotation condition, in which a perturbation will be induced between the anticipated location of the hand and the provided visual feedback, and in the washout condition, in which the rotation will be removed. We expect that subjects with cannabis use disorder will not show the expected implicit motor adaptation to the perturbation and consequently no deterioration of performance on the task, due to cannabis-induced cerebellar damage. In other words, we want to show that this visuomotor task is a cheap and quick biomarker of cerebellar dysfunction in chronic cannabis users.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 -Chronic cannabis use</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Alcohol dependence</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Urine
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The experimental group 1 (cannabis use) will consist of the patients of the Addiction Unit
        of Hospital Clinic that are seeking or already are in treatment for cannabis use or
        participants that fulfil the eligibility criteria and contact the responsible for this
        study investigators , after the diffusion of the study. The experimental group 2 (alcohol
        use) will consist of patients of the Addiction Unit of Hospital Clinic that are in
        treatment for alcohol dependency. The control subjects will be recruited through the public
        diffusion of the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-50 years old

          -  Right-handed

          -  Daily consumption of cannabis for at least 2 years (cannabis group) or diagnosed
             Alcohol Use Disorder (alcohol group)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-corrected visual deficits

          -  Regular consumption of other drugs except nicotine

          -  Other Axis I or neurological diagnosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antoni Gual, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital clinic Bracelona</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Antoni Gual, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34932275400</phone>
    <phone_ext>1719</phone_ext>
    <email>TGUAL@clinic.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hall W, Degenhardt L. Adverse health effects of non-medical cannabis use. Lancet. 2009 Oct 17;374(9698):1383-91. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61037-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19837255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore TH, Zammit S, Lingford-Hughes A, Barnes TR, Jones PB, Burke M, Lewis G. Cannabis use and risk of psychotic or affective mental health outcomes: a systematic review. Lancet. 2007 Jul 28;370(9584):319-28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17662880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silins E, Horwood LJ, Patton GC, Fergusson DM, Olsson CA, Hutchinson DM, Spry E, Toumbourou JW, Degenhardt L, Swift W, Coffey C, Tait RJ, Letcher P, Copeland J, Mattick RP; Cannabis Cohorts Research Consortium. Young adult sequelae of adolescent cannabis use: an integrative analysis. Lancet Psychiatry. 2014 Sep;1(4):286-93. doi: 10.1016/S2215-0366(14)70307-4. Epub 2014 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26360862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Batalla A, Bhattacharyya S, Yücel M, Fusar-Poli P, Crippa JA, Nogué S, Torrens M, Pujol J, Farré M, Martin-Santos R. Structural and functional imaging studies in chronic cannabis users: a systematic review of adolescent and adult findings. PLoS One. 2013;8(2):e55821. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0055821. Epub 2013 Feb 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23390554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lorenzetti V, Solowij N, Yücel M. The Role of Cannabinoids in Neuroanatomic Alterations in Cannabis Users. Biol Psychiatry. 2016 Apr 1;79(7):e17-31. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.11.013. Epub 2015 Dec 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26858212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lorenzetti V, Solowij N, Fornito A, Lubman DI, Yucel M. The association between regular cannabis exposure and alterations of human brain morphology: an updated review of the literature. Curr Pharm Des. 2014;20(13):2138-67. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23829361</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crean RD, Crane NA, Mason BJ. An evidence based review of acute and long-term effects of cannabis use on executive cognitive functions. J Addict Med. 2011 Mar;5(1):1-8. doi: 10.1097/ADM.0b013e31820c23fa. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21321675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bossong MG, Jager G, Bhattacharyya S, Allen P. Acute and non-acute effects of cannabis on human memory function: a critical review of neuroimaging studies. Curr Pharm Des. 2014;20(13):2114-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23829369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broyd SJ, van Hell HH, Beale C, Yücel M, Solowij N. Acute and Chronic Effects of Cannabinoids on Human Cognition-A Systematic Review. Biol Psychiatry. 2016 Apr 1;79(7):557-67. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.12.002. Epub 2015 Dec 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26858214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burns HD, Van Laere K, Sanabria-Bohórquez S, Hamill TG, Bormans G, Eng WS, Gibson R, Ryan C, Connolly B, Patel S, Krause S, Vanko A, Van Hecken A, Dupont P, De Lepeleire I, Rothenberg P, Stoch SA, Cote J, Hagmann WK, Jewell JP, Lin LS, Liu P, Goulet MT, Gottesdiener K, Wagner JA, de Hoon J, Mortelmans L, Fong TM, Hargreaves RJ. [18F]MK-9470, a positron emission tomography (PET) tracer for in vivo human PET brain imaging of the cannabinoid-1 receptor. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Jun 5;104(23):9800-5. Epub 2007 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17535893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kishimoto Y, Kano M. Endogenous cannabinoid signaling through the CB1 receptor is essential for cerebellum-dependent discrete motor learning. J Neurosci. 2006 Aug 23;26(34):8829-37.</citation>
    <PMID>16928872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzoni P, Krakauer JW. An implicit plan overrides an explicit strategy during visuomotor adaptation. J Neurosci. 2006 Apr 5;26(14):3642-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16597717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor JA, Klemfuss NM, Ivry RB. An explicit strategy prevails when the cerebellum fails to compute movement errors. Cerebellum. 2010 Dec;9(4):580-6. doi: 10.1007/s12311-010-0201-x.</citation>
    <PMID>20697860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thames AD, Arbid N, Sayegh P. Cannabis use and neurocognitive functioning in a non-clinical sample of users. Addict Behav. 2014 May;39(5):994-9. doi: 10.1016/j.addbeh.2014.01.019. Epub 2014 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24556155</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor JA, Krakauer JW, Ivry RB. Explicit and implicit contributions to learning in a sensorimotor adaptation task. J Neurosci. 2014 Feb 19;34(8):3023-32. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3619-13.2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24553942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stella N. Chronic THC intake modifies fundamental cerebellar functions. J Clin Invest. 2013 Aug;123(8):3208-10.</citation>
    <PMID>23863631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prashad S, Filbey FM. Cognitive motor deficits in cannabis users. Curr Opin Behav Sci. 2017 Feb;13:1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>27482533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bastian AJ. Moving, sensing and learning with cerebellar damage. Curr Opin Neurobiol. 2011 Aug;21(4):596-601. doi: 10.1016/j.conb.2011.06.007. Epub 2011 Jul 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21733673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Antoni Gual</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD, Head of Addiction Unit</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Visuomotor task</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebellar Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Marijuana Abuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

