<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03667755</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NMRR-17-1070-36021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03667755</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fast Track Recovery Surgery Among Gynecologic Oncology Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fast Track Recovery Feeding With a Whey Protein Infused Carbohydrate Loading Drink and Early Oral Feeding Among Surgical Gynecologic Oncology Patients: A Pragmatic Opened Labelled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universiti Putra Malaysia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universiti Putra Malaysia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      opened labelled randomised trial. Participants will be randomly divided into control &amp;
      intervention group during admission to hospital using random numbers. Participants were
      randomized into two groups: the carbohydrate-protein (CHO-P) group and control (CO) group.
      Participants were given a specific drink to their group on the evening prior to surgery and
      three hours before operation. The CHO-P group received 474ml (evening drink) or 237ml (3hours
      prior to operation drink) of a solution contain 14% whey protein, 86% carbohydrates and 0%
      lipids and the CO group nil-by-mouth at 12 midnight day of operation. All participants fasted
      for solids for 6 hours from the operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Candidates will attend Multidisciplinary Clinic (MDC) as appointment date for examination
      then they will get surgery appointment (admit to ward) 7-14 days after MDC date. Eligible
      patients will be identified from name list available in the electronic medical record.
      Selection of patient will be done by assigned research team member then she will approach and
      inform with study procedures to all potential candidates (selected based on inclusion and
      exclusion criteria) while they attend MDC during study period. Participants will be
      randomized into two groups: the carbohydrate-protein (CHO-P) group and conventional (CO)
      group during admission to hospital via random numbers which are issued by computer program.
      For the concepts of the CONSORT flow diagram are followed [50]. The Patient Information
      Consent Form will be given to identify eligible subjects who agreed to be recruited in the
      study. Subjects are allowed to bring back consent form if she keen to seek advice from family
      member.

      Carbohydrate-protein group: Participants will attend dietitian clinic to have anthropometry &amp;
      dietary assessment on the same day of admission (before admission). Subjects are given a
      specific drink to their group on the evening prior to surgery and three hours before
      operation. The CHO-P group received 474ml (evening drink) or 237ml (3 hours prior to
      operation drink) of a lactose-free clear tea-colour fruit flavoured fluid contains 14% whey
      protein, 86% carbohydrates and 0% lipids. Participants fast for solids for 6 hours from the
      operation. Participants will be given clear fluid (2 packs Resource peach) within 24 hours
      post-surgery (without present of bowel sound) and reviewed by dietitian. Staff nurse
      in-charged will monitor anesthetic risk of drinking whey protein and ensure subject to finish
      specific drinks prior surgery. When they tolerated at least 500ml of clear fluids, they were
      given a regular solid diet.

      Conventional group: Participants will attend dietitian clinic to have anthropometry &amp; dietary
      assessment on the same day of admission (before admission). Participants followed
      conventional operation procedure whereby fasting start 12am until operation. On the first day
      of post-operation day, participants will be reviewed by gynaecologist and dietitian. They are
      allowed for clear fluid once there is bowel sound. After tolerated clear fluid, they will
      proceed for nourishing fluid, then soft diet and they were given a regular solid diet.

      On the day of operation and on the first day of post-operative day, blood samples are
      collected for hemoglobin, renal profile, albumin and C-reactive protein. Biochemical data
      will be record from electronic medical record. Upon discharge, all participants will be sent
      to dietitian clinic to assess anthropometry and dietary data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>length of post-operative hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>period of hospitalization after operation to discharged</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>length of clear fluid toleration</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 1 week)</time_frame>
    <description>period of clear fluid toleration post-operation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>length of solid food toleration</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>period of solid food toleration post-operation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>height</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>outcomes will be measured once (admission). Measurement in meter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>dietary intake trend during hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>daily energy and protein intake throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>kilocalories for energy; gram for protein</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>inflammatory effect</measure>
    <time_frame>on day of operation (before operation and 12 hours after operation)</time_frame>
    <description>C-reactive protein in mg/L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>post-operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>infection (yes/no), ileus (yes/no), nausea (yes/no), vomiting (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>re-admission</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>re-admission within 1 month post operation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>muscle mass</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment will be measured twice (upon admission and upon discharged). Unit of measure for muscle mass is in kilogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>weight</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>outcomes will be measured twice (admission and upon discharged). Units of Measure such as weight in kilogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>outcomes will be measured twice (admission and upon discharge). Units of Measure BMI in kg/m^2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>handgrip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout hospitalization (up to 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>outcomes will be measured twice (admission and upon discharged). Units of Measure is handgrip strength in kilogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">106</enrollment>
  <condition>Fast Track Recovery Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fast track recovery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend dietitian clinic to have anthropometry &amp; dietary assessment on the same day of admission (before admission). Subjects are given a specific drink to their group on the evening prior to surgery and three hours before operation. The CHO-P group received 474ml (evening drink) or 237ml (3 hours prior to operation drink) of a lactose-free clear tea-colour fruit flavoured fluid contains 14% whey protein, 86% carbohydrates and 0% lipids. Participants fast for solids for 6 hours from the operation. Participants will be given clear fluid (2 packs Resource peach) within 24 hours post-surgery (without present of bowel sound) and reviewed by dietitian. Staff nurse in-charged will monitor anesthetic risk of drinking whey protein and ensure subject to finish specific drinks prior surgery. When they tolerated at least 500ml of clear fluids, they were given a regular solid diet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend dietitian clinic to have anthropometry &amp; dietary assessment on the same day of admission (before admission). Participants followed conventional operation procedure whereby fasting start 12am until operation. On the first day of post-operation day, participants will be reviewed by gynaecologist and dietitian. They are allowed for clear fluid once there is bowel sound. After tolerated clear fluid, they will proceed for nourishing fluid, then soft diet and they were given a regular solid diet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fast track recovery surgery with whey protein infused carbohydrate loading and early oral feeding</intervention_name>
    <description>participants will be carbohydrate loaded with whey protein infused carbohydrate drink and started on early oral feeding post-operation</description>
    <arm_group_label>fast track recovery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  who diagnosed with Gynecologic Cancer stage 1 to stage 4

          -  candidates for elective operation treatments

          -  Malaysian aged more than 18 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not a candidate for elective operation treatments

          -  Aged &lt;18 years old

          -  Diagnosed with Diabetes Mellitus/Chronic Kidney Disease/Heart disease/Chronic liver
             disease

          -  Allergy to milk/soy/whey protein

          -  participate other intervention study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>ZURIATI BINTI IBRAHIM Dr, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+60199349317</phone>
    <email>zuriatiib@upm.edu.my</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>CHIOU YI HO, Degree</last_name>
    <phone>+60127603622</phone>
    <email>agneshcy0326@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Putrajaya</city>
        <state>Wilayah Persekutuan Putrajaya</state>
        <zip>62250</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>CHIOU YI HO</last_name>
      <phone>+60127603622</phone>
      <email>agneshcy0326@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universiti Putra Malaysia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>HO CHIOU YI</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dietitian</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pre-operation whey protein infused carbohydrate loading</keyword>
  <keyword>early oral feeding post-operation</keyword>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan, and Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 27, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/55/NCT03667755/Prot_SAP_ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

