<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03665194</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CB-03-01/33</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03665194</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate the Effects of Cortexolone 17α-propionate (and Its Metabolites) on Healthy Volunteers' Heart</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Phase I Study to Investigate the Effects of Systemically Absorbed Cortexolone 17α-propionate (and Its Metabolites) on QT Interval Following Repeat Topical Administration in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cassiopea SpA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cassiopea SpA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomised, double blind placebo controlled Phase I study which will assess the
      safety, tolerability and PK of Cortexolone 17α-propionate (and its metabolites), and its
      effects on the QTc interval when administered as multiple doses to healthy adult volunteers.
      Volunteers will receive a morning and evening dose (12 hours apart) of 225 mg (3 mL
      Cortexolone 17α-propionate applied topically as a 7.5 % solution (75 mg in 1 mL), giving a
      total daily dose of 450 mg (6 mL) per individual.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thirty-two volunteers will be enrolled and evaluated (i.e. complete the study). Subjects will
      be dosed in four groups of eight (purely for logistical reasons relating to the procedure
      times expected with dosing and ECG). Volunteers will receive either the active drug or
      matching placebo in a 3:1 ratio. Therefore within each cohort, six volunteers will receive
      the active drug and two will receive matching placebo.

      Volunteers will be screened within 20 days prior to entering the study on Day -1. Each
      volunteer will receive verbal and written information followed by signing of the ICF prior to
      any screening procedures taking place. Volunteers will be admitted to the study unit on Day
      -1, dosed twice daily on Days 1-3 and once on Day 4 (morning dose only). They will be
      discharged on Day 6 and will have a telephone follow-up on Day 14. If they report any
      relevant Adverse Event (AE) they will be invited to attend the unit for an outpatient visit
      as close to Day 14 as is possible.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 12, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 12, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Thirty-two volunteers will be enrolled and evaluated (i.e. complete the study). Subjects will be dosed in four groups of eight (purely for logistical reasons relating to the procedure times expected with dosing and ECG). Volunteers will receive either the active drug or matching placebo in a 3:1 ratio. Therefore within each cohort, six volunteers will receive the active drug and two will receive matching placebo.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax: Maximum observed plasma concentration Days 1 and 4</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>tmax: Time of maximum observed plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>t½: Apparent plasma terminal elimination half-life</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>AUC0-24h: Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to 24 hours, calculated by the linear/log trapezoidal rule</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>AUC0-t: Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero up to the last quantifiable concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>AUC0-inf: Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>CL: Blood clearance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>λz: Terminal elimination rate constant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>CLr: Renal clearance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>Vz: Volume of distribution</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of Cortexolone 17α-propionate and the two main metabolites Cortexolone 21-propionate (M1) and Cortexolone (M2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples will be collected 1hour pre IMP administration and at 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10,12 hours post IMP administration on Day1 and Day4. Further samples will be collected at 24 hours (Day 5) and 48 hours (Day 6) after the final dose on Day 4.</time_frame>
    <description>MRT: Mean residence time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>QT interval changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1 (each hour starting from 2 till 12 hours post IMP administration), Day 4 (each hour starting from 2 till 12 hours post IMP administration), Day 5 (24 hs post last IMP administration) and Day 6 (48 hs post last IMP administration).</time_frame>
    <description>QT intervals will be assessed using triplicate 12-lead ECGs electronically recorded at each time point and evaluated by a blinded select cardiologist</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-emergent adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with skin reaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 and 14 (if applicable)</time_frame>
    <description>Skin reactions at the site of application will be assessed using a standardised in-house method. Any pain will be assessed using a Visual Analogue Scale (O-10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with clinically significant changes in laboratory safety tests (haematology, chemistry, coagulation and urinalysis)</measure>
    <time_frame>Haematology, chemistry and coagulation: Day-1/1, 3, 5 and 14. Urinalysis: Day-1 and Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with abnormalities on electrocardiogram (ECG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1, 4, 6 and 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with clinically significant changes in vital signs (systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, pulse rate and temperature)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cortexolone 17α-propionate 7.5% solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cortexolone 17α-propionate solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Single topical application to be applied twice daily (0 hour and 12 hour) on Days 1-3 and Once Daily (0 hour) on Day 4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cortexolone 17α-propionate 7.5% solution</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>matching placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle solution</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female subjects ≥18 and ≤40 years at the date of signing informed consent
             which is defined as the beginning of the Screening Period.

          2. Subjects must have a body mass index (BMI) between 18.0-25.0 kg/m² inclusive.

          3. Subjects must be bald, have a shaved head, or be willing to have their head shaved.

          4. Female subjects who are either: (a) Non-childbearing potential, e.g. post-menopausal
             (as defined as amenorrhoea for at least 12 months with no alternative medical cause)
             or permanently sterile (permanent sterilisation methods include hysterectomy,
             bilateral salpingectomy and bilateral oophorectomy) OR (b) Childbearing potential AND
             (if heterosexually active) agree to use at least one form of highly effective
             contraception as defined below, starting at least one menstrual cycle before first
             study drug administration and continuing until at least 3 months after the end of the
             systemic exposure of the study drug.

             Highly effective contraceptive methods for females are as follows:

               -  Combined (oestrogen- and progestogen-containing) hormonal contraception
                  associated with inhibition of ovulation as follows:

                    -  Oral

                    -  Intravaginal

                    -  Transdermal

               -  Progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation
                  as follows: o Oral

                    -  Injectable

                    -  Implantable

               -  Intrauterine device (IUD)

               -  Intrauterine hormone-releasing system (IUS)

               -  Bilateral tubal occlusion

               -  Male partner vasectomised (with documented evidence of azoospermia if possible)

          5. Male subjects, if heterosexually active and with a female partner of childbearing
             potential or a pregnant or breastfeeding partner, must agree to use barrier
             contraception (male condom) for the treatment period and for at least three months
             after the end of the systemic exposure of the study drug. Female partners of male
             subjects who are of childbearing potential must use one or more forms of highly
             effective contraception as defined above, starting at least one menstrual cycle before
             (their male subject's) first study drug administration and continuing until at least
             three months after the end of their male partner's systemic exposure to the study
             drug.

             For male subjects who have had a vasectomy (with documented evidence of azoospermia if
             possible) and agree to use a barrier method (male condom) for the stated time period,
             no additional contraceptive method is required by their female partner.

          6. Subjects must agree not to donate sperm or ova from the time of the first
             administration of study medication until 3 months after the end of the systemic
             exposure of the study drug.

          7. Satisfactory medical assessment with no clinically significant or relevant
             abnormalities as determined by medical history, physical examination, vital signs,
             12-lead ECG, and clinical laboratory evaluation (haematology, biochemistry,
             coagulation and urinalysis) that is reasonably likely to interfere with the subject's
             participation in or ability to complete the study as assessed by the investigator.

          8. Ability to provide written, personally signed, and dated informed consent to
             participate in the study, in accordance with the ICH Good Clinical Practice (GCP)
             Guideline E6 (1996) and applicable regulations, before completing any study-related
             procedures.

          9. An understanding, ability, and willingness to fully comply with study procedures and
             restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current or recurrent disease (e.g., cardiovascular, haematological, neurological,
             endocrine, renal, liver, gastrointestinal, hepatic or other conditions) that could
             affect the action, absorption, or disposition of Cortexolone 17α-propionate, or could
             affect clinical assessments or clinical laboratory evaluations.

          2. Current or relevant history of any physical or psychiatric illness that may require
             treatment or make the subject unlikely to fully comply with the requirements of the
             study or complete the study, or any condition that presents undue risk from the
             investigational product or study procedures.

          3. Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the investigator,
             may put the subject at unacceptable risk because of participation in the study, may
             influence the result of the study, or may affect the subject's ability to participate
             in the study.

          4. History of any pathology affecting the skin such as eczema, psoriasis or any skin
             hypersensitivity.

          5. Have tattoos on the scalp or thigh which would affect the area for topical application
             of the trial drug.

          6. The history or presence of any of the following cardiac conditions: known structural
             cardiac abnormalities; family history of long QT syndrome; cardiac syncope or
             recurrent, idiopathic syncope; exercise related clinically significant cardiac events.

          7. Any clinically significant abnormalities in rhythm, conduction or morphology of
             resting ECG or clinically important abnormalities that may interfere with the
             interpretation of QTc interval changes. This includes subjects with any of the
             following (at screening, Day -1 or pre-dose of Day 1):

               -  Sinus node dysfunction.

               -  Clinically significant PR (PQ) interval prolongation.

               -  Intermittent second or third degree AV block.

               -  Complete bundle branch block.

               -  Sustained cardiac arrhythmia's including (but not limited to) atrial fibrillation
                  or supraventricular tachycardia; any symptomatic arrhythmia with the exception of
                  isolated extra systoles.

               -  More than 200 ventricular ectopic beats in 24 hours.

               -  Ventricular tachycardia (ventricular tachycardia defined as ≥ 3 successive
                  ventricular ectopic beats at a rate of &gt; 120 bpm).

               -  Abnormal T wave morphology.

               -  QT interval corrected using the Fridericia's formula (QTcF) &gt; 450 ms.

               -  Any other ECG abnormalities in the standard 12-lead ECG and 24-hour 12 lead
                  Holter ECG or an equivalent assessment which in the opinion of the investigator
                  will interfere with the ECG analysis.

             Subjects with borderline abnormalities may be included if the deviations do not pose a
             safety risk, and if agreed between the appointed Cardiologist and the investigator.

          8. Has vital signs outside of the following normal range at screening, Day -1 or Day 1
             predose:

               1. Blood pressure (BP):

                  Supine BP (after at least 5 minutes of supine rest):

                    -  Systolic blood pressure: 90 - 140 mmHg.

                    -  Diastolic blood pressure: 40 - 90 mmHg.

               2. Supine pulse rate after at least 5 minutes of rest: 45 - 100 bpm .

          9. Positive test for Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), Hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab),
             or human immunodeficiency virus antibody (HIV Ab) at screening;

         10. Subjects who are pregnant, breast feeding or lactating.

         11. Any clinically relevant abnormal laboratory results (including hepatic and renal
             panels, complete blood count, chemistry panel, coagulation and urinalysis), and vital
             signs, or physical findings at screening, pre-dose of Day 1 (as judged by the
             investigator). In case of uncertain or questionable results, tests performed during
             screening may be repeated before randomization to confirm eligibility or judged to be
             clinically irrelevant for healthy subjects.

         12. Positive test results for alcohol or drugs of abuse at screening or Day -1.

         13. Presence or history of drug or alcohol abuse in the last 5 years, or the inability to
             refrain from alcohol use from 48 hours before screening, dosing and each scheduled
             visit until the end of the study. Alcohol abuse is defined as regular weekly intake of
             more than 14 units, using the following NHS alcohol tracker
             http://www.nhs.uk/Tools/Pages/drinks-tracker.aspx.

         14. Use of tobacco in any form (e.g., smoking or chewing) or other nicotine-containing
             products in any form (e.g., gum, patch, electronic cigarettes) within 3 months prior
             to the planned first day of dosing.

         15. Use of prescription medications within 14 days or 10 half-lives (whichever is longer)
             prior to Day 1 of the dosing period, or any over-the-counter (OTC) medication
             (including multivitamin, herbal, or homeopathic preparations, excluding hormonal
             contraception, hormone-replacement therapy, and/or an occasional dose of
             acetaminophen) within 7 days prior to Day 1 of the dosing period.

         16. Consumption of herbal remedies or dietary supplements containing St. John's Wort in
             the three weeks before the planned Day 1 of the dosing period.

         17. Consumption of drugs or other substances known to be potent inhibitors or inducers of
             CYP P450s in the three weeks before the planned Day 1 of the dosing period. This
             includes food or drink products containing cranberry, pomegranate, star fruit,
             grapefruit, pomelos, exotic citrus fruits or Seville oranges (including marmalade and
             juices made from these fruits).

         18. Consumption of caffeine, caffeine-containing or xanthine-containing products, energy
             drinks containing taurine or glucuronolactone within 48 hours prior to the planned
             first study drug administration.

         19. Has received an investigational product or been treated with an investigational device
             within 90 days prior to first drug administration and will not start any other
             investigational product or device study within 90 days after last study drug
             administration.

         20. Known or suspected intolerance or hypersensitivity to the investigational product, any
             closely related compound or any of the stated ingredients.

         21. History of significant allergic reaction (anaphylaxis, angioedema) to any product
             (food, pharmaceutical, etc).

         22. Has donated or lost 400 mL blood or more within the last 16 weeks preceding the first
             day of dosing.

         23. Has a mental incapacity or language barriers precluding adequate understanding,
             co-operation, and compliance with the study requirements.

             Cassiopea S.p.A. CONFIDENTIAL 30 April 2018 Protocol Ref: CB-03-01/33 Final Version
             5.0 Page 30 of 43 RPL Study No. C16021 C16021_Protocol_v5.0_30Apr2018

         24. An inability to follow a standardized diet and meal schedule or inability to fast, as
             required during the study.

         25. Prior screen failure (where the cause of the screen failure is not deemed to be
             temporary), randomization, participation, or enrolment in this study. Subjects who
             initially failed due to temporary non-medically significant issues are eligible for
             re-screening once the cause has resolved.

         26. Objection by the General Practitioner (GP) to the subject entering the study.

         27. Subjects with any medical history, conditions, or risks that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, may interfere with the subject's full participation in the study or
             compliance with the protocol, or may pose any additional risk for the subject or
             confound the assessment of the subject or outcome of the study.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorg Taubel, MD FFPM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Richmond Pharmacology Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Pharmacology Ltd</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW17 0RE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>QT/QTc Interval</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

