<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03666637</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>femoral neck fracture in adult</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03666637</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Femoral Neck Fracture in Adult and Avascular Necrosis and Nonunion</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Relationship Between Femoral Neck Fracture in Adult and Avascular Necrosis and Nonunion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Security Forces Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Security Forces Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One of the most serious sequelae of femoral neck fractures (FNFs) is avascular necrosis (AVN)
      and nonunion, and this translates to a significant morbidity and mortality. This study was
      conducted to determine the relationship between the etiologies and management of FNFs in our
      institution and its relationship to the development of AVN or nonunion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Femoral neck fractures (FNFs) are fractures of the flattened pyramidal bone connecting the
      femoral head and the femoral shaft. It is not so common in healthy individuals but common
      among athletes, military recruits, and young adults because of high energy cases such as
      sports and road traffic accidents, in adults due to falls, in women with estrogen imbalances,
      and in patients with bone mineralization and deficiencies.

      In the USA in 2013, there were a reported 146 cases per 100,000 population. Mortality can be
      high as much as 30% at one year particularly if there is delaying management over 24 hours.

      FNFs are classified using the Garden Classification based on anteroposterior radiographs into
      Types I to IV wherein Type I is incomplete fracture, Type II is complete but non-displaced
      fracture, Type III is complete and partially displaced fracture and Type IV is complete and
      fully displaced femur. Another classification is the Pauwel's classification which is a
      biomechanical classification based on the vertical orientation of the fracture line, and is
      commonly used to determine the appropriate treatment for FNFs particularly among younger
      adults.

      The radiographic union score for hip (RUSH) is a scoring used to describe healing of femoral
      neck fractures, particularly among patients who might require additional surgery, in which
      patients with a 6-month RUSH score &lt;18 have a greater probability of undergoing reoperation.

      Surgical management of FNFs include open reduction and internal fixation (ORIF) which has
      some fixation failures, primary total hip arthroplasty (TA) which is cost-effective for
      displaced FNFs in patients 45-65 years old, cannulated screw (CS) fixation for the young and
      middle-aged patients, dynamic hip screw fixation (DHS), and hemiarthroplasty. The decision to
      use either of the surgical management depends on several factors including displacement of
      the femoral neck, presence of hip joint arthritis, age, and other factors. Around 24% of
      patients who had THA underwent revision within 5 years because of aseptic loosening,
      infection and many other causes. Some surgeons however prefer ORIF and some prefer THA for
      displaced FNFs particularly among active older patients with Garden III fracture.

      One of the most serious sequelae of FNFs is avascular necrosis (AVN) which occurs in 10-45%
      of patients with FNFs, particularly those who have displaced and nonunion FNFs. Nonunion
      occurs in almost 20% of FNFs, more common in men than women, and common with increasing age.
      Around 33% of displaced FNFs are associated with complications. One study showed that age and
      the type of fixation are not significantly correlated to the incidence of AVN, but the amount
      of vascular damage at the time of the fracture determines the development of vascular
      necrosis. On the other hand, a separate study showed that the fracture type and age are the
      most significant predictors of the development of AVN.

      It has been mentioned that time is essential in the management of FNFs particularly in the
      development of AVN. One study showed that the rates of AVN increases over time when patients
      underwent surgery before 12 hours had elapsed and after 12 hours from 12.5% to 14.0%, while
      another study showed that a delay of more than 48 hours before surgery did not influence the
      rate of union or the development of AVN when compared with operation within 48 hours of
      injury. Some studies reported that bleeding from the holes of cannulated screws predict the
      development of AVN, some due to damage to the blood supply of the femoral head brought about
      by the initial high energy trauma, and some due to the extent of fracture displacement. Other
      studies have suggested that FNFs treated using cannulated screws particularly among
      middle-aged and elderly patients have less incidence of AVN. Because of these, we undertook
      this study to determine the relationship between the etiologies and management of FNFs in our
      institution and its relationship to the development of AVN or nonunion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 20, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of AVN in adult patients with FNF that treated surgically</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>In relation to the time of surgery after the fracture</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>RUSH score (healing)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The radiographic union score for hip (RUSH) is a scoring used to describe healing of femoral neck fractures, particularly among patients who might require additional surgery, in which patients with a 6-month RUSH score &lt;18 have a greater probability of undergoing reoperation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">69</enrollment>
  <condition>Femoral Neck Fractures</condition>
  <condition>Avascular Necrosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dynamic hip screw (DHS) and cannulated screw (CS)</intervention_name>
    <description>A preformed case report form was used to collect the data which included the demographic profile of the patients (age, gender), comorbidities, smoking history, mode of injury (high or low energy), presence of multiple trauma, garden classification, side of injury, time to fixation (in hours), type of reduction, type of implant used, RUSH score (healing), start of weight bearing, development of AVN, and final outcome (whether varus, valgus, displaced or healed).</description>
    <other_name>Time to fixation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        -  All adult patients aged 18 years old to 70 years old admitted and managed for Femur
             Neck Fracture during the last 10 years (2007 - 2017) at Security Forces Hospital,
             Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.

          -  Fresh trauma case including all patients admitted within 24 hours of the injury.

          -  Referred cases including patients referred from other hospitals and patients came from
             the war zone without time limitation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients included must be adult and aged 18 years old to 70 years old

          -  admitted and managed for Femur Neck Fracture.

          -  All fresh trauma and referred cases were included in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have sickle cell disease (SCD), patients who are on steroids, patients
             who have developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH), patients who have ipsilateral
             femoral shaft fracture, immobilized patients, pediatric cases and comatose patients
             were excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Saeed Koaban, FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Security Forces Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Security Forces Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Riyadh</city>
        <zip>12625</zip>
        <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kemmler W, von Stengel S, Kohl M. Exercise Frequency and Fracture Risk in Older Adults-How Often Is Enough? Curr Osteoporos Rep. 2017 Dec;15(6):564-570. doi: 10.1007/s11914-017-0407-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28975497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neubauer T, Brand J, Lidder S, Krawany M. Stress fractures of the femoral neck in runners: a review. Res Sports Med. 2016 Jul-Sep;24(3):185-99. doi: 10.1080/15438627.2016.1191489. Epub 2016 Jun 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27265356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morrissey N, Iliopoulos E, Osmani AW, Newman K. Neck of femur fractures in the elderly: Does every hour to surgery count? Injury. 2017 Jun;48(6):1155-1158. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2017.03.007. Epub 2017 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28325670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kazley JM, Banerjee S, Abousayed MM, Rosenbaum AJ. Classifications in Brief: Garden Classification of Femoral Neck Fractures. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2018 Feb;476(2):441-445. doi: 10.1007/s11999.0000000000000066. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29389800</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shen M, Wang C, Chen H, Rui YF, Zhao S. An update on the Pauwels classification. J Orthop Surg Res. 2016 Dec 12;11(1):161. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27955672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frank T, Osterhoff G, Sprague S, Garibaldi A, Bhandari M, Slobogean GP; FAITH Investigators. The Radiographic Union Score for Hip (RUSH) Identifies Radiographic Nonunion of Femoral Neck Fractures. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2016 Jun;474(6):1396-404. doi: 10.1007/s11999-015-4680-4.</citation>
    <PMID>26728521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hu X, Liu BJ, Wen XM, Zheng YH, Jia K. [Clinical observation of closed reduction and compression cannulated screw fixation for the treatment of femoral neck fracture in young and middle-aged patients]. Zhongguo Gu Shang. 2018 Feb 25;31(2):111-114. doi: 10.3969/j.issn.1003-0034.2018.02.003. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>29536678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen C, Yu L, Tang X, Liu MZ, Sun LZ, Liu C, Zhang Z, Li CZ. Dynamic hip system blade versus cannulated compression screw for the treatment of femoral neck fractures: A retrospective study. Acta Orthop Traumatol Turc. 2017 Oct;51(5):381-387. doi: 10.1016/j.aott.2017.07.006. Epub 2017 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>28844681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calandruccio RA, Anderson WE 3rd. Post-fracture avascular necrosis of the femoral head: correlation of experimental and clinical studies. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1980 Oct;(152):49-84.</citation>
    <PMID>7438624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karaeminogullari O, Demirors H, Atabek M, Tuncay C, Tandogan R, Ozalay M. Avascular necrosis and nonunion after osteosynthesis of femoral neck fractures: effect of fracture displacement and time to surgery. Adv Ther. 2004 Sep-Oct;21(5):335-42.</citation>
    <PMID>15727403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Upadhyay A, Jain P, Mishra P, Maini L, Gautum VK, Dhaon BK. Delayed internal fixation of fractures of the neck of the femur in young adults. A prospective, randomised study comparing closed and open reduction. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2004 Sep;86(7):1035-40.</citation>
    <PMID>15446534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Security Forces Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Raheef Alatassi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Orthopedic Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adult</keyword>
  <keyword>avascular necrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Complications</keyword>
  <keyword>Delayed fixation</keyword>
  <keyword>nonunion</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical timing</keyword>
  <keyword>Pauwels</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteonecrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Femoral Neck Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

