<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03668379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>K01MH113475</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03668379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Adaptive Intervention for Depression Among Latinos Living With HIV.</brief_title>
  <acronym>Latino-SMART</acronym>
  <official_title>An Adaptive Treatment Intervention for Depression and Engagement in HIV Care Among Latinos Living With HIV.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will use a pilot sequential multiple assignment randomized trial (SMART) design to
      build an adaptive treatment strategy (ATS) for depression and engagement in HIV among Latinos
      living with HIV. The ATS is the sequencing of treatments, which are a behavioral activation
      therapy (BAT), a cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT), and mobile health (mHealth) tool. The
      outcomes are to assess the feasibility of the SMART and ATS in the HIV care site and
      acceptability of the SMART and ATS to patients and clinic staff.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project proposes to use a SMART to build an adaptive treatment strategy (ATS) that has a
      mobile health (mHealth) tool (text-messaging) to improve adherence to the treatments for
      depression. The treatments being tested are a behavioral activation therapy (BAT) and
      cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT). The outcomes are feasibility of the SMART and ATS in the
      HIV care site and acceptability of the SMART and ATS to patients and clinic staff. To achieve
      the overall goal, there are two aims. Aim 1 uses qualitative research methods for the conduct
      of focus groups and individual interviews with HIV+ Latinos in both English and Spanish. The
      goal of Aim 1 is to tailor the intervention to the cultural and linguistic needs of Latinos
      and the organization needs of the HIV clinic study site, which informs Aim 2. Aim 1 is guided
      by the CDCs Map of Adaptation tailoring framework, which consist of three Action Steps.
      Action Step 1-3 are to better understand and document: 1) expressions for depression in
      Spanish and barriers to care, 2) language issues in detecting and reporting depressive
      symptoms, 3) cultural perspectives of how depression presents as a barrier to care, and 4)
      attitudes (i.e., cognitive and emotional evaluations) toward BAT and CBT, and text-message
      preference and confidentiality concerns to promote adherence to the intervention activities.
      Aim 2 is to build and test a pilot SMART for an ATS - a set of decision rules that uses
      detectable changes in patient health status to inform the next course of treatment.
      Successful completion of the proposed study will yield pilot data on the feasibility and
      acceptability of an ATS for depression integrated into HIV primary care at the University of
      California San Francisco - Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 26, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study utilizes a Sequential Multiple Assignment Randomized Trial (SMART) design in order to guide a series of adaptive behavioral interventions. In a SMART, eligible participants will be randomized at baseline and assigned to &quot;1st-stage treatments&quot; consisting of either 1. Behavioral Activation Therapy (BAT) or 2. BAT &amp; mHealth. During the first stage treatment, Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) scores will be collected. At the follow-up period, the PHQ-9 will provide a cutoff score to determine whether a participant showed a clinically meaningful response (&quot;responder/non-responder&quot;) to the &quot;1st stage treatment.&quot; &quot;Responder&quot; indicates that patients successfully responded to the 1st stage treatment and will continue the treatment in maintenance mode. &quot;Non-responder&quot; indicates that the patient did not respond to the 1st-stage treatment and are re-randomized to either an augmented or &quot;switched&quot; intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Medical providers of the patients enrolled in the study will be notified that their patient is in a study for depression but not told what intervention arm. At all follow-up outcome points, the assessor will be blind to all intervention arms the patient were randomized to.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite measure of feasibility for the adaptive treatment strategy (ATS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is one composite measure. Feasibility of the adaptive treatment strategy (ATS) will be measured to assess whether the ATS is appropriate for further testing, relevant and sustainable. Feasibility of the ATS will be reported as a composite score of the following measures taken at the end of the second-stage treatment:
Total number of participants screened, eligible and enrolled;
At least 80% of all BAT &amp; CBT sessions completed;
80% retention of participants across all &quot;outcome groups&quot;.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite measure of acceptability for the adaptive treatment strategy (ATS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>This is one composite measure. Acceptability of the adaptive treatment strategy will be measured to determine the tolerability or appropriateness of the SMART intervention from the perspective of both participants and clinicians.Acceptability of the ATS will be reported as a composite score of the following measures taken at the end of the second-stage treatment:
Greater than 90% adherence to the BAT &amp; CBT session schedule;
Responsiveness to text-messages: a) &gt;80% of all two-way messages replied back to study line during the set of blocked hours; b) &gt;90% of participants reporting direct benefit from one-way text messages;
Acceptability responses coded from post-intervention exit interview transcripts;
Limited number of barriers to participation reported by participants in exit interviews;
Responses to a brief survey (to be developed) assessing clinic staff acceptability of the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy (ART)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported adherence will be measured using the the visual analog scale (VAS), a 10-cm line on which participants indicate the percentage of doses (intervals of 10 percentage points indicated from 0% to 100%) of all HIV medications taken in the past 30 days (Amico et al., 2006). This measure will be used for descriptive purposes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral Load</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Viral load measures the amount of HIV virus in the blood. Viral load data abstracted from patient medical records will act as a descriptive measure of HIV-related clinical outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-9 is a survey tool used to screen, diagnose, monitor and measure self-reported depressive symptoms. The tool rates the frequency of symptoms in order to score the severity of symptoms. Changes in PHQ-9 scores from baseline will be used for descriptive purposes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engagement in HIV Care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Engagement in care will be measured utilizing the multidimensional index of engagement in HIV care, a 10-item unit-dimensional patient-centered scale that assesses provider, clinic, and patient-level characteristics associated with being engaged in HIV care. This measure will be used for descriptive purposes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the initial stage treatment, the active comparator arm is the behavioral activation (BAT) program intervention. BAT is informed by behavioral theory and has been shown to be a highly efficacious treatment for depression. A total of five, 1-hour sessions will be delivered every two weeks. During Session 1, the focus will be on providing an introduction to BAT, as well as building &quot;confianza&quot; (mutual trust) between the patient and provider. Sessions 2 &amp; 3 will review the initial session, introduce &quot;high&quot; value activities and barriers to BAT protocols. Sessions 4 &amp; 5 will review progress, challenges &amp; maintenance strategies.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy &amp; mHealth</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the initial stage treatment, the experimental arm will deliver a BAT program identical to the active comparator arm, as well as a mobile health (mHealth) component in the form of one-way and two-way SMS text-messages. Direct personalized text-messages will be delivered twice a week to facilitate engagement with the BAT intervention activities. One-way messages will be sent as appointment and BAT adherence reminders. Two-way messages will be sent once a week during a set block of protected hours, creating a &quot;mobile drop-in clinic&quot; where messages can be sent and received.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augment w/mHealth</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Non-responders&quot; to the first stage treatment of BAT alone may be re-randomized to this augmented intervention to receive text-message support in addition to the BAT intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Maintenance</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Responders&quot; to the 1st-stage treatment of either 1. BAT or 2. BAT &amp; mHealth will continue in maintenance mode. These participants will not receive any additional interventions during the 2nd-stage treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy &amp; mHealth</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Switch to CBT &amp; mHealth</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Non-responders&quot; to the 1st-stage treatment of either 1. BAT or 2. BAT &amp; mHealth may be re-randomized to &quot;switch&quot; interventions in the form of an intensified &quot;dose&quot; of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT). CBT is eight sessions long and covers five modules that can be re-arranged to fit patient needs. Sessions will be scheduled once a week to facilitate more contact with participants. An identical text-messaged tool will be used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy &amp; mHealth</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augment w/BAT &amp; mHealth</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Non-responders&quot; to the BAT &amp; mHealth intervention may be re-randomized to receive an additional &quot;dose&quot; of BAT &amp; mHealth in the form of an additional session of BAT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy &amp; mHealth</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV positive

          -  18 years of age and older

          -  Self identifies as Latino/Hispanic

          -  Fluent in English or Spanish

          -  Receives HIV care at study site clinic

          -  Has a moderate depression severity score or higher (Patient Health Questionnaire-9
             score &gt;9; PHQ)

          -  Agrees to discuss depression, treatment preferences, and mobile health

          -  Owns a mobile phone that can send/receive short-message service (SMS) text messages

          -  Agrees to participate in the intervention that lasts three months

          -  Agrees to have medical and clinical data abstracted one year after baseline

          -  Able and willing to consent to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not HIV positive

          -  Under 18 years of age

          -  Does not self-identify as Latino/Hispanic

          -  Not fluent in English or Spanish

          -  Does not receive primary HIV care at the study site

          -  Has a less than moderate depression severity score (Patient Health Questionnaire-9
             score ≤9; PHQ)

          -  Does not agree to discuss depression, treatment preferences, and mobile health

          -  Does not owns a mobile phone that can send/receive short-message service (SMS) text
             messages

          -  Does not agree to participate in the intervention that lasts three months

          -  Does not agree to have medical and clinical data abstracted one year after baseline

          -  Not able and willing to consent to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John A Sauceda, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Sauceda, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 502-1000</phone>
    <phone_ext>17172</phone_ext>
    <email>john.sauceda@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ward 86 HIV Clinic, Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carina Marquez, MD</last_name>
      <phone>415-476-4082</phone>
      <email>carina.marquez@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pfeiffer PN, Bohnert KM, Zivin K, Yosef M, Valenstein M, Aikens JE, Piette JD. Mobile health monitoring to characterize depression symptom trajectories in primary care. J Affect Disord. 2015 Mar 15;174:281-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2014.11.040. Epub 2014 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25527999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Almirall D, Compton SN, Gunlicks-Stoessel M, Duan N, Murphy SA. Designing a pilot sequential multiple assignment randomized trial for developing an adaptive treatment strategy. Stat Med. 2012 Jul 30;31(17):1887-902. doi: 10.1002/sim.4512. Epub 2012 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22438190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hopko DR, Lejuez CW, Ruggiero KJ, Eifert GH. Contemporary behavioral activation treatments for depression: procedures, principles, and progress. Clin Psychol Rev. 2003 Oct;23(5):699-717.</citation>
    <PMID>12971906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safren SA, O'Cleirigh C, Tan JY, Raminani SR, Reilly LC, Otto MW, Mayer KH. A randomized controlled trial of cognitive behavioral therapy for adherence and depression (CBT-AD) in HIV-infected individuals. Health Psychol. 2009 Jan;28(1):1-10. doi: 10.1037/a0012715.</citation>
    <PMID>19210012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christopoulos KA, Riley ED, Tulsky J, Carrico AW, Moskowitz JT, Wilson L, Coffin LS, Falahati V, Akerley J, Hilton JF. A text messaging intervention to improve retention in care and virologic suppression in a U.S. urban safety-net HIV clinic: study protocol for the Connect4Care (C4C) randomized controlled trial. BMC Infect Dis. 2014 Dec 31;14:718. doi: 10.1186/s12879-014-0718-6.</citation>
    <PMID>25551175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy SA, Lynch KG, Oslin D, McKay JR, TenHave T. Developing adaptive treatment strategies in substance abuse research. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2007 May;88 Suppl 2:S24-30. Epub 2006 Oct 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17056207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dimidjian S, Barrera M Jr, Martell C, Muñoz RF, Lewinsohn PM. The origins and current status of behavioral activation treatments for depression. Annu Rev Clin Psychol. 2011;7:1-38. doi: 10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-032210-104535. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21275642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simoni JM, Wiebe JS, Sauceda JA, Huh D, Sanchez G, Longoria V, Andres Bedoya C, Safren SA. A preliminary RCT of CBT-AD for adherence and depression among HIV-positive Latinos on the U.S.-Mexico border: the Nuevo Día study. AIDS Behav. 2013 Oct;17(8):2816-29. doi: 10.1007/s10461-013-0538-5.</citation>
    <PMID>23812892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McKleroy VS, Galbraith JS, Cummings B, Jones P, Harshbarger C, Collins C, Gelaude D, Carey JW; ADAPT Team. Adapting evidence-based behavioral interventions for new settings and target populations. AIDS Educ Prev. 2006 Aug;18(4 Suppl A):59-73.</citation>
    <PMID>16987089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Latinos</keyword>
  <keyword>Sequential multiple assignment randomized trial designs</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile health</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive-behavioral therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

