<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03660917</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AIFA-2016-02365063</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03660917</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Riluzole in Patients With Spinocerebellar Ataxia Type 7</brief_title>
  <official_title>Riluzole in Patients With Spinocerebellar Ataxia Type 7: a Randomized , Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Pilot Trial With a Lead in Phase</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>S. Andrea Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>S. Andrea Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spinocerebellar ataxia type 7 (SCA7) belongs to the dominant forms of inherited cerebellar
      ataxias (CA), being one of the rarest form. SCA7 has no therapeutic options, so that the
      relentless course, the important visual deficit that accompanies CA, and the possibility of
      disease development in childhood are pressing unmet needs. The investigators published
      encouraging data on riluzole in inherited CA other than SCA7. These results prompted
      off-label use of riluzole in single cases of SCA7 in Italy and United States, suggesting
      possible efficacy of the drug in this condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose a clinical trial in SCA7 patients performing a serial evaluation of
      riluzole effects on stringent outcome measures: ophthalmological metrics, scale for the
      assessment and rating of ataxia (SARA) scores, and safety biomarkers.

      The study design will be a randomized , double-blind, placebo-controlled pilot trial with a
      lead-in phase. The design will include a run-in phase of 6 months for all the participants,
      assessing ophthalmological metrics and SARA scores at the month 0, 3, and 6. Then one arm
      will undergo riluzole for other 12 months, while the other will take placebo for 6 months,
      and riluzole for the following 6 months; from both groups the same evaluations will be
      obtained at the month 12, 15 and 18 of the study.

      Thirty-four patients will be enrolled at 4 clinical Centers (3 in Italy and one in U.S.). The
      clinical epidemiology aspects (design of the study, statistical analysis and enrollment
      process) will be followed by National Rare Diseases Centre and Complex Diseases Group of
      National Centre of Epidemiology, Surveillance and Health Promotion of National Institute of
      Health.

      Eligible subjects for this study are patients (at least 7-year old) with positive genetic
      test for SCA7. Serious systemic illnesses or conditions (cardiac, haematologic and hepatic
      diseases) known for enhancing the side effects of riluzole, pregnancy or breastfeeding will
      be exclusion criteria.

      Participants will be randomly assigned (1:1) to riluzole (50 mg twice daily) or placebo. In
      pre-pubertal subjects the dosage will be adjusted on a mg/m2 basis according to the
      recommended human daily dose (100 mg).

      At baseline and after 3, 6, 12, 15 and 18 months, symptoms, physical and neurological signs,
      and SARA score will be recorded. At the same time points the following quantitative
      ophthalmologic assessments will be performed:

        -  corrected visual acuity (right eye and left eye measurements) expressed as logMAR units
           with the ETDRS chart (either back-illuminated or projected).

        -  Color vision via a Farnsworth D15 Arrangement Test.

        -  Visual evoked potential are elicited using transient Pattern Reversal stimuli and
           monocular stimulation.

        -  Electroretinography

        -  Optical Coherence tomography with macular map of both eyes.

        -  Computerized visual field examination by standard automated perimetry and kinetic
           perimetry Every three months electrocardiogram and a laboratory profile will be obtained
           for drug safety.

      The co-primary endpoints will be the proportion of patients with stability of SARA score and
      visual acuity (in log MAR units) at 18 months, compared to the mean values of t0-t3-t6
      evaluations.

      A sample size of 17 patients per group (a total of 34 patients) had 80% power and an α value
      of 10% to detect a difference between the two groups of 35% in the co-primary end points.
      This calculation took into account published data on riluzole in CA.

      Data will be expressed as mean (SD) for continuous variables and as proportions for
      categorical variables. Comparisons between riluzole and placebo group will be assessed using
      the t test for unpaired data for continuous variables and odds ratio with a relative 95% CI
      for categorical data. An intention-to-treat analysis will be done adopting a last observation
      carried forward method. A logistic regression model will be done at 18 months to adjust the
      results for the main baseline characteristics; p values less than 0.05 will be considered
      significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>We opted for a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled pilot trial with a lead-in phase. Moreover, the patients to be included in the placebo arm will receive riluzole during the last 6 months of study, so that all patients will undergo the active drug in the last phase of the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>visual acuity expressed as log MAR units</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>the metric to quantify the best corrected visual acuity, by applying the ETDRS chart (either back-illuminated or projected) with the patient's correction for distance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the proportion of patients with stable Scale for the assessment and rating of ataxia (SARA) score</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>neurological assessment for ataxia. It has eight categories with accumulative score ranging from 0 (no ataxia) to 40 (most severe ataxia). When completing the outcome measure each category is assessed and scored accordingly. Scores for the eight items range as follows:
Gait (0-8 points), Stance (0-6 points), Sitting (0-4 points) Speech disturbance (0-6 points) Finger chase (0-4 points) Nose-finger test (0-4 points) Fast alternating hand movement (0-4 points) Heel-shin slide (0-4 points) Once each of the 8 categories have been assessed, the total is calculated to determine the severity of ataxia.
For motor activities of the four extremities (items 5-8), assessments are performed bilaterally, and the mean values are used to obtain the total score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Farnsworth D15 Arrangement Test</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>quantitative ophthalmologic assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual evoked potentials</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>quantitative ophthalmologic assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electroretinography</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>quantitative ophthalmologic assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Optical Coherence tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>quantitative ophthalmologic assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scale for the assessment and rating of ataxia (SARA) score</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>neurological assessment for ataxia. It has eight categories with accumulative score ranging from 0 (no ataxia) to 40 (most severe ataxia). When completing the outcome measure each category is assessed and scored accordingly. Scores for the eight items range as follows:
Gait (0-8 points), Stance (0-6 points), Sitting (0-4 points) Speech disturbance (0-6 points) Finger chase (0-4 points) Nose-finger test (0-4 points) Fast alternating hand movement (0-4 points) Heel-shin slide (0-4 points) Once each of the 8 categories have been assessed, the total is calculated to determine the severity of ataxia.
For motor activities of the four extremities (items 5-8), assessments are performed bilaterally, and the mean values are used to obtain the total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>SCA7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Riluzole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Riluzole 50 mg twice daily for 12 months in the treated group. In pre-pubertal subjects the dosage will be adjusted on a mg/m2 basis according to the recommended human daily dose (RHDD; 100 mg).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + riluzole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo twice daily for 6 months and riluzole 50 mg twice daily for the following 6 months in the comparison group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Riluzole</intervention_name>
    <description>Study drug will be orally dispensed in doses of 50 mg twice daily for 12 months in the treated group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + riluzole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Riluzole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo drug for 6 months, however they will receive riluzole during the last 6 months of study, so that all patients will undergo the active drug in the last phase of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + riluzole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  positive genetic test for SCA7.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  cardiac arrhythmias;

          -  haematologic diseases;

          -  hepatic diseases with serum values of alanine aminotransferase, aspartate
             aminotransferase or bilirubin &gt; 1·5 times above normal limit;

          -  pregnancy (women of childbearing potential agreed to use contraception);

          -  breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Experimental Neurological Therapies (CENTERS), S. Andrea Hospital, Faculty of Medicine and Psychology, &quot;Sapienza&quot; University of Rome</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00139</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>S. Andrea Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giovanni Ristori</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinocerebellar Ataxias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinocerebellar Degenerations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Riluzole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

