<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03669575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-1575</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03669575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Omega 7 Oil and Inflammatory Biomarker Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Modulation of Inflammatory Makers by the Supplementation of n7FA for 3 wk, Randomized Placebo Controlled Crossover Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bastyr University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bastyr University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine whether the palmitoleic acid supplementation can
      reduce the serum inflammatory biomarkers and low quality of life scores due to
      musculoskeletal discomfort. The study design is a 2-arm placebo-controlled double blind
      crossover trial. The randomized sequence of a single crossover is divided into 1:1 and each
      supplementation is three weeks with no washout in between.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to investigate whether or not the supplementation of a particular
      omega-7 fatty acid decreases the serum biomarkers of inflammation, i.e. highly sensitive
      C-reactive protein, TNF-alpha and IL-6 of participants who have been experiencing decreased
      quality of life (QOL) and having elevated these serum markers. The study is
      placebo-controlled and conducted in a double blinded manner. Participants will be crossed
      over on supplements (active and placebo) in a random sequence. The total length of a trial is
      six weeks in which the participants will be asked to maintain stable diet. The baseline blood
      draw, physical exam, range of motion, QOL and dietary assessment and taking vitals are
      performed. After the blood test results and/or QOL assessment confirm the eligibility, three
      weeks supply of the investigational supplement will be mailed or picked up in person. The
      supplementation is one gel-capusule a day for three weeks. At the end of three weeks, another
      blood draw, physical exam, range of motion, and QOL assessment are conducted; then the other
      investigational supplement will be provided. The assessment of the second supplement will
      occur after another three-week mark. If no adverse reaction is observed and there is no
      concerns, the participant will be exited from the study.

      The goal of enrollment is 50 participants who are between 18 to 99 years old with decreased
      quality of life and potentially elevated serum markers of inflammation. Volunteers will be
      randomized by a block of four so at any given moment, one group does not exceed more than
      three participants. The study takes place at Kenmore campus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Eligible participants are randomly assigned to one of two crossover arms, i.e verum-placebo or placebo-verum sequence. The verum groups are dosed approximately 900 mg a day omega-7 fatty acid, and placebo group contains other fatty acids except for omega-7. After the baseline assessment, a participant is on the supplement bottle for three weeks before re-assessed, and starts the second bottle without a washout period. The participant is re-assessed at the end of the six weeks before exits the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>The randomization block of four. Participants, research coordinators, and study clinicians are blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CRP (serum)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification of the serum hsCRP level during active supplement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain/discomfort (self-assessment from 1 - 10)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The self-reported level of the musculoskeletal pain/discomfort during active supplement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Omega 7 (plasma)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification of the plasma palmitolenic acid (major omega 7 fatty acid) level during the active supplementation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IL-6 (plasma)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification of the plasma IL-6 level during the active supplementation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TNFalpha (plasma)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification of the plasma TNFalpha level during the active supplementation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Musculoskeletal Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>omega 7 - placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receiving the active first then switch to the placebo after three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo - omega 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receiving the placebo first then switch to the active after three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>omega 7</intervention_name>
    <description>Three weeks omega 7 fatty acid nutritional supplement, approximately 900 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>omega 7 - placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo - omega 7</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Three weeks placebo fatty acids approximately 900 mg/day which does not contain omega 7</description>
    <arm_group_label>omega 7 - placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo - omega 7</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: (any of the below)

          -  baseline CRP 1.0 mg/L or higher

          -  &gt; 3 months (chronic) musculoskeletal pain/discomfort, which the participant is able to
             monitor during the course of trial (6 weeks)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking narcotic or opioid pain medication

          -  Unable to monitor NSAID or OTC pain medication quantity

          -  Unable to visit Kenmore Washington Clinical Research Center for three times

          -  Objection from his/her primary care doctor

          -  Employee or family member of Barlines Organics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Masa Sasagawa, ND, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bastyr University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bastyr University Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kenmore</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98028</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Musculoskeletal Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

