<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03662425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KLMH2018K02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03662425</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>the Effects of Oxytocin on Negative Symptoms and Cognitive Tasks in Schizophrenia and it's Possible Mechanisms.</brief_title>
  <official_title>the Effects of Oxytocin on Negative Symptoms of Schizophrenia and Its Behavioral and Neurobiological Mechanisms</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Mental Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chinese Academy of Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Mental Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was to investigate the effects of oxytocin on negative symptoms and
      cognitive task performance in schizophrenia. We conducted a randomized, placebo-controlled
      trial testing the effects of twice daily intranasal oxytocin treatment for 14 days on
      psychotic symptoms and social cognition in patients with schizophrenia. We hypothesize that
      PANSS scores will decline significantly and several social cognition measures will improved
      significantly or nearly significantly in oxytocin but not placebo recipients. We will collect
      blood samples and MRI data of patients to explore the mechanism of oxytocin . we will also
      recruit some age- and Intelligence quotient-matched control subjects, give them a single dose
      of oxytocin to compare the effects of oxytocin in patients and health subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Social impairment is a primary cause of disability in schizophrenia, responds poorly to
      current antipsychotic medications and is related to deficits in social cognitive abilities,
      which include Theory of Mind, emotion recognition and attributional style. Oxytocin (OT) has
      many pro-social effects in animals and antipsychotic-like efficacy in preclinical tests. In
      this study, We conducted a randomized, placebo-controlled trial testing the effects of twice
      daily intranasal oxytocin treatment for 14 days on psychotic symptoms and social cognition in
      patients with schizophrenia. We will recruit 52 patients, Screening of subjects included a
      review of psychiatric and medical history, physical examination, and blood for standard
      laboratory tests, baseline social cognition measures were obtained followed by psychiatric
      ratings. Daily intranasal treatments were initiated after baseline assessments. Social
      cognition measures and psychiatric ratings were repeated beginning 50 min after the morning
      dose of study medication on treatment day 14. psychiatric ratings include The Positive and
      Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) and The Clinical Assessment Interview for Negative Symptoms
      (CAINS). The social cognition instruments are some social scales such as Toronto Alexithymia
      Scale ,and some computer tests such as Reinforcement Learning Task. We will collect blood
      samples and MRI data of patients to explore the mechanism of oxytocin. To compare the effects
      of oxytocin on social behaviors in patients with schizophrenia and in health controls , we
      will also recruit some age- and IQ-matched control subjects. We will give them a single dose
      of oxytocin , Behavioral tasks will begin 45 minutes after substance administration
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>a 30-items, 7-point rating scale; the 7 rating points represent increasing levels of psychopathology: 1= absent, 2= minimal, 3= mild, 4 = moderate, 5= moderate-severe, 6= severe, 7= extreme; of the 16 items, 7 were chosen to constitute Positive Scale, 7 items for Negative Scale and the remaining 16 items for a General Psychopathology Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>the end of second week</time_frame>
    <description>a 30-items, 7-point rating scale; the 7 rating points represent increasing levels of</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Clinical Assessment Interview for Negative Symptoms (CAINS)</measure>
    <time_frame>the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>including CAINS and CAINS self-reported checklists</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Clinical Assessment Interview for Negative Symptoms (CAINS)</measure>
    <time_frame>the end of second week</time_frame>
    <description>including CAINS and CAINS self-reported checklists</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reinforcement Learning Task</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The learning task was administered via commercially available software and was run on a laptop computer . Participants were presented with 4 pairs of landscape items, 1 pair at a time.Two pairs involved potential gain; if the correct item was selected, participants saw an image of a nickel coupled with the word &quot;Win!,&quot; whereas if the incorrect item was selected, they saw &quot;Not a winner, Try again!&quot; Two other pairs involved learning to avoid losses; in these pairs, selection of the correct response received the feedback &quot;Keep your money!,&quot; whereas selection of the incorrect item resulted in the feedback &quot;Lose!&quot;Following training, the transfer test phase was presented.In these 64 trials, the original 4 training pairs were each presented 4 times, and the 24 novel pairings were each presented twice.Participants were instructed to pick the item in the pair that they thought was &quot;best&quot; based on their earlier learning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Temporal Experience of Pleasure Scale (TEPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and two weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interpersonal Reactivity Index (IRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and two weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toronto Alexithymia Scale (TAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and two weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>emotion recognition task</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>a computer test in which subjects should indicate which word best describes the emotion in the face presented on the screen.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>yoni task</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and two weeks</time_frame>
    <description>a computer test measuring theory of mind</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>schizophrenia with oxytocin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>schizophrenia with Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy controls with oxytocin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy controls with Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxytocin</intervention_name>
    <description>It's a two-week treatment trial.Subjects self-administer intranasal study drug twice daily; before breakfast and before dinner. Each dose consists of six 0.1 ml insufflations (alternating between the left and right nostril) of OT spray containing approximately 24 international units of OT</description>
    <arm_group_label>schizophrenia with oxytocin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>It's a two-week treatment trial. Subjects self-administer intranasal study drug twice daily; before breakfast and before dinner. Each dose consists of six 0.1 ml insufflations (alternating between the left and right nostril) of saline spray containing approximately 24 international units of saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>schizophrenia with Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxytocin</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects self-administer a single dose of oxytocin ,it consists of six 0.1 ml insufflations (alternating between the left and right nostril) of OT spray containing approximately 24 international units of oxytocin</description>
    <arm_group_label>healthy controls with oxytocin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects self-administer a single dose of saline ,it consists of six 0.1 ml insufflations (alternating between the left and right nostril) of saline spray containing approximately 24 international units of saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>healthy controls with Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The diagnosis of schizophrenia according to DSM-IV

          -  patients at an age between 18～55 years old of Han nationality

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  other psychiatric diagnoses

          -  Suffering from serious physical disease and can not accept the treatment

          -  Patients to be diagnosed according to DSM-IV for substance abused, development delayed

          -  Inability to sign informed consent because of capacity due due to severe mental
             illness, significant psychomotor agitation or slowness test completion

          -  IQ&lt;70

          -  claustrophobic

          -  metal implantation in vivo
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhenghui YI, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>86-021-52219023</phone>
    <email>yizhenghui1971@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai Mental Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200030</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhenghui Yi, Ph.D</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>negative symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxytocin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxytocin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

