<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03662555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Stmarys</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03662555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation Combined With Blood Flow Restriction on Muscular and Cardiovascular Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation Combined With Varying Degrees of Blood Flow Restriction on Muscular and Cardiovascular Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Mary's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Mary's University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) has recently been combined with blood flow
      restriction (BFR) in controlled trials and has shown increased muscular strength and size
      compared with NMES and BFR on their own. However, none have used BFR pressures previously
      recommended. The first study of my Ph.D. found 40% and 80% BFR pressures to induce acute
      fatigue and muscle swelling. However, 80% caused higher ratings of pain and perceived
      exertion. The present study will determine whether NMES combined with either 40% or 80% BFR
      causes greater structural muscular adaptations and is perceptually easier after 6 weeks of
      training.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Laboratory testing will take place on 28 separate occasions, 2 familiarisation, 8 testing and
      18 intervention sessions. The first session (FAM 1) will serve as a familiarisation trial to
      the NMES protocol, BFR stimulus and strength testing. It will be conducted 10-14 days prior
      to the intervention period. The second session (FAM 2) will serve as a second familiarisation
      trial to the NMES protocol, BFR stimulus and strength testing. This session will take place 7
      days prior to the beginning of the intervention period and will serve as a standardised
      control period prior to the main testing. The third session (PRE) will take place 1 day prior
      the start of the intervention period and all future sessions will consist of strength, muscle
      and cardiovascular function outcome measures. The fourth session (MID) will take place the
      morning following 3 weeks of training. The fifth session (POST1) will take place 48 hours
      following 6 weeks of training. There will also be post testing sessions after three days
      (POST2), one week (POST3) and two weeks post intervention (POST4) to assess detraining.
      Participants will be provided with protein supplementation after every training session. All
      strength, muscle and hemodynamic measurements will be conducted at St Marys University by
      Paul Head. Supplements should be avoided for 72 hours prior to experimental measures and
      throughout the intervention period. All repeated measures will be performed at a similar time
      of day (± 1 h).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In a multi-arm parallel randomised controlled trial design. The randomisation scheme will be generated via online software (http://www.randomization.com). Participants will be recruited to 6 weeks of training, 3 sessions a week and randomised to one of three groups.
Group 1, participants will undergo NMES and BFR (80% pressure) applied to the quadriceps for 25 min.
Group 2, participants will undergo NMES and BFR (40% pressure) applied to the quadriceps for 25 min.
Group 3, participants will undergo NMES alone (Control) applied to the quadriceps for 25 min.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quadriceps volume and muscle architecture (3D Ultrasound)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle volume of the vastus lateralis and skeletal muscle architecture will be assessed by ultrasound technique (Telemed LogicScan 128 EXT-1Z). Measurement of fascicle length and pennation angle will be acquired at mid-belly, in the mid-sagittal plane.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee extension isometric, eccentric, concentric and endurance strength (Cybex)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal isometric, eccentric and concentric strength of the quadricep muscles will be measured using the same isokinetic dynamometer to assess peak force measurements (Cybex). This digital strain gauge dynamometer displays the force measurement to the nearest 0.1 N. Prior to each measurement, the instrument will be calibrated per the manufacturer's instructions and specifications. The individuals will be seated in a comfortable position with the backrest angled at 100˚ to the seat without shoes or orthotic device on. Maximal voluntary isometric contraction (MVIC) for the quadriceps will tested at 60 degrees from full extension using a goniometer (19-21), and the shin pad positioned 2 cm above the lateral malleolus of the fibula attached to a load cell (22).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Voluntary activation</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The percent of voluntary activation (%VA) will be estimated using the twitch interpolation protocol (25). Doublet stimuli were administered to the femoral nerve approximately 200-300 ms into the MVC. A second doublet will be applied approximately 3 s after the cessation of the MVC at rest (25). The stimuli were rectangular pulses of 200 ls duration and will be delivered using a high-voltage (maximal voltage = 400 V) constant-current stimulator (Digitimer DS7AH, Herthfordshire, UK).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Near-infrared spectroscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Following 10 min of supine rest a near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) optode (Portamon, Artinis medical systems) was placed on the vastus lateralis and secured with an elastic bandage (Tiger Tear, Hampshire, United Kingdom) to prevent movement and covered with an optically dense black material to minimize the intrusion of extraneous light. This protocol was used to characterize the recovery of m˙VO2 and has been shown to be reliable by our group and others (28-30). NIRS will be assessed PRE, MID and POST1, 2, 3 and 4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A blood pressure cuff (Omron) will be placed around the subject's dominant arm and tested after 5 mins of supine rest and then immediately post each intervention session and at POST testing. To assess acute changes in systolic and diastolic blood pressure. Two readings will be taken and if they have a difference of &gt;5 a third reading will be taken and the average recorded (27).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Weakness</condition>
  <condition>Muscle Atrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NMES and BFR (80%)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1, participants will undergo NMES and BFR (80% pressure) applied to the quadriceps for 25 min.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NMES and BFR (40%)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2, participants will undergo NMES and BFR (40% pressure) applied to the quadriceps for 25 min.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NMES alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 3, participants will undergo NMES applied to the quadriceps for 25 min.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuromuscular electrical stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Neuromuscular electrical simulation (NMES) Two self-adhesive electrodes (2 mm thick) will be placed over the rectus femoris, vastus medialis and vastus lateralis muscles. The electrodes will be placed on the motor points of each muscle. The stimulator discharges biphasic rectangular pulses. The stimulation frequency and duty cycle will be 50 Hz and 5 s of stimulation followed by a 5 s pause for each rep. The intensity of electrical flow will be at each subject's maximum that they can tolerate. The stimulation will be for 5 x 5 min sets with 1 min rest between sets.
Blood flow restriction
A handheld Doppler probe (Hi-Dop) will detect their auscultatory and visual pulse using the doppler's screen. The cuff will be inflated initially up to their systolic blood pressure and then incrementally by 10 mmHg until no auscultatory or visual pulse is detected. A percentage of 40% or 80% of each subject's LOP will then be used during the BFR conditions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NMES alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>NMES and BFR (40%)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>NMES and BFR (80%)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blood flow restriction</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adults aged between 18 and 45 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of lower extremity surgery, traumatic injuries to the ankle, knee, hip, pelvis
             and lower back

          -  Current musculoskeletal condition

          -  High blood pressure

          -  Cardiovascular pathology
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Mary's University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Head</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD candidate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Weakness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

