<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03660319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 16-1190</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03660319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of EMT on Anxiety Levels and Perception of Waiting Time in the Radiation Oncology Waiting Room</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of EMT on Anxiety Levels and Perception of Waiting Time in the Radiation Oncology Waiting Room</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be investigating the effects of environmental music therapy (EMT) on patient
      and caregiver anxiety levels and perceptions of waiting time for patients undergoing
      radiation therapy. Environmental music therapy is live music offered by a music therapist
      with the intention of modifying patients' and caregivers' perception of the environment
      itself and in so doing provide an experience of enhanced comfort and relaxation. One hundred
      and sixty patients and their caregivers, when present, who are diagnosed with Cancer,
      including head &amp; neck, breast, prostate, lymphoma, gastro-intestinal, and skin cancers, as
      well as other cancers will be identified and referred by Mount Sinai Downtown radiation
      oncology attending doctors prior to their arrival in the waiting room of the Radiation
      Oncology Suite. All Cancer subjects will be considered regardless of gender or racial/ethnic
      background, and health status with the exception of those less than 18 years of age. Only
      patients who are fluent in English will be eligible to enroll in the study. Patients will
      randomly be assigned to the control or environmental music group. The patients in the control
      group will be able to receive music therapy during radiation therapy, even though they will
      not have music therapy during their waiting room time, as is the focus of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

      Will EMT affectively reduce state anxiety and time distortion in patients receiving radiation
      therapy for cancer and in their personal caregivers during their time in the radiation
      oncology department waiting room? The purpose of this study is to (a) rate the patients level
      of anxiety and discomfort prior to radiation therapy as experienced in the waiting area, (b)
      determine if the following music psychotherapy protocol moderates baseline anxiety related to
      their treatment experience and (c) evaluate how an environmental music therapy protocol
      affects the subjects' perception of the amount of they have waited before treatment measured
      against the actual amount of time they have waited.

      Hypothesis:

      EMT will reduce state anxiety and time distortion for cancer patients and their personal
      caregivers in the radiation oncology waiting room.

      The current study will focus on effects of music therapy on 160 patients and their
      caregivers, who are randomly assigned to two groups. All patients with cancer who receive
      radiation and who are waiting for radiation therapy in the waiting room are eligible, with
      the exception of those patients who are not fluent in English. Enrolled participants will
      complete the abridged State Trait Anxiety Inventory and the Wong-Baker faces scale pre and
      post EMT or no EMT. The music therapist will provide prescribed live patient-preferred music
      in conjunction with the patients' culture, past medical history, past trauma, and assessment
      of psychological stressors to be observed and expressed prior to radiation, as they wait in
      the waiting room. The live music used will provide an anchor and suggest inter-relationship
      possibilities amongst patients and their caregivers during the EMT sessions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 20, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 26, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 26, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants randomized into two groups: Music Therapy Intervention (Environmental Music Therapy) and Control arm with no Music Therapy.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wong-Baker Faces Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety measured by Wong-Baker Faces Scale during their waiting which has 6 faces with the first face scored 0 (no anxiety) to the last face scored 10 (high anxiety), total scale from 0-10, higher score indicating more anxiety</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Short-Form STAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety measured by Short-Form STAI during their waiting. Short-Form STAI is a 6-item instrument. To calculate the total STAI score (range 20 - 80):
reverse scoring of the positive items (calm, relaxed, content) so 1=4, 2=3, 3=2 and 4=1;
sum all six scores;
multiply total score by 20/6; with higher score indicating more anxiety</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Waiting Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Perception of waiting time questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Environmental Music Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Music Therapy Intervention (EMT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control - No Environmental Music Therapy. Does not experience Environmental Music Therapy during wait time in radiation oncology waiting room.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Environmental Music Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Experiencing Environmental Music Therapy during wait time in radiation oncology waiting room.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Environmental Music Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Music Therapy Intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  Receiving treatment for cancer in the radiation oncology department

          -  Personal caregivers of patients receiving treatment for care in the radiation oncology
             department

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults who are not fluent in English

          -  Adults unable to consent

          -  Individuals who are not yet adults (e.g. infants, children, teenagers)

          -  Wards of the State (e.g. foster children)

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Rossetti, MMT</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joanne Loewy, DA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Downtown Union Square</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.musicandmedicine.org</url>
    <description>More information</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>music therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>EMT</keyword>
  <keyword>environmental music therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>radiation oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>waiting room</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

