<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03667638</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>#1055-2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03667638</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Influence of Platelet Concentrates on Wound Healing</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Influence of Autologous Platelet Concentrates on Human Keratinocyte Proliferation in Vitro and Wound Healing in Vivo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hannover Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hannover Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic soft tissues defects can extend into the fat layer or even deeper and can cause
      functional disadvantages. Split-thickness skin grafts (STSGs) used to cover these wounds have
      varying success rates. To improve wound healing in chronic wounds the authors have studied
      the application of autologous platelet concentrates in a human keratinocyte culture model in
      vitro and in a combination with surgical procedures in vivo as second line therapy in
      patients with initially failed wound closure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For in vitro testing on keratinocytes a platelet-mediator concentrate (PMC) was processed
      with a commercially available bed-side system (ATR®, Curasan, Germany). In a clinical study
      soft tissue defects (n=5) were treated using a combination of surgical debridement and
      autologous platelet rich plasma (PRP). Time of healing as determined by epithelization as
      well as Laser Doppler Imaging to visualize blood flow were analyzed. Additionally, changes in
      &quot;ease of surgical wound closure&quot; were determined. Finally, the quality of life of patients
      was assessed using a validated questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound Closure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Area of wound closure in % compared to initial size</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood flow measured in wound margins and wound bed compared to regular skin measured using Laser Doppler Imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of patients' life measured using Wound-QoL® Questionnaire before and after Intervention. Seventeen items are included in the Wound-QoL, which could be attributed to three subscales on everyday life, body, and psyche. The paper presents the overall score. A higher value correlates with more wound related burden, meaning a lower value indicates higher qulitiy of life.
More information: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24899053</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ease of surgical wound closure</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated ease of surgical wound closure. The patients`wound was discussed by at least two surgeons to obtain agreement on a 14- point &quot;Ease of Closure&quot; scale. This was done on day 0 as well as day 21. The scale ranged from a score of 0, meaning the wound was closed or so small as to require no closure technique, to a score of 13, meaning that it was not possible to close the wound with known reconstructive surgical techniques. A higher value therefore correlates with more complex surgery.
More information: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10231510</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Platelet-Rich Plasma</condition>
  <condition>Wound Healing Delayed</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PRP Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PRP injection into wound border</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Platelet-Rich Plasma</intervention_name>
    <description>Adding PRP to wound bed during surgical debridement</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRP Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PRP, PMC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  exposed tendons, ligaments or bone for &gt;3 weeks

          -  no healing tendency

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  sepsis

          -  intensive care treatment

          -  continuous smoking

          -  pregnancy or breast feeding women

          -  participants of other studies.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Vogt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical School Hannover</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical School Hannover</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <state>Niedersachsen</state>
        <zip>30625</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Danielsen P, Jørgensen B, Karlsmark T, Jorgensen LN, Agren MS. Effect of topical autologous platelet-rich fibrin versus no intervention on epithelialization of donor sites and meshed split-thickness skin autografts: a randomized clinical trial. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2008 Nov;122(5):1431-40. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e318188202c.</citation>
    <PMID>18971727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gould L, Abadir P, Brem H, Carter M, Conner-Kerr T, Davidson J, DiPietro L, Falanga V, Fife C, Gardner S, Grice E, Harmon J, Hazzard WR, High KP, Houghton P, Jacobson N, Kirsner RS, Kovacs EJ, Margolis D, McFarland Horne F, Reed MJ, Sullivan DH, Thom S, Tomic-Canic M, Walston J, Whitney JA, Williams J, Zieman S, Schmader K. Chronic wound repair and healing in older adults: current status and future research. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2015 Mar;63(3):427-38. doi: 10.1111/jgs.13332. Epub 2015 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25753048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asadi M, Alamdari DH, Rahimi HR, Aliakbarian M, Jangjoo A, Abdollahi A, Bahar MM, Azadmand A, Forghani N, Sadegh MN, Khayamy ME, Seifalian A. Treatment of life-threatening wounds with a combination of allogenic platelet-rich plasma, fibrin glue and collagen matrix, and a literature review. Exp Ther Med. 2014 Aug;8(2):423-429. Epub 2014 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25009595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Behm B, Babilas P, Landthaler M, Schreml S. Cytokines, chemokines and growth factors in wound healing. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2012 Jul;26(7):812-20. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-3083.2011.04415.x. Epub 2011 Dec 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22211801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alsousou J, Thompson M, Hulley P, Noble A, Willett K. The biology of platelet-rich plasma and its application in trauma and orthopaedic surgery: a review of the literature. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2009 Aug;91(8):987-96. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.91B8.22546. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19651823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Werner S, Grose R. Regulation of wound healing by growth factors and cytokines. Physiol Rev. 2003 Jul;83(3):835-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12843410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter CA, Jolly DG, Worden CE Sr, Hendren DG, Kane CJ. Platelet-rich plasma gel promotes differentiation and regeneration during equine wound healing. Exp Mol Pathol. 2003 Jun;74(3):244-55.</citation>
    <PMID>12782011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Achora S, Muliira JK, Thanka AN. Strategies to promote healing of split thickness skin grafts: an integrative review. J Wound Ostomy Continence Nurs. 2014 Jul-Aug;41(4):335-9; quiz E1-2. doi: 10.1097/WON.0000000000000035. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24988511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Appel TR, Pötzsch B, Müller J, von Lindern JJ, Bergé SJ, Reich RH. Comparison of three different preparations of platelet concentrates for growth factor enrichment. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2002 Oct;13(5):522-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12453130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohn CS, Lockhart E. Autologous platelet-rich plasma: evidence for clinical use. Curr Opin Hematol. 2015 Nov;22(6):527-32. doi: 10.1097/MOH.0000000000000183. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26390166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berg L, Meyer S, Ipaktchi R, Vogt PM, Müller A, de Zwaan M. [Psychosocial Distress at Different Time Intervals after Burn Injury]. Psychother Psychosom Med Psychol. 2017 Jun;67(6):231-239. doi: 10.1055/s-0042-111006. Epub 2016 Sep 29. German.</citation>
    <PMID>27685256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>House SL. Psychological distress and its impact on wound healing: an integrative review. J Wound Ostomy Continence Nurs. 2015 Jan-Feb;42(1):38-41. doi: 10.1097/WON.0000000000000080. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25549307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blome C, Baade K, Debus ES, Price P, Augustin M. The &quot;Wound-QoL&quot;: a short questionnaire measuring quality of life in patients with chronic wounds based on three established disease-specific instruments. Wound Repair Regen. 2014 Jul-Aug;22(4):504-14. doi: 10.1111/wrr.12193.</citation>
    <PMID>24899053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weibrich G, Kleis WK. Curasan PRP kit vs. PCCS PRP system. Collection efficiency and platelet counts of two different methods for the preparation of platelet-rich plasma. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2002 Aug;13(4):437-43.</citation>
    <PMID>12175382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weibrich G, Kleis WK, Hafner G, Hitzler WE, Wagner W. Comparison of platelet, leukocyte, and growth factor levels in point-of-care platelet-enriched plasma, prepared using a modified Curasan kit, with preparations received from a local blood bank. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2003 Jun;14(3):357-62.</citation>
    <PMID>12755786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okuda K, Kawase T, Momose M, Murata M, Saito Y, Suzuki H, Wolff LF, Yoshie H. Platelet-rich plasma contains high levels of platelet-derived growth factor and transforming growth factor-beta and modulates the proliferation of periodontally related cells in vitro. J Periodontol. 2003 Jun;74(6):849-57.</citation>
    <PMID>12886996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kawase T. Platelet-rich plasma and its derivatives as promising bioactive materials for regenerative medicine: basic principles and concepts underlying recent advances. Odontology. 2015 May;103(2):126-35. doi: 10.1007/s10266-015-0209-2. Epub 2015 Jun 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26040505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amable PR, Carias RB, Teixeira MV, da Cruz Pacheco I, Corrêa do Amaral RJ, Granjeiro JM, Borojevic R. Platelet-rich plasma preparation for regenerative medicine: optimization and quantification of cytokines and growth factors. Stem Cell Res Ther. 2013 Jun 7;4(3):67. doi: 10.1186/scrt218.</citation>
    <PMID>23759113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nurden AT, Nurden P, Sanchez M, Andia I, Anitua E. Platelets and wound healing. Front Biosci. 2008 May 1;13:3532-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18508453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrientos S, Stojadinovic O, Golinko MS, Brem H, Tomic-Canic M. Growth factors and cytokines in wound healing. Wound Repair Regen. 2008 Sep-Oct;16(5):585-601. doi: 10.1111/j.1524-475X.2008.00410.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19128254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho JW, Kim SA, Lee KS. Platelet-rich plasma induces increased expression of G1 cell cycle regulators, type I collagen, and matrix metalloproteinase-1 in human skin fibroblasts. Int J Mol Med. 2012 Jan;29(1):32-6. doi: 10.3892/ijmm.2011.803. Epub 2011 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21964487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carmeliet P, Jain RK. Molecular mechanisms and clinical applications of angiogenesis. Nature. 2011 May 19;473(7347):298-307. doi: 10.1038/nature10144. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21593862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mammoto T, Jiang A, Jiang E, Mammoto A. Platelet rich plasma extract promotes angiogenesis through the angiopoietin1-Tie2 pathway. Microvasc Res. 2013 Sep;89:15-24. doi: 10.1016/j.mvr.2013.04.008. Epub 2013 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23660186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnouf T, Tseng YH, Kuo YP, Su CY. Solvent/detergent treatment of platelet concentrates enhances the release of growth factors. Transfusion. 2008 Jun;48(6):1090-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1537-2995.2008.01691.x. Epub 2008 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>18373502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw TJ, Martin P. Wound repair at a glance. J Cell Sci. 2009 Sep 15;122(Pt 18):3209-13. doi: 10.1242/jcs.031187. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19726630</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eppley BL, Woodell JE, Higgins J. Platelet quantification and growth factor analysis from platelet-rich plasma: implications for wound healing. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2004 Nov;114(6):1502-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15509939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaltalioglu K, Coskun-Cevher S. A bioactive molecule in a complex wound healing process: platelet-derived growth factor. Int J Dermatol. 2015 Aug;54(8):972-7. doi: 10.1111/ijd.12731. Epub 2014 Oct 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25312059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anitua E, Aguirre JJ, Algorta J, Ayerdi E, Cabezas AI, Orive G, Andia I. Effectiveness of autologous preparation rich in growth factors for the treatment of chronic cutaneous ulcers. J Biomed Mater Res B Appl Biomater. 2008 Feb;84(2):415-21.</citation>
    <PMID>17595032</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinez-Zapata MJ, Martí-Carvajal AJ, Solà I, Expósito JA, Bolíbar I, Rodríguez L, Garcia J. Autologous platelet-rich plasma for treating chronic wounds. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Oct 17;10:CD006899. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006899.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016;(5):CD006899.</citation>
    <PMID>23076929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SA, Ryu HW, Lee KS, Cho JW. Application of platelet-rich plasma accelerates the wound healing process in acute and chronic ulcers through rapid migration and upregulation of cyclin A and CDK4 in HaCaT cells. Mol Med Rep. 2013 Feb;7(2):476-80. doi: 10.3892/mmr.2012.1230. Epub 2012 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23242428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reinke JM, Sorg H. Wound repair and regeneration. Eur Surg Res. 2012;49(1):35-43. doi: 10.1159/000339613. Epub 2012 Jul 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22797712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzucco L, Borzini P, Gope R. Platelet-derived factors involved in tissue repair-from signal to function. Transfus Med Rev. 2010 Jul;24(3):218-34. doi: 10.1016/j.tmrv.2010.03.004. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20656189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robson MC, Maggi SP, Smith PD, Wassermann RJ, Mosiello GC, Hill DP, Cooper DM. Original articles: ease of wound closure as an endpoint of treatment efficacy. Wound Repair Regen. 1999 Mar-Apr;7(2):90-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10231510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Limbourg A, Korff T, Napp LC, Schaper W, Drexler H, Limbourg FP. Evaluation of postnatal arteriogenesis and angiogenesis in a mouse model of hind-limb ischemia. Nat Protoc. 2009;4(12):1737-46. doi: 10.1038/nprot.2009.185. Epub 2009 Nov 5.</citation>
    <PMID>19893509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khatib M, Jabir S, Fitzgerald O'Connor E, Philp B. A systematic review of the evolution of laser Doppler techniques in burn depth assessment. Plast Surg Int. 2014;2014:621792. doi: 10.1155/2014/621792. Epub 2014 Aug 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25180087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul DW, Ghassemi P, Ramella-Roman JC, Prindeze NJ, Moffatt LT, Alkhalil A, Shupp JW. Noninvasive imaging technologies for cutaneous wound assessment: A review. Wound Repair Regen. 2015 Mar-Apr;23(2):149-62. doi: 10.1111/wrr.12262. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25832563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xian LJ, Chowdhury SR, Bin Saim A, Idrus RB. Concentration-dependent effect of platelet-rich plasma on keratinocyte and fibroblast wound healing. Cytotherapy. 2015 Mar;17(3):293-300. doi: 10.1016/j.jcyt.2014.10.005. Epub 2014 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25456581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilliver SC, Ashworth JJ, Ashcroft GS. The hormonal regulation of cutaneous wound healing. Clin Dermatol. 2007 Jan-Feb;25(1):56-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17276202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hannover Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paulmann, Anastasia</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Platelet-Rich Plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>Laser Doppler Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth Factors</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound Healing</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic wound healing disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Wound quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

