<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03663088</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>StJustineH_CFortin</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03663088</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Global Postural Re-education in Idiopathic Scoliosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study for a Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial on the Effect of Global Postural Re-education in the Treatment of Idiopathic Scoliosis: a Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Justine's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Justine's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In North America, children and adolescents with idiopathic scoliosis (IS) are rarely referred
      for a rehabilitation program whereas the European guidelines stated that scientific evidences
      concerning scoliosis specific physiotherapy exercises were strong enough to recommend the use
      of these exercises at an early stage. The objectives of this pilot study is to assess
      feasibility of conducting a larger randomized control trial (RCT) on the effect of global
      postural re-education (GPR) on scoliosis progression (Cobb angle) and posture, back pain and
      participation and to assess the equivalence of two groups of GPR interventions. A convenience
      sample of 60 adolescents with IS (Cobb angle 15º-50º, Risser sign ≤3) will be recruited at
      CHU Sainte-Justine. Participants will be randomly allocated to GPR-A (individual sessions
      once a week) or GPR-B (individual sessions once per two weeks alternately with class
      exercises once per two weeks) for 6 months. After 6 months, groups will be interchanged for
      another 6 months. Feasibility outcomes will be recruitment rate, consent rate, completion
      rate and adherence to treatment at 12 months. The primary outcome of the effect of GPR will
      be the Cobb angle. Secondary outcomes will be: posture, back pain and participation at 6 and
      12 months. Statistical analyses: For feasibility, percentage of eligible patients recruited,
      percentage of recruited patients who completed the trial and adherence to treatment will be
      calculated. For the preliminary effects of GPR, linear mixed-models will be used to assess
      differences in groups' changes from baseline, to 6 and 12-month while adjusting for
      covariates (age, Risser, adherence). Separate analyses will be conducted for each outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cobb angle</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the frontal radiologic measure of scoliosis: a decrease in Cobb angle by more than 5 degrees indicate improvement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: shoulder elevation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed between a line drawn between the left and right coracoid process markers, and the horizontal: a decrease of this angle indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: right waist angle</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by lines drawn from the upper end of the waist to the center of the waist, and from the cent Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by lines drawn from the upper end of the waist to the center of the waist, and from the center of the waist to the lower end of the waist on the right side: more symmetry with the left side indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: left waist angle</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by lines drawn from the upper end of the waist to the center of the waist, and from the cent Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by lines drawn from the upper end of the waist to the center of the waist, and from the center of the waist to the lower end of the waist on the left side: more symmetry with the right side indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: thoracic scoliosis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by lines drawn from the upper end-vertebra to the apex of the thoracic scoliosis curve and from the apex to the lower end-vertebra of the curve: decrease of this angle indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: lumbar scoliosis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by lines drawn from the upper end-vertebra to the apex of the thoracolumbar or lumbar scoliosis curve, and from the apex to the lower end-vertebra of the curve: decrease of this angle indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: frontal trunk list</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The horizontal distance between C7 and a vertical line drawn from S1: decrease of this measure in millimeter indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: frontal pelvic tilt</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed between the line joining the two anterior superior iliac spine (ASIS) and the horizontal: decrease of this angle indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: right sagittal pelvic tilt</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed between the horizontal and the line joining the posterior superior iliac spine (PSIS) and ASIS on the right side: an angle between 20 and 30 degrees indicate a normal value and a better symmetry between right and left side indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: left sagittal pelvic tilt</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed between the horizontal and the line joining the PSIS and ASIS on the left side: an angle between 20 and 30 degrees indicate a normal value and a better symmetry between right and left side indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posture: scapula asymmetry</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Photographic Postural Assessment Tool: The angle formed by a line drawn from the left and right inferior angles of the scapula and the horizontal: decrease of this angle indicate improvement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in back pain</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the intensity (score) of back pain on the Numeric Pain Rating Scale score (0 no pain to 10 very important pain), lower value indicate improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in score of The youth version of the Child &amp; Adolescent Scale of Participation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in score of The youth version of the Child &amp; Adolescent Scale of Participation (CASP): The CASP questionnaire has 20 items x 4 levels from 1 (unable to participate) to 4 (age expected/full participation) with a maximum of 80 points. Higher value indicate improvement (better participation).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of eligible patients recruited: 70% of participants recruited indicate good recruitment rate</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Completion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of recruited participants who completed the trial: 75% of completion indicate good completion rate</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence (compliance) with GPR treatment in terms of collaboration, presence and implication in home exercises</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence with GPR treatment will be measured by the physiotherapists using the validated 3-item Sport Injury Rehabilitation Adherence Scale (SIRAS, were total score varies from 3 (low adherence) to 15 (high adherence)). We will also compute presence/absence to therapy and we will use a patient/parent logbook for home exercises. Good adherence (compliance) to treatment will be achieved if a participant has a score of at least 12 out of 15 on the SIRAS 80 % of the treatment sessions, is present to therapy 80% of the sessions and completes home exercises 80% of the time.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Idiopathic Scoliosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GPR-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 6-months supervised GPR-A group will receive a 1-hour-long individual session once a week plus a home program (1 or 2 exercises, 2 times a week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GPR-B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 6-months supervised GPR-B group will receive a 1-hour long individual session once per two weeks alternately with a 1-hour-long class of exercises once per two weeks plus a home program (1 or 2 exercises, 2 times a week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GPR-A</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Global postural re-education physiotherapy scoliosis specific exercises</description>
    <arm_group_label>GPR-A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GPR-B</intervention_name>
    <description>Experimental Global postural re-education physiotherapy scoliosis specific exercises combining individual and class exercises</description>
    <arm_group_label>GPR-B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  aged between 8 and 16 years old,

          -  Cobb angle between 15º and 50º,

          -  a Risser sign ≤3 (skeletal growth incomplete),

          -  having recent x-rays (4-6 weeks),

          -  ability to travel weekly to attend GPR interventions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients who are planning surgery or have had surgery,

          -  previous regular physiotherapy or other conservative treatment (chiro, osteopathy),

          -  worn a brace for at least three months prior to GPR interventions,

          -  scheduled for clinic follow-up later than in 6±2 months,

          -  or to be discharged before 12 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carole Fortin, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Justine's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carole Fortin, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>5143741710</phone>
    <phone_ext>8136</phone_ext>
    <email>carole.fortin@umontreal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Sainte-Justine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carole Fortin, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>5143741710</phone>
      <phone_ext>8136</phone_ext>
      <email>carole.fortin@umontreal.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Justine's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carole Fortin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Global postural re-education</keyword>
  <keyword>Cobb angle</keyword>
  <keyword>Posture</keyword>
  <keyword>Back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Participation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Scoliosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

