<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03667144</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL59516.042.17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03667144</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Survival of Double Inlet Left Ventricle Patients Without Fontan Circulation</brief_title>
  <acronym>DILV-S</acronym>
  <official_title>Survival of Double Inlet Left Ventricle Patients Without Fontan Circulation: Intracardiac Anatomy and Hemodynamics, Functional Status and Quality of Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Groningen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Groningen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with univentricular hearts are currently palliated with the Fontan procedures. This
      results in an unphysiologic circulation with poor long-term survival. On the other hand there
      is a small, selected subgroup of patients with univentricular hearts of the double inlet left
      ventricle (DILV) type that survives up to old age without ever having undergone any Fontan
      procedures. Considering the relatively bleak data on long-term survival of DILV patients
      palliated with the Fontan procedure, it seems highly relevant to investigate and determine
      factors that allow a selection of unoperated patients to live to a comparatively high age
      without apparent major complaints. This might have an impact on how (and if, at all) certain
      univentricular patients are selected for operation in the future. For some, a different
      surgical procedure, or even therapeutic nihilism might be a more viable alternative.

      The investigators hypothesise that favourable intracardiac streaming plays a role in making
      these patients viable: certain intracardiac anatomical characteristics allow for favourable
      flow patterns.

      The primary objective of this study is to describe the intracardiac anatomy and hemodynamics
      of DILV patients without Fontan circulation using 4D MRI. Furthermore, the functional status
      and quality of life of these patients will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Patients with univentricular hearts are currently palliated with a sequence of
      operations known as the Fontan procedure. This results in an un-physiologic circulation with
      poor long-term survival. On the other hand there is a small, selected subgroup of patients
      with univentricular hearts of the double inlet left ventricle (DILV) type that survives up to
      old age without ever having undergone any Fontan procedure. Considering the relatively bleak
      data on long-term survival of DILV patients palliated with the Fontan procedure, it is highly
      relevant to investigate and determine factors that allow for a selection of unoperated
      patients to live to a comparatively high age without apparent major complaints. This might
      have an impact on how (and if, at all) certain univentricular patients will be selected for
      operation in the future. For some, a different surgical procedure, or even therapeutic
      nihilism might be a more viable alternative. The investigators hypothesize that favourable
      intracardiac streaming plays a role in making the unpalliated patients viable: certain
      intracardiac anatomical characteristics allow for favourable flow patterns, resulting in
      higher systemic oxygen saturations than expected by mixing pulmonary and systemic venous
      returns.

      Objective: The primary objective of this study is to describe the intracardiac anatomy and
      hemodynamics of DILV patients without Fontan circulation using 4D MRI. Furthermore, the
      functional status and quality of life of these patients will be assessed and compared to a
      matched cohort of Fontan patients.

      Study design: This will be an observational, cross-sectional study. The investigators aim to
      include all DILV patients without Fontan circulation known at the congenital heart disease
      referral centers in the Netherlands and Flanders. The Dutch patients will undergo one 4D MRI,
      a physical examination, cardiopulmonary exercise testing and have a blood sample taken at the
      University Medical Center Utrecht. The patients from the Flemish referral centers will
      undergo the same protocol at the University Medical Center Leuven. Furthermore, patients over
      the age of 18 will be asked to fill out a quality of life questionnaire.

      Study population: Included will be patients over the age of 12 with the diagnosis double
      inlet left ventricle, which have not undergone the Fontan trajectory. For the 4D MRI,
      patients with an MRI non-compatible pacemaker in situ will be excluded.

      Main study parameters/endpoints: This is primarily an explorative study aiming to describe
      the anatomy of unpalliated DILV hearts of patients without Fontan palliation. With 4D MRI,
      the hearts will be grouped according to the angular relationship of the two lines connecting
      the atrioventricular and the ventriculo-arterial valves. This angle can be divided into three
      categories: 1) parallel (i.e. 0°), 2) perpendicular (i.e. 90°) or 3) an in-between variant.
      Accordingly, flow patterns, ranging from linear to turbulent will be measured and correlated
      to the anatomical variants.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: The burden and risks associated with participation in this study are minimal.
      Patients need to visit the site of investigation only once, and the tests done at the visit
      (i.e. 4D MR imaging, exercise and pulmonary function testing and blood sample) are part of
      standard medical care and as such pose negligible risk on the patients. The quality of life
      survey is not part of standard medical care and might be confrontational on a psychological
      level. It is, however, a widely used and scientifically approved survey, which aims to keep
      this burden very low. Due to the extremely low prevalence of the condition to be studied, it
      is of great importance to include every single patient, including children under the age of
      18. Excluding children from this study would further decrease the sample size to a
      significantly smaller number, making it difficult to draw conclusions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Angle between atrioventricular and ventriculoarterial valves</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>This is primarily an explorative study aiming to describe the anatomy of unpalliated DILV hearts. With 4D MRI, the hearts will be grouped according to the angular relationship of the atrioventricular to the ventriculo-arterial valves. This angle can be divided into three categories: 1) parallel (i.e. 0°), 2) perpendicular (i.e. 90°) or 3) an in-between variant. Accordingly, flow patterns, ranging from linear to turbulent will be measured and correlated to the anatomical variants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>New York Heart Association Functional Classification</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>NYHA functional class I to IV</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak VO2</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>peak oxygen uptake (VO2index) during exercise as well as peak VO2 as percentage of predicted (VO2 pred)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral oxygen saturation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Oxygen saturation at rest, measured with oximetry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scores for Quality of life Adults</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life survey overall scores, and scores in the subcategories measured with the Short Form (SF)36 (For patients 18 and older). The SF-36 consists of eight scaled scores, which are the weighted sums of the questions in their section. Each scale is directly transformed into a 0-100 scale on the assumption that each question carries equal weight. The lower the score the more disability. The higher the score the less disability i.e., a score of zero is equivalent to maximum disability and a score of 100 is equivalent to no disability. The eight sections are:
vitality physical functioning bodily pain general health perceptions physical role functioning emotional role functioning social role functioning mental health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scores for Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life survey overall scores, and scores in the subcategories measured with PedsQL (for patients younger than 18). The 23-item PedsQL Generic Core Scales were designed to measure the core dimensions of health as delineated by the World Health Organization, as well as role (school) functioning. The 4 Multidimensional Scales are: Physical Functioning (8 items) Emotional Functioning (5 items), Social Functioning (5 items), School Functioning (5 items) The summary scores are: Total Scale Score (23 items), Physical Health Summary Score (8 items), Psychosocial Health Summary Score (15 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematocrit</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Creatinin</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>eGFR</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>high sensitive Troponin T</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NT-proBNP</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LDH</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ASAT</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ALAT</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alkaline phosphatase</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gamma-GT</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Galectin 3</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bilirubin</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>from venous blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demographics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>sex, age, weight, height</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Highest Level of Education</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Highest level of education as well as their current Profession and their current work Status will be asked of all participants on the Basis of a questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Current Medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to provide the names and the dosage of all medications they are currently using .</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Double Inlet Left Ventricle</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Venous blood samples for biomarker analysis
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Included will be patients over the age of 12 with the diagnosis double inlet left
        ventricle, which have not undergone the Fontan trajectory. For the 4D MRI, patients with an
        MRI non-compatible pacemaker in situ will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis double inlet left ventricle, established by echocardiograph or MRI

          -  Not undergone Fontan trajectory in the past

          -  Be of the age of 12 or older

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • previous (partial) cavopulmonary connection

        The following subjects will be excluded from the MRI part of the study, but will still be
        asked to participate in all the other parts:

        • MRI non-compatible pacemaker in situ
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tjark Ebels, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Center Groningen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sophie L Meyer, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>004917681033255</phone>
    <email>s.l.meyer@umcg.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frescura C, Thiene G. The new concept of univentricular heart. Front Pediatr. 2014 Jul 7;2:62. doi: 10.3389/fped.2014.00062. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25072035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook AC, Anderson RH. The anatomy of hearts with double inlet ventricle. Cardiol Young. 2006 Feb;16 Suppl 1:22-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16401359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franklin RC, Spiegelhalter DJ, Anderson RH, Macartney FJ, Rossi Filho RI, Douglas JM, Rigby ML, Deanfield JE. Double-inlet ventricle presenting in infancy. I. Survival without definitive repair. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 1991 May;101(5):767-76.</citation>
    <PMID>2023434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gersony WM. Fontan operation after 3 decades: what we have learned. Circulation. 2008 Jan 1;117(1):13-5. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.748566. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18172049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poterucha JT, Anavekar NS, Egbe AC, Julsrud PR, Connolly HM, Ammash NM, Warnes CA. Survival and outcomes of patients with unoperated single ventricle. Heart. 2016 Feb;102(3):216-22. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2015-308440. Epub 2015 Dec 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26701967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Macartney FJ, Partridge JB, Scott O, Deverall PB. Common or single ventricle. An angiocardiographic and hemodynamic study of 42 patients. Circulation. 1976 Mar;53(3):543-54.</citation>
    <PMID>1248087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolff D, van Melle JP, Bartelds B, Ridderbos FS, Eshuis G, van Stratum EBHJ, Recinos SJ, Willemse BWM, Hillege H, Willems TP, Ebels T, Berger RMF. Fontan Circulation over Time. Am J Cardiol. 2017 Aug 1;120(3):461-466. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2017.05.005. Epub 2017 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>28624095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolff D, van de Wiel HBM, de Muinck Keizer ME, van Melle JP, Pieper PG, Berger RMF, Ebels T, Weijmar Schultz WCM. Quality of life and sexual well-being in patients with a Fontan circulation: An explorative pilot study with a mixed method design. Congenit Heart Dis. 2018 Mar;13(2):319-326. doi: 10.1111/chd.12576. Epub 2018 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29532606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Groningen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sophie Meyer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. dr. Tjark Ebels</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Double inlet left ventricle without Fontan circulation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

