<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03669913</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MUST 04/10-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03669913</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mitigating Adverse Sexual and Reproductive Health Outcomes Among Young Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mitigating Adverse Sexual and Reproductive Health Outcomes Through a Comprehensive Primary School Sexuality Education Program in South-Western Uganda</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Ghent</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Free University of Brussels</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effectiveness of comprehensive sexuality education (CSE) among young
      adolescents (10-14 years) in schools. A total of 33 schools will participate in the trial
      with 15 intervention arm that will receive CSE education and 18 in the control arm,
      Intervention will go on for one year
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The International Technical Guidance on Sexuality Education (ITGSE) defines CSE as &quot;an
      age-appropriate, culturally relevant approach to teaching about sexuality and relationships
      by providing scientifically accurate, realistic, non-judgmental information and CSE improves
      sexual and reproductive health outcomes of young people by delaying sexual debut, promoting
      condom use and increasing sexual health knowledge, however, most of these outcomes have been
      reported in older adolescents and there is limited evidence for effectiveness of CSE among
      young adolescents

      The study aims at improving adolescent sexual and reproductive health of young adolescents
      through CSE that is led by interdisciplinary university students' team in an environment
      where no consistent or regulated sexual and reproductive health education program currently
      exists
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 8, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A cluster randomized trial where the intervention is structured comprehensive sexuality education lesson packages</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in sexual health knowledge by 15% from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>change in sexual health knowledge(HIV, STI, contraception and puberty knowledge) using an itemized questionnaire developed for the study. The estimated knowlege score will be 25 . Individual items include on knowledge of puberty, HIV/STIs and pregnancy prevention. This includes knowledge on how HIV/AIDS can be acquired (score 0-4), types of common Sexually Transmitted Infections (score 0-4), knowledge of pubertal changes in boys (score 0-6.) and in girls (score 0-7), and knowledge about ways to prevent pregnancy (score 0-4)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proportion of sexually active adolescents by 10% from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in number of those who are sexually active</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gender equitable norm scores by 10% from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescents to adopt a more gender equitable norm attitude. Gender equitable norms scale will be developed on a 4 likert point scale and total scores will range from 0 to 44. The higher the score, the higher the tendency to have gender equitable norms. The score consists of 11 items. Six of these items were adapted from the Attitudes towards Women Scale for Adolescents (AWSA) by Galambos NL et al., 1985 while 5 items were developed to suit the respondents' age and the Ugandan context.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in body image scores by 10% from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescents develop a more positive attitude in appreciation of their body size or shape.The items for this scale were adapted from the Body Image States Scale (BISS-6) by Cash TF et al, 2002 but transformed to a 5 point likert scale including a neutral point for ease of use among respondents. The total expected score was 24 and the higher the score the better the body image</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in self esteem scores by 10% from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescent develop confidence in themselves and their abilities. Self esteem score used was developed by Rosenberg M et al., 1965. The total expected score for the 10 items was 40. The higher the score the better the self esteem</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1100</enrollment>
  <condition>Relationship Problems Specific to Childhood and Adolescence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention arm will receive a pre evaluation survey, 11 lessons on CSE sequentially in a period of one year and a post evaluation survey</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a control arm that receives no intervention but will have and pre and post evaluation in one year</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lessons on comprehensive sexuality education</intervention_name>
    <description>Provision of 11 standardized lessons on comprehensive sexuality education based on international guidance on sexuality education by UNESCO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adolescent 10-14 years in primary school

          -  Adolescent in primary 5 or 6 of education in Uganda

          -  Written consent/assent to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Below 10 years or above 14 years at baseline

          -  No consent obtained
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristien Michielsen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Ghent</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenberg M. Rosenberg self-esteem scale (RSE). Acceptance and commitment therapy. Measures package. 1965;61:52.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cash TF, Fleming EC, Alindogan J, Steadman L, Whitehead A. Beyond body image as a trait: the development and validation of the Body Image States Scale. Eat Disord. 2002 Summer;10(2):103-13.</citation>
    <PMID>16864251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galambos NL, Petersen AC, Richards M, Gitelson IB. The Attitudes Toward Women Scale for Adolescents (AWSA): A study of reliability and validity. Sex roles. 1985;13(5):343-356.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kemigisha E, Nyakato VN, Bruce K, Ndaruhutse Ruzaaza G, Mlahagwa W, Ninsiima AB, Coene G, Leye E, Michielsen K. Adolescents' Sexual Wellbeing in Southwestern Uganda: A Cross-Sectional Assessment of Body Image, Self-Esteem and Gender Equitable Norms. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2018 Feb 22;15(2). pii: E372. doi: 10.3390/ijerph15020372.</citation>
    <PMID>29470388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sexuality</keyword>
  <keyword>education</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescents</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be discretely shared with other researchers on request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 3, 2016</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/13/NCT03669913/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

