<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03664518</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IHBDH-IIT2018006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03664518</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Eltrombopag for Thrombocytopenia With Chronic HBV Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter Single-arm Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Eltrombopag for Thrombocytopenia in Chinese Patients With Chronic HBV Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Qilu Hospital of Shandong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Kunming Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tianjin First Central Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tianjin Medical University Second Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Henan Cancer Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective: To evaluate the efficacy of 6-week Eltrombopag to treat thrombocytopenia
      associated with chronic hepatitis B virus infection. Secondary Objective: To evaluate the
      efficacy and safety of 6-week and 22-week Eltrombopag to treat thrombocytopenia associated
      with chronic hepatitis B virus infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm phase II study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of Eltrombopag to
      treat thrombocytopenia associated with chronic hepatitis B virus infection.

      This study includes two stages. In Stage 1 (Week 1 to Week 6), the short-term efficacy,
      safety and tolerability of Eltrombopag is evaluated. At the end of Stage 1, the subjects who
      can benefit from Eltrombopag treatment (platelet count ≥ 50×109/L) can enter a 16-week
      prolonged stage (Stage 2) to evaluate longer-term efficacy and safety.

      The starting dose of Eltrombopag is 25 mg once daily, and the dose may be increased by 25 mg
      once daily every two weeks if the desired platelet response (&gt;50×109/L) is not achieved. The
      daily dose should not exceed 75 mg.

      In Stage 1, weekly visits are required during the first 6 weeks of the study. In Stage 2,
      platelet counts will be obtained weekly during dose adjustment and every 4 weeks following
      establishment of a stable dose of Eltrombopag (stable dose is defined as the dose which
      remains unchanged for at least 2 weeks).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with a platelet count ≥ 50×109/L at Day 43</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with a platelet count ≥ 50×109/L at Day 43 after the first 6 weeks of Eltrombopag treatment (Stage 1)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>22 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate including: a) the proportion of subjects achieving platelet counts ≥ 50×109/L at least once during the first 6 weeks (stage 1); b) the proportion of subjects whose platelet counts ≥ 30×109/L and at least two times of baseline platelet count at least once during the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding in two stages</measure>
    <time_frame>22 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>according to the WHO bleeding grades to estimate the incidence and severity of bleeding symptoms during the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The duration time with Platelet count ≥ 50×109/L</measure>
    <time_frame>22 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total duration of time a subject had a platelet count ≥ 50×109/L during treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Thrombocytopenia Purpura</condition>
  <condition>Chronic HBV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eltrombopag</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>58 enrolled patients are picked up to take eltrombopag at the indicated dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eltrombopag</intervention_name>
    <description>subjects will initiate treatment with 25 mg eltrombopag. Platelet counts is obtained weekly and dose adjustment should be done according to platelet counts. and maximum dose should not exceed 75 mg daily. Subjects whose platelet count between 50~150×109/L，the eltrombopag dose Maintain. platelet count between 150~250×109/L, need to reduce the dose of eltrombopag to the next lower dose or lower frequency. Subjects whose platelet count exceeds 250×109/L at any point during the treatment period, must have eltrombopag interrupted and increase the frequency of platelet monitoring to twice weekly, until platelet counts fall below 100×109/L.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eltrombopag</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed written informed consent.

          -  Subject is ≥18 years old.

          -  Diagnosis of HBV-infection duration for at least 6 months prior to the study and have
             a platelet count of &lt;30 ×109/L on Day 1 (or within 48 hours prior to dosing on Day 1).

          -  Complete blood count results: white blood cells, absolute neutrophils count and
             hemoglobin are within the laboratory normal range, but abnormalities caused by HBV
             infection can be accepted.

          -  Subject is practicing an acceptable method of contraception. Women of childbearing
             potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test in the whole study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Liver cirrhosis (LC) defined as any of the following:

               1. Any symptom or sign typical of hepatic decompensation: including but not limited
                  to ascites, splenomegaly, dilation of periumbilical collateral veins, hepatic
                  encephalopathy

               2. Child-Pugh class B to C Biopsies are not required either for confirmation or for
                  exclusion of LC, considering the high bleeding risk in these patients.

          -  Positive serology for HIV, hepatitis C virus (HCV), and/or hepatitis D virus (HDV).

          -  Pregnancy or lactation period.

          -  History of alcohol/drug abuse or dependence within 12 months of the study.

          -  History of thrombosis.

          -  The serum chemistry results exceed the upper laboratory normal range by more than 20%;
             except AST, ALT, GGT, ALP of CTCAE grade 1.

          -  Bone marrow examination conducted within 4 weeks prior to first dose reported an
             abnormal result, which in the opinion of the investigator makes the subject unsuitable
             for participation in the study.

          -  Pre-existing cardiac disease, including congestive heart failure of New York Heart
             Association [NYHA] Grade III/IV, arrhythmia requiring treatment or myocardial
             infarction within the last 6 months. No arrhythmia known to increase the risk of
             thrombotic events (e.g. atrial fibrillation), or patients with a QT &gt;450msec or QTc &gt;
             480 for patients with a Bundle Branch Block.

          -  Subject has consumed aspirin, aspirin-containing compounds, salicylates,
             anticoagulants, quinine or non-steroidal anti-inflammatories (NSAIDs) for &gt;3
             consecutive days within 2 weeks prior to the study start and until the end of the
             study.

          -  Non-compliant patient

          -  Reluctance to take effective contraceptive measures during the trial

          -  History of solid organ or bone marrow transplant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>lei zhang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese Academy of Medical Science and Blood Disease Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>yueting huang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>13920284261</phone>
    <email>huangyueting@ihcams.ac.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>lei zhang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>13502118379</phone>
    <email>zhanglei1@ihcams.ac.cn</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ethics Committee of Blood disease hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <state>Tianjin</state>
        <zip>300020</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lijun Liu, Master</last_name>
      <phone>+8613920927593</phone>
      <email>liulijun@ihcams.ac.cn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ott JJ, Stevens GA, Groeger J, Wiersma ST. Global epidemiology of hepatitis B virus infection: new estimates of age-specific HBsAg seroprevalence and endemicity. Vaccine. 2012 Mar 9;30(12):2212-9. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.12.116. Epub 2012 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22273662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang Y, Zhang H, Elizabeth A, Liu XQ. Epidemiology of hepatitis B and associated liver diseases in china. Chin Med Sci J. 2013 Jan;27(4):243-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23294591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toghill PJ, Green S, Ferguson F. Platelet dynamics in chronic liver disease with special reference to the role of the spleen. J Clin Pathol. 1977 Apr;30(4):367-71.</citation>
    <PMID>853132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aref S, Mabed M, Selim T, Goda T, Khafagy N. Thrombopoietin (TPO) levels in hepatic patients with thrombocytopenia. Hematology. 2004 Oct-Dec;9(5-6):351-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15763973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Afdhal N, McHutchison J, Brown R, Jacobson I, Manns M, Poordad F, Weksler B, Esteban R. Thrombocytopenia associated with chronic liver disease. J Hepatol. 2008 Jun;48(6):1000-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2008.03.009. Epub 2008 Mar 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18433919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bussel JB, Marks KM. How effective is eltrombopag for the treatment of thrombocytopenia in patients with HCV infection? Nat Clin Pract Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2008 Aug;5(8):424-5. doi: 10.1038/ncpgasthep1185. Epub 2008 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18607406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang R, Li J, Jin J, Huang M, Yu Z, Xu X, Zhang X, Hou M. Multicentre, randomised phase III study of the efficacy and safety of eltrombopag in Chinese patients with chronic immune thrombocytopenia. Br J Haematol. 2017 Jan;176(1):101-110. doi: 10.1111/bjh.14380. Epub 2016 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27734464</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bussel JB, Cheng G, Saleh MN, Psaila B, Kovaleva L, Meddeb B, Kloczko J, Hassani H, Mayer B, Stone NL, Arning M, Provan D, Jenkins JM. Eltrombopag for the treatment of chronic idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura. N Engl J Med. 2007 Nov 29;357(22):2237-47.</citation>
    <PMID>18046028</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Giannini EG, Afdhal NH. Eltrombopag in patients with chronic liver disease. Expert Opin Pharmacother. 2013 Apr;14(5):669-78. doi: 10.1517/14656566.2013.775249. Epub 2013 Mar 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23452139</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institute of Hematology &amp; Blood Diseases Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhang Lei</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>vice Director of Thrombosis and Hemostasis Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

