<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02663622</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMCC 2015.181</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HUM00107805</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>15-4789</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R44CA221513</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R44CA246991</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02663622</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Trial of CD24Fc for the Prevention of Acute GVHD Following Myeloablative Allogeneic HSCT</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIa and Phase II Expansion Trial of CD24Fc for Prevention of Acute Graft-versus-Host Disease Following Myeloablative Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OncoImmune, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan Rogel Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Indiana University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OncoImmune, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter prospective phase IIa dose escalation and Phase II expansion cohort
      clinical trial designed to determine the efficacy of CD24Fc for acute GVHD prophylaxis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The first part of study is a Phase IIa randomized, double blind, placebo controlled,
      multi-center study to investigate adding CD24Fc to standard of care tacrolimus and
      methotrexate in acute graft-versus host disease (GVHD) prophylaxis for allogeneic
      hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HCT) with matched unrelated donors in treatment of
      leukemia and myelodysplastic syndrome. Three dose cohorts are planned with 240 mg at day -1,
      480 mg at day -1, and the multi-dose cohort of 480-240-240 mg at day -1, day 14 and day 28.
      The CD24Fc : placebo ratio is 3:1.

      The second part is a prospective phase II expansion cohort trial investigating the addition
      of CD24Fc to standard acute graft-versus host disease (GVHD) prophylaxis for allogeneic
      hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HCT). Based on the Phase IIa safety results and the
      pharmacokinetic data, the Phase II expansion dose will be the multi-dose 480-240-240 mg
      regimen administered on day -1, day 14 and day 28. The primary objective of phase II
      expansion is to determine if the addition of CD24Fc to standard GVHD prophylaxis improves 180
      days grade III-IV acute GVHD-free survival (AGFS) when compared to CIBMTR database registered
      control patients who had standard GVHD prophylaxis alone. Eligible patients will be those
      requiring allogeneic HCT for malignant hematologic conditions and receiving a myeloablative
      conditioning regimen. An unrelated donor is required to match at HLA-A, -B, -C, and -DRB1
      loci.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 20, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 4, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Part 1 is double blind, placebo controlled study. Part 2 is open label.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>180 day grade III-IV acute GVHD free survival (AGFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days after HCT.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a composite endpoint to determine the Grade III-IV acute GVHD free survival (AGFS) in 180 days after HCT. The onset day of Grade IIIIV aGVHD, or death of any cause, which comes the first, will be counted as the event.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>One year overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>This is to assess the one year overall survival.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>One year disease free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>This is to assess the one year disease (relapse) free survival.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>180 day grade II-IV acute GVHD free survival (AGFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>This is a composite endpoint to determine the Grade II-IV acute GVHD free survival (AGFS) in 180 days after HCT. The onset day of Grade II-IV aGVHD, or death of any cause, which comes the first, will be counted as the event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Graft Versus Host Disease</condition>
  <condition>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CD24Fc will be given in three dose cohorts. CD24Fc in 240 mg as intravenous (IV) infusion at Day -1 CD24Fc in 480 mg as intravenous (IV) infusion at Day -1 CD24Fc (480 mg (day -1), 240 mg (day +14) and 240 mg (day +28)) as intravenous infusion.
All cohorts + Tacrolimus (begin on day -3. IV [0.03mg/kg/day] or PO [0.045mg/kg/dose] dosing is permitted) + Methotrexate (given intravenously at a dose of 15 mg/m2/dose once daily on Day 1 after HCT, and at a dose of 10 mg/m2/dose on days 3, 6, and 11 after HCT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (saline IV injection solution) + Tacrolimus (begin on day -3. IV [0.03mg/kg/day] or PO [0.045mg/kg/dose] dosing is permitted) + Methotrexate (given intravenously at a dose of 15 mg/m2/dose once daily on Day 1 after HCT, and at a dose of 10 mg/m2/dose on days 3, 6, and 11 after HCT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CD24Fc (480 mg (day -1), 240 mg (day +14) and 240 mg (day +28)) + Tacrolimus (begin on day -3. IV [0.03mg/kg/day] or PO [0.045mg/kg/dose] dosing is permitted) + Methotrexate (given intravenously at a dose of 15 mg/m2/dose once daily on Day 1 after HCT, and at a dose of 10 mg/m2/dose on days 3, 6, and 11 after HCT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CD24Fc</intervention_name>
    <description>Acute GVHD prophylaxis</description>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD24 Fusion Protein</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Acute GVHD prophylaxis</description>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Trexall</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Acute GVHD prophylaxis</description>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CD24Fc Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FK506</other_name>
    <other_name>Prograf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>100 ml saline IV infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Saline Solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        4.1.1 A prospective patient for allogeneic HCT for a malignant hematologic disorder (see
        section 4.1.3 for eligible diagnoses).

        4.1.2 The donor and recipient must have an HLA-8/8 allelic match at the HLA-A, -B, -C, and
        - DRB1 loci. High-resolution typing is required for all alleles for unmatched donors. Only
        matched unrelated donors are acceptable for this trial.

        4.1.3 The following diagnoses are to be included:

          1. Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) or Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) in first or second
             remission. Remission is defined as the absence of blasts in the peripheral circulation
             at the time of enrollment, &lt; 5% blasts in the bone marrow and absence of
             extramedullary disease including CNS involvement.

          2. Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia (CML) in first or subsequent chronic phase failing to
             respond (or intolerant) to at least two different tyrosine kinase inhibitors. CML in
             accelerated or blast phase (CML-AP/BP) are eligible without requirement to fail
             tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy, but must be in remission at time of enrollment.
             Remission is defined as the absence of blasts in the peripheral circulation at the
             time of enrollment, &lt; 5% blasts in the bone marrow and absence of extramedullary
             disease including CNS involvement.

          3. Myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) with intermediate or high-risk IPSS or equivalent
             IPSS-R score with &lt; 10% blasts in the bone marrow.

          4. Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukemia (CMML) with &lt; 10% blasts in the bone marrow.

        4.1.4 Males or non-pregnant, non-lactating females, ≥ 18 years of age. Note there is no
        defined upper age limited, so long as deemed appropriate candidate for myeloablative
        conditioning.

        4.1.5 Karnofsky Performance Status &gt;70%, see Appendix A.

        4.1.6 Patients must have normal or near normal organ function as defined by their treating
        institutions BMT program clinical practice guidelines. In addition, for purposes of this
        protocol minimum organ function criteria within 21 days of beginning conditioning include:

        TABLE 1: Eligibility According to Pre HCT Organ Function Total bilirubin ≤2.5 mg% (unless
        from Gilbert's disease or disease-related) AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) &lt;5.0 X institutional upper
        limit of normal Estimated or actual GFR &gt;50 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine
        levels above institutional normal (GFR should be corrected for BSA) Pulmonary Function
        Tests* DLCO, FEV1, FVC &gt; 50% DLCO should be corrected for hemoglobin Ejection Fraction*
        &gt;50% Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation-Specific Comorbidity Index (HCT-CI) ≤ 5

        *May be assessed up to 6 weeks prior to the start of conditioning therapy

        4.1.7 Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
        document.

        4.1.8 Women of child bearing potential and men must agree to use contraception prior to
        study entry and through day 100 post HCT (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;
        abstinence). Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her
        partner is on treatment in this study, she should inform her study physician immediately.
        Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must also agree to use adequate contraception
        prior to the study until day 100 post HCT (See section 6.0).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        4.2.1 Subjects may not have presence of active CNS disease or extramedullary disease.

        4.2.2 Prior cytotoxic chemotherapy within 21 days from the initiation of HCT conditioning
        (i.e. intensive induction / consolidation for AML). Note, certain low intensity treatments
        not intended to induce remission but rather stabilize disease are acceptable up to 24 hrs
        prior to initiation of HCT conditioning (i.e. Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor, sorafenib).

        4.2.3 Cord blood and haploidentical donors are not eligible.

        4.2.4 HLA-mismatch at the HLA-A, -B, -C, and - DRB1 loci. Note, HLA-DQ mismatches are
        permissible.

        4.2.5 Pregnant and nursing mothers are excluded from this study. This is because the risk
        to the fetus is unknown.

        4.2.6 Any physical or psychological condition that, in the opinion of the investigator,
        would pose unacceptable risk to the patient or raise concern that the patient would not
        comply with protocol procedures.

        4.2.7 Uncontrolled infections. Patients still under therapy for presumed or proven
        infection are eligible provided there is clear evidence (radiologic, clinical and/or
        culture) that the infection is well controlled.

        4.2.8 Patients seropositive or PCR positive for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).
        Patients with evidence of Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C PCR positivity.

        4.2.9 Prior HCT (allograft or prior autograft).

        4.2.10 Use of T cell depletion either ex vivo or in vivo (i.e. ATG, alemtuzumab) is
        prohibited.

        4.2.11 Current or prior diagnosis of antecedent Myelofibrosis is excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pavan Reddy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan Rogel Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toubai T, Rossi C, Oravecz-Wilson K, Zajac C, Liu C, Braun T, Fujiwara H, Wu J, Sun Y, Brabbs S, Tamaki H, Magenau J, Zheng P, Liu Y, Reddy P. Siglec-G represses DAMP-mediated effects on T cells. JCI Insight. 2017 Jul 20;2(14). pii: 92293. doi: 10.1172/jci.insight.92293. eCollection 2017 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28724800</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toubai T, Hou G, Mathewson N, Liu C, Wang Y, Oravecz-Wilson K, Cummings E, Rossi C, Evers R, Sun Y, Wu J, Choi SW, Fang D, Zheng P, Liu Y, Reddy P. Siglec-G-CD24 axis controls the severity of graft-versus-host disease in mice. Blood. 2014 May 29;123(22):3512-23. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-12-545335. Epub 2014 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24695850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toubai T, Mathewson ND, Magenau J, Reddy P. Danger Signals and Graft-versus-host Disease: Current Understanding and Future Perspectives. Front Immunol. 2016 Nov 29;7:539. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27965667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

