<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04327830</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCD315</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04327830</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>What Older Adults and Their Caregivers Need for Making Better Decisions at Home</brief_title>
  <official_title>Decision-making Needs of Older Adults Receiving Home Care From the Perspective of Older Adults, Their Caregivers and Inter-disciplinary Health and Social Care Provicers: Participatory Mixed Methods Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CHU de Quebec-Universite Laval</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SE Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CHU de Quebec-Universite Laval</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Most Canadians wish to stay at home in their old age. As older adults stay at home with the
      support of home and community services, they are often faced with difficult decisions, such
      as &quot;Who will look after me when I can't look after myself any more, or if I have dementia?&quot;
      or &quot;Should I move to a nursing home, or stay here?&quot; Care providers in the home and community
      can support older adults and their families make these difficult decisions by providing them
      with information they need and asking them about their values and preferences. By helping
      older adults and their families know more about their choices and choose options that reflect
      what is important to them, care providers can work with their clients to help them make
      informed health decisions together. In this fellowship, the investigators will study what
      supports are needed for older adults to make informed health decisions from the perspective
      of older adults, caregivers and front-line care providers in the home and community setting
      across Canada. This can help improve the home and community services provided to older adults
      (and their caregivers) so that older adults (and their caregivers) can make better decisions
      together with their health care team.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction Shared decision making is an interpersonal process whereby healthcare providers
      collaborate with and support patients in decision-making. Older adults receiving home care
      need support with decision-making (e.g., information on risks and benefits of options). This
      study will explore what older adults and their caregivers need for making better
      health-related decisions at home, and what health and social care providers need for
      supporting their home care clients with decision-making.

      Methods and analysis This two-phase sequential exploratory mixed methods study will be
      conducted in a pan-Canadian healthcare organization, SE Health. First, the investigators will
      create a participant advisory group (one older adult, one caregiver and two care providers)
      to advise us throughout the research process. In Phase 1 (qualitative), the investigators
      will recruit a convenient sample of older adults and caregivers receiving home care to
      participate in open-ended semi-structured interviews to discuss what health-related decisions
      they face at home and what they need for making better decisions (e.g. types of knowledge,
      sources of support). In Phase 2 (quantitative), interdisciplinary health and social care
      providers (e.g., nurses, personal support workers, occupational therapists, physiotherapists)
      will be invited to answer an online survey to share their views on the decision-making needs
      of older adults and their caregivers. The survey will include close-ended questions informed
      by findings from the qualitative interviews in Phase 1. Finally, qualitative and quantitative
      results will be triangulated from the perspective of older adults, caregivers and health and
      social care providers. Results will be reported using EQUATOR guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making needs of older adults who receive home care services and their caregivers.</measure>
    <time_frame>About 60 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Interview of older adults and their caregivers. Open-ended questions guide by the Ottawa Decision Support Framework (ODSF).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>What health and social care providers need to support older adults and their caregivers with making decisions.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Survey of interdisciplinary health and social care providers, based on the Ottawa Decision Support Framework (ODSF) factors contributing to difficulty.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>-Health and social care providers opinion how often older adults faced difficult decisions. -Shared decision-making. -Others participants involved in the decision making.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 to 10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Opinion frequency; 5-point Likert scale always to never.
Shared decision-making generic approach in 5 questions; 5-point Likert scale always to never.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Older adults and their caregivers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Older adults who have received or are receiving home care services and their caregivers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interdisciplinary health and social care providers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Interdisciplinary health and social care providers who provide home care services to older adults</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decisional needs assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Assessment of decision-making needs</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interdisciplinary health and social care providers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Older adults and their caregivers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Older adults who have received or are receive home care services (and their caregivers)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  older adults who have received, or are receiving home care services

          -  caregivers of older adults who have received, or are receiving home care services

          -  interdisciplinary health and social care providers who provide home care services for
             older adults

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  no experience receiving or providing home care services
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>France Legare</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Laval University /SE Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CERSSPL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Québec</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>1. Statistics Canada. Home health care and related services [Report on the Internet]. Ottawa: Statitics Canada, 2017 (cited July 31, 2019). Accessed on Feb 10, 2020 from: https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/daily-quotidien/190731/dq190731c-eng.htm</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>2. Canadian Institute for Health Information. Home care expenditures in the NHEX Database [Technical note on the Internet] Ottawa: The Institute; 2017 (cited November 2017). Accessed on Feb 20, 2020 from: https://www.cihi.ca/sites/default/files/document/technical_notes_on_home_care-nhex2017-en.pdf.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Shared decision making</keyword>
  <keyword>Home care</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

