<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04326218</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-GIRCI-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04326218</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunopathological Analysis in a French National Cohort of Membranous Nephropathy</brief_title>
  <acronym>IHMN</acronym>
  <official_title>Immunopathological Analysis in a French National Cohort of Membranous Nephropathy (IHMN)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      National cohort of all cases of membranous nephropathy (MN) during a 1 year period in France,
      based on a pathological and/or serological diagnostic, collecting the data on:

        -  incidence of MN

        -  prevalence of anti-PLA2R1 and anti-THSD7A

        -  clinical outcome one year after diagnosis or after relapse (complete remission, partial
           remission or persistent nephrotic syndrome)

        -  environmental risk factors for the onset of MN

        -  HLA markers

        -  patient care status in France
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Membranous nephropathy is a rare auto-immune disease, yet a major cause of nephrotic syndrome
      in adults. It is characterised by the deposition of antigen-antibody complexes on the
      glomerular basement membrane, leading to a decreased filtration rate and eventually kidney
      failure. About one third of cases have a favourable outcome without any treatment, another
      third requires a long term symptomatic treatment to manage their symptoms, and the last third
      of patients advances to end stage renal failure, requiring dialysis and kidney graft. MN can
      be associated with cancer, infections, other auto-immune diseases and with certain drugs
      (secondary MN), but most often it is idiopathic. In the latter form two antigens have been
      identified, PLA2R1 and THSD7A, with corresponding auto-antibodies in 70% and 2% of MN
      patients, respectively. GWAS studies identified several alleles associated with a higher risk
      of developing MN, however, since these are common variants they cannot explain the onset of
      MN in the vast majority of cases. Since MN is a rare disease, the number of new cases per
      each center is low, and nation-wide studies are needed to correctly evaluate its incidence
      and risk factors for the onset of MN, as well as validate previously published findings in
      monocentric studies on the prognostic value of PLA2R1 epitope spreading (immunisation against
      multiple domains of PLA2R1).

      This study aims to establish a French national cohort of all cases of MN in a one year period
      in France. The inclusion will last one year with one additional year of follow-up, for a
      total of 2 years. In the first year, nephrologists of each associate centers in France will
      propose the study to each of their patients diagnosed with MN. In addition, clinical
      information will be collected, as well as a survey on patients' lifestyle habits. Serum
      samples will be sent for centralised analyses in Nice.

      This study will help to clarify the results from single center studies, such as the
      prognostic value of epitope spreading. The information acquired on environmental risk factors
      will help us understand the pathophysiological mechanisms leading to the onset of MN et, by
      association, to other auto-immune diseases. With this knowledge, measures could be put in
      place to protect the population at risk.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Descriptive analysis of patient cohort who will be subjected to specific samples related to the study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the incidence of Membranous Nephropathy (MN) and its evolution</measure>
    <time_frame>one year after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>as either complete remission (UPCR &lt; 0.3 g/g, serum albumin &gt; 35 g/L, eGFR &gt; 60 ml/min/1.73 m²) or partial remission (UPCR &lt; 3.5 g/g and reduction of at least 50% from baseline, &lt; 20% increase of serum creatinin from baseline) or persistent nephrotic syndrome (UPCR &gt; 3.5 g/g, serum albumin &lt; 30 g/L)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of incidence of primary and secondary forms of MN</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of environmental factors associated with the onset of MN</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Thanks to a specific questionnaire data on medical history, lifestyle, demography and profession will be collected
Medical history: prior diagnosis of any autoimmune disease, cancer, infection or other, infection in the month before the diagnosis of MN, thrombosis, drugs taken at the moment of diagnosis, allergies and type of symptomes
Emotional state: emotional state at diagnosis, stressful or destabilizing event in the year preceding diagnosis of MN</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Description of the standard of care for patients with MN in France</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment names and their duration (in weeks) will be collected</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the prognostic value of epitope spreading in patients with PLA2R1-associated MN</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Epitope spreading status is determined by measuring the positivity to anti-CysR, anti-CTLD1 and CTLD7 antibodies in the serum, by the means of ELISA and expressed as RU/mL. The patients with antibodies targetting CysR only are considered as non-spreaders, while the patients additionnaly targetting either CTLD1 and/or CTLD7 are considered as spreaders. Epitope spreading status (non-spreader or spreader) will be correlated to clinical outcome (complete remission, partial remission or persistent nephrotic syndrome, as defined under primary outcome measures) one year after inclusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of HLA typing of MN patients</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Isolation of DNA and genotyping will be performed with the use of standard procedures of Next Generation Sequencing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prognostic value of tissue staining for glomerular deposit of PLA2R1, THSD7A, as welle as of different IgG subclasses</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Positivity for PLA2R1, THSD7A and NELL-1 antigens will be determined using immunostaining with antibodies against PLA2R1, THSD7A and NELL-1, and Positivity for IgG1 IgG2, IgG3 and IgG4 subclasses will be determined using immunostaining with antibodies against IgG1 IgG2, IgG3 and IgG4, respectively, in glomeruli of kidney biopsy at inclusion. The positivity of tissue staining for PLA2R1, THSD7A and NELL-1or Ig subclasses will be correlated to the patient's clinical outcome one year after inclusion (complete remission, partial remission or persistent nephrotic syndrome, as defined under primary outcome measures).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Membranous Nephropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients included will have to be taken blood samples</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood sample</intervention_name>
    <description>Serum samples will be sent for centralised analyses in Nice.
On these samples, different analysis will be performed :
anti-PLA2R1 and anti-THSD7A antibodies
anti-PLA2R1 and anti-THSD7A epitopes
HLA typing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or more

          -  Biopsy on a native kidney consistent with MN and/or positivity for serum anti-PLA2R1
             and/or anti-THSD7A antibodies

          -  Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis error based on the kidney biopsy staining or on serology analyses for the
             positivity for anti-PLA2R1 and/or anti-THSD7A

          -  Patients unable to give an informed consent

          -  Patients withdrawing an informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Barbara SEITZ-POLSKI, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 4 92 03 55 02</phone>
    <email>seitz-polski.b@chu-nice.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis, Membranous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No data will be shared</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

