<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04325802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DERM-2019-28471</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04325802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Chronic Itch in Atopic Dermatitis With Opioid Antagonist Naltrexone</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Chronic Itch in Atopic Dermatitis With Opioid Antagonist Naltrexone and Effects on Skin Circadian Rhythm</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: To study the etiology and the epigenetic pathways leading to and regulating chronic
      itch. Similarly, to examine the mechanisms underlying skin changes, including epigenetic
      alterations while also testing the efficacy of opioid antagonists in atopic dermatitis. In
      this study, the investigators aim to examine chronic sensory disorder mechanisms related to
      chronic itch.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific aims:

      A1 Evaluate the underlying mechanism of itch severity in terms of circadian rhythm by
      collecting epidermis at different circadian stages using suction blisters. This will be done
      in AD patients with chronic itch. The cells will be isolated from part of the suction
      blisters and used to isolate and sequence RNA to evaluate and compare the differential
      protein and RNA expression in suction blister taken from symptomatic &amp; non-symptomatic areas
      in patients with AD at different time points. The investigators will then correlate the itch
      severity symptoms to clock gene and opioid receptor levels and RNA expression differential
      pattern. A1 will be evaluated by study arm A and the results from this study will serve to
      decide on time point taking the suction blisters for the therapeutic/mechanistic studies (arm
      B and C).

      A2 Investigate the mechanistic role and therapeutic efficacy of opioid receptors in chronic
      itch. For this purpose, a cross-over, placebo-controlled design will be used to treat
      patients with opioid receptor antagonist (Naltrexone) by expanding on our existing trial. The
      investigators will collect, evaluate, quantify and compare the differential protein and RNA
      expression in epidermis taken by suction blisters from symptomatic and non-symptomatic areas
      in patients with AD on Placebo or Naltrexone treatment. Transcriptome analysis will be
      focused, but not restricted to, analysis of neuroinflammatory and neuronal markers (including
      cytokines, GPCR and opioid receptors). Confirmation will occur using in-situ hybridization of
      biopsies to correlate specific cell type and location and qPCR expression of in vitro
      cultures. The binding studies using fluorescent labeled opioid ligands and internalization
      pattern will be carried out.

      A3 Test the underlying mechanisms of the opioid system with nerve-keratinocyte interaction
      and possible effects on itch transduction from skin to nerves by using an in vitro
      neuron-keratinocyte co-culture model. Moreover, the investigators plan to validate
      itch-causing networks and pathways found in A2 using this in vitro model and will be able to
      evaluate calcium flux threshold changes after exposure to external stimuli (e.g. light, or
      mechanic stimuli) onto keratinocytes and neuronal somata under different opioid exposure
      conditions. The FC derived sensory neurons will be co-cultured with different patient KC. The
      investigators will test the reaction pattern of KC and transmission of the signal to
      connected peripheral sensory neurons by Fluo-4 AM Calcium imaging and electrophysiology. The
      reaction will be responding to the odorant Sandalore, as the investigators have previously
      published that Sandalore induces these desired calcium fluxes.

      Apply the in vitro epithelial/nerve model to validate possible itch pathways identified by
      epigenetic analysis in the clinical trials by confirming the expression pattern with qPCR and
      functional assays on cells with CRISPR knockout of the RNA targets, opioid trafficking,
      calcium imaging and electrophysiology. Finally, further develop co-cultures between human
      skin and iPS-derived human peripheral neurons to perform functional studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Itch Intensity (Visual Analog Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Change in itch intensity will be measured using a Visual Analogue scale (VAS). Scores range from 0 to 10, with higher scores indicating greater itch intensity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <condition>Pruritus</condition>
  <condition>Pruritus Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo, then Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will start with placebo in week 1 and cross over to Naltrexone in week 3. There will be a wash-out phase during week 2 using only moisturizer regularly and if necessary as rescue medications topical corticosteroids and/or antihistamines. The same rescue medications can be used during the following weeks of the cross-over treatment. At visit 2 and 4 patients will be asked the area where they are experiencing most intense itch and we will take there suction blisters (preferably on the trunk). Suction blisters will be taken after week 1 (1 week on treatment arm 1) and after week 3 (1 week on treatment arm 2).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Intevention, then Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will start with Naltrexone in week 1 and cross over to the palcebo treatment in week 3. There will be a wash-out phase during week 2 using only moisturizer regularly and if necessary as rescue medications topical corticosteroids and/or antihistamines. The same rescue medications can be used during the following weeks of the cross-over treatment. At visit 2 and 4 patients will be asked the area where they are experiencing most intense itch and we will take there suction blisters (preferably on the trunk). Suction blisters will be taken after week 1 (1 week on treatment arm 1) and after week 3 (1 week on treatment arm 2).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Circadian Rhythm of Itch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this arm will receive no intervention, only data collection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naltrexone</intervention_name>
    <description>50mg Naltrexone daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo, then Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Intevention, then Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo (Mannitol) daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo, then Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Intevention, then Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of AD via simplified UK Working Group Criteria and a baseline PSGA score of
             2 or greater

          -  Willingness to adhere to study protocol

          -  Subjects taking hormone-containing medications must be on a stable dose for 6 months
             prior to study start to avoid any confounding influence on sensory and pain perception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of topical or oral anti-inflammatory medications for 2 weeks prior to the study
             start.

          -  Use of topical or oral anti-histamines for 2 weeks prior to the study start (as rescue
             medication allowed).

          -  Use of topical or oral anti-pruritic agents for 2 weeks prior to the study start.

          -  Use of oral neuromodulatory agents for 2 months prior to study start.

          -  Current use of chronic pain medications (including opioids, antidepressants and
             anti-epileptic drugs).

          -  Use of nicotine-containing products for the past 6 months prior to study start.

          -  History of radiation or chemotherapy.

          -  History of traumatic injury on prospective test sites.

          -  Unstable thyroid function within the past 6 months prior to study start to exclude
             thyroid-related neuropathy

          -  Known history of central or peripheral nervous system dysfunction.

          -  History of acute hepatitis, chronic liver disease or end stage liver disease.

          -  History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immune deficiency syndrome.

          -  History of neuropathy associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, diabetes
             mellitus, documented exposure to organophosphates or heavy metals or polychlorinated
             biphenyls.

          -  Known nutritional deficiency (vitamin B12, vitamin D, iron or zinc) within 3 months
             prior to the study start.

          -  Use of illicit drugs within the past 6 months prior to study start and/or opioid use
             disorder.

          -  Regular use of opioids for chronic pain

          -  Lyme disease, porphyria, rheumatoid arthritis, Hansen's disease (leprosy) or use of
             antineoplastic chemotherapeutic agents.

          -  Subject has any medical condition that, in the judgment of the Investigator, would
             jeopardize the subject's safety following exposure to the administered medications.

          -  Adults lacking capacity to consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Bigliardi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Bigliardi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-625-6118</phone>
    <email>mill4869@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Bigliardi, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Itch</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eczema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pruritus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

