<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04325490</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ezerra intertrigo</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04325490</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tapioca Starch Stimutex AS, Aloe Barbadensis, Rose Hip Oil, Allantoin Comparing With Topical 1% Hydrocortisone Cream</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Efficiency and Safety of Liquid Powder Containing Tapioca Starch Stimutex AS, Aloe Barbadensis, Rose Hip Oil and Allantoin Comparing With Topical 1% Hydrocortisone Cream for Treatment of Intertrigo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mahidol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>HOE pharmaceuticals Sdn. Bhd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mahidol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized controlled trial of efficiency and safety of liquid powder containing tapioca
      starch stimutex AS, aloe barbadensis, rose hip oil and allantoin comparing with topical 1%
      hydrocortisone cream for the treatment of intertrigo
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intertrigo is an inflammatory dermatosis involving body folds that develops through friction
      of skin to skin and is influenced by moist conditions. The prevalence of intertrigo was
      reported to be 2.5% for adults with an average age of 41.5 years. Prevalence of intertrigo in
      the large skin folds varies from 6% in hospital patients to 17% in nursing home clients and
      20% in home care patients. The inframammary fold was most often affected (9.9%), followed by
      the inguinal region (9.4%), axilla (0.5%) and abdominal region (0.5%). Intertrigo may be mild
      and asymptomatic, but also may lead to intense erythema and desquamation. The affected skin
      may have a foul odor and may be macerated and ulcerated with copious or purulent discharge.
      The conventional therapy for simple intertrigo is minimizing moisture and friction. Some
      suggest the use of absorptive powders, such as talc and cornstarch, or barrier creams. These
      topical treatments such as topical steroid, however, have little or no proven benefit and may
      cause irritation or facilitate yeast colonization. This study aims to evaluate the efficacy
      and safety of liquid powder containing tapioca starch stimutex AS, aloe barbadensis, rose hip
      oil and allantoin comparing with topical 1% hydrocortisone cream of mild to moderate
      intertrigo patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A double-blined, randomized study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>the two interventions were prepared in an identical neutral package. The same investigator evaluated the skin condition at each follow-up visit. Patients were followed up at 2 weeks.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of liquid powder containing tapioca starch stimutex AS, aloe barbadensis, rose hip oil and allantoin, compared to topical 1% hydrocortisone cream for the treatment of intertrigo.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy was evaluated by the number of patients with improvement in erythema scores on intertrigo lesion after treatment which were assessed by the patients and the same investigator. Erythema scores were recorded using a 4-point scale (0 = none, 1 = mild, 2 = moderate, 3 = severe) on intertrigo lesion at baseline and week 2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects of liquid powder containing tapioca starch stimutex AS, aloe barbadensis, rose hip oil and allantoin, compared to topical 1% hydrocortisone cream for the treatment of intertrigo.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Side effects were calculated by the percentage of patients developed any side effects such as dryness, scaling, atrophy, and telangiectasia at week 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients' satisfction of liquid powder containing tapioca starch stimutex AS, aloe barbadensis, rose hip oil and allantoin, compared to topical 1% hydrocortisone cream for the treatment of intertrigo.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction was measured on intertrigo lesion at the end of study visit by patients using visual analog scales (VAS). The minimum score is 0 (no satisfied) and the maximum score is 10 (most satisfied).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Intertrigo</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liquid powder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Liquid powder containing tapioca starch stimutex AS, aloe barbadensis, rose hip oil and allantoin on the selected intertrigo area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrocortisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1% hydrocortisone cream</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liquid powder</intervention_name>
    <description>apply the study drug 1 fingertip unit to cover intertrigo lesion twice a day for two weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Liquid powder</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydrocortisone cream 1%</intervention_name>
    <description>apply the study drug 1 fingertip unit to cover intertrigo lesion twice a day for two weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrocortisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who had age more than 18 years

          2. One intertrigo lesion at inframammary fold, inguinal region, interdigital, axilla or
             abdominal region with mild to moderate which only has erythema no epidermal loss

          3. Being diagnosed intertrigo by dermatologist. Patients will be clinical and
             investigational with KOH preparation and Wood's lamp diagnosed with intertrigo by
             dermatologist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients receive topical steroids, topical anti-fungal drugs within 2 weeks prior the
             study

          2. Patients with skin conditions including fungal/bacterial infection, Hailey-Hailey
             disease, pemphigus, granuloma, psoriasis, acanthosis, or Darier disease on
             intertriginous areas within 2 weeks prior to the study

          3. Patients with an allergic to tapioca starch และ stimutex AS, aloe Barbadensis, rosa
             hip oil และ allantoin, or topical hydrocortisone

          4. Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          5. Patients with severe intertrigo treated with high potent topical steroid or systemic
             corticosteroid
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kanokvalai Kulthanan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Charussri Leeyaphan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+66815959105</phone>
    <email>charussrilee@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Supenya Varothai, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+66816232535</phone>
    <email>supenya.var@mahidol.ac.th</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology, Faculty of Medicine Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkoknoi</city>
        <state>Bangkok</state>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charussri Leeyaphan, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+6624194333</phone>
      <email>charussrilee@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Supenya Varothai, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+66816232535</phone>
      <email>supenya.var@mahidol.ac.th</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ndiaye M, Taleb M, Diatta BA, Diop A, Diallo M, Diadie S, Seck NB, Diallo S, Ndiaye MT, Niang SO, Ly F, Kane A, Dieng MT. [Etiology of intertrigo in adults: A prospective study of 103 cases]. J Mycol Med. 2017 Mar;27(1):28-32. doi: 10.1016/j.mycmed.2016.06.001. Epub 2016 Aug 21. French.</citation>
    <PMID>27554869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mistiaen P, van Halm-Walters M. Prevention and treatment of intertrigo in large skin folds of adults: a systematic review. BMC Nurs. 2010 Jul 13;9:12. doi: 10.1186/1472-6955-9-12.</citation>
    <PMID>20626853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gabriel S, Hahnel E, Blume-Peytavi U, Kottner J. Prevalence and associated factors of intertrigo in aged nursing home residents: a multi-center cross-sectional prevalence study. BMC Geriatr. 2019 Apr 15;19(1):105. doi: 10.1186/s12877-019-1100-8.</citation>
    <PMID>30987588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalra MG, Higgins KE, Kinney BS. Intertrigo and secondary skin infections. Am Fam Physician. 2014 Apr 1;89(7):569-73.</citation>
    <PMID>24695603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf R, Oumeish OY, Parish LC. Intertriginous eruption. Clin Dermatol. 2011 Mar-Apr;29(2):173-9. doi: 10.1016/j.clindermatol.2010.09.009.</citation>
    <PMID>21396557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hay RJ. The management of superficial candidiasis. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1999 Jun;40(6 Pt 2):S35-42. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10367915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Black JM, Gray M, Bliss DZ, Kennedy-Evans KL, Logan S, Baharestani MM, Colwell JC, Goldberg M, Ratliff CR. MASD part 2: incontinence-associated dermatitis and intertriginous dermatitis: a consensus. J Wound Ostomy Continence Nurs. 2011 Jul-Aug;38(4):359-70; quiz 371-2. doi: 10.1097/WON.0b013e31822272d9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21747256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janniger CK, Schwartz RA, Szepietowski JC, Reich A. Intertrigo and common secondary skin infections. Am Fam Physician. 2005 Sep 1;72(5):833-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16156342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intertrigo</keyword>
  <keyword>Tapioca starch</keyword>
  <keyword>Stimutex AS</keyword>
  <keyword>Aloe barbadensis</keyword>
  <keyword>Rose hip oil</keyword>
  <keyword>Allantoin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intertrigo</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

