<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04328610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-1912-010-086</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04328610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Assess the Efficacy of the LYMPHA in the Prevention of Lymphedema Following Axillary Dissection for Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>LYMPHA</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial to Assess the Efficacy of the Lymphatic Microsurgical Preventive Healing Approach (LYMPHA) to Prevent Lymphedema After Axillary Dissection for Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pusan National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pusan National University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lymphedema is the Build-up of Lymph Fluid in the Body's Tissue Causing Chronic, Debilitating
      Swelling. This Commonly Occurs as a Result of a Disruption of the Lymphatic System During
      Lymph Node Dissection Surgeries. LYMPHA (LYmphatic Microsurgical Preventive Healing Approach)
      is an Innovative Microsurgical Technique Where Blocked Lymphatic Vessels Are Drained Into the
      Blood Circulation by Surgically Creating a Shunt Between a Lymphatic Channel and a Blood
      Vessel Called a Lymphatic-venous Bypass. Recently, LYMPHA Technique Has Been Shown to Prevent
      Lymphedema When Performed at the Time of Nodal Dissection. We Propose a Prospective Study
      Evaluating the Effectiveness of LYMPHA Technique Using Objective Clinical Protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Consenting patients will have the LYMPHA procedure at the time of planned axillary dissection
      surgery for the prevention of upper and extremity lymphedema. The node dissection will be
      performed by Dr. Kang while the LYMPHA technique will be performed by the plastic surgeon,
      Dr. Kim. The LYMPHA procedure consist of performing LVA at the time of the node dissection.
      Patent blue dye will be injected in the volar surface of the upper third of the arm in a
      quantity of about 1-2 ml intradermally, subcutaneously, and under muscular fascia into
      patient approximately 10 minutes before skin incision. This will allow mapping of the
      lymphatic channels for identification for bypass. The node dissection will then be performed
      with preservation of the anterior branch of the axillary vein in the axilla. Afferent
      lymphatic vessels will be sutured into a branch of the axillary vein distal to a competen
      valve. The total duration of the surgery is approximately 3 hours. The LYMPHA technique
      accounts for an additional 30 min to the standard 2-2.5 hours allocated to the node
      dissection.

      Pre-surgery, patients will have baseline limb circumference measurements of both the
      surgery-affected and unaffected arms and by lymphoscintigraphy. Patients will be followed up
      clinically at every 6 months up to a year. At each follow-up visit, patients will have a
      physical examination and their circumference of their limbs taken. Patients will also fill
      out a LyQLI, SF-36, DASH administered by the Clinical Research Coordinator pre-and
      post-surgery. Each patient will have a total of 1 years of participation time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>lymphatic flow</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in lymphatic flow between LYMPHA technique group and Non-LYMPHA technique group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>limb volume</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in limb volume between LYMPHA technique group and Non-LYMPHA technique group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>lymphatic flow</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in lymphatic flow between LYMPHA technique group and Non-LYMPHA technique group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>limb volume</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in limb volume between LYMPHA technique group and Non-LYMPHA technique group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphedema, Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LYMPHA technique group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LVA at the time of Axillary Dissection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-LYMPHA technique group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No preventive surgical approach</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LYMPHA(LYmphatic Microsurgical Preventive Healing Approach) technique</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive a lymphatic-venous anastomosis at time of their required Axillary Dissection</description>
    <arm_group_label>LYMPHA technique group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Node-positive cancer requiring an axillary or lymphadenectomy

          -  Below 30 Body Mass Index

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving a sentinel lymph node biopsy

          -  Patients with established preoperative lymphedema

          -  Patients with post-thrombotic syndrome, peripheral vascular disease

          -  Pregnant patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphedema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Cancer Lymphedema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

