<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04321187</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>31-437 ex 18/19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04321187</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Influence of Prostate Cancer Radiation on Aging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Influence of Radiotherapy on the Dynamics of Aging in Prostate Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Graz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies have reported that cancer survivors develop age-related chronic conditions
      like frailty, sarcopenia, cardiac dysfunction, and cognitive impairment earlier and/or at a
      greater burden than similarly aged individuals never diagnosed with cancer or exposed to
      cancer therapies.

      However, the knowledge about aging-associated consequences of cancer treatment and the
      processes that underlie differential responses to therapy is very limited. In 2018, a think
      tank established by the National Cancer Institute has defined various research needs to
      expand the evidence base for aging-related consequences of cancer treatment, such as studies
      to examine aging-related processes that include regularly performed assessments capturing
      factors associated with physical function or studies to elucidate pathways that lead to the
      emergence of aging phenotypes and to understand the relationships between biomarkers of aging
      and functional outcomes in cancer survivors. In addition, study inclusion of older adults
      with comorbidities and higher levels of frailty has been proposed to achieve an improved
      understanding of functional outcomes at any age.

      Hypotheses / objectives We hypothesize that prostate cancer radiotherapy accelerates
      aging-related processes, furthermore, aging-related biomarkers may predict functional
      outcomes and represent early indicators of aging phenotypes. Primary objectives of the
      proposed study are the determination of the aging-related consequences of radiotherapy in
      prostate cancer patients and the evaluation of the relationship between biomarkers of aging
      and age-related clinical conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Systematic evaluations of functional and cognitive status, comorbidities, health status,
      mobility, nutritional status, psychological status, and social circumstances as well as
      measurements of cellular senescence and chronic inflammation will be performed in a cohort of
      prostate cancer patients at baseline (before radiotherapy), at the end of radiotherapy and at
      follow-up intervals thereafter. The evaluation of aging-related biomarkers will include
      determination of markers of cellular senescence and markers of systemic inflammation. The
      correlation between genetic variants modulating telomere length and the risk of developing
      age-related phenotypes will also be analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functionality - activities of daily living</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Functional decline measured by Activities of Daily Living examination (range, 0-6; high values indicate high functionality and improved outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functionality - instrumental activities of daily living</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Functional decline measured by the Instrumental Activities of Daily Living examination (range, 0-8; high values indicate high functionality and improved outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive disorder measured by the Mini-Mental State Examination (range, 0-30; high values indicate normal cognition and improved outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comorbidities measured by the Charlson comorbidity index (range, 0-37; high score indicates high rate of comorbidities and worse outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Mental disorder measured by the Geriatric depression scale (range, 0-30; higher values indicate depression and worse outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Mobility measured by the Timed up and go test (≥12 seconds to complete the Timed up and go test indicates mobility impairment and worse outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of medications taken</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Polypharmacy represents an aging related condition (high number of medication taken indicates worse outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation induced toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of acute and late side effects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">334</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Aging Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Radiotherapy; Complications</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        prostate cancer patients treated at the Department of Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology,
        Comprehensive Cancer Center, Medical University of Graz. Prostate cancer patients who are
        candidates for curative radiotherapy will be invited to take part by the local
        investigators.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Prostate cancer

          -  Candidate to definitive radiation treatment

          -  Local or locally advanced disease

          -  Aged ≥ 65 years

          -  Informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to give written informed consent

          -  Metastatic disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tanja Langsenlehner</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Graz, Dept. of Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tanja Langsenlehner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>004331638587869</phone>
    <email>tanja.langsenlehner@medunigraz.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tanja Langsenlehner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>004331638587869</phone>
      <email>tanja.langsenlehner@medunigraz.at</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Renner W, Krenn-Pilko S, Gruber HJ, Herrmann M, Langsenlehner T. Relative telomere length and prostate cancer mortality. Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis. 2018 Nov;21(4):579-583. doi: 10.1038/s41391-018-0068-3. Epub 2018 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>30082901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guida JL, Ahles TA, Belsky D, Campisi J, Cohen HJ, DeGregori J, Fuldner R, Ferrucci L, Gallicchio L, Gavrilov L, Gavrilova N, Green PA, Jhappan C, Kohanski R, Krull K, Mandelblatt J, Ness KK, O'Mara A, Price N, Schrack J, Studenski S, Theou O, Tracy RP, Hurria A. Measuring Aging and Identifying Aging Phenotypes in Cancer Survivors. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2019 Dec 1;111(12):1245-1254. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djz136.</citation>
    <PMID>31321426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>telomere length</keyword>
  <keyword>aging</keyword>
  <keyword>radiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>In is not planned to make individual participant data (IPD) available to other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

