<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04325204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00115228</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23AG065452</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04325204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Faith-Based Toolbox for African Americans With Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Creating a Faith-Based Toolbox for African Americans Living With Moderate and Severe Dementia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to create and test faith-based activities that might be useful
      for African American adults with moderate and severe dementia and their caregivers. A total
      of 60 people will take part in the intervention; 30 people with moderate and severe dementia
      and 30 family caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      African Americans (AAs) are more likely than other racial/ethnic groups to be diagnosed with
      Alzheimer's disease and related dementias (ADRD) and will account for 20% of persons living
      with dementia (PLWD) by 2050. PLWD experience progressive distress and confusion, which
      decreases their quality of life and also contributes to the emotional strain, burden, social
      isolation, and depression experienced by caregivers. Research indicates that religiosity (the
      inner commitment to one's faith through integration of religious beliefs and practices into
      one's life) can serve as a protective factor against the stressors associated with caregiving
      and living with ADRD.

      The goal of this clinical feasibility trial and NIH stage 1 intervention development project
      is to go beyond the four walls of the church to find ways to meet the spiritual needs of
      persons living with moderate and severe ADRD &quot;where they are&quot; in order to help them remain
      religiously and spiritually engaged. This study is premised on the notion that
      religious/spiritual engagement is possible and beneficial for PLWD and that this beneficial
      effect will extend to their caregivers.

      The purpose of this project is to design and test the feasibility of employing components of
      a Faith-based Home Activity Toolbox (Faith-HAT) and create intervention tools for a
      full-scale randomized controlled trial (RCT) to test the efficacy-effectiveness of
      faith-based programs on patient and caregiver outcomes.

      Thirty dyads of people with dementia and their caregivers will be enrolled in a 12 week
      program to test the feasibility and preliminary effectiveness of using Faith-HAT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants recruited within 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of the intervention will be assessed by how many months it takes to recruit all study participants. The researchers aim to complete recruitment within 12 months, enrolling 2-3 dyads per month.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Intervention Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 15</time_frame>
    <description>Engagement with the intervention will be assessed by the number of days per week that Faith-HAT was used by dyads during the 12 week intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of dyads completing the study</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 15</time_frame>
    <description>The feasibility of the intervention will be assessed by study retention, specifically, the number of dyads completing the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Zarit Burden Inventory Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of burden felt by caregivers will be assessed with the 22-item Zarit Burden Inventory. Responses are given on a scale from 0 to 4 where for 0 = never and 4 = nearly always. Total scores range from 0 to 88, where higher scores indicate greater feelings of caregiver burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Perceived Stress Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Caregiver stress will be assessed with the 14-item Perceived Stress Scale. Responses are given on a scale of 0 to 4 where 0 = never and 4 = very often. Total scores range from 0 to 56 with higher scores indicating greater perceived stress by caregivers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Center for Epidemiologic Studies - Depression (CES-D) Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Caregiver depression will be assessed with the 20-item Center for Epidemiologic Studies - Depression Scale. Caregivers are asked how frequently they have experienced specific symptoms of depression in the past week. Responses are given as 0 = rarely, 1 = 1-2 days, 2 = 3-4 days, and 4 = 5-7 days. Total scores range from 0 to 80 with higher scores indicating greater symptoms of depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Revised Memory and Behavior Problem Checklist Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The Revised Memory and Behavior Problem Checklist assesses the presence of problematic behaviors in persons with dementia as well as caregiver distress due to those problems. Caregivers complete to 24-item instrument by indicating whether or not the behavior has occurred and how distressing the behaviors are for them on a scale from 0 to 4 (where 0 = not at all and 4 = extremely). Total scores assessing caregiver reactions to problem behaviors range from 0 to 96 and higher scores indicate greater difficulty with problem behaviors.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Caregivers will wear ambulatory blood pressure monitors for 24 hours. Diastolic and systolic blood pressure will be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Heart Rate Variability Time Domain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Caregivers will wear wristband, a wearable-sensor (E4 wristwatch), that detects stress reactivity in an ecologically appropriate setting (to overcome the artificial setting of the clinical site) to collect longer-duration measurement of the time domain of heart rate variability. Mean peak-to-peak intervals will be assessed in seconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Heart Rate Variability Frequency Domain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Caregivers will wear wristband, a wearable-sensor (E4 wristwatch), that detects stress reactivity in an ecologically appropriate setting (to overcome the artificial setting of the clinical site) to collect longer-duration measurement of the frequency domain, measured in Hertz (Hz), of heart rate variability. Parasympathetic control is characterized as high frequency (0.15-0.40 Hz) while low frequency (0.04-0.15 Hz) characterizes both the sympathetic and parasympathetic activities. Exposure of an individual to a physical or mental stressor activates their stress response through the sympathetic nervous system (SNS) axis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Skin Conductance Level (SCL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Caregivers will wear wristband, a wearable-sensor (E4 wristwatch), that detects stress reactivity in an ecologically appropriate setting (to overcome the artificial setting of the clinical site) to collect longer-duration measurement of skin conductance level. Skin conductance level is the electrical conductivity of the skin. Skin conducts electricity better during physiological or psychological arousal, making skin conductance level a maker for measuring emotion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregivers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers of a person living with dementia will participate in the Faith-HAT intervention for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Persons living with dementia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Persons living with dementia will participate in the Faith-HAT intervention for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Faith-based Home Activity Toolbox (Faith-HAT)</intervention_name>
    <description>They will select activities from Faith-HAT at least 3 times a week. Possible examples of these activities include devotional readings, prayer, music, religious images, and video and audio recorded sermons.
Faith-HAT will be placed on online, which requires little technical know-how by users. The PI will provide training to participants on how to use the Faith-HAT and online diary on the tablet computer provided by the project.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Caregivers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Persons living with dementia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Caregiver Inclusion Criteria:

          -  at least 18 years of age

          -  reside with and care for (average of 4 hours/per day of unpaid assistance) for a
             family or friend experiencing signs and symptoms of moderate or severe ADRD as
             indicated through self-report or family caregiver report

          -  able to read, speak, and understand English

          -  cognitively intact

          -  access to a wireless internet connection (wi-fi)

          -  access to a phone or mobile device that accepts text messages

        PLWD Inclusion Criteria:

          -  community-dwelling experiencing signs and symptoms of moderate or severe ADRD through
             self-report or family caregiver report

          -  has a family caregiver that resides with them and is willing to participate

          -  no plan for institutionalization in the next month

          -  history of participating in private or public religious activities

          -  understands English (toolbox activities will be produced in English)

          -  family and self-reporting of the level of cognitive impairment identified according to
             the signs and symptoms of moderate and severe ADRD associated with the Alzheimer's
             Association16 categorization of moderate/middle, and severe/late stages of dementia

        Caregiver Exclusion Criteria:

          -  does not have a history of participating in private or public religious activities

          -  hostile to PLWD religious expression

          -  has active plans to move to another residence without family member with ADRD

        PLWD Exclusion Criteria:

          -  has active plans to move from under care of primary caregiver

          -  routinely attends church

          -  hostile to religion

          -  unwilling to engage in Faith-HAT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fayron Epps, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fayron Epps, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <phone>404-727-6936</phone>
    <email>fepps@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fayron Epps</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Religion</keyword>
  <keyword>Spirituality</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All of the individual participant data collected during the trial will be available for sharing, after deidentification.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available for sharing beginning 3 months and ending 5 years following article publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data will be available for sharing with researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal, in order to achieve aims in the approved proposal. Proposals should be directed to fepps@emory.edu. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement. Data will be available for 5 years at a third party website.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

