<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04322409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20-042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04322409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NMES and Chronic Ankle Instability</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation (NMES) on Improving Function in Individuals With Chronic Ankle Instability</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Appalachian State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Appalachian State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic ankle instability is associated with changes in the nervous system that amount to
      increased difficulty in activating the stabilizing muscles of the ankle. Neuromuscular
      Electrical Stimulation involves using electricity to activate those muscles in bursts, and is
      commonly used to improve muscle function in those with ACL injury. This study will provide 5
      treatments over 2 weeks in patients with Chronic Ankle Instability and determine if
      Electrical Stimulation can change neural excitability, balance, neuromuscular control, and
      perceived function in these individuals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Individuals with joint injuries, including ankle sprain and anterior cruciate ligament (ACL)
      injury have been observed to exhibit changes in central nervous system function that
      potentially predispose them for further injury (Needle et al. 2017). In ankle sprains,
      repeated sensations of rolling and giving-way known as chronic ankle instability (CAI)
      emerges in nearly 50 percent of those with a history of ankle sprain (Holland et al. 2019),
      with symptoms tied to changes in central nervous system function. As the understanding of
      these pathologies have expanded, researchers have begun to attempt to identify
      neuromodulatory interventions capable of addressing injury-induced maladaptive
      neuroplasticity, thus improving function (Bruce et al. 2020, In Press).

      Among those with ACL injury, one of the most common interventions implemented to overcome
      muscle activation deficits includes neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) (Lepley et
      al. 2015). This intervention is often used in the initial stages of post-surgical recovery to
      improve quadriceps function; however, it's use in other populations of joint injury (i.e.
      ankle sprain) is far more limited. Some previous research has looked at the effects of NMES
      on acute ankle sprains, as this is the timeframe in which muscle activation deficits would be
      most evident (Wainwright et al. 2019), but there is very limited evidence in those with CAI.
      It was potentially thought that activation deficits are less evident and strengthening may
      overcome these deficits in those with chronic injury; however, new insights have identified
      additional mechanisms by which NMES may be effective (Lepley et al. 2015). Aside from
      generating activation of a generally inactive muscle, NMES when performed at high intensities
      has been described to improve neuromuscular function through disinhibitory mechanisms. That
      is that increased somatosensation from the electrical stimulation raises the central nervous
      sytem's awareness of that muscle's activation, yielding decreased inhibition and ultimately
      increased neural excitability.

      Our previous research using cortically-directed interventions demonstrated that improving
      neural excitability yielded better function in patients with chronic ankle instability (Bruce
      et al. 2020). This study will follow a similar framework; however, determining if these
      changes can be induced via a peripheral intervention. These findings have the ability to
      reframe the current treatment for CAI.

      We are pursuing the following 2 specific aims:

        1. To determine if NMES changes neural excitability (MEP size, H:M ratio, silent period)
           compared to a placebo treatment in participants with chronic ankle instability.

           H1: NMES will increase MEP size, H:M ratio, and decrease cortical silent period in
           individuals with CAI compared to the placebo treatment.

        2. To determine if changes in neural excitability related to NMES or placebo treatment
           result in improved function (balance, muscle activation, outcomes) in participants with
           chronic ankle instability.

      H2: Increased neural excitability will yield improved balance (postural stability indices),
      muscle activation, and patient-reported function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2x3 Factorial; 2 groups by 3 time points</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tibialis Anterior corticospinal excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Motor evoked potential size of tibialis anterior</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Soleus corticospinal excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Motor evoked potential size of soleus</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peroneus Longus corticospinal excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Motor evoked potential size of peroneus longus</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tibialis anterior reflexive excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>H:M ratio of tibialis anterior</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Soleus reflexive excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>H:M ratio of soleus</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peroneus longus reflexive excitability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>H:M ratio of peroneus longus</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamic postural stability index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Postural stability indices during a hop-to-stabilization task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tibialis Anterior muscle activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean electromyography from the tibialis anterior during a hop-to-stabilization task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Soleus muscle activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean electromyography from the soleus during a hop-to-stabilization task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peroneus Longus muscle activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean electromyography from the peroneus during a hop-to-stabilization task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ankle Eversion Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Isometric ankle eversion strength</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side-to-side Hop Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Time to complete 10 hops over 30 cm lines</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Foot &amp; Ankle ability measure, Disablement in the Physically Active Scale, Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Foot &amp; Ankle ability measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects complete FAAM questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disablement in the Physically Active Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects complete DPA questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week-2 (end of intervention), Week-4 (retention)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects complete TSK-11 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Ankle Instability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NMES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental treatment of Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation over the Peroneus Longus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo treatment of Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation over the same region as the peroneus longus</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuromuscular Electrical Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>5 sessions that consist of NMES over the peroneus longus muscle. This consists of a biphasic current with a phase duration of 240us delivered in a frequency of 75 pules per second, with a ramp-up time of 2-seconds, followed by a 50-s rest period (no stimulation). Each cycle will consist of 10 seconds of &quot;on&quot; time, and 50 seconds off, with 10 cycles being performed each session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NMES</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NMES</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>5 sessions that consist of 11-minutes of TENS over the skin of the peroneus longus. This consists of a biphasic current will be continuously applied at 100 pulses per second, with a phase duration of 100us for 10 minutes. The intensity will be turned up until the point the subjects feel the current (sensory threshold)</description>
    <arm_group_label>TENS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TENS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be healthy subjects between the ages of 18-35. The primary inclusion criteria
        for this study is the presence of chronic ankle instability (CAI). According to guidelines
        from the International Ankle Consortium, this means subjects will report having a history
        of one or more ankle sprains (the first &gt;1 year ago), and repeated sensations of giving-way
        as measured by a score &gt;10 on the Identification of Functional Ankle Instability instrument
        (IDFAI).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of fracture or surgery to the legs

          -  Injury to the lower legs within 3 months prior to reporting for testing that resulted
             in modified physical activity.

          -  Currently involved in an ankle rehabilitation program.

          -  Failing to meet standards for the safe practice of transcranial magnetic stimulation
             and transcranial direct current stimulation (See questionnaire). Briefly, this
             includes personal or family history of seizure or epilepsy; current medication use
             that raises risk of seizure; implanted metal, medication devices, etc.; history of
             brain or heart surgery; and sensitivity of the scalp or skin.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alan R Needle, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>8282624039</phone>
    <email>needlear@appstate.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leon Levine Hall for Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boone</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alan R Needle</last_name>
      <phone>828-262-4039</phone>
      <email>needlear@appstate.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Instability</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

