<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04328649</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PoliclinicoCasilino</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04328649</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical, Structural and Mechanical Features in Patients With Left Bundle Branch Block.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical, Structural and Mechanical Features in Patients With Left Bundle Branch Block: an Observational and Prospective Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Policlinico Casilino ASL RMB</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Policlinico Casilino ASL RMB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical, structural and mechanical features in patients with left bundle branch block.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Left bundle-branch block (LBBB) is an electrocardiographic marker often associated with
      underlying cardiac disease (such as coronary artery disease, dilated cardiomyopathy, etc) but
      in some cases it is also found in patients with isolated LBBB defined as &quot;none apparent
      structural heart disease&quot;.

      Several investigations in animal and human study have showed a different electroanatomical
      activation in isolated LBBB when compared to LBBB in heart failure patients mostly due to
      coronary artery disease. The sequence of endocardial activation through the left ventricle
      has also proven to be heterogeneous in heart failure occuring at different septal regions.
      This electrical and mechanical variability seems to be related to location of LBBB block or
      lesion that could be proximal, distal or diffuse, consequently influencing also
      electrocardiographic aspects.

      These considerations explain and justify the great variability in the proposed &quot;true or
      typical LBBB&quot; definitions (derived from from Strauss, Perrin and Marican definitions and from
      Heart Association/American College Cardiology Foundation/ European Society of Cardiology
      guidelines) but also shift attention to relatively new concept of atypical LBBB definitions
      with extreme left or right axis deviation and of non specific intraventricular conduction
      delay defined as a wide QRS (≥110 ms) without the appearance of left and right bundle-branch
      block. In fact, several investigations have shown that QRS axis deviation is a predictor of
      unfavorable outcome after cardiac resynchronization therapy and LBBB. The less favorable
      outcome of cardiac resynchronization therapy candidates with LBBB and left axis deviation
      seems to be associated to the presence of a shorter activation delay, scar tissue and left
      ventricular hypertrophy. Moreover, actual LBBB definitions recommended by guidelines in
      cardiac resynchronization therapy patients differ significantly and only individual ECG
      criteria (such as electrocardiographic intervals QS or RS in lead V1, notch and no q wave in
      lead V5, V6, I and avL) seems to be associated to clinical outcome when compared with
      combining criteria.

      Finally, a frequent dyssynchrony of ventricular activation due to LBBB may be responsible for
      a dyssynchrony-related cardiomyopathy that needs to be identified early and differentiated
      from other forms of dilated cardiomyopathy through a multiparametric approach such as
      genetic, clinical data, electrocardiography and cardiac magnetic resonance. In fact, in
      isolated LBBB undergone cardiac magnetic resonance it was observed a greater left ventricular
      volumes and lower global left ventricular Ejection Fraction despite the absence of
      cardiovascular disease as compared with control subject. Despite this, comparison between
      isolated LBBB and structural heart disease shows a different myocardial mechanism all the
      more unfavourable the more significant is the presence of underlying myocardial scarring. In
      the other hand, isolated LBBB, dyssynchrony-related cardiomyopathy and myocardial scarring
      could present different temporal phase in the clinical history of the same patient and that
      must be early identified.

      The aim of this present large‐scale prospective observational study is to evaluate 1)
      clinical, electrocardiographic and imaging features in a population of patients with typical
      and atypical LBBB and &quot; non specific intraventricular conduction delay&quot; pattern during a
      long-term follow up and 2) association among eventual different LBBB patterns (typical,
      atypical (LBBB and extreme left and/or right axis deviation, fragmentation) and &quot; non
      specific intraventricular conduction delay &quot; pattern and tissue characterization, mechanical
      myocardial activation and perfusion. 3) a possible time-related evolution from &quot;non specific
      intraventricular conduction delay&quot; patterns to typical or atypical LBBB.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of ECG pattern distribution in LBBB patients</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of underlying structural heart diseases in different LBBB pattern</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with stress induced myocardial ischemia during Stress Magnetic resonance</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number or participants with late gadolinium enhancement during cardiac magnetic resonance</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number and of participants with isolated LBBB evolving to dyssynchrony-related cardiomyopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with mechanical dyssynchrony evaluated with Echocardiography</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Strain, Strain Rate, intraventricular timing Delay between left ventricular lateral and Septal wall</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Left Bundle-Branch Block</condition>
  <condition>Electrocardiographic Pattens</condition>
  <condition>Clinical Features</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        In this prospective observational study we consider to enroll patients with LBBB admitted
        to our Cardiology Department and Ambulatory Care Unit recording different ECG patterns,
        risk factors, genetic, underlying heart disease, imaging parameters (Echocardiographic and
        Cardiac Magnetic Resonance) and treatment (either pharmacological or interventional).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Every patient with electrocardiographic diagnosis of LBBB admitted to our Cardiology
             Department and Ambulatory Care Unit

          -  ECG standard criteria from typical, atypical and NIVCD

          -  Patients who have given their informed consent in writing.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Patients who have not given their informed consent in writing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonardo Calò, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>0623188406</phone>
    <email>leonardo.calo@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Leonardo Calò, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>0623188406</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akhtari S, Chuang ML, Salton CJ, Berg S, Kissinger KV, Goddu B, O'Donnell CJ, Manning WJ. Effect of isolated left bundle-branch block on biventricular volumes and ejection fraction: a cardiovascular magnetic resonance assessment. J Cardiovasc Magn Reson. 2018 Sep 20;20(1):66. doi: 10.1186/s12968-018-0457-8.</citation>
    <PMID>30231875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strik M, Regoli F, Auricchio A, Prinzen F. Electrical and mechanical ventricular activation during left bundle branch block and resynchronization. J Cardiovasc Transl Res. 2012 Apr;5(2):117-26. doi: 10.1007/s12265-012-9351-1. Epub 2012 Feb 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22311563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Surawicz B, Childers R, Deal BJ, Gettes LS, Bailey JJ, Gorgels A, Hancock EW, Josephson M, Kligfield P, Kors JA, Macfarlane P, Mason JW, Mirvis DM, Okin P, Pahlm O, Rautaharju PM, van Herpen G, Wagner GS, Wellens H; American Heart Association Electrocardiography and Arrhythmias Committee, Council on Clinical Cardiology; American College of Cardiology Foundation; Heart Rhythm Society. AHA/ACCF/HRS recommendations for the standardization and interpretation of the electrocardiogram: part III: intraventricular conduction disturbances: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association Electrocardiography and Arrhythmias Committee, Council on Clinical Cardiology; the American College of Cardiology Foundation; and the Heart Rhythm Society. Endorsed by the International Society for Computerized Electrocardiology. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Mar 17;53(11):976-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2008.12.013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19281930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>European Society of Cardiology (ESC); European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA), Brignole M, Auricchio A, Baron-Esquivias G, Bordachar P, Boriani G, Breithardt OA, Cleland J, Deharo JC, Delgado V, Elliott PM, Gorenek B, Israel CW, Leclercq C, Linde C, Mont L, Padeletti L, Sutton R, Vardas PE. 2013 ESC guidelines on cardiac pacing and cardiac resynchronization therapy: the task force on cardiac pacing and resynchronization therapy of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Developed in collaboration with the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA). Europace. 2013 Aug;15(8):1070-118. doi: 10.1093/europace/eut206. Epub 2013 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23801827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strauss DG, Selvester RH, Wagner GS. Defining left bundle branch block in the era of cardiac resynchronization therapy. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Mar 15;107(6):927-34. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2010.11.010. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21376930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Padanilam BJ, Morris KE, Olson JA, Rippy JS, Walsh MN, Subramanian N, Vidal A, Prystowsky EN, Steinberg LA. The surface electrocardiogram predicts risk of heart block during right heart catheterization in patients with preexisting left bundle branch block: implications for the definition of complete left bundle branch block. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2010 Jul;21(7):781-5. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8167.2009.01714.x. Epub 2010 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20132380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kisiel R, Fijorek K, Moskal P, Kukla P, Pavlinec C, Stec J, Czarnecka D, Jastrzębski M. True left bundle branch block and long-term mortality in cardiac resynchronisation therapy patients. Kardiol Pol. 2019;77(3):371-379. doi: 10.5603/KP.a2019.0032. Epub 2019 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>30799545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eschalier R, Ploux S, Ritter P, Haïssaguerre M, Ellenbogen KA, Bordachar P. Nonspecific intraventricular conduction delay: Definitions, prognosis, and implications for cardiac resynchronization therapy. Heart Rhythm. 2015 May;12(5):1071-9. doi: 10.1016/j.hrthm.2015.01.023. Epub 2015 Jan 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25614250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Storkås HS, Hansen TF, Tahri JB, Lauridsen TK, Olsen FJ, Borgquist R, Vinther M, Lindhardt TB, Bruun NE, Søgaard P, Risum N. Left axis deviation in patients with left bundle branch block is a marker of myocardial disease associated with poor response to cardiac resynchronization therapy. J Electrocardiol. 2019 Apr 5. pii: S0022-0736(18)30914-2. doi: 10.1016/j.jelectrocard.2019.04.007. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>31003852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Stipdonk AMW, Hoogland R, Ter Horst I, Kloosterman M, Vanbelle S, Crijns HJGM, Prinzen FW, Meine M, Maass AH, Vernooy K. Evaluating Electrocardiography-Based Identification of Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy Responders Beyond Current Left Bundle Branch Block Definitions. JACC Clin Electrophysiol. 2020 Feb;6(2):193-203. doi: 10.1016/j.jacep.2019.10.009. Epub 2019 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>32081223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanna GD, Merlo M, Moccia E, Fabris E, Masia SL, Finocchiaro G, Parodi G, Sinagra G. Left bundle branch block-induced cardiomyopathy: a diagnostic proposal for a poorly explored pathological entity. Int J Cardiol. 2020 Jan 15;299:199-205. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2019.06.008. Epub 2019 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>31186131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strauss DG, Selvester RH. The QRS complex--a biomarker that &quot;images&quot; the heart: QRS scores to quantify myocardial scar in the presence of normal and abnormal ventricular conduction. J Electrocardiol. 2009 Jan-Feb;42(1):85-96. doi: 10.1016/j.jelectrocard.2008.07.011. Epub 2008 Sep 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18790501</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Policlinico Casilino ASL RMB</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Leonardo Calò, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, FESC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bundle-Branch Block</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Block</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

