<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04320368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Z181100001518005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04320368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>China Alzheimer's and Neurodegenerative Disorder Research</brief_title>
  <acronym>CANDOR</acronym>
  <official_title>China National Clinical Research Center Alzheimer's Disease and Neurodegenerative Disorder Research</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center study that has three cohorts: 1) cognitive normal cohort (CN), 2)
      Alzheimer's disease cohort (AD) and 3) vascular cognitive impairment cohort (VCI). The goal
      of this study is to understand the risk factors of AD and VCI and to identify high risk
      patients for early intervention. It will collect demographic information, family history,
      medical history, neuropsychological tests, imaging studies and biological samples through
      standard and uniform procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this prospective study, we will recruit subjects into one of the three groups based on
      inclusion and exclusion criteria: 1) CN, 2) AD and 3) VCI. We will follow up with each of
      them subject at designated time points up to 2 years. We will collect demographic, medical,
      imaging (MRI and PET scans), genetic information and various biological samples (blood,
      saliva, urine and feces) during the study period. This study uses a case-control study
      design. The matched cases will have similar age, gender and education levels. By studying the
      relationship between risk factors of AD and VCI, we will establish norms and parameters in
      the Chinese population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Data records</measure>
    <time_frame>2-3 years</time_frame>
    <description>We will record the number of participants at several follow-up visits, the basic condition at the follow-up. If the visit is not completed, record the cause of this loss.
At baseline, record the demographic information, past medical history and medication history, vital signs and neuropsychological scales. The PET-CT scan were recorded during the 2-year visit. Collect the results of cerebral MRI, laboratory tests and neuropsychological scales of all participants at baseline, 12 and 24 months and biological samples. For VCI cohort, we will record the basic conditions and partial neuropsychological scales at 3-month and 6-month follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological scales</measure>
    <time_frame>2-3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), Montreal-Cognitive Assessment (MoCA), the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS), The Activities of Daily Living Questionnaire(ADL), Digit Span Memory Test, Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT), Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure Test(ROCF), Trail Making Test A and B, Stroop test, Verbal Fluency Test, Boston Naming Test, Clock-Drawing Test, Narcissism Test (NPI), Symbol Digit Modalities Test(SDMT), Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alzheimer's disease cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>40-100 years old (≥ 40 years old, ≤ 100 years old)
cognitive impairment: Alzheimer's questionnaire ＞4 and MMSE&lt;22
informed consent is signed by the patient or his family members</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vascular cognitive impairment cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>40-100 years old (≥ 40 years old, ≤ 100 years old)
acute cerebral infarction is first diagnosed according to WHO criteria 1
the time from onset to hospital ≤7 days
informed consent is signed by the patient or his family members</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A cohort of people with normal cognitive function</arm_group_label>
    <description>40-100 years old (≥ 40 years old, ≤ 100 years old), without cognitive impairment, Alzheimer's questionnaire ≤4 and MMSE≥22
informed consent is signed by the patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      blood, saliva, urine and feces
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Alzheimer's disease cohort and Vascular cognitive impairment cohort will be recruited from
        participating hospitals.

        Cognitively normal cohort will be recruited from the community.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria Alzheimer's disease cohort

          1. 40-100 years old (≥ 40 years old, ≤ 100 years old)

          2. cognitive impairment: Alzheimer's questionnaire ＞4 and MMSE&lt;22

          3. informed consent is signed by the patient or his family members

        Vascular cognitive impairment cohort

          1. 40-100 years old (≥ 40 years old, ≤ 100 years old)

          2. acute cerebral infarction is first diagnosed according to WHO criteria 1

          3. the time from onset to hospital ≤7 days

          4. informed consent is signed by the patient or his family members

        A cohort of people with normal cognitive function

          1. 40-100 years old (≥ 40 years old, ≤ 100 years old), without cognitive impairment,
             Alzheimer's questionnaire ≤4 and MMSE≥22

          2. informed consent is signed by the patient

        Exclusion criteria:

        1. Alzheimer's disease cohort

          1. Any other diseases that can cause cognitive impairment (such as dementia with Lewy
             bodies (DLB), frontotemporal dementia (FTLD), Parkinson's disease dementia (PDD),
             intracranial masses that impair cognition, history of severe brain trauma, normal
             pressure hydrocephalus, cerebrovascular disease with obvious clinical symptoms, etc.

          2. Sequelae after previous history of severe central nervous system infection, multiple
             sclerosis, autoimmune encephalitis, Hashimoto's encephalopathy, etc.

          3. Previous history of instable epilepsy

          4. Systemic diseases affect the central nervous system, for abnormal liver and kidney
             functions (abdominal dialysis, hemodialysis, AST≥3× upper limit of normal value (ULN),
             ALT≥3× upper limit of normal value (ULN) or total bilirubin ≥2×ULN

          5. History of hereditary diseases that affect cognitive function (such as Huntington's
             disease, down syndrome, CADASIL, adrenal leukodystrophy, mitochondrial encephalopathy,
             etc.)

          6. Long-term heavy drinking history (alcohol content more than 42 degree liquor, more
             than 150g/day, alcohol consumption more than 12 months)

          7. History of severe pulmonary diseases (COPD, pulmonary encephalopathy)

          8. History of serious cardiovascular disease (heart failure, severe hypertension)

          9. Infection and immune-related diseases affecting the central nervous system (systemic
             lupus erythematosus, undertreated HIV infection or a history of CNS syphilis
             infection, etc.)

         10. Metabolic and endocrine disorders (requiring new treatment or adjustment of current
             treatment for thyroid dysfunction, folate or vitamin B12 deficiency)

         11. Unstable psychosis or long-term use of antipsychotic drugs (more than 6 months)

         12. History of malignant tumors (tumors of nervous system and other sites) active for
             nearly 1 year

         13. Contraindications for MRI (e.g. pacemakers, stents, claustrophobia, etc.) or do not
             cooperate or cannot carry out PET examination

         14. Uneducated illiterates

         15. Hearing impairment, visual impairment and poor coordination

         16. Withdraw or reject the study

        2. Vascular cognitive impairment cohort

        1) Previous silent cerebral infarction with no symptoms or signs 2) Non-cerebrovascular
        events 3) The time from onset to treatment is more than 7 days 6)Severe neurological
        impairment (NIHSS score, article 9 &gt; 2;1 a &gt; 1;1 b &gt; 1) 7) Any other diseases that can
        cause cognitive impairment (such as dementia with Lewy bodies (DLB), frontotemporal
        dementia (FTLD), Parkinson's disease dementia (PDD), intracranial masses that impair
        cognition, history of severe brain trauma, normal pressure hydrocephalus, cerebrovascular
        disease with obvious clinical symptoms, etc.

        8) Sequelae after previous history of severe central nervous system infection, multiple
        sclerosis, autoimmune encephalitis, Hashimoto's encephalopathy, etc.

        9) Previous history of instable epilepsy 10) Systemic diseases affect the central nervous
        system, for abnormal liver and kidney functions (abdominal dialysis, hemodialysis, AST≥3×
        upper limit of normal value (ULN), ALT≥3× upper limit of normal value (ULN) or total
        bilirubin ≥2×ULN 11) History of hereditary diseases that affect cognitive function (such as
        Huntington's disease, down syndrome, CADASIL, adrenal leukodystrophy, mitochondrial
        encephalopathy, etc.) 12) Long-term heavy drinking history (alcohol content more than 42
        degree liquor, more than 150g/day, alcohol consumption more than 12 months) 13) History of
        severe pulmonary diseases (COPD, pulmonary encephalopathy) 14) History of serious
        cardiovascular disease (heart failure, severe hypertension) 15) Infection and
        immune-related diseases affecting the central nervous system (systemic lupus erythematosus,
        undertreated HIV infection or a history of CNS syphilis infection, etc.) 16) Metabolic and
        endocrine disorders (requiring new treatment or adjustment of current treatment for thyroid
        dysfunction, folate or vitamin B12 deficiency) 17) Unstable psychosis or long-term use of
        antipsychotic drugs (more than 6 months) 18) history of malignant tumors (tumors of nervous
        system and other sites) active for nearly 1 year 19) contraindications for MRI (e.g.
        pacemakers, stents, claustrophobia, etc.) or do not cooperate or cannot carry out PET
        examination 20) uneducated illiterates 21) hearing impairment, visual impairment and poor
        coordination 22) withdraw or reject the study

        Cognitive normal cohort

          1. any disease that can cause cognitive impairment (such as Alzheimer's disease, dementia
             with Lewy bodies (DLB), frontotemporal dementia (FTLD), Parkinson's disease dementia
             (PDD), intracranial masses that impair cognition, history of severe brain trauma,
             normal pressure hydrocephalus, cerebrovascular disease with obvious clinical symptoms,
             etc.

          2. sequelae after previous history of severe central nervous system infection, multiple
             sclerosis, autoimmune encephalitis, Hashimoto's encephalopathy, etc.

          3. previous history of instable epilepsy

          4. systemic diseases affect the central nervous system, for abnormal liver and kidney
             functions (abdominal dialysis, hemodialysis, AST≥3× upper limit of normal value (ULN),
             ALT≥3× upper limit of normal value (ULN) or total bilirubin ≥2×ULN

          5. history of hereditary diseases that affect cognitive function (such as Huntington's
             disease, down syndrome, CADASIL, adrenal leukodystrophy, mitochondrial encephalopathy,
             etc.)

          6. long-term heavy drinking history (alcohol content more than 42 degree liquor, more
             than 150g/day, alcohol consumption more than 12 months)

          7. history of severe pulmonary diseases (COPD, pulmonary encephalopathy)

          8. history of serious cardiovascular disease (heart failure, severe hypertension)

          9. infection and immune-related diseases affecting the central nervous system (systemic
             lupus erythematosus, undertreated HIV infection or a history of CNS syphilis
             infection, etc.)

         10. metabolic and endocrine disorders (requiring new treatment or adjustment of current
             treatment for thyroid dysfunction, folate or vitamin B12 deficiency)

         11. unstable psychosis or long-term use of antipsychotic drugs (more than 6 months)

         12. history of malignant tumors (tumors of nervous system and other sites) active for
             nearly 1 year

         13. contraindications for MRI (e.g. pacemakers, stents, claustrophobia, etc.) or do not
             cooperate or cannot carry out PET examination

         14. uneducated illiterates

         15. hearing impairment, visual impairment and poor coordination

         16. withdraw or reject the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jiong Shi</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shiping Li, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86 15830116199</phone>
    <email>drlishiping@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Tiantan Hospital，Capital Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>110000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shiping Li, doctor</last_name>
      <phone>+86 15830116199</phone>
      <email>drlishiping@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prince MJ, Wu F, Guo Y, Gutierrez Robledo LM, O'Donnell M, Sullivan R, Yusuf S. The burden of disease in older people and implications for health policy and practice. Lancet. 2015 Feb 7;385(9967):549-62. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61347-7. Epub 2014 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25468153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alzheimer's Association. 2016 Alzheimer's disease facts and figures. Alzheimers Dement. 2016 Apr;12(4):459-509.</citation>
    <PMID>27570871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 10, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 22, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beijing Tiantan Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jiong Shi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>vascular cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>dementia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neurodegenerative Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data are available upon reasonable request.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available at one year after the study completion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Committee review</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

