<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04328558</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Medipol Hospital 10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04328558</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clavipectoral Fascia Plane Block for Clavicle Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effectiveness of Clavipectoral Fascia Plane Block for Analgesia After Clavicle Surgery: Randomized, Prospective Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medipol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medipol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The pain after clavicle fracture surgery may be managed with combined superficial cervical
      plexus-interscalene block and recently clavipectoral fascia plane block (CPB). CPB was
      defined by Valdes in 2017 firstly. It may be used for postoperative analgesia after clavicle
      surgery. CPB may be an alternative to interscalene brachial plexus block.

      The aim of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of the US-guided CPB for postoperative
      analgesia management compare to no intervention control group after clavicle surgery. The
      primary aim is to compare postoperative opioid consumption and the secondary aim is to
      evaluate postoperative pain scores (VAS), adverse effects related with opioids (allergic
      reaction, nausea, vomiting).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clavicle fracture is common in men and children after a direct fall on shoulder during sport
      activity such as cycling or an injury during a traffic accident. The pain after clavicle
      fracture surgery may be managed with combined superficial cervical plexus-interscalene block
      and recently clavipectoral fascia plane block (CPB). CPB was defined by Valdes in 2017
      firstly. It may be used for postoperative analgesia after clavicle surgery. The clavipectoral
      fascia covers the clavicular site of the pectoralis major muscle. It provides the potential
      interfascial space between the clavicle and the pectoralis major muscle. CPB provide
      effective analgesia after clavicle surgery. It is also easy to perform. With this advantage
      and its analgesic effectiveness for clavicle surgery, CPB may be an alternative to
      interscalene brachial plexus block. However, randomized clinical efficacy trials are needed
      to investigate the effectiveness of CPB for clavicle fractures. In the literature, data about
      CPB is so limited, however it seems a good alternative to brachial plexus block for pain
      management after clavicle fracture The aim of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of the
      US-guided CPB for postoperative analgesia management compare to no intervention control group
      after clavicle surgery. The primary aim is to compare postoperative opioid consumption and
      the secondary aim is to evaluate postoperative pain scores (VAS), adverse effects related
      with opioids (allergic reaction, nausea, vomiting).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 22, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>There are two models for this study. The first group is clavipectoral fascia plane block group. The second one is no intervention control group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The patient and the anesthesiologist who performs postoperative pain evaluation will not know the group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline opioid consumption at postoperative 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 24 and 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The primary aim is to compare postoperative opioid consumption</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores (Visual analogue scores-VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from baseline pain scores at postoperative 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, and 24 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative pain assessment will be performed using the VAS score (0 = no pain, 10 = the most severe pain felt). The VAS scores will be recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Clavicle Injury</condition>
  <condition>Clavicle Fracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group CPB = Clavipectoral fascia plane block group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In group CPB, CPB will be performed with patients in the supine position. The probe will be placed on the anterior border of the medial third of the clavicle. A 22-gauge block needle will be inserted in a caudal to cephalic direction, the periosteum of the clavicle and the surrounding fascia will be visualized, 20 ml of 0.25% bupivacaine will be injected between these two layers. The local anesthetic spread to medial and lateral third of the clavicle will be seen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C = Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be administered ibuprofen 400 mgr IV every 8 hours in the postoperative period. A patient controlled device prepared with 10 mcg/ ml fentanyl will be attached to all patients with a protocol included 10 mcg bolus without infusion dose, 10 min lockout time and 4 hour limit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clavipectoral fascia plane block group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be administered ibuprofen 400 mgr IV every 8 hours in the postoperative period. A patient controlled device prepared with 10 mcg/ ml fentanyl will be attached to all patients with a protocol included 10 mcg bolus without infusion dose, 10 min lockout time and 4 hour limit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group CPB = Clavipectoral fascia plane block group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) classification I-II

          -  Scheduled for clavicle surgery under general anesthesia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  history of bleeding diathesis,

          -  receiving anticoagulant treatment,

          -  known local anesthetics and opioid allergy,

          -  infection of the skin at the site of the needle puncture,

          -  pregnancy or lactation,

          -  patients who do not accept the procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bahadir Ciftci</last_name>
    <phone>+905325034428</phone>
    <email>bciftci@medipol.edu.tr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mürsel Ekinci</last_name>
    <phone>+905067137596</phone>
    <email>mekinci@medipol.edu.tr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul Medipol University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Bagcilar</state>
        <zip>34070</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bahadir Ciftci, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+905325034428</phone>
      <email>bciftci@medipol.edu.tr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mürsel Ekinci, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+905067137596</phone>
      <email>drmurselekinci@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atalay YO, Mursel E, Ciftci B, Iptec G. Clavipectoral Fascia Plane Block for Analgesia after Clavicle Surgery. Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim. 2019 Dec;66(10):562-563. doi: 10.1016/j.redar.2019.06.006. Epub 2019 Nov 11. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>31727320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ince I, Kilicaslan A, Roques V, Elsharkawy H, Valdes L. Ultrasound-guided clavipectoral fascial plane block in a patient undergoing clavicular surgery. J Clin Anesth. 2019 Dec;58:125-127. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2019.07.011. Epub 2019 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>31377668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueshima H, Ishihara T, Hosokawa M, Otake H. Clavipectoral fascial plane block in a patient with dual antiplatelet therapy undergoing emergent clavicular surgery. J Clin Anesth. 2020 May;61:109648. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2019.109648. Epub 2019 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>31732427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medipol University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bahadir Ciftci</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Primary researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Clavicle fracture</keyword>
  <keyword>Clavipectoral fascia plane block</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative analgesia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will not plan to share IPD</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

