<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04323423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Glycemic variability &amp; SB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04323423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimal Reduction in SB to Reduce Glycemic Variability</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determining the Optimal Reduction in Sedentary Behaviour to Reduce Glycemic Variability and Maintain Cognition: a Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Western University, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western University, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Older adults spend the majority of their time in sedentary behaviours (SB). High
      amounts of SB have been correlated with reduced cognitive performance. Long periods of time
      spent sitting results in excessive glycemic variability, potentially contributing to
      cognitive decline. Reducing/replacing SB with short intermittent bouts of light physical
      activity have shown positive effects on glycemic variability. Thus, interrupting prolonged
      sitting with bouts of light physical activity may regulate blood glucose and thus mitigate
      cognitive decline.

      Purpose: This study intends to investigate the appropriate interval frequency of
      post-prandial SB reduction, by light physical activity needed to optimize total and
      incremental area under the curve for glucose response in overweight older adults at risk for
      glucose intolerance with mild cognitive impairment in both lab and free-living environments.
      Second, this study aims to investigate the acute impact of reducing SB on glycemic
      variability and its relationship with cognition.

      Hypothesis: First, there will be a dose-dependent response of more frequent interruptions of
      SB (more frequent intervals of light physical activity) with better glycemic control. Second,
      reducing SB will result in less glycemic variability, which will translate into better levels
      of cognitive performance.

      Methods: Generalized linear mixed models with random intercepts will be used to evaluate the
      differential effects of the experimental conditions on the selected outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a randomized crossover trial and reported in accordance with CONSORT
      guidelines. The study will involve a total of three seven-day conditions (2 experimental and
      1 control) with a three-week washout period in-between to minimize practice effects for a
      total intervention period of nine weeks (see figure 1). Each condition will consist of one
      day supervised in the laboratory followed by six at-home days, following lab protocol as
      closely as possible.

      Participants will be referred to the study by their physician. Interested participants will
      be asked to contact the researcher by email or phone call. A phone interview will be used to
      verbally explain the study protocol and screen for eligibility. The interview will consist
      of: 1) Age, height, weight; 2) Smoking status; 3) GDS assessment- short form (Yesavage et
      al., 1983); 4) PA and SB patterns using a modified version of the Physical Activity Scale for
      the Elderly (PASE) (Washburn, Mcauley, Katula, Mihalko, &amp; Boileau, 1999); 6) Medication use;
      7) Alcohol consumption; and lastly 8) Orthopedic concerns or injuries/illness that may limit
      participation. If participants pass the telephone screening, they will be invited to a local
      LifeLabs Centre for a fasted blood test (overnight fast ≥10 h) and an oral glucose tolerance
      test (OGTT).

      Once these tests are completed, results will be interpreted for: 1) Fasted blood glucose
      levels in order to rule out diagnosis of diabetes as well as 2) HbA1C levels, which are the
      best indicator of blood glucose levels over the course of two to three months (Sherwani,
      Khan, Ekhzaimy, Masood, &amp; Sakharkar, 2016). OGTT measures the body's ability to use glucose
      (a type of sugar), that is the body's main source of energy. This test can be used to
      diagnose prediabetes and diabetes. For the purpose of this study it will be used to indicate
      glucose intolerant individuals (as per inclusion criteria).

      If participants are still deemed eligible after the telephone screening and LifeLab Centre
      results, they will be invited into the lab for a familiarization session. They will be
      instructed to avoid caffeine, alcohol and MVPA for 48 hours prior to this session. During
      this session the following information will be obtained;

        -  Written informed consent

        -  Height using a stadiometer and weight using a standard beam scale

        -  Demographics questionnaire (education, ethnicity, family background, comorbidities)

        -  Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PARQ+) (Bredin, Gledhill, Jamnik, &amp;
           Warburton, 2013)

        -  Resting blood pressure- will be measured once on each arm and then twice on the left arm
           with an automated BP monitor

        -  VO2 testing (see protocol for VO2 section) The participants will be
           educated/familiarized on the following;

        -  Cognitive assessments - Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB)

        -  Fitting with an inclinometer (activPAL4) (see ActivPal protocol section)

        -  Fitbit provision (see Fitbit protocol section)

        -  Meal plan

      Participants will be visited at their home ~72hrs prior to each condition to be fitted with
      the CGM, ActivPal and FitBit. They will also be instructed to avoid caffeine, alcohol and
      MVPA for 48 hours prior to each of the three conditions. Participants will be asked to only
      consume the food described in the meal-plan provided for the 48 hours before the first
      laboratory visit. They will be asked to replicate their diet (quantity and timings) prior to
      each subsequent visit. Dinner will be consumed between 7:00 and 9:00 pm, allowing for a 10
      hour fast prior to the experimental condition the next morning. All participants will be
      instructed to arrive at the laboratory (with minimal activity during commute) at
      approximately 7:00 am. Upon arrival, participants will be asked to use the washroom and then
      rest for 30 minutes preceding a blood pressure measurement and first cognitive assessment.
      The participants will undergo the CANTAB cognitive assessments (at ~7:30 am) before meal
      consumption. A standardized breakfast meal will be consumed at 8:00 am, followed by lunch at
      12:00 pm and dinner at 5:00 pm. Participants will be allotted 20 minutes for full meal
      consumption. The CANTAB cognitive assessments will then be re-administered at approximately
      8:00 pm. Participants will be supervised throughout the conditions to ensure adherence to the
      protocols and will be permitted to watch DVDs, read books, magazines, newspapers, talk and/or
      work on a laptop computer. However, what they do during the first condition will be
      documented and then replicated for the remaining experimental conditions. Intensity of the
      bout intervals will be monitored with a heart rate monitor (Polar HR) and kept to 40% of
      their VO2max along with an RPE of 6-9 using the Borg RPE scale (Borg, 1954). The participants
      will be wearing their Fitbit wristwatches and will be asked to take note of the feeling and
      heart rate reading in order to duplicate the intensity of bouts during the at-home portion.
      The intervention conditions are depicted in figure 2. One of the conditions being a control,
      while the remaining two being interventions that are equal in total duration of sedentary
      time and light physical activity.

      Trial conditions were as follows:

        1. Condition A (CON): This will be the control condition. It will consist of uninterrupted
           sitting from 8 am until 7 pm, only rising from the chair to void.

        2. Condition B (LONG): will consist of completing one 10-minute bout of light intensity
           walking (RPE 6-9 and 40% VO2max) 30 minutes post-prandial. Participants will rise from
           their seated position to walk ~10 metres to a treadmill to perform this bout. The
           participant will repeat this after lunch and dinner, for an accumulated total of 30
           minutes of light walking.

        3. Condition two (SHORT): will consist of interrupting sitting with four 2.5-minute bouts
           of light walking at 30 minutes, 60 minutes, 90 minutes and 120 minutes post-prandial.
           Participants will rise from their seated position to walk ~10 metres to a treadmill to
           perform these bouts. The participant will repeat this after breakfast, lunch and dinner
           for an accumulated total of 30 minutes of light walking.

      Once the 12- hour laboratory component is complete, participants will be sent home (still
      wearing the CGM, activPAL and Fitbit) with the intension of replicating the laboratory-based
      protocol after each meal in their own free-living environment. Participants will track their
      mealtimes by sending photos to the researcher before consumption during the 6 at home days.
      The researcher will then go to the participants house on the last day (day 7) of each
      condition to re-administer the CANTAB cognitive assessments and collect the CGM, activPal and
      FitBit. There will then be a 3-week washout period, followed by replication of protocol for
      the remaining two conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized crossover trial and reported in accordance with CONSORT guidelines. The study will involve a total of three seven-day conditions (2 experimental and 1 control) with a three-week washout period in-between to minimize practice effects for a total intervention period of nine weeks. Each condition will consist of one day supervised in the laboratory followed by six at-home days, following lab protocol as closely as possible.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic Variability</measure>
    <time_frame>1-7 days</time_frame>
    <description>to investigate the appropriate interval frequency of post-prandial SB reduction, by light physical activity needed to optimize total and incremental area under the curve for glucose response in overweight older adults at risk for glucose intolerance with mild cognitive impairment in both lab and free-living environments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>1-7 days</time_frame>
    <description>CANTAB will be used to measure change in cognitive function. This is a computerized battery of neuropsychological tests utilizing touch sensitive screen technology that has been shown to be highly sensitive and a precise measure of cognitive function, correlated to neural networks (CANTAB, 2017). The following three cognitive domains were selected for testing; attention and psychomotor function (Motor Screening Task (MOT) and Rapid Visual Information Processing (RVP)), memory (Delayed Matching to Sample (DMS)) and executive function (Intra-Extra Dimensional Set Shift (IED))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Sedentary Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Glucose Intolerance</condition>
  <condition>Overweight and Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (CON)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>1) Condition A (CON): This will be the control condition. It will consist of uninterrupted sitting from 8 am until 7 pm, only rising from the chair to void.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>one 10 minute bout - (LONG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>will consist of completing one 10-minute bout of light intensity walking (RPE 6-9 and 40% VO2max) 30 minutes post-prandial. Participants will rise from their seated position to walk ~10 metres to a treadmill to perform this bout. The participant will repeat this after lunch and dinner, for an accumulated total of 30 minutes of light walking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>four 2.5 minute bouts SHORT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>will consist of interrupting sitting with four 2.5-minute bouts of light walking at 30 minutes, 60 minutes, 90 minutes and 120 minutes post-prandial. Participants will rise from their seated position to walk ~10 metres to a treadmill to perform these bouts. The participant will repeat this after breakfast, lunch and dinner for an accumulated total of 30 minutes of light walking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>interrupting sedentary behaviour with light physical activity</intervention_name>
    <description>replacing sitting with light walking bouts at different frequencies/durations</description>
    <arm_group_label>four 2.5 minute bouts SHORT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>one 10 minute bout - (LONG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 65 years

          -  BMI &gt; 25 kg/m2

          -  Fasting glucose concentration 5.5 - 7.0 mmol/L

          -  Diagnosis of MCI by physician

          -  Self-report being physically inactive (not meeting the current PA guidelines of 150
             min MVPA/week)

          -  Self-report being sedentary &gt;7 hours a day (Maylor et al., 2019)

          -  Able to walk one block without an assistive device

          -  No contraindications to participation in maximal oxygen consumption (VO2max)

          -  Own a smartphone

          -  Able to read, write and understand English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with Diabetes (type I or II)

          -  Currently smoke

          -  Depression (Geriatric Depression Score short-form &gt; 6 (GDS)) (Yesavage, Brink, Rose, &amp;
             et al, 1983).

          -  Medication: hypoglycemics; antilipidemics; antidepressants; beta blockers;
             anti-anxiety agents

          -  Peri-menopausal or menopausal women (must be post-menopausal)

          -  Excessive alcohol consumption (&gt; 8 points on the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification
             Test)

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (measured systolic &gt; 140 mmHg or diastolic &gt; 90 mmHg)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harry Prapavessis, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Western University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Harry Prapavessis, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>519 661-2111</phone>
    <phone_ext>80173</phone_ext>
    <email>hprapave@uwo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Western Ontario</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western University, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Harry Prapavessis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sedentary Behaviour</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Walking</keyword>
  <keyword>Older adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Glycemic variability</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

