<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04328545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-0188</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04328545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation Effect on Pain Threshold and Working Memory: Impact of Age and Protocol Type</brief_title>
  <official_title>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation Effect on Pain Threshold and Working Memory in Healthy Adolescents, Young Adults and Elderly: a Randomized , Cross-over, Single Blind Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) is a non-invasive neuromodulation method which
      has great potential as an aid in the therapeutic management of neuropsychiatric disorders and
      chronic pain syndromes. However, despite promising results, the response to stimulation
      presents great variability among subjects. Age is a factor that is known to influence the
      tDCS effect forging the inconsistency of clinical effect.The purpose of this study is to
      evaluate the effect of tDCS on pain perception and working memory in healthy women from 3
      different age groups: adolescents, young adults and elderly. This is a randomized,
      single-blinded, cross-over study of 2 different active interventions and sham.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) is a neuromodulation method that has great
      potential as an aid in the therapeutic management of neuropsychiatric disorders and chronic
      pain syndromes. tDCS modulates the neuronal membrane potential , facilitating neuronal
      depolarization or hyperpolarization, hence modifying the cortical excitability of the
      stimulated area. However, despite promising results the response to stimulation presents
      great variability among subjects. Chronological age is an important factor in the variation
      of brain plasticity. The dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) is associated with cognitive
      and emotional aspects of pain, in addition to being related to executive components of
      working memory. Anodal tDCS on DLPFC modulates pain level in patients with chronic pain and
      modifies working memory performance in healthy subjects and patients with memory impairment.
      The prefrontal cortex presents a great structural difference throughout lifespan: it is under
      maturational process in the adolescence, reaching peak of maturation in the adult life, and
      initiating process of cerebral senescence in elderly subjects. Therefore, the use of tDCS on
      DLPFC in these three age groups presents potential for a large variation in response. Faced
      with the potential of tDCS for adjuvant use in the treatment of several diseases, it is
      imperative to understand the variability of this intervention between different age groups.
      This knowledge may allow the optimization of neuromodulation protocols, allowing more careful
      and refined use in the clinic. The study primary outcomes is the difference between and
      within age groups on the variation of pre and post tDCS on pain threshold evaluated by Heath
      pain threshold on a Quantitative sensory testing paradigm and working memory performance
      evaluated by n-back test in healthy subjects of three age groups: adolescents, young adults,
      elderly. This is a randomized, single blinded, cross-over, sham-controlled clinical trial.
      The study will be conducted at the Clinical Research Center of the Hospital de Clínicas of
      Porto Alegre (HCPA). It will include 30 women, 10 women by age group: adolescents between 15
      and 16 years,young adults between 30 and 40 years old and elderly women between 60 and 70
      years. Participants will be randomized for a cross-over of three sessions: anodal stimulation
      in DLPFC, anodal stimulation in primary motor cortex (M1) as active control and sham
      stimulation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>single (participants)</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heat pain Threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>percentual change from before the tDCS onset, to immediately after the end of tDCS application for each cross-over session</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Quantitative sensory testing, this measure consists of the average temperature of 3 stimulus with increasing magnitude of heat where the participant presses a button to indicate when he/she first perceives pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Working memory performance</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes after tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>Working memory performance will be evaluated by a computerized n-back test associated with flankers at baseline and after each session of active tDCS (DLPFC or M1) or sham. The measure of performance is the D' discrimination index (calculated based on hit rate and false alarm rate).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inhibitory control performance</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes after tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>A computerized stop-signal task associated with flankers will evaluate inhibitory control. Performance index are calculated with the D' discrimination index (based on hits and false alarms for go and stop trials). The task will be performed at baseline and after the stimulation on each cross-over session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve of the ERP during inhibitory control task</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes after tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the curve of the signal of event-related potential (ERP) evoked during the stop signal task with flankers (inhibitory control performance). The signal will be assessed using an 8 channel EEG device at baseline and after each cross-over session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heat thermal threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>percentual change from before the tDCS onset, to immediately after the end of tDCS application for each cross-over session</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Quantitative sensory testing, this measure consists of the average temperature of 3 stimulus with increasing magnitude of heat where the participant presses a button to indicate when he/she first perceives heat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heat pain tolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>percentual change from before the tDCS onset, to immediately after the end of tDCS application for each cross-over session</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Quantitative sensory testing, this measure consists of the temperature for a stimulus with increasing magnitude of heat where the participant presses a button to indicate the maximum heat tolerated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Moderate pain</measure>
    <time_frame>percentual change from before the tDCS onset, to immediately after the end of tDCS application for each cross-over session</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Quantitative sensory testing, this measure consists of the average temperature of 3 stimulus with increasing magnitude of heat where the participant presses a button to indicate pain perceived at a moderate level, i.e. level of 6 in a numeric pain scale (0 to 10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unpleasantness sensation</measure>
    <time_frame>percentual change from before the tDCS onset, to immediately after the end of tDCS application for each cross-over session</time_frame>
    <description>This measure will be assessed using a numeric pain scale (0 to 10 in which 0 represents no unpleasant sensation and 10 extremely unpleasant sensation) with which participant will indicate how unpleasant was the temperature of the quantitative sensory testing stimulus for the heat pain threshold.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alpha wave power</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes after tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of alpha wave power (8Hz to 12Hz) will be done using an 8 channel EEG device during an &quot;eyes-open and eyes-closed&quot; paradigm where participant is in a resting state at baseline and after each cross-over session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beta wave power</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes after tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of beta wave power (12Hz to 25Hz) will be done using an 8 channel EEG device during an &quot;eyes-open and eyes-closed&quot; paradigm where participant is in a resting state at baseline and after each cross-over session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Theta wave power</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes after tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of theta wave power (4Hz to 8Hz) will be done using an 8 channel EEG device during an &quot;eyes-open and eyes-closed&quot; paradigm where participant is in a resting state at baseline and after each cross-over session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>serum BDNF levels</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 minutes before tDCS onset</time_frame>
    <description>Neuroplasticity biomarker will be assessed using serum brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) at baseline to be correlated with tdcs effects on primary outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation</condition>
  <condition>Working Memory</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anodal tDCS on DLPFC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive anodal tDCS on the left DLPFC for 30 mins duration, cathode will be placed over the right supra orbital area. The electrodes are 25cm², The stimulation current is 2 milliamperes (2mA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anodal tDCS on M1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive anodal tDCS on the left M1 for 30 min duration, cathode will be placed over the right supra orbital area. The electrodes are 25cm², The stimulation current is 2 milliamperes (2mA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive sham tDCS. The anode will be placed on the left DLPFC and the cathode on the over the right supra orbital area. The electrodes are 25cm², There will be a ram up and down of 30 seconds each, after the ramp up the current will be turned off.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anodal tDCS on DLPFC</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive anodal tDCS on the left DLPFC for 30 min duration, cathode will be placed over the right supra orbital area. The electrodes are 25cm², The stimulation current is 2 milliamperes (2mA).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anodal tDCS on DLPFC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DLPFC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anodal tDCS on M1</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive anodal tDCS on the left M1 for 30 min duration, cathode will be placed over the right supra orbital area. The electrodes are 25cm², The stimulation current is 2 milliamperes (2mA).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anodal tDCS on M1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>M1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham tDCS</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive sham tDCS. The anode will be placed on the left DLPFC and the cathode on the over the right supra orbital area. The electrodes are 25cm², There will be a ram up and down of 30 seconds each, after the ramp up the current will be turned off.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sham</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 15 to 16 years for the adolescent group

          -  Age between 30 to 40 years for the young adult group

          -  Age between 60 to 70 years for the elderly group

          -  From completed elementary school to incomplete superior education

          -  right handed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Current smoker or previous smoker within 10 years

          -  Current Substance Use Disorder

          -  Neurological condition (e.g., traumatic brain injury, stroke, brain tumor, epilepsy,
             brain surgery, brain implant)

          -  Any diagnosed Psychiatric condition (e.g., Attention deficit/hyperactivity deficit
             (ADHD), bipolar disorder, major depressive disorder, schizophrenia, generalized
             anxiety disorder)

          -  Use of any antidepressive or psychoactive, psychostimulant medication

          -  Any chronic pain condition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wolnei Caumo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Clinicas e Porto Alegre (HCPA)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande Do Sul</state>
        <zip>90035-003</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gazzaley A, Cooney JW, Rissman J, D'Esposito M. Top-down suppression deficit underlies working memory impairment in normal aging. Nat Neurosci. 2005 Oct;8(10):1298-300. Epub 2005 Sep 11. Erratum in: Nat Neurosci. 2005 Dec;8(12):1791.</citation>
    <PMID>16158065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palm U, Segmiller FM, Epple AN, Freisleder FJ, Koutsouleris N, Schulte-Körne G, Padberg F. Transcranial direct current stimulation in children and adolescents: a comprehensive review. J Neural Transm (Vienna). 2016 Oct;123(10):1219-34. doi: 10.1007/s00702-016-1572-z. Epub 2016 May 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27173384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scharinger C, Soutschek A, Schubert T, Gerjets P. When flanker meets the n-back: What EEG and pupil dilation data reveal about the interplay between the two central-executive working memory functions inhibition and updating. Psychophysiology. 2015 Oct;52(10):1293-304. doi: 10.1111/psyp.12500. Epub 2015 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26238380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Boggio PS, Zaghi S, Lopes M, Fregni F. Modulatory effects of anodal transcranial direct current stimulation on perception and pain thresholds in healthy volunteers. Eur J Neurol. 2008 Oct;15(10):1124-30. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-1331.2008.02270.x. Epub 2008 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18717717</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fregni F, Boggio PS, Nitsche M, Bermpohl F, Antal A, Feredoes E, Marcolin MA, Rigonatti SP, Silva MT, Paulus W, Pascual-Leone A. Anodal transcranial direct current stimulation of prefrontal cortex enhances working memory. Exp Brain Res. 2005 Sep;166(1):23-30. Epub 2005 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>15999258</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Age Groups</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain Threshold</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be shared with coded variables and coded participant numbers, only to editors and reviewers of journals where the studies are submitted and registered and under formal request</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Available in August 2019; Available for 3 years</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>by e-mail, under request</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

