<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04326465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H18-02482</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04326465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fractionated Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy for Treatment of Peyronie's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fractionated Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy for Treatment of Peyronie's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study that evaluates the use of Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy in
      the treatment of Peyronie's Disease. Study participants will be randomized to receive either
      Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy at 5% laser density coverage or at 10% laser density
      coverage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peyronie's Disease is a fibrosing disorder of the penis where scar tissue known as a &quot;plaque&quot;
      forms along the shaft of the penis. This plaque can lead to penile deformity, erectile
      dysfunction and pain during intercourse. Furthermore, Peyronie's Disease has been shown to
      negatively affect the quality of life and cause psychosocial distress. Currently, treatments
      for Peyronie's Disease are invasive (injections or surgery). This study investigates the use
      of a non-invasive and extra-dermal Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy to treat chronic
      phase Peyronie's Disease.

      Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy works by destroying and reducing abnormal collagen (a
      major component found in Peyronie's Disease plaques) in scarred tissue. Although Fractional
      Carbon Dioxide Lasers have yet to be used in the field of urology, it has already been used
      safely and successfully to treat conditions similar to Peyronie's Disease (ie. hypertrophic
      burn scars).

      Study participants enrolled in this study will be required to attend 6 study visits. The
      first study visit is a 'Screening Visit'. At this visit, a medical history and baseline
      penile measurements (degree of curvature, stretched length, and circumference deformity at
      flaccid and erect states) will be collected. Study participants will also be asked to
      complete the International Index of Erectile Function Questionnaire, and Peyronie's Disease
      Questionnaire.

      Following the 'Screening Visit', study participants will be scheduled for four Fractional
      Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy sessions. These sessions will be scheduled once every four weeks
      (totaling of 12 weeks from the first therapy session).

      The last study visit will occur four weeks after the last Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser
      Therapy session. At this visit, post-therapy penile measurements, International Index of
      Erectile Function, and Peyronie's Disease scores will be collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two group randomized design for Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser dosing with pre-test, post-test and between group comparisons (4 laser therapy sessions over 12 weeks in men with Peyronie's Disease).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measured reduction in penile curvature</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in penile measurements (Baseline vs Week 16)</time_frame>
    <description>Penile measurements will be collected at erect states. Penile measurements will be conducted at the screening visit (baseline) and at the last study visit (Week 16).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>International Index of Erectile Function Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in International Index of Erectile Function Questionnaire score (Baseline vs Week 16)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported 15-item questionnaire that assesses erectile dysfunction. Each item is scored from 0 to 5, yielding a total of 0 to 75.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peyronie's Disease Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in Peyronie's Disease Questionnaire score (Baseline vs Week 16)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported 15-item questionnaire that assesses sexual function in individuals with Peyronie's Disease. Scoring of each item is varied (ie. Q1 scored 0 to 4, Q9 scored 0 to 10)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Peyronies Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fractional CO2 Laser Therapy at 5% Laser Density Coverage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants with Peyronies Disease will be treated with a Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser set at a 5% laser density. The patient will receive four laser therapy sessions over 12 weeks (one session every four weeks). Following each session, topical triamcinolone will be applied to the treated area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fractional CO2 Laser Therapy at 10% Laser Density Coverage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants with Peyronies Disease will be treated with a Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser set at a 10% laser density. The patient will receive four laser therapy sessions over 12 weeks (one session every four weeks). Following each session, topical triamcinolone will be applied to the treated area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy at 5% Laser Density Coverage</intervention_name>
    <description>Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy is an ablative therapy where abnormal collagen in scarred tissue is destroyed to permit the formation of more organized collagen. Previous studies have demonstrated its efficacy in treating medical conditions (ex. hypertrophic scars) similar to Peyronies Disease. There is evidence that Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy has the ability to target and alter the molecular pathways that are similar to the ones that lead to Peyronie's Disease.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fractional CO2 Laser Therapy at 5% Laser Density Coverage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy at 10% Laser Density Coverage</intervention_name>
    <description>Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy is an ablative therapy where abnormal collagen in scarred tissue is destroyed to permit the formation of more organized collagen. Previous studies have demonstrated its efficacy in treating medical conditions (ex. hypertrophic scars) similar to Peyronies Disease. There is evidence that Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser Therapy has the ability to target and alter the molecular pathways that are similar to the ones that lead to Peyronie's Disease.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fractional CO2 Laser Therapy at 10% Laser Density Coverage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy males age 18 or older in a stable relationship with a female partner/spouse
             (for at least 3 months and willing to have vaginal intercourse with that female
             partner/spouse.

          2. Diagnosis of Peyronie's Disease for at least 12 months with evidence of stable disease
             as determined by the investigator.

          3. Penile curvature of 30ยบ-90ยบ in the dorsal, lateral, or dorsal/lateral plane (must have
             been possible to delineate the single plane of maximal curvature for evaluation).

          4. Signed informed Ethics-approved consent agreement; signed authorization form to allow
             disclosure of protected information.

          5. Ability to read, complete, and understand the various rating instruments in English.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Penile curvature of &lt;30ยบ or &gt;90ยบ.

          2. Any conditions affecting the penis such as a chordee in the presence or absence of
             hypospadias; thrombosis of the dorsal penile artery; infiltration by a benign or
             malignant mass or an infectious agent; ventral curvature from any cause; presence of
             an active sexually transmitted disease; known active hepatitis B or C; known immune
             deficiency disease (including Human Immunodeficiency Virus).

          3. Failure to achieve a sufficient erection (after prostaglandin or Trimix
             administration), in the opinion of the investigator, to accurately measure the penile
             deformity.

          4. Calcified plaque as evident by appropriate radiographic evaluation, i.e. penile
             ultrasound that would prevent treatment with Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser.

          5. Isolated hourglass deformity of the penis without curvature.

          6. Treatment or plans to undergo treatment for Peyronie's Disease, including but not
             limited to any previous surgery, oral/topical agents within 3 months, intralesional
             medical therapies within 3 months, extracorporeal shock wave therapy within 6 months,
             or use of mechanical devices within 2 weeks before the start of the study.

          7. Use of or plans to use a mechanical devices to induce a passive erection within 2
             weeks before the start of study.

          8. Erectile dysfunction that was unresponsive to Phosphodiesterase inhibitors.

          9. Received an investigation drug or treatment within 30 days before start of the study.

         10. At any time, received Collagenase clostridium histolyticum for the treatment of
             Peyronie's Disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ryan Flannigan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UBC Faculty of Medicine - Department of Urologic Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Justin Chan, BMSc</last_name>
    <phone>778-887-1339</phone>
    <email>justinyhchan@alumni.ubc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ryan Flannigan, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peyronies Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Fractionated Carbon Dioxide Laser</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Penile Induration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

