<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04320355</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-3351</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04320355</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exploring the Effects of Soft Tissue Manual Therapy on Caesarean Section Scar</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploring the Effects of Soft Tissue Manual Therapy on the Viscoelastic Properties, Pressure Sensitivity and Touch Sensitivity of the Caesarean Section Scar</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université de Sherbrooke</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Interdisciplinary Network Complementary &amp; Alternative Medicine Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Société Européenne de Recherche en Ostéopathie Pédiatrique et Périnatale (SEROPP)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université de Sherbrooke</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Caesarean section is one of the most common inpatient surgical procedures.
      Complications of obstetric wounds are estimated to account for 2.8-26.6% of cases. Between 11
      and 15% of women would develop pain and discomfort following a Caesarean section. Manual
      therapies may be an interesting non-pharmacological approach to treating the signs and
      symptoms of scarring complications following a Caesarean section. However, the current
      literature with an in vivo perspective remains modest results for the effects of tissue
      physiology and their effects on pain.

      Method: Using an exploratory &quot;proof of concept&quot; type descriptive design with before and after
      measurements, the immediate and 7-day effects following the application of soft tissue manual
      therapy on the Caesarean section scar will be evaluated. The objectives are to describe and
      explore differences from the effects of soft tissue manual therapy on the viscoelastic
      properties, pressure sensitivity and touch sensitivity of the Caesarean section scar.
      Thirty-eight women aged between 18 and 40 years with a Caesarean section scar who attend
      first-line or specialized obstetrics and perinatal clinics will be recruited.

      Anticipated results This project will document the viscoelastic characteristics, pressure
      sensitivity and touch sensitivity of the C-section scar and surrounding unhealed tissue to
      improve our understanding of the plausibility of the effects of manual therapy, an approach
      used to treat the signs and symptoms associated with C-section scarring.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methods of manual treatment of scars have demonstrated some effectiveness, although the
      effects and physiology by which mechanical forces of the therapist's hand provide benefits
      are poorly understood. This research will improve understanding of certain tissue
      characteristics and physiology elicited during treatment, and provide better conceptual
      explanations of the effects of manual therapies.

      This study consists of 2 steps. The first step consists of the reliability of the Myoton Pro.
      The second step consists to describe and explore the effects of the soft tissue manual
      therapy on viscoelastic properties, touch sensibility and pressure sensibility on the
      Caesarean scar and the unscarred skin.

      Objective(s)

      The main objective of this project is to evaluate the effects of the application of
      mechanical force by the therapist's hand on the Caesarean section scar. The specific
      objectives are to document the following, prior to and following the application of
      mechanical force by the therapist's hand:

        1. Determine the reliability and discrimination of the Myoton Pro.

        2. The viscoelastic properties of the Caesarean section scar and surrounding healthy
           tissues;

        3. The sensitivity of the Caesarean section scar to pressure compared with surrounding
           healthy tissues;

        4. The touch sensitivity of the Caesarean section scar compared with surrounding healthy
           tissue; and

        5. Differences in viscoelastic properties, pressure sensitivity and touch sensitivity
           before and after the independent variable.

      Recruitment Recruitment will be recruited women attending primary care and specialized
      obstetrics and perinatal clinics in the Vaudreuil-Soulanges region, Candiac on the south
      shore of Montreal, Repentigny located in the Lanaudière region and community organizations
      with a perinatal orientation located in the Montreal region. Posters will be put up and
      announcements will be made on the research centre's Facebook page as well as the page
      dedicated to the project. Interested will be able to communicate directly with the student
      researcher via digital platform. A brief description of the implications will be sent using
      digital platform. They will then be asked if they are still interested in participating and
      if they agree to be contacted by the student researcher in order to verify the eligibility
      criteria. The student-researcher will request contact information such as email address and a
      valid telephone number in order to make contact. During this telephone contact, the
      student-researcher will explain the elements of the study, reiterate the free nature of their
      participation and verify the eligibility criteria. The student-researcher will then suggest
      an appointment.

      Data collection Phase 1: Reliability of the Myoton Pro The experimental procedure will take
      place at the Longueuil Campus of the Université de Sherbrooke located in Longueuil. Three
      evaluators will perform the measurements. The investigator will call them Evaluator 1 (E1),
      Evaluator 2 (E2) and Evaluator 3 (E3). E1 will invite participants to lie supine on a
      treatment table. E1 will place a pillow under the participants' knees to reduce the lower
      extremity strain. They will be asked to undress their abdomen to make the scar visible. The
      E1 will locate a point in the centre of the scar and a healthy control point about 2 cm above
      the scar and identify them with an indelible black pencil. The E1 will take four measurements
      of each point alternately using the MyotonPro. E2 will then take four measurements at the
      same points using the MyotonPro using the same procedure. Finally, this procedure will be
      repeated by E3.

      Phase 2:

      The experimental procedure will take place at the AXiO sports medicine clinic in
      Vaudreuil-Dorion, the FDL massage therapy and osteopathy clinic located in Candiac, the
      Parent-aise osteopathy clinic located in Repentigny and the ENOSI osteopathy centre located
      in Montreal. Measurements of the dependent variables with the MyotonPro, Von Frey's algometer
      and microfilaments will be taken by a research assistant. She will be trained beforehand on
      the following elements: 1) the use of Von Frey's microfilaments, 2) the use of the algometer,
      3) the use of the Myoton Pro, 4) their application on the tissue and scar points previously
      identified by the student researcher, 5) computer data entry. The POSAS questionnaire will be
      administered by the student researcher, who will explain it to the participants.

      Upon their arrival, participants will be greeted by the student researcher. The student
      researcher will give them the consent form, reiterate the free and informed nature of the
      questionnaire and make sure they understand it. She will ensure that the form is signed. She
      will then give them the POSAS questionnaire to which will be annexed to the socio-demographic
      and clinical data questionnaire.

      The student-researcher will invite the participants into a room and they will then lie supine
      on a treatment table. She will then invite the participants to undress the lower abdominal
      area. The student-researcher will make sure that the Caesarean section scar and the area
      around it are clearly visible. She will place a pillow under the participants' knees for
      maximum reduction of any tension surrounding the scar, which will lengthen the lower limbs.

      The student-researcher will identify five points on the Caesarean scar, five points on the
      upper scar border, five points on the lower scar border and five additional points about 2 cm
      above the scar in the healthy surrounding tissue and mark them with a nontoxic pencil. She
      will then leave the room.

      Using Von Frey's microfilaments, the research assistant will make an initial assessment of
      the sensitivity to touch of the five points of the Caesarean scar and the healthy tissue.
      Using the Myoton Pro, the research assistant will make an initial measurement of the
      viscoelastic properties of the healthy, scarred tissue points and the upper and lower scar
      edges (for a total of 20 points). Then, the research assistant will use the algometer placed
      perpendicularly to each identified point and will make a first measurement of pressure
      sensitivity on the surrounding tissue surfaces and on the Caesarean section scar (T0). In
      order to ensure reproducibility, 3 measurements per point will be taken before the manual
      technique is applied. The measurements will be recorded in the participant's file, without
      the knowledge of the student researcher.

      The student-researcher will enter the room. She will place the glove with the force sensor on
      the thumb of her right hand. She will evaluate the Caesarean section scar and identify the
      most rigid scar areas when compression is applied. In these identified areas, the
      student-researcher will apply the manual therapy procedure described in the independent
      variable (compression + shear) section. This procedure will be applied to all identified
      rigid areas of the Caesarean section scar.

      This procedure will take 20 minutes (approximately 2 minutes per rigid area). After this
      time, the student-researcher will remove the force sensor and leave the room. The research
      assistant will perform the evaluation of Von Frey's microfilaments, measurements of
      viscoelastic properties using the Myoton pro and pressure sensitivity using the algometer at
      the same tissue and scar points (T1). This same procedure will be performed again seven days
      later, before (T2) and after the procedure (T3). Following the last measurement time, a
      complete treatment of the scar area and surrounding tissues will be offered to the
      participants. Note that an anonymous code will be assigned to each participant and their
      information. The research assistant will collect the data using an Excel file. The data from
      the MyotonPro will be collected and automatically saved in a computer folder and later merged
      into the Excel file.

      Sampling The sample of the accessible population will be drawn from a non-probabilistic
      convenience sample.

      Sample size

      Phase 1:

      The sample size was determined by assuming a predetermined intra-participant standard
      deviation (Bland and Altman, 1996). Using Bland's formula for repeatability studies, the
      following parameters were considered: 1) an intra-participant standard deviation of 10%; 2)
      four measurements at a point on the scar and four measurements at a healthy control point two
      centimetres above the scar per participant and per evaluator; and 3) three evaluators. Using
      these parameters, the sample size required to estimate the magnitude of the 95% confidence
      interval of the precision estimates is 18 participants.

      Phase 2:

      The exploratory component of this project will provide data with respect to viscoelastic
      properties, and sensitivity to pressure and touch. Since to our knowledge, no study could
      inform the sample size calculation, the investigator assume a medium effect size with a power
      of 80% and a type I error of 5%. Given these assumptions, the sample size requires 32
      participants. Anticipating a 10% drop-out rate, the resulting total sample size is 38
      participants.

      Analysis plan

      Phase 1:

      In order for the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) to be established accurately, the
      prerequisites of the analysis of variance (ANOVA) must be met. The normality of the
      observations will be checked using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Using a two-factor ANOVA, the
      intra-participant standard deviation, repeatability coefficient and ICC will be calculated to
      establish intra- and inter-rater reliability.

      Phase 2:

      Descriptive analyses will be conducted based on socio-demographic data and the
      characteristics of the participants. The continuous variables, if normally distributed, will
      be summarized using means and standard deviation. The continuous variables, if not normally
      distributed, will be summarized using medians and intervals. Ordinal and discrete variables
      will be summarized using percentages.

      With respect to the Caesarean section scar, the viscoelastic properties and sensitivity to
      pre- and post-pressure will be compared using a multi-level longitudinal regression model, if
      data is normally distributed. Otherwise, nonparametric tests will be performed. The pre- and
      post-intervention touch sensitivity of the Caesarean section scar will be compared using the
      Friedman test. A student's paired test will be used to compare POSAS, viscoelastic properties
      and pressure sensitivity of healthy tissues means. The Wilcoxon rank test will be used for
      the touch sensitivity of healthy tissues. Finally, the comparison between the Caesarean scar
      and healthy tissues will be made with the student's test in the case of a normal distribution
      of data. Otherwise, a nonparametric test will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 9, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>An exploratory descriptive design with before and after measurements.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Viscoelastic properties: Stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>The change in stiffness is evaluated before and after the intervention. To evaluate this change, two visits each 7 days are required. Stiffness will be assessed at the beginning of each visit and following the intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The MyotonPro allows the evaluation of five parameters. Stiffness (N/m) is manifested by the resistance to deformation induced by the applied force of the external mechanical arm.The MyotonPro is a portable device that induces a low-force external impulse from a small mechanical external arm. The pulse induces soft tissue oscillations. These are transformed under the force of an acceleration signal and allow the calculation of mechanical and viscoelastic tissue properties.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The viscoelastic properties: Elasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>The change in Elasticity is evaluated before and after the intervention. To evaluate this change, two visits each 7 days are required. Elasticity will be assessed at the beginning of each visit and following the intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The MyotonPro allows the evaluation of five parameters. The MyotonPro is a portable device that induces a low-force external impulse from a small mechanical external arm. The pulse induces soft tissue oscillations. These are transformed under the force of an acceleration signal and allow the calculation of mechanical and viscoelastic tissue properties. The ability of the tissue to return to its initial shape characterises elasticity (D). This can be identified by the logarithmic decrement, i.e. the logarithmic measurement of the dissipation of mechanical energy induced by the external arm of the MyotonPro.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The viscoelasticity properties: Tone</measure>
    <time_frame>The change in tone is evaluated before and after the intervention. To evaluate this change, two visits each 7 days are required. Tone will be assessed at the beginning of each visit and following the intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The MyotonPro is a portable device that induces a low-force external impulse from a small mechanical external arm. The pulse induces soft tissue oscillations. These are transformed under the force of an acceleration signal and allow the calculation of mechanical and viscoelastic tissue properties. The MyotonPro allows the evaluation of five parameters. The oscillation frequency (Hz) characterizes the resting tone, i.e. the intrinsic cell tension.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>The change in pressure is evaluated before and after the intervention. To evaluate this change, two visits each 7 days are required. Pressure will be assessed at the beginning of each visit and following the intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Pressure sensitivity rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Touch sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>The change in touch sensitivity is evaluated before and after the intervention. To evaluate this change, two visits each 7 days are required. Touch sensitivity will be assessed at the beginning of each visit and following the intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Touch sensitivity rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Appearance of the caesarean section</measure>
    <time_frame>The change in appearance is evaluated before the intervention. To evaluate this change, two visits each 7 days are required. Appearance will be assessed at the beginning of each visit.</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Section Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Soft tissue manual therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The researcher student will place the gloves with the force sensor on the thumb of her right and left hand. She will evaluate the Caesarean section scar and identify the most rigid scar areas when compression is applied. On these identified areas, the researcher student will apply the manual therapy procedure described in the independent variable (compression + shear) section. This procedure will be applied to all identified rigid areas of the Caesarean section scar.This procedure will last 10 minutes (approximately 2 minutes per rigid area). After this time, the researcher-student will remove the force sensor and leave the room.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soft tissue manual therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is a type of massage.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Soft tissue manual therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Woman with a caesarean section scar of 6 months or more but less than two years old

          2. with one or more caesarean sections

          3. between the ages of 18 and 40

          4. with a Pfannenstiel or transverse caesarean section.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. one of the following pathologies: diabetes or under treatment for cancer

          2. on anti-inflammatory medication at the time of data collection or they have taken this
             type of medication in the month prior to data collection

          3. applied a product or cream to their scar on the day of data collection

          4. contraindications to their skin inductions

          5. had a treatment (e.g., a treatment to prevent the development of cancer)

          6. undergoing treatment (e.g. laser, massage or other local intervention) for their scar
             in the three months prior to the data collection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nathaly NG Gaudreault, Ph. D, Pt</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Isabelle IG Gilbert, M. Sc (c)</last_name>
    <phone>450-466-5000</phone>
    <phone_ext>4825</phone_ext>
    <email>isabelle.gilbert3@usherbrooke.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nathaly NG Gaudreault, Ph. D, Pt</last_name>
    <phone>819 821-8000</phone>
    <phone_ext>18613</phone_ext>
    <email>Nathaly.Gaudreault@USherbrooke.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique d'ostéopathie et de massothérapeie FDL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Candiac</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J5R 4R5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ENOSI centre d'ostéopathie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3N 1W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anais AB Beaupré</last_name>
      <phone>514-370-2266</phone>
      <email>anaisbeau.pré@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinide d'ostéopathie Parent-Aise</name>
      <address>
        <city>Repentigny</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J5Y 3R2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AXiO Medecine Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vaudreuil-Dorion</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J7V 9R2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maxime MC Chevrier</last_name>
      <phone>450-319-1707</phone>
      <email>axiovaudreuil@santeaxio.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marie-Hélène MJ Saint-Jacques</last_name>
      <phone>450-319-1707</phone>
      <email>mstjacques@santeaxio.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adcock D, Paulsen S, Davis S, Nanney L, Shack RB. Analysis of the cutaneous and systemic effects of Endermologie in the porcine model. Aesthet Surg J. 1998 Nov-Dec;18(6):414-20.</citation>
    <PMID>19328171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Benna S, Al-Ajam Y, Tzakas E. Superficial fascial system repair: an abdominoplasty technique to reduce local complications after caesarean delivery. Arch Gynecol Obstet. 2009 May;279(5):673-5. doi: 10.1007/s00404-008-0802-5. Epub 2008 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18810475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bartholomew, S., Deb-Rinker, P., Dzakpasu, S., Système canadien de surveillance périnatale, et Public Health Agency of Canada. (2015). Indicateurs de la santé périnatale au Canada 2013 : Un rapport du Système canadien de surveillance périnatale.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arora PD, Narani N, McCulloch CA. The compliance of collagen gels regulates transforming growth factor-beta induction of alpha-smooth muscle actin in fibroblasts. Am J Pathol. 1999 Mar;154(3):871-82.</citation>
    <PMID>10079265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beyaz SG, Özocak H, Ergönenç T, Palabyk O, Tuna AT, Kaya B, Erkorkmaz Ü, Akdemir N. Chronic postsurgical pain and neuropathic symptoms after abdominal hysterectomy: A silent epidemic. Medicine (Baltimore). 2016 Aug;95(33):e4484. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000004484.</citation>
    <PMID>27537570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beyene RT, Kavalukas SL, Barbul A. Intra-abdominal adhesions: Anatomy, physiology, pathophysiology, and treatment. Curr Probl Surg. 2015 Jul;52(7):271-319. doi: 10.1067/j.cpsurg.2015.05.001. Epub 2015 Jun 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26258583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bizzini M, Mannion AF. Reliability of a new, hand-held device for assessing skeletal muscle stiffness. Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 2003 Jun;18(5):459-61.</citation>
    <PMID>12763442</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bland JM, Altman DG. Measurement error. BMJ. 1996 Jun 29;312(7047):1654. Corrected and republished in: BMJ. 1996 Sep 21;313(7059):744.</citation>
    <PMID>8664723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouffard NA, Cutroneo KR, Badger GJ, White SL, Buttolph TR, Ehrlich HP, Stevens-Tuttle D, Langevin HM. Tissue stretch decreases soluble TGF-beta1 and type-1 procollagen in mouse subcutaneous connective tissue: evidence from ex vivo and in vivo models. J Cell Physiol. 2008 Feb;214(2):389-95.</citation>
    <PMID>17654495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandsborg B, Dueholm M, Kehlet H, Jensen TS, Nikolajsen L. Mechanosensitivity before and after hysterectomy: a prospective study on the prediction of acute and chronic postoperative pain. Br J Anaesth. 2011 Dec;107(6):940-7. doi: 10.1093/bja/aer264. Epub 2011 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21890662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buhimschi CS, Buhimschi IA, Yu C, Wang H, Sharer DJ, Diamond MP, Petkova AP, Garfield RE, Saade GR, Weiner CP. The effect of dystocia and previous cesarean uterine scar on the tensile properties of the lower uterine segment. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Mar;194(3):873-83.</citation>
    <PMID>16522428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bujold E, Gauthier RJ. Neonatal morbidity associated with uterine rupture: what are the risk factors? Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Feb;186(2):311-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11854656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chamorro Comesaña A, Suárez Vicente MD, Docampo Ferreira T, Pérez-La Fuente Varela MD, Porto Quintáns MM, Pilat A. Effect of myofascial induction therapy on post-c-section scars, more than one and a half years old. Pilot study. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2017 Jan;21(1):197-204. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2016.07.003. Epub 2016 Jul 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28167179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen F, Dellalana LE, Gandelman JS, Vain A, Jagasia MH, Tkaczyk ER. Correction: Non-invasive measurement of sclerosis in cutaneous cGVHD patients with the handheld device Myoton: a cross-sectional study. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2020 May;55(5):992. doi: 10.1038/s41409-020-0780-1.</citation>
    <PMID>31953531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cowman MK, Schmidt TA, Raghavan P, Stecco A. Viscoelastic Properties of Hyaluronan in Physiological Conditions. F1000Res. 2015 Aug 25;4:622. doi: 10.12688/f1000research.6885.1. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26594344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>da Silva RC, de Sá CC, Pascual-Vaca ÁO, de Souza Fontes LH, Herbella Fernandes FA, Dib RA, Blanco CR, Queiroz RA, Navarro-Rodriguez T. Increase of lower esophageal sphincter pressure after osteopathic intervention on the diaphragm in patients with gastroesophageal reflux. Dis Esophagus. 2013 Jul;26(5):451-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1442-2050.2012.01372.x. Epub 2012 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22676647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Damon Mok, W. K. L. (2014). Reliability and Asymmetry Profiles of Myotonometric Measurements in Healthy Skeletal Muscles. Journal of Novel Physiotherapies, 05(01).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dellalana LE, Chen F, Vain A, Gandelman JS, Põldemaa M, Chen H, Tkaczyk ER. Reproducibility of the durometer and myoton devices for skin stiffness measurement in healthy subjects. Skin Res Technol. 2019 May;25(3):289-293. doi: 10.1111/srt.12646. Epub 2018 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>30414198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deslauriers V, Rouleau DM, Alami G, MacDermid JC. Translation of the Patient Scar Assessment Scale (PSAS) to French with cross-cultural adaptation, reliability evaluation and validation. Can J Surg. 2009 Dec;52(6):E259-63.</citation>
    <PMID>20011161</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duffy KJ, Flickinger KL, Kristan JT, Repine MJ, Gianforcaro A, Hasley RB, Feroz S, Rupp JM, Al-Baghli J, Pacella ML, Suffoletto BP, Callaway CW. Quantitative sensory testing measures individual pain responses in emergency department patients. J Pain Res. 2017 May 24;10:1241-1253. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S132485. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28579822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freedman BR, Bade ND, Riggin CN, Zhang S, Haines PG, Ong KL, Janmey PA. The (dys)functional extracellular matrix. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2015 Nov;1853(11 Pt B):3153-64. doi: 10.1016/j.bbamcr.2015.04.015. Epub 2015 Apr 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25930943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geber C, Klein T, Azad S, Birklein F, Gierthmühlen J, Huge V, Lauchart M, Nitzsche D, Stengel M, Valet M, Baron R, Maier C, Tölle T, Treede RD. Test-retest and interobserver reliability of quantitative sensory testing according to the protocol of the German Research Network on Neuropathic Pain (DFNS): a multi-centre study. Pain. 2011 Mar;152(3):548-56. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.11.013. Epub 2011 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21237569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gracovetsky S. Can fascia's characteristics be influenced by manual therapy? J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2016 Oct;20(4):893-897. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2016.08.011. Epub 2016 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>27814871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grinnell F, Zhu M, Carlson MA, Abrams JM. Release of mechanical tension triggers apoptosis of human fibroblasts in a model of regressing granulation tissue. Exp Cell Res. 1999 May 1;248(2):608-19.</citation>
    <PMID>10222153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hausse des taux de césariennes et baisse des taux de naissances | ICIS. (2018, avril 19). Consulté 24 mai 2018, à l'adresse https://www.cihi.ca/en/c-section-rates-continue-to-increase-while-birth-rates-decline.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hinz B. The myofibroblast: paradigm for a mechanically active cell. J Biomech. 2010 Jan 5;43(1):146-55. doi: 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2009.09.020. Epub 2009 Oct 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19800625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hinz B, Mastrangelo D, Iselin CE, Chaponnier C, Gabbiani G. Mechanical tension controls granulation tissue contractile activity and myofibroblast differentiation. Am J Pathol. 2001 Sep;159(3):1009-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11549593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Humphrey JD, Dufresne ER, Schwartz MA. Mechanotransduction and extracellular matrix homeostasis. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2014 Dec;15(12):802-12. doi: 10.1038/nrm3896. Epub 2014 Oct 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25355505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ingber DE. Mechanobiology and diseases of mechanotransduction. Ann Med. 2003;35(8):564-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14708967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jafari, L., Gaudreault, N., et Langelier, E. (2016). Viscoelasticity, viscoplasticity and mechanobiological response of fibrous tissues : Current concepts. Journal of Bodywork and Movement Therapies, 20(1), 147‑148.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelly-Martin R, Doughty L, Garkavi M, Wasserman JB. Reliability of modified adheremeter and digital pressure algometer in measuring normal abdominal tissue and C-section scars. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2018 Oct;22(4):972-979. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2018.02.017. Epub 2018 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30368344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kendig CE. What is Proof of Concept Research and how does it Generate Epistemic and Ethical Categories for Future Scientific Practice? Sci Eng Ethics. 2016 Jun;22(3):735-53. doi: 10.1007/s11948-015-9654-0. Epub 2015 May 26.</citation>
    <PMID>26009258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan KM, Scott A. Mechanotherapy: how physical therapists' prescription of exercise promotes tissue repair. Br J Sports Med. 2009 Apr;43(4):247-52. doi: 10.1136/bjsm.2008.054239. Epub 2009 Feb 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19244270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiener, A., Galli, L., Commare, A., Sabbioni, L., Dall'Asta, A., Frusca, T., et Ghi, T. (2017). EP22.04 : Assessment of Caesarean section scar stiffness by ultrasound elastography. Ultrasound in Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology, 50, 359‑359.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koo TK, Li MY. A Guideline of Selecting and Reporting Intraclass Correlation Coefficients for Reliability Research. J Chiropr Med. 2016 Jun;15(2):155-63. doi: 10.1016/j.jcm.2016.02.012. Epub 2016 Mar 31. Erratum in: J Chiropr Med. 2017 Dec;16(4):346.</citation>
    <PMID>27330520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martínez Rodríguez R, Galán del Río F. Mechanistic basis of manual therapy in myofascial injuries. Sonoelastographic evolution control. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2013 Apr;17(2):221-34. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2012.08.006. Epub 2012 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23561871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Micallef L, Vedrenne N, Billet F, Coulomb B, Darby IA, Desmoulière A. The myofibroblast, multiple origins for major roles in normal and pathological tissue repair. Fibrogenesis Tissue Repair. 2012 Jun 6;5(Suppl 1):S5. doi: 10.1186/1755-1536-5-S1-S5. eCollection 2012.</citation>
    <PMID>23259712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Neill S, O'Neill L. Improving QST Reliability--More Raters, Tests, or Occasions? A Multivariate Generalizability Study. J Pain. 2015 May;16(5):454-62. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2015.01.476. Epub 2015 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25683899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pesteil, F., Vignaud, L., Bonté, F., et Desmoulière, A. (2017). Rôles primordiaux des fibroblastes dermiques dans la cicatrisation cutanée. Revue Francophone de Cicatrisation, 1(3), 45‑49.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosińczuk J, Taradaj J, Dymarek R, Sopel M. Mechanoregulation of Wound Healing and Skin Homeostasis. Biomed Res Int. 2016;2016:3943481. doi: 10.1155/2016/3943481. Epub 2016 Jun 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27413744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schleip, R. (2003). Fascial plasticity - a new neurobiological explanation Part 2. Journal of Bodywork and Movement Therapies, 7(2), 104‑116.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schleip R, Naylor IL, Ursu D, Melzer W, Zorn A, Wilke HJ, Lehmann-Horn F, Klingler W. Passive muscle stiffness may be influenced by active contractility of intramuscular connective tissue. Med Hypotheses. 2006;66(1):66-71. Epub 2005 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>16209907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider S, Peipsi A, Stokes M, Knicker A, Abeln V. Feasibility of monitoring muscle health in microgravity environments using Myoton technology. Med Biol Eng Comput. 2015 Jan;53(1):57-66. doi: 10.1007/s11517-014-1211-5. Epub 2014 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25331739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seliger G, Chaoui K, Lautenschläger C, Jenderka KV, Kunze C, Hiller GGR, Tchirikov M. Ultrasound elastography of the lower uterine segment in women with a previous cesarean section: Comparison of in-/ex-vivo elastography versus tensile-stress-strain-rupture analysis. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2018 Jun;225:172-180. doi: 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2018.04.013. Epub 2018 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>29729520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silver FH, Ebrahimi A, Snowhill PB. Viscoelastic properties of self-assembled type I collagen fibers: molecular basis of elastic and viscous behaviors. Connect Tissue Res. 2002;43(4):569-80.</citation>
    <PMID>12685863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simons DG, Mense S. Understanding and measurement of muscle tone as related to clinical muscle pain. Pain. 1998 Mar;75(1):1-17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9539669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomonow M, He Zhou B, Baratta RV, Lu Y, Zhu M, Harris M. Biexponential recovery model of lumbar viscoelastic laxity and reflexive muscular activity after prolonged cyclic loading. Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 2000 Mar;15(3):167-75.</citation>
    <PMID>10656978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Standley PR. My personal journey that led to the crossroads of interdisciplinary manual medicine research: serendipitous opportunities afforded a basic scientist. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2013 Jan;17(1):79-82. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2012.08.002. Epub 2012 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>23294687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tena B, Escobar B, Arguis MJ, Cantero C, Rios J, Gomar C. Reproducibility of Electronic Von Frey and Von Frey monofilaments testing. Clin J Pain. 2012 May;28(4):318-23. doi: 10.1097/AJP.0b013e31822f0092.</citation>
    <PMID>22001670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tulandi T, Agdi M, Zarei A, Miner L, Sikirica V. Adhesion development and morbidity after repeat cesarean delivery. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Jul;201(1):56.e1-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2009.04.039.</citation>
    <PMID>19576375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van de Kar AL, Corion LU, Smeulders MJ, Draaijers LJ, van der Horst CM, van Zuijlen PP. Reliable and feasible evaluation of linear scars by the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2005 Aug;116(2):514-22.</citation>
    <PMID>16079683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van De Water L, Varney S, Tomasek JJ. Mechanoregulation of the Myofibroblast in Wound Contraction, Scarring, and Fibrosis: Opportunities for New Therapeutic Intervention. Adv Wound Care (New Rochelle). 2013 May;2(4):122-141. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24527336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Wal MB, Tuinebreijer WE, Lundgren-Nilsson Å, Middelkoop E, van Zuijlen PP. Differential item functioning in the Observer Scale of the POSAS for different scar types. Qual Life Res. 2014 Sep;23(7):2037-45. doi: 10.1007/s11136-014-0637-4. Epub 2014 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24510653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vermillion ST, Lamoutte C, Soper DE, Verdeja A. Wound infection after cesarean: effect of subcutaneous tissue thickness. Obstet Gynecol. 2000 Jun;95(6 Pt 1):923-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10831993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vránová H, Zeman J, Cech Z, Otáhal S. Identification of viscoelastic parameters of skin with a scar in vivo, influence of soft tissue technique on changes of skin parameters. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2009 Oct;13(4):344-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2008.06.004. Epub 2008 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19761958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wasserman, Jennifer B., Abraham, K., Massery, M., Chu, J., Farrow, A., et Marcoux, B. C. (2018). Soft Tissue Mobilization Techniques Are Effective in Treating Chronic Pain Following Cesarean Section : A Multicenter Randomized Clinical Trial. Journal of Womenʼs Health Physical Therapy, 1</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wasserman JB, Steele-Thornborrow JL, Yuen JS, Halkiotis M, Riggins EM. Chronic caesarian section scar pain treated with fascial scar release techniques: A case series. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2016 Oct;20(4):906-913. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2016.02.011. Epub 2016 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>27814873</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weibel S, Neubert K, Jelting Y, Meissner W, Wöckel A, Roewer N, Kranke P. Incidence and severity of chronic pain after caesarean section: A systematic review with meta-analysis. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2016 Nov;33(11):853-865. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27635953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wight TN, Potter-Perigo S. The extracellular matrix: an active or passive player in fibrosis? Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2011 Dec;301(6):G950-5. doi: 10.1152/ajpgi.00132.2011. Epub 2011 Apr 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21512158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong VW, Beasley B, Zepeda J, Dauskardt RH, Yock PG, Longaker MT, Gurtner GC. A Mechanomodulatory Device to Minimize Incisional Scar Formation. Adv Wound Care (New Rochelle). 2013 May;2(4):185-194.</citation>
    <PMID>24527342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang J, Miller CJ, O'Malley V, Bowman EB, Etzkorn JR, Shin TM, Sobanko JF. Patient and Physician Assessment of Surgical Scars: A Systematic Review. JAMA Facial Plast Surg. 2018 Jul 1;20(4):314-323. doi: 10.1001/jamafacial.2017.2314.</citation>
    <PMID>29392275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Isabelle Gilbert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Caesarean</keyword>
  <keyword>Manual therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Thresholds</keyword>
  <keyword>Viscoelastic properties</keyword>
  <keyword>scar</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

