<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04325568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21HG010420</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04325568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Developing Clinical Tools to Communicate Genetic Risk for Individuals Who Are Clinical High Risk for Psychosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Developing Clinical Translational Tools to Communicate Genetic Risk Among Individuals Who Are at Clinical High Risk for Psychosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      While great strides are being made in identifying early signs that place people at a 'high
      risk state' for different illness conditions, at the same time, advances are being made in
      the identification of genes associated with 'high-risk states'. This study proposes to
      develop two innovative clinical tools that could greatly facilitate dissemination of a
      beneficial genetic malleability framing to high-risk youth in order to encourage increased
      treatment engagement and uptake of healthy behaviors. The impact of genetic information
      assumes special importance in the 'high-risk state' because achieving the best possible
      outcome is more likely if individuals actively choose to engage in beneficial treatment and
      health-promoting behaviors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project seeks to understand how individuals already in a high-risk state will interpret
      genetic information informing risk of 'conversion' to a full disorder. How individuals
      interpret this possibility carries important consequences for how they choose to respond,
      which may range from fatalistic acceptance of the disorder to proactive preventative
      behavior. With the aim to encourage an active pro-health response, the investigators propose
      developing two tools for communicating genetic risk and evaluate them regarding their
      effectiveness in inducing a positive response to the risk of illness. The two tools will
      consist of: 1) a clinician manual, designed to be used by trained clinicians to communicate
      risk to CHR youth; 2) a high-impact, computerized tutorial ('AutoTutor') that has been used
      to convey genetic risk for breast cancer (i.e. BRCA gene). To create these two tools, experts
      in psychiatric genetics and stigma will work to develop the two tools to convey genetic risk
      information to youth and young adults identified as in a 'clinical high-risk state' (CHR) for
      psychosis. The investigators assess primary outcomes of increased intent to engage in
      treatment and healthy behaviors, and a secondary outcome of reduction in stigma. While
      specific genes for risk of psychosis are not yet used in diagnosis or treatment, a genetic
      malleability (GM) framing conforms to the known genetic risk for psychosis, and has a strong
      likelihood of being used in the not too distant future. Because of the relatively large
      innovation involved, the investigators seek to establish initial acceptability, safety, and
      efficacy of each tool. The investigators then use a nonrandomized, within- subject, pre- vs.
      post design to examine whether providing the genetic malleability framing via each tool (n=27
      CHR youth per tool, N=54 total) leads to improved outcomes. For each tool, participants will
      be conveyed hypothetical information proposing being identified as having a substantially
      elevated, genetically-malleable risk for developing psychosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a pre-post design (N=54) in which the first 27 participants will take part in the clinician manual intervention and the next 27 participants will be assigned to the AutoTutor. Participants will only complete either the clinical manual intervention or the AutoTutor intervention, but not both. These groups will not be compared to one another. Each participant will be assessed on all outcomes before and after the intervention and will only take part in either the clinician manual or Autotutor. Since each participant is only getting one intervention and the clinician manual and AutoTutor are not being compared to each other the most appropriate study design is single group (and cannot be considered factorial, crossover, parallel, or sequential).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Masking will not be used. Again, the 27 participants will be assigned to the clinician manual and the next 27 participants will be assigned to Autotutor. The investigators are doing this in order to prevent contamination.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increased Intent to Engage in Treatment and Healthy Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Asks participants to rate their likelihood of engaging in treatment and uptake of healthy behaviors if they were told they had a genetic risk for psychosis. (Because this is an exploratory R21 trial, the investigators are also testing and validating new measures for this specific group and purpose).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Measure for Intent to Engage in Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>New computerized, behavioral task assessing intent to engage in healthy behaviors via time (in seconds) and engagement with (number of clicks) with a social media platform. (Because this is an exploratory R21 trial, the investigators are also testing and validating new measures for this specific group and purpose).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Stigma About Genetic Risk for Psychosis Development</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Assess participants self-stigma if they were told they had a genetic risk for psychosis. 7 items, measured on a 4-point scale (strongly disagree, somewhat disagree, somewhat agree, strongly agree). Because this an exploratory R21 trial, the investigators are also testing and validating new measures for this specific group and purpose; however, this is based off a published stereotype awareness and agreement scale previously used among CHR (Yang et al., 2015)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anticipated Discrimination from Others Due to Genetic Risk for Psychosis Development</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Assess participants anticipated discrimination if they were told they had a genetic risk for psychosis. 18 items measured on a 4-point scale (very unlikely, somewhat unlikely, somewhat likely, very likely). Because this is an exploratory R21 trial, the investigators are also testing and validating new measures for this specific group and purpose however, this is based off a published discrimination scale (Wahl, 1999).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anticipated Rejection from Others Due to Genetic Risk for Psychosis Development</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Assess participants anticipated rejection if they were told they had a genetic risk for psychosis. 3 items measured on a 4-point scale (very unconcerned, somewhat unconcerned, somewhat concerned, very concerned). Because this is an exploratory R21 trial, the investigators are also testing and validating new measures for this specific group and purpose; however, these items are based off of a published rejection sensitivity scale (Link, Wells, Phelan, Yang, 2015).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implicit Association Test</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Measures associations to 'Normal/Abnormal' and 'Changeable/Permanent' stereotypes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clinician Manual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the Clinician Manual arm will be introduced to a trained clinician and will complete one 60-minute session covering equivalent topics addressed in the PsyGist program. The manual will consist of: (1) a section exploring the youth's causal model for their high-risk state; (2) individualization per their causal model; and (3) tutorials that convey the main concepts of genetic malleability.
Clinicians will assess individual causal models via discussion with CHR youth about their at- risk state. Individualization of genetic framing will occur using youths' causal models and will fall into 1 of 3 categories (per PsyGist): 'primarily genetic', 'primarily environmental' or 'combined'.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AutoTutor (PsyGist)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>AutoTutor is an intelligent system that simulates talking with a human tutor. Our AutoTutor, called PsyGist, has 3 parts: (1) assessment of the youth's causal model for their high-risk state; (2) an individualized 'pre-tutorial' vignette matched to their causal model; (3) a 'tutorial' presenting the 'genetic malleability' framing.
PsyGist will guide participants through its three components.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PsyGist and Clinician Manual</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a pre-post test design aimed at conveying future genetic risk information to those at clinical high risk for psychosis. Participants will be assigned to either complete the Clinician Manual intervention (n= 27 participants) or PsyGist intervention (n=27 participants).</description>
    <arm_group_label>AutoTutor (PsyGist)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Clinician Manual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or females between the ages of 16- 30

          -  Current or previous COPE participant

          -  Identified as at clinical high risk for psychosis as defined as having at least one of
             the following: a)attenuated positive symptoms b)brief intermittent positive symptoms

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Meeting CHR via only the Genetic risk and deterioration (GRD) syndrome. If the
             participant meets the GRD syndrome only, the investigators exclude the rare Genetic
             risk + deterioration (GRD) syndrome (comprising &lt;1% of CHR cases) because GRD requires
             having a 1st degree relative with any psychotic disorder, which may be linked with
             stronger reactions to genetic framings.

          -  IQ &lt; 80

          -  Inability to adopt hypothetical situation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lawrence Yang, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lawrence Yang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-992-6334</phone>
    <email>lawrence.yang@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ragy Girgis, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-5553</phone>
    <email>ragy.girgis@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ragy Girgis, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-774-5553</phone>
      <email>Ragy.Girgis@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is not a plan to make IPD available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

