<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03744000</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INNOVATION-CORE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03744000</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Deferred Stenting in Patients With Anterior Wall STEMI</brief_title>
  <acronym>INNOVATIONCORE</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Immediate Stent Implantation Versus Deferred Stent Implantation on Clinical Outcomes in Patients With Anterior Wall ST-segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Korea University Anam Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Abbott</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Samjin Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Korea University Anam Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Trial Name) Impact of Immediate SteNt ImplaNtatiOn Versus Deferred Stent ImplAntaTION on
      Clinical Outcomes in Patients with AnteRior Wall ST-segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction
      (INNOVATION-CORE)

      Objectives) To evaluate the impact of deferred versus immediate stenting in patients with
      acute ST-segment elevation anterior wall myocardial infarction (STEMI) on

        1. the clinical efficacy and safety

        2. the microvascular obstruction using Cardiac magnetic resonance (MR)

        3. the structural and functional cardiac remodeling using conventional echocardiography and
           strain imaging

        4. the intravascular findings using optical coherence tomography (OCT)

      Study Design) A multicenter, prospective, randomized, controlled, open-label clinical trial
      for anterior wall STEMI patients

      Patient Enrollment) 460 patients will be enrolled at 20 centers in South-Korea

      Patient Follow-Up) Clinical follow-up will occur at 1, 6, 12 months, 2, 3 years and 5 years.
      Investigator or designee may conduct follow-up as telephone contacts or office visits.

      Primary Endpoint) Composite of all-cause death, hospitalization due to heart failure,
      recurrent myocardial infarction (MI), target vessel revascularization (TVR) at 2 years.

      Secondary Endpoints)

        1. Clinical events A. All-cause death B. Cardiac death C. Hospitalization due to heart
           failure D. Recurrent MI E. TVR F. Stent thrombosis

        2. Imaging parameters A. Echocardiographic parameters i. Left ventricle (LV) remodeling
           index ii. %LV strain iii. Regional wall motion abnormality B. Cardiac MR parameters
           (optional) i. Infarct size ii. Microvascular obstruction (MVO) size iii. MVO incidence
           iv. MVO to infarct ratio C. OCT parameters (optional) i. Plaque morphology ii. Lipid
           index iii. Minimal scaffold area and area stenosis iv. Stent malapposition
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Study background The main treatment for acute ST segment elevation myocardial infarction
           due to thrombogenesis and complete occlusion resulting from rupture or erosion of the
           atherosclerotic plaque in the coronary artery is to rapid open of the coronary artery
           through the coronary intervention. Infarction-associated epicardial coronary arteries
           reach Thrombolysis In Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) 3 blood flow in approximately 90% of
           patients after primary coronary intervention. However, many of these patients had
           microvascular dysfunction assessed by myocardial brush and ST segment complete response,
           and only about 35% of these patients achieved ideal reperfusion in which blood flow was
           smoothly delivered to the myocardium and tissue. A &quot;no-reflow&quot; phenomenon or
           microvascular obstruction, a serious form of microvascular dysfunction, raises the late
           mortality rate of patients who underwent reperfusion from 1.9 to 7.1 times. It is also
           well known that the phenomenon increases the incidence of re-infarction and the size of
           myocardial infarction and induces left ventricular remodeling after several months.

           To date, two treatment strategies have been proven to be effective in the treatment of
           distal microvascular embolism, which are manual thrombus aspiration and intracoronary
           administration of abciximab.

           Recently, the theory that deferred stenting can reduce microvascular obstruction has
           been suggested. The theoretical basis for the hypothesis is that prolonged antiplatelet
           therapy and anticoagulation for a deferral period may enable the resolution of the
           thrombus burden in infarct-related arteries, which is a substrate of distal embolization
           and subsequent microvascular obstruction. additional rationale is what is called the
           &quot;vascular cooling down&quot; to avoid mechanical stimulus in the milieu of active
           inflammation within an infarct-related artery in the early stages of myocardial
           infarction and prolong exposure to intensive statin therapy before stent implantation.

           Based on this theory, four randomized control trials were published recently, but their
           results were different. According to the subgroup analysis of the INNOVATION study, in
           the cases of anterior wall myocardial infarction, deferred stenting strategy reduced not
           only the infarction size but also the incidence of microvascular obstruction. These
           findings suggest that the left anterior descending artery has more microvascular bed
           than the other vessels, and thus the positive result of deferred stenting could be
           maximized. However, these subgroup analysis results do not have sufficient statistical
           power to conclude deferred stenting is beneficial in the left anterior wall myocardial
           infarction, it is important to reaffirm the results with a large randomized control
           trial exclusively selected for left anterior wall myocardial infarction.

           In this study, we sought to evaluate the impact of deferred versus immediate stenting in
           patients with acute ST-segment elevation anterior wall myocardial infarction on clinical
           efficacy and safety.

        2. Study objectives The primary objective of this study was to evaluate 1) the clinical
           efficacy and safety of immediate versus deferred stent implantation in patients with
           acute ST-segment elevation anterior wall myocardial infarction; 2) the degree of
           microvascular occlusion reflecting distal microvascular embolization using Cardiac MR
           and 3) the LV strain using echocardiography.

        3. Medical devices and therapeutic agents The medical devices and therapeutic agents to be
           used in this study are the treatment modalities that have been proven to be beneficial
           in the treatment and prognosis evaluation of acute ST segment elevation myocardial
           infarction in general. The stent is a third-generation drug-coated stent, and we intend
           to unify it as one type (Xience alpine, everolimus eluting coronary stent, Abbott, USA)
           in order to prevent the difference in results due to differences in stent types.

        4. Expected effects of the research The treatment of acute myocardial infarction has been
           continuously developed not only in the revascularization of the coronary arteries but
           also in the improvement of microvascular perfusion. In addition to conventional thrombus
           aspiration, the use of Glycoprotein IIb / IIIa inhibitors such as Abxicimab has been
           used to improve the therapeutic results. However, it is also true that such treatment
           methods alone have limitations in the prevention and treatment of microvascular
           obstruction. Recently, deferred stenting has been attracting attention as a new method
           to reduce microvascular occlusion. Especially, deferred stenting is expected to have a
           positive result in left anterior wall MI with high microvascular volume. It is expected
           to be able to determine the effect of deferred stenting strategy on the incidence of
           clinical events and improvement of microvascular revascularization in patients with ST
           elevation anterior wall myocardial infarction through this study.

        5. Clinical trial monitoring Monitor personnel designated by the investigator to obtain
           quality test data will review the clinical trial data at appropriate intervals to ensure
           accuracy, completeness, and compliance with the protocol. The monitoring personnel can
           investigate all documents and essential records held by clinical investigators or
           clinical trial laboratories, including the medical records (office, clinic, and
           hospital) of the subjects participating in the clinical trial. Clinical investigators
           and researchers should allow access to these records to the monitoring personnel. The
           monitoring plan will be conducted three times in total, at the time of registering the
           number of subjects corresponding to 50% or more of the total enrollment number, when the
           completed research subject reaches 70% or more, and immediately before the end of the
           study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 3, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>composite of all-cause death, hospitalization due to heart failure, recurrent MI, TVR, major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause death</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac death</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization due to heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrent MI</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TVR</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stent thrombosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial admission date to last outpatient clinic visit or clinical outcome of interest occurs, whichever occur first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MVO volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Post MI 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MVO incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>Post MI 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MVO to infarct size</measure>
    <time_frame>Post MI 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">460</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction With ST Elevation</condition>
  <condition>Anterior Wall Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate stenting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Within enrolled patients who agreed to participate in the study, signed informed consent and being satisfied with inclusion and exclusion criteria, stent implantation is done on the initial procedure in immediate stenting group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deferred stenting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Within enrolled patients who agreed to participate in the study, signed informed consent and being satisfied with inclusion and exclusion criteria, only TIMI Ⅲ flow achievement is done on the initial procedure and stent implantation is deferred for 3-7 days in the deferred stenting group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immediate stenting</intervention_name>
    <description>Abciximab (0.25㎎/㎏) intracoronary injection will be performed to all possible patients after guidewire has passed culprit lesion. Additional manual thrombus aspiration or balloon angioplasty can be performed by operator to achieve TIMI Ⅲ flow. When TIMI Ⅲ flow is achieved after these procedures, patient will be randomized to immediate stenting or deferred stenting group. In immediate stenting group, stenting will be done immediate after achieving TIMI III flow during initial procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate stenting</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferred stenting</intervention_name>
    <description>Abciximab (0.25㎎/㎏) intracoronary injection will be performed to all possible patients after guidewire has passed culprit lesion. Additional manual thrombus aspiration or balloon angioplasty can be performed by operator to achieve TIMI Ⅲ flow. When TIMI Ⅲ flow is achieved after these procedures, patient will be randomized to immediate stenting or deferred stenting group. In deferred stenting group, second stage procedure (stent implantation) will be done at 3 to 7 days after TIMI Ⅲ flow has achieved.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Deferred stenting</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Typical ischemic chest pain lasting more than 30 minutes

          2. New ST elevation at the J point in two contiguous leads with the cut-points: ≥0.1 mV
             in all leads other than leads V2-V3 where the following cut-points apply: 0.2 ≥mV in
             men ≥40 years; ≥0.25 mV in men &lt;40 years, or ≥0.15 mV in women27 or new left bundle
             branch block28.

          3. Symptom onset of chest pain within 6 hours

          4. If left anterior descending artery is culprit lesion on coronary angiography (Ostium
             to mid lesion). However, if the right coronary artery is hypoplastic and the distal
             portion of the left anterior descending artery feeds to the area of the posterior
             lower coronary artery (PDA), culprit lesion of the distal part of left anterior
             descending artery can also be included in the study.

          5. If TIMI blood flow before intervention is 0, 1 or 2

          6. If TIMI 3 blood flow was secured before coronary stenting by intracoronary abciximab
             injection, manual thrombus aspiration and balloon dilatation

          7. Patients who wrote the informed consent: The subject should be able to receive
             informations of treatment, risks, effects and other therapeutic modalities regarding
             staged percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) at least verbally, and investigators
             should be provided written informed consent from a subject or a legally recognized
             representative prior to giving any treatment related to the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. If there is a previous history of myocardial infarction or coronary artery bypass
             surgery

          2. Cardiogenic shock

          3. Rescue PCI after thrombolytic therapy

          4. If the life expectancy of the accompanying disease is expected to be less than one
             year or the patient is not cooperating with the protocol.

          5. In cases where the left main lesion is an infarction related artery (If the left main
             lesion is a simple left main branch lesion rather than an infarction related vessel,
             it is included in the study)

          6. STEMI due to Stent thrombosis

          7. A major dissection (Type C to F) occurred during the procedure including balloon
             dilatation for securing TIMI blood flow and the risk of acute closure at the time of
             staged stenting was expected
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cheol Woong Yu, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cardiovascular center, Korea University Anam Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cheol Woong Yu, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+82-2-920-6726</phone>
    <email>ycw717@naver.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hyungdon Kook, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+82-10-9000-8095</phone>
    <email>kookhyungdon@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Korea University Anam Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>02841</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheol Woong Yu, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+82-2-920-6726</phone>
      <email>ycw717@naver.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Korea University Anam Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Cheol Woong Yu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>STEMI</keyword>
  <keyword>Deferred stenting</keyword>
  <keyword>Anterior wall myocardial infarction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anterior Wall Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

