<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03742505</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VITdALIZE-KIDS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03742505</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rapid Normalization of Vitamin D Deficiency in PICU</brief_title>
  <acronym>VITdALIZE-KIDS</acronym>
  <official_title>Rapid Normalization of Vitamin D Deficiency in PICU: A Multi-Centre Phase III Double-Blind Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>EURO-PHARM International Canada, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Critical Care Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitamin D plays an important role in calcium balance, heart and lung health, inflammation,
      infection prevention, and muscle strength. Due to these roles, it has been suggested that
      critically ill patients with low vitamin D levels might have higher rates of death and worse
      long-term health. We believe that identifying critically ill children with vitamin D
      deficiency and then restoring vitamin D levels quickly could represent a safe, easy and
      inexpensive means of reducing patient illness, preventing death and improving quality of
      life. This clinical trial will determine whether rapid normalization of vitamin D deficiency
      improves survival and health-related quality of life following critical illness. The
      VITdALIZE-KIDS trial is a multicentre randomized clinical trial in Canadian Pediatric
      Intensive Care Units (PICUs). Critically ill children who agree to participate (consent given
      by caregivers) will have their blood vitamin D level measured, and those who are vitamin D
      deficient will be randomized to receive a single dose of either high-dose vitamin D3 or
      placebo (no drug).

      Study participants assigned to the high-dose vitamin D arm will receive 10,000 IU/kg of
      enteral cholecalciferol (up to a maximum of 400,000 IU). We have tested this dose in a pilot
      trial, and no patient experienced serious adverse events related to vitamin D administration.
      Patients will be followed for 90 days to determine whether they survived and had a
      significant change in their health and quality of life. Vitamin D deficiency is a common
      problem not only among critically ill Canadian children, but in PICUs worldwide. In addition
      to being applicable in Canada, our study protocol was designed to be generalizable and
      meaningful to critically ill children worldwide.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Documented roles for vitamin D in calcium homeostasis, cardiovascular and
      respiratory health, innate immunity, and neuromuscular function have led to the hypothesis
      that vitamin D deficiency (VDD) represents a modifiable risk factor for outcomes in critical
      illness. Recently, dozens of adult and pediatric intensive care unit (ICU) studies have
      reported high deficiency rates (50% globally) and associations between VDD, organ dysfunction
      and mortality. Given the cumulative body of basic science and clinical literature, it has
      been hypothesized that high-dose vitamin D supplementation could improve ICU outcomes. Recent
      meta-analyses of multiple small to moderate sized adult clinical trials have suggested
      improvements in clinical outcome following high-dose supplementation, including survival. Two
      large multicentre trials have been initiated in the United States and Europe to confirm these
      findings. In contrast, the benefits and risks of rapid normalization of vitamin D status in
      the pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) have not been evaluated as part of a large
      multicentre clinical trial.

      Study Design: VITdALIZE-KIDS is a Phase III double blind randomized clinical trial (RCT) to
      determine whether rapid normalization of VDD in critically ill children improves clinical
      outcome. In total, 766 critically ill children with VDD will be enrolled from PICUs in
      Canada.

      Objectives: Primary: We will determine if rapid normalization of vitamin D status reduces the
      decline in health-related quality of life (HRQL), including mortality, that follows pediatric
      critical illness. Secondary: We will evaluate the impact of rapid normalization of vitamin D
      status on new or progressive multi-organ dysfunction.

      Eligibility Criteria: 1) Anticipated ICU stay of &gt;48 hours; 2) age 37 weeks corrected
      gestational age to &lt;18 years; 3) expected to require in-hospital clinically indicated blood
      work &gt;48 hours post-enrollment (range 2-7 days); 4) does not meet any exclusion criteria; and
      5) blood 25 hydroxyvitamin D (25OHD) under 50 nmol/l. Patients meeting who meet all
      eligibility criteria and provide consent will be enrolled and randomized.

      Interventions: Single dose at enrolment of 10000 IU/kg of cholecalciferol (max 400000 IU) or
      placebo equivalent in volume to the appropriate dose of cholecalciferol. This dose was
      evaluated in our pilot dose evaluation trial and shown to be effective (raised group 25OHD
      levels &gt;75 nmol/L in &gt;75% of participants) and safe (no cases of hypercalcemia or
      nephrocalcinosis, no difference in the rate of hypercalciuria between study arms).
      Participants may also receive standard vitamin D dosing at the discretion of the care team
      (e.g. 400-1000 IU/day).

      Data Collection: Baseline HRQL (prior to admission) will be obtained within 72 hours of PICU
      admission. Follow-up measurements will be obtained in person (for patients who are still in
      hospital) or by telephone (for patients who have been discharged from hospital) at 28 and 90
      days. Data on organ dysfunction, demographics, hospital course, adverse events, and health
      resource utilization will be collected throughout PICU and hospital stay. A blood sample
      collected at enrollment on Day 5 (range: Day 3-7) to determine 25OHD response and evaluate
      vitamin D axis functioning. An additional blood sample will be collected following specific
      interventions known to significantly reduce 25OHD concentrations, including: cardiopulmonary
      bypass (CPB), extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO), plasma exchange. A urine sample
      will be collected an enrollment and on Day 5 (range: Day 3-7) for analysis of
      calcium:creatinine ratio.

      Significance: High VDD rates in PICUs and the recognized interaction between vitamin D status
      and the health of multiple organ systems suggests vitamin D could represent an inexpensive
      and safe means of improving outcome. However, the true benefits or risks have not been
      evaluated in PICU in a clinical trial. The proposed trial seeks to address this question.
      Study findings will be used to inform guidelines for vitamin D supplementation in PICU, which
      will be easily generalizable to critically ill children worldwide.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pragmatic, Phase III, multi-centre, double-blinded randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The randomization lists will only be accessible to the Methods Centre at the Ottawa Hospital Research Institute and the research pharmacist(s). The active drug and placebo are identical (e.g. colour, consistency, volume, taste, smell, containers).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be health related quality of life. Health related quality of life will be measures using the age-appropriate PedsQL scale (Ages: 2-7, PedsQL 4.0 Generic Core Scales; Ages 1-24 months: PedsQL™ Infant Core Scales (1-24 months). The PedsQL requires only 23 items to score (36 items for the infant scales), a task easily completed in 5-7 minutes and assesses four domains: physical, emotional, social, and school functioning. The mean PedsQL Core Scale is equal to the sum of all items over the number of items answered on all the Scales and generates a number out of 100. The scoring for the scale is the same for both the PedsQL 4.0 Generic Core Scale and PedsQL Infant Core Scale, allowing the score from either scale to be reported together as one outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>New and/or progressive multiple organ dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who develop new or progressive multiple organ dysfunction (NPMODS) will be determined using the updated Pediatric Logistic Organ Dysfunction Score (PELOD-2). For patients with no organ dysfunction at randomization, new multiple organ dysfunction syndrome (MODS) will be defined as the development of ≥2 simultaneous organ dysfunctions during the 28 days following randomization (for patients without organ dysfunction at enrolment) or ≥1 simultaneous organ dysfunction (for patients with at least one existing organ dysfunction at enrolment). Progressive MODS will be defined as development of ≥1 additional simultaneous organ dysfunction in a patient with MODS at enrolment. All deaths will be considered Progressive MODS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status</measure>
    <time_frame>28 and 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured using the Functional Status Scale (FSS), which was developed specifically for PICU research, has been both validated against the pediatric performance scales (PCPC/POPC) and has had meaningful change established (3 points). The FSS includes 6 functional domains (mental status, sensory function, communication, motor function, feeding, and respiratory status) and uses a 5-point scale to rate infant function from 1 (normal) to 5 (very severe dysfunction); total scores range from 6 (normal) to 30 (very severe dysfunction).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>28 and 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Consistent with most critical care studies we will evaluate mortality alone</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PICU length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days post-randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (in hours and days) of PICU length of stay from time of PICU admission and from time of study enrollment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days post-randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Duration (in days) of hospital length of stay from time of admission and from time of study enrollment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 90 days post-randomization</time_frame>
    <description>We will report on the frequency of expected and unexpected serious adverse events plausibly associated with vitamin D administration.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Vitamin D toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 90 days post-randomization</time_frame>
    <description>We will report on the frequency of biochemical and clinical events potentially related to vitamin-D. Biochemical and clinical events possible related to vitamin D administration include hypercalcemia, nephrocalcinosis/renal stones (symptomatic), and gastric perforation/bleeding.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vitamin D status and axis functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>We will evaluate for change in vitamin D status and axis functioning through blood concentrations of the 1,25(OH)2D and 25OHD metabolites.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolomic profiling</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>Non-targeted metabolomics analysis will be performed on blood and urine using an extensively validated multiplexed separation method for high throughput metabolic phenotyping based on muti-segment injection capillary electrophoresis-mass spectrometry10. This method is applicable to the analysis of a wide array of ionic/polar metabolites in volume-limited biological samples with data fidelity, including matching serum and urine specimens.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Analysis - C-Reactive Protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-set of 100 patients (assuming adequate biological sample volume is obtained), we will report on and compare, by group, the baseline and post-intervention levels of multiple biomarkers shown to be vitamin D responsive in other related populations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Analysis - Pro-inflammatory cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-set of 100 patients (assuming adequate biological sample volume is obtained), we will report on and compare, by group, the baseline and post-intervention levels of multiple biomarkers shown to be vitamin D responsive in other related populations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Analysis - Anti-inflammatory cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-set of 100 patients (assuming adequate biological sample volume is obtained), we will report on and compare, by group, the baseline and post-intervention levels of multiple biomarkers shown to be vitamin D responsive in other related populations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Analysis - Brain natriuretic peptide</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-set of 100 patients (assuming adequate biological sample volume is obtained), we will report on and compare, by group, the baseline and post-intervention levels of multiple biomarkers shown to be vitamin D responsive in other related populations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Analysis - Cathelicidin</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-set of 100 patients (assuming adequate biological sample volume is obtained), we will report on and compare, by group, the baseline and post-intervention levels of multiple biomarkers shown to be vitamin D responsive in other related populations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Analysis - Bone markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrolment and on &gt;48 hours following enrollment (range: Day 2-7)</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-set of 100 patients (assuming adequate biological sample volume is obtained), we will report on and compare, by group, the baseline and post-intervention levels of multiple biomarkers shown to be vitamin D responsive in other related populations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">766</enrollment>
  <condition>Vitamin D Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Approximately half of the subjects randomized into VITdALIZE-KIDS will be randomized into the Vitamin D Group and will receive a single dose of cholecalciferol at enrolment.
Participants may also receive standard vitamin D dosing at the discretion of the care team (e.g. 400-1000 IU/day).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Approximately half of the subjects randomized into VITdALIZE-KIDS will be randomized into the Placebo Group and will receive a single dose of placebo at enrolment.
Participants may also receive standard vitamin D dosing at the discretion of the care team (e.g. 400-1000 IU/day).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cholecalciferol</intervention_name>
    <description>Single enteral cholecalciferol load at a dose of 10,000 IU/kg (maximum 400,000 IU)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Single enteral placebo dose equivalent in volume to the appropriate weight-based dose of cholecalciferol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Anticipated PICU stay ≥48 hours

          -  Corrected gestational age 37 weeks to age 18 years

          -  Expected to require clinically indicated blood work &gt;48 hours following study
             enrollment (Range: 2-7 days)

          -  Vitamin D deficiency, as defined by blood 25OHD &lt; 50 nmol/L at the time of screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treating physician refuses enteral drug administration due to gastrointestinal
             disorder,

          -  Persistent hypercalcemia (ionized calcium &gt;1.40 mmol/L (age &gt;2 months), &gt;1.45 (age &lt;2
             months) excluding transient abnormalities and those related to parenteral calcium
             administration for hypocalcemia;

          -  Confirmed or suspected William's syndrome;

          -  Known nephrolithiasis or nephrocalcinosis;

          -  Imminent plan for withdrawal of treatment or transfer to another ICU not participating
             in the VITdALIZE-KIDS trial;

          -  Physician refusal;

          -  Previous enrollment in this trial;

          -  Granulomatous disease (tuberculosis or sarcoidosis);

          -  Severe liver failure;

          -  Hypersensitivity or allergy to vitamin D or any of the non-medicinal ingredients of
             the formulation;

          -  Patient on thiazide diuretics also receiving regular ongoing calcium supplementation
             above the daily recommended intake;

          -  Adolescent female of child-bearing age with a positive pregnancy serum test;

          -  Patient on digoxin-therapy; and

          -  Treating physician intends to administer vitamin D doses above 1000 IU (e.g. patient
             presents with isolated clinical symptoms of severe VDD, severe burns).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dayre McNally, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dayre McNally, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>613-737-7600</phone>
    <phone_ext>3553</phone_ext>
    <email>dmcnally@cheo.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Katie O'Hearn, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>613-737-7600</phone>
    <phone_ext>4006</phone_ext>
    <email>kohearn@cheo.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alberta Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T3B 6A8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Simon Parsons, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BC Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6H 3V4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Srinivas Murthy, MD, CM</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Srinivas Murthy, MD, CM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IWK Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3K 6R8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kristina Krmpotic, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristina Krmpotic, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McMaster Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 3Z5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Choong, MB, MSc</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen Choong, MB, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philip Britz-McKibbin, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Critical Care, Department of Pediatrics, Victoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6C 3T6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Gunz, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Gunz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dayre McNally, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dayre McNally, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kusum Menon, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margaret Lawson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pavel Geier, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montreal Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4A 3J1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Fontela, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia Fontela, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre hospitalier universitaire Sainte-Justine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T 1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marisa Tucci, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philippe Jouvet, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Dayre McNally</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pediatric Intensivist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

