<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03748563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DS-MCE-GOV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03748563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>DS-MCE vs EGD for Diagnosing Gastroesophageal Varices</brief_title>
  <official_title>Detachable String Magnetically Controlled Capsule Endoscopy vs. EGD for Diagnosing Gastroesophageal Varices in Patients With Liver Cirrhosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Changhai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ruijin Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Tongji Hospital, Tongji University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth People’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yangpu District Central Hospital Affiliated to Tongji University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Qilu Hospital of Shandong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Third Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wuhan Union Hospital, China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Changhai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to assess the accuracy of the detachable string magnetically
      controlled capsule endoscopy (DS-MCE) in identifying and grading gastroesophageal varices in
      patients undergoing screening or surveillance for gastroesophageal varices using EGD as the
      golden standard.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The presence of large gastroesophageal varices relates to an increased risk of bleeding,
      esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) is recognized as the gold standard for the detection
      gastroesophageal varices of cirrhotic patients. EGD is however an invasive procedure and
      there is potential for procedure-related complications.

      The development of esophageal capsule endoscopy (ECE) makes it possible to capture clear
      images of esophageal disease without the need for sedation. However, ECE was not accurate
      enough to replace EGD in diagnosing or grading gastroesophageal varices.

      A new technique, so-called detachable string magnetically controlled capsule endoscopy
      (DS-MCE) was developed by ANKON. The movement of capsule can be controlled by the hollow
      string in the esophagus. If attached from the hollow string, the capsule can be controlled
      manually by a magnet robot or automatically using a default mode.

      In this study, the primary aim is to assess the accuracy of the DS-MCE in identifying and
      grading the presence of gastroesophageal varices using EGD as the golden standard.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A prospective self-controlled comparative multi-center study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic yield of the DS-MCE in identifying the presence of gastroesophageal varices</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>assess the diagnostic yield (sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value(PPV), negative predictive value (NPV)) of the DS-MCE in identifying the presence of gastroesophageal varices in participant patients, using esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) as the golden standard.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic yield of the DS-MCE in differentiating high-risk gastroesophageal varices compared to EGD</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>assess the diagnostic yield (sensitivity, specificity, PPV, NPV) of the DS-MCE in differentiating high-risk gastroesophageal varices compared to EGD.
&quot;High risk varices&quot; are defined as small sized varices (diameter &lt; 5 mm) with red color signs or large-sized varices (diameter ≥ 5 mm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic yield of the DS-MCE in identifying portal hypertensive gastropathy (PHG)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>assess the diagnostic yield (sensitivity, specificity, PPV, NPV) of the DS-MCE in identifying portal hypertensive gastropathy (PHG) using the EGD as gold standard.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the prevalence of portal hypertensive enteropathy (PHE) in the small bowel</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>assess the prevalence of PHE in the small bowel of participant patients. The DS-MCE digital image stream will be reviewed by endoscopists, portal hypertensive enteropathy will be classified as absent or present.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>circumferential visualization of the Z line</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the circumferential visualization of the Z line will be calculated during the DS-MCE procedure.
Circumferential visualization of the Z line by the DS-MCE will be defined by quadrants as follows: Z line not observed at all; less than 2 quadrants (&lt; 50 %) of the Z line observed; between 2 quadrants and 3 quadrants (50 % ± 75 %) observed; more than 3 quadrants (&gt; 75 %) observed; and entire Z line (100 %) observed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>quality score of Z-line images</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the quality score of air-bubble and saliva interference on the Z-line view will be calculated during DS-MCE procedure.
The effect of bubbles/saliva on the appearance of the Z line area will be scored as follows: 0 = no interference by bubbles/saliva on the Z line area;1 = minor interference of bubbles/saliva on the Z line area; 2 = major interference of bubbles/saliva on the Z line area.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>transit time of DS-MCE in the gastrointestinal tract</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>assess the transit time of DS-MCE in the gastrointestinal tract (esophagus, stomach, small bowel).
Esophageal transit time: time from the capsule entering to leaving the esophagus.
Gastric transit time: time from the capsule entering to leaving the stomach.
Small bowel transit time: time from the capsule entering to leaving the small bowel.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>degree of comfort</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>evaluate patient's degree of comfort throughout the DS-MCE procedure. Patients will be asked to fill in a questionnaire to give scores about degree of comfort throughout the procedure. Overall discomfort was scored on a scale of 0 to 10 (0, no discomfort; 10, the overall discomfort of EGD). Lower scores represent that the examination of DS-MCE is more comfortable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the presence of adverse events during DS-MCE procedure and EGD procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of adverse events during DS-MCE procedure and EGD procedure will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">512</enrollment>
  <condition>Cirrhosis, Liver</condition>
  <condition>Portal Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DS-MCE and EGD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All the enrolled participants will undergo the examination of detachable string magnetically controlled capsule endoscopy (DS-MCE) first, followed by EGD within 48 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DS-MCE and EGD</intervention_name>
    <description>Procedure of DS-MCE:
The DS-MCE system mainly consists of two parts: the NaviCam magnetic capsule guidance system and the detachable string part. In the esophagus, the movement of capsule can be controlled by the hollow string as the latex sleeve tightly wrapped around the end of the capsule. If attached from the hollow string, the capsule can be controlled manually by a magnet robot in the stomach or automatically using a default mode in the small bowel.
Procedure of EGD:
Subjects will undergo standard esophagogastroduodenoscopy(EGD) procedure within 48 hours after DS-MCE procedure. The EGD will be performed using conventional standard forward viewing upper gastrointestinal video endoscopes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DS-MCE and EGD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Gender is not limited.

          2. Patients aged 18 years or older.

          3. Both inpatients and outpatients.

          4. Clinically evident or biopsy-proven liver cirrhosis, without previous diagnosis of
             gastroesophageal varices but with clinical indication for screening endoscopy for the
             detection of varices, or with prior endoscopic diagnosis of gastroesophageal varices
             and indication for surveillance endoscopy.

          5. Able to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients aged less than 18 years.

          2. Patients with active upper gastrointestinal bleeding.

          3. Previous history of variceal bleeding.

          4. Previous endoscopic treatment of gastroesophageal varices (such as: endoscopic
             variceal ligation, endoscopic injection sclerotherapy).

          5. Patients with cancer on active treatment with chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy.

          6. Pregnancy or suspected pregnancy.

          7. Suspected or known intestinal stenosis or other known risk factors for capsule
             retention.

          8. Pacemaker or other implanted electromedical devices which could interfere with
             magnetic resonance.

          9. Patients with dysphagia.

         10. Life-threatening conditions.

         11. Patients who refuse to undergo or do not tolerate EGD.

         12. Patients whose consents for removal of remained DS-MCE are unable to be obtained.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhuan Liao</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Changhai Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhuan Liao, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>86-21-31161004</phone>
    <email>liaozhuan@smmu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Changhai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <zip>200433</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhuan Liao</last_name>
      <phone>86-21-31161004</phone>
      <email>liaozhuan@smmu.edu.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xi Jiang</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jun Pan</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Franchis R; Baveno VI Faculty. Expanding consensus in portal hypertension: Report of the Baveno VI Consensus Workshop: Stratifying risk and individualizing care for portal hypertension. J Hepatol. 2015 Sep;63(3):743-52. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2015.05.022. Epub 2015 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26047908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>North Italian Endoscopic Club for the Study and Treatment of Esophageal Varices. Prediction of the first variceal hemorrhage in patients with cirrhosis of the liver and esophageal varices. A prospective multicenter study. N Engl J Med. 1988 Oct 13;319(15):983-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3262200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spina GP, Arcidiacono R, Bosch J, Pagliaro L, Burroughs AK, Santambrogio R, Rossi A. Gastric endoscopic features in portal hypertension: final report of a consensus conference, Milan, Italy, September 19, 1992. J Hepatol. 1994 Sep;21(3):461-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7836719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sarin SK, Lahoti D, Saxena SP, Murthy NS, Makwana UK. Prevalence, classification and natural history of gastric varices: a long-term follow-up study in 568 portal hypertension patients. Hepatology. 1992 Dec;16(6):1343-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1446890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kodama M, Uto H, Numata M, Hori T, Murayama T, Sasaki F, Tsubouchi N, Ido A, Shimoda K, Tsubouchi H. Endoscopic characterization of the small bowel in patients with portal hypertension evaluated by double balloon endoscopy. J Gastroenterol. 2008;43(8):589-96. doi: 10.1007/s00535-008-2198-1. Epub 2008 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>18709480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Amico G, De Franchis R; Cooperative Study Group. Upper digestive bleeding in cirrhosis. Post-therapeutic outcome and prognostic indicators. Hepatology. 2003 Sep;38(3):599-612.</citation>
    <PMID>12939586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garcia-Tsao G, Sanyal AJ, Grace ND, Carey W; Practice Guidelines Committee of the American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases; Practice Parameters Committee of the American College of Gastroenterology. Prevention and management of gastroesophageal varices and variceal hemorrhage in cirrhosis. Hepatology. 2007 Sep;46(3):922-38. Erratum in: Hepatology. 2007 Dec;46(6):2052.</citation>
    <PMID>17879356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lapalus MG, Dumortier J, Fumex F, Roman S, Lot M, Prost B, Mion F, Ponchon T. Esophageal capsule endoscopy versus esophagogastroduodenoscopy for evaluating portal hypertension: a prospective comparative study of performance and tolerance. Endoscopy. 2006 Jan;38(1):36-41.</citation>
    <PMID>16429353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gralnek IM, Adler SN, Yassin K, Koslowsky B, Metzger Y, Eliakim R. Detecting esophageal disease with second-generation capsule endoscopy: initial evaluation of the PillCam ESO 2. Endoscopy. 2008 Apr;40(4):275-9. doi: 10.1055/s-2007-995645.</citation>
    <PMID>18389444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Franchis R, Eisen GM, Laine L, Fernandez-Urien I, Herrerias JM, Brown RD, Fisher L, Vargas HE, Vargo J, Thompson J, Eliakim R. Esophageal capsule endoscopy for screening and surveillance of esophageal varices in patients with portal hypertension. Hepatology. 2008 May;47(5):1595-603. doi: 10.1002/hep.22227.</citation>
    <PMID>18435461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Changhai Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhuan Liao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Capsule Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Portal Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Cirrhosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Portal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

