<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03741140</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C17-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03741140</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterizing the Neural Bases of Motivational Disorders After Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>StrokeMotiv</acronym>
  <official_title>Characterizing the Neural Bases of Motivational Disorders After Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to quantify elementary mechanisms of motivation, with innovative
      tools adapted to clinical settings, in healthy subjects, and in stroke patients, and to
      investigate their predictive value related to morbimortality, disability, and dependence. The
      secondary aim of the study is to investigate the neural substrates of motivational
      mechanisms, and to study the impact of lesions in the grey and the white matter, the
      influence of lesion site, and the consequences of disconnection in functional networks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Disorders of motivation, such as apathy, are among the most prevalent symptoms in
      neuropsychiatric disorders and during chronic diseases. They have a major impact on patients'
      physical activity and lifestyle, and on their involvement in their own care. They affect a
      wide range of morbidity outcomes, alter functional recovery in rehabilitation, impair
      long-term disability, and prevent patients from returning to an active and independent life.
      Yet, the neural bases of motivational deficits remain largely unknown. Current diagnostic
      tools are sparse and cannot distinguish between distinct mechanisms responsible for apathetic
      syndromes. Besides, current treatments remain extremely limited. However, recent advances in
      the field of neuroeconomics - the science of decision-making - have provided concept and
      tools to study the neurobiological bases of elementary cognitive processes underlying
      motivated behaviors. These theories suggest that the brain implements optimization processes
      that determine our behaviors by minimizing the cost of our actions while maximizing their
      expected benefits. The adaptation of tools developed for basic research now enables the
      assessment of these cognitive mechanisms.

      Elementary deficits of motivation will be assessed with a phenotyping battery of motivation
      tests in 20 healthy subjects, 20 patients with a recent stroke in the medial prefrontal
      cortex, and 20 patients with a stroke in the insula. This battery will allow us to
      characterize, at the patient's level, elementary processes such as the encoding and the
      learning rate of goal values or effort costs, the modulation of value with delay or episodic
      context, the modulation of cost with fatigue, and the resolution of cost-benefit trade-offs.
      We will monitor morbimortality outcomes, such as the functional recovery in rehabilitation,
      the delay of professional activity recovery after stroke, disability, quality of life and
      burden for caregivers. Symptom-Lesion mapping studies and voxel-based morphometry studies
      will be performed using whole brain MRI measures of structural and functional integrity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reward sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The reward sensitivity measures the impact of reward values on behavior</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effort sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The effort sensitivity measures the impact of effort costs on behavior</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>medial frontal stroke</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 patients with a recent stroke (&lt;1 month) in the medial frontal lobe will be included in this arm, and will undergo motivation phenotyping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lateral frontal stroke</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 patients with a recent stroke (&lt;1 month) in the lateral frontal lobe will be included in this arm, and will undergo motivation phenotyping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 patients Healthy participants will be included in this arm, and will undergo motivation phenotyping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivation tests</intervention_name>
    <description>Motivation tests will characterize elementary deficits of motivation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>lateral frontal stroke</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>medial frontal stroke</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;18

          -  Stroke &lt; 1 month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other neurological or psychiatric disease

          -  use of illicit psychoactive drugs

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Contra-indication to MRI scan

          -  Severe cognitive deficit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

