<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03745677</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R18HS025649</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03745677</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Redesigning Systems to Improve Quality for Hospitalized Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESET</acronym>
  <official_title>Redesigning Systems to Improve Quality for Hospitalized Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Society of Hospital Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Kentucky</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alamance Regional Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baptist Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Good Samaritan Regional Medical Center, Oregon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ball Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Texas at Austin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite recent improvements, healthcare systems are still a long way from consistently
      delivering high quality care to hospitalized patients. In this study, the research team is
      assisting hospitals in implementing a set of complementary, mutually reinforcing
      interventions to redesign care for hospitalized medical patients. The investigators
      anticipate the interventions will improve teamwork and patient outcomes and that identifiable
      factors and strategies will be associated with successful implementation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most adults requiring hospitalization are admitted for medical conditions, yet the optimal
      model of care for these patients is yet to be established. Current care delivery models lack
      the ability to optimally coordinate care on a daily basis and improve performance over time.
      A growing body of research has tested interventions to redesign aspects of care delivery for
      hospitalized medical patients. These interventions improve processes and culture, but the
      evidence that patient outcomes have improved is equivocal. Importantly, most studies have
      examined the effect of single interventions in isolation, yet these interventions are better
      conceptualized as complementary and mutually reinforcing components of a redesigned clinical
      microsystem. Clinical microsystems are the front line care giving units where patients,
      families, and care teams meet. Our research team developed a set of complementary, mutually
      reinforcing interventions based on available evidence and anchored in a clinical microsystem
      framework. The 5 Advanced and Integrated MicroSystems (AIMS) interventions include: 1)
      Unit-based Physician Teams, 2) Unit Nurse-Physician Co-leadership, 3) Enhanced
      Interdisciplinary Rounds, 4) Unit-level Performance Reports, 5) Patient Engagement
      Activities. Our long term goal is to discover and disseminate the optimal model of care to
      improve outcomes for hospitalized patients. Our specific objective for this proposal is to
      implement a set of evidence-based complementary interventions across a range of clinical
      microsystems, identify factors and strategies associated with successful implementation, and
      evaluate the impact on quality. Our research team is using mentored implementation, i.e.,
      coaching by external professionals who are experts in the area of focus, to help facilitate
      change. The research team has enrolled 4 hospitals in this quality improvement mentored
      implementation study. Our hypothesis is that uptake of the complementary components of the
      intervention set will result in improvements in teamwork climate and patient outcomes.

      Specific Aims of the Redesigning Systems to Improve Quality for Hospitalized Patients (RESET)
      study include:

        1. Conduct a multi-site mentored implementation study in which each site adapts and
           implements complementary interventions to improve care for medical patients.

        2. Evaluate the effect of the intervention set on teamwork climate and patient outcomes
           related to safety, patient experience, and efficiency.

        3. Assess how site-specific contextual factors interact with the variation in the intensity
           and fidelity of implementation to effect teamwork and patient outcomes.

      The findings generated from this study will be directly applicable to hospitals throughout
      the U.S. and our partnership with the Society of Hospital Medicine, the American Nurses
      Association, and the Institute for Patient- and Family-Centered Care will ensure effective
      dissemination and impact.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two group pretest-posttest analysis</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Teamwork climate using the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Administered annually in years 1 through 4</time_frame>
    <description>14 item validated survey tool to assess teamwork climate in clinical settings. The survey will be administered via REDcap to all nurses, physicians, pharmacists, social workers, and case managers on study units.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Medical record review of patients hospitalized in years 1 through 3.</time_frame>
    <description>We will use the Medicare Patient Safety Monitoring System (MPSMS) methodology to detect adverse events. MPSMS is a medical record-based national patient safety surveillance system that provides rates for specific inpatient adverse event measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient experience</measure>
    <time_frame>Years 1 through 3.</time_frame>
    <description>We will use Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems (HCAHPS) global ratings of hospital care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Years 1 through 3</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay for patients admitted to study unit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>30 day readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>Years 1 through 3</time_frame>
    <description>30 day readmissions for patients admitted to the study units</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5808</enrollment>
  <condition>Interdisciplinary Communication</condition>
  <condition>Interpersonal Relations</condition>
  <condition>Adverse Event</condition>
  <condition>Interprofessional Relations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each study site has selected 1-2 units ideally suited for initial implementation of the Advanced and Integrated MicroSystems (AIMS) interventions (Phase I Implementation) and 1-2 units for later implementation of AIMS interventions (Phase II Implementation). During Implementation Phase I, AIMS interventions were implemented on the initial, phase I Implementation units. The phase II units serve as control units during phase I.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During Implementation Phase II, Advanced and Integrated MicroSystems (AIMS) interventions are being implemented on additional, phase II implementation units, leveraging lessons learned during phase I.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Advanced and Integrated MicroSystems (AIMS) interventions</intervention_name>
    <description>Each of 4 sites is receiving mentorship from nurse and physician with expertise in implementing similar interventions. The AIMS interventions consist of 1) unit-based physician teams, 2) unit nurse-physician co-leadership, 3) enhanced interprofessional rounds, 4) unit-level performance reports, and 5) patient engagement activities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients admitted, under inpatient or observation status, to study units

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients transferred from other hospitals and those initially admitted to other units.

          -  Patients admitted under non-medical services on the study units.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin O'Leary</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kevin O'Leary, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>3129265924</phone>
    <email>keoleary@nm.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jane Kim, M.Ed.</last_name>
    <email>jane.kim@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baptist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pensacola</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Sullivan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>850-434-4011</phone>
      <email>john.sullivan@bhcpns.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laurie Veve, RN</last_name>
      <phone>850.434.4011</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Ball Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muncie</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>47303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Gamble, MD</last_name>
      <phone>765-747-3111</phone>
      <email>cdgamble@IUHealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah Madden, RN</last_name>
      <phone>765.747.3111</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alamance Regional Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vipul Shah, MD</last_name>
      <phone>336-832-7000</phone>
      <email>Vipul.Shah@conehealth.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carol Harris, RN</last_name>
      <phone>3368327000</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Legacy Good Samaritan Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ellen Duplain, MD</last_name>
      <phone>503-413-7711</phone>
      <email>EDUPLAIN@LHS.ORG</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jeanna Stephan, RN</last_name>
      <phone>503-413-7711</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary KJ, Killarney A, Hansen LO, Jones S, Malladi M, Marks K, M Shah H. Effect of patient-centred bedside rounds on hospitalised patients' decision control, activation and satisfaction with care. BMJ Qual Saf. 2016 Dec;25(12):921-928. doi: 10.1136/bmjqs-2015-004561. Epub 2015 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26628552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary KJ, Creden AJ, Slade ME, Landler MP, Kulkarni N, Lee J, Vozenilek JA, Pfeifer P, Eller S, Wayne DB, Williams MV. Implementation of unit-based interventions to improve teamwork and patient safety on a medical service. Am J Med Qual. 2015 Sep-Oct;30(5):409-16. doi: 10.1177/1062860614538093. Epub 2014 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24919598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary KJ, Buck R, Fligiel HM, Haviley C, Slade ME, Landler MP, Kulkarni N, Hinami K, Lee J, Cohen SE, Williams MV, Wayne DB. Structured interdisciplinary rounds in a medical teaching unit: improving patient safety. Arch Intern Med. 2011 Apr 11;171(7):678-84. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2011.128.</citation>
    <PMID>21482844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary KJ, Wayne DB, Landler MP, Kulkarni N, Haviley C, Hahn KJ, Jeon J, Englert KM, Williams MV. Impact of localizing physicians to hospital units on nurse-physician communication and agreement on the plan of care. J Gen Intern Med. 2009 Nov;24(11):1223-7. doi: 10.1007/s11606-009-1113-7. Epub 2009 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19768510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary KJ, Johnson JK, Manojlovich M, Astik GJ, Williams MV. Use of Unit-Based Interventions to Improve the Quality of Care for Hospitalized Medical Patients: A National Survey. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2017 Nov;43(11):573-579. doi: 10.1016/j.jcjq.2017.05.008. Epub 2017 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29056177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pannick S, Davis R, Ashrafian H, Byrne BE, Beveridge I, Athanasiou T, Wachter RM, Sevdalis N. Effects of Interdisciplinary Team Care Interventions on General Medical Wards: A Systematic Review. JAMA Intern Med. 2015 Aug;175(8):1288-98. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2015.2421. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26076428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh S, Tarima S, Rana V, Marks DS, Conti M, Idstein K, Biblo LA, Fletcher KE. Impact of localizing general medical teams to a single nursing unit. J Hosp Med. 2012 Sep;7(7):551-6. doi: 10.1002/jhm.1948. Epub 2012 Jul 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22791661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson EC, Godfrey MM, Batalden PB, Berry SA, Bothe AE Jr, McKinley KE, Melin CN, Muething SE, Moore LG, Wasson JH, Nolan TW. Clinical microsystems, part 1. The building blocks of health systems. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2008 Jul;34(7):367-78.</citation>
    <PMID>18677868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kara A, Johnson CS, Nicley A, Niemeier MR, Hui SL. Redesigning inpatient care: Testing the effectiveness of an accountable care team model. J Hosp Med. 2015 Dec;10(12):773-9. doi: 10.1002/jhm.2432. Epub 2015 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26286828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein J, Payne C, Methvin A, Bonsall JM, Chadwick L, Clark D, Castle BW, Tong D, Dressler DD. Reorganizing a hospital ward as an accountable care unit. J Hosp Med. 2015 Jan;10(1):36-40. doi: 10.1002/jhm.2284. Epub 2014 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25399928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li J, Hinami K, Hansen LO, Maynard G, Budnitz T, Williams MV. The physician mentored implementation model: a promising quality improvement framework for health care change. Acad Med. 2015 Mar;90(3):303-10. doi: 10.1097/ACM.0000000000000547.</citation>
    <PMID>25354069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kevin O'Leary</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Hospital Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

