<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03748979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-925-1003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1221-3144</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>JapicCTI-184207</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03748979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of TAK-925 in Healthy Volunteers and Patients With Narcolepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 3-Part, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Multiple Rising Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of TAK-925 in Healthy Volunteers and Patients With Narcolepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and
      pharmacodynamics of TAK-925 when administered to healthy participants and narcolepsy
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called TAK-925. TAK-925 is being tested in healthy
      participants and patients with narcolepsy. This study will look at the safety, tolerability,
      pharmacokinetics, and efficacy of TAK-925.

      This study will consist of three parts. Part A will be a randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled, multiple rising dose (MRD) study in healthy participants. Part B is a
      randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled MRD study in patients with narcolepsy. Part C is
      a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group, multiple repeat dose study in
      patients with narcolepsy. Part A' is a single dose study in healthy participants.

      The study will enroll approximately 96 participants planned as total. All participants except
      Part A' will be randomly assigned (by chance, like flipping a coin) to one of the two
      treatment groups—which will remain undisclosed to the patient and study doctor during the
      study (unless there is an urgent medical need):

      Part A:

        -  TAK-925 (Dose Levels A1-A6)

        -  Placebo

      Part B:

        -  TAK-925 (Dose Levels B1-B4)

        -  Placebo

      Part C:

        -  TAK-925 (Dose Levels C1-C2)

        -  Placebo

      Part A':

      • TAK-925 (Dose Levels A'1-A'2)

      All participants will be asked to take TAK-925 or Placebo at the same time each day from Day
      1 to Day 7 in Parts A, B and C, and take TAK-925 on Day 1 in Part A'.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted in Japan. The overall study period is approximately
      15 days in Parts A, B and C, and approximately 7 days for Part A'. Participants will be
      partly admitted to a hospital during the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 25, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Experience at Least One Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (TEAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>An Adverse Event (AE) is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant who has signed informed consent to participate in a study; it does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment. A treatment-emergent adverse event (TEAE) is defined as an adverse event with an onset that occurs after receiving study drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Observed Plasma Concentration at the End of Administration for TAK-925 in Parts A, B and C</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-Time Curve during a Dosing Interval (AUCtau) for TAK-925 in Parts A, B and C</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accumulation Ratio Based on AUCtau for TAK-925 in Parts A, B and C</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Sleep Latency in the Maintenance of Wakefulness Test (MWT) to Days 1 and 7 in Parts B and C</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 1 and to Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>The reported data for this outcome measure will be percentage of the participant who recorded the MWT over 40 minutes in Day 1 and Day 7 in Parts B and C. The MWT is a measure that evaluates a person's ability to remain awake under soporific conditions for a defined period of time. In the MWT, time from start of the test to the time point of falling asleep will be measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>17</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Participants</condition>
  <condition>Narcolepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A1; TAK-925 (Dose Level A1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A2; TAK-925 (Dose Level A2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A2, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy participants. Dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A3; TAK-925 (Dose Level A3)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A3, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy participants. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A4; TAK-925 (Dose Level A4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A4, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy participants. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A5; TAK-925 (Dose Level A5)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A5, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy participants. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A6; TAK-925 (Dose Level A6)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A6, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy elderly participants. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part A (Cohorts A1-A6); TAK-925 Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925 Placebo, once daily for up to 7 days in healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B1; TAK-925 (Dose Level B1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level B1, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B2; TAK-925 (Dose Level B2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level B2, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy. Dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B3; TAK-925 (Dose Level B3)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level B3, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B4; TAK-925 (Dose Level B4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level B4, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part B (Cohorts B1-B4); TAK-925 Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925 Placebo, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort C1; TAK-925 (Dose Level C1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level C1, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy. Dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort C2; TAK-925 (Dose Level C2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level C2, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy. This group is an additional optional cohort and dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part C (Cohorts C1-C2); TAK-925 Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925 Placebo, once daily for up to 7 days in patients with narcolepsy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A'1; TAK-925 (Dose Level A'1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A'1, single dose in healthy participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A'2; TAK-925 (Dose Level A'2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-925, Dose Level A'2, single dose in healthy participants. Dose level will be determined based on the data of safety, tolerability and PK data from previous cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-925</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-925</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A'1; TAK-925 (Dose Level A'1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A'2; TAK-925 (Dose Level A'2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A1; TAK-925 (Dose Level A1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A2; TAK-925 (Dose Level A2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A3; TAK-925 (Dose Level A3)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A4; TAK-925 (Dose Level A4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A5; TAK-925 (Dose Level A5)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A6; TAK-925 (Dose Level A6)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B1; TAK-925 (Dose Level B1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B2; TAK-925 (Dose Level B2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B3; TAK-925 (Dose Level B3)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B4; TAK-925 (Dose Level B4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort C1; TAK-925 (Dose Level C1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort C2; TAK-925 (Dose Level C2)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-925 Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part A (Cohorts A1-A6); TAK-925 Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part B (Cohorts B1-B4); TAK-925 Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part C (Cohorts C1-C2); TAK-925 Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy adult participants and Healthy elderly participants:

        • Participant weighs at least 50 kg (Healthy adults participants) / 40 kg (Healthy elderly
        participants) and has a body mass index (BMI) from 18.5 to 30 kg/m^2, inclusive at
        Screening.

        Narcolepsy patients:

          -  Patient weighs at least 40 kg inclusive at Screening (≥50 kg is required for Cohort
             B4).

          -  A diagnosis of narcolepsy, as defined by the International Classification of Sleep
             Disorders, Third Edition (ICSD-3).

          -  At Day -1, Epworth sleepiness scale (ESS) score ≥10

        Exclusion Criteria:

        All Participants:

          -  Participants consume excessive amounts, defined as greater than 6 servings (1 serving
             is approximately equivalent to 120 mg of caffeine) of coffee, tea, cola, energy
             drinks, or other caffeinated beverages per day.

          -  Participants have a moderate to severe substance use disorder.

          -  Participants have a risk of suicide according to endorsement of item 4 or 5 with
             Screening/Baseline visit C-SSRS or has made a suicide attempt in the previous 6
             months.

          -  Participants have a lifetime history of major psychiatric disorder, such as bipolar
             disorder or schizophrenia.

          -  Participants experienced sleep wake cycle disturbance with external factors such as
             irregular work hours.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sumida Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sumida-ku</city>
        <state>Tokyo</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hakata Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PS Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Narcolepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Takeda makes patient-level, de-identified data sets and associated documents available for all interventional studies after applicable marketing approvals and commercial availability have been received (or program is completely terminated), an opportunity for the primary publication of the research and final report development has been allowed, and other criteria have been met as set forth in Takeda's Data Sharing Policy (see www.TakedaClinicalTrials.com for details). To obtain access, researchers must submit a legitimate academic research proposal for adjudication by an independent review panel, who will review the scientific merit of the research and the requestor's qualifications and conflict of interest that can result in potential bias. Once approved, qualified researchers who sign a data sharing agreement are provided access to these data in a secure research environment.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

