<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03745261</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Yong Chong Cao for COPD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03745261</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Yong Chong Cao Capsule on Outcomes in Patients With Mild to Severe COPD</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-center, Open-label, Randomized, Controlled Study to Evaluate the Effectiveness of Yong Chong Cao Capsule on Outcomes in Patients With Mild to Severe COPD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henan University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jiangsu Famous Medical Technology Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Henan University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of Yong Chong Cao capsule on outcomes
      in patients with mild to severe Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to compare the effectiveness of two treatments for mild to severe
      COPD patients: one, Yong Chong Cao capsule treatment and conventional medicine based on 2017
      Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) and Chinese Treatment
      Guidelines; the other, Bailing capsule treatment and conventional medicine.

      COPD, with high prevalence, morbidity, mortality and economic burdens, affects millions
      worldwide. Although many therapies exist and are being developed to relieve symptoms and
      reduce mortality in COPD, most have only been studied in placebo-controlled efficacy studies
      in highly selected populations. There are few clinical trials to compare therapeutic
      alternatives in real world. Furthermore, some randomized controlled trials on Yong Chong Cao
      capsule, one therapeutic type of Cordyceps sinensis in traditional Chinese medicine (TCM)
      interventions, especially based on the syndrome of insufficiency of qi of the lung and kidney
      patterns, have been the certain evidence for showing definite effect for COPD patients. In
      addition, studies in real world populations of COPD that received different cordyceps
      sinensis therapies that do have efficacy evidence was found wide variations in care delivery.
      In short, there is a need to compare the effectiveness of two capsule in patients with mild
      to severe COPD.

      This is a multi-center, open-label, randomized, controlled study to evaluate the
      effectiveness of Yong Chong Cao capsule for patients with mild to severe COPD compared with
      Bailing capsule. Following a 14 day run-in period, approximately 240 subjects will be
      randomly assigned to Yong Chong Cao capsule treatment group, Bailing capsule treatment group
      for 24 weeks. After the 24 weeks treatment period, subjects in two treatments arms will
      follow-up 24 weeks. The primary outcome measure is the frequency of exacerbations. The
      secondary efficacy measures include FEV1, dyspnea (MMRC), exercise capacity(6MWD), quality of
      life (CAT, SGRQ). Safety will be assessed through the collection of adverse events. There
      will be a total of 4 study visits (baseline, the 12 and 24 weeks of the treatment, the 24
      weeks of follow-up).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The frequency of exacerbation of COPD</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in the frequency of exacerbation at the week 12 and week 24 of the treatment phase, and at the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>The exacerbation of COPD often results in reduced quality of life, increased rate of lung function decline, increased hospitalization. It is important to assess the changes of exacerbations over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Modified Medical Research Council scale scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in the mMRC scores at the week 12 and week 24 of the treatment phase, and the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Using Modified Medical Research Council ( mMRC) scale to assess a patient's level of dyspnea. The MMRC scale is a simple grading system that scored from 0 (less severe) to 4 (severe).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Forced expiratory volume in one second</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in FEV1 at the week 24 of the treatment phase and the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) is the amount of air that can be exhaled in one second. A positive change from baseline in FEV1 indicates improvement in lung function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in COPD Assessment Test scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in the CAT scores at the week 12 and week 24 of the treatment phase, and the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the COPD Assessment Test ( CAT) , to assess the impact of COPD on a person's symptom, and how this changes over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Six Minutes Walking Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in the 6WMD scores at the week 12 and week 24 of the treatment phase, and the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the results of six Minutes Walking Distance (6MWD)Test to assess the exercise tolerance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in St Georges respiratory questionnaire scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in the SGRQ scores at the week 12 and week 24 of the treatment phase, and the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire(SGRQ), to assess the impact of COPD on a person's life, and how this changes over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in clinical COPD questionnaire scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in the CCQ scores at the week 12 and week 24 of the treatment phase, and the week 24 of the follow-up phase compared with baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the clinical COPD questionnaire (CCQ), to assess the impact of COPD on a person's life, and how this changes over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>YCC capsule+conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be given Yong Chong Cao (YCC) capsule and conventional medicine based on the classes of medications recommended by 2017 GOLD and Chinese Treatment Guidelines for COPD,which are Group A patients: Salbutamol (Ventolin®),Group B and Group C patients: Tiotropium Bromide (Spiriva®),Group D patients: Salmeterol / fluticasone (Seretide®).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BL capsule + conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be given Bailing (BL) capsule and conventional medicine based on the classes of medications recommended by 2017 GOLD and Chinese Treatment Guidelines for COPD, which are Group A patients: Salbutamol (Ventolin®),Group B and Group C patients: Tiotropium Bromide (Spiriva®),Group D patients: Salmeterol / fluticasone (Seretide®).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Salbutamol (Ventolin®)</intervention_name>
    <description>According to the revised 2017 GOLD, patients will be divided into Group A, B, C, and D based on individualized assessment. Salbutamol will be used to Group A patients: Salbutamol (Ventolin®, GlaxoSmithKline) 100μg/dose. 100 μg each time (when needed), and the maximum dose is 8-12 inhalations a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BL capsule + conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>YCC capsule+conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Group A patients: Salbutamol (Ventolin®).</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tiotropium Bromide (Spiriva®)</intervention_name>
    <description>Tiotropium Bromide Powder for Inhalation will be used to Group B and Group C patients: Tiotropium Bromide Powder for Inhalation(Spiriva®, Boehringer Ingelheim), 18μg/ capsule, 10 capsules. 18μg each time, once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BL capsule + conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>YCC capsule+conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Group B and C patients: Tiotropium Bromide (Spiriva®)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Salmeterol / fluticasone (Seretide®)</intervention_name>
    <description>Salmeterol / fluticasone will be used to Group D patients: Salmeterol / fluticasone (Seretide®, GlaxoSmithKline), 50/250 μg / dose, 60 inhalations. 50/250 μg each time, twice daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BL capsule + conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>YCC capsule+conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Group D patients: Salmeterol / fluticasone (Seretide®)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>YCC capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>According to traditional Chinese syndrome differentiation and treatment, patients with syndrome of insufficiency of qi of the lung and kidney will be given Yong Chong Cao (YCC)capsule (Kecai®, Guangdong daguang pharmaceutical group Co., Ltd), 1 g each time, three times a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>YCC capsule+conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BL capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>According to traditional Chinese syndrome differentiation and treatment, patients with syndrome of insufficiency of qi of the lung and kidney will be given Bailing(BL) capsule (Bailing®, Huadong Medicine Co.,Ltd), 1 g each time, three times a day</description>
    <arm_group_label>BL capsule + conventional medicine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A confirmed diagnosis of mild to severe COPD.

          -  Medically stable.

          -  Syndrome differentiation belongs to syndrome of insufficiency of qi of the lung and
             kidney.

          -  Age between 18 and 80 years.

          -  With the informed consent signed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women.

          -  Current respiratory disorders other than COPD (e.g., bronchiectasis, bronchial asthma,
             tuberculosis, lung fibrosis, pulmonary thromboembolic, diffuse panbronchiolitis, lung
             cancer).

          -  Complicated with heart failure (NYHA Class III or IV), or myocardial infarction within
             six months ,or unstable hemodynamics.

          -  Complicated with serious hepatic and renal diseases (liver cirrhosis, portal
             hypertension, bleeding of varicose veins, dialysis, or renal transplantation).

          -  Any psychiatric condition rendering the patient unable to understand the nature, scope
             and possible consequences of the study.

          -  Participating in other trials or allergic to the used medicine.

          -  Participating in other clinical trials with other interventions in one month.

          -  Allergic to the used medicine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suyun Li, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of HUCM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jiajia Wang, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+86 371 66248624</phone>
    <email>wangiahn@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yang Xie, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86 371 66248624</phone>
    <email>xieyanghn@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Henan University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zhengzhou</city>
        <state>Henan</state>
        <zip>450000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yang Xie, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>+8637166248624</phone>
      <email>xieyanghn@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</keyword>
  <keyword>mild, moderate, severe</keyword>
  <keyword>Medicine, Chinese Traditional</keyword>
  <keyword>Cordyceps sinensis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bromides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albuterol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tiotropium Bromide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salmeterol Xinafoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone-Salmeterol Drug Combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

