<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03745911</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>X31005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-004486-27</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03745911</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paclitaxel and TAK-228 in Urothelial Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Paclitaxel and TAK-228 in Metastatic Urothelial Carcinoma (UC) and the Impact of PI3K-mTOR Pathway Genomic Alterations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Associació per a la Recerca Oncologica, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pivotal S.L.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Associació per a la Recerca Oncologica, Spain</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase II Multicentre, single arm, open label study of Paclitaxel and TAK-228 in metastatic
      urothelial carcinoma (UC) and the impact of PI3K-mTOR pathway genomic alterations
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway has been shown to be altered in a large percentage of metastatic
      urothelial carcinoma (UC) tumors. Within this pathway, the PI3 kinase alpha subunit (PIK3CA)
      is frequently mutated in muscle invasive bladder cancer (MIBC) (15-20%) and PTEN is
      inactivated in another 30%.

      Due to TAK-228's effects on the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway in preclinical studies and the
      frequency of pathway alterations in UC tumors, TAK-228 is a rational therapy for bladder
      cancer.

      This clinical investigation may also reveal how alterations in the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway
      correlate with treatment response. In preclinical bladder cell line models and xenografts
      done in our lab, synergistic effect has been seen with the combination with paclitaxel.

      The primary end-point is objective response rate (ORR) with the goal of increasing the rate
      from 10% to 26%. Response rates will be measured using RECIST 1.1 criteria. PFS and OS will
      be measured from the start date of treatment with TAK-228 and paclitaxel. Grade 3, 4 or
      serious adverse events will be collected and compared to the catalogued events in the phase
      II trial in breast cancer (NCT01351350). Patient tumors will be analyzed for genetic
      alterations within the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway to determine if alterations within this pathway
      correlate with response rate, PFS, or OS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response rate (ORR), defined as the sum of the complete and partial responses (CR+PR), with the goal of increasing the rate from 10% to 26%. Response rates will be measured using RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events [Safety and Tolerability]</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the safety and evaluate the tolerability of TAK-228 in combination with paclitaxel in patients with metastatic, previously treated transitional cell carcinoma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from the first day of therapy to the first evidence of progression as defined by RECIST, or death from any cause, whichever is first. Patients who die without a reported prior progression will be considered to have progressed on the day of their death. Patients alive and without disease progression will be censored at the time of the last objective tumor assessment. Patients who do not progress and are subsequently lost to follow-up will have their data censored at the day of their last objective tumor assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from the first day of therapy to the date of death from any cause. If the patient is alive at the end of the follow-up period or is lost to follow-up, OS will be censored on the last date the patient is known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of PI3K/ AKT/ mTOR pathway mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient tumors samples will be analyzed for genetic alterations within the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway to determine if alterations within this pathway correlate with response rate, in patients with UC</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of PI3K/ AKT/ mTOR pathway mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient tumors samples will be analyzed for genetic alterations within the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway to determine if alterations within this pathway correlate with PFS, in patients with UC</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of PI3K/ AKT/ mTOR pathway mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient tumors samples will be analyzed for genetic alterations within the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway to determine if alterations within this pathway correlate with OS, in patients with UC</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To discover biomarkers in the serum or plasma (pre and post treatment) of subjects that may predict response to therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Findings suggest S2481 phosphorylation could be a marker for activity of mTORC2. S2481 has the potential to be a prognostic, predictive, and pharmacodynamic marker:
• Characterize the phosphorylation of S2481 of mTOR in UC tumor tissue</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To discover biomarkers in the serum or plasma (pre and post treatment) of subjects that may predict response to therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Findings suggest S2481 phosphorylation could be a marker for activity of mTORC2. S2481 has the potential to be a prognostic, predictive, and pharmacodynamic marker:
Evaluate whether basal levels of mTOR S2481 phosphorylation correlate with prognosis and/or are predictive of clinical outcomes of the study patients treated with the combination</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To discover biomarkers in the serum or plasma (pre and post treatment) of subjects that may predict response to therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>34 months</time_frame>
    <description>Findings suggest S2481 phosphorylation could be a marker for activity of mTORC2. S2481 has the potential to be a prognostic, predictive, and pharmacodynamic marker:
Assess for changes in tumoral phospho-S2481 after treatment in the biopsy subset of patients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Urothelial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paclitaxel plus TAK-228</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Paclitaxel will be given on days 1, 8, and 15 of each 28 day cycle intravenously (every Monday or first day of business week if holiday), the day before the first TAK-228 dose. It should be given over approximately one hour.
TAK-228 will be given orally on Days 2-4, 9-11, 16-18 and 23-25 of each 28-day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel and TAK-228</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment with TAK-228 oral (D2, 3 and 4 of each week) and paclitaxel (D1 of each week) on Days 1, 8 and 15 for each 28-days cycle until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. If paclitaxel is stopped, TAK-228 may be continued</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paclitaxel plus TAK-228</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female patients 18 years or older.

          2. Patients must have a diagnosis of metastatic or advanced histologically confirmed UC
             (urothelial cancer). Mixed histologies are allowed.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1.

          4. Female patients who:

               -  Are postmenopausal for at least 1 year before the screening visit, OR

               -  Are surgically sterile, OR

               -  If they are of childbearing potential, agree to practice 1 effective method of
                  contraception and 1 additional effective (barrier) method, at the same time, from
                  the time of signing the informed consent through 90 days (or longer as mandated
                  by local labeling [e.g., USPI, SmPC, etc,]) after the last dose of study drug, OR

               -  Agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the patient. (Periodic abstinence [e.g., calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, postovulation methods], withdrawal, spermicides only, and
                  lactational amenorrhea are not acceptable methods of contraception. Female and
                  male condoms should not be used together).

             Male patients, even if surgically sterilized (i.e., status post-vasectomy), who:

               -  Agree to practice highly effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and through 120 days after the last dose of study drug, OR

               -  Agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the patient. (Periodic abstinence [e.g., calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, postovulation methods for the female partner], withdrawal,
                  spermicides only, and lactational amenorrhea are not acceptable methods of
                  contraception. Female and male condoms should not be used together).

               -  Agree not to donate sperm during the course of this study or within 120 days
                  after receiving their last dose of study drug

          5. Screening clinical laboratory values as specified below:

               -  Bone marrow reserve consistent with: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x
                  109/L; platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L; hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL without transfusion
                  within 1 week preceding study drug administration.

               -  Hepatic: total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), transaminases
                  (aspartate aminotransferase/serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase-AST/SGOT and
                  alanine aminotransferase/serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase-ALT/SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x
                  ULN (≤ 5 x ULN if liver metastases are present);

               -  Renal: creatinine clearance ≥50 mL/min based either on Cockroft-Gault estimate or
                  based on urine collection (12 or 24 hour);

               -  Metabolic: Glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) &lt;7.0%, fasting serum glucose (≤ 130
                  mg/dL) and fasting triglycerides ≤ 300 mg/dL.

          6. Ability to swallow oral medications.

          7. Voluntary written consent must be given before performance of any study related
             procedure not part of standard medical care, with the understanding that consent may
             be withdrawn by the patient at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          8. Patients who have a history of brain metastasis are eligible for the study provided
             that all the following criteria are met:

               -  Brain metastases which have been treated.

               -  No evidence of disease progression for ≥3 months before the first dose of study
                  drug.

               -  No hemorrhage after treatment.

               -  Off-treatment with dexamethasone for 4 weeks before administration of the first
                  dose of TAK-228.

               -  No ongoing requirement for dexamethasone or anti-epileptic drugs.

          9. Patients having received prior systemic chemotherapy treatment for UC, with no limit
             for number of prior systemic chemotherapeutic or investigational treatment regimens.
             Specifically, subjects must meet one or more of the following criteria:

             • Progression after treatment with a regimen that includes a platinum salt (e.g. -
             carboplatin or cisplatin) for Stage IV disease.

             OR

             • Disease recurrence within one years from the date of last dose of chemotherapy or
             surgery until day the informed consent is signed) after neoadjuvant or adjuvant
             treatment with a regimen that includes a platinum salt.

         10. Measurable disease, as defined by RECIST v.1.1. If all sites of measurable disease
             have been irradiated, one site must have demonstrated growth after irradiation.

         11. Normal (or within 5% of lower limit) left ventricular ejection fraction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment with paclitaxel for UC (in any setting - neoadjuvant, adjuvant or for
             metastatic disease). Patients treated with prior docetaxel are eligible.

          2. Previous treatment with PI3K, AKT, dual PI3K/mTOR inhibitors, TORC1/2 inhibitors or
             TORC1 inhibitors.

          3. Manifestations of malabsorption due to prior gastrointestinal (GI) surgery, GI
             disease, or for an unknown reason that may alter the absorption of TAK-228. In
             addition, patients with enteric stomata are also excluded.

          4. Poorly controlled diabetes mellitus defined as HbA1c &gt; 7%; subjects with a history of
             transient glucose intolerance due to corticosteroid administration are allowed in this
             study if all other inclusion/exclusion criteria are met.

          5. Presence of central nervous system metastasis, except for those matching requirements
             detailed per inclusion criterion 8.

          6. Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic disease or any concurrent condition which
             in the Investigator's opinion makes it undesirable for the subject to participate in
             the trial or which would jeopardize compliance with the protocol.

          7. History of any of the following within the last 6 months prior to study entry:

               -  Ischemic myocardial event, including angina requiring therapy and artery
                  revascularization procedures

               -  Ischemic cerebrovascular event, including TIA and artery revascularization
                  procedures

               -  Requirement for inotropic support (excluding digoxin) or serious (uncontrolled)
                  cardiac arrhythmia (including atrial flutter/fibrillation, ventricular
                  fibrillation or ventricular tachycardia)

               -  Placement of a pacemaker for control of rhythm

               -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure (See Appendix C)

               -  Pulmonary embolism.

          8. Significant active cardiovascular or pulmonary disease at the time of study entry,
             including:

               -  Uncontrolled high blood pressure (i.e., systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mm Hg,
                  diastolic blood pressure &gt; 95 mm Hg). Use of anti-hypertensive agents to control
                  hypertension before Cycle 1 Day 1 is allowed.

               -  Pulmonary hypertension.

               -  Uncontrolled asthma or O2 saturation &lt; 90% by ABG (Arterial Blood Gas) analysis
                  or pulse oximetry on room air.

               -  Significant valvular disease; severe regurgitation or stenosis by imaging
                  independent of symptom control with medical intervention, or history of valve
                  replacement.

               -  Medically significant (symptomatic) bradycardia.

               -  History of arrhythmia requiring an implantable cardiac defibrillator.

               -  Baseline prolongation of the rate-corrected QT interval (QTc) (e.g., repeated
                  demonstration of QTc interval &gt; 480 milliseconds, or history of congenital long
                  QT syndrome, or torsades de pointes).

          9. History of arrhythmia (multifocal premature ventricular contractions (PVCs), bigeminy,
             trigeminy, ventricular tachycardia, or uncontrolled atrial fibrillation), which is
             symptomatic or requires treatment (CTCAE grade 3) or asymptomatic sustained
             ventricular tachycardia.

         10. Controlled atrial fibrillation such as with medication or cardioversion is not
             excluded.

         11. Treatment with systemic corticosteroids (either IV or oral steroids, excluding
             inhalers or low-dose hormone replacement therapy, i.e., prednisone ≤10mg or its
             equivalent) within 1 week before administration of the first dose of study drug.

         12. Women who are currently pregnant or breast feeding.

         13. Receipt of any investigational agent, chemotherapy or radiation therapy within 21 days
             prior to Study Day 1.

         14. Any unresolved non-hematologic toxicity greater than CTCAE grade 1 from previous
             anti-cancer therapy (other than alopecia).

         15. Major surgery within 4 weeks, or incompletely healed surgical incision before starting
             study therapy

         16. Grade 2 or greater peripheral neuropathy

         17. Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 2 years before administration of
             the first dose of study drug, or previously diagnosed with another malignancy and have
             any evidence of residual disease. Patients with non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma
             in situ of any type are not excluded if they have undergone complete resection.

         18. Other clinically significant co-morbidities, such as uncontrolled pulmonary disease,
             active central nervous system disease, active infection, or any other condition that
             could compromise the patient's participation in the study.

         19. Known human immunodeficiency virus infection

         20. Known hepatitis B surface antigen-positive, or known or suspected active hepatitis C
             infection.

         21. Any serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the investigator's opinion,
             potentially interfere with the completion of treatment according to this protocol

         22. Patients who are taking proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) within 7 days of the first dose
             of study drug or who require treatment with PPIs throughout the trial or those who are
             taking H2 receptor antagonists within 24 hours of the first dose of study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joaquín Bellmunt, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital del Mar</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alejo Rodríguez-Vida, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital del Mar</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joaquím Bellmunt, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 932 483 860</phone>
    <email>jbellmunt@imim.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Inmaculada Musté</last_name>
    <phone>+34 932 274 760</phone>
    <email>oncologia.apro@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario de Elche</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elche</city>
        <state>Alicante</state>
        <zip>03203</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Federico J. Vázquez Mazón, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <email>fvazquezmd@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Federico J. Vázquez Mazón, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parc Taulí Hospital Universitario</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sabadell</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08208</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teresa Bonfilll, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <email>terebonfill@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teresa Bonfill, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clínica Universitaria de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José Luis Pérez Gracia, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <email>jlgracia@unav.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Luis Pérez Gracia, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital del Mar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alejo Rodríguez-Vida, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <email>arodriguezvida@hospitaldelmar.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alejo Rodríguez-Vida, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José Pablo Maroto Rey, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <email>jmaroto@santpau.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Pablo Maroto Rey, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://apro.org.es/</url>
    <description>APRO Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iyer G, Al-Ahmadie H, Schultz N, Hanrahan AJ, Ostrovnaya I, Balar AV, Kim PH, Lin O, Weinhold N, Sander C, Zabor EC, Janakiraman M, Garcia-Grossman IR, Heguy A, Viale A, Bochner BH, Reuter VE, Bajorin DF, Milowsky MI, Taylor BS, Solit DB. Prevalence and co-occurrence of actionable genomic alterations in high-grade bladder cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2013 Sep 1;31(25):3133-40. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2012.46.5740. Epub 2013 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23897969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guo Y, Chekaluk Y, Zhang J, Du J, Gray NS, Wu CL, Kwiatkowski DJ. TSC1 involvement in bladder cancer: diverse effects and therapeutic implications. J Pathol. 2013 May;230(1):17-27. doi: 10.1002/path.4176. Epub 2013 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23401075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wagle N, Grabiner BC, Van Allen EM, Hodis E, Jacobus S, Supko JG, Stewart M, Choueiri TK, Gandhi L, Cleary JM, Elfiky AA, Taplin ME, Stack EC, Signoretti S, Loda M, Shapiro GI, Sabatini DM, Lander ES, Gabriel SB, Kantoff PW, Garraway LA, Rosenberg JE. Activating mTOR mutations in a patient with an extraordinary response on a phase I trial of everolimus and pazopanib. Cancer Discov. 2014 May;4(5):546-53. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-13-0353. Epub 2014 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24625776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel R, Naishadham D, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2013. CA Cancer J Clin. 2013 Jan;63(1):11-30. doi: 10.3322/caac.21166. Epub 2013 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23335087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortmann CA, Mazhar D. Second-line systemic therapy for metastatic urothelial carcinoma of the bladder. Future Oncol. 2013 Nov;9(11):1637-51. doi: 10.2217/fon.13.139. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24156324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaughn DJ, Broome CM, Hussain M, Gutheil JC, Markowitz AB. Phase II trial of weekly paclitaxel in patients with previously treated advanced urothelial cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Feb 15;20(4):937-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11844814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>von der Maase H, Sengelov L, Roberts JT, Ricci S, Dogliotti L, Oliver T, Moore MJ, Zimmermann A, Arning M. Long-term survival results of a randomized trial comparing gemcitabine plus cisplatin, with methotrexate, vinblastine, doxorubicin, plus cisplatin in patients with bladder cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Jul 20;23(21):4602-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16034041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verdoorn BP, Kessler ER, Flaig TW. Targeted therapy in advanced urothelial carcinoma. Oncology (Williston Park). 2013 Mar;27(3):219-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23687793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ching CB, Hansel DE. Expanding therapeutic targets in bladder cancer: the PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathway. Lab Invest. 2010 Oct;90(10):1406-14. doi: 10.1038/labinvest.2010.133. Epub 2010 Jul 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20661228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Platt FM, Hurst CD, Taylor CF, Gregory WM, Harnden P, Knowles MA. Spectrum of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase pathway gene alterations in bladder cancer. Clin Cancer Res. 2009 Oct 1;15(19):6008-17. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-0898. Epub 2009 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>19789314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowles DW, Diamond JR, Lam ET, Weekes CD, Astling DP, Anderson RT, Leong S, Gore L, Varella-Garcia M, Vogler BW, Keysar SB, Freas E, Aisner DL, Ren C, Tan AC, Wilhelm F, Maniar M, Eckhardt SG, Messersmith WA, Jimeno A. Phase I study of oral rigosertib (ON 01910.Na), a dual inhibitor of the PI3K and Plk1 pathways, in adult patients with advanced solid malignancies. Clin Cancer Res. 2014 Mar 15;20(6):1656-65. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-2506. Epub 2014 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24493827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowles DW, Ma WW, Senzer N, Brahmer JR, Adjei AA, Davies M, Lazar AJ, Vo A, Peterson S, Walker L, Hausman D, Rudin CM, Jimeno A. A multicenter phase 1 study of PX-866 in combination with docetaxel in patients with advanced solid tumours. Br J Cancer. 2013 Sep 3;109(5):1085-92. doi: 10.1038/bjc.2013.474. Epub 2013 Aug 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23942080</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomez-Pinillos A, Ferrari AC. mTOR signaling pathway and mTOR inhibitors in cancer therapy. Hematol Oncol Clin North Am. 2012 Jun;26(3):483-505, vii. doi: 10.1016/j.hoc.2012.02.014. Epub 2012 Mar 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22520976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seront E, Rottey S, Sautois B, Kerger J, D'Hondt LA, Verschaeve V, Canon JL, Dopchie C, Vandenbulcke JM, Whenham N, Goeminne JC, Clausse M, Verhoeven D, Glorieux P, Branders S, Dupont P, Schoonjans J, Feron O, Machiels JP. Phase II study of everolimus in patients with locally advanced or metastatic transitional cell carcinoma of the urothelial tract: clinical activity, molecular response, and biomarkers. Ann Oncol. 2012 Oct;23(10):2663-70. Epub 2012 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22473592</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Milowsky, M.I., Final results of a multicenter, open-label phase II trial of dovitinib (TKI258) in patients with advanced urothelial carcinoma with either mutated or nonmutated FGFR3. 2013, J Clin Oncol 2013; 31(Suppl 6) [abstract: 255].</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bajorin DF. Paclitaxel in the treatment of advanced urothelial cancer. Oncology (Williston Park). 2000 Jan;14(1):43-52, 57; discussion 58, 61-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10680149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raghavan D. Progress in the chemotherapy of metastatic cancer of the urinary tract. Cancer. 2003 Apr 15;97(8 Suppl):2050-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12673696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi JF. Phase I study of atacicept in relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma (MM) and Waldenström's macroglobulinemia. Clin Lymphoma Myeloma Leuk. 2011 Feb;11(1):136-8. doi: 10.3816/CLML.2011.n.031.</citation>
    <PMID>21454215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiang GG, Abraham RT. Targeting the mTOR signaling network in cancer. Trends Mol Med. 2007 Oct;13(10):433-42. Epub 2007 Oct 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17905659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sabatini DM. mTOR and cancer: insights into a complex relationship. Nat Rev Cancer. 2006 Sep;6(9):729-34. Epub 2006 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16915295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jessen K, Wang S, Kessler L, et al. INK128 is a potent and selective TORC1/2 inhibitor with broad oral antitumor activity. Mol Cancer Ther. 2009;8(12 Suppl) Abstract B148</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kessler L, Wang S, Xin G, Kucharski J, Staunton J, Lan L, et al. INK128, an orally active TORC1/2 kinase inhibitor, shows broad antitumor activity and enhances efficacy of cytotoxic as well as targeted agents. Cancer Res 2010;70(8; Supplement 1 Abstract 4496).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hassan B, Akcakanat A, Takafumi S, Evans K, Adkins F, Meric-Bernstam F. Inhibitor MLN0128 Has Antitumor Efficacy In Cell Lines With Intrinsic And Acquired Rapamycin-Resistance. Academic Surgical Congress 2013(Abstract ASC20130420).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shafer A, Zhou C, Gehrig PA, Boggess JF, Bae-Jump VL. Rapamycin potentiates the effects of paclitaxel in endometrial cancer cells through inhibition of cell proliferation and induction of apoptosis. Int J Cancer. 2010 Mar 1;126(5):1144-54. doi: 10.1002/ijc.24837.</citation>
    <PMID>19688827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shu CH, Yang WK, Shih YL, Kuo ML, Huang TS. Cell cycle G2/M arrest and activation of cyclin-dependent kinases associated with low-dose paclitaxel-induced sub-G1 apoptosis. Apoptosis. 1997;2(5):463-70.</citation>
    <PMID>14646529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mondesire WH, Jian W, Zhang H, Ensor J, Hung MC, Mills GB, Meric-Bernstam F. Targeting mammalian target of rapamycin synergistically enhances chemotherapy-induced cytotoxicity in breast cancer cells. Clin Cancer Res. 2004 Oct 15;10(20):7031-42.</citation>
    <PMID>15501983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Voss M, Gordon MS, Mita M, Rini B, Makker V, Macarulla T, et al. Phase I study of investigational oral mTORC1/2 inhibitor TAK-228 (formerly MLN0128): expansion phase in patients with renal, endometrial, or bladder cancer. ESMO poster Sept 2015</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghobrial IM, Siegel DS, Vij R, Berdeja JG, Richardson PG, Neuwirth R, Patel CG, Zohren F, Wolf JL. TAK-228 (formerly MLN0128), an investigational oral dual TORC1/2 inhibitor: A phase I dose escalation study in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma, non-Hodgkin lymphoma, or Waldenström's macroglobulinemia. Am J Hematol. 2016 Jun;91(4):400-5. doi: 10.1002/ajh.24300.</citation>
    <PMID>26800393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>TAK-228 Investigator Brochure Edition 10. 22 March 2017</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>PACLITAXEL - paclitaxel injection, solution [package insert]. Princeton, NJ. Sandoz; 2011</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Urothelial carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

