<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03743740</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KA-17132</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03743740</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Spinal Stabilization Exercises in Patients With Myasthenia Gravis</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Spinal Stabilization Exercises on Fatigue, Muscle Strength, Pulmonary Functions and Functional Capacity in Patients With Myasthenia Gravis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hacettepe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hacettepe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Myasthenia Gravis (MG) is an autoimmune disease characterized by increased exercise-induced
      fatigue and muscle weakness. MG is a disease caused by impaired receptor function due to
      antibodies to nicotinic acetylcholine receptors in postsynaptic region in voluntary skeletal
      muscles.Spinal stabilization exercises, which use the basic principles of motor learning,
      aiming to improve the coordination, contraction rate and endurance of the body muscles by
      increasing kinesthetic awareness, can be used to strengthen body stability.

      The aim of this study was to investigate the effects of spinal stabilization exercises on
      fatigue, muscle strength, pulmonary functions and functional capacity in patients with MG.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Myasthenia Gravis (MG) is an autoimmune disease characterized by increased exercise-induced
      fatigue and muscle weakness. MG is a disease caused by impaired receptor function due to
      antibodies to nicotinic acetylcholine receptors in postsynaptic region in voluntary skeletal
      muscles. The disease usually begins with ptosis from ocular symptoms. With the progression of
      the disease, symptoms of bulbar muscles and extremity muscles are added to the ocular
      symptoms. Bulbar symptoms occur when speaking, swallowing, chewing difficulties and
      difficulty breathing, while the symptoms in the extremity muscles arise as the difficulty of
      raising the arms uphill and the strain of climbing stairs.

      The weakness of the limb muscles is proximal and distal in the arms and more proximal muscles
      in the legs. As the disease progresses, weakness occurs in most striated muscles. This causes
      weakness in the trunk muscles.

      In the literature, the physiotherapy methods used in MG patients include breathing exercises,
      aerobic exercises and resistant exercises.Spinal stabilization exercises enable activation of
      the trunk muscles.

      Spinal stabilization exercises, which use the basic principles of motor learning, aiming to
      improve the coordination, contraction rate and endurance of the body muscles by increasing
      kinesthetic awareness, can be used to strengthen body stability. Spinal stabilization
      exercises are a type of exercise that aims more smooth limb movements with a strong spine,
      ensuring smoothness and stability of the spine. In the literature, there is no study using
      spinal stabilization exercises in MG patients. The aim of this study was to investigate the
      effects of spinal stabilization exercises on fatigue, muscle strength, pulmonary functions
      and functional capacity in patients with MG.

      Method The study was planned as randomized, single-blind and cross-over. Randomization will
      be done with closed envelope system. Group 1 will be written on five sheets and group 2 will
      be written on another five sheets.

      Then, these papers will be placed on the envelopes, these envelopes will be mixed in a box
      and patients will be asked to withdraw from these envelopes.

      Thus, patients will be divided into 2 groups. Assessments will be made by Yeliz Salcı and
      Ebru Kütük Çalıkçı. The assessors will not know who is in the which group. Treatment
      intervention will be done by Ali Naim Ceren. The assessors will evaluate patients without
      knowing the patients' groups. So the work will be single blind. Group 1, 3 days per week for
      6 weeks so that it will be taken to the physiotherapy program consisting of spinal
      stabilization exercises. Also the treatment will be supported by home program exercises. The
      patients will be rested for 4 weeks to eliminate the effects of the spinal stabilization
      program. After this period, only the home program will be given for 6 weeks. In Group 2;
      treatment will start with a 6-week home program, followed by a 4-week break.

      At the end of this period to be 3 days a week for 6 weeks spinal stabilization exercise
      program will be implemented. In addition to this exercise program, patients will be given a
      home program. The home program will include breathing exercises tailored to the patient's
      needs, calisthenic exercises, and MAT activities.

      Assessments will be made at the beginning of the treatment, after 6 weeks of treatment, at
      the end of 4 weeks of rest and at the end of 6 weeks of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 8, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 22, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>muscle strength of extremity muscle in patient with Myasthenia Gravis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>change in muscle strength will be measured with a digital hand held dynamometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fatigue perception</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>fatigue perception will be assessed with visual analog scale (VAS). VAS is a straight line with a length of 10 cm meaning of 0 is that I am not tired. The meaning of 10 is that I am too tired. According to the degree of fatigue patients feel, patients give a score in this range.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>fatigue will be assessed with fatigue severity scale (FSS). FSS is a scale with scores ranging from 7 to 63. It includes 9 questions. Increase of score in this scale means that fatigue severity is increasing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>respiratory functions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>respiratory functions will be assessed with respiratory function tests. Respiratory function tests will be performed with portable spirometry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>functional capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>functional capacity will be assessed with 6 minute walk test. The 6-minute walk test will record the distance traveled in the 30-meter corridor at maximal speed for 6 minutes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It will be evaluated with Myastenia GravisvQuality of Life Questionnaire 15</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Myasthenia Gravis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>first, patients will undergo spinal stabilization exercise and home based program 3 days per week for 6 weeks.
then, exercises will be suspended for 4 weeks. then, patients will undergo home based program 3 days per week for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>first, patients will undergo home based program 3 days per week for 6 weeks. then, exercises will be suspended for 4 weeks. then, patients will undergo spinal stabilization exercise and home based program 3 days per week for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spinal stabilization exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>The effects of spinal stabilization exercise in patients with myasthenia gravis will be investigated.There is no study in the literature that previously applied spinal stabilization exercises in patients with myasthenia gravis. The benefits of spinal stabilization exercises in other diseases are shown.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>home based program</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Being diagnosed with MG by a neurologist,

          -  Aged between18-65 years,

          -  To be in Stage II or III according to the Clinical Classification of the Medialia
             Gravis Functional Assessment (MGFA),

          -  The Mini Mental Test score should be over 24 in order to be cooperative to the
             physiotherapist's instructions,

          -  To volunteer to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Having a cognitive problem and having a Mini Mental Test score below 24

          -  To have had myasthenic crisis in the last month,

          -  Modification of medical treatment and dose in the last month,

          -  Systemic, orthopedic and neurological disease in addition to the disease

          -  Participation in physiotherapy program in the last six months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hacettepe University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <zip>06100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilhus NE. Myasthenia Gravis. N Engl J Med. 2016 Dec 29;375(26):2570-2581. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra1602678. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28029925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akuthota V, Ferreiro A, Moore T, Fredericson M. Core stability exercise principles. Curr Sports Med Rep. 2008 Feb;7(1):39-44. doi: 10.1097/01.CSMR.0000308663.13278.69. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18296944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicolle MW. Myasthenia Gravis and Lambert-Eaton Myasthenic Syndrome. Continuum (Minneap Minn). 2016 Dec;22(6, Muscle and Neuromuscular Junction Disorders):1978-2005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27922503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Féasson L, Camdessanché JP, El Mandhi L, Calmels P, Millet GY. Fatigue and neuromuscular diseases. Ann Readapt Med Phys. 2006 Jul;49(6):289-300, 375-84. Epub 2006 Apr 25. Review. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>16780988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elsheikh B, Arnold WD, Gharibshahi S, Reynolds J, Freimer M, Kissel JT. Correlation of single-breath count test and neck flexor muscle strength with spirometry in myasthenia gravis. Muscle Nerve. 2016 Jan;53(1):134-6. doi: 10.1002/mus.24929.</citation>
    <PMID>26437790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salci Y, Karanfil E, Balkan AF, Kütükçü EÇ, Ceren AN, Ayvat F, Bekircan-Kurt CE, Armutlu K. Functional exercise capacity evaluated by timed walk tests in myasthenia gravis. Muscle Nerve. 2019 Feb;59(2):208-212. doi: 10.1002/mus.26345. Epub 2018 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30230561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang Y, Zhang M, Guo J, Ma S, Fan L, Wang X, Li C, Guo P, Wang J, Li H, Li Z. Quality of life in 188 patients with myasthenia gravis in China. Int J Neurosci. 2016;126(5):455-62. doi: 10.3109/00207454.2015.1038712. Epub 2015 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26000922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hacettepe University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ali Naim Ceren</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Weakness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myasthenia Gravis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

