<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03740061</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SARCUS2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03740061</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Muscle Assessment Through Ultrasound in the Evaluation of Acute Sarcopenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Evaluation of Acute Sarcopenia in Hospitalized Elderly: Muscle Characteristics Assessment Through Ultrasound</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universiteit Antwerpen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Ramon y Cajal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Bialystok</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jagiellonian University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitat Pompeu Fabra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Istanbul University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oldenburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universiteit Antwerpen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Traditionally, muscle mass - a part of the concept of sarcopenia - is measured by computed
      tomography (CT) or dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) scan. These devices are not always
      easily available in clinical practice and cannot be used bedside. An innovation in sarcopenia
      is the assessment of muscle mass and quality with ultrasound. Because this device is much
      more available and applicable in all patients, diagnosis of acute sarcopenia would be much
      easier with ultrasound. Moreover, if other factors that contribute to accelerated decline in
      muscle mass and function can be determinated, the sensiblisation and early screening for
      acute sarcopenia in those individuals can hopefully prevent them from declining.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methods Study design A prospective, multicenter, international observational study will be
      conducted. The study is designed to determine the effect of hospitalisation due to acute
      illness on the changes in muscle mass and muscle function. The secondary endpoint of the
      study is to identify health related parameters associated with the development of acute
      sarcopenia.

      Subjects Inclusion criteria Patients admitted between the 1st of December 2018 until the 31th
      of November 2019 will be eligible for inclusion. Included wards for admission are: internal
      medicine, acute geriatrics, orthogeriatrics and rehabilitation. Age limit will be set on 65
      years and older.

      Exclusion criteria Patients on dialysis will be excluded because of possible metabolic
      features. Individuals with paresis of the lower limbs or hemiparesis due to a stroke will be
      excluded because of neurological involvement that can influence the results. Hypo-or
      hyperthyroid patients will be excluded because of the role of thyroid hormones in muscle
      homeostasis. Pitting oedema of the legs (due to heart failure, anasarca oedema, renal failure
      or liver cirrhosis) or severely dehydrated patients will be excluded because fluid shifts
      could influence the ultrasound measurement results. Because of possible previous changes in
      muscle mass, architecture and function, patients with systemic connective tissue disorders,
      myositis, calcification and ossification of muscle, systemic atrophies primarily affecting
      the central nervous system and demyelinating diseases of the central nervous system will be
      excluded. Patients using chronic oral corticosteroids will be excluded.

      Settings and locations The study will be a multicenter study held in different university and
      tertiary teaching hospitals throughout Europe.

      Measurements

      Patient characteristics Date of birth, gender, height and weight will be registered. If the
      patient is bedridden, weight can be measured through either weight chairs or weight measuring
      lifts. Height will be estimated using the ulna length or knee height. Date of admission and
      discharge will be noted. The home care setting of the patient will be registered. The main
      reason of hospital admission will be registered.

      Comorbidities on admission will be registered through the Cumulative Illness Rating Scale for
      Geriatrics (CIRS-G). The CIRS-G was designed to estimate the survival of elderly persons,
      assessing disease severity using a score from 0 to 4 in 14 different categories of organ
      systems: cardiac, vascular, hematological, respiratory, ophthalmological and
      otorhinolaryngological, upper gastro-intestinal, lower gastro-intestinal, hepatic and
      pancreatic, renal, genito-urinary, musculoskeletal and tegumental, neurological,
      endocrine/metabolic/breast and psychiatric. Score '0' stands for 'no problem affecting that
      system', score '1' stands for 'current mild problem or past significant problem', score '2'
      stands for 'moderate disability or morbidity', score '3' stands for 'severe problem' and
      score '4' stands for 'extremely severe problem'.

      Laboratory values that will be checked are either nutritional through albumin and prealbumin,
      inflammatory through C-reactive protein (CRP) and white blood cell count, and the measurement
      of 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25-OH-vitamin D). Blood samples will be collected on day of
      admission. Laboratory values that are not expected to fluctuate strongly (albumin,
      pre-albumin, 25-OH-vitamin D) will be taken within the first 5 days of admission.

      Muscle mass In order to obtain reliable and consistent measurements, all ultrasonography will
      be done by an ultrasonographist that is trained to perform the measurements proposed. For the
      measurements, a linear probe of 5 cm width will be used. Frequency of the beam will be set on
      12 MHz.

      Patients should not have had any physical exercise in the 30 minutes before the measurement.
      Muscles should be completely relaxed and patients should be placed in the supine position,
      with hips in neutral position and knees fully extended. The dominant leg will be taken for
      the measurements. To calculate the relative muscle thickness values, the total length of
      muscle will be noted.

      Ultrasonographic data of the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle (rectus femoris, vastus
      lateralis, vastus medialis, vastus intermedius) will be taken. Measuring points will be
      specified according to the propositions of the SARCUS-working group. Muscle thickness,
      fascicle length, pennation angle, muscle cross-sectional area and echo-intensity of all
      muscles listed will be taken.

      The first measurement will be taken as early as possible within 48 hours after admission at
      the latest. Follow-up measurements will be taken according to the type of ward the patient is
      admitted to. For patients that are expected to be hospitalized for a limited time (&lt;5 days),
      the follow-up measurement will be done 3 days after initial measurement. For patients that
      are expected to be hospitalized for a longer time (&gt;7 days), measurements will be repeated 7
      days after initial measurement, to be repeated after another 7 days as long as the patient is
      hospitalized.

      Muscle strength and function Muscle strength will be measured through hand grip strength
      using a Jamar dynamometer, using the Southampton protocol. The first measurement will be
      taken as early as possible within 48 hours after admission at the latest. Follow-up
      measurements will be taken according to the type of ward the patient is admitted to. For
      patients that are expected to be hospitalized for a limited time (&lt;5 days), the follow-up
      measurement will be done 3 days after initial measurement. For patients that are expected to
      be hospitalized for a longer time (&gt;7 days), measurements will be repeated 7 days after
      initial measurement, to be repeated after another 7 days as long as the patient is
      hospitalized. Measurement will be done directly after the ultrasonographic assessment. If
      feasible, muscle function will be measured through gait speed, using the 4-meter walking test
      at usual gait speed. In case of those bedridden, gait speed will not be measured.

      In-hospital activity Registration of activity level during hospitalisation will be performed
      by means of pedometers in those centers that have access to these devices. Both amount of
      steps and step length will be noted, and total walked distance per day can hereby be
      calculated.

      Nutritional status Nutritional state of the patient will be registered through the
      Mini-Nutritional Assessment - Short Form (MNA-SF). For diagnosis of malnutrition, the new
      Global Leadership Initiative on Malnutrition (GLIM)-criteria will be used.

      Questionnaires The SARC-F and FRAIL-scale will be completed as routine screening
      questionnaires for sarcopenia and frailty, respectively. The SAR-QOL questionnaire will be
      used to evaluate the self-reported quality of life.

      Statistical analysis Databases will be kept up in a Microsoft Access database. Statistical
      analysis will be done by using SPSS Statistics version 24. Descriptive analyses will be used
      for determining the clinical and demographic characteristics. A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test will
      be used to verify the normal distribution of the different variables. Further statistical
      analyses will be performed by Chi Square test, Fisher exact, Mann-Whitney U test or Fisher
      exact test, depending on the distribution and the nature of the variables analysed. P-values
      of ≤0.05 will be considered statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle thickness (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle thickness (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle cross-sectional area (in square centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle cross-sectional area (in square centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle pennation angle (in degrees) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle pennation angle (in degrees) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle fascicle length (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle fascicle length (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle echo-intensity (gray values in Houndsfield units) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change over 7 days in ultrasonographic measured muscle echo-intensity (gray values in Houndsfield units) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle thickness on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle thickness (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle cross-sectional area on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle cross-sectional area (in square centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle pennation angle on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle pennation angle (in degrees) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle fascicle length on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle fascicle length (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle echo intensity on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle echo intensity (gray values in Houndsfield units) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle strength measured by hand grip strength (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle thickness on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the relation is between (changes in) muscle thickness (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle and muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle cross-sectional area on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle cross-sectional area (in square centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle pennation angle on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle pennation angle (in degrees) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle fascicle length on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle fascicle length (in centimeter) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of muscle echo intensity on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determining what the influence of (changes in) muscle echo intensity (gray values in Houndsfield units) in the four bellies of the quadriceps muscle is on muscle function measured by short physical performance battery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>9</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcopenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Antwerp</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Barcelona</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Istanbul</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oldenburg</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Krakow</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bialystok</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rome</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Madrid</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leuven</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasonographic assessment of muscle</intervention_name>
    <description>Ultrasonographic assessment of quadriceps muscle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Antwerp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Barcelona</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bialystok</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Istanbul</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Krakow</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Leuven</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Madrid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oldenburg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rome</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All participants ages 65 years or older and admitted to one of the ward of one of the
        centers in the given time period.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All participants ages 65 years AND

          -  Admitted to one of the ward of one of the centers in the given time period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients on dialysis will be excluded because of possible metabolic features.

          -  Individuals with paresis of the lower limbs or hemiparesis due to a stroke will be
             excluded because of neurological involvement that can influence the results.

          -  Hypo-or hyperthyroid patients will be excluded because of the role of thyroid hormones
             in muscle homeostasis.

          -  Pitting oedema of the legs (due to heart failure, anasarca oedema, renal failure or
             liver cirrhosis) or severely dehydrated patients will be excluded because fluid shifts
             could influence the ultrasound measurement results.

          -  Because of possible previous changes in muscle mass, architecture and function,
             patients with systemic connective tissue disorders, myositis, calcification and
             ossification of muscle, systemic atrophies primarily affecting the central nervous
             system and demyelinating diseases of the central nervous system will be excluded.

          -  Patients using chronic oral corticosteroids will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stany Perkisas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stany Perkisas, MD</last_name>
    <phone>003232803539</phone>
    <phone_ext>0032</phone_ext>
    <email>stany.perkisas@zna.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ZNA Middelheim</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerpen</city>
        <zip>2020</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stany Perkisas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>032803539</phone>
      <phone_ext>0032</phone_ext>
      <email>stany.perkisas@zna.be</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stany Perkisas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute sarcopenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hospitalized older people</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcopenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 23, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/61/NCT03740061/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

