<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03741738</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2018-0686</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03741738</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Investigation on the Expression of High Mobility Group Protein Box-1 (HMGB1) in Peripheral Blood of Vitiligo Patients and Healthy Controls According to Clinical Features, Treatment and Disease Activity</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Investigation on the Expression of High Mobility Group Protein Box-1 (HMGB1) in Peripheral Blood of Vitiligo Patients and Healthy Controls According to Clinical Features, Treatment and Disease Activity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitiligo is an acquired depigmented disorder that causes white spots on the skin due to the
      loss of melanocytes. It is a common disease which accounts for 0.5-1% of the whole
      population. It is a refractory skin disease with 25-50 thousand patients in Korea. And it is
      often caused in the exposed areas of the patient, causing a great deal of mental and social
      dysfunction in the patient's life, and may lead to suicide attempts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A nationwide study conducted by the Korean Academy of vitiligo showed that 61.8% of patients
      with vitiligo always have emotional impairment. In addition, the incidence of recurrence is
      high, and the recurrence rate is reported up to 40% within one year after the discontinuation
      of treatment. Therefore, development of a marker for monitoring the disease activity is very
      important and desperately needed.

      HMGB1 is a protein located in the nucleus, such as histone, and binds to genes and
      transcription factors to stabilize and control the DNA transcription. However, when released
      from the cells, it acts as a danger signal and is thought to cause autoimmune diseases such
      as inflammatory diseases and lupus. The present study demonstrated through ex vivo tissue
      culture that HMGB1 can induce melanocyte apoptosis by inducing apoptosis and also observed
      that serum concentration of HMGB1 was higher in vitiligo patients than in normal controls .
      The aim of this study is to investigate the usefulness of HMGB1 as a biomarker for predicting
      the severity of disease and to confirm the association between HMGB1 levels and vitiligo
      activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 29, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 29, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum HMGB1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Comparative analysis of serum HMGB1 between active non-segmental vitiligo and normal controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum HMGB1</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of serum HMGB1 between segmental vitiligo and normal control</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Vitiligo</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-segmental vitiligo :</arm_group_label>
    <description>A. Patients aged 19 years or older who were clinically diagnosed with non-segmented leukopenia at Severance Hospital.
B. Patients (36 patients) who experienced worsening symptoms within the last 3 months and 10 patients whose symptoms were stable within 3 months C. Patients with vitiligo lesion at least 3% of the skin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Segmental VT or Focal VT</arm_group_label>
    <description>A. The investigators evaluated patients who were diagnosed as segmental vitiligo clinically on Severance hospital and who were 19 years old or older.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal control</arm_group_label>
    <description>A. Subjects aged 19 or older who do not have not only vitiligo but also other skin and systemic diseases</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum of patient will be evaluated
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who visted Severance hospital due to vitiligo
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Non-segmental vitiligo :

             A. Patients aged 19 years or older who were clinically diagnosed with non-segmented
             leukopenia at Severance Hospital.

             B. Patients (36 patients) who experienced worsening symptoms within the last 3 months
             and 10 patients whose symptoms were stable within 3 months C. Patients with vitiligo
             lesion at least 3% of the skin

          2. Segmental VT or Focal VT A. The investigators evaluated patients who were diagnosed as
             segmental vitiligo clinically on Severance hospital and who were 19 years old or
             older.

          3. Normal control A. Subjects aged 19 or older who do not have not only vitiligo but also
             other skin and systemic diseases

          4. Subjects who voluntarily signed a written consent before he / she fully explained the
             purpose and contents of the examination prior to clinical research

          5. Subjects who can follow up during the clinical study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients diagnosed with nevus depigmentosus in vitiligo group

          2. Patients under the age of 19

          3. Patients taking steroids and immunosuppressants within the last 4 weeks

          4. Patients using steroids and immunomodulatory ointment within the last 2 weeks

          5. Patients who have been treated with short-wave UV therapy and excimer laser within the
             last month

          6. Subjects with a disease known to have elevated blood levels of HMGB1 (lupus, systemic
             cirrhosis Symptoms, infectious diseases, etc.) on normal group

          7. Subjects do not want it or did not fill out a consent form

          8. Subjects who are pregnant or lactating

          9. Patients whose clinical investigator is deemed unsuitable as a subject for the
             following patients or other pathologies 1) If the site of treatment has infectious or
             inflammatory skin disease 2) If the site of treatment has melasma or other pigmented
             dermatologic disease 3) If subjects have keloid disease, collagen, or elastic fiber
             disease 4) If subjects have chronic wasting disease (asthma, diabetes, etc.) 5) If
             subjects are taking anticoagulants and are at risk of bleeding 6) If subjects have an
             autoimmune disease 7) Subjects with psychiatric problems 8) Acute patients

         10. Others in addition to the above items, if it is deemed difficult for clinical practice
             to be conducted at the discretion of the clinical trial manager (including illiteracy
             and other foreigners exclusion)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sang Ho Oh, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+82 2 2228 2080</phone>
    <email>oddung93@yuhs.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology, Severance Hospital, Cutaneous Biology Research Institute, Yonsei University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sang Ho Oh, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+82 2 2228 2080</phone>
      <email>oddung93@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitiligo</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

