<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03741296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-0278</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03741296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>REVISITS: Revision Single or Two Stage Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>REVISITS</acronym>
  <official_title>REVISITS Trial: Revision Single or Two Stage Surgery for Periprosthetic Hip Infection - a Multicentre Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hip replacement surgery is common, with over 60,000 cases in Canada annually. After hip
      replacement, about 1-2% patients develop a deep infection in their artificial hip implant,
      called a periprosthetic joint infection (PJI). It can results in severe pain, disability and
      death.

      There are two types of surgical treatment: a single-stage revision that involves removing the
      joint, thoroughly cleaning the infected area and implanting a new joint, all in the same
      surgical procedure; a two-stage revision involves removing the joint, waiting at least 8
      weeks while treating the patients with antibiotics and then doing re-implantation of the
      joint.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peri-prosthetic infection is an uncommon but severe complication of joint replacement
      (arthroplasty) with a reported rate between 0.6 to 2.2%. Although the likelihood of infection
      is relatively small, the psychological and economic impact, as well as long-term implications
      to both the patient and healthcare system, can be catastrophic.

      The current gold standard treatment for peri-prosthetic infection is a two-stage strategy,
      where the artificial hip joint is removed and a new replacement delayed for at least 8 weeks
      until clear evidence of infection eradication is obtained. During this time the patient may
      be non-ambulatory, non- or partial-weight bearing and then a wait for re-listing for the
      second surgery.

      An alternative treatment that has recently been more widely used is to perform a single stage
      revision. That involves removing the implants and then irrigating and debriding and finally
      implanting the new replacements prostheses. This is all done in one surgery. The advantage of
      this technique is that there is only one procedure and usually the patient is allowed to bear
      weight on the joint.

      Primary Objective:

      To compare pain and physical function assessed by the Oxford hip score, between the single
      and two-stage revision surgery for a periprosthetic hip infection in adults

      Secondary Objectives:

      To compare pain, function, quality of life, rates of reinfection, complications,
      cost-effectiveness and health economic impact.

      Tertiary Objectives:

      To involve building partnerships between patients, researchers and clinicians. Patients will
      be engaged in the trial development and knowledge translation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a study is a multicentre, prospective, parallel, two-arm, randomized controlled trial aiming to assess the efficacy of single stage revision peri-prosthetic joint infection of hip arthroplasty in adult's patients, compared to the current gold standard of care, two-stage revision.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported hip function</measure>
    <time_frame>Questionnaire will be completed by patients at 9 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by means of the Oxford Hip Score - A short questionnaire consists of 12 questions ranging from 0 to 48 points, designed to assess function and pain after hip replacement surgery. Higher values represent a better outcome. Scores between 40-48 indicate satisfactory joint function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health status and quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Questionnaire will be completed by patients before the surgery and at 6, 9, 12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D-5L) is a questionnaire where patients self-rate their level of severity of health status and health-related quality of life. Consists of 5 dimensions (mobility, self care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression) and each one of them has 5 levels (no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems) where patients will indicate how they feel regarding their health status and quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reinfection rates</measure>
    <time_frame>will be assessed at 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9,12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Recurrence of infection by the same organism or reinfection with a new organism as determined by the criteria using the Musculoskeletal Infection Society criteria.
There is a sinus tract communicating with the prosthesis; or
A pathogen is isolated by culture from at least two separate tissue or fluid samples obtained from the affected prosthetic joint; or
Four of the following six criteria exist:
Elevated serum erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and serum C-reactive protein (CRP) concentration
Elevated synovial leukocyte count,
Elevated synovial neutrophil percentage (PMN%)
Presence of purulence in the affected joint
Isolation of a microorganism in one culture of periprosthetic tissue or fluid
Greater than five neutrophils per high-power field in five high-power fields observed from histologic analysis of periprosthetic tissue at 400x magnification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported hip function</measure>
    <time_frame>Questionnaire will be completed by patients at 12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by means of the Oxford Hip Score - A short questionnaire consists of 12 questions ranging from 0 to 48 points, designed to assess function and pain after hip replacement surgery. Higher values represent a better outcome. Scores between 40-48 indicate satisfactory joint function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Pain Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Pain scale will be assessed before the surgery and at 24 and 48 hours, 6 weeks, 3,6, 9, 12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assess pain from a visual scale that ranges from 0 to 10. Straight line with the endpoints defining extreme limits such as 'no pain at all' (zero) and 'pain as bad as it could be' (ten)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>Will be assessed within 30 days of discharge</time_frame>
    <description>If patients who were discharged after surgery have an unplanned readmission for any cause to an hospital, the reason for readmission being related or not to the surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Will be assessed from admission to discharge (up to 30 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of a single episode of hospitalization (in days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Total Hip Replacement</condition>
  <condition>Arthroplasty Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>single stage revision</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One surgery where the infected artificial joint will be removed along with all components, cement, and any potentially infected material. The surgical site will be debrided and washed out before a new artificial hip joint (prosthesis) is implanted. All the procedures will be done in a single surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>two-stage revision</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo 2 separated surgeries. In the first operation, the infected artificial joint will be removed along with all components, cement, and any potentially infected material. The surgical site will be debrided, washed out and a spacer will be placed in the hip (temporarily replace prosthesis).
A secondary surgery to re-implant the hip will be performed with an interval period of 4-10 weeks when the infection is cleared.
The site will be debrided and irrigated, and any component/spacer will be removed. A new artificial joint will then be implanted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Single stage revision</intervention_name>
    <description>One-stage exchange hip joint replacement surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>single stage revision</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Two-stage revision</intervention_name>
    <description>Two-stage exchange hip joint replacement surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>two-stage revision</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients aged 18 years or above

          -  A clinical diagnosis of deep hip periprosthetic joint infection according to the
             Musculoskeletal Infection Society criteria

          -  Require revision surgery (either single-or two-stage revision) for hip periprosthetic
             joint infection in the opinion of the treating consultant orthopaedic surgeon

          -  The patient is not a candidate for Debridement, Antibiotics and Implant Retention
             (DAIR) treatment with retention of the implant

          -  Willing and able to sign the written consent, follow the protocol and attend follow-up

          -  Able to read and understand English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Culture-negative infection (organism not identified)

          -  Patients with systemic sepsis who require emergent surgery

          -  Resistant organisms not sensitive to available intravenous antibiotics

          -  Revision surgery or previous two-stage reimplant

          -  Unable or unwilling to undergo either single-or two-stage revision surgery

          -  Cognitive impairment (dementia, Alzheimer, etc.) which will prevent patients from
             completing the primary outcome measure

          -  Medical contra-indication to surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amit Atrey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luana Melo, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>416-864-6060</phone>
    <email>melol@smh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kunutsor SK, Whitehouse MR, Blom AW, Beswick AD; INFORM Team. Re-Infection Outcomes following One- and Two-Stage Surgical Revision of Infected Hip Prosthesis: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. PLoS One. 2015 Sep 25;10(9):e0139166. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0139166. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26407003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopez D, Leach I, Moore E, Norrish AR. Management of the Infected Total Hip Arthroplasty. Indian J Orthop. 2017 Jul-Aug;51(4):397-404. doi: 10.4103/ortho.IJOrtho_307_16.</citation>
    <PMID>28790468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kapadia BH, Berg RA, Daley JA, Fritz J, Bhave A, Mont MA. Periprosthetic joint infection. Lancet. 2016 Jan 23;387(10016):386-394. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61798-0. Epub 2015 Jun 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26135702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dale H, Fenstad AM, Hallan G, Havelin LI, Furnes O, Overgaard S, Pedersen AB, Kärrholm J, Garellick G, Pulkkinen P, Eskelinen A, Mäkelä K, Engesæter LB. Increasing risk of prosthetic joint infection after total hip arthroplasty. Acta Orthop. 2012 Oct;83(5):449-58. doi: 10.3109/17453674.2012.733918.</citation>
    <PMID>23083433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blom AW, Taylor AH, Pattison G, Whitehouse S, Bannister GC. Infection after total hip arthroplasty. The Avon experience. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2003 Sep;85(7):956-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14516026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips JE, Crane TP, Noy M, Elliott TS, Grimer RJ. The incidence of deep prosthetic infections in a specialist orthopaedic hospital: a 15-year prospective survey. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2006 Jul;88(7):943-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16799001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenguerrand E, Whitehouse MR, Beswick AD, Jones SA, Porter ML, Blom AW. Revision for prosthetic joint infection following hip arthroplasty: Evidence from the National Joint Registry. Bone Joint Res. 2017 Jun;6(6):391-398. doi: 10.1302/2046-3758.66.BJR-2017-0003.R1.</citation>
    <PMID>28642256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen SY, Hu CC, Chen CC, Chang YH, Hsieh PH. Two-Stage Revision Arthroplasty for Periprosthetic Hip Infection: Mean Follow-Up of Ten Years. Biomed Res Int. 2015;2015:345475. doi: 10.1155/2015/345475. Epub 2015 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26064901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kunutsor SK, Whitehouse MR, Blom AW, Board T, Kay P, Wroblewski BM, Zeller V, Chen SY, Hsieh PH, Masri BA, Herman A, Jenny JY, Schwarzkopf R, Whittaker JP, Burston B, Huang R, Restrepo C, Parvizi J, Rudelli S, Honda E, Uip DE, Bori G, Muñoz-Mahamud E, Darley E, Ribera A, Cañas E, Cabo J, Cordero-Ampuero J, Redó MLS, Strange S, Lenguerrand E, Gooberman-Hill R, Webb J, MacGowan A, Dieppe P, Wilson M, Beswick AD; Global Infection Orthopaedic Management Collaboration. One- and two-stage surgical revision of peri-prosthetic joint infection of the hip: a pooled individual participant data analysis of 44 cohort studies. Eur J Epidemiol. 2018 Oct;33(10):933-946. doi: 10.1007/s10654-018-0377-9. Epub 2018 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29623671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kunutsor SK, Whitehouse MR, Lenguerrand E, Blom AW, Beswick AD; INFORM Team. Re-Infection Outcomes Following One- And Two-Stage Surgical Revision of Infected Knee Prosthesis: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. PLoS One. 2016 Mar 11;11(3):e0151537. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0151537. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26967645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hip replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>periprosthetic hip infection</keyword>
  <keyword>single stage revision</keyword>
  <keyword>two-stage revision</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

