<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02478892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 26214</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02478892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preliminary Evaluation of Screening for Pancreatic Cancer in Patients With Inherited Genetic Risk</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preliminary Evaluation of Screening for Pancreatic Cancer in Patients With Inherited Genetic Risk</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, observational study evaluating the utility of endoscopic
      ultrasound or MRI for the identification of preneoplastic and neoplastic pancreatic lesions
      in patients at high risk for pancreatic cancer, specifically those with BRCA1/2, ATM, or
      PALB2 mutations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic Ultrasound (EUS) has emerged as a critical component in the imaging, staging, and
      diagnosis of pancreatic cancer. Not only can EUS delineate a mass utilizing sonography
      through the wall of the stomach or duodenum, but it also can obtain diagnostic fine needle
      aspiration of suspicious lesions. Especially in patients with incomplete visualization of a
      mass on cross-sectional imaging, EUS can provide valuable anatomic information prior to
      surgical exploration. While several studies have demonstrated that EUS has high sensitivity
      and specificity in diagnosing pancreatic masses, head-to-head comparisons with established
      modalities like CT have been often methodologically flawed. In a meta-analysis, it was found
      that of 4 studies that assessed resectability, 2 showed no difference and 1 favored each
      modality. As such, estimates of accuracy for assessing preoperative resectability have also
      ranged in several studies from 63-93%. As such it has been recognized as an accepted modality
      for the evaluation of potential pancreatic malignany.

      While screening in the general population is not feasible given the low incidence of PDAC,
      screening in high risk cohorts may allow for early detection of resectable, and potentially
      curable tumors. Clinical outcome of patients with smaller, non-metastasized tumors have a
      significantly improved 5-year survival. Generally the current recommendation is that patients
      who are first degree relatives of patients with PDAC from a familial PDAC kindred with at
      least 2 affected first-degree relatives, patients with Peutz-Jegher's syndrome, and patients
      with CDKN2A/BRCA1/BRCA2/ATM/PALB2/Lynch mutations with a first or second degree relative with
      pancreatic cancer would qualify for screening in the context of the CAPS5 trial. However,
      very recent evidence in a large Canadian study of pancreatic cancer patients demonstrated
      germline carrier status for BRCA1/2, and ATM in their cohort was associated with first degree
      relatives with breast and colorectal cancer but not pancreatic cancer, suggesting that we may
      have to re-evaluate criteria for pancreatic cancer screening in this population. Thus, the
      risk of pancreatic cancer development in this cohort of patients would not be addressed by
      the CAPS5 protocol, but would uniquely be addressed in our proposed study. In terms of
      modality, interval, and age to start/stop, there remains debate but generally annual EUS/MRI
      has been utilized. Therefore, amongst patients with increased risk of pancreatic cancer, like
      those with BRCA1/2, ATM, or PALB2 mutations, the successful identification of early
      neoplastic/preneoplastic lesions of the pancreas would allow for timely intervention and
      improved survival in this cohort and thus would be of high clinical relevance.

      Thus we propose to utilize the unique cohort of increased risk patients followed at the
      University of Pennsylvania, to identify patients with BRCA1, BRCA2, ATM, or PALB2 mutations,
      regardless of family history of pancreatic cancer, and enroll them on an annual prospective
      pancreatic screening program. The hypothesis is that through early screening interventions,
      morbidity and mortality from this under-recognized malignancy in this high-risk patient
      population will be reduced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>identifying pancreatic neoplastic lesions lesions in patients with BRCA1/2 mutations and other less common, but related mutations (ATM, PALB2) as well as mutations identified in the future.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of the study is the observational screening of patients with BRCA1/2, ATM, or, PALB2 mutations for pancreatic neoplastic lesions, to assess for both the feasibility of this approach in this high risk population as well as to better establish the incidence of these lesions in this cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prophylactic endoscopic ultrasound or MRI of the abdomen</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients will be followed up clinically with routine, prophylactic endoscopic ultrasound or MRI surveillance every 12 months for a duration of 10 years</description>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      For circulating colonic epithelial cell analysis, at least one ml whole blood will be
      required for analysis. A total of 40mL of blood will be collected for analysis.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients at high risk for pancreatic cancer, specifically those with BRCA1/2, ATM, or PALB2
        mutations.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Age &gt;= 18

          -  Documented germline pathogenic or likely pathogenic BRCA1, BRCA2, ATM, or PALB2
             mutation

          -  If no history of PDAC in a first or second degree relative, age &gt;= 50

          -  If there is a history of PDAC in a first or second degree relative, minimum age of
             eligibility is 10 years younger than the age of onset of the youngest relative with
             pancreatic cancer

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Known infection with HIV, HBC, or HCV

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19004</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>high risk</keyword>
  <keyword>specifically those with BRCA1/2 mutations</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

