<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03728413</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11/LO/1023_V3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03728413</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Age on Adaptive Immunity in Adults Infected With Respiratory Syncytial Virus</brief_title>
  <acronym>INFLAMMAGE</acronym>
  <official_title>The Impact of Age on Adaptive Immunity in Adults Infected With Respiratory Syncytial Virus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will for the first time systematically investigate the immune responses in an
      elderly cohort challenged with a well-defined RSV inoculum. With a global aging population
      and continuing difficulties in generating vaccines that can reliably induce protective
      immunity in the elderly, these data will indicate the targets at which development of
      vaccines against RSV and other infections should be directed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) is one of the most common causes of chest infection
      worldwide, with 64 million episodes and 160,000 deaths each year. Despite this, it remains an
      underappreciated health problem and there are currently no specific treatments or vaccines
      against it. Although RSV infection is most frequent in young children, the majority of deaths
      occur in older adults, particularly in those with underlying heart and lung disease. This is
      believed to be due in part to the ageing immune system's reduced ability to protect against
      infection and symptomatic disease. However, little is known about the way human immune
      responses to RSV infection in older individuals differ from those of younger people. Further
      understanding of the mechanisms underlying immunity and potential impairments in these
      higher-risk people are therefore necessary. This project aims to study the role of T cells
      (which destroy virus-infected cells and are likely to be essential for recovery from
      infection) in healthy older volunteers after they have been given an RSV-induced common cold.
      Samples will be taken from the blood and respiratory tract in order to identify the
      differences in T cell responses that occur in older adults compared with their younger
      counterparts. Participants will be carefully screened to ensure they do not have any
      underlying health problems that might make them more at risk of severe disease and will be
      monitored closely throughout the course of infection. The investigators anticipate that T
      cell function even in healthy older individuals will be impaired compared to young adults,
      thus contributing in those with additional health problems to more severe disease. By
      analysing the networks of genes that are switched on and off, the investigators aim to
      identify the particular defects underlying these functional defects in order to ultimately
      define targets for novel treatments and T cell-stimulating vaccines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 28, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 28, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>RSV challenge remains safe and tolerable in older adults.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through pilot study completion, up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability of experimental challenge with RSV Memphis 37, assessed by the number of participants with study-related adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom severity in RSV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported upper and lower respiratory and systemic symptoms by diary card</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral load measurement in RSV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in viral load by qPCR of 7 days post inoculation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody responses to RSV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of RSV specific antibodies at 0,7,10,14 and 28 days post inoculation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>T cell responses to RSV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of RSV specific T cells at 0,7,10,14 and 28 days post inoculation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">108</enrollment>
  <condition>RSV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly Non-smoking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>RSV A Memphis 37 will be given as intra-nasal drops.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly ex and current smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>RSV A Memphis 37 will be given as intra-nasal drops.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Young non-smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>RSV A Memphis 37 will be given as intra-nasal drops.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RSV A Memphis 37</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be inoculated using intra-nasal drops with diluted inoculum at a given dose divided equally between the two nostrils. Dose: Good Manufacturing Practices-certified RSV Memphis 37 10(4) PFU in 1ml, 25% sucrose/Dulbecco's Modification of Eagle's Medium. Inoculations using intranasal drops will be done using a 1mL pipette with subjects supine. This will be done slowly with sufficient interval between each inoculation (2-3 minutes) to ensure maximum contact time between with the nasal and pharyngeal mucosa. Subjects will be asked not to swallow during the procedure to ensure maximal pharyngeal contact.
Following inoculation, advice regarding hand hygiene will be given, subjects will be provided with alcohol hand gel and facemasks to reduce spread of virus in the environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly Non-smoking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly ex and current smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Young non-smokers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy persons aged 18 to 40 years or 60 to 75 years, able to give informed consent

          -  Current smoker/ex-smoker of at least 20 pack years or non-smoker

          -  Spirometry within the normal range for age and height (+/- 15%)

          -  FEV1/FVC &gt;70% pre-bronchodilator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic respiratory disease (asthma, COPD, rhinitis, sinusitis) in adulthood

          -  Inhaled bronchodilator or steroid use within the last 12 months

          -  Habitual use of any medication or other product (prescription or over-the-counter) for
             symptoms of rhinitis or nasal congestion within the last 3 months

          -  Acute upper respiratory infection (URI or sinusitis) in the past 6 weeks

          -  Subjects with allergic symptoms present at baseline

          -  Clinically relevant abnormality on chest X-ray

          -  Those in close domestic contact (i.e. sharing a household with, caring for, or daily
             face to face contact) with children under 3 years, other elderly adults (&gt;65 years),
             immunosuppressed persons, or those with chronic respiratory disease

          -  Subjects with known or suspected immune deficiency

          -  Receipt of systemic glucocorticoids (in a dose ≥ 5 mg prednisone daily or equivalent)
             within one month, or any other cytotoxic or immunosuppressive drug within 6 months
             prior to challenge

          -  Known IgA deficiency, immotile cilia syndrome, or Kartagener's syndrome

          -  History of frequent nose bleeds

          -  Any significant medical condition or prescribed drug deemed by the study doctor to
             make the participant unsuitable for the study

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative hCG urine pregnancy test *

          -  Positive urine drug screen

          -  Women of childbearing potential will have a pregnancy test performed prior to virus
             inoculation to exclude pregnancy and be required to use contraception throughout the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Chiu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher Chiu, MRCP FRCPath PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+442083832301</phone>
    <email>c.chiu@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zoe Gardener, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>+442083832301</phone>
    <email>z.gardener@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imperial College London</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W12 0NN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher Chiu, BMBCh MRCP FRCPath PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+442083832301</phone>
      <email>c.chiu@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Zoe Gardener, BSc</last_name>
      <phone>+442083832301</phone>
      <email>z.gardener@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Chiu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Human</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Syncytial Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>RNA Virus Infections</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Syncytial Virus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data may be shared, all data will be anonymised.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

