<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03727672</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>638/5.11.2015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03727672</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Salivary Inflammatory Markers in Tension Type Headache and Migraine</brief_title>
  <acronym>SalHead</acronym>
  <official_title>Salivary Inflammatory Markers (Interleukin -1β, Interleukin -6, C- Reactive Protein) in Tension Type Headache and Migraine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Data role of salivary inflammatory markers in migraine and Tension Type headache (TTH) are
      lacking. Τhe investigators studied whether headache attacks are associated with changes in C
      reactive protein (CRP), Interleukin -1β and Interleukin -6 in saliva in patients with Tension
      Type Headache and Migraine and age matched healthy controls . Τhe investigators, also
      investigated whether these markers could be influenced by comorbidities such as depression
      and anxiety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sixty subjects of both genders, aged from 18 to 60 years old, with primary headaches TTH and
      migraine, according to the International Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd edition
      (beta version), were enrolled from the outpatient headache clinic of University Hospital of
      Athens between January to March 2016. 30 healthy control subjects aged matched were recruited
      mainly from hospital staff and patients' relatives.

      Initially, the participants completed the Hamilton Anxiety (HAM-A), Scale Beck Depression
      Inventory (BDI). All patients had to keep a headache diary during the four-week run-in
      period. All headache suffers were instructed to collected salivary headache-free baseline
      samples at the time of study screening when they had been free of headache for at least 48
      hours (time point A). All headache suffers collected additional samples during
      moderate/severe headache (time point B), and at self-defined resolution phase 24 hours of
      their headache attack (time point C). Healthy control subjects were instructed to collected
      samples at the time of study screening (time point D). Every week, until four weeks and one
      month after the end of the study, participants were contacted, in order to ensure the
      compliance and the appropriate use of the technique. One year later longitudinal data would
      also be obtain.

      Saliva Sample Collection Detailed instructions for the correct collection of saliva samples
      were given to all participants. Such instructions include avoiding eating a major meal and
      teeth brushing 60 minutes prior to sample collection. Also consumption of high sugar and
      caffeine content foods as well as high acidity foods have to be excluded before saliva sample
      collection. Mouth rinse with water in order to remove any food residue and saliva sample
      collection at least 10 minutes after mouth rinse was recommended. Unstimulated whole saliva
      that pooled on the mouth floor were collected from patients and healthy volunteers in high
      quality polypropylene vials by the passive drool technique. Finally, all samples were stored
      in a plastic container at 2-4 ° C until analysis. Saliva was collected from the participants,
      at 8.00 a.m. in the morning in order to rule out any confounding factor caused by circadian
      rhythm.

      Sample Analysis Morning samples were kept in the refrigerator at 4°C and at the end of the
      day were brought to the laboratory where they were centrifuged 3000 rpm at 4°C and the
      supernatant was aliquoted in to polypropylene Cryogenic vials. Vials were frozen in -80°C
      until analyzed. Saliva transferrin levels were measured by competitive immunoassay kits and
      Interleukin-6, Interleukin-1β and CRP levels were measured by sandwich ELISA kits.
      Transferrin levels were used as a screening tool for the presence of blood in saliva samples
      and samples with transferrin values greater than 1 mg/dl were considered as candidates for
      exclusion in other salivary assays. Cortisol assay has a sensitivity of &lt; 0.007 μg/ml and an
      inter-assay coefficient of variation of &lt; 11% while these characteristics are 0.07 pg/ml and
      8 for Interleukin-6, 0.37 pg/ml and 7 for Interleukin-1β, 10 pg/ml and 11.2 for CRP as well
      as 0.08 mg/dl and 7.2 for transferrin respectively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>migraine/Tension type Headache and C reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>establish whether attacks of migraine and Tension type Headache are associated with changes in the concentration of C reactive protein</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>migraine/Tension type Headache and Interleukin -1β</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>establish whether attacks of migraine and Tension type Headache are associated with changes in the concentration of Interleukin-1β</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>migraine/Tension type Headache and Interleukin-6 levels</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>establish whether attacks of migraine and Tension type Headache are associated with changes in the concentration of Interleukin-6 levels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>C reactive protein concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>C reactive protein concentrations as assessed using sandwich ELISA kits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interleukin-1β concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Interleukin-1β concentrations as assessed using sandwich ELISA kits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interleukin-6 levels concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>2,5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Interleukin-6 levels concentrations as assessed using sandwich ELISA kits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>2,5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety as assessed using the Hamilton Anxiety (HAM-A)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>2,5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Depression as assessed using the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine</condition>
  <condition>Tension-Type Headache</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tension type headache patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>30 subjects of both genders, aged from 18 to 60 years old, with primary headaches (TTH) , according to the International Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd edition (beta version) , were enrolled from the outpatient headache clinic of the first Neurological Hospital of University of Athens between January to March 2016.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Migraine patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>30 subjects of both genders, aged from 18 to 60 years old, with migraine, according to the International Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd edition (beta version) , were enrolled from the outpatient headache clinic of the first Neurological Hospital of University of Athens between January to March 2016.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>age matched controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>30 healthy control subjects aged matched were recruited mainly from hospital staff and patients' relatives</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Saliva transferrin levels were measured by competitive immunoassay kits and Interleukin-6,
      Interleukin-1β and CRP levels were measured by sandwich ELISA kits.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects of both genders, aged from 18 to 60 years old, with primary headaches TTH and
        migraine, according to the International Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd edition
        (beta version), were enrolled from the outpatient headache clinic of the first Neurological
        Hospital of University of Athens between January to March 2016. Fifteen healthy control
        subjects aged matched were recruited mainly from hospital staff and patients' relatives
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  aged from 18 to 60 years old

          -  Tension type Headache (TTH) and migraine, fulfilling the criteria International
             Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd edition (beta version)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  abnormal plasma CRP, Interleukin-1β and Interleukin-6 levels (&gt;10 mg/L)

          -  smoking cigarettes &gt; 1 pack/day;

          -  current pregnancy, lactation, or hormonal contraceptive use

          -  alcohol or substance abuse

          -  drug use such as anticoagulants, statins, or hormonal drugs

          -  anti-inflammatory therapy

          -  other primary or secondary headaches

          -  major psychiatric disease

          -  oral health problems.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>ANASTASIA BOUGEA, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Evangelia Kararizou, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>00302107289268</phone>
    <email>ekarariz@med.uoa.gr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eginition Hospital, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, School of Medicine, Athens, Greece</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>11528</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>EVANGELIA KARARIZOU</last_name>
      <phone>00302107289268</phone>
      <email>ekarariz@med.uoa.gr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sjögren E, Leanderson P, Kristenson M, Ernerudh J. Interleukin-6 levels in relation to psychosocial factors: studies on serum, saliva, and in vitro production by blood mononuclear cells. Brain Behav Immun. 2006 May;20(3):270-8. Epub 2005 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>16183246</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anastasia Bougea</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Primary headaches</keyword>
  <keyword>CRP</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin1β</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin6</keyword>
  <keyword>markers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tension-Type Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>database</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

