<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03722589</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7179</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03722589</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity Trial of Egg- Versus Non-Egg-Based Influenza Vaccines Among HCP</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Open-Label Trial to Compare the Immunogenicity of Cell Culture-Based and Recombinant Unadjuvanted Quadrivalent Influenza Vaccines to Conventional Egg-Based Unadjuvanted Quadrivalent Influenza Vaccines Among Healthcare Personnel Aged 18-64 Years</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baylor Scott and White Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Abt Associates</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized, open-label trial will assess humoral and cell-mediated immune responses to
      cell culture-based and recombinant unadjuvanted quadrivalent influenza vaccines compared to
      conventional egg-based unadjuvanted quadrivalent standard dose (15µg of HA per strain)
      influenza vaccines among persons aged 18-64 years. The trial will be conducted at two sites
      in the United States during two influenza seasons (2018-19 and 2019-20). Stratified
      enrollment procedures will be used to enroll a mix of participants based on age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In year 1 of the trial (the 2018-19 Northern Hemisphere influenza season), eligible
      participants at each site will be randomized 2:2:1:1 to receive a single dose of cell
      culture-based vaccine (Flucelvax™ Quadrivalent by Seqirus, Inc., 15µg of HA per strain)
      versus recombinant vaccine (Flublok® Quadrivalent by Sanofi Pasteur, 45µg of HA per strain)
      versus one of two standard dose egg-based vaccines (Fluzone® Quadrivalent by Sanofi Pasteur,
      15µg of HA per strain and Fluarix® Quadrivalent by GlaxoSmithKlein, 15µg of HA per strain)
      during August-September of 2018. All study vaccines are licensed for use in adults aged &gt;18
      years in the United States. Participants will have blood collected just prior to vaccination
      and at approximately 28 days and 6 months post-vaccination (or at the end of influenza virus
      circulation as determined by available surveillance data) to evaluate humoral immune
      responses to vaccination. Additional blood will be collected from a subset of participants
      pre-vaccination and at approximately 7 days, 28 days and 6 months post-vaccination (or at the
      end of influenza virus circulation) to evaluate cell-mediated immune responses to
      vaccination. Active surveillance with mid-turbinate nasal swab collection for influenza-like
      illness (ILI) defined as new onset of cough or worsening of chronic cough within the
      preceding 7 days will be conducted during the period of influenza circulation at each study
      site. Additional blood will also be collected at 6 months post-vaccination (or at the end of
      influenza virus circulation) from participants with reverse-transcription polymerase chain
      reaction (RT-PCR)-confirmed ILI during the influenza season to evaluate cell-mediated immune
      responses to natural influenza virus infection.

      In year 1, sites will aim to enroll 864 participants (432 per site) at the start of the
      2018-19 season, including up to 200 participants (up to 100 per site) who will contribute
      additional blood at all study visits to evaluate cell-mediated immune responses to
      vaccination. Efforts will be made to retain participants enrolled in the first year of the
      study for both years of the study. Sites will also enroll additional participants at the
      start of the 2019-20 season to make up for participants who withdraw or are lost to follow-up
      prior to the start of the 2019-20 season. Both participants and study investigators will be
      aware of study arm assignments with the exception of laboratory investigators who will be
      blinded to study arm assignment until testing is completed, as appropriate.

      In year 1 , relative efficacy of single doses of study vaccines will be assessed by comparing
      immunologic responses to vaccination among participants between study arms using Fluzone®
      Quadrivalent and Fluarix® Quadrivalent as the comparator groups for participants in the
      Flucelvax™ Quadrivalent or Flublok® Quadrivalent arms. In addition, the effect of frequency
      of prior vaccination during the preceding five years on immunologic responses to vaccine will
      be evaluated in subgroup analysis. Both humoral (influenza antibody) and cell-mediated
      (influenza- specific CD4 and CD8 T cell) immune responses will be evaluated.

      In year 2 of the trial, (the 2019-20 Northern Hemisphere influenza season), participants from
      the first year of the trial who received Flucelvax™ Quadrivalent or Flublok® Quadrivalent
      will be randomized 1:1 to receive Flucelvax™ Quadrivalent or Flublok® Quadrivalent, and
      participants who received an egg-based standard-dose vaccine in year one (Fluzone®
      Quadrivalent or Fluarix Quadrivalent) will be randomized 1:1:1 to receive Flucelvax™
      Quadrivalent , Flublok® Quadrivalent , or Fluzone® Quadrivalent. In addition, both sites will
      enroll additional participants in year 2 to achieve a total of 150 participants per site
      (including participants who continue from year one plus additional newly enrolled
      participants) who received egg-based standard dose influenza vaccine during the 2018-2019
      influenza season and who will be randomized 1:1:1 to receive Flucelvax™ Quadrivalent,
      Flublok® Quadrivalent, or Fluzone® Quadrivalent in year two. The Kaiser Permanente Northwest
      site site will also enroll up to 80 new participants for a non-randomized study arm that will
      receive Fluzone® High-Dose. All study vaccines except Fluzone High-Dose are licensed for use
      in adults aged &gt;=18 years in the United States. Fluzone High-Dose is licensed for use in
      adults aged &gt;=64 years in the United States and will be used off-label in this trial.
      Participants will have blood collected just prior to vaccination and at approximately 28 days
      post-vaccination (or at the end of influenza virus circulation as determined by available
      surveillance data) to evaluate humoral immune responses to vaccination. Additional blood will
      be collected from a subset of participants pre-vaccination and at approximately 7 and 28 days
      post-vaccination to evaluate cell-mediated immune responses to vaccination.

      In year 2, sites will aim to retain from year 1 or newly enroll 750 participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microneutralization (MN) assay response to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 - seroconversion rate (SCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>MN responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including by assessing SCR in the various vaccine arms defined as the proportion of participants with paired samples that achieved ≥ 4 fold rises comparing post- versus pre-vaccination titers, and post vaccination titers ≥ 40</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MN assay response to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 - geometric mean titer (GMT)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>MN responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including by assessing GMTs in the various vaccine arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MN assay response to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 - mean fold rise (MFR)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>MN responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including MFR defined as the ratio of the post-vaccination titer value to the pre-vaccination value</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MN assay response to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 - GMT ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>MN responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including GMT ratio defined as the ratio of the post-vaccination GMT between comparison groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemagglutination inhibition (HI) responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria viruses - SCR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including by assessing SCR in the various vaccine arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria viruses - GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including by assessing GMTs in the various vaccine arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria viruses - MFR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including by assessing MFR in the various vaccine arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria viruses - GMT ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to the cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days post-vaccination, including by assessing GMT ratio for each vaccine arm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - seropositivity</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including post-vaccination titers greater than or equal to seropositive thresholds at 1:40, 1:80, and 1:160</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - SCR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including by assessing SCR in the various vaccine arms defined as the proportion of participants with paired samples that achieved ≥ 4 fold rises comparing post- versus pre-vaccination titers, and post vaccination titers ≥ 40</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including by assessing GMTs in the various vaccine arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - GMT ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including GMT ratio defined as the ratio of the post-vaccination GMT between comparison groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - MFR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including MFR defined as the ratio of the post-vaccination titer value to the pre-vaccination value</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MN responses to cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - SCR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>MN responses to cell-grown influenza A/H3N2 vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including by assessing SCR in the various vaccine arms defined as the proportion of participants with paired samples that achieved ≥ 4 fold rises comparing post- versus pre-vaccination titers, and post vaccination titers ≥ 40</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days - seropositivity</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI responses to cell-grown influenza A/H1N1, influenza B/Yamagata, and influenza B/Victoria vaccine reference viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including post-vaccination titers greater than or equal to seropositive thresholds at 1:40, 1:80, and 1:160</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses - GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including GMT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses - SCR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including SCR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses - MFR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including MFR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses - seropositivity</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to egg-grown vaccine reference viruses for all vaccine viruses for each study season at approximately 28 days, including post-vaccination titers greater than or equal to seropositive thresholds at 1:40, 1:80 and 1:160 as measured by HI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GMT by HI for all vaccine viruses at 6 months - cell-grown</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>GMT as measured by HI for all vaccine virus subtypes/lineages at 6 months post-vaccination using cell-grown vaccine reference viruses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GMT by HI for all vaccine viruses at 6 months - egg-grown</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>GMT as measured by HI for all vaccine virus subtypes/lineages at 6 months post-vaccination using egg-grown vaccine reference viruses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses - SCR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses at approximately 28 days (if appropriate), including SCR</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses - GMT</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses at approximately 28 days (if appropriate), including GMT</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses - MFR</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses at approximately 28 days (if appropriate), including MFR</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>HI responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses - seropositivity</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>HI and/or MN responses to cell-grown wild-type influenza viruses at approximately 28 days (if appropriate), including post-vaccination titers greater than or equal to seropositive thresholds at 1:40, 1:80, 1:160 as measured by HI</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>GMT as measured by neuraminidase inhibition assay (NAI) pre- and post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>GMT as measured by NAI pre- and post-vaccination (28-days)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>GMT as measured by antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC) pre- and post-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>GMT as measured by ADCC pre- and post-vaccination (28-days)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of laboratory confirmed influenza illness</measure>
    <time_frame>Local influenza season (approximately 4-6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) confirmed influenza illnesses, monitored by active surveillance during the local flu season</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cell-mediated immunity, time point 1</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Mean percentages of strain-specific T cell surface markers of activation, antibody secreting plasmablasts and memory B cells to hemagglutinin (HA), interferon-gamma (IFN- gamma), interleukin 2 (IL-2), and Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) responses to wild-type cell-grown strains and antigen-specific B and T cell repertoire, and single cell transcriptome analysis (where feasible) at 7 days post-vaccination</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cell-mediated immunity, time point 2</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Mean percentages of strain-specific T cell surface markers of activation, antibody secreting plasmablasts and memory B cells to hemagglutinin (HA), interferon-gamma (IFN- gamma), interleukin 2 (IL-2), and Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) responses to wild-type cell-grown strains and antigen-specific B and T cell repertoire, and single cell transcriptome analysis (where feasible) at 28 days post-vaccination</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cell-mediated immunity (CMI), time point 3</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Mean percentages of strain-specific T cell surface markers of activation, antibody secreting plasmablasts and memory B cells to hemagglutinin (HA), interferon-gamma (IFN- gamma), interleukin 2 (IL-2), and Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) responses to wild-type cell-grown strains and antigen-specific B and T cell repertoire, and single cell transcriptome analysis (where feasible) at 12 months post-vaccination</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">864</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Flublok (Recombinant)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Flublok® Quadrivalent by Sanofi Pasteur, 45µg of HA per strain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Flucelvax (Cell-based)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Flucelvax™ Quadrivalent by Seqirus, Inc., 15µg of HA per strain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluarix (Egg-based)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fluarix® Quadrivalent by GlaxoSmithKlein, 15µg of HA per strain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone (Egg-based)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fluzone® Quadrivalent by Sanofi Pasteur, 15µg of HA per strain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone (Egg-based) High-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fluzone® Trivalent High-Dose by Sanofi Pasteur, 60µg of HA per strain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flublok</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL intramuscular dose of Flublok</description>
    <arm_group_label>Flublok (Recombinant)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flucelvax</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL intramuscular dose of Flucelvax</description>
    <arm_group_label>Flucelvax (Cell-based)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluarix</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL intramuscular dose of Fluarix</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fluarix (Egg-based)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL intramuscular dose of Fluzone</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone (Egg-based)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluzone High-Dose</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL intramuscular dose of Fluzone</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fluzone (Egg-based) High-Dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthcare personnel (HCP) who have direct contact with patients, including dentists
             and other dental health personnel

          -  Enrolled in Scott &amp; White Healthcare or Kaiser Permanente health network for at least
             one month

          -  Aged 18-64 years for newly enrolled participants

          -  Aged 18-65 years for participants who were originally enrolled in year one of the
             study and return for year 2

          -  Available and willing to participate in study follow-up through the end of the
             2019-2020 influenza season (i.e. at least approximately 18 months if enrolled during
             season 1 or 6 months if enrolled during season 2)

          -  Received an egg-based standard dose influenza vaccine during the 2018-2019 influenza
             season (for participants enrolled for the first-time during year two)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Already received an influenza vaccine during the current influenza season

          -  Previous hypersensitivity reaction to the study vaccines as reported by the subject

          -  Received any vaccine in the 4 weeks prior to the first study visit or plans to receive
             a vaccine (other than influenza vaccine provided through the study protocol) in the 4
             weeks following the first study visit

          -  Currently participating in a study that involves an experimental agent (vaccine, drug,
             biologic, device, blood product, or medication), or has received an experimental agent
             within 1 month prior to enrollment in this study, or expects to receive an
             experimental agent during participation in this study

          -  Any condition that the principle investigator (PI) believes may interfere with
             successful completion of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fatimah Dawood, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brendan Flannery, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Northwest</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97227</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Scott and White Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Temple</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76543</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will be made available to contractor and site research staff. This data can be made available to other researchers upon request.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Study period</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

