<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03723564</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-007726</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03723564</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Serial Amnioinfusions as Regenerative Therapy for Pulmonary Hypoplasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Serial Amnioinfusions as Regenerative Therapy for Pulmonary Hypoplasia in Fetuses With Intrauterine Renal Failure or Severe Renal Anomalies- a Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rodrigo Ruano M.D., Ph.D</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Congenital lower urinary tract obstruction (LUTO) is a heterogeneous group of congenital
      anomalies that lead bladder outlet obstruction. If a complete obstruction is present, the
      perinatal mortality is estimated to be as high as 90% because of severe pulmonary hypoplasia
      due to the lack of amniotic fluid. Survivors have significant risk of renal impairment (90%)
      requiring dialysis or renal transplantation if no fetal intervention is performed.

      Renal agenesis is the congenital absence of one or both kidneys due to complete failure of
      the kidney to form. As many as 33% of fetuses with bilateral renal agenesis are stillborn,
      and the rest of them die immediately after birth due to severe pulmonary hypoplasia.

      The objective of the serial amnioinfusions for fetuses with these conditions will be to
      reduce the severity of pulmonary hypoplasia (regenerating the lung functionality) and
      therefore increase the chance that the newborn survives to begin peritoneal dialysis.
      Although there is initial evidence that serial amnioinfusions are feasible for the pregnant
      women and the fetuses, there is still a need to have a prospective clinical trial to confirm
      the hypothesis that serial amnioinfusions could prevent severe pulmonary hypoplasia allowing
      the newborns with bilateral renal agenesis or severe LUTO to survive to begin peritoneal
      dialysis.

      Therefore, the investigators aim to study the hypothesis that serial amnioinfusions for
      fetuses with severe LUTO and renal failure and those with bilateral renal agenesis will
      reduce the severity of pulmonary hypoplasia and therefore increase the chance that the
      newborn survives to begin peritoneal dialysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All women with fetuses having either severe LUTO with intrauterine renal failure or bilateral
      renal agenesis that meet the inclusion criteria will be invited to participate in this study.
      For those patients, the actual standard of care is expectant prenatal management or
      termination of pregnancy (&lt;22 weeks according to law). This study will offer serial
      amnioinfusions for patients with LUTO or bilateral renal agenesis. Due to the rarity and
      complexity of these cases, the investigators expect to enroll a maximum of 5 women with
      affected fetuses per year. After two years (approximately 10 cases), a review of the data
      will be completed including all outcomes to determine whether to continue towards the
      original goal of treating 40 patients (20 mothers with affected fetuses) or to close the
      study,.

      All procedures are anticipated to take place in the Family Birth Center at Mayo Clinic,
      Rochester. Serial ultrasound-guided amnioinfusion procedures will be performed on fetuses
      having severe LUTO or bilateral renal agenesis that are diagnosed between 18 0/7-25 6/7
      weeks. This procedure will be performed in a sterile fashion within the operating room using
      the same technique that is routinely used to perform the ultrasound-guided amnioinfusion.
      Once consented, weekly ultrasound monitoring will be conducted and if the amniotic fluid
      index (AFI) is determined to be &lt;2 cm, amnioinfusion will proceed. Prior to each infusion,
      5mLs of amniotic fluid will be collected to study surrogate markers of lung function
      (research only). Using a 22-gauge needle, warm sterile lactated ringer solution will be
      infused into the amniotic cavity until the AFI is equal to 8 cm. Some studies have
      demonstrated that the composition of the amniotic fluid during second and third trimester is
      closer to the lactated ringer solution. This procedure will be continued weekly until the
      fetus reaches 34 weeks, after which only monitoring will occur. If preterm premature rupture
      of the membranes (PPROM) occurs prior to 34 weeks, no further amnioinfusion procedures will
      be performed. Patients with PPROM will be managed according to the standardized clinical
      management. The anticipated length of stay in the hospital after each infusion is
      approximately 2 days if no uterine contractions are observed.

      The prenatal care, delivery and postnatal management of the infant will be conducted
      according to the standardized clinical care. Delivery will be scheduled at the Mayo Clinic
      Family Birth Center and the infants will be followed for 24 months by the multi-specialty
      team as part of the standard clinical management including follow-up with neonatologist (NICU
      team), pediatric nephrology and transplant team according to the clinical protocol for
      postnatal renal replacement therapy and transplant. Neurodevelopment of the children will
      assessed using a combination of clinical examination and the Bayley Scale of Infant
      Development during the first 24 months of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>First amnioinfusion through delivery which may be up to 22 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of Adverse Events experienced</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to renal transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects able to receive renal transplant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to dialysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of birth up to one month</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects able to receive dialysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Failure Congenital</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Renal Anomaly Nos</condition>
  <condition>Renal Agenesis and Dysgenesis</condition>
  <condition>Lower Urinary Tract Obstructive Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amnioinfusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lactated Ringers Solution for Injection --- Serial ultrasound-guided amnioinfusion procedures will be performed on fetuses having severe LUTO or bilateral renal agenesis that are diagnosed between 18 0/7-25 6/7 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lactated Ringers Solution for Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Using ultrasound guidance, a 22 gauge needle will be introduced into amniotic cavity. Warmed Lactated Ringers solution will be injected into the amniotic cavity until an AFI of 8.0 cm is achieved</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amnioinfusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lactated Ringers Solution for Infusion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women with singleton uterine pregnancy

          -  Maternal age &gt; age 18

          -  Fetus &lt; 26 weeks gestational age with severe LUTO and intrauterine renal failure

          -  Fetus &lt; 26 weeks gestational age with bilateral renal agenesis

          -  Fetus with absence of chromosome abnormalities

          -  Fetus with absence of associated anomalies

          -  Mother has negative Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, and HIV testing

          -  Mother meets psychosocial criteria that allows her to make a conscious decision about
             her fetus/infant

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Associated fetal anomaly unrelated to LUTO or renal agenesis

          -  Increased risk for preterm labor including short cervical length, history of
             incompetent cervix with or without cerclage, and previous preterm birth

          -  Placental abnormalities known at time of enrollment

          -  Maternal-fetal Rh isoimmunization, Kell sensitization or neonatal alloimmune
             thrombocytopenia affecting the current pregnancy

          -  Maternal medical condition that is a contraindication to surgery or anesthesia

          -  Mother has declined invasive testing

          -  Inability to comply with the travel and follow-up requirements of the trial

          -  Participation in another interventional study that influences maternal and fetal
             morbidity and mortality

          -  Participation in this clinical trial during a previous pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rodrigo Ruano, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shonie L Buenvenida, BSN, RN</last_name>
    <phone>507.293.1487</phone>
    <email>buenvenida.shonie@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maureen A Lemens, BSN, RN</last_name>
    <phone>507.293.1487</phone>
    <email>lemens.maureen@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shonie L Buenvenida, BSN, RN</last_name>
      <email>buenvenida.shonie@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maureen A Lemens, BSN, RN</last_name>
      <phone>507.293.1487</phone>
      <email>lemens.maureen@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rodrigo Ruano, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mayo.edu/research/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rodrigo Ruano M.D., Ph.D</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bilateral renal agenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>lower urinary tract obstruction</keyword>
  <keyword>congenital renal anomalies</keyword>
  <keyword>fetal surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>amnioinfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>fetus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

