<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03726593</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WR2530</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03726593</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Drug Combinations of Atovaquone-Proguanil (AP) With ACT</brief_title>
  <acronym>APACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicenter Therapeutic Efficacy Assessment of Pyronaridine-Artesunate (Pyramax®) and New Drug Combinations With Atovaquone-Proguanil for the Treatment of Uncomplicated P. Falciparum Malaria in Cambodia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Armed Forces Research Institute of Medical Sciences, Thailand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Parasitology, Entomology, and Malaria Control (CNM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Naval Medical Research Unit-2 (NAMRU-2)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Armed Forces Research Institute of Medical Sciences, Thailand</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigators are conducting this study due to recent reports of many of existing malaria
      drugs becoming less effective for treatment of malaria. The drugs may not always kill all the
      parasites, therefore not all patients with malaria are being cured. The main objective of the
      study is to find out which malaria drugs and what drug combinations are still effective in
      Cambodia, an area of multi-drug resistance where 4-5 artemisinin-based combination therapies
      have shown inadequate response, below that established by the World Health Organization
      (WHO). New drug combinations (taking more than one drug for malaria at the same time), as
      long as well tolerated, can provide cure in patients that harbor parasites not responsive to
      standard first-line medications. Human genetic testing will be done to identify patients who
      may have suboptimal response to treatments and to study the differences in human gene
      expression to explain why some persons are at higher risk of complications during treatment.
      Markers of drug resistance to commonly used antimalarial drugs will also be evaluated and
      shared with national malaria program (CNM) to better guide future malaria treatment decisions
      in Cambodia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Efficacy to drugs that are currently available and new antimalarial candidates that are in
      development are threatened by multidrug resistant (MDR) malaria parasites, widely prevalent
      in Cambodia. Without effective interventions, MDR malaria can pose a substantial public
      health threat in the years to come. Therefore, accurate, timely and relevant data on
      antimalarial drug resistance is of critical importance. Prompt, effective and well-tolerated
      treatment remains one of the cornerstones in the malaria case management. Recent malaria
      outbreak in Thailand and rise of malaria cases observed in Cambodia in 2017 has brought to
      the forefront the urgency with which new drug candidates and new combination drug treatments
      must be identified; otherwise, patients may be left with ineffective treatments. Lack of
      available alternatives has a potential to result in significant setback to the recent gains
      in malaria control and malaria elimination efforts. Innovative approaches to treatment
      proposed here, using current ACTs in combination with non-ACT drugs, such as
      atovaquone-proguanil, need to be investigated to assess drug tolerability and overall
      efficacy when used under combination treatment. By early investment in the studies of drugs
      such as pyronaridine-artesunate (ASPY), in combination with other antimalarials, and drug
      combinations proposed under this protocol, this study will try to provide the latest evidence
      on the interventions that are most likely to work, even in areas of MDR, such as Cambodia,
      and along the Cambodia-Thai border. It is hoped that our approach for using combination
      treatments will not only provide more effective treatments, but it might prolong the lifespan
      of the remaining antimalarials and delay the spread of MDR malaria to neighboring countries.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, open-label clinical trial to evaluate the tolerability and clinical and parasitological responses after treatment of Pf and/or mixed infections (Pf/Pv) in volunteers with uncomplicated malaria. The assignment of volunteers will be 1:1:1 for ASPY (Pyramax), AP+ASPY (AP+Pyramax), and AP+ASMQ. All study drug administration will be by directly observed therapy (DOT).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>42-day polymerase chain reaction (PCR) corrected adequate clinical and parasitological response (ACPR), following treatment with ASPY and new drug combinations (AP+ACTs).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of molecular markers of drug resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of enrollment and day of malaria recurrence up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug susceptibility testing of parasite isolates against standard antimalarial drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of enrollment and day of malaria recurrence up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Ex vivo drug susceptibility testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmakokinetics of each study drug - (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>multiple time points up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Peak plasma concentration (Cmax) for study drugs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmakokinetics of each study drug - (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>multiple time points up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmakokinetics of each study drug - volume of distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>multiple time points throughout 6 weeks of follow up</time_frame>
    <description>volume of distribution for study drugs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmakokinetics of each study drug - (T1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>multiple time points up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>elimination half-life (T1/2) for study drugs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kaplan Meier survival analysis of asexual blood stage parasitemia and sexual stage gametocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gametocyte carriage rates on days 0, 1, 2, 3, and weeks 1 through 6 for each treatment arm</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0, 1, 2, 3, and weekly, up to week 8</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of hepatotoxicity events for each treatment arm</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3 and week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Alanine aminotransferase (ALT)&gt;5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) or percent of volunteers meeting the Hy's law definition (ALT or aspartate aminotransferase [AST] &gt;3 x ULN and total bilirubin &gt;2 x ULN) at any post-dose time point within 6 weeks of follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Grade 1 - mild, Grade 2 - moderate, Grade 3 - severe, Grade 4- life threatening</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who say they are willing to take the same drug combination in the future</measure>
    <time_frame>day 2 and week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Point efficacy with 95% Confidence Interval against blood stage malaria infection classified according to the WHO malaria treatment outcome classifications (ETF, LTF, LCTF, LPTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks, 6 weeks, and 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Comparative incidence of G6PD deficiency in the study population as determined by G6PD rapid-diagnostic tests (RDTs) and quantitative tests, to include sensitivity, specificity, negative predictive value (NPV) and positive predictive value (PPV) for each of the point-of-care tests against 10%, 30%, and 60% thresholds of normal G6PD activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of infected mosquitos following membrane feeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, Day 3, Day 7, and on day of malaria recurrence up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">252</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria (Drug Resistant)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ASPY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Artesunate-pyronaridine, once daily for three days, following standard weight-based dosing per drug label. All volunteers with P.f monoinfection will receive single dose of primaquine (PQ) (15 mg) for transmission blocking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AP+ASPY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Atovaquone-Proguanil (AP) + Artesunate-Pyronaridine (ASPY), once daily for three days, following standard weight-based dosing per drug label for each drug. All volunteers with P.f monoinfection receive single dose of PQ (15 mg) for transmission blocking</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AP+ASMQ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Atovaquone-Proguanil (AP) + Artesunate-Mefloquine (ASMQ); ASMQ once daily for three days (D0, D1, D2), following standard weight-based dosing per drug label. Subsequently, volunteers continue their treatment with AP once daily starting on day 3, for three additional days (D3, 4, 5). All volunteers with P.f monoinfection receive single dose of PQ (15 mg) for transmission blocking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Artesunate and Pyronaridine</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard weight based dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>ASPY</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atovaquone Proguanil and Artesunate Pyronaridine</intervention_name>
    <description>Both drugs (AP) and (ASPY) are administered once a day, on days 0, 1, and 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AP+ASPY</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atovaquone Proguanil and Artesunate Mefloquine</intervention_name>
    <description>Sequential treatment with ASMQ (on days 0, 1, and 2) followed by the treatment with AP for 3 more days (total 6 days treatment)</description>
    <arm_group_label>AP+ASMQ</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Understands Khmer spoken language

          -  Male or female (18 to 70 years old)

          -  Microscopic confirmation of asexual stages of Pf or mixed infection with Pf, with
             baseline asexual parasite densities between 100/µL to 200,000/µL

          -  Able to take oral medications

          -  Hemoglobin on day of enrollment ≥9.0 g/dL

          -  Agree to follow-up for the anticipated study duration, including a minimum of 3 nights
             at the medical treatment facility (inpatient hospitalization) and weekly follow-up
             visits for at least 6 weeks

          -  If the volunteer is on active duty in the military, the volunteer has written
             permission from their supervisor or states to have been authorized by his/her
             supervisor or the local commander to participate; and allow study staff to contact
             their supervisor to confirm this information

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergic reaction to any of the study drugs or history of severe intolerance to
             any of the antimalarials used in this study.

          -  Pregnant or lactating females and females of childbearing potential who do not agree
             to use an acceptable form of contraception during the study period and for 6 weeks
             following the last dose of the study drug.

          -  Symptoms of severe vomiting (inability to tolerate oral fluids or oral medications
             during the previous 8 hours or vomiting &gt;3 times in the last 24 hrs).

          -  Diagnosis of severe malaria

          -  Abnormal liver function tests i.e AST or ALT or total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 upper limit of
             normal (ULN) with nausea AND right upper quadrant abdominal pain OR jaundice on exam

          -  Isolated AST or ALT or Total Bilirubin &gt;2x ULN

          -  Known significant cardiovascular, liver or renal abnormality or any other clinically
             significant illness, which in the opinion of the investigator would place the
             volunteer at significantly higher risk

          -  Treatment for malaria within the last 4 weeks

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Judged by the investigator to be otherwise unsuitable for study participation (to
             include, but not limited to, taking other medications that are known to cause serious
             drug-drug interactions with the study drugs, as determined by the study physician, or
             having suspected medical condition or taking other drugs that may affect test results
             interpretation or put the volunteer at much higher risk)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mariusz Wojnarski, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Armed Forces Research Institute of Medical Sciences (AFRIMS) Bangkok, Thailand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mariusz Wojnarski, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+66-84-527-4646</phone>
    <email>MARIUSZ.WOJNARSKI.MIL@AFRIMS.ORG</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Norman Waters, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+66 (0)2 696 2798</phone>
    <email>Norman.Waters.mil@afrims.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kratie Referral Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kratie</city>
        <country>Cambodia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Somaly Kieng, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>+855 72 971 755</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chanthap Lon, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>855 23 881 845</phone>
      <email>chanthapl@afrims.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Darapiseth Sea, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dysoley Lek, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stung Treng Referral Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stung Treng</city>
        <country>Cambodia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dysoley Lek, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anlong Veng Referral Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ânlóng Vêng</city>
        <country>Cambodia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Phan Kong, M.A</last_name>
      <phone>016 51 09 09</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chanthap Lon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Darapiseth Sea, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dysoley Lek, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cambodia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>plasmodium falciparum</keyword>
  <keyword>malarone</keyword>
  <keyword>atovaquone</keyword>
  <keyword>mefloquine</keyword>
  <keyword>pyramax</keyword>
  <keyword>pyronaridine</keyword>
  <keyword>combination treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>triple therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>multidrug resistant malaria</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Artesunate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mefloquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atovaquone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Proguanil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyronaridine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atovaquone, proguanil drug combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The study site will maintain appropriate medical and research records for this trial until completion of the study, in compliance with Section 4.9 of International Conference on Harmonization E6 Good Clinical Practices, and institutional requirements. The investigators and other study personnel assigned from National Center for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control (CNM), Armed Forces Research Institute of Medical Sciences (AFRIMS) and Naval Medical Research Center NMRC-Asia and their respective representatives are authorized access to the study data as part of their duties. The database may be shared with other collaborators, on a mutually agreed basis. Sharing and publication of the data with other parties can be done only after inter-institutional agreements are in place. The research findings may be disseminated to policy makers and other researchers for an informed decision on drug policy for the treatment of malaria.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

