<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03724656</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Gastrointestinal RCT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03724656</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Intraoperative Stimulation of Acupoints on Postoperative Gastrointestinal Motility Recovery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Intraoperative Stimulation of Acupoints on Postoperative Gastrointestinal Motility Recovery in Patients Undergoing Non-gastrointestinal Abdominal Surgery: A Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tianjin Nankai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tianjin Nankai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Research name: Effects of intraoperative stimulation of acupoints on postoperative
           gastrointestinal motility recovery in patients undergoing non-gastrointestinal abdominal
           surgery.

        2. Research center: Multicenter research

        3. Research design: A randomized controlled study method would be used in this study, in
           which the investigators would provide electroacupuncture on the basis of general
           anesthesia for non-gastrointestinal abdominal surgery. The effects of electroacupuncture
           on postoperative gastrointestinal motility recovery in patients undergoing
           non-gastrointestinal abdominal surgery will be observed and compared with the control
           group.

        4. Research population: Patients who are greater or equal to 18 years old and less than 64
           years old , meanwhile intend to receive selective/limited non-gastrointestinal surgery
           under general anesthesia.

        5. Number of participants: 600

        6. Interventions: The treatment group received electroacupuncture intervention 30 minutes
           before induction of anesthesia. In the treatment group, bilateral Neiguan point,
           bilateral Zusanli point and bilateral Hegu point were selected, then electroacupuncture
           was applied and the needle was retained until the end of operation. The control group
           was treated with non-acupoint shallow acupuncture method. The needle was inserted 5 cm
           beside the acupoint and the needling depth was less than 2 mm. At the same time, the
           manual stimulation was avoided, &quot;Deqi&quot; was not obtained, electroacupuncture was applied,
           electric current was regulated, and the needle was retained until the end of the
           operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a large sample, randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled and long-term
      follow-up design. In this study, bilateral Neiguan(PC6), bilateral Zusanli(ST36)and bilateral
      Hegu (LI4)points were selected for perioperative TAES treatment. accompanied with evaluating
      the postoperative gastrointestinal motility, the incidence of postoperative nausea and
      vomiting , as well as the effects on postoperative NRS pain and sleep quality scores . To
      clarify the effect of TAES on the postoperative spontaneous voiding in patients for
      laparoscopic surgery is of great significance to the clinical applications and popularization
      of traditional acupuncture treatment perioperatively across the world.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative venting</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Record the time from the end of the procedure to the patient's first venting after operation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical tests</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma motilin，gastrin ，Vasoactive intestinal peptide (VIP)，SOD（Superoxide Dismutase） and MDA（Malonaldehyde）</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>bowel sounds and defecation</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>record the recovery time of postoperative bowel sounds and defecation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative nausea and vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Record the incidence of postoperative nausea and vomiting in patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>acupuncture treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the TAES treatment group received Transcutaneous Acupoint Electrical Stimulation(TAES) 30 minutes before induction of anesthesia. Bilateral Neiguan（PC6）, bilateral Zusanli（ST36）and bilateral Hegu （LI4）point were selected by electroacupuncture stimulation apparatus (HANS G6805-2, Huayi Co, Shanghai, China).After &quot;Deqi&quot;, electroacupuncture stimulation apparatus is connected and maintained until the end of operation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham acupuncture treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group was treated with non-acupoint shallow acupuncture method. The needle was inserted 5 cm beside the acupoint and the needling depth was less than 2 mm. At the same time, the manual stimulation and &quot;Deqi&quot; was avoided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>acupuncture treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>TAES treatment 30 minutes before induction of anesthesia. Bilateral Neiguan（PC6）, bilateral Zusanli（ST36）and bilateral Hegu （LI4）point were selected by electroacupuncture stimulation apparatus (HANS G6805-2, Huayi Co, Shanghai, China).After &quot;Deqi&quot;, electroacupuncture stimulation apparatus is connected and maintained until the end of operation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>acupuncture treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sham acupuncture treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the sham acupuncture group received shallow needling (0.30mm×25mm) at bilateral sham points(nonacupoints located 5cm beside acupoints, about 20mm). The control group was treated with non-acupoint shallow acupuncture method and the needling depth was less than 2 mm. At the same time, the manual stimulation and &quot;Deqi&quot; was avoided.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham acupuncture treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Inclusion Criteria

        Subjects enrolled in this study must accord with all of the following criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years old and &lt;64 years old, gender, ethnicity is not limited;

          2. It is intended to selective/limited non-gastrointestinal surgery under general
             anesthesia;

          3. Agree to participate in the study and sign an informed consent form;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Refusing to participate in this study;

          2. Patients with cardiac pacemakers and some special groups, such as pregnant women and
             those who have had many long-term acupuncture treatment experience;

          3. Patients with peptic ulcer, perforation or obstruction;

          4. Patients with chronic liver and renal dysfunction, and those who use β-blockers or
             antihypertensive drugs;

          5. The attending doctors or researchers believe that there are other unsuitable
             situations for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yu Jianbo, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Nankai Hospital of Tianjin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhang Yuan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>13642066361</phone>
    <email>13642066361@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yu Jianbo, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>（022）27435008</phone>
    <email>yujianbo11@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee CH, Kim DK, Yook TH, Sasaki M, Kitamura N. Effectiveness of electroacupuncture at Zusanli (ST36) on the immunohistochemical density of enteroendocrine cells related to gastrointestinal function. J Acupunct Meridian Stud. 2012 Apr;5(2):63-71. doi: 10.1016/j.jams.2012.01.002. Epub 2012 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22483184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang CP, Kao CH, Chen WK, Lo WY, Hsieh CL. A single-blinded, randomized pilot study evaluating effects of electroacupuncture in diabetic patients with symptoms suggestive of gastroparesis. J Altern Complement Med. 2008 Sep;14(7):833-9. doi: 10.1089/acm.2008.0107.</citation>
    <PMID>18721079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Güngördük K, Özdemir İA, Güngördük Ö, Gülseren V, Gokçü M, Sancı M. Effects of coffee consumption on gut recovery after surgery of gynecological cancer patients: a randomized controlled trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2017 Feb;216(2):145.e1-145.e7. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2016.10.019. Epub 2016 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27780709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tianjin Nankai Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jianbo Yu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Department of Anesthesiology, Director, Chief physician, Professor, Doctoral tutor Affiliation: Tianjin Nankai Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transcutaneous Acupoint Electrical Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>non-gastrointestinal abdominal surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>gastrointestinal motility</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

