<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03721809</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017/185/HP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03721809</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterization of the Inflammatory Profile of Patients With Macrophage Activation Syndrome Secondary to Bacterial Sepsis</brief_title>
  <acronym>SAMOKINE</acronym>
  <official_title>Characterization of the Inflammatory Profile of Patients With Macrophage Activation Syndrome Secondary to Bacterial Sepsis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Rouen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Rouen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The pathophysiology of macrophage activation syndrome has been mainly studied in pediatric
      genetic primary forms. There is little data in secondary forms related to bacterial sepsis.
      Because of the seriousness of this entity (43% of deaths in intensive care in the largest
      cohort published so far by the medical resuscitation team of Rouen University Hospital), it
      is necessary to better understand the physiopathological mechanisms to be able to propose a
      suitable therapy. For now, the management of this syndrome is far from consensual. Some
      authors advocate a single etiological treatment, while others suggest the need for intensive
      management of anti-inflammatory and immunosuppressive type. The fragility of resuscitation
      patients does not allow intensive immunosuppressive therapies as proposed by some authors. In
      the era of immunotherapy, the precise knowledge of physiopathological data would make it
      possible to propose a targeted therapy with little risk of adverse effects. Recent work has
      indeed shown excellent tolerance of immunotherapy during sepsis and could be applied
      eventually in patients with macrophage activation syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>quantitative measurement of plasma IL-1β in MAS patients secondary to septic sepsis / bacterial septic shock in comparison with a control population of sepsis /septic shock.</measure>
    <time_frame>performed on day 1</time_frame>
    <description>measured by the luminex method</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Macrophage Activation Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>macrophage activation syndrome secondary to bacterial sepsis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients hospitalized in medical intensive care for macrophage activation syndrome secondary to bacterial sepsis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>bacterial sepsis/septic shock</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients hospitalized in medical intensive care for sepsis / septic shock</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood samples</intervention_name>
    <description>There are 3 specific blood sampling times for each patient, on D1, D2 and D5 (D1 being the day of inclusion): cytokine samples (IL-1β, IL-6, IL-10, TNF-α, IFN-gamma) on 5ml dry tube.
On D1, a 2.5ml PAXgene tube will also be taken for each patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>bacterial sepsis/septic shock</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>macrophage activation syndrome secondary to bacterial sepsis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patient hospitalized in intensive care for macrophage activation syndrome secondary to
        sepsis / bacterial septic shock with a strong clinical probability score (defined by a
        HScore&gt; 80% cf appendix 4) (experimental population) or Patient hospitalized in intensive
        care for sepsis or septic shock (control population)

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Person affiliated with a social security scheme or beneficiary of such a scheme

          -  Trusted person or informed patient who has signed the consent to participate in the
             research. (If the patient is unable to sign his / her consent (emergencies) the
             consent will be signed by the person of trust, and consent to further study will be
             requested from the patient).

          -  Effective contraception in women of childbearing potential (negative pregnancy test).
             For postmenopausal women, a confirmation diagnosis should be obtained (amenorrhea for
             at least 12 months before the inclusion visit).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding woman

          -  Person deprived of liberty by an administrative or judicial decision

          -  Protected major subject, under tutorship or curatorship

          -  Patient participating in another interventional clinical trial with the same primary
             objective
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macrophage Activation Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

