<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03724604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XJTU1AF-CRF-2017-020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03724604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NSE/Alb as a Prognostic Biomarker for Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>NARPBLC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Cohort Study on NSE/Alb as a Prognostic Biomarker for Lung Cancer Patients in Multicenter</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shaanxi Provincial Cancer Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shaanxi Provincial People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Xi'an Central Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The incidence and mortality rate of lung cancer is the highest in the world. Current studies
      have found that tumor markers, inflammatory or nutritional indicators have a good predictive
      value for the prognosis of patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). Neuron specific
      enolase (NSE) and serum albumin (Alb) are important indicators for monitoring tumor
      progression and nutritional status in lung cancer patients, respectively. Previous studies
      suggested that the higher the NSE, the worse prognosis of NSCLC patients, while the lower the
      Alb, the worse the prognosis of patients with malignant tumors. Through a retrospective
      study, the investigators found that NAR (NSE Alb Ratio) was higher and prognosis was poorer
      in patients undergoing NSCLC surgery. This is better than the previous assessment indicators
      PLR (platelet to lymphocyte ratio), NLR (neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio), AGR (albumin to
      globulin ratio), NAR can better assess prognosis. Therefore, on the basis of the previous
      retrospective analysis, the optimal NAR cut-off value was calculated according to ROC curve,
      and the value was grouped into multi-center prospective cohort study, and the relationship
      between NAR and other clinical indicators was studied by chi-square test. Univariate and
      multivariate analysis of Cox proportional hazard regression model was used to determine the
      prognostic factors. Finally, NSCLC patients were stratified according to tumor stage and
      pathological classification, and the differences of survival time between high NAR group and
      low NAR group were compared again under different stages and types, and the different stages
      of NAR in NSCLC patients were further analyzed. The clinical significance of typing. By
      exploring and validating the relationship between NAR and the prognosis of NSCLC patients,
      the investigators try to establish a new prognostic index. Obviously, it has important value
      for clinical application.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>The time from randomization to death due to any cause. The last follow-up time is usually calculated as the time of death for those who have been lost before death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Refers to the time from randomization to relapse or death due to disease progression. It is usually the end point after radical surgery. DFS is more difficult to record as an end point than OS because it requires careful follow-up and timely detection of disease recurrence. In this study, as an important prognostic indicator for patients undergoing NSCLC surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">202</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high NAR</arm_group_label>
    <description>Neuron-Specific Enolase to Albumin Ratio is higher than 3.2×10-7</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>low NAR</arm_group_label>
    <description>Neuron-Specific Enolase to Albumin Ratio is lower than 3.2×10-7</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuron-Specific Enolase to Albumin Ratio</intervention_name>
    <description>Previous studies have shown that inflammation and nutrition-related factors such as CRP/Alb (C-reactive protein-albumin ratio), PLR (platelet-to-lymphocyte ratio), NLR (neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio) can help to assess the prognosis of malignant tumors. This study is the first time to combine NSCLC tumor marker NSE and patient nutrition-related indicators Alb to predict the prognosis of patients, trying to find high sensitivity and specificity for NSCLC prognostic indicators to guide clinical work.</description>
    <arm_group_label>high NAR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>low NAR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Sample sources: Xi'an Jiaotong University First Affiliated Hospital, Second Affiliated
        Hospital, Shaanxi Provincial People's Hospital, Shaanxi Provincial Cancer Hospital and
        other hospitals.

        Subject recruitment process:

          1. Subject screening: Subjects were screened according to inclusion and exclusion
             criteria.

          2. Recruitment of the research subject: In the course of clinical diagnosis and
             treatment, the competent doctor recruits.

          3. Subject informed consent: inform patients to collect their clinical data and follow up
             for clinical studies, signing informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) pathological diagnosis of non-small cell lung cancer

          -  (2) 18-70 years of age and no gender restriction.

          -  (3) patients who were admitted for the first time and underwent routine blood tests,
             three lung cancer and liver function tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) pregnant or lactating women

          -  (2) patients with other malignancies at the same time

          -  (3) patients with acute and chronic inflammation, autoimmune diseases, and patients
             with obvious liver and renal insufficiency.

          -  (4) patients with incomplete clinical and pathological data.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sida Qin, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sida Qin, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+8615829916265</phone>
    <email>sida.qin@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First hospital affiliated Xi'an jiaotong university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shaanxi</state>
        <zip>710061</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sida Qin</last_name>
      <phone>+8615829916265</phone>
      <email>sida.qin@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neuron-Specific Enolase</keyword>
  <keyword>Albumin</keyword>
  <keyword>Prognostic Biomarker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

