<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03722537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAR9273</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03722537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Osteochondral Allograft in the Surgical Treatment of Basal Joint Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Osteochondral Allograft in the Surgical Treatment of Basal Joint Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study comparing the current standard of care surgical treatment to a newer surgical
      procedure involving the implantation of osteochondral allograft at the base of the thumb.
      Patients will be followed at 1, 3, 6 months and 1 year post-operatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Basal joint arthritis of the thumb is a common condition associated with considerable
      morbidity. Many non-operative and operative treatments have been described, but few
      multicenter prospective evidence based trials exist comparing standard treatments. This
      continuing search for consensus and improvement of best clinical practice has been reviewed
      in a thorough meta-analysis of operative treatments for basal joint arthritis. Operative
      treatments range from osteotomy, partial or complete trapeziectomy with or without
      reconstruction of the ligaments, tendon interposition to arthrodesis, however the functional
      outcome varies. Allograft has been previously described in joint replacement / prosthetic
      implantation surgery in other areas of the body, however not in the thumb. The purpose of
      this study is to investigate using osteochondral allograft in the surgical intervention phase
      of treatment for patients with basal joint arthritis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand (DASH) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>The DASH (Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand) is a 30-item questionnaire that includes 21 physical function items, 6 symptom items, and 3 social/role function items used to evaluate a patient's ability to perform upper extremity activities. Higher scores indicate a greater level of disability and severity, whereas, lower scores indicate a lower level of disability. The score on both test ranges from 0 (no disability) to 100 (most severe disability).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the Thumb Disability Exam (TDX)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>The TDX is a questionnaire that measures changes in thumb function and pain, specifically for those with basal joint arthritis.The TDX is scored on a scale of 0 to 100, with a higher score indicating a greater degree of disability in the thumb.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale for pain (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year post-operatively</time_frame>
    <description>The VAS is a validated technique that measures acute and chronic pain. Using a ruler, the score is determined by measuring the distance (mm) on the 10-cm line between the &quot;no pain&quot; anchor and the patient's mark, providing a range of scores from 0-100. A higher score indicates greater pain intensity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Basal Joint Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ligament Reconstruction Tendon Interposition (LRTI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Selected randomly, 100 patients will receive this treatment. During the LRTI (standard of care procedure), the arthritic bone that the thumb rests on (the trapezium) is removed. A small cut is made in the forearm to release a tendon, which is moved to the base of the thumb to fill in the area from which the trapezium bone was removed. A small suture anchor is then placed into a thumb bone which holds everything together.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Osteochondral Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Selected randomly,100 patients will receive this treatment. In this procedure, the arthritic bone that the thumb rests on (the trapezium) is removed and replaced with femoral trochlear osteochondral allograft that is designed to be similar in morphology to the human trapezium articular surface, known as the 'Cartibend©' .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Osteochondral Allograft</intervention_name>
    <description>The arthritic bone that the thumb rests on (the trapezium) is removed and replaced with femoral trochlear osteochondral allograft that is designed to be similar in morphology to the human trapezium articular surface.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Osteochondral Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cartibend</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ligament Reconstruction Tendon Interposition</intervention_name>
    <description>During the LRTI, the arthritic bone that the thumb rests on (the trapezium) is removed. A small cut is made in the forearm to release a tendon, which is moved to the base of the thumb to fill in the area from which the trapezium bone was removed. A small suture anchor is then placed into a thumb bone which holds everything together.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ligament Reconstruction Tendon Interposition (LRTI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Indicated for operative management of basal joint arthritis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women/fetuses/neonates, prisoners

          -  Previously operated on for treatment of basal joint arthritis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melvin P Rosenwasser, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Seth Shoap</last_name>
    <phone>484-392-3255</phone>
    <email>scs2217@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Melvin Rosenwasser</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Robert E. Carroll Professor of Surgery of the Hand</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Allograft</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteochondral Allograft</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

