<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03729544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018P001681</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03729544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Computerized Decision Support to Increase Detection of Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension in Patients With Prior Pulmonary Embolism</brief_title>
  <acronym>CTEPH-DETECT</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of Electronic Alert-Based Computerized Decision Support to Increase Detection of Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension in Patients With Prior Pulmonary Embolism (CTEPH-DETECT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To address the knowledge gap that exists among providers resulting in underdiagnosis of
      chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH), the investigators have devised this
      400-patient single-center Quality Improvement Initiative in the form of a randomized
      controlled trial of an EPIC Best Practice Advisory (BPA) on-screen alert versus no
      notification to increase echocardiographic screening for CTEPH and the diagnosis of CTEPH in
      patients with prior pulmonary embolism (PE) and symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary
      hypertension or recent pulmonary testing suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms at 3
      months.

      Aim #1: To determine the impact of a Best Practice Advisory (BPA), using the EPIC Electronic
      Health Record computerized decision support (CDS) software, on echocardiographic screening
      for CTEPH in patient with prior PE and symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary hypertension or
      recent pulmonary testing suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms.

      Aim #2: To determine the impact of an EPIC BPA on the diagnosis of CTEPH in patient with
      prior PE and symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary hypertension or recent pulmonary testing
      suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design: 400-patient single-center Quality Improvement Initiative in the form of a
      randomized controlled trial. The allocation ratio will be 1:1 for an EPIC Best Practice
      Advisory (BPA) on-screen alert versus no notification. Investigators will be assessing the
      impact of the EPIC BPA on echocardiographic screening for chronic thromboembolic pulmonary
      hypertension (CTEPH) and the diagnosis of CTEPH in the patients enrolled in this Quality
      Improvement Initiative. While investigators will randomize patients by Attending Physician of
      Record to minimize cluster-effect, the observational unit will be the patient.

      Type of control : The control group will have no electronic alert notification issued to the
      responsible provider.

      Number of subjects: 400 subjects will be enrolled with 200 subjects to be randomized to the
      alert group and 200 subjects to the control group in a 1:1 allocation ratio.

      Primary Efficacy Outcome: Frequency of echocardiographic screening for CTEPH in patients with
      prior pulmonary embolism (PE) and symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary hypertension or
      recent pulmonary testing suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms at 3 months.
      Investigators will review the order entry and cardiology test results sections of the
      Electronic Health Record (EPIC) to make this determination.

      Secondary Efficacy Outcome: Frequency of CTEPH diagnosis at 3 months. The diagnosis of CTEPH
      will be confirmed by clinical notation in the EHR or a mean pulmonary-artery pressure greater
      than 25 mmHg that persists 6 months after PE diagnosis.

      Safety Outcomes: Because there is no reasonable expectation for adverse events or patient
      safety concerns with this Quality Improvement Initiative focused on increasing provider
      awareness about the risk of CTEPH and the indication for screening with echocardiography,
      investigators will not collect any safety outcomes or variables.

      Plan for statistical analysis: The primary statistical analysis will be the comparison of the
      frequency of echocardiographic screening for CTEPH in the alert group compared with the
      control (no alert) group. A secondary statistical analysis will be the comparison of the
      frequency of CTEPH diagnosis in the alert group compared with the control (no alert) group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>400-patient single-center Quality Improvement Initiative in the form of a randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>The allocation ratio will be 1:1 for an EPIC BPA on-screen alert versus no notification. Investigators will be assessing the impact of the EPIC BPA on echocardiographic screening for CTEPH and the diagnosis of CTEPH in the patients enrolled in this Quality Improvement Initiative. While investigators will randomize patients by Attending Physician of Record to minimize cluster-effect, the observational unit will be the patient. The cluster-effect describes a type of confounding observed in studies of provider behavior that can result in a bias of the outcome toward the null. In such a case, a provider may carry over knowledge gained from the alert for the intervention group patient to the care of the control group patient.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of echocardiographic screening for CTEPH in patients with prior PE and symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary hypertension or recent pulmonary testing suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms at 3 months following randomization.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will review the Provider Order Entry and cardiology test results sections of the Electronic Health Record (EPIC) to make this determination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of CTEPH diagnosis at three months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The diagnosis of CTEPH will be confirmed by clinical notation in the EHR or a mean pulmonary artery pressure greater than 25 mmHg that persists 6 months after PE diagnosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alert</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>On-screen computerized decision support alert during the outpatient clinical encounter that notifies the provider that the patient should be screened for CTEPH</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Alert</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No provider notification</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>On-screen computerized decision support alert</intervention_name>
    <description>On-screen electronic alert during the outpatient clinical encounter that notifies him or her that the patient should be screened for CTEPH</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alert</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BWH outpatient

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Evaluated in Primary Care or Cardiovascular Medicine Clinic

          -  Persistent or new symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary hypertension [syncope,
             malaise and fatigue, dyspnea, exercise intolerance, hemoptysis, chest pain,
             dizziness/vertigo, gait abnormality, cardiomegaly, ascites, and peripheral edema] OR
             recent pulmonary testing (pulmonary function tests [PFTs], chest X-ray, or chest CT)
             suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms at least 6 months from the diagnosis of PE

          -  Have not undergone echocardiography within the prior 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Absence of persistent or new symptoms/signs suggestive of pulmonary hypertension OR
             recent pulmonary testing (pulmonary function tests [PFTs], chest X-ray, or chest CT)
             suggesting unexplained respiratory symptoms

          -  PE within the last 6 months

          -  Echocardiogram or invasive hemodynamic assessment with the prior 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory Piazza, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>BWH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gregory Piazza, MD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>6177326984</phone>
    <email>gpiazza@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Claire E Galvin, BS</last_name>
    <phone>6177326984</phone>
    <email>cegalvin@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gregory Piazza, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-307-1932</phone>
      <email>gpiazza@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Piazza, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samuel Z Goldhaber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piazza G, Goldhaber SZ. Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jan 27;364(4):351-60. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra0910203. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21268727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Samuel Z.Goldhaber, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Interim Chief of Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>echocardiography</keyword>
  <keyword>pulmonary embolism</keyword>
  <keyword>pulmonary hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>screening</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

