<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03721003</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IPMISTBISCE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03721003</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intracranial Pressure Monitoring in Sever Traumatic Brain Injury Single Center Experience</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intracranial Pressure Monitoring in Sever Traumatic Brain Injury Single Centre Experience</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial pressure (ICP) is defined as the pressure inside the skull, and therefore, the
      pressure inside the brain tissue and the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). The relationship between
      CSF and intracranial blood volumes is described by the Monroe Kellie doctrine; because the
      brain is incompressible, when the skull is intact, the sum of the volumes of brain, CSF, and
      intracranial blood is constant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ICP &gt;15 mmHg is considered to be elevated, and this is considered an important cause of
      secondary injury leading to irreversible brain injury and death. ICP monitoring is used in a
      number of conditions; traumatic brain injury, intracerebral haemorrhage, subarachnoid
      haemorrhage, hydrocephalus, malignant infarction, cerebral oedema, CNS infections, hepatic
      encephalopathy, to name a few, and in all of these conditions ICP monitoring in the light of
      other parameters can influence management for better outcomes.

      There are 4 ways to monitor intracranial pressure:

        1. An intra-parenchymal method, the catheter is placed into the brain parenchyma through a
           burr hole; it has a lower complication rate, lower infection rate, and no chance of
           catheter occlusion or leakage. Neurological injury is minimized because of the small
           diameter of the probe. In addition, malposition of the transducer has less impact on
           errors of measurement.

        2. An intra-ventricular method, the catheter is placed into one of the ventricles (lat.
           Ventricle). The catheter can also be used for therapeutic CSF drainage and for
           administration of drugs.

        3. Subdural method, this method is used if monitoring needs to be done right away. A hollow
           screw is inserted through a burr hole and placed through the Dura mater.

        4. An epidural sensor is inserted between the skull and dural tissue. This procedure is
           less invasive than other methods.

      ICP monitoring methods is associated with a number of complications. These include risk of
      infection, haemorrhage, obstruction, difficulty in placement, malposition, etc.

      The use of an ICP monitor is associated with significantly lower mortality when compared with
      patients treated without an ICP monitor
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>analyse role of ICP monitoring of patient with diffuse traumatic brain injury</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>study the significance of application of ICP monitor on outcome of patients with diffuse traumatic brain injury using glascow coma scale The Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) is a neurological scale which aims to give a reliable and objective way of recording the conscious state of a person for initial as well as subsequent assessment. A patient is assessed against the criteria of the scale, and the resulting points give a patient score between 3 (indicating deep unconsciousness) and either 14 (original scale) or 15 (more widely used modified or revised scale)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Head Injury Trauma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ICP monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>4- Use the Touhy needle to tunnel under the scalp from the Burr Hole site to the desired MICROSENSOR exit site.
5- Place the tip of the MICROSENSOR in the Parenchyma through the puncture in the Dura</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        history of present illness will be taken clinical assesment will be done ct brain will be
        done after that ICP monitor will be applied
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt;18

          2. GCS &lt; 8

          3. patient with severe brain insult ( Marshall class II to IV)

          4. patients admitted within 24 hours from the trauma time

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients admitted for surgery (ex; surgical EDH) .

          2. patient diagnosed as brain death
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mosab Samir</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Craniocerebral Trauma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

