<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03854877</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FinnishIOH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03854877</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>DagisWork-a Workplace Health Behaviour E-intervention</brief_title>
  <acronym>DagisWork</acronym>
  <official_title>DagisWork - Improved Health Behaviour and Wellbeing: a Randomized Controlled Workplace Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Helsinki</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Jyvaskyla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main aim of the study is to test effectiveness of a multiple intervention program aimed
      at making positive changes to health behaviour and stress. Effectiveness of a 4 month
      workplace intervention, with virtual coaching and co-worker-support, will be assessed as
      changes in subjective and objective measures of stress, work ability, recovery and health
      behaviour.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Consequences of psychosocial stress can be seen in personnel's health such as long lasting
      imbalance between consumptive and restoring physiological processes (allostatic load, AL)
      that increase the risk of physical diseases and mental health problems and poor health
      behaviours. Chronic work stress induces adverse emotional and physical responses, which are
      triggered by perception of demands that exceed the person's capacity to cope (Folkman et al.
      1986).

      Health behaviour can be improved both by increasing personnel's' resources and removing
      stress-causing factors (Lamontagne et al. 2007). Mindfulness based cognitive therapy aims at
      increasing stress resources by developing emotional and behavioral experiences. It combines
      aspects of cognitive approach including dialectic behavior therapy and Acceptance and
      Commitment Therapy (ACT). Mindfulness and acceptance-based interventions have positive
      consequences for physical activity and quality of life (Kangasniemi et al. 2015, Khoury et
      al. 2015). Novel results suggest that the approach is effective to reduce work stress also
      (Aikens et al. 2014). A four month intervention with virtual life habit coaching,
      individualised exercises and mindfulness-based techniques will be performed. The aim is to
      achieve significant and long lasting changes in life habits and stress of employees.

      The extensive measurements including both self-evaluated and objective measurements together
      with multifaceted viewpoint provide profound knowledge of occupational health. They also
      create a comprehensive picture of preschool setting as an arena for healthy lifestyle and
      well-being. A new issue is the concert of different kinds of work load factors, and their
      interacting role in biomarkers for work stress. If proven effective, the health behaviour
      intervention tested in preschool environment, can be modified to suit also other occupational
      settings. The health economic evaluation, together with aforementioned measurement, offer
      information for different stakeholders on whether interventions are economically worthwhile
      for participating municipalities and occupational health care. The results of study are
      beneficial also for policy-makers in different sectors.

      Aims and hypotheses Primary hypotheses

        1. The intervention has a positive effects on long-term physiological adaptation to stress,
           biological health risk factors, recovery, and sickness absences among personnel.

        2. The interventions directly enhance personnel's health behavior including eating habits,
           physical activity and experienced stress.

      Secondary hypotheses

        1. The physiological change in stress regulating systems caused by work related factors
           (psychosocial, cognitive, and physical) is associated with personnel's change health
           risk load (AL) and recovery.

        2. Subjective psychological and cognitive factors of stress, recovery and even mental
           health symptoms are individually related to physiological responses, which can be
           characterized more precisely by the combined assessment of hormonal, neuronal responses
           and new methods of system biology.

        3. The intervention will have positive economic effect (costs and benefits).

        4. The intervention will have positive changes in self-efficasy
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cluster randomized two group behavioral intervention</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Allostatic load (AL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in stress after four months</time_frame>
    <description>Allostatic load (AL) (allostatic load and allostatic overload refers to the cumulative result of an allostatic state) is measured by the following primary and secondary markers: salivary cortisol (µg/dl) heart rate variability measurement [RMSSD, (ms)], (hsCRP (mg/l), HbA1c (mmol/mol), triglycerides (mmol/l). Salivary cortisol is the mean of morning and evening samples (Aardal, E.&amp;Holm, A. 1995), (RMSSD is the value on recovery during sleeping (First_beat Manual 2014). Clinical cutoff values are used for salivary cortisol, hsCRP, HbA1c and triglycerides and age-reference value (HUSLAB Manual 2018). All markers are dichotomized (0 = below the clinical or age-reference; 1= exceeds the clinical or age-reference). Total Allostatic load is calculated as the sum of all measures (range 0 to 5) (Altman et. al.1986). Total Allostatic load we shown before and after the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in stress after four months</time_frame>
    <description>General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-12). The scale includes 12 items. The four response choices (0 &quot;Not at all&quot;, 1 &quot;Same as usual&quot;, 2 &quot;Rather more than usual&quot; and 3 &quot;Much more than usual&quot;) will be dichotomized as follows: 1=0, 2=1, 3=2, 4=3. GHQ-12 case ≥ 3 points (range 0-36). The higher values indicate higher psychological symptoms. The reference mean value is 10.3 (SD 5.0) points (Holi, Marttunen, Aalberg 2003).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic benefits</measure>
    <time_frame>Sickness absence absence [ (Time Frame: approx. 3 years (from 2016 to 2019) ]</time_frame>
    <description>Length (1-365 days/year) of sickness absence and frequency of sickness absence episodes (i.e. frequency of all sickness absence periods within year) obtained from employer records, including dates of absence due to sickness without medical cause information.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intuitive eating</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months</time_frame>
    <description>The Intuitive Eating Scale, 21-items. All items are rated on a five point Likert-scale (1 totally disagree, 5 totally agree). The sum of all items indicates the level of eating habits. Higher values indicate better eating habits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating habits</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months.</time_frame>
    <description>The three factor eating questionnaire-R 18 (TFEQ-18). All items of the three factors (cognitive restraint, uncontrolled eating, emotional eating) are rated on a four point Likert- scale (1 definitely true, 4 definitely false). Higher values indicate higher cognitive restraint, uncontrolled eating and emotional eating.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measured physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months</time_frame>
    <description>Accelerometer. Average number of steps per week, at least five days and 10 hours data/day. The program counts the physical activity time in different levels (inactive, light, moderate and heavy). The higher number of steps indicate higher physical activity as well as the moderate or heavy activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Work ability</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months</time_frame>
    <description>Question on the current Work Ability (WA) compared with the lifetime best is assessed using one item with a response scale from 0 not able to work at all to 10, my best work ability ever. The result are reported as mean and classification. The higher value is better work ability (Seitsamo et al. 2011).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive failures at work</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months</time_frame>
    <description>Workplace cognitive failure scale (WCFS) (Wallace &amp; Chen, 2005). The 15 items of the scale are rated on a 5-point scale (1 =never to 5=several times per day) and sum up to total WCF. All items are summed -up to total WCFS. The higher value indicates more cognitive failures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months</time_frame>
    <description>The Self-efficacy beliefs questionnaire (Scharzer &amp; Renner 2000). External and internal attribute. The scale are rated on a 5-point scale (1 =never to 5=several times per day). All items are summed-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after four months</time_frame>
    <description>The Jenkins sleep questionnaire. Four items of the scale are rated on a 6-point scale (1= never to 6 = every night). All items are summed-up. The higher value means more problems in sleeping (Jenkins et al 1988).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health behaviour intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Personalised health behaviour e-health intervention. The intervention uses the principles of acceptance-commitment therapy (ACT). It aims to promote health habits. Based on personal needs participants can choose tasks for physical activity, relaxation, healthy eating, sleep etc. They get regular feedback, tasks and support from their personal trainer via phone and computer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Only before and after measurements</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health behaviour intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention uses the principles of acceptance-commitment therapy (ACT). It aims to increase healthy eating and good sleep. Based on personal needs participants can choose task for physical activity, relaxation, healthy eating, sleep eg. Their get regular feedback and support from their personal trainer via phone and computer.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health behaviour intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Voluntary

          -  Working in municipal city of Espoo or Kouvola in preschool

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Retirement during the intervention
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>68 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sampsa Puttonen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <state>Uusimaa</state>
        <zip>00250</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health behaviour</keyword>
  <keyword>Work place intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>e-health</keyword>
  <keyword>Mindfulness</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

