<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03856840</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018/0181</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03856840</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cytokines in Blister Fluids of Bullous Pemphigoid (BP)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BP</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Cytokines and Immunoglobulins in Serum and Blister Fluids Appeared Before Treatment and Subsequently Under Treatment in Bullous Pemphigoid</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mahmut Can Koska</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istanbul Medeniyet University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigates the differences of Eosinophil Cationic Protein, Tumor Necrosis
      Factor-alpha and Anti-BP180-NC16A IgG levels of blister fluids in Bullous Pemphigoid patients
      which appeared before and under treatment subsequently. These molecules will also be measured
      in blood serum before and under treatment. Changes of titers in serum and differences between
      blister fluids will be compared to observe whether correlation exists between them. These
      measures will also be compared between groups of responders and non-responders to the
      first-line treatment options to analyze correlation with treatment success.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bullous Pemphigoid is an auto-immune bullous disorder in which auto-antibodies to
      hemidesmosomes, complement pathway, inflammatory cells and mediators play a crucial roles for
      disease pathogenesis.

      Anti-BP180-NC16A IgG is an antibody that it primarily triggers inflammatory reactions and
      complement cascade in bullae development and plays major roles in disease pathogenesis. It is
      secreted by plasma cells which is induced by T-helper 2 cells and their cytokines in serum
      and lesional tissue. Anti-BP180 antibody detection in serum is very important in diagnosis
      and titers correlate with disease activity. Anti-BP180 antibody can also be detected in
      blister fluids and it may aid diagnosis.

      Eosinophil cationic Protein is a cytokine and secreted by Eosinophil which is found in
      abundant numbers and correlated with tissue damage in Bullous Pemphigoid lesions. Serum
      titers of Eosinophil Cationic Protein has a correlation with disease activity and it is
      higher in blister fluid than serum. Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha is an another cytokine which
      is secreted from inflammatory cells initially after inflammatory cascade is triggered. It is
      also found increased in serum blister fluids. Tumor necrosis factor-alpha is associated with
      clinical severity in bullous pemphigoid.

      In Bullous Pemphigoid, development of bulla is required to be stopped if treatment will be
      considered as successful. Nevertheless smaller, more rapidly healing vesicles and bullae
      appear under treatment which are not regarded as findings of treatment failure. In this study
      we will measure Eosinophil Cationic Protein, Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha and Anti-BP180-NC16A
      IgG levels with E.L.I.S.A. technique in these subsequently appeared blisters if they will
      appear and compare them with pretreatment blisters. We will also measure levels of these
      molecules in blood serum before and under treatment. We will analyze corralation between
      blood serum and blister fluids. Also we will compare responder patients and non-responder
      patients to first-line treatment options to observe correlation of changes and differences in
      these body fluids with treatment success.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 29, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 27, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 23, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Month</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Titers of Eosinophil Cationic Protein in blister fluid and blood serum</measure>
    <time_frame>14 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated of measurements of Eosinophil Cationic Protein (pg/ml) by ELISA technique in blister fluids and serums that obtained before treatment and under first and second weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Titers of Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha in blister fluid and blood serum</measure>
    <time_frame>14 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated of measurements of Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha (pg/ml) by ELISA technique in blister fluids and serums that obtained before treatment and under first and second weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Titers of Anti-BP180-NC18A IgG in blister fluid and blood serum</measure>
    <time_frame>14 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated of measurements of Anti-BP180-NC18A IgG (U/ml) by ELISA technique in blister fluids and serums that obtained before treatment and under first and second weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to control of disease activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time interval between initiation of treatment and control of disease activity/beginning of consolidation phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consolidation phase of Outcome Measures for Bullous Pemphigoid</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time interval between control of disease activity and end of consolidation phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Failure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 week</time_frame>
    <description>Development of nontransient lesions that heal in more than one week, continued extension of old lesions, failure of established lesions to begin to heal or continued pruritus despite of Treatment of one month.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse/Flare</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>Appearance of more than three lesions per month or at least one large eczematous lesion or urticarial plaques that do not heal within one week, or extension of established lesions or daily pruritus in patient who was achieved disease control</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bullous Pemphigoid disease severity assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>One day</time_frame>
    <description>This assessment will depend on multiple factors according to more than one classification. Patients will be separated to mild, moderate, severe conditions according to their clinical findings.
Mild: Involvement of less than %10 of skin surface area and appearance of less than 10 bullae in each day. Both feature will be necessary to regard individual patient's disease as mild.
Moderate: Involvement of %10-30 of skin surface area and appearance of less than 10 bullae in each day. Both feature will be necessary to regard individual patient's disease as moderate.
Severe: Involvement of more than %30 of skin surface area or appearance of more than 10 bullae in each day or B.P.D.A.I. score more than 56 (without Visual analogue score of pruritus). Existence of even one of this findings will ve sufficient to regard individual patient's disease as severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bullous Pemphigoid Disease Area Index (B.P.D.A.I.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>BPDAI is an index to assess disease area and severity depending on involvement of mucosa and skin region, lesion number and size. Minimum score is 0 and maximum score is 360.
This index will be calculated at before treatment, second week and fourth week of treatment. After first month it will be calculated in each follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bullous Pemphigoid Disease Area Index (B.P.D.A.I.)-Damage score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>Scars of previous lesions are also included to this index, minimum score is 0 and maximum score is 12.
This index will be calculated at before treatment, second week and fourth week of treatment. After first month it will be calculated in each follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bullous Pemphigoid Disease Area Index (B.P.D.A.I.)-Pruritus score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analogue score of pruritus is also part of this index. Minimum score is 0 and maximum score is 10. This score will be assessed for last 24 hours, last one week, last one month one by one; thus maximum score will be 30.
This index will be calculated at before treatment, second week and fourth week of treatment. After first month it will be calculated in each follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Pemphigoid, Bullous</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bullous Pemphigoid Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Bullae and blood serum, which are obtained before and under treatment, will be compared in each other regardless of any condition.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blister Fluid: Blister fluids will be obtained from all enrolled patients in specific three
      intervals: Before treatment, 4-7. and 8-14. days of treatment in 24 hours after they appear.

      Bullae of only one individual day will be selected for each interval to study if they
      appeared.

      Blood Serum: Blood serum will be obtained from all enrolled patients before treatment,
      seventh day of treatment and fourteen day of treatment.

      Obtaining blood serum from patients was added to study afterward. New ethical committee
      approval was received for that modification in recruitment status at May 17, 2018. Thus blood
      serum weren't obtained patients who were recruited before that approval. But other specimens
      obtained from these patients will be included study.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All Bullous Pemphigoid patients presented to concerning clinics who accept the terms and
        definitions and sign consent form.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patiens presented to clinics who is diagnosed with Bullous Pemphigoid by findings
             of clinical, histopathological, Direct Immunoflorescent evaluation.

          -  All relapsed/flared Bullous Pemphigoid patients.

          -  Patients who accept the terms and conditions and sign consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are received treatment before presenting clinics where the study is
             conducted.

          -  Patients who reject to join to study and the terms and condition

          -  Patients who leave the study by own decision
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mehmet Salih Gurel, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul Medeniyet University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul Medeniyet University Goztepe Training and Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Kadikoy</state>
        <zip>37722</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul Training and Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>İstanbul</city>
        <state>Samatya</state>
        <zip>34098</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernard P, Antonicelli F. Bullous Pemphigoid: A Review of its Diagnosis, Associations and Treatment. Am J Clin Dermatol. 2017 Aug;18(4):513-528. doi: 10.1007/s40257-017-0264-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28247089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bağcı IS, Horváth ON, Ruzicka T, Sárdy M. Bullous pemphigoid. Autoimmun Rev. 2017 May;16(5):445-455. doi: 10.1016/j.autrev.2017.03.010. Epub 2017 Mar 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28286109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt E, Zillikens D. Pemphigoid diseases. Lancet. 2013 Jan 26;381(9863):320-32. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61140-4. Epub 2012 Dec 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23237497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt E, della Torre R, Borradori L. Clinical features and practical diagnosis of bullous pemphigoid. Dermatol Clin. 2011 Jul;29(3):427-38, viii-ix. doi: 10.1016/j.det.2011.03.010. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21605808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marzano AV, Tedeschi A, Fanoni D, Bonanni E, Venegoni L, Berti E, Cugno M. Activation of blood coagulation in bullous pemphigoid: role of eosinophils, and local and systemic implications. Br J Dermatol. 2009 Feb;160(2):266-72. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2133.2008.08880.x. Epub 2008 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18945300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engineer L, Bhol K, Kumari S, Razzaque Ahmed A. Bullous pemphigoid: interaction of interleukin 5, anti-basement membrane zone antibodies and eosinophils. A preliminary observation. . Cytokine. 2001 Jan 7;13(1):32-38.</citation>
    <PMID>11145840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Provost TT, Tomasi TB Jr. Immunopathology of bullous pemphigoid. Basement membrane deposition of IgE, alternate pathway components and fibrin. Clin Exp Immunol. 1974 Oct;18(2):193-200.</citation>
    <PMID>4619597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Auria L, Pimpinelli F, Ferraro C, D'Ambrogio G, Giacalone B, Bellocci M, Ameglio F. Relationship between theoretical molecular weight and blister fluid/serum ratio of cytokines and five other molecules evaluated in patients with bullous pemphigoid. J Biol Regul Homeost Agents. 1998 Jul-Sep;12(3):76-80.</citation>
    <PMID>9795835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giusti D, Gatouillat G, Le Jan S, Plée J, Bernard P, Antonicelli F, Pham BN. Eosinophil Cationic Protein (ECP), a predictive marker of bullous pemphigoid severity and outcome. Sci Rep. 2017 Jul 6;7(1):4833. doi: 10.1038/s41598-017-04687-5.</citation>
    <PMID>28684769</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tedeschi A, Marzano AV, Lorini M, Balice Y, Cugno M. Eosinophil cationic protein levels parallel coagulation activation in the blister fluid of patients with bullous pemphigoid. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2015 Apr;29(4):813-7. doi: 10.1111/jdv.12464. Epub 2014 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24650303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Auria L, Pietravalle M, Mastroianni A, Ferraro C, Mussi A, Bonifati C, Giacalone B, Ameglio F. IL-5 levels in the serum and blister fluid of patients with bullous pemphigoid: correlations with eosinophil cationic protein, RANTES, IgE and disease severity. Arch Dermatol Res. 1998 Jan-Feb;290(1-2):25-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9522998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dierksmeier U, Frosch PJ, Czarnetzki BM. Eosinophil chemotactic factor (ECF) in blister fluid of dermatological diseases. Br J Dermatol. 1980 Jan;102(1):43-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6990957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ameglio F, D'Auria L, Cordiali-Fei P, Mussi A, Valenzano L, D'Agosto G, Ferraro C, Bonifati C, Giacalone B. Bullous pemphigoid and pemphigus vulgaris: correlated behaviour of serum VEGF, sE-selectin and TNF-alpha levels. J Biol Regul Homeost Agents. 1997 Oct-Dec;11(4):148-53.</citation>
    <PMID>9582615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murrell DF, Daniel BS, Joly P, Borradori L, Amagai M, Hashimoto T, Caux F, Marinovic B, Sinha AA, Hertl M, Bernard P, Sirois D, Cianchini G, Fairley JA, Jonkman MF, Pandya AG, Rubenstein D, Zillikens D, Payne AS, Woodley D, Zambruno G, Aoki V, Pincelli C, Diaz L, Hall RP, Meurer M, Mascaro JM Jr, Schmidt E, Shimizu H, Zone J, Swerlick R, Mimouni D, Culton D, Lipozencic J, Bince B, Grando SA, Bystryn JC, Werth VP. Definitions and outcome measures for bullous pemphigoid: recommendations by an international panel of experts. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2012 Mar;66(3):479-85. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2011.06.032. Epub 2011 Nov 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22056920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eming R, Sticherling M, Hofmann SC, Hunzelmann N, Kern JS, Kramer H, Pfeiffer C, Schuster V, Zillikens D, Goebeler M, Hertl M, Nast A, Orzechowski HD, Sárdy M, Schmidt E, Sitaru C, Sporbeck B, Worm M. S2k guidelines for the treatment of pemphigus vulgaris/foliaceus and bullous pemphigoid. J Dtsch Dermatol Ges. 2015 Aug;13(8):833-44. doi: 10.1111/ddg.12606.</citation>
    <PMID>26213827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao CY, Murrell DF. Advances in understanding and managing bullous pemphigoid. F1000Res. 2015 Nov 20;4. pii: F1000 Faculty Rev-1313. doi: 10.12688/f1000research.6896.1. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26918143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lévy-Sitbon C, Barbe C, Plee J, Goeldel AL, Antonicelli F, Reguiaï Z, Jolly D, Grange F, Bernard P. Assessment of bullous pemphigoid disease area index during treatment: a prospective study of 30 patients. Dermatology. 2014;229(2):116-22. doi: 10.1159/000362717. Epub 2014 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25011586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joly P, Roujeau JC, Benichou J, Delaporte E, D'Incan M, Dreno B, Bedane C, Sparsa A, Gorin I, Picard C, Tancrede-Bohin E, Sassolas B, Lok C, Guillaume JC, Doutre MS, Richard MA, Caux F, Prost C, Plantin P, Chosidow O, Pauwels C, Maillard H, Saiag P, Descamps V, Chevrant-Breton J, Dereure O, Hellot MF, Esteve E, Bernard P. A comparison of two regimens of topical corticosteroids in the treatment of patients with bullous pemphigoid: a multicenter randomized study. J Invest Dermatol. 2009 Jul;129(7):1681-7. doi: 10.1038/jid.2008.412. Epub 2009 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>19177141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feliciani C, Joly P, Jonkman MF, Zambruno G, Zillikens D, Ioannides D, Kowalewski C, Jedlickova H, Kárpáti S, Marinovic B, Mimouni D, Uzun S, Yayli S, Hertl M, Borradori L. Management of bullous pemphigoid: the European Dermatology Forum consensus in collaboration with the European Academy of Dermatology and Venereology. Br J Dermatol. 2015 Apr;172(4):867-77. doi: 10.1111/bjd.13717.</citation>
    <PMID>25827742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istanbul Medeniyet University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mahmut Can Koska</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pemphigoid, Bullous</keyword>
  <keyword>Bullous Pemphigoid</keyword>
  <keyword>Blister Fluid</keyword>
  <keyword>Eosinophil Cationic Protein</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-BP180</keyword>
  <keyword>Disease activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Disease severity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pemphigoid, Bullous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blister</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

