<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03859414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLI-05993AB4-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-003310-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03859414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PK of BDP/FF/GB Single-inhaler Triple Therapy in Japanese vs. Caucasians</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-center, Randomized, Double-blind, Single Dose, 4-way Cross-over, Placebo-controlled Ethnic Sensitivity Study to Assess the Pharmacokinetics (PK), Pharmacodynamics (PD), Safety, and Tolerability of Different Dosages of CHF 5993 Pressurized Metered Dose Inhaler (pMDI) in Caucasian and Japanese Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chiesi Farmaceutici S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chiesi Farmaceutici S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of conducting this study is to obtain PK data of Beclometasone Dipropionate
      (BDP)/Beclometasone-17-MonoPropionate (B17MP), Formoterol Fumarate (FF) and Glycopyrronium
      Bromide (GB) after inhalation of CHF 5993 in Japanese as well as Caucasian healthy subjects
      under the same setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study is single-centre, randomized, double-blind, single-dose, 4-way cross-over,
      placebo-controlled.

      The safety, tolerability, PD and PK of CHF 5993 will be assessed in Japanese and Caucasian
      healthy volunteers.

      A total of 32 healthy male and female volunteers are planned to be included where they will
      receive four different treatments (study drug or placebo) over four treatment periods.

      Standard safety assessments will be conducted during the study, including safety blood and
      urine laboratory tests, liver function tests, vital signs, physical examinations, ECGs,
      24-hour Holter and observations of any adverse events. Blood samples will also be collected
      for PK analysis. Blood and urine samples will be collected for pharmacodynamics analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 24, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 24, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>4-way Crossover Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve (AUC) of B17MP, formoterol and GB</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration for B17MP and FF, over 48 hours after administration for GB</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum of Concentration (Cmax) of B17MP, FF and GB</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration for B17MP and FF, over 48 hours after administration for GB</time_frame>
    <description>Peak Plasma Concentration after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the general safety and tolerability in terms of number of Treatment Emergent Adverse Event (TEAEs), Adverse Drug Reaction (ADRs), serious TEAEs, severe TEAEs and TEAEs leading to study discontinuation and to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the general safety and tolerability in terms number of subjects with TEAEs, ADRs, serious TEAEs, severe TEAEs and TEAEs leading to study discontinuation and to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the general safety and tolerability in terms of incidence of TEAEs, ADRs, serious TEAEs, severe TEAEs and TEAEs leading to study discontinuation and to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory parameters (biochemistry)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of PD profile in terms of plasma cortisol, serum potassium and serum glucose after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory parameters (urinalysis)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of PD profile in terms of urine cortisol and creatinine excretion after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of PD profile in terms of the Heart Rate after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12-lead ECG parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of pharmacodynamics profile in terms of 12-lead ECG parameters extracted from Holter after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 24 hours after administration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of pharmacodynamics profile in terms of vital signs (systolic and diastolic blood pressure) after a single-dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose administration of CHF 5993 100/6/12.5 µg pMDI 2 inhalations. Total dose of CHF 5993 pMDI = 200/12/25 µg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose administration of CHF 5993 200/6/12.5 µg pMDI 2 inhalations. Total dose of CHF 5993 pMDI = 400/12/25 µg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Supra-therapeutic Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose administration of CHF 5993 100/6/12.5 µg pMDI 8 inhalations Total dose of CHF 5993 pMDI = 800/48/100 µg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose administration of CHF 5993 pMDI placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Dose 1</intervention_name>
    <description>CHF 5993 100/6/12.5 µg pMDI, fixed combination of BDP 100 µg + FF 6 µg + GB 12.5 µg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Dose 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Dose 2</intervention_name>
    <description>CHF 5993 200/6/12.5 µg pMDI, fixed combination of BDP 200 µg + FF 6 µg + GB 12.5 µg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Dose 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Supra-therapeutic Dose</intervention_name>
    <description>CHF 5993 200/6/12.5 µg pMDI, fixed combination of BDP 200 µg + FF 6 µg + GB 12.5 µg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supra-therapeutic Dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>CHF 5993 placebo pMDI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject's written informed consent obtained prior to any study related procedure;

          -  Healthy male and female subjects aged 20 to 55 years inclusive;

          -  For Japanese subjects: must be a Japanese subject who has resided outside Japan for no
             more than 5 years, born in Japan and holding a Japanese passport, with all 4
             grandparents Japanese, as confirmed by interview;

          -  Subject must be willing and able to adhere to the prohibitions and restrictions
             specified in this protocol and to comply with the correct use of the devices specified
             in this protocol;

          -  Body mass index within the range of 18.0 to 25.0 kg/m2 inclusive;

          -  Non-smokers or ex-smokers who smoked &lt;5 pack years and stopped smoking &gt;1 year prior
             to screening;

          -  Subject must be healthy on the basis of physical examination, medical history, vital
             signs, and 12 -lead digitised Electrocardiogram (12-lead ECG);

          -  Vital signs (Blood pressure and body temperature) within normal limits;

          -  12-lead ECG considered as normal;

          -  Lung function measurements within normal limits;

          -  Women of non-childbearing potential (WONCBP) and women of childbearing potential
             (WOCBP) fulfilling one of the following criteria: a) WOCBP with fertile male partners:
             they and/or their partner must be willing to use a highly effective birth control
             method from the signature of the informed consent and until the follow-up visit or b)
             WOCBP with non-fertile male partners: (contraception is not required in this case).

          -  Female subject, except if postmenopausal, must have a negative serum beta-human
             chorionic gonadotropin at screening and a negative urine pregnancy test at Day -1
             prior the first drug administration;

          -  Subjects must agree not to donate sperm or ova from the time of the first
             administration of study medication until three months after the end of the systemic
             exposure of the study drug or until the last follow-up visit, whichever occurs later;

          -  Males fulfilling one of the following criteria: a) Males with pregnant or non-pregnant
             WOCBP partners: they must be willing to use male condom from the signature of the
             informed consent and until the follow-up visit or b) Non-fertile male subjects
             (contraception is not required in this case) or c) Males with partner not of
             childbearing potential (contraception is not required in this case).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in another clinical trial with an investigational drug in the 90 days or
             5 half-lives of non-biological entities of that investigational drug (whichever is
             longer) preceding the administration of the study drug;

          -  Clinically relevant and uncontrolled respiratory, cardiac, hepatic, gastrointestinal,
             renal, endocrine, metabolic, neurologic, or psychiatric disorders that may interfere
             with successful completion of this study;

          -  Any other abnormal findings on vital signs, ECG, physical examination or laboratory
             evaluation of blood and urine samples that the investigator judges as likely to
             interfere with the study or pose an additional risk in participating;

          -  Medical diagnosis of narrow-angle glaucoma, prostatic hypertrophy or bladder neck
             obstruction that in the opinion of the investigator would prevent use of
             anticholinergic;

          -  History of asthma, including childhood asthma, Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease
             (COPD) or any other chronic pulmonary diseases or condition;

          -  Positive HIV1 or HIV2 serology;

          -  results from the Hepatitis serology at screening which indicates acute or chronic
             Hepatitis (i.e. positive HB surface antigen (HBsAg), HB core antibody (anti-HBc), or
             Hepatitis C (positive HCV antibody);

          -  Blood donation or blood loss (equal or more than 450 mL), less than 2 months prior to
             randomisation;

          -  Abnormal haemoglobin level defined as &lt;12.0 g/dL in females and &lt;14.0 g/dL in males;

          -  Positive urine test for cotinine at screening or prior to randomisation;

          -  Unsuitable veins for repeated venepuncture;

          -  History or clinical evidence of drug and/or alcohol abuse within 12 months prior to
             screening and randomisation;

          -  Known intolerance/hypersensitivity to any of the excipients/components contained in
             any of the formulations used in the trial;

          -  Taking any drug treatment, including prescribed or Over the Counter (OTC) medicines as
             well as homeopathic remedies etc., in the 14 days before the screening and prior
             randomisation, with the exception of occasional paracetamol (maximum 3 g per day with
             a maximum of 10 g per 14 days for mild non-exclusionary conditions), hormonal
             contraceptives; hormonal replacement treatment for post-menopausal women, occasional
             ibuprofen (maximum 1.2 g per day, not to exceed 12 g in the 14 days before the
             screening);

          -  Taking enzyme-inducing drugs, enzyme-inhibiting drugs, biologic drugs or any drug
             known to have a well-defined potential for hepatotoxicity (e.g. isoniazide,
             nimesulide, ketoconazole) in the 3 months before screening or prior to randomisation;

          -  Heavy caffeine drinker &gt;28 cups/week of coffee or similar caffeinated beverages e.g.,
             tea, cola per day);

          -  Bacterial or viral respiratory tract, sinus or middle ear infection affecting health
             status within 4 weeks prior to randomisation;

          -  Night shift workers with night shifts within 8 weeks prior to randomisation and during
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Pharmacology Ltd</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Tooting</state>
        <zip>SW17 0RE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

