<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03859739</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8558-002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MK-8558-002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03859739</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Anti-Retroviral Activity of MK-8558 Monotherapy in Anti-Retroviral-Naïve HIV-1 Infected Participants (MK-8558-002)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Dose Clinical Trial to Study the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Anti-Retroviral Activity of MK-8558 Monotherapy in Anti-Retroviral-Naïve HIV-1 Infected Participants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and
      anti-retroviral activity of MK-8558 monotherapy in anti-retroviral-naïve HIV-1 infected
      participants. The primary hypothesis is that at a dose that exhibits an acceptable safety and
      tolerability profile, MK-8558 has superior anti-retroviral activity compared to historical
      placebo data.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 29, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 29, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Plasma HIV-1 Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 168 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The mean change from baseline in plasma HIV-1 RNA concentration will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants experiencing ≥1 Adverse Event (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 35 days post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants experiencing ≥1 AE will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Discontinue From the Study Due to an Adverse Event (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 35 days post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who discontinue from the study due to an AE will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve from 0 to 168 hours (AUC0-168) for MK-8558 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC0-168 for MK-8558 in plasma will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve from 0 up to the Last Quantifiable Time-Point (AUC0-last) for MK-8558 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC0-last for MK-8558 in plasma will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve from 0 to Infinity (AUC0-inf) for MK-8558 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC0-inf for MK-8558 in plasma will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Concentration (Cmax) for MK-8558 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The Cmax for MK-8558 in plasma will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Maximum Observed Concentration (Tmax) for MK-8558 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The Tmax for MK-8558 in plasma will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration at 168 Hours Post-Dose (C168hr) for MK-8558 in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>168 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The C168hr for MK-8558 in plasma will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Clearance (CL/F) for MK-8558</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>CL/F for MK-8558 will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vz/F) for MK-8558</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Vz/F for MK-8558 will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal Half Life (t1/2) for MK-8558</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 120, 168, 240, 336, 504 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>t1/2 for MK-8558 will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel A. MK-8558 400 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single oral dose of MK-8558 administered at 400 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel B. MK-8558 at dose level 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single oral dose of MK-8558 administered at dose level 2. Dose level 2 shall not exceed 900 mg. Per protocol, dose will be selected following review of data from panel A.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel C. MK-8558 at dose level 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single oral dose of MK-8558 administered at dose level 3. Dose level 3 shall not exceed 1600 mg. Per protocol, dose will be selected following review of data from panel B.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel D. MK-8558 at dose level 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single oral dose of MK-8558 administered at dose level 4. Dose level 4 shall not exceed 1600 mg. Per protocol, Panel D is optional pending results of Panels A-C, and dose will be selected following review of data from panel C.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-8558</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose of MK-8558 administered as a tablet at a dose up to 1600 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel A. MK-8558 400 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel B. MK-8558 at dose level 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel C. MK-8558 at dose level 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel D. MK-8558 at dose level 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Other than having HIV infection, is in good health based on medical history, physical
             examination, vital sign (VS) measurements, and laboratory safety tests, at the
             pre-study (screening) visit and/or prior to administration of the study drug

          -  Is documented as being HIV-1 positive

          -  Has a screening plasma HIV-1 RNA ≥ 2,500 copies/mL within 30 days prior to the
             treatment phase of this study

          -  Has a screening plasma CD4+ T-cell count of &gt;200/mm^3

          -  Is antiretroviral therapy (ART)-naïve

          -  Is willing to receive no other ART prior to Day 11 post-dose of the trial, unless the
             physician/Investigator believes that there is a strong indication to start ART before
             Day 11

          -  Has a Body Mass Index (BMI) ≤35 kg/m^2

          -  Males must agree to abstinence, or barrier contraception plus partner contraception,
             unless confirmed to be azoospermic due to vasectomy or medical cause, for at least 35
             days after the last dose of MK-8558

          -  Females must not be pregnant or breastfeeding, and must be a woman of nonchildbearing
             potential, or a woman of childbearing potential using highly effective birth control
             with low user dependency or who is abstinent on a long-term and persistent basis
             during the intervention period and at least 35 days after the last dose of study
             medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has acute (primary) HIV-1 infection

          -  Has a history of clinically significant endocrine, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular,
             hematological, hepatic (with the exception of Gilbert's disease), immunological
             (outside of HIV-1 infection), renal, respiratory, genitourinary, or major neurological
             (including stroke and chronic seizures) abnormalities or diseases

          -  Is mentally or legally incapacitated or has a history of a clinically significant
             psychiatric disorder (with the exception of situational depression) of the last 5
             years

          -  Has a history of cancer unless disease is adequately treated and deemed &quot;cured&quot;

          -  Has an estimated creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≤ 90 mL/min

          -  Has a history of significant multiple and/or severe allergies, or has had an
             anaphylactic reaction or significant intolerability to prescription or
             non-prescription drugs or food, or has hereditary galactose intolerance, lactase
             deficiency, or glucose-galactose malabsorption

          -  Is positive for hepatitis B surface antigen

          -  Has a history of chronic hepatitis C unless there has been documented cure

          -  Had major surgery, donated or lost 1 unit of blood (approximately 500 mL) within 4
             weeks prior to the pre-study (screening) visit

          -  Is unable to refrain from or anticipates the use of any medication, including
             prescription and nonprescription drugs or herbal remedies beginning approximately 2
             weeks (or 5 half-lives) prior to administration of the initial dose of study drug,
             throughout the study, until the post-study visit. There may be certain medications
             that are permitted

          -  Has participated in another investigational study within 4 weeks (or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is greater) prior to the pre-study (screening) visit. The window will be
             derived from the date of the last visit in the previous study

          -  Is under the age of legal consent or not capable of giving consent

          -  Has been committed to an institution by way of official or judicial order

          -  Is an excessive smoker (i.e., more than 10 cigarettes/day) and is unwilling to
             restrict smoking to ≤10 cigarettes per day

          -  Consumes more than 3 glasses of alcoholic beverages (1 glass is approximately
             equivalent to: beer [354 mL/12 ounces], wine [118 mL/4 ounces], or distilled spirits
             [29.5 mL/1 ounce]) per day. Participants who consume 4 glasses of alcoholic beverages
             per day may be enrolled at the discretion of the investigator

          -  Consumes excessive amounts, defined as more than 6 servings (1 serving is
             approximately equivalent to 120 mg of caffeine) of coffee, tea, cola, energy drinks,
             or other caffeinated beverages per day

          -  Has a positive urine drug screen (except for cannabis) at screening and/or pre-dose;
             rechecks are allowed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charite Research Organisation GmbH ( Site 0001)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Matei Bals Infectious Diseases Institute ( Site 0002)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucharest</city>
        <state>Bucuresti</state>
        <zip>021105</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>http://engagezone.msd.com/doc/ProcedureAccessClinicalTrialData.pdf</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>http://engagezone.msd.com/ds_documentation.php</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

