<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03851211</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UR17/104867</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03851211</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prolaris Enhanced Risk Stratification - an ecONomic and clinicAL Evaluation</brief_title>
  <acronym>PERSONAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Prolaris Enhanced Risk Stratification - an ecONomic and clinicAL Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One in 8 men will be diagnosed with prostate cancer during their lifetime. The majority of
      men diagnosed with prostate cancer have early stage disease, which can be managed in a
      variety of ways, ranging from monitoring to international treatment. However is it not always
      clear which treatment option is best.

      All men with newly diagnosed localised prostate cancer are assigned a disease risk category
      (low/intermediate/high risk). This is based on clinical findings and prostate biopsy results,
      but these factors are limited in their ability to distinguish between aggressive and indolent
      prostate cancers. The current risk grouping can make it difficult to plan appropriate
      treatment tailored and personalised to the individual patient.

      There is evidence reporting overtreatment of localised prostate cancer in the UK. However,
      many patients with aggressive disease are wrongly assigned a low risk categorisation and are
      recommended surveillance when better suited to more interventional treatment.

      Myriad Genetics have developed a test, called Prolaris which measures how fast cells in a
      prostate cancer are dividing to assess its aggressiveness. The Prolaris test is performed on
      routine prostate biopsy tissue, so patients are not subjected to any additional invasive
      investigations.

      In this study, led by Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust, the aim is find out if the
      Prolaris® test score helps patients with newly diagnosed prostate cancer and their clinical
      team make better informed treatment choices that are tailored to the individual patient.

      The aim to achieve a Prolaris risk score for 100 patients and determine the impact it has on
      treatment decision making. The research team will look at how the test fits into routine
      clinical practice, investigate the clinician and patient views and understanding on the test
      report and assess the quality of life of patients in the different risk and treatment groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prolaris test outcome received via report.</measure>
    <time_frame>30-60mins</time_frame>
    <description>Results of the test received.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment counselling</measure>
    <time_frame>30-60mins</time_frame>
    <description>Feedback of the results of the prolaris test. Consultant Urologist will see each participant in clinic after receipt of the Prolaris test report. They will explain the results to the patient and the patient will have the opportunity to ask any questions that they may have. The patient will then be able to decide on their treatment option.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Men who have a diagnosis of prostate cancer on their prostate biopsy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical suspicion of prostate cancer

          -  Able to provide informed written consent

          -  No contraindication to prostate biopsy

          -  Newly diagnosed treatment-naive patient with histologically proven localised
             adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Low or intermediate D'Amico risk prostate cancer

          -  Sufficient quantity and quality of tissue remains from biopsy to perform genomic
             testing

          -  No contraindication to radical treatment if diagnosed with localised prostate cancer

          -  Estimated life expectancy &gt;10 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Men with locally advanced, clinical node positive or metastatic disease

          -  Patients who lack capacity to consent to study participation

          -  Non-adenocarcinoma prostate cancer histology
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>William Cross, MRCS</last_name>
    <phone>0113 243 3144</phone>
    <email>williamcross@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St James's University Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS9 7TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Cross, MRCS</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

