<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03852524</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018H0260</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03852524</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Subcutaneous Methylnaltrexone Versus Placebo for Postoperative Ileus Prevention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double-Blind, Randomized Trial of Peri-operative Subcutaneous Methylnaltrexone Versus Placebo for Postoperative Ileus Prevention After Adult Spinal Arthrodesis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled trial will prospectively evaluate the clinical benefit for
      subcutaneous methylnaltrexone (MNTX) in counteracting the obstipatory (causing constipation)
      effects of spinal surgery without increasing narcotic usage or otherwise disrupting the
      recovery course of patients. Using a double-blind randomized design, either subcutaneous MNTX
      (0.15 mg/kg rounded to 8 mg or 12 mg) or placebo will be administered starting before surgery
      and then daily for three days. Information will be collected from medical records in IHIS up
      to 30 days prior to surgery and then for up to 30 days after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative Ileus refers to the transient interruption of propulsive motor activity of the
      gastrointestinal (GI) tract that prevents effective movement of its contents and tolerance of
      oral intake. Although POI is generally considered to significantly increase hospital stays
      and inpatient costs after spinal surgery, the incidence, associated risk factors, and
      effective preventative strategies remain poorly characterized. The proposed etiologies
      underlying POI are broad and remain incompletely characterized. They include post surgical
      sympathetic nervous system activation, inflammatory factors, and the effects of analgesics on
      GI tract motility. Treatment often consists of aggressive bowel regimens, nasogastric tube
      insertion for decompression, and the application of various laxatives, suppositories, and
      enemas. The widespread use of these measures is unfortunately not supported by high level
      evidence. The incidence of POI after spinal fusion is reported to range between 0.6 to 16.7%.
      This estimated range likely represents a gross underestimate of POI given the retrospective
      nature of studies undertaken to date. Fineberg and colleagues reported that the risk
      increases nearly 3-fold following anterior lumbar spinal fusions as compared to posterior
      surgeries. Furthermore, the only risk factors they identified to be correlated with POI is
      male gender, = 3 fusion levels, alcohol abuse, anemia, electrolyte abnormalities, and weight
      loss. Kiely and colleagues found that ileus was associated with the administration of certain
      intravenous solutions such as lactated ringers and sodium chloride. Interestingly, they found
      that albumin administration was associated with a reduced incidence of ileus postoperatively.
      Lee and colleagues evaluated POI following orthopedic surgery and reported an incidence of
      2.1%. They found that patients who developed POI were more likely to be older, had higher
      blood loss during surgery, and also had higher rates of preoperative constipation. This
      study, however, included all types of orthopedic surgeries (not limited to spinal fusion).
      Early clinical studies evaluated the effectiveness of MNTX in treating opioid-induced
      constipation (OIC). Several clinical trials confirmed that MNTX was well tolerated and
      counteracted the GI effects of opioids, thereby enhancing gut motility without inhibiting
      their analgesic properties. Only two studies to date have evaluated the potential
      effectiveness of MNTX in reducing the incidence of POI following GI surgery. Both studies
      were unfortunately hampered by serious design flaws. Most importantly, neither study included
      pre-operative administration of MNTX. As such, MNTX remains at this time approved only for
      chronic OIC based on two double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trials conducted in
      patients with advanced illness wherein MNTX rapidly induced laxation as compared to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion to receive methylnaltrexone or placebo. Participants will remain in the group they are randomized to for the duration of the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first bowel movement</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The time it takes for the participant to have a bowel movement from the end of surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The number of days it takes for the participant to meet all discharge criteria and be released from the hospital.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to discharge eligibility</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The time it takes for the participant to meet all discharge criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Daily narcotics</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of daily narcotics (in morphine milli-equivalents) given to a patient</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">82</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Ileus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study arm will receive subcutaneous methylnaltrexone (0.15mg/kg rounded to 8 or 12 mg) before surgery and then daily, for the following three days after surgery (four doses).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo arm will receive subcutaneous placebo before surgery and then daily, for the following three days after surgery (four doses).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylnaltrexone</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomization of methylnaltrexone to placebo will be at a 1:1 ratio. Those receiving methylnaltrexone (study drug) will receive a subcutaneous dose pre-surgery and daily for three days following surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomization of methylnaltrexone to placebo will be at a 1:1 ratio. Those receiving placebo will receive a subcutaneous dose pre-surgery and daily for three days following surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is scheduled to undergo a 1 - 3 level lumbar spinal fusion for degenerative
             spinal conditions including neurogenic claudication and/or lumbar radiculopathy with
             stenosis and/or spondylolisthesis.

          -  Subject must be over the age of 18 years old.

          -  Subject has been unresponsive to conservative care for a minimum of 6 months.

          -  The subject must in the investigator's opinion, be psychosocially, mentally, and
             physically able to fully comply with this protocol and have the ability to understand
             and give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous Treatment with MNTX

          -  History of mechanical gastrointestinal obstruction

          -  History of OIC refractory to outpatient medical management

          -  Presence of a peritoneal catheter for intraperitoneal chemotherapy or dialysis

          -  Clinically relevant active diverticular disease

          -  Recent history of bowel surgery within previous 12 months

          -  Use of vinca alkaloids within previous four months

          -  Renal failure defined as EGFR &lt;30 ml/min per 1.73 m^2 or requires dialysis

          -  Known or suspected allergy to MNTX or similar compounds (e.g. naltrexone or naloxone)

          -  Participation in a study with investigational products within 30 days before first
             dose of MNTX

          -  Pregnant or nursing

          -  Clinically important abnormalities that may interfere with participation or compliance
             to the study, as determined by investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shelby D Miracle, BA</last_name>
    <phone>614-366-1648</phone>
    <email>shelby.miracle@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amy J Minnema, MS</last_name>
    <phone>614-685-9827</phone>
    <email>amy.minnema@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shelby Miracle, BA</last_name>
      <phone>614-366-1648</phone>
      <email>shelby.miracle@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Amy Minnema, MS</last_name>
      <phone>614-685-9827</phone>
      <email>Amy.Minnema@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francis Farhadi, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>H Francis Farhadi, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spinal Arthrodesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ileus</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative Ileus</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult Spinal Deformity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ileus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylnaltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

