<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03855332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13891</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>206589/Z/17/Z</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03855332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oxford Haemodynamic Adaptation to Reduce Pulsatility Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>OxHARP</acronym>
  <official_title>Oxford Haemodynamic Adaptation to Reduce Pulsatility: Randomised, Placebo-controlled, Double-blind Crossover Trial of Effects of Sildenafil on Cerebral Arterial Pulsatility in Patients With Cryptogenic or Lacunar Stroke and Small Vessel Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wellcome Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic damage to small blood vessels deep in the brain is seen in half of patients over the
      age of 60 and almost all patients over the age of 80, and is responsible for up to a third of
      strokes and almost half of patients with dementia. However, there is limited evidence for how
      small vessel disease develops and no specific treatment. One potential explanation is that
      greater pulsations in blood pressure are transmitted to the brain through stiff blood
      vessels, resulting in increased pressure hitting the brain each time the heart beats and
      reduced blood flow between heart beats.

      Sildenafil is used to open up blood vessels (a vasodilator) in patients with erectile
      difficulties or poor blood supply to the lungs. This trial will test sildenafil (50mg, thrice
      daily) against placebo and a similar drug (cilostazol 100mg, twice daily) in 75 patients with
      previous stroke or mini-stroke and small vessel disease, given in random order to every
      participant for 3 weeks each. It will primarily assess changes in pulsations of blood flow to
      the brain on each tablet, measured with an ultrasound scanner (transcranial ultrasound). To
      understand why any changes occur, we will also measure the stiffness of arteries, the blood
      pressure at the heart and how much blood vessels in the brain open up when participants
      breathe air with added carbon dioxide (6%), using ultrasound in all participants and on MRI
      brain scans in 30 patients.

      This study will test whether a vasodilator used in other conditions with a good safety
      profile can reduce pulsations in blood flow to the brain, to assess whether it is a good
      candidate drug to reduce the progression of small vessel disease in future clinical trials.
      This would be the first effective treatment for a condition associated with a very high
      burden of disability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomised, double-blind, placebo and active controlled, crossover design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Middle cerebral arterial pulsatility index</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in Gosling's pulsatility index after three weeks treatment with sildenafil versus placebo, in 75 patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage increase in MCA velocity on 6% CO2 vs medical air</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in cerebrovascular reactivity after 3 weeks of treatment with sildenafil versus placebo in 75 patients: cereborovascular reactivity calculated by the percentage increase in mean MCA velocity whilst breathing 6% CO2 compared to breathing medical air.
Non-inferiority of 3 weeks of treatment with cilostazol 100mg bd compared to sildenafil 50mg tds for difference in Gosling's pulsatility index and cerebrovascular reactivity to 6% CO2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reactivity of BOLD signal on MRI to 6% CO2 challenge</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in cerebrovascular reactivity after 3 weeks of treatment with sildenafil versus placebo in 30 patients: cerebrovascular reactivity calculated by the percentage increase in BOLD signal on MRI whilst breathing 6% CO2 compared to breathing medical air.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Small Vessel Cerebrovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will undergo three phases in random order:
The placebo phase will include overencapsulated placebo, matched to overencapsulated active agents, 2 tablets 3 times daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sildenafil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25mg three times daily, overencapsulated tablet, increased after 1 week to 50mg three times daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cilostazol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>50mg bd, overencapsulated tablet (with midday placebo), increased after 1 week to 100mg bd (with midday placebo)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sildenafil</intervention_name>
    <description>See above</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sildenafil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cilostazol</intervention_name>
    <description>See above</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cilostazol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Overencapsulated placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             study.

          -  Male or Female, aged 18 years or above.

          -  Can record MCA waveform on at least one side ('useable TCD window')

          -  Non-disabling, ischaemic stroke or TIA, &gt;1 month prior to randomisation, of either
             cryptogenic or lacunar aetiology, confirmed clinically or on brain imaging

          -  White matter hyperintensities on MRI (Fazekas scale) or CT (Blennow scale) consistent
             with cerebral small vessel disease

          -  Age below 60 MRI Fazekas score 1 to 3 (max 2 points in periventricular or deep score)
             or CT Blennow score 1 to 3 (max 2 points in periventricular or deep score)

          -  Age above 60 MRI Fazekas score 1 to 4 (max 2 points in periventricular or deep score)
             or CT Blennow score 1 to 4 (max 2 points in periventricular or deep score)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women, women of childbearing age not taking contraception.

          -  Other major neurological or psychiatric conditions affecting the brain and interfering
             with the study design (e.g. multiple sclerosis)

          -  Other causes of stroke such as

               -  ≥50% luminal stenosis (NASCET) in large arteries supplying the infarct area

               -  major-risk cardioembolic source of embolism (permanent or paroxysmal atrial
                  fibrillation, sustained atrial flutter, intracardiac thrombus, prosthetic cardiac
                  valve, atrial myxoma or other cardiac tumours, mitral stenosis, recent (&lt;4 weeks)
                  myocardial infarction, left ventricular ejection fraction less than 30%, valvular
                  vegetations, or infective endocarditis)

               -  other specific causes of stroke (e.g. arteritis, dissection, drug misuse)

          -  Large vessel occlusion on MRA or CTA (carotid, basilar or MCA)

          -  Modified Rankin Score &gt;3

          -  Unable to swallow

          -  Renal impairment (eGFR &lt;35ml/min)

          -  Significant biochemical abnormalities (sodium &lt;130, K+ &lt;2.5 or &gt;5.5, LFTs &gt;3 x upper
             limit of normal range)

          -  Life expectancy &lt;2 years

          -  Contraindication to active agents

               -  Concurrent use of alphablocker

               -  Regular use of nitrate (ISMN, GTN, other)

               -  Heart failure (NYHA 2-4)

               -  Severe aortic stenosis

               -  Bilateral renal artery stenosis

               -  Uncontrolled arrhythmias

               -  Previous priapism

               -  Anatomical deformation of the penis

               -  Recent myocardial infarction (within 6 months)

               -  Unstable angina

               -  History of non-arteritic ischaemic optic neuropathy

               -  Hypotension: BP &lt;90/60

               -  Haemodynamically significant aortic / mitral valve disease

               -  Sickle cell disease, myeloma, leukaemia

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (BP &gt;180/110 despite treatment with 3
                  antihypertensives)

          -  Scheduled elective surgery or other procedures requiring general anaesthesia during
             the study.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the study or the
             participant's ability to participate in the study.

          -  Participants who have participated in another research study involving an
             investigational product in the past 12 weeks.

          -  Use of an anticoagulant (warfarin, dabigatran, rivaroxaban etc) or more than one
             antiplatelet drug.

          -  Predisposition to intracerebral haemorrhage (previous ICH, likely cerebral amyloid
             angiopathy) or intraocular haemorrhage (uncontrolled diabetic retinopathy or
             neovascularisation)

          -  Allergy to constituents of medications or components of placebo / overencapsulation

          -  Use of CYP inducers that interact with study medications (ketoconazole, erythromycin).

        Exclusion criteria specific for MRI substudy

          -  Not able to transfer to MRI scanner

          -  Active respiratory illness (such as moderate to severe asthma or COPD) such that they
             are unable to tolerate MRI or unable to lie flat

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Contraindication to MRI scan (pacemaker, aneurysm clip etc)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr A Webb, DPhil</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dr A Webb, DPhil</last_name>
    <phone>+441865231601</phone>
    <email>alastair.webb@ndcn.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oxford</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxon</state>
        <zip>OX39DU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alastair Webb, DPhil</last_name>
      <phone>+441865231601</phone>
      <email>alastair.webb@ndcn.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebrovascular Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Small Vessel Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cilostazol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sildenafil Citrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This will be determined on specific request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

