<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03859089</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-96275KCRA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03859089</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cannabis for Opioid Substitution Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>COST</acronym>
  <official_title>Cannabis for Opioid Substitution Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cannabis Research Associates</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cannabis Research Associates</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to define common strains of cannabis that adult chronic cancer
      and non-cancer pain syndrome patients are using as a replacement for opioids (narcotics).
      Identified strains, if any, will then be tested via randomized controlled trials to support
      an application for a Health Canada Drug Identification Number.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The search for safer alternatives to opioids for treating chronic cancer and non-cancer pain
      syndromes currently is an important initiative. Cannabis Research Associates (CRA) has been
      commissioned by Northern Green Canada Inc. to conduct a multi-phase study that will first
      define common strains of cannabis that patients use as a replacement for opioids, then
      conduct a randomized controlled trial to support an application to Health Canada for a Drug
      Identification Number. This protocol summarizes the methods for phase I.

      In total, the Investigators plan to recruit 1,200 adult patients (&gt; 25 years) currently using
      cannabis to treat chronic cancer and non-cancer pain syndromes conditions. Patients will be
      recruited from six pain clinics throughout Ontario. Pain clinics have not yet been
      identified. The study Investigators will invite licensed physicians from various private pain
      clinics to collaborate on this study.

      This is an observational cohort study involving a mixed methods approach. Patients interested
      in participating will have the option to have an online survey link emailed to them so they
      can complete the survey at a convenient time. Or, patients can choose to complete the online
      survey in person with the assistance of a Research Assistant. Research Assistants will have
      hard copy surveys to serve as a back-up solution should they be faced with Internet
      connectivity and/or online survey hosting issues. No personal identifying information will be
      collected. Hard copy data will be stored in locked cabinets and shipped via courier to
      Cannabis Research Associates in batches.

      All aspects of this study will be executed under the supervision of the study Investigators.
      Scientific independence from the sponsoring body will be maintained, and no censorship of
      data management, analysis, or presentation/publication will be permitted.

      This study will be executed under the approval and ongoing supervision of the Research Ethics
      Board, as required.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cannabis as replacement for opioids</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Define common strains of cannabis that patients are using as a replacement for opioids (should any exist)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <condition>Cannabis Use</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medical Cannabis</intervention_name>
    <description>N/A - Observational Cohort Study</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult chronic cancer and non-cancer pain syndrome patients currently taking medical
        cannabis and are currently or have previously taken opioids to treat pain.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients aged &gt; 25 years—CPSO Policy states that physicians cannot prescribe
             medical cannabis to persons under the age of 25 unless all other conventional
             therapies have failed. Furthermore, there is evidence to support that cannabis use in
             younger persons can have lasting effects since the brain is still developing (Wier K,
             2015).

          2. English-speaking, or with the assistance of a family member/friend that can interpret
             English for the patient.

          3. Qualifying medical diagnosis for appropriate use of medical cannabis by a licensed
             physician.

          4. Current medical cannabis use to treat chronic cancer and non-cancer pain syndromes.

          5. Current or past use of prescription opioids to treat chronic cancer and non-cancer
             pain syndromes.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1. Patients taking medical cannabis for reasons other than chronic cancer and non-cancer
        pain syndromes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ira Price, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cannabis Research Associates</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrea J Afinec, BScH</last_name>
    <phone>647 341-4230</phone>
    <email>aafinec@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Synergy Health Services Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ira Price, MD FRCPC</last_name>
      <phone>1-855-800-2226</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>medical cannabis</keyword>
  <keyword>opioids</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>substitution</keyword>
  <keyword>alternative</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Marijuana Abuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>N/A - no plans to share individual participant data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

