<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03857217</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL69209.068.19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03857217</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Post-Cardiotomy Extra-Corporeal Life Support Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PELS</acronym>
  <official_title>Post-Cardiotomy Extra-Corporeal Life Support Study: a Retrospective International Multicenter Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Extracorporeal life support is increasingly used after cardiac surgery. Despite improved
      technology, outcome still remains poor.

      This retrospective multicenter cohort study aims to find the (risk) factors associated with
      the poor prognosis of these patients.

      Adult patients who received ECLS after cardiac surgery between 2000 and 2018 are eligible for
      inclusion
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of post-cardiotomy extracorporeal life support (PC-ECLS) reported in the
      literature varies between 0.6% and 3.6% of all cardiac surgical cases and has represented the
      most frequent indication for ECLS up to 2012.

      Indications for PC-ECLS usually include intra-operative failure to wean from cardiopulmonary
      bypass due to perioperative left, right or biventricular failure, or refractory cardiogenic
      shock/cardiac arrest in the postoperative period.

      Recently, The Extracorporeal Life Support Organization (ELSO) Registry reported a remarkable
      increase in the use of ECLS as a supportive therapy after cardiac surgery. However a
      disappointing trend was observed with regards to the in-hospital survival rate, reaching only
      15% in the latest period.

      Furthermore, despite this increase in use and new technological developments in this area,
      only a few comprehensive and dedicated reports about PC-ECLS have been presented.
      Nevertheless, PC-ECLS, has represented the main indication for ECLS utilization, and is
      characterized by specific aspects (duration and type of underlying disease, severity of
      comorbidities, indication and type of surgical procedure, modality of access and timing of
      implant, complication types and rates) when compared to other ECLS indications. Often these
      aspects are exacerbated when there is limited experience in these procedures, particularly in
      centers without well-established ECLS programs. All of these factors may potentially
      influence ECLS management and final outcomes in post-cardiotomy patients, and make this
      particular setting one in which there are higher risks for unfavorable results. Careful
      evaluation of patient features, complication rates and management, and in-hospital outcomes
      according to accumulated experience should provide meaningful information to assess center
      performance. Furthermore, analysis of overall and trends of outcomes will hopefully indicate
      further areas of improvement in order to improve the ECLS results. Additionally, a rather
      small patient cohort within the PC-ELS group, receives veno-venous (VV) support due to
      post-cardiotomy respiratory failure. While there is only limited data available regarding
      survival and predictors for a favorable outcome after post-cardiotomy VV-ECMO, these patients
      will be included in the current trial as well, potentially clarifying additional predictors
      for survival in this specific patient group. Finally, Extracorporeal carbon-dioxide removal
      (ECCOR) has as added a new dimension to the intensive care management of acute cardiac and/or
      respiratory failure in adult patient care. However, regarding post-cardiotomy patients, no
      studies have been published before. Therefore, as an additional subject, patients receiving
      ECCOR-support as an ECLS modality after cardiac surgery will be included to the current study
      as well in order to provide the first post-cardiotomy ECCOR results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In-hospital survival</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days (expected)</time_frame>
    <description>to assess the rate of survival</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-operative death</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days (expected)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the intra-operative rate of death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term death</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1-year</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the rate of death at long-term follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>during the hospitalization (within 2 months: expected)</time_frame>
    <description>Rethoracotomy for bleeding, Acute Renal Insufficiency, Respiratory insufficiency, Pneumonia, Adult Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS), Postoperative Transient Ischemic Attack (TIA), Postoperative Stroke, Vasoplegic syndrome, Postoperative Right Ventricular Dysfunction, Leg Ischemia, Leg Fasciotomy, Gastro-Intestinal Complications, Laparotomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac-related death</measure>
    <time_frame>during the hospitalization (within 2 months: expected)</time_frame>
    <description>Death for cardiac disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualify of file</measure>
    <time_frame>during the hospitalization (within 2 months: expected)</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the change in the quality of life after the procedure. The EQ-5D-5L descriptive system comprises the following 5 dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. Each of the 5 dimensions is divided into 5 levels of perceived problems: Level 1: indicating no problem; Level 2: indicating slight problems; Level 3: indicating moderate problems; Level 4: indicating severe problems; Level 5: indicating extreme problems. Higher scores indicate higher levels of health. An unique health state is defined by combining 1 level from each of the 5 dimensions. A total of 3125 possible health states is defined in this way. Each state is referred to in terms of a 5 digit code. For example state 12345 indicates no problems with mobility, slight problems with washing or dressing, moderate problems with doing usual activities, severe pain or discomfort and extreme anxiety or depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiogenic Shock</condition>
  <condition>Resuscitation</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-cardiotomy patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients submitted to cardiac surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extra-Corporeal Membrane Oxygenation</intervention_name>
    <description>ECMO is implanted in cardiac surgery patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Post-cardiotomy patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients that require ECLS after cardiac screened for inclusion
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiac surgery prior to Extracorporeal Life Support (ECLS: VA-ECMO, VV-ECMO, ECCOR2)
             / Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO);

          -  Patients who received treatment (cardiac surgery AND adjuvant ECLS) between January
             2000 and December 2018

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Extra-corporeal life support (ECLS) in patients who had cardiac surgery procedures,
             but with implant not strictly related to surgery-related hospitalization;

          -  ECMO implant after discharge will not be considered.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorusso Roberto, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0031433877095</phone>
      <email>roberto.lorussobs@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Berta Ganizada, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>0031617377191</phone>
      <email>berta.ganizada@mumc.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roberto Lorusso, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Glenn Whitmann, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kiran Shekar, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Elsharkawy HA, Li L, Esa WA, Sessler DI, Bashour CA. Outcome in patients who require venoarterial extracorporeal membrane oxygenation support after cardiac surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2010 Dec;24(6):946-51. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2010.03.020.</citation>
    <PMID>20599396</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rastan AJ, Dege A, Mohr M, Doll N, Falk V, Walther T, Mohr FW. Early and late outcomes of 517 consecutive adult patients treated with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for refractory postcardiotomy cardiogenic shock. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2010 Feb;139(2):302-11, 311.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2009.10.043.</citation>
    <PMID>20106393</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Whitman GJ. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for the treatment of postcardiotomy shock. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2017 Jan;153(1):95-101. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2016.08.024. Epub 2016 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>27666787</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Saxena P, Neal J, Joyce LD, Greason KL, Schaff HV, Guru P, Shi WY, Burkhart H, Li Z, Oliver WC, Pike RB, Haile DT, Schears GJ. Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Support in Postcardiotomy Elderly Patients: The Mayo Clinic Experience. Ann Thorac Surg. 2015 Jun;99(6):2053-60. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2014.11.075. Epub 2015 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>25865760</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fukuhara S, Takeda K, Garan AR, Kurlansky P, Hastie J, Naka Y, Takayama H. Contemporary mechanical circulatory support therapy for postcardiotomy shock. Gen Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2016 Apr;64(4):183-91. doi: 10.1007/s11748-016-0625-4. Epub 2016 Feb 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26874519</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sauer CM, Yuh DD, Bonde P. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation use has increased by 433% in adults in the United States from 2006 to 2011. ASAIO J. 2015 Jan-Feb;61(1):31-6. doi: 10.1097/MAT.0000000000000160.</citation>
    <PMID>25303799</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McCarthy FH, McDermott KM, Kini V, Gutsche JT, Wald JW, Xie D, Szeto WY, Bermudez CA, Atluri P, Acker MA, Desai ND. Trends in U.S. Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation Use and Outcomes: 2002-2012. Semin Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2015 Summer;27(2):81-8. doi: 10.1053/j.semtcvs.2015.07.005. Epub 2015 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26686427</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Song JH, Woo WK, Song SH, Kim HH, Kim BJ, Kim HE, Kim do J, Suh JW, Shin YR, Park HK, Lee SH, Joo HC, Lee S, Chang BC, Yoo KJ, Kim YS, Youn YN. Outcome of veno-venous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation use in acute respiratory distress syndrome after cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass. J Thorac Dis. 2016 Jul;8(7):1804-13. doi: 10.21037/jtd.2016.05.86.</citation>
    <PMID>27499972</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nakamura H, Yamaguchi H, Amano A, Nakao T. Venovenous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation is effective against post-cardiotomy acute respiratory failure in adults. Gen Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2013 Jul;61(7):402-8. doi: 10.1007/s11748-013-0226-4. Epub 2013 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23436039</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shekar K, Mullany DV, Thomson B, Ziegenfuss M, Platts DG, Fraser JF. Extracorporeal life support devices and strategies for management of acute cardiorespiratory failure in adult patients: a comprehensive review. Crit Care. 2014 May 9;18(3):219. doi: 10.1186/cc13865. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25032748</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shock, Cardiogenic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

