<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03851003</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5822-18-SMC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03851003</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Influence of Endometrial Suturing on the Risk of Uterine Scar Defect</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Influence of Endometrial Suturing During Cesarean Section on the Risk to Develop Uterine Scar Defect: A Randomized Control Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheba Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheba Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Caesarean section (CS) is the commonest major operation performed on women worldwide with
      progressively rising incidence. Consequently, long-term adverse sequelae due to uterine scar
      defect have been increasing. Given the association between uterine scar defect and
      gynecological symptoms, obstetric complications and potentially with subfertility, it is
      important to elucidate the etiology in order to develop preventive strategies. Surgical
      technique of uterine incision closure seems to be the most important determinant of defect
      formation. The aim of this prospective randomized study is to evaluate specifically the
      influence of inclusion versus exclusion of the endometrium during suturing the uterine
      incision on the risk to develop uterine scar defect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Caesarean section (CS) is the commonest major operation performed on women worldwide with
      progressively rising incidence. Consequently, long-term adverse sequelae due to uterine scar
      defect have been increasing. Common gynecological complains include chronic pelvic pain,
      dyspareunia, dysmenorrhea and postmenstrual spotting and infertility. Obstetric sequelae seem
      to be increasing such as cesarean scar ectopic pregnancy, placenta previa, and placenta
      accrete, all associated with major maternal morbidity and even mortality. Given the
      association between uterine scar defect and gynecological symptoms, obstetric complications
      and potentially with subfertility, it is important to elucidate the etiology in order to
      develop preventive strategies. Probable risk factors suggested are single-layer myometrium
      closure, multiple CSs and uterine retroflexion, however, surgical technique of uterine
      incision closure seems to be the most important determinant of defect formation. It is
      proposed that continuous, non-locking absorbable sutures in two layers, without including
      much of decidua and without undue tight (constricting) pulling of sutures are likely to
      result in good healing of uterine scar. The aim of this prospective randomized study is to
      evaluate specifically the influence of inclusion versus exclusion of the endometrium during
      suturing the uterine incision on the risk to develop uterine scar defect.

      Material and Methods Prospective randomized single blinded study conducted in a single
      tertiary center. All women at term (≥37 weeks of gestation) with singleton pregnancy that are
      about to go threw cesarean section attending the pre- operative clinics, will be offered to
      participate in the study. After signing informed consent, women will be block randomized for
      one of two groups: A- uterine incision repair including suturing of the endometrium, B -
      uterine incision repair without including the endometrium. All operation will be performed by
      a single highly skilled obstetrician. All other stages of operations will be similar in both
      of the groups including: low segment incision, delivery of the fetus and the placenta,
      uterine revision, intraperitoneal uterine repair, use of stratafix thread in double layer
      suturing. Operative and post operative data will be collected from the medical files
      including: operation duration, estimated blood loss, operation complications ( hypotension,
      bladder gut or vascular perforation ) , post operative complications ( hemorrhage,
      endometritis, vascular - thromboembolic event, ileus ). All women will be invited to the
      gynecologic clinics six month post operation for vaginal sonographic evaluation of the
      uterine scar and for filling questionnaire concerning possibility of uterine scar defect (
      spotting, pelvic pain, fertility abnormalities ).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Uterine incision repair will include or exclude suturing of the endometrium</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Women will not know which arm they were allocated to</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with uterine scar defect six month post cesarean section</measure>
    <time_frame>Until six month post cesarean section, and through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Uterine scar defect with residual myometrium thickness of less then 2.5 mm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spotting</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of spotting complains since operation reported by the women</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abdominal pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of abdominal pain since operation reported by the women and estimated by &quot;The Visual Analogue Scale&quot; (VAS) for the estimation of pain. In this scale, women will be asked to mark the pain that they are experiencing on a 10cm-long horizontal line labeled &quot;no pain&quot; on the far left and &quot;worst pain ever&quot; on the far right. Pain intensity is determined by the length of the line as measured from the left-hand side to the point marked. The following cut points on the pain VAS will be use: no pain (0-0.4 cm), mild pain (0.5-4.4 cm), moderate pain (4.5-7.4 cm), and severe pain (7.5-10 cm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Wound Disruption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Uterine incision repair including suturing of the endometrium</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non - Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Uterine incision repair without suturing of the endometrium</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endometrial suturing</intervention_name>
    <description>Suturing will include endometrium during cesarean incision repair</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non- endometrial suturing</intervention_name>
    <description>Suturing will not include endometrium during cesarean incision repair</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non - Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaginal ultrasonography</intervention_name>
    <description>All women will be invited six month post operation for vaginal sonographic evaluation of the uterine scar</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non - Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>All women will be invited six month post operation for filling questionnaire concerning possibility of uterine scar defect ( spotting, pelvic pain, fertility abnormalities )</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non - Endometrial suturing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Term pregnancy (≥37 weeks of gestation)

          -  Elective CS

          -  Singleton pregnancy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uterine scar

          -  Multiple gestation

          -  Thrombophilia

          -  Dysmorphic uterus

          -  Connective tissue disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>42 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aya Mohr Sasson, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>0523692906</phone>
    <email>mohraya@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. Aya Mohr-Sasson</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat-Gan</city>
        <zip>56506</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. A Mohr-Sasson</last_name>
      <phone>97235302777</phone>
      <phone_ext>97235302777</phone_ext>
      <email>mohraya@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mathai M, Hofmeyr GJ, Mathai NE. Abdominal surgical incisions for caesarean section. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 May 31;(5):CD004453. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004453.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23728648</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wang CB, Chiu WW, Lee CY, Sun YL, Lin YH, Tseng CJ. Cesarean scar defect: correlation between Cesarean section number, defect size, clinical symptoms and uterine position. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Jul;34(1):85-9. doi: 10.1002/uog.6405.</citation>
    <PMID>19565535</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tulandi T, Cohen A. Emerging Manifestations of Cesarean Scar Defect in Reproductive-aged Women. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2016 Sep-Oct;23(6):893-902. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2016.06.020. Epub 2016 Jul 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27393285</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>van der Voet LF, Bij de Vaate AM, Veersema S, Brölmann HA, Huirne JA. Long-term complications of caesarean section. The niche in the scar: a prospective cohort study on niche prevalence and its relation to abnormal uterine bleeding. BJOG. 2014 Jan;121(2):236-44. doi: 10.1111/1471-0528.12542.</citation>
    <PMID>24373597</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sholapurkar SL. Etiology of Cesarean Uterine Scar Defect (Niche): Detailed Critical Analysis of Hypotheses and Prevention Strategies and Peritoneal Closure Debate. J Clin Med Res. 2018 Mar;10(3):166-173. doi: 10.14740/jocmr3271w. Epub 2018 Jan 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29416572</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vervoort AJ, Uittenbogaard LB, Hehenkamp WJ, Brölmann HA, Mol BW, Huirne JA. Why do niches develop in Caesarean uterine scars? Hypotheses on the aetiology of niche development. Hum Reprod. 2015 Dec;30(12):2695-702. doi: 10.1093/humrep/dev240. Epub 2015 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26409016</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sheba Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Aya Mohr-Sasson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cesarean section</keyword>
  <keyword>niche</keyword>
  <keyword>uterine scar defect</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

