<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03850041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-5747</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03850041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Fluid Volume Shifts on Upper Airway Collapse and Obstructive Sleep Apnea in Surgical Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Variability and Impact of Segmental Neck and Leg Fluid Volume Shifts on Upper Airway Collapse and Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) Severity in Surgical Patients With OSA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Lung Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to examine the contribution of intravenous (IV) fluid
      administration and rostral fluid shift from the legs to the neck thereby leading to worsening
      of sleep apnea following surgery. In this prospective, observational cohort study, 50
      consecutive preoperative adult obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) patients, requiring at least one
      night hospital stay post surgery, will be recruited. Recent research from general population
      suggests that intravenous (IV) fluid administration worsens the severity of OSA by shifting
      of fluid from the legs to the neck thus increasing neck size and causing airway collapse. The
      results of this study will be used to design future clinical trials evaluating methods to
      decrease postoperative OSA worsening, as well as decreasing OSA-related postoperative
      complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study investigators hypothesize that in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) patients undergoing
      elective non-cardiac surgery, preferential increase in neck fluid volume following
      intravenous administration during general anesthesia results in worsening apnea-hypopnea
      (AHI) and postoperative respiratory complications.This is a two-center study where the study
      population will be drawn from patients visiting preoperative clinic at University Health
      Network Hospitals, Toronto Western Hospital, and Toronto General Hospital.

      Objectives of the study

        -  Measure the change in the leg, neck and total fluid volume from preoperative baseline,
           postoperative care unit (PACU), first postoperative night (Night 1) and the morning
           after surgery (Day 2)

        -  Assess the impact of the change in neck fluid volume on respiratory mechanics and
           postoperative apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) the first postoperative night (Night 1) In this
           study, the investigators will perform serial measurements of segmental and total body
           water shifts occurring after surgery, at various time-points on the night and the
           morning after surgery. The investigators will monitor indices such as the Apnea Hypopnea
           index (AHI) and oxygen desaturation index (ODI) to examine changes in the severity of
           OSA. Internal validity of this study will be made more robust by use of well-validated
           methods such as Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA) for fluid measurements, portable
           Apnea Link for OSA severity and tremflow airway oscillometry for the airway resistance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck, leg and total body water volumes preoperatively and on postoperative night 1 and the morning after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the leg fluid, neck fluid and total body water using the bioelectrical impedance analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apnea-hypopnea index on the night of surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the AHI (Apnea-hypopnea index) events/hour ,to determine severity of Obstructed Sleep Apnoea on the night of the surgery, using the following scale for ApneaLink device data:
No OSA( AHI: 0-5 events/hour),
Mild OSA(AHI: 6 to 15 events/hour),
Moderate OSA (AHI : 16-30 events/hour) and
Severe OSA (AHI: &gt;30 events/hour),</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck Circumference on Postoperative Night 1</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Neck circumference (in cm) will be assessed with a measuring tape and reported for correlation with other data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Surgical patients attending the preoperative assessment clinic in Toronto Western Hospital
        (UHN) who will be undergoing elective non-cardiac surgery, requiring general anesthesia,
        lasting for 1-2 hours or more and requiring same day admission for a minimum of 2 days
        postoperatively.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients (&gt;18 yrs)

          2. Previously diagnosed OSA (AHI &gt; 10), untreated or non-compliant to treatment, or
             patients screened as suspected OSA (STOP Bang &gt;3, and confirmed to have OSA with AHI &gt;
             10 on a portable sleep study)

          3. ASA physical status I - IV

          4. Patients undergoing elective non-cardiac surgery under general anesthesia;

          5. Patients requiring overnight admission.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients compliant on OSA treatment such as continuous positive airway pressure
             therapy or an oral appliance

          2. Vascular surgery on the lower limbs, or metal implants in lower limbs

          3. Pregnant or lactating patients

          4. Cardiac, intra-cranial, or neck procedures.

          5. Inability to communicate: with health care providers or the research personnel,
             inability to perform breathing maneuvers such as spirometry, or inability to follow
             instructions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD,FRCPC</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (416) 603-5118</phone>
    <email>mandeep.singh@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nayeemur Rahman, MBBS,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>416-603-5800</phone>
    <phone_ext>3959</phone_ext>
    <email>nayeemur.rahman@uhnresearch.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <phone>+1 (416) 790-0808</phone>
      <email>mandeep.singh@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <phone>+1 (416) 790-0808</phone>
      <email>mandeep.singh@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nayeemur Rahman, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+1 (416) 603-5800</phone>
      <phone_ext>3959</phone_ext>
      <email>nayeemur.rahman@uhnresearh.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11254524?dopt=Abstract</url>
    <description>Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Mar;163(3 Pt 1):685-9. Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea and related clinical features in a population-based sample of subjects aged 30 to 70 yr.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18431116?dopt=Abstract</url>
    <description>Anesthesiology. 2008 May;108(5):812-21. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31816d83e4. STOP questionnaire: a tool to screen patients for obstructive sleep apnea.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25247853?dopt=Abstract</url>
    <description>Anesthesiology. 2014 Oct;121(4):707-18. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000407. A matched cohort study of postoperative outcomes in obstructive sleep apnea: could preoperative diagnosis and treatment prevent complications?</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19220528?dopt=Abstract</url>
    <description>Intern Med J. 2009 Nov;39(11):757-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1445-5994.2008.01827.x. Epub 2008 Nov 3. Validation of a portable recording device (ApneaLink) for identifying patients with suspected obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Durán J, Esnaola S, Rubio R, Iztueta A. Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea and related clinical features in a population-based sample of subjects aged 30 to 70 yr. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Mar;163(3 Pt 1):685-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11254524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chung F, Yegneswaran B, Liao P, Chung SA, Vairavanathan S, Islam S, Khajehdehi A, Shapiro CM. STOP questionnaire: a tool to screen patients for obstructive sleep apnea. Anesthesiology. 2008 May;108(5):812-21. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31816d83e4.</citation>
    <PMID>18431116</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mutter TC, Chateau D, Moffatt M, Ramsey C, Roos LL, Kryger M. A matched cohort study of postoperative outcomes in obstructive sleep apnea: could preoperative diagnosis and treatment prevent complications? Anesthesiology. 2014 Oct;121(4):707-18. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000407.</citation>
    <PMID>25247853</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ng SS, Chan TO, To KW, Ngai J, Tung A, Ko FW, Hui DS. Validation of a portable recording device (ApneaLink) for identifying patients with suspected obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome. Intern Med J. 2009 Nov;39(11):757-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1445-5994.2008.01827.x. Epub 2008 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19220528</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

