<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03859011</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201900266</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03859011</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acupuncture Relief for Chronic Neck Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Cost-Effectiveness of Acupuncture for Chronic Neck Pain: A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Utica College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will measure the effectiveness of &quot;usual care&quot; for chronic neck pain as defined in
      the protocol, compared with usual care plus acupuncture for chronic neck pain. This study's
      hypothesis is that combining acupuncture with usual care will show a clinically relevant
      increase in the effectiveness of the integrated therapies, compared with usual care alone.
      This study will also measure the cost-effectiveness of acupuncture for chronic neck pain. the
      hypothesis is that in economic evaluation terms, integrating acupuncture with usual care will
      not create significant overall costs, relative to the benefits which study patients obtain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Low back and neck pain accounts for the third-highest amount of U.S. healthcare spending,
      estimated at $87.6 billion annually. Moderate quality evidence already exists showing
      acupuncture's effectiveness for low back pain. Other than a few mostly foreign randomized
      controlled trials (RCTs) on acupuncture for neck pain, there are fewer quality studies on
      acupuncture's effectiveness for neck pain than for low back pain. The safety of acupuncture
      is well established. The risk of hematoma or infection due to acupuncture is lower than with
      venipuncture.

      There is a lack of evidence on the cost-effectiveness relationship of this treatment strategy
      in the United States. A PubMed search found only three cost-effectiveness analyses of
      acupuncture for neck pain studies, all done abroad.

      Since Medicare and several large private insurance companies still do not cover acupuncture,
      patient access to this therapy is significantly limited by out-of-pocket cost. A quality
      comparative effectiveness and cost-effectiveness study on acupuncture for chronic neck pain
      is needed from several perspectives. From the patient perspective, such a study would inform
      patients and providers in decision-making regarding integrating acupuncture in the care plan.
      From a third-party payer perspective, such a study would inform insurance companies whether
      it is cost-effective for them to cover acupuncture for this specific diagnosis. From a
      societal perspective, such a study would inform policy decision-makers whether acupuncture is
      a sound &quot;investment&quot; to better make resource allocation decisions for its citizens.

        1. The primary aim of this trial is to explore the comparative effectiveness of acupuncture
           plus &quot;usual care&quot; vs. usual care alone for reducing chronic neck pain.

        2. The secondary aim of this trial is to evaluate the cost-effectiveness of acupuncture for
           this condition from multiple perspectives.

      The primary endpoint will be determined by comparing the mean change score on the neck
      disability index from baseline (month 0) to the treatment completion (month 2.5), and 3.5
      months after completion of the acupuncture treatment (month 6) between groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Control Trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Neck Disability Index (NDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline though 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The NDI will be used to measure pain and functional disability in the neck, and is the most widely used questionnaire to evaluate cervical pain and dysfunction in daily life. It consists of 10 questions, with a 6-point Likert scale from 0 to 5 points. The overall score ranges from 0 to 50 points, and a higher score indicates a greater degree of perceived functional disability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Numeric Pain Rating Scale (NRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline though 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be instructed to report the intensity of neck pain experienced within the past week on a linear scale of 0 to 10 (0, no pain; 10, pain as bad as it could be).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EuroQol 5-Dimension (EQ-5D-5L) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline though 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D-5L consists of five categories (mobility, personal care, daily activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression), and each category contains five statements describing personal health status10. Each dimension can be score on one of five levels: no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems and extreme problems. Participants will be instructed to select the most appropriate one among the five statements. The responses represent a health state, which then be converted into a utility score between 0 and 1, where 0 represents death and 1 represents perfect health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PROMIS® Scale v1.2. PROMIS® (Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline though 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient questionnaire be used to evaluate and monitor physical, mental and social health. The ten-question assessment uses a 5-point Likert scale with 5=never and 1= always. The higher score indicates better health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Acupuncture Expectancy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline though 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>This four-question assessment uses a 5-point Likert scale with 1=not at all and 5= Completely. The higher score indicates a higher expectation that acupuncture will be helpful.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cost Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline though 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient questionnaire to be used to evaluate the direct non health care costs of therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Neck Pain, Posterior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After obtaining baseline data and questionnaires, patients will receive usual care (for example physical therapy, oral pain medication or ointments), plus acupuncture 2X/week over 2 weeks, then once per week over 8 weeks (12 total treatments over 10 weeks), then no acupuncture between 10 weeks and 6 months. After treatment is completed, final measurement instruments are applied at 6 months. Questionnaires will be readministered at 2.5 and 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Usual&quot; care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After obtaining baseline data and questionnaires, patients will receive usual care (for example physical therapy, oral pain medication or ointments) for 6 months. Questionnaires will be readministered at 2.5 and 6 months. After the control phase the participants will continue usual care (for example physical therapy, oral pain medication or ointments), plus acupuncture 2X/week over 2 weeks, then once per week over 8 weeks (12 total treatments over 10 weeks, 8.5 months), then no acupuncture between 8.5 months and 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will have DBC Spring Ten acupuncture needles (manufactured in China) manually inserted bilaterally on five standardized acupuncture points according to the treatment points of GB20, BL10, BL11, SI3, BL62 at 6-8 mm depth for 20 minutes each using a tonification technique to elicit a de qi response.
After those needles are removed, the number of additional needles and additional acupuncture points used will be chosen at the acupuncturist's discretion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Usual&quot; care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Physical therapy, oral medications and topical ointments pre the discretion of the primary physician</description>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;Usual&quot; care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have Grade II neck pain with no signs or symptoms of major structural pathology but
             major interference with activities of daily living.

          -  Pain will be more than 4 out of 10 on the brief pain inventory short form at the time
             of screening and a diagnosis of non-specific neck pain (axial and muscular neck pain,
             without radicular symptoms, is included) by a clinician based on history taking and
             physical examination, including any imaging examinations. Neck pain is defined as
             &quot;pain, ache, or discomfort&quot; in the area between the occiput and the third thoracic
             vertebra and between the medial borders of the scapulae.

          -  Have persistent or recurrent neck pain lasting longer than 3 months, and occurring at
             least once per week

          -  Have had at least one physician or emergency department visit for neck pain within the
             past 3 months AND be currently taking pain medication as prescribed, such as:

               -  Acetaminophen

               -  NSAIDS

               -  Narcotics (≤ 30 Oral Morphine Equivalents (OME)

               -  Robaxin (or equivalent)

          -  Be able to maintain a prone position for at least 20 minutes per the intervention
             methodology

          -  Be able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have as their primary complaint radicular pain in the upper extremity with the
             distribution of a particular nerve root that is greater than the chronic neck pain.

          -  Have one of the following cervical neurological abnormalities:

               1. paresthesia (sensory deficits),

               2. positive sign on a special test: shoulder abduction relief sign test (Bakody
                  sign), Spurling test,

               3. hyporeflexia of the deep tendon reflex,

               4. pathological reflex: Hoffman sign, ankle clonus, Babinski sign, or

               5. muscle atrophy;

          -  Have major cervical spinal pathology such as neoplasm, spinal fractures, myelopathy,
             spondylitis, systemic inflammatory diseases, other non-mechanical cause of neck pain
             and congenital abnormality,

          -  Have a history of cervical spinal surgery or be pre-scheduled for such surgery prior
             to enrollment in the study;

          -  Report pain in another region that is more severe than the neck pain;

          -  Have a body mass index greater than 40;

          -  Report a history of hypersensitive reaction to previous acupuncture treatment, metal
             allergy, keloid, severe atopy, open skin sores, and other skin hypersensitivities;

          -  Have hemorrhagic disease and/or factors that can affect hemostasis, such as
             anti-coagulant or anti-platelet drug use;

          -  Have uncontrolled diabetes.

          -  Have a history of neurotic or major psychiatric disability or cognitive instability;

          -  Have a current or recent (within the past 6 months) history of alcoholism, or or
             current or recent history of drug abuse, including abusing opioids or other controlled
             pain medication;

          -  Have head or neck cancer, or neck pain associated with ongoing radiation treatment to
             the head or neck;

          -  Be involved in known litigation related to neck pain;

          -  Report current use of dry needling trigger point therapy;

          -  Pregnancy;

          -  Report a recent history of prior acupuncture treatment within the past six months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Mongan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Professor, Department of Anesthesiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kelly Flynn</last_name>
    <phone>904-244-4378</phone>
    <email>Kelly.Flynn@jax.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UF Health Jacksonville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UF Jax ASCENT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acupuncture</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>disability</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neck Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

