<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03859154</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05/19/IEC/JMMC&amp;RI</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1229-0385</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03859154</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Waveform Analysis In Snakebite Victims With Hematotoxicity</brief_title>
  <acronym>WISH</acronym>
  <official_title>Waveform Analysis In Snakebite Victims With Hematotoxicity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In hematotoxic snakebites, due to the lack of a better alternative, 20 minute whole blood
      clotting test (20'WBCT) or Clotting time remains the standard test in developing countries
      even though its reliability and sensitivity has been shown to be low.

      Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) based Clot Waveform Analysis (CWA) is an optic
      absorbance assay that can be used as a global clotting test.

      It essentially detects the change in colour of the plasma as coagulation progresses and
      quantifies the change in the form of a waveform.

      In this study, the investigators intend to study prospectively the behaviour of clot wave
      (CW) in hematotoxic bites.

      A pilot observational study was initially conducted (IEC Ref No. 42/16/IEC/JMMC and RI) and
      CWA showed changes which provided information earlier than the conventional coagulation
      studies in the snakebite victims studied.

      While aPTT or WBCT reflects clotting time, CWA conveys the dynamic process of clot formation.
      CWA may reveal disorders of clotting in snakebite victims before the conventional tests
      become abnormal.

      Here the investigators aim to study the changes in CWA in snakebite victims who develop
      coagulation disorders in blood
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Viperidae bites are quite common in India and are notorious to cause hematotoxicity.

      In hematotoxic bites, the test recommended to ascertain the development of coagulopathy is a
      whole blood clotting test (WBCT) as per the current guidelines.

      Eventhough the reliability and sensitivity of WBCT has been shown to be low, it still remains
      the standard test.

      There exists a need to explore other coagulation studies in snakebite to look for a better
      and efficient alternative.

      Clot waveform analysis (CWA) is an activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)-based optic
      absorbance assay that can be used as a global clotting test.

      It has been shown useful in identifying disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) in
      sepsis with high specificity (97.6%) and sensitivity (98%), and the test is recommended by
      the British Committee for Standards in Hematology guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment
      of DIC.

      CWA is based on the traditional aPTT assay. On assessing aPTT with light transmission, a
      change in the light absorbance is observed as the clot stabilizes by fibrin polymerization.

      Plotting the milliabsorbance (mAbs) of the sample to time, a curve is obtained which reflects
      the optical profile that is generated as a clot is formed.

      This tracing against time gives a qualitative assessment of fibrin polymerization.

      The delta in absorbance (dAbs) is based on the change in mAbs value from the baseline to the
      endpoint (plateau) along the Y-axis of the clot curve. The dAbs values of &lt;100 mAbs denote
      low fibrinogen samples

      The normal clot waveform has five main phases: delay, baseline, acceleration, deceleration,
      and end point.

      The &quot;delay&quot; period begins at 0 and precedes the &quot;baseline.&quot; which denotes the mixing of the
      reagents and system optimization of light intensity.

      The &quot;baseline&quot; is the portion of the curve which appears after all reagents have been added
      to the time and the clot formation begins.

      The aPTT value is noted at this point (vertical red line). The &quot;acceleration&quot; phase denotes
      fibrin clot formation, whereas &quot;deceleration&quot; denotes decreasing rate of clot formation.

      There are two more curves that are plotted in CWA, the first derivative and the second
      derivatives. They are both derivatives of the absorbance curves. The first derivative
      reflects the coagulation velocity, whereas the second derivative reflects the acceleration of
      coagulation.

      The investigators in this study aim to assess the changes in the CW form in viper-envenomated
      victims and to compare CWA with standard tests such as prothrombin time (PT) with the
      international normalized ratio (INR), aPTT, clotting time (CT) (modified Lee and White
      method) and 20'WBCT( twenty minute whole blood clotting test)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clot wave form 1st derivative changes</measure>
    <time_frame>For all aPTT samples done at admission, just prior to antivenom administration, 6 hours after antivenom administration completion and 6 hours after blood product administration, upto 7 days post admission.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the 1 st derivative</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clot wave form 2nd derivative changes</measure>
    <time_frame>For all aPTT samples done at admission, just prior to antivenom administration, 6 hours after antivenom administration completion and 6 hours after blood product administration, up to 7 days post admission.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the 2nd derivative</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in delay phase, baseline, acceleration, deceleration and end point phases of CWA</measure>
    <time_frame>For all aPTT samples done at admission, just prior to antivenom administration, 6 hours after antivenom administration completion and 6 hours after blood product administration, up to 7 days post admission.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the predefined Clot wave segments</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clotting time (CT)</measure>
    <time_frame>For all CT samples done at admission, just prior to antivenom administration, 6 hours after antivenom administration completion and 6 hours after blood product administration, up to 7 days post admission..</time_frame>
    <description>The absolute clotting time by modified lee white method done for all samples as per institutional protocol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum coagulation velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>For all aPTT samples done at admission, just prior to antivenom administration, 6 hours after antivenom administration completion and 6 hours after blood product administration, up to 7 days post admission.</time_frame>
    <description>maximum coagulation velocity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>sensitivity and specificity of CWA in detecting envenomation compared to 20'WBCT and MLW (Modified Lee and White) method</measure>
    <time_frame>from admission till time of objective detection of coagulopathy, or up to 48 hours of admission, whichever is earliest</time_frame>
    <description>To test how sensitive and specific changes in CWA is in detecting coagulopathy in snakebite victims compared to the World Health Organisation Recommended twenty minute whole blood clotting test and the modified lee white clotting time done as per institute protocol</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>correlation of CWA with serum fibrinogen levels</measure>
    <time_frame>For all serum Fibrinogen and aPTT sample sent simultaneously upto 48 hours of admission.</time_frame>
    <description>For all serum Fibrinogen and aPTT sample sent simultaneously correlation of CWA parameters with serum fibrinogen levels</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Snakebite</condition>
  <condition>Coagulopathy, Consumption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Viper bite victims</arm_group_label>
    <description>Snakebite victims in whom the snake has been brought and positively identified as Viperidae AND simultaneous aPTT has been sent AND consenting to be part of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nonvenomous snakebite</arm_group_label>
    <description>age and gender matched victims of snake bite in whom the culprit snake brought along has been identified as a non venomous one.
AND consenting to be part of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All victims of snakebite consenting to be part of the study presenting to the emergency
        department at Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute Thrissur, Kerala,
        India

        Snake bite registry would be established All consecutive cases would be enrolled in the
        study if they consent to be part of it.

        Sub group analysis excluding the dry bites,would be done Sub group analysis of the victims
        of hematotoxic snakebite would be done
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -snakebite victims were activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) sample has been sent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not consenting to be part of the study

          -  OR known case of coagulation disorders

          -  OR chronic liver disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Siju V Abraham, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Siju V Abraham, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>919447754321</phone>
    <email>sijuvabraham@jmmc.ac.in</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thrissur</city>
        <state>Kerala</state>
        <zip>686012</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Siju Varghese Abraham, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+919447754311</phone>
      <email>sijuvabraham@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abraham SV, Rafi AM, Krishnan SV, Palatty BU, Innah SJ, Johny J, Varghese S. Utility of Clot Waveform Analysis in Russell's Viper Bite Victims with Hematotoxicity. J Emerg Trauma Shock. 2018 Jul-Sep;11(3):211-216. doi: 10.4103/JETS.JETS_43_17.</citation>
    <PMID>30429630</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Siju V Abraham, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor in the Department of Emergency Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disseminated Intravascular Coagulation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Snake Bites</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

