<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03853616</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M-2017-322</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-002848-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03853616</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MB-CART19.1 r/r CD19+ B-cell Malignancies (BCM)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Safety, Dose Finding and Feasibility Trial of MB-CART19.1 in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory CD19 Positive B Cell Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Miltenyi Biomedicine GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Miltenyi Biomedicine GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase l/ll multi-centric, single arm, prospective open, dose-escalation study in
      patients with relapsed or refractory CD19-positive B cell malignancies (ALL, NHL, CLL). The
      trial will include adult and pediatric patients. The trial consists of 2 parts: Part I and
      Part II. In total approximately 48 patients will be included in Part I of the trial. There
      will be three individual cohorts, defined by disease biology: pediatric ALL and aggressive
      pediatric NHL (Cohort 1), adult ALL (Cohort 2) and adult NHL/CLL (Cohort 3).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Part I (Phase I) will evaluate the safety of the MB-CART19.1 and determine the
      recommended dose levels for the Part II (Phase II) efficacy evaluation in each of the three
      disease cohorts.

      Dose evaluation will start in Cohorts 1 and 2 with Dose Level 1 and in Cohort 3 with Dose
      Level 2, sparing Dose Level 1 (see figure 1). Each of the cohorts will evaluate the safety of
      MB-CART19.1.

      In each dose level of each of the three cohorts three 3 + 3 patients will be treated. A
      particular dose level will be expanded to 6 patients if one patient out of 3 patients treated
      at that particular dose level develops DLT. Once this occurs, further dose-escalations are
      halted until the dose has proven to be safe in the expanded cohort. If 2 or more in a cohort
      of 6 patients develop DLT no further dose escalation is allowed, and the next lower dose
      level will be expanded to 6 patients in total. The highest dose among the dose levels tested
      at which no more than one out of six patients experiences DLT will be considered the MTD. In
      Dose Level 3, three additional patients will be treated, if no DLT occurred. Dose Level 0
      will be tested only if Dose Level 1 is not tolerable.

      Cohort 3 will Start with Dose Level 2. If Dose Level 2 is not tolerated, Dose Level 1 will be
      tested. DLT will be evaluated within 4 weeks after the infusion of MB-CART19.1. An interval
      of at least 28 days between the treatment of the first and the second patient in each dose
      level (and in each cohort) is mandatory.

      Part II (Phase II) will evaluate the efficacy and safety in patients treated with the
      recommended dose in Cohorts 1 to 3, respectively. After review of completed day 28 safety and
      efficacy data within Part I (Phase I) by the SMB, the design of Phase II, specifically the
      number and types of Phase II cohorts and the recommended dose level(s) for Phase II will be
      determined and thus, the number of patients to be treated will be calculated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Determination of the recommended dose of MB-CART19.1</measure>
    <time_frame>until day 28 after infusion of MB-CART19.1</time_frame>
    <description>Determined on the basis of the maximum tolerated dose (MTD); MTD is defined as the highest dose level at which &lt; 33% of patients experience Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT). Safety and toxicity assessment of MB-CART19.1 per adverse events (AE) reporting classified according to CTCAE version 5.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Determination of the Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days after infusion of MB-CART19.1 (and at month 3 in NHL patients not in CR on day 28)</time_frame>
    <description>ORR in ALL patients is defined as the rate of complete remission (CR, CRh); ORR in NHL patients is defined as the rate of overall response (CR or PR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Overall incidence and severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>throug study completion, an average of 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>per adverse events (AE) reporting classified according to CTCAE version 5.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Response to treatment for each timepoint</measure>
    <time_frame>day 28</time_frame>
    <description>ORR in ALL (Rate of CR/CRh)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Response to treatment for each timepoint</measure>
    <time_frame>day 28, week 12, month 6, 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate MRD-negative CR in ALL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Response to treatment for each timepoint</measure>
    <time_frame>day 28, patients not in CR on day 28: month 3</time_frame>
    <description>ORR in NHL/CLL (Rate of CR/PR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Occurence of B-cell depletion</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Circulating B cell numbers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I - Phenotype and persistence of MB-CART19.1</measure>
    <time_frame>days 2, 7, 10, 14, 28, weeks 8, 12, months 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, 60</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples for determination of persistence/phenotyping of infused MB-CART19.1 will be analysed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Overall incidence and severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>per adverse events (AE) reporting classified according to CTCAE version 5.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Number of patients with successful MB-CART19.1 production</measure>
    <time_frame>day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients meeting the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria for who an autologous MB-CART19.1 product can be generated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Rate of ALL patients achieving MRD negative CR</measure>
    <time_frame>day 28, week 12, month 6, 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate MRD-negative CR in ALL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of response rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 year after MB-CART19.1 infusion in patients not receiving alloSCT</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of survival and relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Occurrence of B cell depletion</measure>
    <time_frame>days 7, 10, 14, 28, weeks 8, 12, 16, months 6, 8, 10, 12, 24, 36, 48, 60</time_frame>
    <description>Circulating B cell numbers in the peripheral blood will be assessed by Flow cytometry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II - Phenotype and persistence of MB-CART19.1</measure>
    <time_frame>days 2, 7, 10, 14, 28, weeks 8, 12, months 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, 60</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples for determination of persistence/phenotyping of infused MB-CART19.1 will be analysed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Recurrent</condition>
  <condition>B-cell Lymphoma Recurrent</condition>
  <condition>B-cell Lymphoma Refractory</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Recurrent</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Refractory</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 0: 1x10e5 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In each dose level of each of the three cohorts three 3 + 3 patients will be treated. A particular dose level will be expanded to 6 patients if one patient out of 3 patients treated at that particular dose level develops DLT. Once this occurs, further dose-escalations are halted until the dose has proven to be safe in the expanded cohort. If 2 or more in a cohort of 6 patients develop DLT no further dose escalation is allowed, and the next lower dose level will be expanded to 6 patients in total. The highest dose among the dose levels tested at which no more than one out of six patients experiences DLT will be considered the MTD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 1: 5x10e5 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose evaluation will start in Cohorts 1 and 2 with Dose Level 1. In each dose level of each of the three cohorts three 3 + 3 patients will be treated. A particular dose level will be expanded to 6 patients if one patient out of 3 patients treated at that particular dose level develops DLT. Once this occurs, further dose-escalations are halted until the dose has proven to be safe in the expanded cohort. If 2 or more in a cohort of 6 patients develop DLT no further dose escalation is allowed, and the next lower dose level will be expanded to 6 patients in total. The highest dose among the dose levels tested at which no more than one out of six patients experiences DLT will be considered the MTD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 2: 1x10e6 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose evaluation will start in Cohort 3 with Dose Level 2, sparing Dose Level 1. If Dose Level 2 is not tolerated, Dose Level 1 will be tested. In each dose level of each of the three cohorts three 3 + 3 patients will be treated. A particular dose level will be expanded to 6 patients if one patient out of 3 patients treated at that particular dose level develops DLT. Once this occurs, further dose-escalations are halted until the dose has proven to be safe in the expanded cohort. If 2 or more in a cohort of 6 patients develop DLT no further dose escalation is allowed, and the next lower dose level will be expanded to 6 patients in total. The highest dose among the dose levels tested at which no more than one out of six patients experiences DLT will be considered the MTD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 3: 3x10e6 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In each dose level of each of the three cohorts three 3 + 3 patients will be treated. A particular dose level will be expanded to 6 patients if one patient out of 3 patients treated at that particular dose level develops DLT. Once this occurs, further dose-escalations are halted until the dose has proven to be safe in the expanded cohort. If 2 or more in a cohort of 6 patients develop DLT no further dose escalation is allowed, and the next lower dose level will be expanded to 6 patients in total. The highest dose among the dose levels tested at which no more than one out of six patients experiences DLT will be considered the MTD. In Dose Level 3, three additional patients will be treated, if no DLT occurred. Dose Level 0 will be tested only if Dose Level 1 is not tolerable.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II - Recommended dose MB-CART19.1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase II will evaluate the efficacy and safety in patients treated with the recommended dose in Cohorts 1 to 3, respectively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MB-CART19.1</intervention_name>
    <description>MB-CART19.1 consists of autologous CD19 Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) transduced CD4/CD8 enriched T cells targeting CD19-positive tumor cells in b cell malignancies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 0: 1x10e5 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 1: 5x10e5 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 2: 1x10e6 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: DL 3: 3x10e6 MB-CART19.1 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II - Recommended dose MB-CART19.1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD19-targeting CAR T cells</other_name>
    <other_name>Anti-CD19 CAR T cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients must have r/r CD19-expressing ALL or NHL/CLL

          -  CD19 expression must be detected on the malignant cells by flow cytometry (leukemia,
             malignant effusion in NHL) or immunohistochemistry (NHL);

          -  Age ≥ 1 year (if deemed fit by treating investigator);

          -  Absolute CD3+ T cell count ≥100/μl;

          -  ECOG performance score of 0-2 if &gt;16 years old, or Lansky performance score of &gt;50 if
             ≤16 years old at screening;

          -  No active Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, HIV1/2;

          -  No childbearing potential or negative pregnancy test at screening and before
             chemotherapy in women with childbearing potential;

          -  Signed and dated informed consent/assent by patients

          -  and meet the following disease-specific criteria:

        ALL:

          -  patients with &gt;5% blasts in BM (M2 or M3) after at least one standard chemotherapy and
             one salvage regimen who are ineligible for allogeneic stem cell transplant (alloSCT)
             or have refractory disease activity precluding alloSCT at this time, or

          -  patients who have relapsed post alloSCT at least 100 days posttransplant, with no
             evidence of active GVHD, and no longer taking immunosuppressive agents for at least 30
             days prior to enrollment.

          -  patients with Ph+ ALL if they are intolerant to tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI)
             therapy, or if they have r/r disease after treatment with at least 2 different TKIs.

          -  ALL patients with combined bone marrow and CNS and/or testicular relapse are eligible
             only if the extramedullary disease has been successfully cleared by conventional
             therapy at the time of inclusion (e.g. intrathecal chemotherapy, orchiectomy).

        Pediatric aggressive NHL (1-17 years):

          -  patients after at least one salvage chemotherapy as bridge to alloSCT or

          -  patients ineligible for alloSCT or

          -  patients who have relapsed post alloSCT at least 100 days posttransplant, with not
             evidence of active GVHD, and no longer taking immunosuppressive agents for at least 30
             days prior to enrollment.

          -  patients with CNS disease (excluding isolated CNS lymphoma) are eligible only if
             disease has been successfully cleared by intrathecal chemotherapy at the time of
             inclusion.

        Adult NHL:

          -  patients after at least one standard chemotherapy and one salvage regimen as bridge to
             alloSCT or

          -  patients who are ineligible for alloSCT or

          -  patients who have relapsed post alloSCT at least 100 days posttransplant, with no
             evidence of active GVHD, and no longer taking immunosuppressive agents for at least 30
             days prior to enrollment.

          -  patients with CNS disease (excluding isolated CNS lymphoma) are eligible only if
             disease has been successfully cleared by intrathecal chemotherapy at the time of
             inclusion.

        CLL:

          -  patients with r/r disease after established and approved treatment options have
             failed.

          -  patients not eligible or appropriate for conventional alloSCT.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Isolated CNS or testicular relapse in ALL;

          -  Isolated CNS lymphomas;

          -  Active solid brain metastases or history of solid brain metastases

          -  Current autoimmune disease, or history of autoimmune disease with potential CNS
             involvement;

          -  Active clinically significant CNS dysfunction (including but not limited to
             uncontrolled seizure disorders, cerebrovascular ischemia or hemorrhage, dementia,
             paralysis);

          -  History of an additional malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma
             in situ unless disease free for ≥3 years;

          -  Pulmonary function: Patients with pre-existing severe lung disease or an oxygen
             requirement of &gt;28% O2 supplementation or active pulmonary infiltrates on chest X-ray;

          -  Cardiac function: Fractional shortening &lt;28% or left ventricular ejection fraction
             &lt;50% by echocardiography;

          -  Renal function: GFR ≤29 mL/min/1.73 m2 by CKD-EPI for patients 18 yrs (Levey et al.
             2009) or creatinine clearance ≤29 mL/min/1.73 m2 by Schwartz formula (Schwartz et al.
             1976) for patients &lt;18 yrs of age;

          -  Liver function: Patients with a serum bilirubin &gt;3 times upper limit of normal or an
             AST or ALT &gt; 5 times upper limit of normal, unless due to leukemic liver infiltration
             in the estimation of the investigator;

          -  Rapidly progressive disease that in the estimation of the investigator would
             compromise ability to complete study therapy;

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding females;

          -  Medications:

               -  Systemic chemotherapies, corticosteroids with the exception of physiologic
                  replacement dosing, tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKI) within 7 days prior to
                  leukapheresis,

               -  Fludarabine/clofarabine or immunosuppressive drugs and antibodies (e.g.
                  rituximab, calcineurin inhibitors, blinatumomab) or investigational drugs or
                  donor lymphocyte transfusions or radiation therapy within 30 days prior to
                  apheresis,

               -  Alemtuzumab within 3 months prior to leukapheresis,

               -  Exception: Intrathecal chemotherapy is allowed prior to treatment, but should be
                  discontinued in ALL and BL 10 days prior to MB-CART19.1 infusion to limit risk of
                  neurotoxicities;

          -  Hypersensitivity against any drug or its ingredients/impurities that is scheduled or
             likely to be given during trial participation, e.g. as part of the mandatory
             lymphodepletion protocol, pre-medication for infusion, rescue medication/salvage
             therapies for treatment related toxicities;

          -  Intake of concomitant medication contraindicated for other reasons than
             hypersensitivity, e.g. live vaccines and fludarabine;

          -  Contraindication of trial related procedures as judged by the investigator, e.g.
             lumbar punctures for CSF sampling;

          -  Female patients of child-bearing potential not willing to practice a highly effective
             form of birth control from the time of enrollment and for 12 months after dosing the
             IMP;

          -  Male patients of fathering potential not willing to practice a highly effective form
             of birth control from the time of enrollment and for 12 months after dosing the IMP;

          -  Concurrent participation in another interventional trial that could interact with this
             trial, e.g. CAR T trials;

          -  Cerebral dysfunction, legal incapacity of adult patients;

          -  Committal to an institution on judicial or official order.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudia Rössig, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Univeristy Hospital Muenster</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandra Merckling</last_name>
    <phone>+49 2204 8306 6648</phone>
    <email>alexandra.merckling@miltenyi.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christine Schubert</last_name>
    <phone>+49 2204 8306 6564</phone>
    <email>christine.schubert@miltenyi.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Erlangen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andreas Mackensen, Prof.Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)9131 8535 954</phone>
      <email>andreas.mackensen@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Barbara Ferstl, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)9131 8543 104</phone>
      <email>barbara.ferstl@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Münster - Klink für Kinderheilkunde und Jugendmedizin / Pädiatrische Hämatologie und Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudia Rössig, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)251 83 47 741</phone>
      <email>rossig@ukmuenster.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Birgit Burkhardt, PD Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)251 83 52 840</phone>
      <email>birgit.burkhardt@ukmuenster.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Münster - Medizinische Klinik A / KMT Zentrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthias Stelljes, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 251 83 52801</phone>
      <email>matthias.stelljes@ukmuenster.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jan Henrik Mikesch, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 251 83 52801</phone>
      <email>jan-henrik.mikesch@ukmuenster.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

