<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03851965</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UTHDA-AC01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03851965</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of the Soluble Urokinase Plasminogen Activator Receptor in Non-cardiac Surgery (SPARSE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPARSE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Observational Study on Assessment of the Soluble Urokinase Plasminogen Activator Receptor in Adult Patients Undergoing Major Non-cardiac Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Thessaly</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Thessaly</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In critically ill patients, the soluble urokinase plasminogen activator receptor (suPAR)
      level is significantly increased. suPAR is an independent prognostic marker, and the change
      over time correlates with organ dysfunction. suPAR is elevated and has a prognostic value in
      patients with systemic inflammatory response syndrome, sepsis/septic shock, burn injuries,
      and traumatic brain injuries. SPARSE is a prospective observational study aiming to
      investigate if suPAR measured preoperatively and immediately after surgery can predict the
      risk of future complications and post-operative mortality in adults following major
      non-cardiac surgery. Participants will undergo sampling of peripheral venous blood,
      immediately after arrival to the Operating Room and at the Post-Anesthesia Care Unit, and
      plasma suPAR levels will be determined. In addition to routine hemodynamic data, sublingual
      microvascular flow will be measured using noninvasive technology. The primary endpoint will
      be the presence of complications and/or admission to ICU and/or mortality within the first 60
      postoperative days. Target enrollment will be 100 patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND

      Soluble urokinase plasminogen activator receptor

      The biomarker soluble urokinase plasminogen activator receptor (suPAR) is the soluble form of
      the cell membrane-bound protein urokinase plasminogen activator receptor (uPAR), which is
      expressed mainly on immune cells, endothelial cells, and smooth muscle cells. uPAR is
      released during inflammation or immune activation, and therefore the suPAR level reflects the
      extent of immune activation in the individual. All human beings have a baseline level of
      suPAR that is individually determined and increases with age. Studies have shown that the
      suPAR level is associated with morbidity and mortality in a number of acute and chronic
      diseases and in the general population. The suPAR level is elevated across diseases, and not
      solely associated with one specific disease. Therefore, suPAR is applicable as a prognostic
      marker and not as a diagnostic marker. This characteristic may be utilized for risk
      stratification in unselected patients.

      In critically ill patients, the suPAR level is significantly increased. suPAR is an
      independent prognostic marker, and the change over time correlates with organ dysfunction.
      suPAR is elevated and has a prognostic value in patients with: SIRS (systemic inflammatory
      response syndrome), sepsis/septic shock, burn injuries, and traumatic brain injuries. The
      suPAR level reflects the body's immune response to infections, and the level increases with
      the severity of the infection. In patients with organ dysfunction, the suPAR value is often a
      two-digit value. In particular hepatic and renal dysfunction affects the suPAR level.

      suPAR in surgery

      The suPAR level is elevated in patients with infections, chronic diseases, and cancer
      compared to healthy individuals. A high suPAR level is associated with increased mortality
      risk, poor prognosis, postoperative pneumonia, and prosthetic joint infection. suPAR is a
      well-studied biomarker predicting prognosis, disease severity, and organ dysfunction and is
      being considered as a marker of the individual's inflammatory status. It has been
      demonstrated that biomarkers are able to improve triage and are effective in identifying high
      and low risk patients among acutely admitted patients. Improving the preoperative risk
      stratification using biomarkers may optimize the patient's clinical outcome.

      AIM

      SPARSE is a single-center observational study aiming to investigate if suPAR measured
      preoperatively and immediately after surgery can predict the risk of future complications and
      post-operative mortality in adults following major non-cardiac surgery.

      METHODS

      Design

      This is a prospective observational study designed in accordance with the declaration of
      Helsinki. The study will be register at Clinical Trials.gov and will be approved by the
      Institutional Review Board of the University Hospital of Larisa, under reference number.

      Management of Anesthesia and Surgical Procedures

      Endotracheal intubation and anesthetic care will be performed according to institutional
      routine. Intravenous induction of general anaesthesia will include midazolam 0.15-0.35 mg/kg
      iv over 20-30 seconds, fentanyl 1μg/kg, propofol 1.5-2 mg/kg, ketamine 0.2 mg/kg (intravenous
      bolus), and rocurnium 0.6 mg/kg. All drugs will be prepared in labelled syringes and
      induction will be achieved by administration of a predetermined iv bolus dose on the basis of
      the patient's weight and/or age. Laryngoscopy and intubation will proceed in a standard
      fashion, while the position of the endotracheal tube will be confirmed by auscultation and
      capnography/capnometry. The patients will then connected to an automated ventilator (Draeger
      Primus®; Drägerwerk AG &amp; Co., Lübeck, Germany).

      All patients will be ventilated using a lung-protective strategy with tidal volume of 7
      mL/kg, positive end-expiratory pressure of 6-8 cmH2O, plateau pressures &lt;30 cmH2O, and
      recruitment maneuvers repeated every 30 min after tracheal intubation. Maintenance of general
      anesthesia will include desflurane 1.0 MAC with 40% oxygen and 60% air, while intraoperative
      dose changes will be left to the anesthesiologist in charge of the patient. Depth of
      anesthesia (bispectral index-BIS, Covidien, France) will be monitored, with the target
      ranging between 40 and 60. Normocapnia will be maintained by adjusting the respiratory rate
      as needed, while normothermia (37ºC) will be maintained throughout the intraoperative period.

      Sampling and laboratory measurements

      Participants will undergo sampling of peripheral venous blood, immediately after arrival to
      the OR, and at the Post-Anesthesia Care Unit (PACU). Blood samples drawn from all patients
      and EDTA plasma will be stored at -80° C until suPAR levels are determined.

      Microcirculation flow analysis

      In addition to routine hemodynamic data, sublingual microvascular flow will be measured using
      noninvasive technology. Measurements will be obtained preoperatively (PRE), intraoperatively
      (INT), and postoperatively after arrival in the PACU (POST). At each time point, the
      microcirculatory network of the sublingual mucosa will be imaged using sidestream darkfield
      (SDF+) videomicroscopy which has an increased optical resolution resulting in one pixel
      recording an area of 0.56 μm2.

      Data Collection and Monitoring

      Data analysis will be based on predefined data points on a prospective data collection form.
      The staff will be blinded to measurements until the end of the study and all data are
      analyzed. Clinical monitoring throughout the study will be performed to maximize protocol
      adherence, while an independent Data and Safety Monitoring research staff will monitor
      safety, ethical, and scientific aspects of the study. Data collection will include
      demographics, anesthesia parameters, C-reactive protein, P-POSSUM score, ACS-NSQIP score,
      APACHE II, SOFA, and the Charlson Age-Comorbidity Index (Charlson score). A SAS macro based
      on ICD-10 diagnoses will be used to calculate the Charlson score. Two other simpler models
      adding predictive value to the ASA classification will be also used; the Surgical Mortality
      Probability Model and a similar model proposed by Glance and Donati.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 5, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 5, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the first 90 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with postoperative complications</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants admitted to Intensive Care Unit</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the first 60 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants admitted to Intensive Care Unit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of deaths</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the first 60 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of deaths</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with intraoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with desaturation [SpO2 &lt;92% for 3 minutes or more], need for unplanned recruitment maneuvers, hypotension [defined as systolic blood pressure &lt;90 mmHg or mean arterial pressure &lt;65 mmHg for 3 minutes or more or need of vasoactive drugs for correction]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with need for unplanned vasoactive drugs during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with need for vasoactive drugs not planned before and/or continuous infusion during surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with acute new arrhythmia during sugery</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with atrial fibrillation, sustained ventricular tachycardia, supraventricular tachycardia, and/or cardiac arrest during surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of reintubations</measure>
    <time_frame>At 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants being reintubated after extubation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>At 30 days, at 90 days, and at 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgery--Complications</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Soluble Urokinase Plasminogen Activator Receptor</intervention_name>
    <description>Preoperative and postoperative determination of the Soluble Urokinase Plasminogen Activator Receptor levels in patients undergoing non-cardiac major surgery.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive patients who are scheduled to undergo elective major non-cardiac surgery with
        expected duration ≥2 hours under general anesthesia
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All operative approaches

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists' (ASA) physical status I to IV

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Any infection within the previous 4 weeks

          -  Severe liver disease

          -  Renal replacement therapy pre-operatively

          -  Previously received transplant

          -  Allergies

          -  Inflammatory disorders

          -  Immune system disorders

          -  Connective tissue disease

          -  Administration of opioids during the past week

          -  Asthma

          -  Obesity (BMI ≥ 30 kg m-2)

          -  Mental disability

          -  Severe psychiatric disease

          -  Alcohol or other abuse,

          -  Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity

          -  Subjects within the exclusion period of another study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Athanasios Chalkias, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Thessaly, Faculty of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Larisa, Department of Anesthesiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Larisa</city>
        <state>Thessaly</state>
        <zip>41110</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stephens RW, Nielsen HJ, Christensen IJ, Thorlacius-Ussing O, Sørensen S, Danø K, Brünner N. Plasma urokinase receptor levels in patients with colorectal cancer: relationship to prognosis. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1999 May 19;91(10):869-74.</citation>
    <PMID>10340907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Svendsen MN, Ytting H, Brünner N, Nielsen HJ, Christensen IJ. Preoperative concentrations of suPAR and MBL proteins are associated with the development of pneumonia after elective surgery for colorectal cancer. Surg Infect (Larchmt). 2006 Oct;7(5):463-71.</citation>
    <PMID>17083312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eugen-Olsen J, Andersen O, Linneberg A, Ladelund S, Hansen TW, Langkilde A, Petersen J, Pielak T, Møller LN, Jeppesen J, Lyngbaek S, Fenger M, Olsen MH, Hildebrandt PR, Borch-Johnsen K, Jørgensen T, Haugaard SB. Circulating soluble urokinase plasminogen activator receptor predicts cancer, cardiovascular disease, diabetes and mortality in the general population. J Intern Med. 2010 Sep;268(3):296-308. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2796.2010.02252.x. Epub 2010 May 28.</citation>
    <PMID>20561148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Thessaly</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Athanasios Chalkias, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Asst. Professor of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Soluble urokinase plasminogen activator receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Major non-cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>Perioperative</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plasminogen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All IPD that underlie results in a publication</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Starting 6 months after publication and for the next 6 months.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data access requests will be reviewed by an external Independent Review Panel. Requestors will be required to sign a Data Access Agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 11, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/65/NCT03851965/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 11, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/65/NCT03851965/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

