<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03854981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18316</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03854981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-operative Exercise and Nutrition Therapy on Cardio-metabolic Health in Patients Undergoing Bariatric Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Pre-operative Exercise and Nutrition Therapy on Insulin Resistance and Vascular Health in Patients Undergoing Bariatric Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is a major health concern that has been associated with an estimated 2.8 million
      deaths worldwide each year. The number of individuals considered obese with a Body Mass Index
      (BMI) above 30 kg/m2 has grown to more than 500 million. The increased morbidity and
      mortality associated with obesity stems from a long list of comorbidities, including
      hypertension, coronary artery disease, stroke, cancer, and type 2 diabetes (T2D). Bariatric
      surgery is an emerging intervention that has been used frequently to induce weight loss for
      obese individuals and it has been shown to improve glycemic control and insulin resistance in
      people at risk for type 2 diabetes. Surgery may also lead to healthy improvements in
      inflammation, immune cells and vascular health. It is already known that exercise and weight
      loss from lifestyle modification can improve glycemic control, insulin resistance,
      inflammation, and arterial stiffness. However, no work has been done to examine a combination
      of bariatric surgery and pre-surgery exercise. Recent work by the team has evidence
      demonstrating that health status pre-surgery has an impact on post-surgery outcomes. Such
      findings suggest that improvements in health status from exercise before surgery may improve
      surgery outcomes as well as surgery-induced health outcomes. To date, no study has
      systematically examined the role of exercise on the prevalence of surgery complications or on
      post-surgery weight loss, glycemic control, and insulin resistance. Moreover, no work
      currently exists on exercise, with or without bariatric surgery on adipose tissue derived
      inflammation. Therefore, the purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of
      pre-surgery lifestyle intervention with exercise on bariatric surgery outcomes. To test this
      objective, subjects will participate in a match paired study, based on BMI. Subjects will
      undergo testing of blood chemistry and related measures of health before (pre-test) and after
      (post) intervention. Then all subjects will receive bariatric surgery. Post surgery outcomes
      will be assessed by examining surgery operating time, changes in blood chemistry, adipose
      tissue biopsies and other measures indicative of glucose and vascular health. After this
      surgery, subjects will return for testing about 30d later.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 11, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 22, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Insulin Resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion, up to about 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mixed Meal Tolerance Test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Augmentation Index in %</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion, up to about 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Arterial Stiffness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Blood lipids in mg/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion, up to about 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cholesterol and triglycerides</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Stay Post Surgery in minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Recovery from surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operating time in minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Surgical Procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Length of Surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in blood glucose in mg/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion, up to about 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>For the Mixed Meal Tolerance Test</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in blood pressure in mmHg</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion, up to about 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>At the Mixed Meal Tolerance Test</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight and height will be combined to determine BMI in kg/m^2</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion, up to about 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>At the Mixed Meal tolerance Test</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of adiponectin in pg/mg</measure>
    <time_frame>Surgical Procedure</time_frame>
    <description>From adipose biopsy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of leptin in pg/mg</measure>
    <time_frame>Surgical Procedure</time_frame>
    <description>From adipose biopsy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Bariatric Surgery Candidate</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>If subjects are assigned to this group they will not be provided materials to increase exercise participation. Subjects will however be asked to participate in the standard education sessions that are provided to all bariatric surgery patients. This standard care includes meetings with a nutritionist, psychologist, and bariatric surgeon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise + Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to exercise 5 days/week for 30 min/day at an intensity of 65-85% of their measured HRmax. Walking will be the main type of exercise. In addition to this training program, subject's will participate in the standard education sessions that are provided to all bariatric surgery patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to exercise 5 days/week in addition to receiving standard care before bariatric surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise + Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard preoperative care of bariatric surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise + Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and Females, 18-70 years of age

          -  BMI &gt;30 and &lt;70 kg/m2

          -  Sedentary (Not currently participating in exercise training: &gt;30 min. of physical
             activity per day, &gt;3 days/week)

          -  HCT for women &gt; 36%, Men &gt;38%

          -  Non-pregnant (women).-self reported

          -  Smoker (if bariatric surgery patient) or non-smoker (enrolled for the dietary portion
             of the study)

          -  Has the ability/willingness to participate in the study and agree to any of the arms
             involved in the study.

          -  No prior surgical procedure for obesity with the exception of a laparoscopic
             adjustable gastric banding (LAGB) under the condition that the band had not been
             adjusted in less than or equal to 1 year

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently participating in exercise training: &gt;30 min. of physical activity per day,
             &gt;2 days/week)

          -  Cigarette smoking (presently or in the past 6 months), drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  History of congestive heart failure, ischemic heart disease, severe pulmonary disease.

          -  History of cancer (within 5 years)

          -  Diagnosed as insulin-dependent diabetes.

          -  Change in psychotropic medication dosage in past six weeks

          -  AST or ALT &gt; 3 times normal range

          -  Currently involved in any active weight loss treatment program (other than
             self-directed attempt at calorie restricting diet) or lean patients (BMI &lt;29 kg/m2).

          -  Current purging behavior occurring &gt; once a week over the past six weeks (self-induced
             vomiting for weight control purposes, laxative or diuretic abuse)

          -  Revisional bariatric procedures including a RYGB reversal to a SG or a LAGB revision
             to a SG or RYGB if the band has been adjusted in greater than or equal to 1 year.

          -  Active psychotic illness, including bipolar affective disorders.

          -  Evidence of current suicidality or homicidality

          -  Conditions associated with significant cognitive dysfunction (e.g. dementia) or
             medical instability that puts the participant at risk

          -  Contraindication to exercise (severe/uncontrolled CVD; inability to walk 2 blocks,
             bone or joint problems )

          -  Allergy to &quot;caine&quot; family drugs (e.g. lidocaine).

          -  Currently taking active weight suppression medication (e.g. phentermine,bupropion SR,
             topiramate).

          -  On medication known to cause substantial weight gain (e.g. atypical antipsychotics
             such as olanzapine, sodium valproate, steroid therapy). This would not include
             medications commonly used in this population that usually result in only mild weight
             loss (e.g. SSRIs).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven K Malin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Kashyap SR. Differences in Weight Loss and Gut Hormones: Rouen-Y Gastric Bypass and Sleeve Gastrectomy Surgery. Curr Obes Rep. 2015 Jun;4(2):279-86. doi: 10.1007/s13679-015-0151-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26627222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Bena J, Abood B, Pothier CE, Bhatt DL, Nissen S, Brethauer SA, Schauer PR, Kirwan JP, Kashyap SR. Attenuated improvements in adiponectin and fat loss characterize type 2 diabetes non-remission status after bariatric surgery. Diabetes Obes Metab. 2014 Dec;16(12):1230-8. doi: 10.1111/dom.12376. Epub 2014 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25132119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shada AL, Hallowell PT, Schirmer BD, Smith PW. Aerobic exercise is associated with improved weight loss after laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding. Obes Surg. 2013 May;23(5):608-12. doi: 10.1007/s11695-012-0826-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23196991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coen PM, Tanner CJ, Helbling NL, Dubis GS, Hames KC, Xie H, Eid GM, Stefanovic-Racic M, Toledo FG, Jakicic JM, Houmard JA, Goodpaster BH. Clinical trial demonstrates exercise following bariatric surgery improves insulin sensitivity. J Clin Invest. 2015 Jan;125(1):248-57. doi: 10.1172/JCI78016. Epub 2014 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>25437877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khanna V, Malin SK, Bena J, Abood B, Pothier CE, Bhatt DL, Nissen S, Watanabe R, Brethauer SA, Schauer PR, Kirwan JP, Kashyap SR. Adults with long-duration type 2 diabetes have blunted glycemic and β-cell function improvements after bariatric surgery. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2015 Mar;23(3):523-6. doi: 10.1002/oby.21021. Epub 2015 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>25651277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mechanick JI, Youdim A, Jones DB, Garvey WT, Hurley DL, McMahon MM, Heinberg LJ, Kushner R, Adams TD, Shikora S, Dixon JB, Brethauer S; American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists; Obesity Society; American Society for Metabolic &amp; Bariatric Surgery. Clinical practice guidelines for the perioperative nutritional, metabolic, and nonsurgical support of the bariatric surgery patient--2013 update: cosponsored by American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists, The Obesity Society, and American Society for Metabolic &amp; Bariatric Surgery. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2013 Mar;21 Suppl 1:S1-27. doi: 10.1002/oby.20461.</citation>
    <PMID>23529939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Niemi N, Solomon TP, Haus JM, Kelly KR, Filion J, Rocco M, Kashyap SR, Barkoukis H, Kirwan JP. Exercise training with weight loss and either a high- or low-glycemic index diet reduces metabolic syndrome severity in older adults. Ann Nutr Metab. 2012;61(2):135-41.</citation>
    <PMID>23036993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Haus JM, Solomon TP, Blaszczak A, Kashyap SR, Kirwan JP. Insulin sensitivity and metabolic flexibility following exercise training among different obese insulin-resistant phenotypes. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Nov 15;305(10):E1292-8. doi: 10.1152/ajpendo.00441.2013. Epub 2013 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24064339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakamura K, Fuster JJ, Walsh K. Adipokines: a link between obesity and cardiovascular disease. J Cardiol. 2014 Apr;63(4):250-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jjcc.2013.11.006. Epub 2013 Dec 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24355497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sjöström L, Lindroos AK, Peltonen M, Torgerson J, Bouchard C, Carlsson B, Dahlgren S, Larsson B, Narbro K, Sjöström CD, Sullivan M, Wedel H; Swedish Obese Subjects Study Scientific Group. Lifestyle, diabetes, and cardiovascular risk factors 10 years after bariatric surgery. N Engl J Med. 2004 Dec 23;351(26):2683-93.</citation>
    <PMID>15616203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schauer PR, Burguera B, Ikramuddin S, Cottam D, Gourash W, Hamad G, Eid GM, Mattar S, Ramanathan R, Barinas-Mitchel E, Rao RH, Kuller L, Kelley D. Effect of laparoscopic Roux-en Y gastric bypass on type 2 diabetes mellitus. Ann Surg. 2003 Oct;238(4):467-84; discussion 84-5.</citation>
    <PMID>14530719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Finnegan S, Fealy CE, Filion J, Rocco MB, Kirwan JP. β-Cell dysfunction is associated with metabolic syndrome severity in adults. Metab Syndr Relat Disord. 2014 Mar;12(2):79-85. doi: 10.1089/met.2013.0083. Epub 2013 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24283920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu B, Kuang L, Liu J. Bariatric surgery relieves type 2 diabetes and modulates inflammatory factors and coronary endothelium eNOS/iNOS expression in db/db mice. Can J Physiol Pharmacol. 2014 Jan;92(1):70-7. doi: 10.1139/cjpp-2013-0034. Epub 2013 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24383875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yassine HN, Marchetti CM, Krishnan RK, Vrobel TR, Gonzalez F, Kirwan JP. Effects of exercise and caloric restriction on insulin resistance and cardiometabolic risk factors in older obese adults--a randomized clinical trial. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2009 Jan;64(1):90-5. doi: 10.1093/gerona/gln032. Epub 2009 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19164269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Virginia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven K. Malin, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Insulin Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Risk</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

