<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02633878</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHOP-IT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02633878</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chinese Herbal Medicine and Micronized Progesterone for Live Births in Threatened Miscarriage</brief_title>
  <official_title>Chinese Herbal Medicine and Micronized Progesterone for Live Births in Threatened Miscarriage: An International Cooperative Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Heilongjiang University of Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Heilongjiang University of Chinese Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Threatened miscarriage is manifested by vaginal bleeding, with or without abdominal pain,
      while the cervix is closed and the fetus is viable and inside the uterine cavity. Threatened
      miscarriage is a common complication of pregnancy occurring in 20% of all clinically
      recognized pregnancies and about half of these will eventually result in pregnancy loss. The
      goal of this double-bind, randomized and double dummy controlled trial is to determine which
      of the two oral medications, CHM or micronized progesterone, and will mostly likely result in
      live birth in women with threatened miscarriage. We will evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      CHM and micronized progesterone for treating threatened miscarriage in this trial. Our
      primary outcome of this trial is a live birth. We hypothesize that: 1. treatment with CHM
      plus micronized progesterone placebo or micronized progesterone plus CHM placebo or CHM plus
      Micronized progesterone is more likely to result in live birth than the control arm which
      will be CHM placebo plus micronized progesterone placebo; 2. CHM plus micronized progesterone
      placebo and micronized progesterone plus CHM placebo will have similar treatment effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The causes of spontaneous miscarriage are diverse and comprise chromosomal, genetic,
      anatomical, immunological, hormonal, infectious and psychological factors, the other factors
      contribute to an increased risk include advancing paternal and maternal age and mothers with
      systemic diseases, such as diabetes or thyroid dysfunction. However, the incidence is
      difficult to determine precisely due to occur very early during a pregnancy and almost 30% of
      early pregnancy may go unrecognized; the pathogenesis of pregnancy loss in this condition is
      still remains obscure. Compared with healthy women, the women with threatened miscarriage not
      only were found to have increased rate of antepartum haemorrhage, prelabour rupture of the
      membranes, preterm delivery, and intrauterine growth restriction, but also suffer significant
      psychological impairment including considerable anxiety and stress, depression, sleep
      disturbances, anger, and marital disturbances.

      To date, therapies have limited effectiveness in treating threatened miscarriage and are
      empirical. Bed rest does not prevent pregnancy loss. Acetaminophen may have some effects on
      relieving pain only. The most commonly used prescription medication was human chorionic
      gonadotropin (hCG), maintaining the luteotrophic effects to support continued secretion of
      estrogen and progesterone, However, the beneficial effects of hCG still cannot be verified.
      Progesterone is another most commonly used traditional medication to treat threatened
      miscarriage, maintaining the endometrial proliferation and preventing spontaneous pregnancy
      loss. A number of recent studies in women with threatened miscarriage that has shown a
      reduction in pregnancy loss with progesterone treatment. Progestogens are a group of
      hormones, including both the natural female sex hormone progesterone and the synthetic forms.
      Micronized progesterone is a kind of progesterone; it is structurally and pharmacologically
      very similar to natural progesterone and has good oral bioavailability. It is especially
      suitable for women with threatened miscarriage as it does not have androgenic or oestrogenic
      effects on the foetus. A recent review of maternal use of Micronized progesterone during
      pregnancy also found no evidence for an increased risk of congenital malformations. However
      it may only be suitable to treat women with threatened miscarriage who have low progesterone
      levels due to corpus luteum deficiency at the first trimester pregnancy. There is no evidence
      to identify the beneficial effects of progesterone to treat threatened miscarriage due to
      others factors. At the same time, progesterone treatment is also expensive. New or adjuvant
      treatments that are suitable to treat women with threatened miscarriage due to various
      factors, and readily accessible, affordable, and safe are needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Live birth rate</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;20 weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative live birth rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ongoing pregnancy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Beyond gestation 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative Ongoing pregnancy rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ongoing pregnancy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Beyond gestation 20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative Ongoing pregnancy rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ongoing pregnancy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Beyond gestation 32 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative Ongoing pregnancy rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Live birth rate</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;37 weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative live birth rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Premature live birth rate</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;24, but&lt; weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative Premature live birth rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-β2 glycoprotein-I antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The number or percentage of Anti-β2 glycoprotein-I antibodies positive patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lupus anticoagulant</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The number or percentage of Lupus anticoagulant positive patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-cardiolipin antibody</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The number or percentage of Anti-cardiolipin antibody positive patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy loss rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Before 20 weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>The number or percentage of patients who have a pregnancy loss</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy loss rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After 20 weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>The number or percentage of patients who have a pregnancy loss</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Progesterone</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, each visit and end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Value (Units: ng/ml)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Zung Self-Rating Anxiety Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-12 Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change in scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event and/or serious adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>During treatment, the second and third trimester, postpartum, fetus and newborn</time_frame>
    <description>Pregnancy-induced hypertension, diabetes and antepartum haemorrhage, preterm birth, postdate delivery, preeclampsia and so on</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1656</enrollment>
  <condition>Threatened Miscarriage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHM+MP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CHM one dose in the morning and in the evening respectively until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days); MP 100mg tablet by mouth, every 8 hours until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHM Placebo+MP Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CHM Placebo one dose in the morning and in the evening respectively until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days); MP Placebo 100mg tablet by mouth, every 8 hours until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHM+MP Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CHM one dose in the morning and in the evening respectively until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days); MP Placebo 100mg tablet by mouth, every 8 hours until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHM Placebo+MP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CHM Placebo one dose in the morning and in the evening respectively until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days); MP 100mg tablet by mouth, every 8 hours until 12 weeks of gestations (84 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chinese Herbal Medicine plus Progesterone Capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; Granules plus Micronized Progesterone Capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHM+MP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; plus Micronized Progesterone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chinese Herbal Medicine Placebo plus Progesterone Capsules Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; Granules Placebo plus Micronized Progesterone Capsules Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHM Placebo+MP Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; Placebo plus Micronized Progesterone Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chinese Herbal Medicine plus Progesterone Capsules Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; Granules plus Micronized Progesterone Capsules Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHM+MP Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; plus Micronized Progesterone Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chinese Herbal Medicine Placebo plus Micronized Progesterone</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; Granules Placebo plus Micronized Progesterone Capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHM Placebo+MP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>&quot;New Shoutai Pill&quot; Placebo plus Micronized Progesterone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          1. Age of women between 20-37 years.

          2. Pregnant. The fetus is viable inside the uterine cavity during early pregnancy[1]
             (5-10 week gestations /35-70 days) as confirmed by positive serum hCG tests and
             ultrasound, and need to meet either of the following two terms: ① vaginal bleeding
             with or without abdominal pain, while the cervix is closed by speculum exam;
             ②Recurrent miscarriage (≥2 prior pregnancy losses including biochemical pregnancy and
             intrauterine pregnancy loss or a pregnancy loss ≥ 6 weeks from LMP).

        Exclusion criteria

          1. Multiple pregnancies (include twin pregnancies).

          2. Ectopic pregnancy. We will define an ectopic pregnancy as any suspected adnexal mass
             or large amounts of free fluid in the pelvis without an accompanying intrauterine
             pregnancy.

          3. Pregnancies of Unknown Location (PUL). This will include pregnancies with an hCG level
             &gt;2500mIU/mL without visualization of an intrauterine or extrauterine (i.e. ectopic)
             pregnancies.

          4. (4)Non-viable pregnancy. We will define a non-viable pregnancy as: ①an intrauterine
             pregnancy with a fetal pole without visualized fetal heart motion (&gt;49 days); ②a
             gestational sac&gt;20 mm in any diameter without a yolk sac; ③absence of a normal
             gestational sac at 5 weeks of pregnancy, absence of a yolk sac at 5.5-6 weeks of
             pregnancy, or absence of cardiac activity at 7 weeks of pregnancy by ultrasound;
             ④falling serum hCG values on serial visits or between baseline and randomization
             visit, or serial serum hCG levels which show a plateau (2-day increase ≤ 10%).

          5. Intrauterine abnormalities and Fibroids distorting uterine cavity (as assessed by
             ultrasound).

          6. Bleeding attributed to a vulvar, vaginal, or cervical source unrelated to the
             pregnancy.

          7. For this threatened miscarriage, use of the same or similar Chinese medicine and/or
             progesterone more than one week.

          8. Use of agents that may contribute to bleeding such as aspirin, NSAIDs, etc.

          9. Presence of a congenital or acquired bleeding diathesis, i.e. Hemophilia, Von
             Willebrands's Disease, use of anti-coagulants, etc.

         10. Presence of contributing major medical disorders (regardless of severity). These
             include poorly controlled diabetes, uncontrolled hypertension, systemic lupus
             erythematosus (SLE), untreated or active cancer (any cancer in remission or
             non-melanoma skin cancer is not included in the exclusion criteria), liver disease,
             renal disease, rheumatoid arthritis, cardiac disease, pulmonary disease other than
             mild asthma, neurologic disease requiring medical treatment, uncontrolled
             hypothyroidism, uncontrolled seizure disorder. Untreated vitamin B12 deficiency,
             severe anemia (hct &lt; 30%), hemophilia, gout, nasal polyps, among others.

         11. Known current or recent alcohol abuse or illicit drug use.

         12. Known abnormal parental karyotype.

         13. Unwilling to give informed consent.

         14. Unwillingness to be randomized and do not want to take daily medications according to
             the protocol for up to 12 week gestations (84 days).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Participants should be in pregnancy</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>37 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xiaoke Wu, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>First Affiliated Hospital of Heilongjiang Chinese Medicine University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiaoke Wu, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+0086-13796025599</phone>
    <email>xiaokewu2002@vip.sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shenzhen Hospital of Beijing University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenzhen</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Huiru Tang</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Huiru Tang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Daqing Longnan Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daqing</city>
        <state>Heilongjiang</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xuewu Zhou</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xuewu Zhou</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xuzhou Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xuzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bei Zhang</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bei Zhang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xuzhou Maternal and Child Health Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xuzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zhenxing Hu</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhenxing Hu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Jiangxi University of Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanchang</city>
        <state>Jiangxi</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ruining Liang</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruining Liang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dalian Maternity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dalian</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rui Cao</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rui Cao</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanxi Province Hospital of Chinese medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taiyuan</city>
        <state>Shanxi</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jinfeng Zhang</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jinfeng Zhang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hangzhou hospital of Chinese medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Qin Zhang</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Qin Zhang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wenzhou Hospital of Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wenzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yun Sun</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yun Sun</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Heilongjiang University of Chinese Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xiaoke Wu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Obstetrics and Gynecology Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Threatened Miscarriage</keyword>
  <keyword>The First Trimester</keyword>
  <keyword>Micronized Progesterone</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese Herbal Medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Live Birth</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Spontaneous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Threatened</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Progesterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Subject's privacy is protected undoubtedly at the time of the informed consent signing</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

