<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02639325</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>160041</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>16-N-0041</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02639325</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tumor Related Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tumor Related Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Some people with brain tumors have seizures related to the tumor. This is called
      tumor-related epilepsy. Usually brain tumors are treated by removing as much of the brain
      tumor as possible without causing problems. Researchers think this may improve the outcome
      for people with brain tumors. It may completely relieve or greatly reduce the number of
      seizures they have.

      Objectives:

      To evaluate people with brain tumors that are associated with seizures and to offer surgical
      treatment. Also, to study how surgery affects seizures.

      Eligibility:

      People age 8 and older who have a brain tumor with associated seizures. They must be willing
      to have brain surgery to treat their epilepsy.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with a review of their medical records.

      Participants will have a medical history and physical exam.

      Participants will be admitted to the hospital at NIH. They will have

      Medical history

      Physical exam

      Neurological exam

      Tests of memory, attention, and thinking

      Questions about their symptoms and quality of life

      Blood drawn

      They may also have:

      MRI or CT scan. They will lie on a table that slides in and out of a machine that takes
      pictures. For part of the MRI, they will get a dye through an intravenous (IV) catheter.

      Video electroencephalography monitoring. Electrodes will be placed on the scalp. The
      participant s brain waves will be recorded while doing normal activities. Participants will
      be videotaped.

      Participants will keep a seizure diary before and after surgery.

      Participants will have surgery to remove their brain tumor and the brain area where their
      seizures start.

      They will stay in the hospital up to a week after surgery.

      Participants have for follow-up visits at NIH.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      This protocol is being performed to 1) study the natural history and disease pathogenesis in
      patients with tumor related epilepsy, 2) collect prospective data on seizure outcomes
      following standard surgical treatment of brain tumors with associated seizures2, 3) follow
      the clinical course of patients after surgical resection of brain tumors with associated
      seizures, such as outcomes in seizure activity as they relate to type of tumor and extent of
      resection, 4) investigate neuropsychological and cognitive outcomes as they relate to
      surgical and seizure outcomes, 5) evaluate patient reported outcomes such as symptom burden
      changes as a result of surgical resection in patients with tumor-related epilepsy, 6) examine
      changes in structural and, when available, functional imaging in the context of tumor related
      epilepsy before and after surgical resection, 8) investigate molecular markers of
      tumor-related seizures in tumor and peritumoral specimens and, when available, to compare
      them to electrophysiological markers of tumor-related seizure activity.

      Study Population

      Patients 8 years and older with brain tumors and associated seizures may participate in this
      study.

      Study Design

      Patients will be screened by study neurosurgeon or neuro-oncologists to verify their
      confirmed or likely diagnosis of brain tumor and associated seizures. Patients confirmed to
      have a brain tumor with associated seizures will be offered standard diagnostic and surgical
      procedures. Non-invasive diagnostic procedures include structural MRI and neuropsychological,
      cognitive, and outcome assessments. Some patients may receive functional MRI when clinically
      indicated, which will be performed under separate NIH protocols. Prior to tumor resection,
      diagnostic invasive monitoring with intracranial electrodes for further localization of
      seizure focus and identification of eloquent cortex may be clinically required. In these
      cases, invasive monitoring will be performed under a separte protocol, 11-N-0051 Epilepsy
      Surgery. Patients will be followed for three-six months after the surgical procedure to
      collect prospective data on seizure outcomes following standard surgical treatment of brain

      tumors with associated seizures. Patients may also be seen at one year following surgery if
      medically stable and healthy. Participants in this protocol will not forego other standard
      treatments for their brain tumor, including chemotherapy and radiation treatment.
      Participation in this protocol will not preclude eligibility or participation in other NIH
      clinical trials.

      Outcome Measures

      The primary outcome measure is the change in seizure frequency, as measured by the Engel
      scale before and 3-6 months after treatment. Secondary outcome measures include 1) mean Engel
      Class and absolute and relative change in seizure frequency three-six months after surgery
      stratified by the type of brain tumor and location and Engel scale, seizure frequency, and
      mean Engel Class and absolute and relative change in seizure frequency one year after surgery
      stratified by the type of brain tumor and location; 2) extent of tumor and peri-tumoral
      resection as seen on MRI imaging and correlation with seizure outcome; 3) changes in
      neuropsychological and cognitive assessment following surgical resection stratified by
      location and type of tumor and extent of resection; 4) longitudinal changes in symptom burden
      and interference scores using established instruments in brain tumor patients; 5) changes in
      structural imaging following surgical resection; 6) change in the use of anti-epileptic
      medication; and 7) percentage of patients with permanent neurological side-effects from
      surgical treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 26, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in seizure frequency, as measured by the Engel scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The Engel scale of patients 3-6 months after treatment.Engel s classification:Class I: patients who were completely seizure free, had auras only, or had convulsions with drug withdrawal only;Class II: rare disabling seizures or nocturnal seizures only;Class III: worthwhile improvement (frequent seizures but fewer than previously);Class IV: no improvement (frequent seizures with unchanged frequency compared to before surgery). Seizure frequency before and after surgical resection will be documented to determine Engel classification.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Engel Class stratified by the type of brain tumor and location</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Mean Engel Class three to six months after surgery stratified by the type of brain tumor and location and Engel scale, seizure frequency, and mean Engel Class one year after surgery stratified by the type of brain tumor and location</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of tumor and peri-tumoral resection as seen on MRI imaging and correlation with seizure outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Extent of tumor resection as seen on MRI imaging and correlation with seizure outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neuropsychological and cognitive assessment following surgical resection stratified by location and type of tumor and extent of resection</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in neuropsychological and cognitive assessment following surgical resection stratified by location and type of tumor and extent of resection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal changes in symptom burden and interference scores using established instruments in brain tumor patients</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in symptom burden and interference with daily activities and quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in structural imaging following surgical resection</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in structural imaging following surgical resection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the use of anti-epileptic medication</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients who are able to be completely withdrawn from anti-epileptic medication</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with permanent neurological side-effects from surgical treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3-6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients with permanent neurological side-effects from surgical treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Brain Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who have solitary primary or recurrent brain tumor with associated seizures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        One hundred patients, male and female, age 8 or older, with tumor related epilepsy will be
        enrolled. Patients who withdraw from the protocol will be replaced. The target number of
        patients completing this study is 100.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible for entry into the study, a candidate must meet all the following criteria:

          -  Be 8 years of age or older.

          -  Have solitary primary or recurrent brain tumor with associated seizures. Brain tumor
             may be diagnosed radiologically. Associated seizures are defined as those with
             activity starting within three months of radiologic diagnosis of the primary or
             recurrent tumor. In cases when the timing of seizure activity is unclear with respect
             to the timing of diagnosis, seizures will be considered associated with the tumor if
             seizure semiology is consistent with that location. Ongoing seizures are not required.
             Patients can be included if they have had a single previous seizure. Patients who have
             not experienced seizures after institution of anti-convulsant therapy are not
             excluded.

          -  Agree to undergo brain surgery.

          -  Willing and able to appoint a durable power of attorney.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Candidates will be excluded if they:

          -  Have a bleeding disorder that cannot be corrected before invasive testing or surgery,
             or other medical conditions that would make surgery unsafe, such as lung or cardiac
             disease that would render them unable to tolerate the risk of general anesthesia, or
             severe immunodeficiency or systemic cancer not related to a brain lesion.

          -  Cannot have an MRI scan.

          -  Have multiple brain tumors, evidence of carcinomatous meningitis, gliomatosis cerebri,
             or primary CNS lymphoma. Patients with multiple metastatic lesions that for which
             surgery is not indicated will be exluded. Patients with peripheral neurological or
             systemic metabolic disorders that cause seizures will be excluded.

          -  Have an underlying seizure disorder that is unrelated to the brain tumor, or
             underlying neurological disorder that is unrelated to the brain tumor and that may
             contribute to seizure activity.

          -  At the time of enrollment, lack consent capacity due to cognitive impairment that
             would make them incapable of understanding the explanation of the procedures in this
             study. Cognitive capacity to consent will be determined at the time of enrollment.
             Patients with mental disorders or those patients who are cognitively impaired yet
             still retain consent capacity will not be excluded. Children may be enrolled if there
             is a parent or guardian able to consent on their behalf.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kareem A Zaghloul, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gretchen C Scott, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-2921</phone>
    <email>SNBrecruiting@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2016-N-0041.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 15, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Seizure Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Seizures</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

