<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03574207</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>096-18-FB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03574207</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation to Improve Hippocampal-dependent Declarative Memory Abilities</brief_title>
  <official_title>Targeted Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation to Improve Hippocampal-dependent Declarative Memory Abilities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nebraska</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nebraska</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose a pilot study of the potential for non-invasive transcranial
      magnetic stimulation (TMS) to improve memory in healthy adults (young and old) and to treat
      memory deficits in older adults with amnestic mild cognitive impairment (aMCI). aMCI is a
      condition that frequently precedes Alzheimer's disease (AD), and a key symptom of aMCI is
      clinically significant memory loss (i.e., rapid forgetting) greater than expected for age.
      The investigators will test whether a form of non-invasive brain stimulation repetitive
      transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) can improve memory abilities in healthy young
      adults, healthy older adults, and older adults with aMCI by retuning memory-related brain
      networks. This study's specific aims are to: 1) Measure changes in declarative memory
      performance after treatment with targeted rTMS; 2) Measure modulation of functional brain
      networks after treatment with targeted rTMS. To achieve these aims, the investigators will
      recruit participants from a standing registry and other sources, test their memory abilities,
      apply rTMS to a specific brain region, and then test their memory abilities again. As a
      control, all participants will receive sham rTMS that does not stimulate the brain in one of
      the two phases of participation. By testing whether real rTMS improves memory abilities more
      than sham rTMS, the investigators will determine whether rTMS can reliably improve memory in
      the populations of interest. Also, the investigators will measure changes in brain activity
      before and after stimulation using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and
      magnetoencephalography (MEG). This study is a key first step which will support the
      investigators' long-term goal of treating memory deficits in neurological patients. The
      investigators expect that rTMS will improve memory abilities in all participants, and that
      the improvements in memory will be attributable to changes in the connectivity of
      memory-related brain networks. This study has clear clinical and translational relevance
      because it adapts a novel technique addressing a key symptom of AD to new populations. The
      investigators expect that the findings will improve the field's understanding of memory loss
      in healthy aging, aMCI, and AD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in memory performance measured with the number of studied face-word associations recalled</measure>
    <time_frame>Potential changes will be assessed after each one-week rTMS treatment period. Results will be reported at the end of the study (approximately one year).</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure memory performance before and after treatment to determine whether performance differs as a result of treatment. The main task will be a face-word association task in which participants will study a list of faces paired with single words. After a short delay, one studied face will be presented at a time, and participants will be prompted to recall the word associated with the face. The number of correct face-word associations recalled is the dependent measure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in intrinsic functional connectivity between the target brain region stimulated with rTMS and other brain regions.</measure>
    <time_frame>Potential changes will be assessed after each one-week rTMS treatment period. Results will be reported at the end of the study (approximately one year).</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use MRI and MEG to measure brain function before and after treatment to determine whether brain function differs as a result of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Memory Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Stimulation then Sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All procedures are identical in both arms with the exception of the order of stimulation administration. In Arm A, transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) will be applied in the first week of participation, and sham stimulation will be applied in the second week of participation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Sham then Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All procedures are identical in both arms with the exception of the order of stimulation administration. In Arm B, sham stimulation will be applied in the first week of participation, and transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) will be applied in the second week of participation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial magnetic stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Transcranial magnetic stimulation non-invasively applies very small amounts of electrical current to brain tissue; sham stimulation uses the same approach but applies little or no actual stimulation to the brain by using less power or greater distance between the head and the stimulator.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Stimulation then Sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Sham then Stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        The investigators anticipate enrolling 48 subjects total:

          -  16 healthy young adults (age 19-35)

          -  16 healthy older adults (demographically matched to aMCI group for age, sex, and
             educational attainment)

          -  16 older adults diagnosed with amnestic mild cognitive impairment (aMCI)

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults 19 years of age and older

          2. Healthy adults without history of psychiatric or neurological disease OR previous
             diagnosis of amnestic MCI

          3. Must be able to provide informed consent

          4. Must have the ability to comply with basic instructions and have the ability to sit
             comfortably still for TMS, neuroimaging, and other study procedures.

          5. Right-handed based on self-report (pre-screening) and evaluation with a standard test.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individuals who have ferrous metal implanted in their body (other than in their teeth)
             or any other non-removable medical and/or metallic implant

          2. Individuals who have increased intracranial pressure

          3. Individuals who have any major medical illness (e.g., cancer, HIV+, hepatitis, heart
             disease)

          4. Individuals who have confounding/dual diagnoses (e.g., comorbid mental illness and
             substance use disorder)

          5. Individuals with current diagnoses of alcohol or substance abuse/dependence

          6. Individuals with epilepsy, any history of seizures, or using medication that lowers
             seizure threshold

          7. Individuals with any neurological disorder other than aMCI (e.g., stroke, traumatic
             brain injury)

          8. Pregnant females --- as determined by urine pregnancy test --- will be excluded from
             this study due to uncertainty of the effects of MRI and TMS on the fetus

          9. Not right-handed based on self-report (pre-screening) or evaluation with a standard
             test

         10. Not a native English speaker.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas Christopher-Hayes</last_name>
    <phone>4025595805</phone>
    <email>wnl@unmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nebraska Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68198-8440</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David E Warren, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>402-559-5805</phone>
      <email>david.warren@unmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nebraska</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David E. Warren</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Memory Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The investigators have not yet determined whether or how data may be shared with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

