<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03574025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEUROPACK study protocol</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03574025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NEUROlogical Prognosis After Cardiac Arrest in Kids</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEUROPACK</acronym>
  <official_title>An Observational Study of Neurodevelopmental Outcome After Cardiac Arrest in Children Admitted to Paediatric Intensive Care in the United Kingdom and Ireland</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Each year around 2000 children have a cardiac arrest in the United Kingdom (UK) and
      approximately one fifth are admitted to Pediatric Intensive Care Unit. Many of these children
      eventually die and among those who survive, some will be left with brain damage which could
      affect their quality of life. Currently, it is difficult for doctors to predict how much
      brain damage there is at an early stage after cardiac arrest and if this will improve in
      time.

      NEURO-PACK aims to follow up children 3 months after their cardiac arrest to assess their
      quality of life and current functional status (has the child returned to usual routine as
      before cardiac arrest/mild disability, can the child not participate in certain activities as
      they were before the cardiac arrest/moderate disability, or if the child has near to no
      mobility/severe disability). Investigators will find this out by using a questionnaire and
      the research team will telephone patients and their families 3 months after the child's
      cardiac arrest. This telephone call should take no longer than 30 minutes. This will then be
      analysed and will help towards constructing a tool which will help doctors to predict which
      children who have had a cardiac arrest may survive with minimal brain damage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will be recruited from participating PICU's. There is currently lack of accurate
      data to enable clinicians to predict which of these children die or survive with brain
      injury. This affects clear communication with families as well as decisions to apply critical
      care interventions by clinicians. There is also an important knowledge gap with regards to
      outcome of children who are admitted to pediatric intensive care after a cardiac arrest and
      then survive to discharge.

      Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Patients aged 24 hours up to 16th birthday

        2. Requiring &gt; 1minute cardiopulmonary resuscitation

        3. Admitted to PICU after Out of Hospital Cardiac Arrest or In Hospital Cardiac Arrest

        4. Requiring mechanical ventilation at PICU admission

        5. Surviving to 3 months follow up.

      Exclusion criteria:

        1. Cardiac arrest occurring within a PICU or NICU (Neonatal Intensive Care Unit)

        2. Clinical team at participating sites feel inclusion is inappropriate

        3. Parent/ guardian or family member unable to understand the telephone questionnaires for
           outcome assessments in English

      The NEURO-PACK observational study enables the prospective collection of a cohort of children
      after out-of-hospital or in-hospital cardiac arrest. Data will be collected prospectively
      after eligible patients are screened and informed consent has been obtained. Participants and
      their families will be contacted by the Trials office,3 months after the patients cardiac
      arrest to complete a questionnaire over the telephone regarding functional status. Only
      contact information of the parents/guardians will be shared with the central Trials Office
      once informed consent has been obtained so that follow-up assessments can be completed. This
      information will be stored in locked cabinets, in a swipe card Trials Office based in
      Birmingham for five years, in line with Good Clinical Practice (GCP) guidance.

      The information collected from patients and their families will be analyzed and used to help
      construct a clinical prediction tool which will help clinicians to predict which children who
      have had cardiac arrest may survive with minimal brain damage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Family-Based</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival with good neurodevelopmental outcome assessed using the Vineland Adaptive Behavioral Score 2nd Edition (VABS-II).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after date of cardiac arrest</time_frame>
    <description>The VABS-II is a measure of adaptive behavior validated from birth to adulthood. VABS-II standardized score &gt; 70 is pre-defined as a 'Good outcome'. A score of 70 or less and death is a 'Poor outcome'. The VABS-II outcome score will be used to create a clinical prediction model of neurodevelopmental outcome within one hour of admission to pediatric intensive care for future reference that clinicians can use to predict which children with cardiac arrest may survive with minimal brain damage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurodevelopmental outcome assessed using the Pediatric Cerebral Performance and Category (PCPC) and Pediatric Overall Performance Category Scale (POPC)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after date of cardiac arrest</time_frame>
    <description>Pediatric Cerebral Performance Category (PCPC) measures cognitive impairment after child's critical illness. Scale 1 to 6 (1 Normal, 2 Mild disability, 3, Moderate disability, 4, Severe disability, 5 Coma/vegetative state, 6, Brain death/death). Pediatric Overall Performance Category Scale (POPC).assesses functional morbidity. Scale 1 to 6 (1 Good overall performance, 2 Mild overall disability, 3 Moderate overall disability, 4 Severe overall disability, 5 Coma or vegetative state, 6 Brain death/death).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Arrest Questionnaire</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children who will survive 3 months after Cardiac Arrest</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>To telephone the patient/family to look into how the patient is doing, moderate/severe brain damage.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Arrest Questionnaire</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children aged more than 24 hours and up to their 16th birthday who are admitted to PICU
        after a cardiac arrest outside of the unit.

        Patients aged less than 24 hours will not be included as these patients are frequently
        managed within the neonatal intensive care unit setting. Patients aged 16 years or greater
        are frequently managed in the UK within the adult intensive care setting. Only patient
        admitted to a PICU will be eligible.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients aged 24 hours up to 16th birthday

          2. Requiring &gt; 1minute cardiopulmonary resuscitation

          3. Admitted to PICU after Out of Hospital Cardiac Arrest or In Hospital Cardiac Arrest

          4. Requiring mechanical ventilation at PICU admission

          5. Surviving to 3 months follow up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cardiac arrest occurring within a PICU or NICU (Neonatal Intensive Care Unit)

          2. Clinical team at participating sites feel inclusion is inappropriate

          3. Parent/ guardian or family member unable to understand the telephone questionnaires
             for outcome assessments in English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barney Scholefield</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Birmingham Women's and Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Barney Scholefield</last_name>
    <phone>0121 333 9684</phone>
    <email>bwc.neuropack@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kate Penny-Thomas</last_name>
    <phone>0121 333 9684</phone>
    <email>bwc.neuropack@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Birmingham Women and Children's Hospital PICU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>B4 6NH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barney Scholefield</last_name>
      <phone>0121 3339684</phone>
      <email>bwc.neuropack@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Observational, Paediatric, Cardiac Arrest, PICU,</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>there is no plan to share individual participant data, however, we will be using and sharing data collected as a whole to construct a prediction tool to help clinicians predict the level of brain damage after cardiac arrest occurs.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

