<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03578549</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00136199</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03578549</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnostic Device for the Assessment of Pulpal Blood Flow</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pulse Oximeter is a Potential Diagnostic Device for the Assessment of Pulpal Blood Flow</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess tooth health by using a pulse oximeter which measures
      the blood flow within the tooth. This method is not currently being used in dentistry. We
      hypothesize that if we can measure both sensation and blood flow in a tooth, we will be able
      to better determine if the tooth is &quot;alive or dead&quot;. In the future, this method may help
      determine which teeth are diseased and require dental treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The vitality of the pulp is determined according to the health of the vascular supply not the
      sensory fibers. Conventional subjective tooth assessments (percussion, palpation, cold, and
      electrical pulp testing) and objective pulpal blood flow measurements will be used for teeth
      that are planned for extraction and also up to 2-5 additional teeth in each participant. The
      correlation between a single combined score from collective conventional subjective tooth
      assessments and the objective pulse oximetry reading for selected teeth will be used to
      evaluate if pulse oximeter measurements are a reliable marker for patient's reported
      symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Oximetry Testing of Teeth Scheduled to be Extracted and Others</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Subjective and Objective Measurements of Pulpal Status</measure>
    <time_frame>Single visit, less than one hour testing</time_frame>
    <description>The vitality of the pulp is determined according to the health of the vascular supply not the sensory fibers. Conventional subjective tooth assessments (percussion, palpation, cold, and electrical pulp testing) and objective pulpal blood flow measurements will be used for teeth that are planned for extraction and also up to 2-5 additional teeth in each participant. The correlation between a single combined score from collective conventional subjective tooth assessments and the objective pulse oximetry reading for selected teeth will be used to evaluate if pulse oximeter measurements are a reliable marker for patient's reported symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Pulp Test</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oximetry testing of healthy teeth and those requiring removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To assess the ability of pulse oximeter to assess the presence of pulse in teeth and to correlate pulse oximeter readings with conventional pulp testing measures including cold test, electrical pulp test, percussion and palpation testings, pulse oximeter will be used with a special holding frame, for 15-30 seconds.
Note: the reading will not affect clinical practice; it is simply to gather data to see if pulse oximetry can facilitate diagnostic practices in the future</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulse Oximetry</intervention_name>
    <description>Pulse Oximeter is being applied with a special holding tool to test the oximeter for its ability to measure pulpal blood flow, but no effect of the oximeter is being measured. Thus, to that degree the use is observational rather than interventional.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oximetry testing of healthy teeth and those requiring removal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        In order to be eligible to participate in this study, you must meet the following criteria:

          1. Must be a patient of the Oral Surgery Clinic at the University of Michigan School of
             Dentistry

          2. Must be scheduled for at least one tooth extraction at Oral Surgery Clinic

          3. Must be able to understand and willing to cooperate with all study procedures

          4. Must be able to sign an IRB-approved written consent

          5. Must have at least two teeth with an intact crown, without any full metallic crown
             coverage, and/or previous root canal treatments

          6. Must have no history of spontaneous pain, and/or lingering pain to cold/hot in teeth
             that are not going to be extracted on that day.

          7. If one of the teeth mentioned in inclusion #6 is being extracted, be willing to give
             your extracted tooth/teeth for further analysis to determine of the tooth is &quot;alive or
             dead&quot;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  An individual who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from
             participation in this study:

               -  If participant self-reports liver, kidney, heart, blood, metabolic or systemic
                  disease which may make execution of the protocol or interpretation of the results
                  difficult

               -  If participant has severe physical impairments (e.g., complete blindness or
                  deafness) and/or cognitive impairments (e.g., dementia) that precludes
                  participation in the procedures outlined in this proposal

               -  If participant is or could be pregnant

               -  If participant is currently receiving radiation

               -  If participant not able to hold mouth open for extended period of time
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Darya Dabiri, DMD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Darya Dabiri, DMD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>734-998-6983</phone>
    <email>daryad@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathy Scott</last_name>
    <phone>734-998-7022</phone>
    <email>jrsj@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oral and Maxiofacial Surgery Clinic, U of Michigan School of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Darya Dabiri</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Darya Dabiri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Post Doc Research Fellow, Faculty of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dental Pulp Test</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitality Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulpal Blood Flow Measure</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

