<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03575273</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00092798</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30DK072488</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03575273</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Methadone Maintenance Therapy on Food Reward Processing in Opioid Dependence</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Methadone Maintenance Therapy on Food Intake and Food Reward Processing in Opioid Dependence: An Event-related Brain Potential Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mid-Atlantic Nutrition Obesity Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Methadone maintenance therapy (MMT) has shown clear efficacy for relieving opioid withdrawal
      symptoms and reducing the morbidity and mortality of opioid dependence. A notable phenomenon
      associated with MMT is increased food intake, enhanced sweet preferences, and weight gain.
      The underlying neural mechanisms for opioid-related overconsumption are not well understood
      but are thought to arise from role in 1) increasing the palatability and hedonic aspects of
      food and 2) diminishing satiety signaling systems. In the proposed project, the investigators
      will examine methadone's potential role in opioid-related overconsumption of food. The
      investigators propose to examine eating behavior, sucrose preferences, and an event-related
      potential (ERP) component that is induced by appetitive motivation for highly rewarding foods
      in patients with a history of opioid dependence receiving methadone maintenance therapy
      (O+MMT) and not receiving opioid agonist therapy (O-MMT). A matched sample of obese and
      overweight adults without history of opioid use (HOC) will also be examined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methadone maintenance therapy (MMT) has shown clear efficacy for relieving opioid withdrawal
      symptoms and reducing the morbidity and mortality of opioid dependence. A notable phenomenon
      associated with MMT is increased food intake, enhanced sweet preferences, and weight gain.
      The underlying neural mechanisms for opioid-related overconsumption are not well understood
      but are thought to arise from role in 1) increasing the palatability and hedonic aspects of
      food and 2) diminishing satiety signaling systems. In the proposed project, the investigators
      will examine methadone's potential role in opioid-related overconsumption of food. The
      investigators propose to examine eating behavior, sucrose preferences, and an event-related
      potential (ERP) component that is induced by appetitive motivation for highly rewarding foods
      in patients with a history of opioid dependence receiving methadone maintenance therapy
      (O+MMT) and not receiving opioid agonist therapy (O-MMT). A matched sample of obese and
      overweight adults without history of opioid use (HOC) will also be examined. Specifically,
      group differences in food intake and eating behaviors in the O+MMT group relative to
      individuals in the O-MMT and HOC group will be examined. Individuals will complete 24-hour
      dietary food recalls and inventories to characterize eating behavior and food addiction.
      Participants will complete psychophysical measures of chemosensory functioning of sucrose
      preference and pleasantness and identification ratings for odors varying in participants'
      hedonic characteristics. Individuals will also complete validated computer tasks to assess
      food preferences. Differences in cortical ERPs for high-reward food relative to low-reward
      food and non-food items will be examined. Event-related potentials will be recorded as
      participants view photos of rewarding and non-rewarding food items, as well as non-food
      items. ERP components that index sustained attentional engagement will be measured and
      compared.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The investigators will recruit thirty individuals meeting criteria for opioid dependence of which 15 will be receiving MMT (O+MMT) and 15 will be on no opioid agonist therapy (O-MMT). The investigators will attempt to match the O-MMT group to the O+MMT group for clinical characteristics and smoking burden. Fifteen obese/overweight adults without history of opioid/substance use will be matched to the patient groups for age, gender, education, smoking and BMI.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-related potentials measured via BrainVision actiCHamp system</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline visit</time_frame>
    <description>Cortical ERPs for high-reward food relative to low-reward food and non-food items will be measured using a BrainVision actiCHamp system (32-channel amplifier). For each group, the grand averages and standard deviations for the late positive potential will be calculated. Group differences in LPP will be assessed within and between picture categories for each arm of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chemosensory Processing</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline visit</time_frame>
    <description>For the odorants, participants provide a rating of intensity and pleasantness based on a -5 to 5 point scale for each of the 16 markers. Afterwards, averages of all 16 marker scores will be calculated for the mean ratings of intensity and pleasantness. Odor identification accuracy will be assessed for each marker, with the score representing the total items correct out of 16.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Preferences Task</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline visit</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are showed images of high fat savory, low fat savory, high fat sweet, and low fat sweet foods. Participants must select one of the two pictures to answer the question &quot;which food item do you most want to eat right now.&quot; Selection averages of each category and time for selection, for each arm of the study, are automatically calculated by E-Prime software.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progressive Ratio Task</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline visit</time_frame>
    <description>Participants begin with 20 M&amp;Ms and a computer prompt that specifies how many times the mouse must be clicked to earn a piece of candy. Participants can earn as little as desired. The click ratio starts at 10 and geometrically increases in increments of 2 (i.e., 10, 20, 40, 80, etc.). The computer program E-Prime automatically records the participant's work capacity and the administrator records the number of M&amp;Ms left in the cup.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with a history of opioid dependence receiving methadone maintenance therapy will be administered Sniffin' Sticks Odor Identification and Hedonic Scale, Sucrose Taste Preference Assessment, Food Preferences Task, Progressive Ratio Task, Clinical Electrophysiology, and Standardized Meal and Hunger and Satiety Ratings</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with a history of opioid dependence not current receiving methadone maintenance therapy will be administered Sniffin' Sticks Odor Identification and Hedonic Scale, Sucrose Taste Preference Assessment, Food Preferences Task, Progressive Ratio Task, Clinical Electrophysiology, and Standardized Meal and Hunger and Satiety Ratings</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy controls without history of opioid use will be administered Sniffin' Sticks Odor Identification and Hedonic Scale, Sucrose Taste Preference Assessment, Food Preferences Task, Progressive Ratio Task, Clinical Electrophysiology, and Standardized Meal and Hunger and Satiety Ratings</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sniffin' Sticks Odor Identification and Hedonic Scale</intervention_name>
    <description>This task measures odor identification accuracy and perceived pleasantness of odors.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sucrose Taste Preference Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>This task measures participant ratings of sucrose preference.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Food Preferences Task</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants rate images of various food stimuli. Variables derived include relative preferences and reaction time (in milliseconds).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progressive Ratio (PR) Task</intervention_name>
    <description>In the PR task, the subject is required to make an increasing number of operant responses for each successive reward</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical Electrophysiology</intervention_name>
    <description>To examine motivated attention in response to food stimuli, brain electrophysiology via event related potentials (ERPs) will be assessed while participants view and rate images of food and non-food items.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standardized Meal and Hunger and Satiety Ratings</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive a standardized meal and complete hunger and satiety ratings.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence not on methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Opioid dependence receiving methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  English-speaking individuals

          -  Must be between 18 and 60 years of age

          -  For the O+MMT group, participants must be receiving MMT for at least 3 months

          -  For the O-MMT group, participants must have concluded their MMT (if applicable) at
             least three months prior to the date of the screening visit.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Individuals may not have a history of major neurological disorders

          -  No unstable medical issues that would affect appetite or blood glucose

          -  No pervasive developmental disorder or intellectual disability

          -  No significant visual/auditory impairment

          -  No history or current episode of psychosis

          -  No current opioid abuse

          -  No current antipsychotic medication use

          -  No major conditions that affect chemosensory function (e.g., history of nasal fracture
             or respiratory infection)

          -  Individuals with contraindication for the EEG will be excluded

          -  Individuals who are current pregnant or breastfeeding will not be enrolled

          -  For HOC, individuals with history of opioid dependence or current or past psychiatric
             disorders will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vidya Kamath, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Broadway Center for Addictions</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>methadone</keyword>
  <keyword>opioid dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>food reward</keyword>
  <keyword>olfactory</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

