<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03572140</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RAVS in HCV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03572140</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety of Sofosbuvir ,Daclatasvir in HCV Patients and RAVS in Resistent and Relapsed Cases</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAVs</acronym>
  <official_title>Safety of Sofosbuvir Plus Daclatasvir in Patients With Chronic Hepatitis c Virus and Assessment of Resistance Associated Variants in Resistant and Relapsed Cases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To identify side effects of Sofosbuvir/ Daclatasvir treatment regimen of chronic HCV GT-4
      infection.

        -  To assess the occurrence and the prevalence of RAVs in patients with treatment failure
           and relapse after sofosbuvir and daclatasvir with assessment of their types .

        -  To examine the GT4 subtypes by phylogenetic analysis and baseline sequence variability
           among subtypes and their potential impact on treatment outcome and development of viral
           resistance in patients who received a regimen of Sofosbuvir/ Daclatasvir for treatment
           of chronic HCV GT-4.

        -  To assess the differences in patient demographics across GT4 subtypes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis C virus (HCV) chronically infects approximately 120-130 million individuals
      worldwide .Mortality related to HCV infection has been estimated at approximately 300,000
      deaths per year..

      Direct antiviral agents (DAAs) effectively eradicate HCV and rapidly improve residual liver
      functions. Current HCV eradication rates have exceeded 90% in a very short time .

      Hepatitis C virus genotype 4 (GT4) is genetically diverse, with 17 confirmed subtypes, and
      comprises approximately 13% of infections worldwide [3]. In Egypt, GT4 accounts for
      approximately 90% of infections, with subtype 4a predominating .

      Sofosbuvir and daclatasvir are generally well tolerated with only a few adverse effects
      reported.

      Hepatitis C virus resistant associated variants (RAVs) are seen in most patients who do not
      achieve sustained virological response (SVR). These resistance-associated mutations depend on
      the class of direct-acting antiviral drugs used and also vary between hepatitis C virus
      genotypes and subtypes.

      Donaldson et al performed an analysis on four phase III clinical trials in search of common
      RAVs against sofosbuvir, discovering L159F, C316N, and V321A were associated with virological
      failure. Interestingly, this study also verified S282R mutation as associating with failure.

      NS5A RAVs can be very common, with Y93H detected in up to 15% of the population and L31M in
      up to 6.3%. Other RAVs tend to also be fairly common detected in approximately 0.3%-3.5% of
      the population
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>relevance of HC RAVs to the outcomes of therapy with Sofosbuvir in treatment of egyptian patients infected with HCV genotype 4</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>that may be used in the future to predict the response to Sofosbuvir and this will save a huge cost for Egypt .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">297</enrollment>
  <condition>HCV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group A</arm_group_label>
    <description>RAVS IN resistent cases after daclatasvir plus sofosbuvir treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group B</arm_group_label>
    <description>RAVS IN relapsed cases after daclatasvir plus sofosbuvir treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RAVS In relapsed and resistent cases</intervention_name>
    <description>assessment of RAVS in relapsed and resistant cases after sofosbuvir plus daclatasvir regimen</description>
    <arm_group_label>group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      fresh blood sample at base line before treatment and another specimen after the end of
      treatment for resistent and relapsed cases
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cases will be recruited from the viral hepatitis clinic, department of tropical medicine,
        Alrajhi Liver hospital, Assiut University. The lab. work will be done by researchers from
        Medical Microbiology and Immunology department, Faculty of Medicine, Assiut
        University-University of Cincinnat, USA and Clinical pathology department, Assiut
        University.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Anti HCV positive patients either chronic HCV or liver cirrhosis. • Detectable HCV RNA
             by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) prior to treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Co-infection with hepatitis B virus .

          -  Presence of malignancy before treatment.

          -  End-stage liver disease (Child score more than 9).

          -  Major co-morbid disease e.g heart failure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ahlam Farghaly, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>haidi ramadan, Lecturer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rasha Ali, Assistant lecturer</last_name>
    <phone>01062821017</phone>
    <email>rasha.maree77@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>hellal hetta, Lecturer</last_name>
    <phone>01002386255</phone>
    <email>hellalhetta@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ben Ari Z. [Chronic hepatitis C infection--eradication of the virus]. Harefuah. 2014 Jul;153(7):392-3, 433. Hebrew.</citation>
    <PMID>25189028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conti F, Buonfiglioli F, Scuteri A, Crespi C, Bolondi L, Caraceni P, Foschi FG, Lenzi M, Mazzella G, Verucchi G, Andreone P, Brillanti S. Early occurrence and recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma in HCV-related cirrhosis treated with direct-acting antivirals. J Hepatol. 2016 Oct;65(4):727-733. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2016.06.015. Epub 2016 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27349488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reig M, Mariño Z, Perelló C, Iñarrairaegui M, Ribeiro A, Lens S, Díaz A, Vilana R, Darnell A, Varela M, Sangro B, Calleja JL, Forns X, Bruix J. Unexpected high rate of early tumor recurrence in patients with HCV-related HCC undergoing interferon-free therapy. J Hepatol. 2016 Oct;65(4):719-726. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2016.04.008. Epub 2016 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27084592</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamal SM, Nasser IA. Hepatitis C genotype 4: What we know and what we don't yet know. Hepatology. 2008 Apr;47(4):1371-83. doi: 10.1002/hep.22127. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18240152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Lello FA, Neukam K, Parra-Sanchez M, Plaza Z, Soriano V, Cifuentes C, Mira JA, Poveda E, Pineda JA. Hepatitis C virus genotype 4 in Southern and Central Spain does not originate from recent foreign migration waves. J Med Virol. 2013 Oct;85(10):1734-40. doi: 10.1002/jmv.23657. Epub 2013 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23861220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donaldson EF, Harrington PR, O'Rear JJ, Naeger LK. Clinical evidence and bioinformatics characterization of potential hepatitis C virus resistance pathways for sofosbuvir. Hepatology. 2015 Jan;61(1):56-65. doi: 10.1002/hep.27375. Epub 2014 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25123381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rasha Maree Omar Ali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HCV</keyword>
  <keyword>Sofosbuvir</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>RAVs</keyword>
  <keyword>Daclatasvir</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

