<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03579017</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016/3166</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03579017</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Edinburgh Cognitive and Behavioural Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Screen in Norway: A Validation Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cognitive Impairment in ALS: Screening Tools, Experiences and Prognosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Western Norway University of Applied Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Haukeland University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive impairment is present in about 30-50% of the patients with amyotrophic lateral
      sclerosis (ALS). Suitable screening tools are available, but none of these are evaluated in a
      Norwegian population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Screening of cognitive and behavioral impairment is a distinct recommendation in ALS-specific
      health-care. Thus, a rapid screening tool valid for use in Norway is urgent. However,
      cognitive assessment for patients with ALS can be difficult due to the complexity of
      cognitive impairment, as well as motor challenges with writing, drawing and speaking.
      Therefore, only ALS-specific, multi domain screening instruments with integrated behavioral
      sections should be used. Internationally, the Edinburgh cognitive and behavioral amyotrophic
      lateral sclerosis screen (ECAS), is recommended for the purpose. Besides being quick and easy
      to administer, the ECAS is shown to be sensitive and have high specificity to ALS-specific
      dysfunction and behavioral changes. The introduction of ECAS has probably contributed to a
      more nuanced picture of cognitive impairment in ALS than previously assumed. Therefore the
      ECAS has been translated and culturally adapted into Norwegian (ECAS-N). Based on scores from
      healthy people, Norwegian age- and educational-adjusted norms for verbal fluency (n=277) and
      cut-off-scores (n=85) for abnormal findings are established. However, further investigation
      of psychometric properties of the ECAS-N is needed. The objectives of the study are: 1. To
      investigate if the ECAS-N reflect cognitive impairment (internal consistency), and is robust
      to measurement errors due to different times of testing (test-retest reliability) and
      different raters (interrater reliability) 2. To investigate if the ECAS-N can be used to
      distinguish between people with ALS-specific cognitive impairment, and those who do not have
      cognitive impairment, and those who have cognitive impairment due to other disorders
      (construct validity).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Edinburgh cognitive and behavioural amyotrophic lateral sclerosis screen - Norwegian Version (ECAS-N)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will use the ALS-specific sub-score (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 100), the ALS non-specific sub-score (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 36), a summed total ECAS-N score (minimum score =0, maximum score =136), the sub score of behavioural changes (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 10) and the sub score of psychotic change (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 3). A dichotomized cut-off scores for normality will also be used for the ALS-specific cut-off score of 65 or over, the non ALS-specific cut-off score of 24 or over and the total ECAS-N cut-off score of 92 or over. For the ALS-specific scores, non ALS-specific scores and total ECAS-N scores, high scores indicate less problems than low scores. For the sub score of behavioural change and the sub score of psychotic change, high scores indicate more problems than low scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal cognitive assessment (MoCA) - Norwegian version</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will use the total MoCA score (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 30) and a dichotomized cut-off score for normality of 26 or over. High scores indicate less problems than low scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from 4 months Edinburgh cognitive and behavioural amyotrophic lateral sclerosis screen - Norwegian Version (ECAS-N) at 8 months</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will use the changed ALS-specific sub-score (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 100), the changed ALS non-specific sub-score (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 36), a changed summed total ECAS-N score (minimum score =0, maximum score =136), the changed sub score of behavioural changes (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 10) and the changed sub score of psychotic change (minimum score = 0, maximum score = 3). A changed dichotomized cut-off scores for normality will also be used for the ALS-specific cut-off score of 65 or over, the non ALS-specific cut-off score of 24 or over and the total ECAS-N cut-off score of 92 or over. For the ALS-specific scores, non ALS-specific scores and total ECAS-N scores, high scores indicate less problems than low scores. For the sub score of behavioural change and the sub score of psychotic change, high scores indicate more problems than low scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with ALS</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with ALS will be tested by two independent testers with the ECAS-N at 4 months (baseline) and 8 months (follow-up), and the MoCA at 4 months (baseline) by one tester</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Persons with no cognitive impairment will be tested with the ECAS-N once, by one tester</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls with dementia</arm_group_label>
    <description>Persons with cognitive impairment due to other disorders will be tested with the ECAS-N once, by one tester</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ECAS-N</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants included will be tested with the ECAS-N</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls with dementia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with ALS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Edinburgh cognitive and behavioral ALS screen (Norwegian)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MoCA</intervention_name>
    <description>All included patients With ALS will be tested With the MoCA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with ALS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Montreal cognitive assessment (MoCA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who fulfill the inclution criteria and attending to the ALS-unit at HUH, St.Olavs
        Hospital, Hospital of Southern Norway or Namsos Hospital, within 4 months after being
        diagnosed With ALS.

        Healthy People and patients with dementia will constitute Control groups
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  voluntary informed consent

          -  native Norwegian speaker

          -  aged between 35 and 85 years old (only for Controls)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  great difficulties in writing og Reading

          -  comorbid Medical history

          -  neurological disorders others than ALS

          -  psychiatric history of importance to cognitive function
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tina Taule, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tina Taule, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+47 41694143</phone>
    <email>tina.taule@helse-bergen.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tiina Rekand, professor</last_name>
    <email>tiina.rekand@helse-bergen.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haukeland University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <zip>5021</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tina Taule, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+47 41694143</phone>
      <email>tina.taule@helse-bergen.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tiina Rekand, Professor</last_name>
      <email>tiina.rekand@helse-bergen.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive</keyword>
  <keyword>Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Validation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

