<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03571516</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHP633-301</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-003606-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03571516</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Efficacy and Pharmacokinetic Study of Teduglutide in Infants 4 to 12 Months of Age With Short Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-label, 24-Week Safety, Efficacy, and Pharmacokinetic Study of Teduglutide in Infants 4 to 12 Months of Age With Short Bowel Syndrome Who Are Dependent on Parenteral Support</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shire</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate the safety, efficacy/pharmacodynamics (PD) and
      pharmacokinetics (PK) of teduglutide treatment in infants with short bowel syndrome (SBS)
      dependent on parenteral (PN) support.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 14, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 14, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Achieve At least a 20 Percent (%) Reduction From Baseline in Weight-normalized Parenteral Nutrition (PN) Fluid Volume at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who achieve at least a 20% reduction from baseline in weight-normalized average daily PN volume at Week 24/ end of treatment (EOT) will be summarized by treatment arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Concentration of Teduglutide</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; 1, 4 hours post-dose, and 2 hours post-dose on Week 7</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma Concentration as a Pharmacokinetic parameter of Teduglutide will be assessed. The estimation will be calculated by using a population PK modeling approach.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to Week 28 (Follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event (AE) is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment. TEAEs are defined as AEs that start or deteriorate on or after the date of the first dose of investigational product.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Body Weight Z-Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1,Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24 and Week 28</time_frame>
    <description>The Z-score indicates the number of standard deviations away from the mean.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Length Z-Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24 and Week 28</time_frame>
    <description>The Z-score indicates the number of standard deviations away from the mean.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Head Circumference Z-Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24 and Week 28</time_frame>
    <description>The Z-score indicates the number of standard deviations away from the mean.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Weight-for-Length Z-Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 5, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24 and Week 28</time_frame>
    <description>The Z-score indicates the number of standard deviations away from the mean.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Urine Output</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Urine output will be recorded in the output diary over a 48-hour period of nutritional stability before every clinic visit, and within 1 week of implementing a change in the PN prescription.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Stool Output</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20, Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Stool output will be recorded in the output diary over a 48-hour period of nutritional stability before every clinic visit, and within 1 week of implementing a change in the PN prescription.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibodies to Teduglutide</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12 and Week 28</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants classified as having positive specific antibodies to teduglutide will be used to summarize the presence of antibodies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Achieve At least a 20 Percent (%) Reduction From Baseline in Weight-normalized Parenteral (PN) Calories at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who achieve at least a 20% reduction from baseline in weight-normalized parenteral calories at Week 24/EOT will be summarized by treatment arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Enteral Autonomy at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who have achieved enteral autonomy at a given visit if the investigator prescribes no PS at that visit and there is no use of PN recorded in the participant diary during the week prior to that visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Achieve Enteral Autonomy</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline up to Week 28</time_frame>
    <description>A participant will be considered to have achieved enteral autonomy (completely weaned off PN) if the investigator prescribes no PN and for the remainder of the treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Weight-normalized Parenteral nutrition (PN) Fluid Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20 and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in weight-normalized PN fluid volume will be analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Weight-normalized Parenteral Calories</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20 and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in weight-normalized parenteral calories will be analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Weight-normalized Enteral Fluid Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20 and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in weight-normalized enteral fluid volume will be analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Weight-normalized Enteral Caloric Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1, Week 3, Week 5, Week 7, Week 9, Week 12, Week 16, Week 20 and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in weight-normalized enteral caloric intake will be analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Achieve At least a 20 Percent (%) Increase From Baseline in Weight-normalized Enteral (EN) Fluid Intake at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who demonstrate an increase in weight-normalized enteral fluid intake by at least 20% from baseline to Week 24/EOT will be summarized by treatment arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Acheive At least a 20 Percent (%) Increase From Baseline in Weight-normalized Enteral (EN) Caloric Intake at Week 24</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline up to Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who demonstrate an increase in weight-normalized enteral caloric intake by at least 20% from baseline to week 24/EOT will be summarized by treatment arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Short Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teduglutide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 0.05 milligram per kilogram (mg/kg) subcutaneous (SC) injection of teduglutide into abdomen or into either the thigh or arm once daily (QD) in addition to standard medical therapy for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SOC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive standard medical therapy for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teduglutide</intervention_name>
    <description>SC injection of 0.05 mg/kg teduglutide will be administered QD into abdomen or into either the thigh or arm for 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Teduglutide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Medical Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard medical therapy will be administered for 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SOC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Teduglutide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Syringe</intervention_name>
    <description>Teduglutide will be administered using syringe (510k number: K980987).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SOC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Teduglutide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Needle</intervention_name>
    <description>Teduglutide will be administered using needle (510k number: K021475).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SOC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Teduglutide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent by the parent or legal guardian.

          -  Male or female infant 4 to 12 months corrected gestational age at screening.

          -  Weight at least 5 kilogram (kg) and weight-for-length Z-score greater than -2 at
             screening and baseline.

          -  Short bowel syndrome with dependence on parenteral support to provide at least 50% of
             fluid or caloric needs.

          -  Stable PN requirements for at least 1 month prior to screening, defined as a less than
             or equal to (&lt;=) 10% change in the weight-normalized PN total fluid and caloric
             intake, despite attempts to wean PN, not withstanding transient instability for events
             such as sepsis or interruption of central venous access.

          -  Parent or legal guardian understands and is willing and able to fully adhere to study
             requirements as defined in this protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous treatment with teduglutide.

          -  Intestinal malabsorption due to a genetic condition, such as cystic fibrosis,
             microvillus inclusion disease, etc.

          -  Severe, known dysmotility syndrome, such as pseudo-obstruction or persistent, severe,
             active gastroschisis-related dysmotility, that is the primary contributing factor to
             feeding intolerance and inability to reduce PN support, prior to screening.
             Dysmotility is defined as severe if it is expected to limit the advancement of enteral
             feeding.

          -  Inability to advance oral or enteral feeding due to lack of access to the gut, such as
             oral aversion in the absence of a feeding tube.

          -  Intestinal obstruction or clinically significant intestinal stenosis.

          -  Major gastrointestinal surgical intervention, such as serial transverse enteroplasty
             or major intestinal resection or anastomosis, within 3 months prior to screening or
             planned during the study period.

          -  Unstable cardiac disease.

          -  Renal dysfunction, defined as estimated glomerular filtration rate less than (&lt;) 50
             milliliter per minute (mL/min) per 1.73 square meter (m^2).

          -  Biliary obstruction, stenosis, or malformation.

          -  Clinically significant pancreatic disease.

          -  Severe hepatic dysfunction or portal hypertension, defined by at least 2 of the
             following parameters:

               1. International normalized ratio (INR) greater than (&gt;) 1.5 not corrected with PN
                  vitamin K

               2. Platelet count &lt;100×10^3/ microliter (mcL) due to portal hypertension

               3. Presence of clinically significant gastric or esophageal varices

               4. Documented cirrhosis

          -  Persistent cholestasis defined as conjugated bilirubin &gt;4 milligram per deciliter
             (mg/dL) (&gt;68 micromoles per liter [mcmol/L]) over a 2 week period.

          -  More than 3 serious complications of intestinal failure (example [e.g.],
             catheter-associated bloodstream infections, interruption of nutrition due to feeding
             intolerance, catheter-associated thrombosis, severe fluid or electrolyte disturbances)
             within 1 month prior to or during screening.

          -  A history of cancer or a known cancer predisposition syndrome, such as juvenile
             polyposis or Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome, or first degree relative with early onset of
             gastrointestinal cancer (including hepatobiliary and pancreatic cancers).

          -  Concurrent treatment with glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1); glucagon-like peptide-2
             (GLP-2); insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1); growth hormone, somatostatin, or
             analogs of these hormones; or glutamine.

          -  Participation in a clinical study using an experimental drug within 3 months or 5.5
             half-lives of the experimental drug, whichever is longer.

          -  Known or suspected intolerance or hypersensitivity to the investigational product,
             closely-related compounds, or any of the stated ingredients.

          -  Any condition, disease, illness, or circumstance that, in the investigator's opinion,
             puts the participant at any undue risk, prevents completion of the study, or
             interferes with analysis of the study results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shire</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Helsingin yliopistollinen keskussairaala</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00290</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Pellegrin - Hôpital des Enfants</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <state>Gironde</state>
        <zip>33000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Jeanne de Flandre - CHRU Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <state>Nord</state>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Pediatrico Bambino Gesù</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00165</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Greater London</state>
        <zip>WC1N 3JH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Manchester Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <state>Greater Manchester</state>
        <zip>M13 9WL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alder Hey Childrens Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>Merseyside</state>
        <zip>L12 2AP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Birmingham Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>B4 6NH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Short bowel syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Teduglutide</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Short Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Teduglutide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data from this particular study will not be shared as there is a reasonable likelihood that individual patients could be re-identified (due to the limited number of study participants/study sites, …).</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

