<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03577054</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MUST 16/09-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03577054</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of a Mobile Application for HBB Prompt Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>HBB-Prompt</acronym>
  <official_title>Development of a Mobile Application Through User Centered Design to Improve Helping Babies Breath Skills Retention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Hospital for Sick Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study applies an iterative user-centred design approach involving frontline birth
      attendants to create a mobile application (&quot;HBB Prompt&quot;) to improve skills retention after
      initial newborn stabilization training through the Helping Babies Breathe (HBB) program. HBB
      Prompt will then be piloted at one site after HBB training and skills retention will be
      compared with a control site without HBB Prompt after HBB training.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Helping Babies Breathe (HBB) is a newborn stabilization course that has been shown to reduce
      neonatal mortality by up to 47%. Such mortality impact is however not sustained due to rapid
      skills deterioration.

      The investigators propose to improve sustainability of HBB's impact by increasing skills
      retention with an innovative mobile application called HBB Prompt. HBB Prompt will be an
      interactive tool that guides frontline providers through the steps needed to save newborn
      babies at birth. HBB Prompt will facilitate individual and group training in health
      facilities using the Low Dose High Frequency model (LDHF) for resuscitation skills retention.

      The investigators will robustly develop HBB Prompt by integrating human factors and
      user-centered design approaches. The investigators will engage end-users and HBB Master
      Trainers to iteratively collect feedback to develop HBB Prompt for both individual and small
      group resuscitation practice. The iterative approach will mitigate the common scenario of
      mobile health (mHealth) solutions unable to achieve sustained success at scale due to lack of
      comprehensive input from frontline users.

      The investigators will pilot the app at a single centre and compare it to a control site for
      HBB skills retention at different time points after initial HBB training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes assessor at analysis stage will be masked to allocation of participants</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Helping Babies Breathe Objective Structured Clinical Exam (OSCE) B score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months from initial HBB training</time_frame>
    <description>standardized comprehensive evaluation of HBB skills, 17 out of 23 constitutes a pass score with 23 being the highest score. The OSCE B is a standard Helping Babies Breathe assessment tool that comprises the steps required in successfully assisting a neonate in its transition after birth</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OSCE B score</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately before initial HBB training</time_frame>
    <description>standardized comprehensive evaluation of HBB skills, 17 out of 23 constitutes a pass score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OSCE B score</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after initial HBB training</time_frame>
    <description>standardized comprehensive evaluation of HBB skills, 17 out of 23 constitutes a pass score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OSCE B score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months from initial HBB training</time_frame>
    <description>standardized comprehensive evaluation of HBB skills, 17 out of 23 constitutes a pass score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OSCE B score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months from initial HBB training</time_frame>
    <description>standardized comprehensive evaluation of HBB skills, 17 out of 23 constitutes a pass score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HBB 2.0 Knowledge Check</measure>
    <time_frame>at unannounced visits within 12 months of training</time_frame>
    <description>18 questions pertaining to newborn resuscitation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bag and mask ventilation skills check</measure>
    <time_frame>at unannounced visits within 12 months of training</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of bagging skills to assist breathing - score out of 14</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bag and mask ventilation quality measures with AIR Device</measure>
    <time_frame>at unannounced visits within 12 months of training</time_frame>
    <description>Augmented Infant Resuscitator (AIR) to objectively measure quality of newborn resuscitation during every ventilation epoch. AIR records time stamped data on ventilation quality, such as presence of air leak or obstruction and ventilation rate (www.air-device.com)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OSCE A</measure>
    <time_frame>at unannounced visits within 12 months of training</time_frame>
    <description>standardized evaluation of resuscitation skills (slightly different scenario than for OSCE B), 9 out of 12 constitutes a pass score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App analytics - pattern of usage</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 months after initial training in intervention arm only</time_frame>
    <description>automated reports from the app regarding usage of different components of the app</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App analytics - frequency of usage</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 months after initial training in intervention arm only</time_frame>
    <description>frequency of access to different parts of the app, duration of app usage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App analytics - trends of performance</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 months after initial training in intervention arm only</time_frame>
    <description>time trends of knowledge checks and simulation evaluations as noted in the app</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of practice</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 months after initial training</time_frame>
    <description>for both intervention and control arms, log-books will be reviewed for frequency of practice and in the intervention arm, this will be compared to what is reported through the app</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exit focus group feedback on barriers and facilitators to HBB training and skills maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study (12 months from the start)</time_frame>
    <description>both intervention and control group participants will be interviewed to provide feedback on facilitators and barriers to HBB skills maintenance, and in the intervention arm, whether HBB Prompt helped or hindered their skills maintenance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Delivery Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 month study period</time_frame>
    <description>number of births will be recorded from the birth register of each site</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Infants requiring bagging</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 month study period</time_frame>
    <description>number of babies requiring bagging will be recorded from the birth register of each site</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fresh stillbirths</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 month study period</time_frame>
    <description>number of fresh stillbirths will be recorded from the birth register of each site</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>In hospital neonatal mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>during 12 month study period</time_frame>
    <description>number of neonatal deaths prior to discharge will be recorded from the birth register of each site</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Birth Asphyxia</condition>
  <condition>Neonatal Death</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HBB Prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators will train frontline health providers in Helping Babies Breathe (HBB) 2.0 and Essential Care for Every Baby (ECEB). Providers will undergo ECEB training in addition to HBB as these training programs are recommended by the Uganda Ministry of Health to be offered together.
Providers at this hospital will have access to the most updated version of HBB Prompt (beta) after HBB training.
Participants in will be asked to achieve a minimum practice target of once per day (low-dose high frequency training). The recommended frequency to use the app will be once per shift.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators will train frontline health providers in Helping Babies Breathe (HBB) 2.0 and Essential Care for Every Baby (ECEB). Providers will undergo ECEB training in addition to HBB as these training programs are recommended by the Uganda Ministry of Health to be offered together.
The control group will not have exposure to the HBB Prompt app post training. Participants in will be asked to achieve a minimum practice target of once per day (low-dose high frequency training).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HBB Prompt</intervention_name>
    <description>Mobile app developed through user-centred design in phase 1 of this study</description>
    <arm_group_label>HBB Prompt</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>mobile app</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-Dose High Frequency training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be encouraged to practice their HBB skills daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HBB Prompt</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LDHF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Frontline birth attendants involved in the delivery or care of babies in the maternity
             ward, theater or pediatric wards with a possibility of involvement in newborn
             resuscitation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Health workers providing care in other wards other than maternity and pediatrics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Santorino Data, MBChB, MMed</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francis Bajunirwe, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+256772576396</phone>
    <email>fbaj@must.ac.ug</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mbarara University of Science and Technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mbarara</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Santorino Data, MBChB, MMed</last_name>
      <phone>256712214458</phone>
      <email>sdata@must.ac.ug</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Santorino Data, MBChB, MMed</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Msemo G, Massawe A, Mmbando D, Rusibamayila N, Manji K, Kidanto HL, Mwizamuholya D, Ringia P, Ersdal HL, Perlman J. Newborn mortality and fresh stillbirth rates in Tanzania after helping babies breathe training. Pediatrics. 2013 Feb;131(2):e353-60. doi: 10.1542/peds.2012-1795. Epub 2013 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23339223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kc A, Wrammert J, Clark RB, Ewald U, Vitrakoti R, Chaudhary P, Pun A, Raaijmakers H, Målqvist M. Reducing Perinatal Mortality in Nepal Using Helping Babies Breathe. Pediatrics. 2016 Jun;137(6). pii: e20150117. doi: 10.1542/peds.2015-0117.</citation>
    <PMID>27225317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goudar SS, Somannavar MS, Clark R, Lockyer JM, Revankar AP, Fidler HM, Sloan NL, Niermeyer S, Keenan WJ, Singhal N. Stillbirth and newborn mortality in India after helping babies breathe training. Pediatrics. 2013 Feb;131(2):e344-52. doi: 10.1542/peds.2012-2112. Epub 2013 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23339215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bang A, Patel A, Bellad R, Gisore P, Goudar SS, Esamai F, Liechty EA, Meleth S, Goco N, Niermeyer S, Keenan W, Kamath-Rayne BD, Little GA, Clarke SB, Flanagan VA, Bucher S, Jain M, Mujawar N, Jain V, Rukunga J, Mahantshetti N, Dhaded S, Bhandankar M, McClure EM, Carlo WA, Wright LL, Hibberd PL. Helping Babies Breathe (HBB) training: What happens to knowledge and skills over time? BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2016 Nov 22;16(1):364.</citation>
    <PMID>27875999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reisman J, Arlington L, Jensen L, Louis H, Suarez-Rebling D, Nelson BD. Newborn Resuscitation Training in Resource-Limited Settings: A Systematic Literature Review. Pediatrics. 2016 Aug;138(2). pii: e20154490. doi: 10.1542/peds.2015-4490. Epub 2016 Jul 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27388500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mduma E, Ersdal H, Svensen E, Kidanto H, Auestad B, Perlman J. Frequent brief on-site simulation training and reduction in 24-h neonatal mortality--an educational intervention study. Resuscitation. 2015 Aug;93:1-7. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2015.04.019. Epub 2015 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25957942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arabi AM, Ibrahim SA, Ahmed SE, MacGinnea F, Hawkes G, Dempsey E, Ryan CA. Skills retention in Sudanese village midwives 1 year following Helping Babies Breathe training. Arch Dis Child. 2016 May;101(5):439-42. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2015-309190. Epub 2016 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26826172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wyckoff MH, Aziz K, Escobedo MB, Kapadia VS, Kattwinkel J, Perlman JM, Simon WM, Weiner GM, Zaichkin JG. Part 13: Neonatal Resuscitation: 2015 American Heart Association Guidelines Update for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2015 Nov 3;132(18 Suppl 2):S543-60. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000267. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26473001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>FDIs, I. (2009). 9241-210 (2009). Ergonomics of human system interaction-Part 210: Human-centered design for interactive systems (formerly known as 13407). International Organization for Standardization (ISO). Switzerland.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krueger RA, Casey MA. Focus Groups: A practical guide for applied research. 4th ed. California: Sage Publications Inc., 2008.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Helping Babies Breathe</keyword>
  <keyword>newborn resuscitation</keyword>
  <keyword>skills retention</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile health</keyword>
  <keyword>user-centred design</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Perinatal Death</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asphyxia Neonatorum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asphyxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 18, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/54/NCT03577054/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

