<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03570372</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17RS4920</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03570372</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Internet-based Treatment for Adults With Autism Spectrum Disorder</brief_title>
  <acronym>MILAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Internet-based Treatment for Adults With Autism Spectrum Disorder (MILAS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Örebro County Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Susanne Bejerot, professor, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Örebro County Council</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The group of patients diagnosed with Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is increasing and so is
      the need for new and effective treatment methods. ASD is characterized, among other things,
      by difficulties in social interaction and communication. These difficulties often affects
      their quality of life and causes a risk of developing social anxiety or other forms of mental
      illness, which often leads to isolation and may cause difficulties in participating in
      regular face- to- face psychological treatment. Although research shows that group therapy is
      favorable for this group of patients, many with ASD refrain from group-treatment due to
      social anxiety or difficulties with public transport. In order to increase the availability
      of evidence based psychological treatment for these patients, it seems important to be able
      to offer a web-based treatment option, with the ability to participate in online group
      sessions.

      The aim of the study is to investigate whether Internet-based CBT is an effective method of
      raising the quality of life and improving the mental health of adults with ASD.

      A randomized controlled study design will be used. Assessment will be conducted through video
      interviews, recruiting 84 patients with ASD and normal intellectual abilities. Symptoms of
      depression and other forms of psychopathology will be assessed through MINI-7 interviews.
      Primary outcome measures are quality of life and symptoms of depression and anxiety.
      Participants in the intervention group receives a 37 session blended treatment combining
      individual ICBT delivered through a treatment platform called Stöd och Behandling (SOB) with
      the opportunity to participate in regular group discussions delivered through a discussion
      forum online. Participants in the control groups are offered self-studies through psycho
      educative books about ASD. Data will be collected at baseline, mid-treatment, post-treatment
      and after six and 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is characterized by significant difficulties in
      social interaction and communication as well as routine boundaries and constraints in
      behavioral patterns. People with ASD have difficulties in the ability to mentalize, i.e.
      difficulties in understanding how another person feels and thinks. Another characteristic of
      persons with ASD is that they are detailed in their way of processing information and
      therefore have difficulties in generalizing and managing changes in everyday life. Lacking in
      planning, organizing, evaluating and adjusting their behaviors can lead to extensive needs of
      support. About 40% of adult patients with ASD exhibit depressive symptoms. Different types of
      anxiety disorders are also very common as well as obsessive compulsive disorder and eating
      disorder. Many people experience constant stress and vigilance following efforts to behave
      socially adequately and managing unpredictable situations.

      In contrast to the common belief that people with ASD are uninterested in others, they are in
      fact often eager to fit in, acquire friends and engage in relationships. However, the
      majority live alone. The uneven profile of strengths and weaknesses is often combined with
      chronic stress and experience of failures and misunderstandings. In addition to having
      difficulties in socializing, many also have difficulties in initiating and solving problems,
      which contributes to unemployment.

      Psychological treatment Many people with ASD find it difficult to identify and express
      feelings and thoughts, which is a common element in psychotherapeutic treatment. This can
      hinder psychological treatment from progressing as expected. The goals of treatment are often
      to increase the person's quality of life and ability to live an independent life, and a major
      focus in treatment for children with ASD is on psycho education, cognitive interventions and
      social skills. Treatment of adults with ASD is less explored. Experience from clinical
      practice suggests that psychological interventions should be practical and focused on
      behavioral change strategies, but to date, few treatments using Cognitive Behavioral Therapy
      (CBT) have been scientifically evaluated for persons with ASD.

      A group format has been considered to have several benefits in psychological treatment for
      adults with ASD. It offers an opportunity for participants to discover that they are not
      alone in their quest to fit in socially. A group also provides the opportunity to reproduce
      problematic social situations, provide behavioral feedback and enable exercises of skills in
      a structured environment.

      In several studies, internet based psychological treatment has proven to be effective in
      treating a variety of psychiatric diagnoses. Courses and information-based training materials
      have been offered in some regions in Sweden, but only for children and adolescents with ASD.
      Until now, no internet based cognitive behavioral treatment (ICBT) has been used for treating
      adults with ASD. Since many with ASD have severe social anxiety or having difficulty with
      travel, it seems important to be able to offer a web-based treatment option. This could
      enable social interaction, learning and a sense of belonging, regardless of where they live
      and the ability to leave the home as well as contributing to a more equal care.

      Earlier study Susanne Bejerot, a Swedish psychiatrist and psychotherapist with CBT focus,
      has, together with colleagues, developed a new group based CBT manual (called ALMA) for
      adults with ASD. The treatment aims to give participants a deep understanding of the
      diagnosis and increase their quality of life. A randomized controlled study of this treatment
      has been published in a reputable journal . Groups of 6-8 adults with ASD received the
      intervention for a total of two semesters. The treatment significantly improved the quality
      of life (Cohen's d = 0.43) and in a cumulative long-term follow-up (&gt; 8 months), it was found
      that the improvement was lasting. In addition, 88% of the participants gained increased
      self-understanding, higher self-acceptance (72%) and increased well-being (67%).

      Current study

      The current study originates from the above-mentioned ALMA treatment. The CBT based material
      used in ALMA will be transformed and adapted to an internet-based format. The effects of the
      internet-based version will be evaluated using the same population as in the ALMA study -
      i.e. adults with ASD.

      Purpose The purpose of the study is to investigate whether Internet-based CBT is an effective
      method of raising the quality of life and improving the mental health of adults with ASD.
      Whether the occurrence of schizotypal personality traits predicts outcome or dropout will
      also be investigated. Since internet based treatment is relatively unexplored for patients
      with ASD, the research Group will also investigate the patients' subjective experience of
      such treatment, as well as systematically investigate what the written communication between
      patient and therapists will contain.

      Research questions

        1. Will adults with autism spectrum disorder follow an internet-based individual therapy
           that includes the possibility of participating in group sessions online for two
           semesters and, if so, will they experience it as meaningful?

        2. Will an internet-based treatment lead to a greater increase in quality of life compared
           to an active control group, and will this difference remain at follow-up after 6 and 12
           months?

        3. Will an internet-based treatment lead to decreased symptoms of depression and anxiety
           and better knowledge of autism compared to an active control group and will this
           differences remain at follow up?

        4. Will the number of days in psychiatric inpatient care two years before and two years
           after the intervention differ between the group receiving internet-based CBT and the
           active control group?

        5. How do participants experience internet-based treatment?

        6. What content does the written communication between therapists and participants have?

        7. Will schizotypal personality traits predict dropout or outcome?

      Method

      Design and selection Randomized controlled treatment design with two conditions. The
      experiment group receives internet-based individual treatment with the possibility of
      participating in group discussions online. An active control group reads two books about ASD,
      one describing ASD and the other are stories of individuals who themselves have ASD. 84
      persons with ASD between 16 and 55 years will be recruited from all over the country (with
      priority from Örebro and Uppsala regions). Exclusion criteria are ongoing psychotherapy with
      CBT or social behavior training, serious mental illness, mental developmental disorder or
      high risk of suicide. Additional exclusion criteria include inability to fill out forms and
      answer questions on the internet, inability to read and understand the Swedish language, as
      well as reported threatening behavior.Participants will either be randomized into the
      intervention group or active control group.

      Recruitment Information about the project is given to personnel working with the patient
      group in psychiatric and habilitation centers. Information will also be available in waiting
      rooms of healthcare facilities, in social media and on websites for psychiatric and
      autism-related associations, as well as through local press advertising. Information will
      clearly indicate how to apply for interest to the study. Potential participants will
      themselves submit an application of interest to participate via 1177.se, the website for
      Swedish healthcare e-services. Assessment interviews will be conducted through video link and
      symptoms of depression and other forms of psychopathology will be assessed through MINI-7
      interviews.

      Intervention

      The control group receive 36 modules of internet based CBT (ICBT). Theoretical base and tasks
      in each module will be presented in text. Each participant has a personal therapist who
      guides the participant throughout the treatment and provides support and feedback linked to
      each completed module of the treatment. The modules contain the following themes:

        -  Psychoeducation - diagnostic criteria, symptoms, mentalization, perception etc

        -  Social interaction - relations, communication

        -  Mental health/illness - depression, anxiety

        -  Goal settings- individual goals, what can i change?

        -  Behavioral change - problem solving strategies, energy prioritizing

        -  Life quality - food, sleep, physical activity

        -  Stress management - relaxation, mindfulness

        -  Everyday strategies - facilitate everyday life, structure and organization

        -  Social and civil rights - housing support, job opportunities, law and ethics

      The sessions with group discussions will be held at a certain time every 3rd week. The
      discussions revolve around specific questions linked to the theme of the current treatment
      week. The discussions will be supervised and led by a therapist and are held through a closed
      discussion forum online.

      Control group The control group is offered self-studies by reading the book &quot;What does the
      disability mean ?: Living with autism / Asperger syndrome&quot;, as well as a book containing
      biographical stories from people who themselves have ASD. The first book will be read during
      the first half of the project, and the second will be in the second half.

      Data Collection Each potential participant will initially be asked to answer a questionnaire
      online. The questionnaire includes questions about psychiatric symptoms, quality of life,
      demographic variables, employment and knowledge about ASD etc. Information that verifies the
      ASD diagnosis is obtained from the patients' medical record with the participant's consent.
      An interview via video or telephone is conducted with all potential participants and they are
      interviewed with a structured assessment tool for psychiatric diagnostics (M.I.N.I. version
      7). Information about prior treatment will also be collected, as well as a summary of prior
      amount of care utilization, in order to enable a health-economic analysis. A questionnaire
      that focuses on the participant's level of knowledge about ASD is distributed before and
      after treatment, to investigate whether participants have acquired knowledge of ASD during
      the course of intervention. Information about the patient's expectations of treatment is
      obtained before start. Data on patient satisfaction with treatment and possible side effects
      are obtained after the end of treatment.

      Power Calculation The experience of treatment for adults with ASD is very limited, and
      therefore, there are quite few previous results to be based on when making assumptions about
      the expected effect. However, a previous study of adult patients with ASD found an effect
      size of d = 0.43 (SD = 1.68) on self-assessed quality of life, measured before and after CBT
      in group. To get 80% power to find a difference of that size (given an alpha level of 0.05),
      42 participants will be recruited. In the previous study (on site) there was a loss of 17%.
      It is difficult to estimate how much the loss occurs when the treatment is administered
      through internet, but if assumed that the loss is 50%, the intention is to include at least
      84 participants in order to answer the scientific questions. The calculations are made using
      the PS - Power and Sample Size Calculations software.

      Measurement Quality of life is measured by Brunnsviken Brief quality of Life questionnaire
      (BBQ) and RAND-36 before and after the end of treatment and in a 6-month and one-year
      follow-up. Clinical Global Impression (CGI) is used to measure global mental health and its
      change after treatment. EQ-5D and Sense of Coherence Scale (SOC) measure overall health and
      experience of context. Depression and anxiety are measured with Hospital Anxiety Depression
      Scale (HADS), schizotypic traits with SPQ and obsessive symptoms are assessed with BOCS.
      Suicide thoughts are examined using one item in PHQ-9 in addition to structured questions
      about suicidal thoughts included in the structured diagnostic interview material M.I.N.I.
      (version 7.0.0). The self-assessment form RAADS - Ritvo Autism-Asperger's Diagnostic Scale is
      used to measure autistic traits and the level of participant autism is evaluated by clinics
      before and after the intervention. Participants expectations on the treatment are assessed at
      the beginning. Expectations are measured with Patient Prognostic Expectancy Inventory and
      PATHEV. Knowledge about autism is measured before, during and after treatment using Autism
      Knowledge questionnaire, which is a questionnaire created for the project. Self-acceptance,
      self-awareness, mood and ability to ask for help, as well as the extent of social contacts,
      sickness absence, and occurrence of work / studies will be measured after the intervention
      using a collection of follow-up questions compiled for a previous project. Satisfaction with
      the treatment is measured with CSQ and negative side effects are measured through Negative
      Effects questionnaire (NEQ) after the end of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in life quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline, at 9 weeks, at 18 weeks, at 6 months and at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Possible interaction effect between group and time in respect of differences in quality of life of the intervention group and the control group between pre, post and follow-up measurement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depressive and anxiety symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline, at 9 weeks, at 18 weeks, at 6 months and at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Possible interaction effect between group and time in respect of differences in Depressive and anxiety symptoms of the intervention group and the control group between pre, post and follow-up measurement. Depression and anxiety symptoms will be measured using HADS</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge of ASD</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline, at 9 weeks and at 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Possible interaction effect between group and time in respect of differences in knowledge about ASD of the intervention group and the control group between pre, post and follow-up measurement. Change in knowledge of ASD will be measured using using &quot;Autism Knowledge questionnaire&quot;, which is a questionnaire created for the project.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective experience of ICBT</measure>
    <time_frame>At 19 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The subjective experience of participating in an internet based treatment will be qualitatively evaluated using semi structured interview.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Content of communication</measure>
    <time_frame>At 20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Thematic content of the written communication between participant and therapist will be assessed using content analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between schizotypal traits using SPQ and effect in quality of Life using BBQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Correlation are measured from Baseline, at 9 weeks and at 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Potential correlation between schizotypal traits using the questionnaire Schizotypal traits questionnaire (SPQ) and effect in quality of Life using Brunnsviken Brief Quality of life questionnaire (BBQ)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>36 week internet-based CBT with therapist support. Regular online group discussions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Reads 2 books about Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Internet-based treatment for adults with autism spectrum</intervention_name>
    <description>Internet-based CBT. The intervention includes 36 modules focusing on: Psychoeducation, individual goal setting, behavioral change, management strategies, mindfulness techniques, stress management, sleep techniques, information about societal rights.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychoeducation about autism spectum disorder</intervention_name>
    <description>Self-studies by reading the book &quot;What does the disability mean ?: Living with autism / Asperger syndrome. Project Empowerment &quot;(2004), by Norrö &amp; Swing Åström, as well as a book of biographical stories of people who have ASD. The first book will be read during the first half of the project, and the second will be in the second half.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have ASD diagnosis

          -  Must have normal IQ

          -  Must be able to understand and read swedish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  high risk of suicide

          -  psychosis

          -  inability to fill out forms and answer questions on the internet

          -  inability to read and understand the Swedish language

          -  reported threatening behavior

          -  ongoing psychotherapy with CBT or social behavior training

          -  mental development disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Britta Westerberg</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Region Örebro County</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Region Örebro County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Örebro</city>
        <state>Örebro County</state>
        <zip>70217</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1983 Jun;67(6):361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>6880820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ware, JE., Kosinski, M. &amp; Gandek, B. (2005). SF-36 health survey: Manual and interpretation guide. Lincoln: Quality Metric, Inc.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>EuroQol Group. EuroQol--a new facility for the measurement of health-related quality of life. Health Policy. 1990 Dec;16(3):199-208.</citation>
    <PMID>10109801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shulte, D., (2005). Zeitschrift für Klinische Psychologie und Psychotherapie, 34, 176-188.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sheehan, D.V., Lecrubier, Y., Sheehan, K., Harnett, J., Weiller, E., Keskiner, A., Schinka, J., Knapp, E., Sheehan, M. F. &amp; Dunbar, G. C. (1997). Reliability and validity of the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I.) according to the SCID-P. European Psychiatry, Vol 12(5), 1997, 232-241</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rydén, E. &amp; Bejerot, S. (2008). Autism Spectrum Disorders in an adult Psychiatric Population. A Naturalistic Cross-Sectional controlled study. Clinical Neuropsychiatry, 5, 1, 13-21.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rozental A, Kottorp A, Boettcher J, Andersson G, Carlbring P. Negative Effects of Psychological Treatments: An Exploratory Factor Analysis of the Negative Effects Questionnaire for Monitoring and Reporting Adverse and Unwanted Events. PLoS One. 2016 Jun 22;11(6):e0157503. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0157503. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27331907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richards D, Richardson T. Computer-based psychological treatments for depression: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Rev. 2012 Jun;32(4):329-42. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2012.02.004. Epub 2012 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22466510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramsay, JR., Brodkin, R. Cohen, ES. Listerud, MR. &amp; Rostain, J. (2005). &quot;Better Strangers&quot;: Using the Relationship in Psychotherapy for Adult Patients with Asperger Syndrome. Psychotherpy: Theory, Research, Practice, Training, 42, 483-93</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raine, A., &amp; Benishay, D (1995). The SPQ-B: A Brief Screening Instrument for Schizotypal Personality Disorder. Journal of Personality Disorders: Vol. 9, No. 4, pp. 346-355.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin PJ, Sterne AL. Prognostic expectations and treatment outcome. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1975 Aug;43(4):572-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1159154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen DL, Attkisson CC, Hargreaves WA, Nguyen TD. Assessment of client/patient satisfaction: development of a general scale. Eval Program Plann. 1979;2(3):197-207.</citation>
    <PMID>10245370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kroenke K, Spitzer RL, Williams JB. The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure. J Gen Intern Med. 2001 Sep;16(9):606-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11556941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howlin, P. (2003). Autism preparing for adulthood. London: Routledge.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howlin, P. (2000). Outcome in adult life for more able individuals with autism or Asperger syndrome. Autism, 4, 63-83</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hesselmark E, Plenty S, Bejerot S. Group cognitive behavioural therapy and group recreational activity for adults with autism spectrum disorders: a preliminary randomized controlled trial. Autism. 2014 Aug;18(6):672-83. doi: 10.1177/1362361313493681. Epub 2013 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24089423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guy, W. (1976). The Clinical Global Impression Scale. ECDEU Assessment Manual for Psychopharmacology. 218-222</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaus, LV. (2007). Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy for Adult Asperger Syndrome. New York, NY: Guilford Press.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frith U, Happé F. Autism: beyond &quot;theory of mind&quot;. Cognition. 1994 Apr-Jun;50(1-3):115-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8039356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frisch, MB., Cornell, Villanueva &amp; Retzlaff. (1992). Clinical validation of the Quality of Life Inventory. A measure of life satisfaction for use in treatment planning and outcome assessment. Psychol Assess, 4, 92-101.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bejerot S, Eriksson JM, Mörtberg E. Social anxiety in adult autism spectrum disorder. Psychiatry Res. 2014 Dec 15;220(1-2):705-7. doi: 10.1016/j.psychres.2014.08.030. Epub 2014 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>25200187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bejerot S, Edman G, Anckarsäter H, Berglund G, Gillberg C, Hofvander B, Humble MB, Mörtberg E, Råstam M, Ståhlberg O, Frisén L. The Brief Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (BOCS): a self-report scale for OCD and obsessive-compulsive related disorders. Nord J Psychiatry. 2014 Nov;68(8):549-59. doi: 10.3109/08039488.2014.884631. Epub 2014 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24568661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Attwood T. (2008). Den kompletta guiden till Aspergers syndrom. Stockholm: Cura.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antonovsky A. The structure and properties of the sense of coherence scale. Soc Sci Med. 1993 Mar;36(6):725-33.</citation>
    <PMID>8480217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersen LM, Näswall K, Manouilenko I, Nylander L, Edgar J, Ritvo RA, Ritvo E, Bejerot S. The Swedish version of the Ritvo autism and asperger diagnostic scale: revised (RAADS-R). A validation study of a rating scale for adults. J Autism Dev Disord. 2011 Dec;41(12):1635-45. doi: 10.1007/s10803-011-1191-3.</citation>
    <PMID>21327833</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Region Örebro County</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fredrik Holländare</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor of Philosophy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Life quality</keyword>
  <keyword>ASD</keyword>
  <keyword>Internet based treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>ICBT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

