<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03577301</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATN145</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03577301</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Young Men's Health Project Targeting HIV Risk Reduction and Substance Abuse</brief_title>
  <acronym>YMHP</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparative Effectiveness Trial of Clinic-Based Delivery of an HIV Risk Reduction Intervention for Young Men Who Have Sex With Men (YMSM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Florida State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Florida State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      YMHP is a counseling intervention program for which the goals are to better understand
      HIV-prevention focused self-management behaviors among HIV-negative YMSM, and to study the
      implementation of YMHP to improve portability and scalability. The clinic sites will help
      investigators to assess and address practical problems at the frontline of service provision
      to pave the way for a comprehensive program to reduce HIV infection among YMSM that reflects
      the complexities of real world adolescent HIV clinics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Adapt YMHP for clinic and phone delivery by existing HIV clinic staff community health
           workers (CHWs), who work with YMSM ages 15-24. Investigators will conduct focus groups
           with staff to obtain input on how best to implement YMHP to maximize feasibility,
           acceptability, and sustainability, as well as issues with adapting the YMHP for delivery
           to YMSM ages 15-18 and for phone delivery.

        2. Compare the effectiveness of clinic-based versus phone-based delivery of YMHP in the
           context of health care access. In order to inform future implementation, investigators
           will test the effectiveness of YMHP delivered via these two modalities.

             1. Assess the cost-effectiveness of both delivery formats of YMHP to enhance the
                likelihood of uptake of this best evidence intervention. The hypothesis is that
                phone-based will be more cost-effective than clinic-based

             2. Assess the Five Components of the Self-Management Model and how these components
                vary over time, are directly improved by the interventions, and mediate
                intervention effects.

        3. Test a sustainable model of YMHP implementation in real world adolescent clinics.
           Investigators will utilize local supervisors within the clinic setting to sustain the
           CHWs fidelity to delivering the motivational interviewing (MI)-based YMHP intervention.
           Fidelity will be monitored throughout the trial and assessments and qualitative
           interviews will be conducted with key stakeholders to determine the barriers and
           facilitators of YMHP implementation utilizing the Exploration, Preparation,
           Implementation, Sustainment model (EPIS).

      Aims will be achieved over two phases of the study.

      Phase I: Investigators will conduct research (Exploration and Preparation phases of EPIS
      model) to obtain implementation feedback to best adapt YMHP for clinic-based CHWs, further
      incorporate PrEP navigation services, and expand the YMHP protocol to be relevant for
      Telephone-based Motivational Interviewing (TBMI). We will train a minimum of 2 CHWs at each
      clinic drawing on the Implementation Science Core (ISC) to apply best-practices in training.
      Once CHWs demonstrate competence according to the Motivational Interviewing Treatment
      Integrity (MITI), Phase 2 will begin.

      Phase II: Personnel will recruit and enroll 180 YMSM, ages 15-24, 60 at each of the three
      sites. Sessions will be audio-recorded for MITI fidelity coding, and CHWs and supervisors
      will be given implementation support throughout. Prior to implementation, immediately at the
      conclusion of the intervention delivery phase, and one year after, the ISC will conduct
      interviews with CHWs, supervisors, and clinic leaders to obtain information about the
      barriers and facilitators of implementation and sustainment.

      Target n: 180 YMSM across three sites (60 per site).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual Self Management Change</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Month Interval</time_frame>
    <description>Computer Assisted Self Interview (CASI) scored through Qualtrics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual Health Management Change</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Month Interval</time_frame>
    <description>Serologic lab test of blood sample - positive or negative for HIV and other Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Substance Abuse Change</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Month Interval</time_frame>
    <description>Nucleic Acid Amplification (NAA) Urinalysis Drug Screen</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clinic-based Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the intervention in person following HIV counseling and testing. The intervention involves completion of the 4 YMHP sessions and the delivery of pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) information and navigation services to interested participants. This arm is closed to enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Remote Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the intervention by remote delivery following HIV counseling and testing. Just as the clinic-based participants, he intervention involves completion of the 4 YMHP sessions and the delivery of pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) information and navigation services to interested participants. This arm is closed to enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multi-modal Delivery</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 4 session MI intervention. Session 1 is always delivered in person immediately after baseline. Session 2-4 can be delivered in person or remotely based upon youth preference. This arm is open to enrollment as of 11/15/2019.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment as usual control = individual HIV testing with referrals and link age to care as provided by the sites under routine circumstances. This arm is open to enrollment as of 11/15/2019.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinic-based Delivery</intervention_name>
    <description>A minimum of 2 community health workers (CHWs) will be trained to deliver clinic-based intervention sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clinic-based Delivery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remote Delivery</intervention_name>
    <description>A minimum of 2 community health workers (CHWs) will be trained to deliver intervention sessions to the participant in a location remote from the clinic setting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Remote Delivery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multi-modal Delivery</intervention_name>
    <description>A minimum of 2 community health workers (CHWs) will be trained to deliver clinic-based or remote intervention sessions. First MI session is in person immediately after baseline. Sessions 2-4 can be delivered in person or remotely based on youth preference.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multi-modal Delivery</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-negative test result from the past 90 days

          -  15-24 years of age

          -  Born biologically male or currently identifying as male

          -  Sex with men in the past 90 days

          -  ≥ 5 days of illicit drug use in the past 90 days

          -  ≥ 1 episode of Condomless Anal Sex (CAS) in the past 90 days, or a positive STI test
             result in the past 90 days.

          -  Able to communicate in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious cognitive or psychiatric impairments

          -  Currently taking Truvada as Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis (PrEP)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sylvie Naar, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Florida State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tyrel Starks, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-206-7919</phone>
    <email>tstarks@chestnyc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lawrence Friedman, PhD</last_name>
      <email>lfriedman@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Donna Maturo</last_name>
      <email>dmaturo@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lawrence Friedman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anguliqe Outlaw, PhD</last_name>
      <email>aoutlaw@med.wayne.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Monique Green-Jones, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>313-577-0792</phone>
      <email>mogreen@med.wayne.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Tanney</last_name>
      <email>tanney@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kim Desir</last_name>
      <email>desirk@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary Tanney</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Men Who Have Sex with Men (MSM)</keyword>
  <keyword>PrEP</keyword>
  <keyword>YMHP</keyword>
  <keyword>YMSM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 19, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/01/NCT03577301/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

