<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03578432</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHXB-17-0072-70-15</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-00492</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CRAD001XUA274T</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PHXB-17-0072-70-15</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA023074</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03578432</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Everolimus in Restoring Salivary Gland Function in Participants With Locally Advanced Head and Neck Cancer Treated With Radiation Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Evaluation of Everolimus (a Rapamycin Analog) in Restoring Salivary Gland Function to Patients Treated With Radiotherapy for Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arizona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arizona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This early phase 1 trial studies the use of everolimus in restoring salivary gland function
      in participants with locally advanced head and neck cancer after concurrent chemoradiation or
      radiation therapy alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the recovery of salivary gland function after administration of a 5-day course
      of everolimus, administered two weeks after completion of radiation or chemoradiation
      therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the decrease of saliva flow rates during radiation or chemoradiation therapy.

      II. To describe the changes in saliva protein composition during radiation or chemoradiation
      therapy and following administration of a 5-day course of everolimus.

      OUTLINE: This is an early phase 1 proof of principal study.

      Participants receive everolimus orally (PO) once daily (QD) for 5 days beginning 2 weeks
      after completion of radiation or chemoradiation treatment. Participants also undergo saliva
      output testing at baseline prior to radiation or chemoradiation treatment, after 3 weeks of
      RT/chemoRT, after 6 weeks of RT/chemoRT, prior to everolimus administration, at completion of
      the 5 day everolimus course, and at 1, 3, and 6 months after the completion of radiation or
      chemoradiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    UACC-PHX is no longer able to support the study and Novartis is unable to provide drug beyond
    December 2019.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent recovery of salivary gland function</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months after completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>The primary end point of the analysis will be the percent recovery of salivary gland function, with pre-everolimus treatment saliva flow rate as the denominator and the saliva flow rate at 3 months after completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy as the numerator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of saliva flow rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured during radiotherapy treatment at 3, 6 weeks, and prior to everolimus administration and the subsequent recovery of saliva flow rates at completion of the 5 day everolimus course and 1, 3 and 6 months after radiation therapy/chemoradiation therapy completion to determine the kinetics and stability of saliva flow rate recovery. Will be explored using graphical methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Saliva protein composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Protein composition within the saliva will be measured and will be expressed as percent decrease and recovery of amylase at all available time points. Will be explored using graphical methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total score obtained on Xerostomia Visual Analog Scale survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Will be explored using graphical methods. Subjective assessment of salivary dysfunction. • Scale ranges: not difficult at all - very difficult. • Not difficult at all is considered better, very difficult is considered worse. Subscales are summed. Scale ranges: 1-5 = • 1 (Never), 2 (hardly ever), 3 (occasionally), 4 (fairly often), 5 (very often). • Sub scales are summed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total score obtained on Xerostomia Inventory Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Will be explored using graphical methods. Measures xerostomia symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Salivary Gland Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Xerostomia</condition>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive care (everolimus, saliva output testing)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive everolimus PO QD for 5 days beginning 2 weeks after radiation treatment. Participants also undergo saliva output testing at baseline prior to radiation or chemoradiation treatment, after 3 weeks of RT/chemoRT, after 6 weeks of RT/chemoRT, prior to everolimus administration, at completion of the 5 day everolimus course, and at 1, 3, and 6 months after the completion of radiation or chemoradiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive care (everolimus, saliva output testing)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>42-O-(2-Hydroxy)ethyl Rapamycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Afinitor</other_name>
    <other_name>Certican</other_name>
    <other_name>RAD 001</other_name>
    <other_name>RAD001</other_name>
    <other_name>Votubia</other_name>
    <other_name>Zortress</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive care (everolimus, saliva output testing)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supportive care (everolimus, saliva output testing)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Performance status Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) ≤ 2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Platelets ≥ 100 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt; 9 g/dL

          -  Total serum bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 2.5 x upper
             limits of normal (ULN) (≤ 5 x ULN in patients with liver metastases)

          -  International normalized ratio (INR) ≤ 2

          -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

          -  Fasting serum cholesterol ≤ 300 mg/dL or ≤ 7.75 mmol/L and fasting triglycerides ≤ 2.5
             x ULN

               -  NOTE: in case one or both of these thresholds are exceeded, the patient can only
                  be included after initiation of appropriate lipid lowering medication

          -  Signed informed consent obtained prior to any screening procedures

          -  Patients with locally advanced squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck, treated
             with curative intent either in the post-operative or definitive setting with high dose
             radiotherapy (≥ 50 Gy) with or without chemotherapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients currently receiving anticancer therapies or who have received anticancer
             therapies within 2 weeks of the start of everolimus (including chemotherapy, radiation
             therapy, antibody based therapy, etc.)

          -  Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycin analogs (e.g.
             sirolimus, temsirolimus)

          -  Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of oral everolimus

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) &gt; 8% despite
             adequate therapy; patients with a known history of impaired fasting glucose or
             diabetes mellitus (DM) may be included, however blood glucose and antidiabetic
             treatment must be monitored closely throughout the trial and adjusted as necessary

          -  Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions such as:

               -  Unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial
                  infarction ≤ 6 months prior to start of everolimus, serious uncontrolled cardiac
                  arrhythmia, or any other clinically significant cardiac disease

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure of New York heart Association class III or
                  IV

               -  Active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infection, liver disease such as
                  cirrhosis, decompensated liver disease, and active and chronic hepatitis (i.e.
                  quantifiable hepatitis B virus [HBV]-deoxyribonucleic acid [DNA] and/or positive
                  hepatitis B virus surface antigen [HbsAg], quantifiable hepatitis C virus
                  [HCV]-ribonucleic acid [RNA])

               -  Known severely impaired lung function (spirometry and carbon monoxide diffusing
                  capacity [DLCO] 50% or less of normal and oxygen [O2] saturation 88% or less at
                  rest on room air)

               -  Active, bleeding diathesis

          -  Chronic treatment with corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents; topical or
             inhaled corticosteroids are allowed

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity

          -  Patients who have received live attenuated vaccines within 1 week of start of
             everolimus and during the study; patient should also avoid close contact with others
             who have received live attenuated vaccines; examples of live attenuated vaccines
             include intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, Bacillus
             Calmette-Guerin (BCG), yellow fever, varicella and TY21a typhoid vaccines

          -  Patients who have a history of another primary malignancy, with the exceptions of:
             nonmelanoma skin cancer, and carcinoma in situ of the cervix, uteri, or breast from
             which the patient has been disease free for ≥ 3 years

          -  Patients with a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable or will not be able to complete the entire study

          -  Patients who are currently part of or have participated in any clinical investigation
             with an investigational drug within 1 month prior to dosing

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP) (including female pediatric patients who are
             menarcheal or who become menarcheal during the treatment), defined as all women
             physiologically capable of becoming pregnant, must use highly effective methods of
             contraception during the study and 8 weeks after; women are considered post-menopausal
             and not of child-bearing potential if they have had 12 months of natural (spontaneous)
             amenorrhea with an appropriate clinical profile (e.g. age appropriate, history of
             vasomotor symptoms); highly effective contraception methods include combination of any
             two of the following:

               -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or placement
                  of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS) or other forms of
                  hormonal contraception that have comparable efficacy (failure rate &lt; 1%), for
                  example, hormone vaginal ring or transdermal hormone contraception; in case of
                  use of oral contraception women should have been stable on the oral agent for a
                  minimum of 3 months before taking everolimus

               -  Total abstinence

               -  Male partner sterilization; (the vasectomized male partner should be the sole
                  partner for that subject)

               -  Female sterilization have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without
                  hysterectomy), total hysterectomy or tubal ligation at least six weeks prior
                  torandomization; in the case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive
                  status of the woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment is
                  she considered not of child-bearing potential

          -  Male patients whose sexual partner(s) are WOCBP who are not willing to use adequate
             contraception, during the study and for 8 weeks after the end of treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Panayiotis Savvides</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Arizona Cancer Center at Dignity Health St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Arizona Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Xerostomia</keyword>
  <keyword>Dry Mouth</keyword>
  <keyword>Salivary Gland Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Head and Neck Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Mouth Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Everolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>Rapamycin</keyword>
  <keyword>Neck Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Saliva</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Xerostomia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 22, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/32/NCT03578432/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

