<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03577288</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>69HCL18_0224</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03577288</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Emotion in Virtual Reality on Behavior of Children and Young Adults</brief_title>
  <acronym>EPREV-EA</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Appearance and Control of Emotions in Virtual Reality on Behaviour in Children and Young Adults: Link With Feeling of Presence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospices Civils de Lyon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recently, researchers in the field of cognitive psychology have shown a great interest in
      Virtual Reality (VR). Indeed, this technology is the most advanced to create immersion and
      sense of presence in a virtual environment (VE) and gives the opportunity to study cognitive
      mechanisms in more ecological way. However, little is known about the impact of VR on the
      cognition and emotional states of the VR users. According to the scientific literature, the
      sense of presence (the fact that the user experiences the sense of being in the VE) is
      strongly related to the emotional experience, but it is not clear what mechanisms underline
      this relation. Thus, more research is necessary to its better understanding. Moreover, a few
      studies have shown age related differences in sense of presence, with children having greater
      inclination for sense of presence than adults. This might be explained by the fact that
      frontal cortex (which is responsible for a control of the sense of presence) is still
      developing in childhood (the maturation last for the beginning of adulthood).

      The goal of the present study is to examine which factors might be responsible of the
      interaction between the sense of presence, the immersion and the emotional experience in
      Virtual Reality, and the age-related difference. Thus, the investigator study 2 types of
      healthy participants (volunteers) in order to examine the age-related difference in this
      interaction: young adults between 18 and 25 years old and children between 8 to 14 years old.
      To study different factors potentially involved in the interaction four experiments will be
      conducted. In each experiment the investigator manipulate one type of factor to study its
      impact on emotions and the sense of presence in a VE: (1) the image quality, (2) the fact
      that participant had an avatar (body) in the VE, (3) the possibility to interact or not in VE
      and (4) the nature of elements with which it is possible to interact (objects or living
      being). In the end of this study the investigator hope to contribute to the knowledge of
      adapted use of VR for different type of users, such as children and young adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 25, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 25, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>measure of valence and arousal with Self-Assessment Manikin (SAM) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of emotion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>response to the presence questionnaire (PQ, Witmer &amp; Singer, 1998</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of feeling of presence questionnaire PQ, Witmer &amp; Singer, 1998</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluation of feeling of immersion by a Likert scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of feeling of immersion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>responses evoked by the stimuli of interest</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>During Experience in Virtual Reality (EVR) we will measure responses evoked by the stimuli of interest: with oculometer time fixation and pupillary dilatation, and with oximeter heart rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of evoked potential</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>During EVR only in Experiment 1B we will measure, using EEG, evoked potential, particularly Late Positive Potential (LPP)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of head movements evoked by the stimuli of interest</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>During EVR except Experiment 1B we will measure, using the device integrated in VR equipment, head movements evoked by the stimuli of interest</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">510</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 1 A, B - Level of realism of EVR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants (50 children and 50 young adults for part A, and 50 other children and 50 other young adults) will be exposed to virtual experience having different level of realism. In one condition the realism will be high (very close to the real word) and in the second condition the realism will be low (comparable to cartoon). The stimuli of interest included in virtual experience will be of three emotional categories : negative, positive and neutral.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 2 - Presence and size of avatar</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants (50 children and 100 young adults) will be exposed to virtual experiences in which in one condition they will be part of the virtual environment in a body of an avatar and in another condition the avatar will not be present.
Children will be exposed to only one of the two possible situations: with an avatar or without an avatar for the entire experience. Adults will be exposed to only one of the four possible situations: with standard size avatar, with giant avatar, with tiny avatar, or without avatar.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 3 - Interaction in virtual experience</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants (50 children and 50 young adults) will be submitted to two conditions of virtual experience, one condition in which it is possible to interact with the stimuli presented in the virtual environment and another condition in which it is not possible to interact. In addition, the stimuli of interest will be of one of three emotional categories : negative, positive and neutral. Thus participants will be exposed to six short virtual experiences.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 4 - Animate/Inanimate nature of interactive objects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants (30 children and 30 young adults) will be exposed to the virtual experience during which they will be able to interact in one condition with animated (e.g., dog, bird) stimuli and in another condition with inanimate (e.g., book, jacket) stimuli. The animate and inanimate stimuli of interest will be of three emotional categories : negative, positive and neutral.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>manipulation of the level of realism</intervention_name>
    <description>The realism of the virtual experience will be manipulated. In one condition the realism will be high and in another condition the realism will be low. In addition, emotional category of stimuli for each virtual experience condition will be manipulated. Thus, each participant will be submitted to six virtual experiences (e.g., high realism with negative stimuli, low realism with negative stimuli, high realism with positive stimuli).
The measures of the pupillary responses, gaze fixation, heart rate, head movement (only in part A) and Late Positive Potential (EEG - only in part B) will be realized. In addition, the participants will respond to the scales and questionnaire evaluating their emotion, feeling of presence and feeling of immersion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 1 A, B - Level of realism of EVR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>manipulation of the presence and size of avatar</intervention_name>
    <description>The presence of avatar in the virtual experience will be manipulated. In one condition the avatar will be present and in another condition the avatar will not be present. In addition, emotional category of stimuli for each virtual experience condition will be manipulated. Thus, each participant will be submitted to six virtual experiences (e.g., with avatar and negative stimuli, without avatar and negative stimuli, with avatar and positive stimuli, etc.).
Children will be exposed to only one of the two possible situations: with an avatar or without an avatar for the entire experience. Adults will be exposed to only one of the four possible situations: with standard size avatar, with giant avatar, with tiny avatar, or without avatar.
The measures of the pupillary responses, gaze fixation, heart rate, head movement will be realized. In addition, the participants will respond to the scales and questionnaire evaluating their emotion, feeling of presence and feeling of immersion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 2 - Presence and size of avatar</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>manipulation of interaction</intervention_name>
    <description>Virtual experience condition will be manipulated. In one condition the participants will be exposed to the virtual experience in which they will be able to interact with some of the stimuli, in another condition they will not be able to interact with the stimuli (passive watching). In addition, emotional category of stimuli for each virtual experience condition will be manipulated. Thus, each participant will be submitted to six virtual experiences (e.g., interaction possible - negative stimuli, interaction impossible - negative stimuli, interaction possible - positive stimuli).
The measures of the pupillary responses, gaze fixation, heart rate, head movement will be realized. In addition, the participants will respond to the scales and questionnaire evaluating their emotion, feeling of presence and feeling of immersion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 3 - Interaction in virtual experience</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>manipulation of the nature of stimulus</intervention_name>
    <description>The nature of the stimuli with which the participants will interact will be manipulated. During virtual experience the participants will have a choice to interact or not with the virtual environment, in one condition with animate stimuli and in another condition with inanimate stimuli. In addition, emotional category of animate and inanimate stimuli will be manipulated. Thus, each participant will be submitted to six virtual experiences (e.g., condition with animate negative stimuli, condition with inanimate negative stimuli, condition with animate positive stimuli). The measures of the pupillary responses, gaze fixation, heart rate, head movement will be realized. In addition, the participants will respond to the scales and questionnaire evaluating their emotion, feeling of presence and feeling of immersion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experiment 4 - Animate/Inanimate nature of interactive objects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Children:

          -  Age comprised between 8 and 14

          -  Native French speaker

          -  Two parents gave their informed consent for a participation of their child in the
             study

        Young adults :

          -  Students

          -  Age comprised between 18 and 25

          -  Native French speaker

          -  Participant gave his/her informed consent for a participation in the study

          -  Participant has health insurance

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Children:

          -  Neurodevelopmental deficits, diagnosis of intellectual deficiency (Scores below 70 for
             Vineland II scale et Total IQ Total below 70 for WPPSI-IV (Wechsler, 2014) or WISC-V
             (Wechsler, 2016)) new by parents or legal representative

          -  Learning disorder (difficulties in learning and using scholar skills since at least 6
             months new by teacher, parents or legal representative)

          -  History of psychiatric disorder new by parents or legal representative

          -  Neurological disorders new by parents or legal representative

          -  Drugs intake having impact on motor, cognitive or memory capacities (e.g., corticoids)
             new by parents or legal representative

          -  Visual or hearing disorders without correction

          -  Epilepsy

          -  Child, parents or legal representative no agreement to participate to the study

        Young Adults :

          -  Neurological disorders new by participants

          -  Drugs intake having impact on motor, cognitive or memory capacities (e.g., corticoids)

          -  History of psychiatric disorder new by participant

          -  Use of drugs of alcohol

          -  Visual or hearing disorders without correction

          -  Epilepsy

          -  No agreement to participate to the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>28 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hanna CHAINAY</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université Lyon 2</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hanna CHAINAY</last_name>
    <phone>04 78 77 43 52</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>hanna.chainay@univ-lyon2.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EA3082 Laboratoire d'Etude des Mécanismes Cognitifs Institut de Psychologie Université Lyon 2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hanna CHAINAY</last_name>
      <phone>04 78 77 43 52</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>hanna.chainay@univ-lyon2.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hanna CHAINAY</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Feelings</keyword>
  <keyword>Emotions</keyword>
  <keyword>Virtual Reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Young Adult</keyword>
  <keyword>Child</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

