<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03575221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>180120</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>18-CH-0120</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03575221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural History of the Collagen-Related Disorder Osteogenesis Imperfecta and Genotype Phenotype Correlation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Natural History of the Collagen-Related Disorder Osteogenesis Imperfecta and the Genotype-Phenotype Correlation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Osteogenesis Imperfecta (OI) is a connective tissue disorder. OI affects many aspects of a
      person s health and growth. It can cause frequent fractures, short stature, and bowing of the
      long bones. There is no known cure for OI so researchers want to learn more about it.

      Objectives:

      To obtain a natural history of the course of OI. To find changes in genes that affect the
      disease.

      Eligibility:

      People from birth to age 12 years with certain types of OI

      People who previously had childhood data collected in certain other protocols

      Design:

      Participants will stay in the clinic for a few days each visit. Visits will be about every
      3-4 months to age 5 then about every 6-12 months. Visits may include:

      Medical history

      Physical exam

      Hearing test

      Dental exam

      Blood, urine, and heart tests

      Breathing measured while wearing a clear plastic hood for about 30 minutes

      Tests of motion, strength, and motor skills

      X-rays of the left hand, chest, legs, and spine

      Bone density scan. Participants will lie on a flat table while a very small dose of x-rays is
      passed through the body.

      Computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging scans. Participants will lie on an exam
      table that moves in and out a scanner.

      Breathing tests using stickers on the chest, a light probe on a finger or foot, and a face
      mask

      Ultrasound of the kidneys, ureters, and bladder

      Questionnaires

      A small section of skin removed from the arm or thigh

      For some tests, participants may take medicine to make them sleepy.

      Participants may give separate consent for photos to be taken.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose a longitudinal study of the natural history of the collagen-related disorder
      osteogenesis imperfecta (OI). The overall objectives are to 1) obtain a comprehensive
      assessment of the natural history and progression of the multiple secondary features of
      osteogenesis imperfecta, and 2) further the understanding of genotype-phenotype correlation
      using biosamples collected from well-characterized affected individuals. This study is in
      part a continuation of protocol 97-CH-0064, and thus will continue to follow individuals with
      OI enrolled in that protocol, to incorporate biosamples obtained, and to analyze data
      collected under that protocol.

      The major objectives of protocol 97-CH-0064 have focused on radiographic features including
      scoliosis and rib deformities, bone density, intensive rehabilitation, and physical therapy.
      New developments in genetics, bone tissue biology, and pathophysiology of OI in the past
      decade, along with the increasing life expectancy of affected individuals, highlight a need
      for the continuation and expansion of this natural history study to understand the full
      phenotypic disease spectrum, and to generate biobanks of tissue samples from
      well-characterized study participants for continued research.

      This proposed protocol will:

        1. Continue to follow study participants, use biosamples, and analyze data gathered under
           protocol 97-CH-0064 (which will be closed upon the start of this protocol).

        2. Expand to include currently known collagen-related OI types V-XVIII and potential
           additional types, in addition to collagen OI types III and IV included under protocol
           97-CH-0064.

        3. Extend the age criteria for study participants to include individuals of all ages, with
           age at study enrollment targeted to those from birth to 12 years. This will allow us to
           follow clinical outcomes of young adults who had aged out of prior NICHD OI research
           programs.

      The major objectives will focus on:

        1. Continued comprehensive assessment of radiographic, bone density, audiology, dental,
           cardiovascular, pulmonary, and neurologic manifestations, and physical rehabilitation.
           The immediate goals from this will encompass a) identifying underlying contributing
           factors and comorbidities for scoliosis, b) gaining insight into occurrence and
           progression of cardiac valvular abnormalities, and c) elucidating the pathogenesis of
           primary lung parenchymal defects in individuals with OI.

        2. Additional comprehensive assessment of endocrine and renal systems. The novel evaluation
           of metabolism in individuals with OI will allow understanding of obesity prevalence in
           this population.

        3. Continued genetic and molecular biology investigations of OI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2029</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2029</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical course, underlying pathogenesis, and comorbidities in the assessed systems in individuals with OI</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>clinical course</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of genotype and phenotype</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>genotype-phenotype correlations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Causes of morbidities in individuals with OI</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>clinical course</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability and feasibility of each measure of the clinical battery of assessments based on clinical observation</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">125</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteogenesis Imperfecta</condition>
  <condition>Short Stature</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enrollees</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with Osteogenesis Imperfecta</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals of all ages, races, genders, and nationalities@@@@@@
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Individuals previously enrolled in 97-CH-0064, or other NIH OI study protocols for
             whom childhood data were collected at the NIH.

          -  Individuals from birth to age 12 years at enrollment with a diagnosis of OI type III -
             XVIII and potential additional types.

               -  Diagnosis of OI determined by identification of:

                    1. A mutation in one allele of genes causing autosomal dominant OI types
                       (COL1A1, COL1A2, or IFITM5), OR

                    2. at least one mutation in genes that are indicative of the autosomal
                       recessive OI types.

        OR

        Individuals with a clinical diagnosis of OI, and a mutation in one of the above genes
        identified through the screening protocol.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Individuals with the diagnosis of OI Type I.

          -  Individuals who cannot travel to the NIH because of their medical condition.

          -  Individuals who, in the opinion of the Investigator, are unable to comply with the
             protocol or have medical conditions that would potentially increase the risk of
             participation.

        &lt;TAB&gt;

        There are no exclusionary criteria related to race or gender for this protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joan C Marini, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joan C Marini, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-3418</phone>
    <email>marinij@cc1.nichd.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2018-CH-0120.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 1, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteogenesis Imperfecta</keyword>
  <keyword>Collagen</keyword>
  <keyword>Short Stature</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteogenesis Imperfecta</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

