<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03573973</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20986</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03573973</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Responses to Adjusted Product Placement and Its Effects on Diet - 2</brief_title>
  <acronym>WRAPPED2</acronym>
  <official_title>Nudging Healthier Dietary Habits: Evaluation of a Supermarket Placement Strategy in the WRAPPED Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Southampton NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Health Research, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Southampton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Southampton NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is the largest supermarket trial internationally and will assess the effectiveness
      and cost-effectiveness of improving the placement of fresh fruit and vegetables in discount
      supermarkets in improving the fresh fruit and vegetable purchasing of women aged 18-45 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      WRAPPED2 (Women's Responses to Adjusted Product Placement and its Effects on Diet - 2) is a
      natural experiment with a prospective matched controlled cluster design. The setting is a
      discount supermarket chain in the United Kingdom regularly used by disadvantaged families for
      their main shop. The intervention is a store refurbishment programme that involves creation
      of a new fresh fruit and vegetable section in the store entrance. Control stores keep the
      existing layout with a limited range of fresh fruit and vegetables and placement of fresh
      fruit and vegetables at the back of the store.

      A total of 45 participants will be recruited from each of 18 intervention and 18 matched
      control stores through the retailer's loyalty card scheme (postal letter) and shop floor
      recruitment; these methods proved effective during the pilot. Participants will be women aged
      18-45 years who shopped at a study store in the 12 weeks before recruitment. This study is
      unique in its collection of individual level sales data, as well as demographic and dietary
      information, and is the first to collect outcome data for more than one family member.
      Participant's weekly sales data will be obtained through the retailer's loyalty card scheme
      and will cover 3 months before refurbishment, plus 0-3 months and 3-6 months after. Change in
      women's fresh fruit and vegetable purchasing from baseline to 3 months is the primary
      outcome. Secondary outcome data about women's diets, their young child's diet (2-6 years),
      food shopping habits, perceptions of supermarket environment, and psychosocial and
      demographic characteristics will be collected by telephone survey before refurbishment, and
      1, 3 and 6 months after. Weekly sales data for study stores will be provided by the retailer.

      Cost-effectiveness will be assessed from individual, retailer and societal perspectives.
      Process evaluation will assess implementation, mechanisms of impact and context.

      This study is politically and scientifically important being one of the first field studies
      of this kind. The findings could provide strong evidence for future public health policy
      interventions to help address inequalities in diet and non-communicable disease risk by
      supporting development of a healthy store layout that could be adopted more widely in food
      retail outlets.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Natural experiment with prospective matched controlled cluster design. The setting is a UK discount supermarket chain.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant's weekly fruit and vegetable purchasing patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 month period post-refurbishment</time_frame>
    <description>These data will be obtained through the retailer's loyalty card scheme and provide information about the number of items of each product purchased at each store visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Women's dietary quality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 month follow-up post intervention commencement</time_frame>
    <description>20-item food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) will be used to create standardised diet quality scores for each woman. A dietary quality score for each woman will be calculated by multiplying their reported frequency of consumption of each of the 20 items from their FFQ by corresponding weightings derived from the appropriate principal components analysis and then summing the results.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's dietary quality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 month follow-up post intervention commencement</time_frame>
    <description>20-item food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) will be used to create standardised diet quality scores for each child. Dietary quality scores will be calculated by multiplying the reported frequency of consumption of each of the 20 items from their FFQ by corresponding weightings derived from the appropriate principal components analysis and then summing the results.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Women's daily fruit and vegetable intake</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months follow-up post intervention commencement</time_frame>
    <description>2-item tool has been validated against urinary potassium and plasma ascorbic acid to describe high (≥5 portions/day) and low (≤2.5 portions/day) intake.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weekly store sales of fresh fruit and vegetables</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 and 0-6 month periods post-refurbishment</time_frame>
    <description>Store sales data will be provided from electronic transaction records aggregated to the weekly level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether change in participants' in fruit and vegetable purchasing patterns (intervention effects) differ according to their level of educational attainment</measure>
    <time_frame>0-6 month period post-refurbishment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess interaction on intervention effects according to participants' highest educational qualification attained in 3 groups (low=GCSE/school departure before 16 years of age, medium=A-levels/HND/diploma, high=degree)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic evaluation to assess the costs and benefits of the intervention from individual, retailer and societal perspectives</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month period post-refurbishment</time_frame>
    <description>Use participant survey and purchasing data for food expenditure, time spent food shopping, as well as travel costs to and from supermarkets; retailer costs will be estimates generated through discussion with supermarket staff; societal costs will be estimated for resources associated with the capital investment, changes in food expenditure, time and travel costs for individuals and health and social care costs for diet-related health conditions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1080</enrollment>
  <condition>Diet Modification</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fresh fruit and vegetable placement intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention is a store refurbishment programme that includes the creation of a new fresh fruit and vegetable section at the store entrance with expanded range thus improving the availability and position of fresh fruit and vegetables.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control condition is the existing store layout with a limited range of fresh fruit and vegetables that are placed at the back of the store.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Improved product placement of fresh fruit and vegetables</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention includes the creation of a new fresh fruit and vegetable section at the store entrance with expanded range thus improving the placement (availability and position) of fresh fruit and vegetables.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fresh fruit and vegetable placement intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>The control condition is the existing store layout with a limited range of fresh fruit and vegetables that are placed at the back of the store.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women aged 18-45 years

          -  Hold a store loyalty card

          -  Shop regularly in a study store

          -  Shoppers who choose items in-store but opt for home delivery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women under the age of 18 or over 45 years

          -  Males or children

          -  Irregular shopper or online-only shopper

          -  Do not hold store loyalty card
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christina Vogel, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 2380 764042</phone>
    <email>cv@mrc.soton.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Janis Baird, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 2380 764057</phone>
    <email>jb@mrc.soton.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univeristy of Southampton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <state>Hampshire</state>
        <zip>SO16 6YD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina Vogel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>023 8076 4042</phone>
      <email>cv@mrc.soton.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janis Baird, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>023 8076 4057</phone>
      <email>jb@mrc.soton.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dietary inequalities</keyword>
  <keyword>Public Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Choice architecture</keyword>
  <keyword>Supermarkets</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

