<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03573518</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BTX.2018.001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03573518</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of BTX 1503 in Patients With Moderate to Severe Acne Vulgaris</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Vehicle-Controlled Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of BTX 1503 in Patients With Moderate to Severe Acne Vulgaris</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Botanix Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Botanix Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to assess safety and efficacy of various doses of BTX 1503
      liquid formulation in subjects with moderate to severe acne vulgaris of the face.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a multi-center, randomized, double-blinded, vehicle-controlled, parallel group,
      dose-finding study in pediatrics, adolescents and adults (aged 12 to 40 years). The objective
      of this study is to assess the safety and efficacy of various doses of BTX 1503 in subjects
      with moderate to severe acne vulgaris of the face.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 5, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute Change from Baseline in inflammatory lesion counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change from Baseline in non-inflammatory lesion counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change from Baseline in inflammatory lesion counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change from Baseline in non-inflammatory lesion counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with at least a 2-grade reduction from Baseline IGA</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with an IGA score of &quot;clear&quot; or &quot;almost clear&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with an IGA score of &quot;clear&quot; or &quot;almost clear&quot; and at least 2-grade reduction from Baseline IGA</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">368</enrollment>
  <condition>Acne Vulgaris</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BTX 1503 Dose 1 BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BTX 1503 Dose 1 twice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BTX 1503 Dose 1 QD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BTX 1503 Dose 1 once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BTX 1503 Dose 2 QD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BTX 1502 Dose 2 once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vehicle twice daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle QD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vehicle once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BTX 1503</intervention_name>
    <description>BTX 1503 Dose 1 liquid formulation, or BTX 1503 Dose 2 liquid formulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>BTX 1503 Dose 1 BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BTX 1503 Dose 1 QD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BTX 1503 Dose 2 QD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vehicle</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vehicle QD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject (or legal guardian) has the ability and willingness to sign a written informed
             consent/assent.

          2. Subject is of either gender and 12 to 40 years of age.

          3. Subject is in good general health without clinically significant haematological,
             cardiac, respiratory, renal, endocrine, gastrointestinal, psychiatric, hepatic, or
             malignant disease, as determined by the investigator.

          4. Subject has suitable venous access for blood sampling.

          5. Subject is able and willing to complete the study and to comply with all study
             instructions and attend the necessary visits.

          6. Subject has acne vulgaris of the face defined as:

               1. 20 to 50 (inclusive) inflammatory lesions on the face

               2. 20 to 100 (inclusive) non-inflammatory lesions on the face

               3. An Investigator's Global Assessment (IGA) score for acne severity of 3 or 4
                  (moderate or severe) assessed on the face.

          7. Subject has ≤ 2 nodular/cystic acne lesions (&gt;5 mm in diameter).

          8. Subject must refrain from the use of other treatments for acne during the study.

          9. Subject must agree to not wash or shave their face, swim or otherwise get their face
             wet for at least 1 hour after application of study medication.

         10. Subject must agree to maintain their regular use of sunscreens, moisturizers, shaving
             cream, and facial make up throughout the entire course of the study.

         11. Male subjects and their partners must agree and commit to use a barrier method of
             contraception during the study and for 90 days after last study drug application.

         12. A negative UPT result for all WOCBP at the Screening Visit and Baseline Visit, if
             applicable. A WOCBP is one who is not permanently sterilized or is not postmenopausal.
             Postmenopausal is defined as 24 months with no menses without an alternative medical
             cause.

         13. Sexually active women must agree to use the following throughout the study and for 30
             days after last study drug application:

             a. One of these highly effective contraception methods i. Intrauterine device (IUD);
             hormonal (injections, implants, transdermal patch, vaginal ring; tubal ligation;
             partner vasectomy, OR b. Oral contraceptives WITH a barrier method (listed below), OR
             c. Two barrier forms of contraception (listed below) i. Male or female condom;
             diaphragm; cervical cap.

         14. Male subjects must refrain from sperm donation during the study treatment period until
             90 days after final study drug administration.

         15. Male subjects must agree to keep their face clean shaven (no moustache or goatee;
             short sideburns acceptable) throughout the study and use the same method for shaving
             as was used for the 4 weeks prior to the Screening Visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. People who would otherwise qualify for the study but are living in the same household
             as a study subject, are not allowed to participate in the study.

          2. Female subject who is breast feeding, pregnant, or planning to become pregnant any
             time during the course of the study.

          3. Subject with history of known or suspected intolerance to the drug product excipients.

          4. Subject has known HIV infection.

          5. Subject has acne conglobata, acne fulminans, secondary acne (chloracne),
             pseudo-folliculitis, severe acne requiring systemic treatment, or is taking a
             medication known to induce or exacerbate acne.

          6. Subject has severe truncal acne.

          7. Subject has excessive facial hair that would interfere with the evaluation of safety
             or with the diagnosis or assessment of acne vulgaris.

          8. Subject has sunburns, unevenness in skin tones, tattoos, scars, excessive hair,
             freckles, birthmarks, moles, or other skin damage or abnormality that would result in
             the inability to evaluate the skin of the face.

          9. Subject has any skin condition of the face other than acne vulgaris.

         10. Subject has used oral retinoid (e.g. isotretinoin) within 6 months (180 days) prior to
             the Baseline Visit.

         11. Subject has used Vitamin A supplements greater than 10,000 units/day within 6 months
             (180 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         12. Subject has used androgen receptor blockers (such as spironolactone or flutamide)
             within 3 months (90 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         13. Subject has initiated treatment with hormonal therapy or changed dosing with hormonal
             therapy within 3 months (90 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         14. Subject has had facial procedures (chemical or laser peel, microdermabrasion, etc.)
             within 8 weeks (56 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         15. Subject has had treatment with systemic antibiotics within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to
             the Baseline Visit.

         16. Subject has had treatment with systemic anti-acne drugs within 4 weeks (28 days) prior
             to the Baseline Visit.

         17. Subject has had treatment with systemic anti-inflammatory drugs within 4 weeks (28
             days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         18. Subject has had treatment with systemic (oral) corticosteroids other immunosuppressive
             medications within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         19. Subject has had treatment with prescription topical retinoid use on the face (e.g.
             tretinoin, tazarotene) within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         20. Subject has had treatment with topical prescription antibiotics (e.g. dapsone,
             clindamycin, erythromycin, or sulfacetamide) or combination products that include a
             topical antibiotic within 2 weeks (14 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         21. Subject has had treatment with over-the-counter (OTC) topical medications for the
             treatment of acne vulgaris including benzoyl peroxide, topical anti- inflammatory
             medications, corticosteroids, adapalene, α-hydroxy/glycolic acid on the face within 2
             weeks (14 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         22. Subject is currently using any medication that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             may affect the evaluation of the study product or place the subject at undue risk.

         23. Subject has had photodynamic therapy within 8 weeks (56 days) prior to the Baseline
             Visit.

         24. Subject has used a tanning bed within 2 weeks (14 days) prior to the Baseline Visit.

         25. Subject has used home-based light treatment within 2 weeks (14 days) prior to the
             Baseline Visit.

         26. Subject has an underlying disease that requires the use of interfering topical or
             systemic therapy.

         27. Subject has other dermatological conditions that require the use of interfering
             topical or systemic therapy or that might interfere with study assessments such as,
             but not limited to, atopic dermatitis, psoriasis, perioral dermatitis, or rosacea.

         28. Subject has had excessive sun exposure (in the opinion of the investigator) within one
             week prior to the Baseline Visit and an unwillingness to refrain from excessive sun
             exposure during the study.

         29. Subject has a clinically relevant history or currently suffering from any disease or
             condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, may affect the evaluation of the
             study product or place the subject at undue risk. This may include respiratory
             (including chronic asthma requiring repetitive drug interventions), gastrointestinal,
             renal, hepatic, hematological, lymphatic, neurological, cardiovascular, psychiatric,
             musculoskeletal, genitourinary, immunological, dermatological, or connective tissue
             diseases or disorders.

         30. Subject has a clinically relevant history of, or current evidence of, abuse of alcohol
             or other drugs. Subjects may be deemed eligible if the UDS identifies
             subject-reported, prescribed drugs or appropriate levels of alcohol, as determined by
             the investigator.

         31. Subject has participated in another investigational drug or device research study
             within 4 weeks (28 days) of the Baseline Visit or five half-lives of the drug,
             whichever is longer.

         32. Any other reason that would make the subject, in the opinion of the investigator or
             sponsor, unsuitable for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Applied Research Center of Arkansas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Encino Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Encino</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91436</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dermatology Specialist, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murrieta</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92562</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Quest Dermatology Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Northridge</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91324</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Science Insitute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Monica</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Well Phrama Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tory Sullivan, M.D., PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Miami Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33162</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Precision Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sunrise</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33351</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DS Research - Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40241</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Delricht Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metro Boston Clinical</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brighton</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>02135</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minnesota Clinical Study Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fridley</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55432</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medisearch Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Joseph</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine - Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>JDR Dermatology Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89148</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Acne Treatment and Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morristown</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07960</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aventiv Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dublin</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Hershey Medical</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Partners, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johnston</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02919</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greenville Dermatology, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Coastal Carolina Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mount Pleasant</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29464</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Avant Research Associates, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DermReasearch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78759</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>J&amp;S Studies, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>College Station</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77845</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Suzanne Bruce and Associates, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77056</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cmax Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Adelaide</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Skin Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Benowa</city>
        <zip>4217</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Burswood Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burwood</city>
        <zip>6100</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Skin &amp; Canver Foundation Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carlton</city>
        <zip>053</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sinclair Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Melbourne</city>
        <zip>3002</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fremantle Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fremantle</city>
        <zip>6160</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Eastern Health Specialist</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hectorville</city>
        <zip>5073</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St George Dermatology &amp; Skim Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kogarah</city>
        <zip>2217</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Captain Sterline Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Woden Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phillip</city>
        <zip>2606</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Varacity Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Woolloongabba</city>
        <zip>4102</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Synthetic CBD</keyword>
  <keyword>Cannabidiol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acne Vulgaris</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

