<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02681783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRaCTICAL 100-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02681783</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PRedictive Factors and Changes From Treatment in iPCV Versus CSR Versus nAMD With afLibercept</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRaCTICAL</acronym>
  <official_title>PRedictive Factors and Changes From Treatment in Idiopathic Polypoidal Choroidal Vasuclopathy Versus Central Serous Chorioretinopathy Versus Neovascular Age Related Macular Degeneration With afLibercept</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The presence of PEDs in nAMD, CSR and iPCV can present a diagnostic challenge in the elderly
      population; despite detailed diagnostic testing to differentiate these three conditions,
      misdiagnosis and mistreatment still occurs. One potential way of differentiating these three
      conditions might be to compare cytokine profiles in nAMD versus CSR versus iPCV. This
      information may be useful in creating a diagnostic aqueous cytokine and hormone profile to
      differentiate between nAMD, CSR and iPCV.

      The primary goal of this study is to compare baseline aqueous cytokine and cortisol levels
      between nAMD, CSR, and iPCV patients and age-matched cataract controls. The secondary
      objective is to assess intra-group changes in visual and anatomical outcomes in nAMD, CSR and
      iPCV patients with PED treated with aflibercept and correlate these changes to baseline
      cytokines.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The presence of Pigment Epithelial Detachments (PEDs) in neovascular Age-related Macular
      Degeneration (nAMD), Central serous chorioretinopathy (CSR) and idiopathic Poplypoidal
      Choroidal Vasculopathy (iPCV) can present a diagnostic challenge in the elderly population;
      despite detailed diagnostic testing to differentiate these three conditions, misdiagnosis and
      mistreatment still occurs. One potential way of differentiating these three conditions might
      be to compare cytokine profiles in nAMD versus CSR versus iPCV. In nAMD, growth factors and
      cytokines, such as vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), pigment epithelium derived
      factor (PEDF), interleukin 6 (IL-6) and placenta growth factor (PLGF) are known to play an
      important role in the development of CNV angiogenesis. Aqueous samples from CSR eyes have
      been analyzed for various growth factors and cytokines, where levels of interlukin (IL)-6,
      IL-8 and monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 do not differ from healthy controls, and
      platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) levels appear to be lower than controls. In addition,
      there is evidence to demonstrate that CSR is associated with elevated cortisol serum levels.
      Cortisol has been analyzed in the aqueous humor of glaucoma and cataract patients; however,
      the presence of cortisol in aqueous humor in CSR patients has not yet been identified. One
      study comparing iPCV versus controls found elevated levels of IL-23. Cytokines have also been
      compared between nAMD and iPCV showing elevated levels of CRP and IL-10 in eyes with iPCV or
      nAMD. However, there have not been any studies yet comparing aqueous cytokine levels,
      including PLGF between iPCV, CSR, and nAMD patients. This information may be useful in
      creating a diagnostic aqueous cytokine and hormone profile to differentiate between nAMD, CSR
      and iPCV.

      If left untreated, PEDs associated with nAMD, CSR, and iPCV may lead to the loss of central
      vision. We propose to compare the effectiveness of aflibercept in the treatment of PEDs
      associated with nAMD, CSR and iPCV.

      The primary goal of this study is to compare baseline aqueous cytokine and cortisol levels
      between nAMD, CSR, and iPCV participants and age-matched cataract controls. We will not be
      looking at changes in cytokine levels after treatment. The secondary objective is to assess
      intra-group changes in visual and anatomical outcomes in nAMD, CSR and iPCV participants with
      PED treated with aflibercept and correlate these changes to baseline cytokines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline aqueous humour cytokine levels in nAMD, CSR, and iPCV patients</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months from baseline intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is to compare the baseline aqueous inflammatory cytokine levels (pg/ml) and baseline aqueous cortisol levels (pg/ml) through analyzing anterior chamber aqueous fluid in patients with nAMD, CSR, and iPCV patients receiving aflibercept intravitreal injections, and compare with the aquueous fluid of age-matched control patients undergoing cataract surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the intra-group changes in best-corrected visual acuity using Snellen eye charts after aflibercept treatment in patients with nAMD, CSR, and iPCV for 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months from baseline intervention</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the intra-group changes in best-corrected visual acuity using Snellen eye charts after aflibercept treatment in patients with nAMD, CSR, and iPCV for 4 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the intra-group changes in anatomical changes via OCT imaging from baseline after aflibercept treatment in patients with nAMD, CSR, and iPCV for 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months from baseline intervention</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the intra-group changes in anatomical changes via OCT imaging from baseline after aflibercept treatment in patients with nAMD, CSR, and iPCV for 4 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</condition>
  <condition>Age Related Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Idiopathic Poplypoidal Choroidal Vasculopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>neovascular AMD group with PED</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be administered aflibercept intravitreal injection 2 mg (0.05 mL), administered at baseline, month 1, and month 2, for a total of 3 injections. Study will end for these patients at month 4, where no injection will be given. A clinical exam and OCT imaging will be performed each visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CSR group with PED</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be administered aflibercept intravitreal injection 2 mg (0.05 mL), administered at baseline, month 1, and month 2, for a total of 3 injections. Study will end for these patients at month 4, where no injection will be given. A clinical exam and OCT imaging will be performed each visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iPCV group with PED</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be administered aflibercept intravitreal injection 2 mg (0.05 mL), administered at baseline, month 1, and month 2, for a total of 3 injections. Study will end for these patients at month 4, where no injection will be given. A clinical exam and OCT imaging will be performed each visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cataract patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with cataracts requiring cataract surgery will serve as study controls. No intervention will be applied to these patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>aflibercept</intervention_name>
    <description>Therapeutic/Pharmacological Classification: VEGF - Anti-neovascularization agent Route(s) of Administration: Intravitreal Injection Dosage Form: Solution 40 mg/ml Proposed Indication: Treatment of Pigment Epithelial Detachments (PEDs) associated with neovascular Age-related Macular Degeneration (nAMD), Central serous chorioretinopathy (CSR), and idiopathic Poplypoidal Choroidal Vasculopathy (iPCV).</description>
    <arm_group_label>CSR group with PED</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>iPCV group with PED</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>neovascular AMD group with PED</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Eylea</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria for all study eye groups:

          1. 18 years of age or older

          2. Ability to provide signed informed consent

          3. Capable of complying with study protocol and required diagnostic tests

          4. Meets study eye criteria for each respective group (see Section 5 above)

          5. Participants in the nAMD, CSR, and iPCV groups must use an acceptable method of birth
             control during this study and for 6 months following completion of the study. The
             participants in the control group will not be receiving IP and are not required to
             meet this inclusion criterion.

        Exclusion criteria for all study eye groups:

          1. Previous intraocular injections including anti-VEGF therapy or steroid medication, or
             macular laser for all groups

          2. Any co-existing maculopathy or retinopathy in the study eye

          3. Participants with a history of either type I or type II diabetes

          4. Intraocular surgery in the study eye within the past 4 months

          5. Currently on systemic steroid therapy in any form (drops, skin creams,
             inhalation/intranasal sprays, intravenous) or immunosuppression for the last 3 months

          6. Participants on renal dialysis

          7. Pregnant and nursing mothers

          8. Participants who are hypersensitive to this drug, to any ingredient in the
             formulation, or to any component of the container.

          9. Ocular or periocular infection

         10. Active intraocular inflammation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Radha P. Kohly, MD PhD FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Radha P. Kohly, MD PhD FRCSC</last_name>
    <phone>4164805607</phone>
    <email>radha.kohly@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charlene Muller, RN PHN CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>416-480-5091</phone>
    <email>charlene.muller@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Radha Kohly</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, University of Toronto</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aflibercept</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Serous Chorioretinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

