<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02684162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0117</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-00343</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-0117</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02684162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Guadecitabine and Donor Lymphocyte Infusion in Treating Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia or Myelodysplastic Syndrome Relapsing After Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Toxicity of SGI-110 With DLI for the Treatment of AML or MDS Relapsing After Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase IIa trial studies how well guadecitabine works in treating patients with acute
      myelogenous leukemia and myelodysplastic syndrome that has returned after a period of
      improvement after allogeneic stem cell transplant. Guadecitabine may stop the growth of
      cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Sometimes the
      transplanted cells from a donor can make an immune response against the body's normal cells
      (called graft-versus-host disease). Giving guadecitabine before the transplant may stop this
      from happening. Once the donated stem cells begin working, the patient's immune system may
      see the remaining cancer cells as not belonging in the patient's body and destroy them.
      Giving an infusion of the donor's white blood cells (donor lymphocyte infusion) may boost
      this effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the complete response (CR) rate of guadecitabine (SGI-110) with or without
      donor lymphocyte infusion (DLI) either for the treatment of morphologic relapse or the
      presence of minimal residual disease (MRD) in patients with acute myeloid leukemia or
      myelodysplastic syndrome after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in patients with AML
      and MDS (cohort 1 and 2).

      II. The relapse-free survival with the use of SGI-110 as maintenance therapy in patients with
      high risk acute myeloid leukemia or myelodysplastic syndrome after hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (cohort 3).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the safety and toxicity of SGI-110 with or without DLI in this subject
      population.

      II. To evaluate overall response and survival.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive guadecitabine subcutaneously (SC) once daily (QD) on days 1-5. Treatment
      repeats every 28 days for up to 12 cycles in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity. Patients also receive DLI intravenously (IV) over 10-30 minutes on day
      6 of cycles 2, 4, and 6 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 22, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response (CR) rate (Cohort 1 and 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>After enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Up to 12 courses</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse free survival (RFS) (Cohort 3)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The Bayesian method of Thall et al will be used to monitor RFS time in this cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of hematologic and non-hematologic toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed up to 4 courses (16 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Using the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.0. Will be tabulated within each subgroup (minimal residual disease and relapsed).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 courses (48 weeks)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of time from start of treatment to time of remission, assessed up to 12 courses (48 weeks)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute graft versus host disease (GVHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 6 of second course of guadecitabine (day 34)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of chronic GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 courses (48 weeks)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Within each treatment cohorts, these events will be tabulated and the distributions of OS time estimated using the method of Kaplan and Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival time (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Within each treatment cohorts, these events will be tabulated and the distributions of DFS time estimated using the method of Kaplan and Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>High Risk Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>High Risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Minimal Residual Disease</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (guadecitabine, DLI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive guadecitabine SC QD on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 12 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients also receive DLI IV over 10-30 minutes on day 6 of cycles 2, 4, and 6 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Donor Lymphocytes</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (guadecitabine, DLI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Guadecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (guadecitabine, DLI)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DNMT inhibitor SGI-110</other_name>
    <other_name>S110</other_name>
    <other_name>SGI-110</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (guadecitabine, DLI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of AML and MDS according to World Health Organization (WHO) classification
             that underwent first allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplant (HSCT) with either
             peripheral blood or bone marrow as the source of the hematopoietic stem cells

          -  No more than 1 antigen mismatch at human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-A, B, C, DRB1 and
             DQB1 locus for either related or unrelated donor

          -  High risk AML and MDS patients will be included; cohort 1: morphological relapse after
             stem cell transplant:

               -  MDS patients: re-appearance of dysplastic changes in the bone marrow, with or
                  without increase in bone marrow last count, which is pathologically consistent
                  with myelodysplastic syndrome;

               -  AML patients: bone marrow blast count &gt;= 5%

          -  Cohort 2: Persistence or reappearance of minimal residual disease by flow cytometry or
             cytogenetic or molecular testing while being in morphological remission after
             allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  Cohort 3: High risk AML and MDS patients who are in complete remission morphologically
             with no evidence of minimal residual disease by flow cytometry or cytogenetic or
             molecular testing after allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  MDS patients:

               -  Cytogenetics consistent with poor or very poor risk group by 5-risk
                  classification;

               -  Cytogenetics consistent with monosomal karyotype

               -  Bone marrow blast count &gt; 5% but less than 20% at any time during their disease
                  course before HSCT

               -  Peripheral blood blast =&lt; 5% at HSCT

               -  Therapy-related MDS

          -  AML patients:

               -  Cytogenetics and molecular features consistent with adverse risk group;

               -  Presence of minimal residual disease by multi-color flow cytometry or
                  cytogenetics or molecular studies at the time of HSCT;

               -  Presence of active disease defined as bone marrow blast count &gt; 5% but less than
                  =&lt; 10% at the time of HSCT

               -  Peripheral blood blast count =&lt; 5% at HSCT

               -  Therapy-related AML

          -  Be able to start the drug therapy between 42 to 100 days following allogeneic SCT;

               -  No more than 1 prior allogeneic SCT

               -  Post-transplant bone marrow consistent with complete remission with no evidence
                  of minimal residual disease by flow-cytometry or cytogenetics or molecular
                  testing

               -  Adequate engraftment within 14 days prior to starting study drug: absolute
                  neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.0 x 10^9/L without daily use of myeloid growth
                  factor; and, platelet &gt;= 50 x 10^9/L without platelet transfusion within 1 week

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1, or 2

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL or creatinine clearance greater or equal than 40 cc/min
             as defined by the Cockcroft-Gault equation

          -  Serum bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Aspartate transaminase (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) or alanine transaminase
             (alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 2.5 x upper limit (UL)

          -  No active bleeding

          -  No uncontrolled graft versus host disease (GVHD)

          -  No clinical evidence of life-threatening infection

          -  Capable of understanding the investigational nature, potential risks and benefits of
             the study, and able to provide valid informed consent

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) negative and hepatitis B surface antigen (HBs-Ag)
             negative

          -  Negative serum or urine pregnancy test for women with reproductive potential; the only
             subjects who will be exempt from this criterion are postmenopausal women (defined as
             women who have been amenorrheic for &gt; 12 months) or subjects who have been surgically
             sterilized or otherwise proven sterile

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of any anti-leukemic agents after relapse is documented (note that the use of
             these anti-leukemic agents given as post-transplant maintenance therapy is allowed in
             this study, e.g., subcutaneous or oral 5-azacytidine or FLT3 inhibitors for
             maintenance) for cohorts 1 and 2

          -  Bone marrow blast count &gt; 60% for cohort 1

          -  Use of any of the following after transplantation and prior to starting study therapy
             for cohort 3:

               -  Investigational agents/therapies

               -  Anti-leukemic agents given as post-transplant maintenance therapy (e.g.,
                  subcutaneous or oral 5-azacytidine or FLT3 inhibitors for maintenance)

          -  Active acute graft versus host disease (GVHD) grade II or higher

          -  Active chronic GVHD that is extensive

          -  Concurrent use of systemic immune suppressive other than calcineurin inhibitors and
             sirolimus

          -  Active uncontrolled systemic fungal, bacterial or viral infection

          -  Symptomatic or uncontrolled arrhythmias

          -  Significant active cardiac disease within the previous 6 months, including: New York
             Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV congestive heart failure; unstable angina or
             angina requiring surgical or medical intervention, and/or; myocardial infarction

          -  Known active viral infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B
             virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV)

          -  Prior history of solid tumor unless the subject has been free of the disease for &gt;= 1
             year; however, subjects with the following history/concurrent conditions are allowed:
             basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin; carcinoma in situ of the cervix;
             carcinoma in situ of the breast; incidental histologic finding of prostate cancer (T1a
             or T1b using the tumor, node, metastasis [TNM] clinical staging system)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Betul Oran</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Betul Oran, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-8750</phone>
    <email>BOran@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Betul Oran</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-8750</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Betul Oran</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm, Residual</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Guadecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

