<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03709849</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Z171100001017104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03709849</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness and Safety of Bushen Culuan Decoction for Anovulatory Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Safety of Bushen Culuan Decoction for Anovulatory Infertility：A Clinical Research of &quot;Same Treatment for Different Diseases&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xiyuan Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dongzhimen Hospital, Beijing</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing First Hospital of integrated Chinese and Western Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing Fengtai Hospital of Integrated Traditional and Western Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xiyuan Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to evaluate the effectiveness and safety of Bushen Culuan Decoction in the
      treatment of anovulatory infertility, including anovulatory abnormal uterine bleeding,
      polycystic ovarian syndrome, hyperprolactinemia, luteinized unruptured follicle syndrome,
      corpus luteum insufficiency and ovarian insufficiency, through a randomised, double-blinded,
      double-dummy, parallel positive controlled, adaptive multicenter clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anovulation is one of the main causes of female infertility. Anovulatory infertility account
      for a proportion of 25-30% in whole female infertility.

      In western medicine, hormone induced ovulation and assisted reproduction technology are two
      main ways to solve the problem and Clomiphene citrate is the first-line medication in
      ovulation induction. There are many side effects being reported in the treatment with modern
      medicine technique such as ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome, complication with uteroscope
      and puncture egg retrieval, low pregnancy rate with high ovulation rate, potential cancer
      occuring risk and offspring healthy risk.

      Bushen Culuan Decoction is a traditional Chinese medicine recipe with 10 Chinese herbs
      including Tusizi, Yinyanghuo, Xianmao, Xuduan, Gouqizi, Nvzhenzi, Zelan, Shengpuhuang,
      Xiangfu and Chuanshanlong. Previous laboratory and exploratory clinical researches have
      proved Bushen Culuan Decoction had an exactly efficacy in treating anovulatory infertility
      safely.

      In the first stage, the primary sample size In the study is 528. Half patients will receive
      Bushen Culuan Decoction and clomiphene citrate placebo, while the other half will receive
      clomiphene citrate tablets and Bushen Culuan Decoction placebo. When 1/3 of 528 patients
      complete the treatment, we will analysis the treatment efficacy of 6 diseases separately, and
      find which of them could be the target diseases of Bushen Culuan Decoction. Then we will
      modify the sample size depending on the result in first stage, and the research will only be
      processed in the target diseases being chosen. In the next stage, half patients will receive
      Bushen Culuan Decoction and clomiphene citrate placebo, while the other half will receive
      clomiphene citrate tablets and Bushen Culuan Decoction placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 12 menstrual cycles from the first time that patient taking medicines. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ovulation Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At every ovulation phase (about day14 in a period cycle) within 3 or 6 menstrual cycles from the first time that patient taking medicines. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>If the patient participate 1 treatment cycle, the ovulation will be measured 3 menstrual cycles, and if the patient participate 2 treatment cycle, the ovulation will be measured 6 menstrual cycles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basal Body Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>At every morning within 3 or 6 menstrual cycles from the first time that patient taking medicines to the end of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endocrine Hormone</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Including Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH), Luteinizing Hormone (LH), Prolactin (PRL), Estradiol (E2), Progesterone(P), Testosterone (T).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inhibin B</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-Mullerian Hormone (AMH)</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antral Follicle Count</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of Uterus and Bilateral Ovaries at the Early Follicle Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thickness of Endometrium at the Early Follicle Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of Endometrium at the Early Follicle Phase</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The type of endometrium is measured by ultrasound. The type of endometrium contains type A, B, and C. Type A means the endometrium thickness is about 4-9mm, and there is a &quot;trilaminar patterns&quot; in the image. Type B means the endometrium thickness is about 9-12mm, the image shows moderate homogeneous echo. Type C means the endometrium thickness is about 10-14mm with a strong homogeneous echo. The type only represents different forms of endometrium, but not represents endometrium level or grade.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the Size of Dominant Follicle</measure>
    <time_frame>At every ovulation phase (about day14 in a period cycle) within 3 or 6 menstrual cycles from the first time that patient taking medicines. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak-Systolic Flow Velocity of Uterus and Bilateral Ovaries</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulsatility Index of Uterus and Bilateral Ovaries</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Pulsatility Index (PI) of Uterus and Bilateral Ovaries is the pulsatility index of uterine arteries and bilateral ovarial arteries. The normal range of uterine PI has no unified standard, but the smaller the index is, the better the endometrial receptivity is. Generally, when uterine PI&lt;2, the endometrial receptivity will be good enough to get zygote implantation, and when uterine PI&gt;3, the endometrial receptivity is too improper to get zygote implantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resistant Index of Uterus and Bilateral Ovaries</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Resistant Index (RI) of Uterus and Bilateral Ovaries is the resistant index of uterine arteries and bilateral ovarial arteries. The normal range of uterine RI has no unified standard, but the smaller the index is, the better the endometrial receptivity is.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coagulation Indicator</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Including prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time, fibrinogen and thrombin time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Traditional Chinese Medicine Symptom Score</measure>
    <time_frame>At the early follicle phase (day 3 in a period cycle) before the 1st cycle of the treatment and at the 7th cycle of the treatment. (Each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Traditional Chinese Medicine Symptom Score (point) including:
amenorrhea (0-3); delayed menstruation (0-3); scant menstruation (0-3); weakness in lower back, waist and knees (0-3); dizziness and tinnitus (0-3); sexual apathy (0-3); fatigue (0-3); colorless transparent urination(0-3); frequent urination at night (0-3); feeling obstruction with menstruation (0-3); profuse menstruation with dark color (0-3); clot in menstruation (0-3); stabbing pain in lower abdomen area, may aggravating with sexual intercourse (0-3); dysmenorrhea (0-3) The total score will be measured by summing the subitems' score above, and the total score range is 0-42. The higher the score is, the worse the situation is.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">528</enrollment>
  <condition>Anovulatory Infertility</condition>
  <condition>Abnormal Uterine Bleeding-Ovulatory Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Polycystic Ovarian Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Hyperprolactinemia</condition>
  <condition>Luteinized Unruptured Follicle Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Corpus Luteum Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Insufficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention, dosage and frequency: drug: Bushen Culuan Decoction 13g tid and Clomiphene Citrate Tablets placebo 50mg qd; Dosage form: Bushen Culuan Decoction is dissolved medicine and Clomiphene Citrate Tablets placebo is tablets; Duration: the medicine will be taken from 5th day of a menstrual cycle, Bushen Culuan Decoction is taken for 14 days while Clomiphene Citrate Tablets placebo being taken for 5 days. Then patients stop taking the medicine until the 5th day of next menstrual cycle. If the patient doesn't have a regular menstrual cycle, the medicine will be taken from 5th day from vaginal bleeding caused by taking progesterone. Each treatment cycle contains 3 menstrual cycle. If the patient regains normal ovulation at the end of the first treatment cycle, she will reach the end of the whole treatment, and if not she will start the second treatment cycle. All treatment will be terminated after 2 treatment cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention, dosage and frequency: drug: Clomiphene Citrate Tablets 50mg qd and Bushen Culuan Decoction placebo 13g tid; Dosage form: Clomiphene Citrate Tablets is tablet and Bushen Culuan Decoction placebo is dissolved medicine; Duration: the medicine will be taken from 5th day of a menstrual cycle, Clomiphene is taken for 5 days while Bushen Culuan Decoction placebo being taken for 14 days while. Then patients stop taking the medicine until the 5th day of next menstrual cycle. If the patient doesn't have a regular menstrual cycle, the medicine will be taken from 5th day from vaginal bleeding caused by taking progesterone. Each treatment cycle contains 3 menstrual cycle. If the patient regains normal ovulation at the end of the first treatment cycle, she will reach the end of the whole treatment, and if not she will start the second treatment cycle. All treatment will be terminated after 2 treatment cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>experimental group: Bushen Culuan Decoction and Clomiphene Citrate Tablets placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>the same as group description including dosage, frequency and duration</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>control group: Clomiphene Citrate Tablets and Bushen Culuan Decoction placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>the same as group description including dosage, frequency and duration</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>brand name of Clomiphene Citrate Tablets: Fertilan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 21~40 years old;

          2. Diagnosed with infertility;

          3. Diagnosed with one of below diseases: anovulatory abnormal uterine bleeding,
             polycystic ovarian syndrome, hyperprolactinemia, luteinized unruptured follicle
             syndrome, corpus luteum insufficiency and ovarian insufficiency,

          4. Diagnosed with TCM syndrome of kidney deficiency and blood stasis syndrome;

          5. Patients who has normal sexual intercourse during treatment;

          6. Voluntary to sign the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Infertility due to congenital physiological defect or malformation;

          2. Infertility due to hereditary factors；

          3. Infertility due to oviduct defect, immune factors, uterine fibroid, adenomyosis,
             endometriosis or hypoplasia of uterus；

          4. Spouse has reproductive defects；

          5. Severe abnormity of cardiovascular system, liver function, kidney function or
             hemopoietic system；

          6. Allergy to experimental drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kun Ma, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xiyuan Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kun Ma, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>86-010-64089750</phone>
    <email>makun12348@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yuan Yuan, Master</last_name>
    <phone>86-15801296950</phone>
    <email>gloriaflx0515@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anovulatory Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Bushen Culuan Decoction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperprolactinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anovulation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Citric Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Citrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clomiphene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enclomiphene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zuclomiphene</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

