<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03700580</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P1G10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03700580</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial Using the Proteolytic Fraction P1G10 From V. Cundinamarcensis to Heal Diabetic Foot Ulcer</brief_title>
  <acronym>P1G10</acronym>
  <official_title>Application of a Double Blind Clinical Trial Protocol for Evaluation of Healing Action of P1G10, From V Cundinamarcensis to Chronic Neuropathic Wounds in Diabetic Foot Ulcers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carlos E Salas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Minas Gerais</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study was to investigate the role of the proteolytic fraction from
      Vasconcellea cundinamarcensis, designated as P1G10, on healing of chronic foot ulcers in
      neuropathic patients diagnosed with diabetes type 2. Fifty patients were enrolled in a
      prospective, randomized, double-blind trial, to verify the efﬁcacy and safety of a topical
      dressing containing 0.1% P1G10, versus a Hydrogel (positive control) protocol currently
      applied at the Health Center to treat this condition. Upon completion of the intervention,
      the outcome evaluated the number of patients attaining full epithelization (100%), or at
      least 80% healing in both arms (P1G10 versus Hydrogel). Statistical analysis compared the
      endpoint data on each group to assess the signiﬁcance of differences.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Volunteers admitted for the study were randomly assigned into two distinct treatment groups.
      Randomization was performed by simple and stratified draw for each type of treatment. The
      treatment options were: a) Hydrogel™ and b) P1G10. The active principle had been previously
      dissolved in water and dispersed into Polawax dressing at 0.1% w/w final. Polawax™ is an
      emulsifying wax for cosmetic preparations. According to the manufacturers, it is able to hold
      together all types of ingredients without residue or separation. It is, therefore, ideal for
      &quot;oil in water&quot; creams and lotions. Number were used to identify both formulations.

      The staff participating in this clinical trial, including researchers was unaware of the
      identity of the formulation applied on each proband. Each formulation used during the
      intervention was dispensed weekly at the Laboratory of Antitumor Substances of the Institute
      of Biological Sciences of the Federal University of Minas Gerais by members of the research
      group who had no contact with the staff responsible for the application of the protocol. The
      formulations were stored at 4°C until its application.

      The treatment and the collection of data, took place between August 2012 and October 2016,
      and it was carried out by health professional and a technical assistant previously trained to
      evaluate and perform the procedure.

      The application of the intervention was done three times per week (Monday, Wednesday and
      Friday), completing 48 applications or until full epithelialization of the ulcer was
      observed, whichever occurred first. The treatment was performed exclusively at the outpatient
      level. When the proband could not attend the scheduled treatment, he (she) was instructed to
      perform the dressing change only with 0.9% saline solution. Patients who missed two
      consecutive scheduled interventions were withdrawn from the study.

      Ulcers were cleaned with 0.9% physiological solution using soft pressure, without scrubbing
      or addition of antiseptic substances. Subsequently, a thin layer of the ointment containing
      P1G10 or Hydrogel was applied over the ulcer bed, covering all its extension. Then double
      gauze was applied, fixed with adhesive tape and crepe bandage, if necessary. In cases of
      users with more than one wound, each wound received identical treatment, but only one ulcer
      was selected for the study.

      During the first week of treatment, the subjects were observed for 30 minutes after the
      intervention, in order to verify possible undesirable effects. After this interval, if they
      did not present adverse events, they were released. Users were also instructed to contact the
      responsible investigators by telephone if they observed the emergence of any adverse effects.
      A prior trial of the formulation containing 0.1% P1G10 applied onto the arm of healthy
      individuals during one-month did not induce local or systemic affects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 15, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 15, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 14, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The intervention encompassed a topical application on the ulcer bed of the active fraction 0.1% P1G10 dispersed in hydrosoluble vehicle. The control group received hydrogel with the same frequency adopted for P1G10 (Three times per week during 16 weeks). Regardless the intervention prior to each application the ulcer bed was cleaned with 0.9% physiological serum without antiseptic.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>100% epithelization</measure>
    <time_frame>The primary outcome (100% epithelization) is measured at the time of the intervention (1-16 weeks). If this endpoint is attained at a given date, the interval between the first intervention and the endpoint date is the period scored for the event.</time_frame>
    <description>A primary end point was considered as full re-epithelization (100%) of the injury assessed by presence of epithelial tissue in 100% of the bed occurring during, or at the end of 48 applications. Quantification of healing is assessed by measure of the wound area, registered with Sony camera (Cyber-shot), 18.2 megapixels. Along the ulcer is positioned a standard mold (5.1 x 15.0) cm including proband's initials, record number and date of treatment. A transparent sterile paper superimposed on the wound, measured the orthogonal lengths to estimate the wound area. Normal distribution of data was evaluated with Shapiro-Wilk test. The differences in values between groups were assessed by t- test. Wound healing incidence was expressed as 1000 person-day with 95% confidence interval in both groups. To minimize the effect of noncompliance and missing outcomes, the data were analyzed as &quot;intention to treat&quot; thus including every subject enrolled in each group during the initial assignment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>80% epithelization</measure>
    <time_frame>The secondary outcome (80% epithelization) is measured at the time of the intervention (1-16 weeks). If this endpoint is attained at a given date, the interval between the first intervention and the endpoint date is the period scored for the event.</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary end point was considered as 80% re-epithelization of the injury assessed by presence of epithelial tissue in 80% of the bed occurring during, or at the end of 48 applications. Quantification of healing is assessed by measure of the wound area, registered with Sony camera (Cyber-shot), 18.2 megapixels. Along the ulcer is positioned a standard mold (5.1 x 15.0) cm including proband's initials, record number and date of treatment. A transparent sterile paper superimposed on the wound measured the orthogonal lengths to estimate the wound area. Normal distribution of data was evaluated with Shapiro-Wilk test. The differences in values between groups were assessed by t- test. Wound healing incidence was expressed as 1000 person-day with 95% confidence interval in both groups. To minimize the effect of noncompliance and missing outcomes, the data were analyzed as &quot;intention to treat&quot; thus including every subject enrolled in each group during the initial assignment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot</condition>
  <condition>Neuropathy, Diabetic</condition>
  <condition>Foot Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrogel treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>It refers to the standard treatment currently applied for foot ulcers at the Health Center where the study was conducted. The intervention was applied to the cohort, three times a week during 16 weeks or when the wound attained full epithelization. The wound bed was cleaned with physiological serum before application of Hydrogel.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P1G10 treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>It refers to the experimental parallel intervention consisting of three weekly applications of 0.1% P1G10 dispersed in the hydrosoluble vehicle during a 16-week period, or until full epithelization of the wound. The wound bed was cleaned with physiological serum before application of the drug.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydrogel treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydrogel dressing containing water, carboxymethyl cellulose and sodium alginate in non-specified proportions, purchased in bulk amounts was sterile dispensed in smaller amounts (200 g) for frequent use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrogel treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gel Comfeel ®</other_name>
    <other_name>Coloplast</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydrogel Purilon ®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>P1G10</intervention_name>
    <description>P1G10 containing dressing composed by 8% Polawax, 6% liquid vaseline, 0.06% butylated hydroxytoluene, 0.15% Nipagin, 5% propyleneglycol, 0.1% Nipazol, 0.1% ethylenediaminetetraacetate disodium salt, 0.03% methyl-aminopropanol-95, 0.3% Imidazolidinyl urea, 2% Cyclomethicone, 78.2% distilled water. A single batch of the formulation was made and used throughout the intervention. A sample of this preparation was used to assess the extended stability of the formulation. The formulation was dispensed into 100 g dispensers for weekly use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>P1G10 treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of diabetes 2 had

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dl

          -  total leukocytes ≥ 300/ mm3

          -  platelets ≥ 100.00/mm3

          -  total bilirubin ≤ 1.0 mg/dL

          -  aspartate aminotransferase between 14 and 17 U/L in males and 10 and 33 U/L in females

          -  pyruvate transaminase between 10 and 40 U/L in males and 7 and 35 U/L in females

          -  creatinine between 0.70 and 1.20 mg/dL in males and 0.6 and 1.0 mg/dL in females

        Exclusion criteria

          -  pregnant females

          -  lactating mothers

          -  highly exuding ulcers

          -  patients receiving alternative treatments for ulcers

          -  reported allergy to the components included in the formulation,

          -  concomitant uncontrolled morbidity

          -  current active infections,

          -  HIV serum positives

          -  diagnosed with neoplasia or undergoing treatment with a cytostatic, or
             immunosuppressing agent

          -  individuals subjected to radiotherapy within the last 3 months before beginning the
             trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miriam T Lopes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Minas Gerais</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unidade de Referência Secundária (URS) Padre Eustáquio, do Distrito Sanitário Noroeste da Secretaria Municipal e Saúde de Belo Horizonte.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belo Horizonte</city>
        <state>Minas Gerais</state>
        <zip>30720-100</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freitas KM, Barcelos LS, Caliari MV, Salas CE, Lopes MTP. Healing activity of proteolytic fraction (P1G10) from Vasconcellea cundinamarcensis in a cutaneous wound excision model. Biomed Pharmacother. 2017 Dec;96:269-278. doi: 10.1016/j.biopha.2017.09.109. Epub 2017 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28988012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tonaco LAB, Gomes FL, Velasquez-Melendez G, Lopes MTP, Salas CE. The Proteolytic Fraction from Latex of Vasconcellea cundinamarcensis (P1G10) Enhances Wound Healing of Diabetic Foot Ulcers: A Double-Blind Randomized Pilot Study. Adv Ther. 2018 Apr;35(4):494-502. doi: 10.1007/s12325-018-0684-2. Epub 2018 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>29564750</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Minas Gerais</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlos E Salas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Biochemistry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diabetes type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>wound healing</keyword>
  <keyword>peripheral neuropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>P1G10</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Neuropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

