<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03709563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HAIR 2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03709563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Nutraceutical Supplement With Standardized Botanicals in Males With Self-Perceived Thinning Hair and Loss</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of an Oral Nutraceutical Supplement With Standardized Botanicals in Males With Self-Perceived Thinning Hair and Loss</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>DeNova Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>DeNova Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hair loss study in men with self-perceived thinning hair and loss
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hair counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 90, 180, 270, 360</time_frame>
    <description>The change in vellus and terminal hair counts / average number of hairs (N/cm2) within 2 ROIs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Shaft Thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 90, 180, 270, 360</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hair density</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 90, 180, 270, 360</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Hair Loss</condition>
  <condition>Hair Thinning</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Nutraceutical Supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Nutraceutical Supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized Botanicals. Take 4 capsules by mouth daily with a meal</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Nutraceutical Supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo. Take 4 capsules by mouth daily with a meal</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males between 21-45 years of age, inclusive

          2. Have self-reported thinning or hair loss for more than 3 months prior to screening

          3. Clinically confirmed to have hair loss or thinning by the investigator via physical
             exam, including subjects with male pattern hair loss with frontal and vertex patterns
             II, IIIv or IV using the Norwood Hamilton Hair Loss Scale (NHS).

          4. In good general health, as determined by the Investigator

          5. Willing and able to attend all study visits

          6. Willing to maintain the same hair style as at the Screening Visit for the duration of
             the study.

          7. Willing to use a mild non-medicated shampoo and conditioner for the duration of the
             study (medicated shampoo and conditioner refer to any prescription shampoo or
             conditioner as well as any over-the counter medicated shampoo or conditioner, such as
             those for treatment of dandruff or promoting hair growth)

          8. Be willing and able to cooperate with the requirements of the study.

          9. Voluntarily sign and date an informed consent agreement approved by the Institutional
             Review Board.

         10. Be able to complete and understand the various rating instruments in English.

             -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinical diagnosis of alopecia areata or scarring forms of alopecia

          2. Scalp hair loss on the treatment area, due to disease, injury, or medical therapy

          3. Current skin disease (e.g., psoriasis, atopic dermatitis, skin cancer, eczema, sun
             damage, seborrheic dermatitis), cuts and or abrasions on the scalp or condition (e.g.,
             sunburn, tattoos) on the treatment area that, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             might put the subject at risk or interfere with the study conduct or evaluations.

          4. History of surgical correction of hair loss on the scalp (i.e. Hair transplant).

          5. Use of any products or devices purported to promote scalp hair growth (e.g.,
             finasteride or minoxidil) within the 6 months prior to the Baseline Visit.

          6. Use of anti-androgenic therapies (e.g., spironolactone, flutamide, cyproterone
             acetate, progesterone, and bicalutamide) within 3 months prior to the Baseline Visit.

          7. History of burning, flaking, itching, and stinging of the scalp.

          8. History of malignancy (except cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma and basal cell
             carcinoma) or currently undergoing chemotherapy or radiation treatments.

          9. A known history of autoimmune thyroid disease, any other thyroid disorder/abnormality
             or other autoimmune disorders that in the opinion of the Investigator may interfere
             with the study treatment.

         10. A known history of depression or bipolar disease or any other condition that may
             impact the subject's participation in the opinion of the investigator.

         11. Recent utilization of low level lasers for hair growth.

         12. Any condition that the Investigator thinks may put the Subject at risk or interfere
             with their participation in the study.

         13. Known history or recent blood work indicating iron deficiency, bleeding disorders or
             platelet dysfunction syndrome as well as subjects receiving anticoagulant therapy or
             smokers with usage &gt;20 cigarettes/day.

         14. Use of any medications that are known to potentially cause hair loss or affect hair
             growth, as determined by the Investigator.

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Males only</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DeNova Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotrichosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

