<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03702296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018/2288</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03702296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can the Use of Ear Plugs and Eye Masks Help to Improve Sleep Quality After Major Abdominal Surgery?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can the Use of Ear Plugs and Eye Masks Help to Improve Sleep Quality After Major Abdominal Surgery?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Singapore General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Singapore General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The importance of good sleep has been gaining interest in critically ill patients as poor
      sleep is associated with increased rates of delirium, non-invasive ventilation failure and
      stress to the patient.

      The use of earplugs and eye masks has been shown to result in longer sleep time and better
      sleep quality. The primary outcome of this randomized control trial is to evaluate if the use
      of eye masks and earplugs in patients undergoing major abdominal surgery will lead to
      improved sleep quality. Secondary outcomes include the level of noise intensity in the
      various monitored units, incidence of delirium, nursing demand, length of hospitalization and
      anaesthetic techniques. With these findings, we hope to be able to improve patients' overall
      satisfaction with the healthcare received.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The importance of good sleep has been gaining interest in critically ill patients as poor
      sleep has been found to be associated with increased rates of delirium, non-invasive
      ventilation failure, and may serve as a stressor to patients. The use of earplugs and eye
      masks to improve sleep quality has been described in the critically ill patient population
      and outcomes have suggested that such interventions have resulted in longer sleep time and
      Rapid Eye Movement sleep, shorter sleep onset latency and less awakenings, with an enhanced
      perceived sleep quality. In the post-anaesthesia care unit, these interventions have also led
      to significantly preserved sleep quality in patients. The primary outcome of this randomized
      control trial is to evaluate if the use of eye masks and earplugs in patients undergoing
      major abdominal surgery, and who will be admitted to a monitored unit postoperatively, will
      lead to improved sleep quality. Secondary outcomes evaluated include the level of noise
      intensity in the various monitored units (Intensive Care Unit/Intermediate Care Area/High
      Dependency Ward), incidence of delirium, nursing demand, length of hospitalization and
      anaesthetic techniques. With these findings, we hope to be able to improve patients' overall
      satisfaction with the healthcare received.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 29, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blinded assessors will review the patients for 3 days post-operatively and assess sleep quality using the Richard-Campbell sleep questionnaire.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of sleep quality between the 2 arms based on Richard Campbell sleep questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of overall patient satisfaction between the 2 arms based on Richard Campbell sleep questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of nursing interventions required during the night</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective assessment by nurses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of delirium, based on twice daily scoring on the Neecham Confusion Tool</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Neecham Confusion Tool consists of 9 scoring components: Attention (score of 0-4), Command (score of 0-5), Orientation (0-5), Appearance (0-2), Motor Behaviour (0-4), Verbal Behaviour (0-4), Vital Function Stability (0-2), Oxygen Saturation Stability (0-2) and Urinary Continence Control (0-2). The sum of the scores from each component is combined into a Total Neecham Score, with higher scores indicating that the patient is less likely at risk of delirium.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospitalisation</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Noise intensity in the various monitored care units</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using a sound detector, in decibels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep</condition>
  <condition>Major Abdominal Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Critical Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be provided with ear plugs and eye masks, to be used from 10pm to 6am, for 3 days post-operatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No ear plugs or eye masks provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ear plugs and eye masks</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the intervention arm will be provided with ear plugs and eye masks and instructed on the use of these during sleep</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients who are 21 years old and above, undergoing elective major abdominal
             surgery in Singapore General Hospital, and who are anticipated to require a monitored
             bed postoperatively will be identified via Operating Theatre Management system the day
             before surgery. Postoperatively, these patients must have a Glasgow Coma Scale of at
             least 10, able to obey verbal commands and stay in a monitored unit postoperatively
             (Intensive Care Unit/Intermediate Care Area/High Dependency).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have known hearing impairment, dementia, confusion, delirium or with a
             tracheostomy will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Singapore General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

