<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03704480</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMMUNO-BIL D18-1 PRODIGE 57</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03704480</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Durvalumab Plus Tremelimumab Combination Immunotherapy With or Without Weekly Paclitaxel in Patients With Advanced Biliary Tract Carcinoma (BTC) After Failure of Platinum-based Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMMUNO-BIL</acronym>
  <official_title>Durvalumab Plus Tremelimumab Combination Immunotherapy With or Without Weekly Paclitaxel in Patients With Advanced Biliary Tract Carcinoma (BTC) After Failure of Platinum-based Chemotherapy: a Randomized Non-comparative Two-arm Phase II Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GERCOR - Multidisciplinary Oncology Cooperative Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GERCOR - Multidisciplinary Oncology Cooperative Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      IMMUNO-BIL is a non-comparative randomized 1:1 phase II study. This study will assess the
      efficacy and safety of the combination of durvalumab plus tremelimumab with or without weekly
      paclitaxel in patients with advanced BTC after failure of platinum-based chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Biliary tract carcinoma (BTC, adenocarcinoma in more than 90% of cases) is the second primary
      liver tumor in incidence after hepatocellular carcinoma (2,000 new cases/year in France).

      The prognosis of biliary malignancies is poor, with a 5-year overall survival rate (OS) of
      about 10-15%, most often due to late diagnosis, at an advanced stage.

      In advanced BTC, the gemcitabine plus platinum (cisplatin [GEMCIS] or oxaliplatin [GEMOX])
      doublet of chemotherapy is the standard first-line treatment and no targeted therapy has been
      validated in this indication to date. There is no second-line therapeutic standard;
      chemotherapy (mainly, 5-FU-based combination) yields limited median progression-free survival
      (PFS) and OS of abouty 2-3 months and 6-7 months respectively, justifying the exploration of
      new therapeutic options.

      Immune therapies (mainly, immune checkpoint inhibitors [ICI]) have opened new opportunities
      in cancer therapy. Hence, anti-CTLA-4 and anti-PD-1/PD-L1 monoclonal antibodies (mAb) have
      demonstrated robust clinical activity and obtained FDA approval in several cancers. Recent
      data showed encouraging results with anti-PD-1 mAb as a monotherapy in PD-L1-positive
      pre-treated advanced BTC. The effects of ICI in combination with second-line chemotherapy in
      patients with advanced BTC have not been explored to date.

      Platinum salts can induce &quot;immunogenic cell death&quot;. Therefore, previous treatment with
      platinum may increase tumor immunogenicity and sensitivity to immune therapy, particularly,
      ICI. The second-line setting after failure of platinum-based chemotherapy may then be an
      optimal biological context for testing immune therapy in advanced BTC.

      Durvalumab is a human immunoglobulin (Ig) G1 kappa (IgG1κ) anti-PD-L1 mAb. Tremelimumab is a
      human IgG2 anti-CTLA-4 mAb. Paclitaxel is a chemotherapy belonging to the taxane family.
      Taxanes may enhance the effect of immunotherapy by increasing the sensitivity of the tumor
      and activating the immune system. Taxanes are used in some patients with advanced biliary
      cancer.

      These data suggest that BTC may be a good candidate for immune therapy. The combination of
      anti-CTL4 and anti-PD1/PD-L1 mAb is expected to be active in both immune-inflamed and
      non-inflamed BTC, and in PD-L1 high and low tumors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS at 4 months according to iRECIST (centralized review of CT-scan imaging) Note: disease progression on CT-scan imaging must be confirmed by a new imaging at 4 weeks in order to meet iRECIST criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events graded according to National Cancer Institute-Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events [NCI-CTCAE] criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>From signature of informed consent to 3 months after last study treatment administration</time_frame>
    <description>All grade and severe (grade 3-5) adevrse events, according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) v 5.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as the time from date of randomization to date of death. In the absence of confirmation of death, survival time will be censored at the date of the last clinical assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RECIST v1.1 and iRECIST criteria comparaison for tumor response evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 months, evaluation every 2 months during treatment period and end of treatment (until the date of first documented progression or date of death, assessed up to 30 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related Quality of life (HRQoL) assessed by EORTC QLQ-C30 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, every 2 months during treatment period and end of treatment (until the date of first documented progression or date of death)</time_frame>
    <description>A quality of life score is obtained according to the answers to the questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related Quality of life (HRQoL) assessed by EORTC QLQ-BIL21 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, every 2 months during treatment period and end of treatment (until the date of first documented progression or date of death)</time_frame>
    <description>A quality of life score is obtained according to the answers to the questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality-Adjusted Time Without Symptoms of Disease or Toxicity of Treatment (Q-Twist)</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Q-TWiST analysis considers three health states, TOX, TWiST, and REL, and the duration of each state is calculated for every patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictive markers of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 2, Month 4, Month 8, Month 12, Month 18, Month 24 and end of study (until the date of first documented progression or date of death, assessed up 30 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Biliary Tract Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A : Durvalumab plus tremelimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One cycle equals 4 weeks (D1=D28);
Durvalumab: 1,500 mg by IV infusion on D1, until progression or unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent.
Tremelimumab: 75 mg by IV infusion on D1 for the first 4 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: Durvalumab plus tremelimumab plus paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One cycle equals 4 weeks (D1=D28); Durvalumab: 1,500 mg by IV infusion on D1, until progression or unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent.
Tremelimumab: 75 mg by IV infusion on D1 for the first 4 cycles. Paclitaxel: 80 mg/m2, every week for 3 weeks (D1-D8-D15), by IV infusion, until progression or unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent (at least 6 cycles, at the discretion of the investigator).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>1500mg by intravenous (IV) infusion on D1 until progression or unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A : Durvalumab plus tremelimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: Durvalumab plus tremelimumab plus paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tremelimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>75mg by IV infusion on D1 for the first 4 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A : Durvalumab plus tremelimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: Durvalumab plus tremelimumab plus paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>80mg/m² every week for 3 weeks (D1-D8-D15), by IV infusion until progression or unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent (at least 6 cycles at the discretion of the investigator)</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: Durvalumab plus tremelimumab plus paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent obtained from the patient prior to performing any
             protocol-related procedures, including screening evaluations.

          2. Willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study including
             undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and examinations including follow up.

          3. Histologically or cytologically proven BTC (extrahepatic CCA, intrahepatic CCA, or
             gallbladder carcinoma).

          4. Failure (documented progression or toxicity) of previous platinum-based (cisplatin or
             oxaliplatin) therapy (e.g. GEMCIS, GEMOX, FOLFIRINOX) Note: a maximum of 1 previous
             chemotherapy line is allowed; maintenance therapy with chemotherapy or targeted agent,
             except immunotherapy, will be permitted.

          5. Age ≥ 18 years at the time of study entry.

          6. ECOG PS 0-1.

          7. Recurrent or advanced disease not amenable to surgery, radiation, or combined modality
             therapy with curative intent (previous resection of primary tumor allowed).

          8. Measurable or evaluable (radiologically detectable disease which does not fulfill
             RECIST criteria for measurable disease) lesions according to RECIST v1.1 criteria
             (CT-scan &lt; 3 weeks).

          9. Have tissue from an archival tissue sample that has been identified and confirmed as
             available for study, or newly obtained core or excisional biopsy of a tumor lesion.

         10. Adequate organ function, as defined by the following:

               -  Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt;
                  3 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Total serum bilirubin &lt; 1.5 ULN

               -  Prothrombin ratio &gt; 70%

               -  Serum albumin ≥ 28 g/L

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dl

               -  White blood cell count (WBC) ≥ 3,000/μL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500/μL

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/μL

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 ULN or creatinine clearance &gt; 50 mL/min (MDRD).

         11. Body weight &gt; 40 kg.

         12. Any other prior therapy directed at the malignant tumor, including chemotherapy,
             chemoembolization therapy, molecular targeted therapy (including antiangiogenics), and
             radiotherapy, must be discontinued at least 2 weeks prior to registration and at least
             3 weeks before day 1 on trial.

         13. Life expectancy ≥ 3 months.

         14. Evidence of post-menopausal status or negative urinary or serum pregnancy test for
             female pre-menopausal patients. Women will be considered post-menopausal if they have
             been amenorrheic for 12 months without an alternative medical cause. The following
             age-specific requirements apply:

             Women &lt; 50 years of age would be considered post-menopausal if they have been
             amenorrheic for 12 months or more following cessation of exogenous hormonal treatments
             and if they have luteinizing hormone and follicle-stimulating hormone levels in the
             post-menopausal range for the institution or underwent surgical sterilization
             (bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy).

             Women ≥ 50 years of age would be considered post-menopausal if they have been
             amenorrheic for 12 months or more following cessation of all exogenous hormonal
             treatments, had radiation-induced menopause with last menses &gt; 1 year ago, had
             chemotherapy-induced menopause with last menses &gt; 1 year ago, or underwent surgical
             sterilization (bilateral oophorectomy, bilateral salpingectomy or hysterectomy).

             Women participants of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             within the 7 days prior to the first treatment administration. Both women participants
             of childbearing potential and men participants who are sexually active with women of
             childbearing potential must agree to use a reliable method of birth control (i.e.
             pregnancy rate &lt; 1% per year); women of childbearing potential will be instructed to
             adhere to contraception for a period of 180 days after the last dose of durvalumab and
             tremelimumab or 90 days after the last dose of durvalumab monotherapy or 6 months
             after the last dose of paclitaxel. Men participants who are sexually active with women
             of childbearing potential will be instructed to adhere to contraception and must
             refrain from sperm donation for a period of 180 days after the last dose of durvalumab
             and tremelimumab or 90 days after the last dose of durvalumab monotherapy or 6 months
             after the last dose of paclitaxel.

         15. Registration in a national health care system (PUMA included).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study (applies to both AstraZeneca
             staff and/or staff at the study site).

          2. Concurrent enrolment in another clinical study, unless it is an observational
             (non-interventional) or supportive care clinical study or during the follow-up period
             of an interventional study.

          3. Receipt of the last dose of anticancer therapy (investigational product, chemotherapy,
             targeted therapy, biologic therapy, tumor embolization, monoclonal antibodies) ≤ 21
             days prior to the first dose of study drug. If sufficient wash-out time has not
             occurred due to the schedule or pharmacokinetics properties of an agent, a longer
             wash-out period will be required, as agreed by AstraZeneca/MedImmune and the
             investigator.

          4. Mixed histology (hepatocholangiocarcinoma).

          5. Extensive tumor massively replacing both entire lobes.

          6. Obstructive jaundice (bilirubin &gt; 1.5 ULN) without adequate biliary drainage.

          7. Any unresolved toxicity NCI CTCAE Grade ≥ 2 from previous anticancer therapy with the
             exception of alopecia, vitiligo, and the laboratory values defined in the inclusion
             criteria

               -  Patients with Grade ≥ 2 neuropathy will be excluded

               -  Patients with irreversible toxicity not reasonably expected to be exacerbated by
                  treatment with durvalumab or tremelimumab may be included only after consultation
                  with the Study Physician.

          8. History of allogenic organ transplantation.

          9. Any systemic steroid therapy (&gt; 10 mg daily dose of prednisone or equivalent) whatever
             the duration of this corticotherapy

             Note: The following are exceptions to this criterion:

               -  Intranasal, inhaled, topical steroids, or local steroid injections (e.g., intra
                  articular injection)

               -  Systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses not to exceed 10 mg/day of
                  prednisone or its equivalent

               -  Steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., CT scan
                  premedication).

         10. Active infection including tuberculosis (clinical evaluation that includes clinical
             history, physical examination and radiographic findings, and TB testing in line with
             local practice), hepatitis B (known positive HBV surface antigen (HBsAg) result),
             hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency virus (positive HIV 1/2 antibodies) Note:
             Patients with past HBV infection or resolved HBV infection (defined as having a
             negative HBsAg test and a positive hepatitis B core antigen [HBc] antibody test) are
             eligible.

             Note: Patients positive for HCV antibody are eligible only if polymerase chain
             reaction testing is negative for HCV ribonucleic acid (RNA).

         11. Diagnosis of any second malignancy within the last 5 years, except for adequately
             treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, or in situ carcinoma of the cervix
             uteri.

         12. Prior treatment with taxane or any immune ICI, including durvalumab and tremelimumab
             or any other anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, or anti-CTLA-4 antibody.

         13. Known active central nervous system metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis;
             patients with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided they are
             stable (without evidence of progression by imaging for at least 4 weeks prior to the
             first dose of trial treatment and any neurologic symptoms have returned to baseline),
             have no evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using steroids &gt; 10
             mg/day of prednisone or equivalent for at least 14 days prior to trial treatment.

         14. Uncontrolled massive pleural effusion or massive ascites.

         15. Active or prior documented autoimmune or inflammatory disorders (including
             inflammatory bowel disease [e.g., colitis or Crohn's disease], diverticulitis [with
             the exception of diverticulosis], systemic lupus erythematosus, Sarcoidosis syndrome,
             or Wegener syndrome [granulomatosis with polyangiitis, Graves' disease, rheumatoid
             arthritis, hypophysitis, uveitis, etc]), that has required systemic treatment (i.e.
             with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive drugs)
             Note: Patients with vitiligo, alopecia, or any chronic skin condition that does not
             require systemic therapy are exception to this criterion.

             Note: History of autoimmune-related hypothyroidism on a stable dose of thyroid
             replacement hormone may be eligible.

             Note: Controlled Type 1 diabetes mellitus on a stable insulin regimen may be eligible.

         16. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness, including but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, interstitial lung disease, serious chronic
             gastrointestinal conditions associated with diarrhea, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirement, substantially increase
             risk of incurring AEs or compromise the ability of the patient to give written
             informed consent.

         17. Live vaccine administration within 30 days prior to the first dose of study treatment
             Note: Patients, if enrolled, should not receive live vaccine whilst receiving
             investigational product and up to 30 days after the last dose of investigational
             product.

         18. Known or suspected allergy or hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs or any of the
             study drug excipients (taxane, durvalumab, or tremelimumab).

         19. Mean QT interval corrected for heart rate using Fridericia's formula (QTcF) ≥ 470 ms.

         20. History or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality that
             might confound the results of the trial, interfere with participation for the full
             duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of the participant, in the
             opinion of the treating investigator.

         21. Radiotherapy treatment to more than 30% of the bone marrow or with a wide field of
             radiation within 4 weeks of the first dose of study drug.

         22. Major surgical procedure (as defined by the Investigator) within 28 days prior to the
             first dose of investigational product Note: Local surgery of isolated lesions for
             palliative intent is acceptable.

         23. Pregnancy/lactation.

         24. Tutelage or guardianship.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cindy NEUZILLET</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut Curie site de Saint Cloud</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cindy NEUZILLET</last_name>
    <phone>0140298500</phone>
    <email>cindy.neuzillet@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marie-Line GARCIA LARNICOL</last_name>
    <phone>0140298500</phone>
    <email>marie-line.garcia-larnicol@gercor.com.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHRU Jean Minjoz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besançon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christophe BORG, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christophe BORG, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Polyclinique Bordeaux Nord Aquitaine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cédric LECAILLE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cédric LECAILLE, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Duchenne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boulogne-sur-Mer</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vincent BOURGEOIS, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vincent BOURGEOIS, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Morvan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean Philippe METGES, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean Philippe METGES, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Beaujon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clichy</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pascal HAMMEL, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pascal HAMMEL, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHPSO Site de Creil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Creil</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabeth CAROLA, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elisabeth CAROLA, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Henri Mondor</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christophe TOURNIGAND, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>CHRISTOPHE TOURNIGAND, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Georges François Leclerc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie VINCENT, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie VINCENT, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Dijon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sylvain MANFREDI, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sylvain MANFREDI, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Andrée Dutreix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dunkerque</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean Philippe WAGNER, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean Philippe WAGNER, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Hospitalier franco-Britannique</name>
      <address>
        <city>Levallois-Perret</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Benoist CHIBAUDEL, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Benoist CHIBAUDEL, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHRU Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anthony TURPIN, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anthony TURPIN, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Léon Bérard</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christelle de la FOUCHARDIERE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christelle de la FOUCHARDIERE, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Privé Jean Mermoz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jérôme DESRAME, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jérome DESRAME, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital la Timone</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laëtitia DAHAN, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laëtitia DAHAN, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint Eloi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric ASSENAT, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric ASSENAT, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Prive du confluent SAS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hélène CASTANIE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hélène CASTANIE, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Romain CORIAT, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Romain CORIAT, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint Antoine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna PELLAT, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna PELLAT, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Mutualiste Montsouris</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christophe LOUVET, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christophe LOUVET, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Haut Lévêque</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean Frédéric BLANC, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean Frédéric BLANC, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Poitiers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poitiers</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David TOUGERON, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David TOUGERON, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Robert Debré</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reims</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandra HEURGUE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexandra HEURGUE, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Eugène Marquis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julien EDELINE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julien EDELINE, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Curie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Cloud</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cindy NEUZILLET, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cindy NEUZILLET, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHI Poissy Saint Germain</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Germain-en-Laye</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Asmahane TEILLET, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Asmahane TEILLET, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Paul Strauss</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meher Ben Abdelghani, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Meher Ben Abdelghani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Insitut Gustave Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David MALKA, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David MALKA, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Durvalumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tremelimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

