<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03705494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BFPC1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03705494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Home-based Breastfeeding Peer Counselling Programme</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility Randomised Controlled Study of an Innovative Postnatal Home-based Breastfeeding Peer Counselling Programme</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A feasibility study is proposed in the current study as women who had given birth to their
      first babies recruited to a previous project specifically expressed the need for postnatal
      breastfeeding support from peer counsellors at home and there is evidence that this could be
      of benefit for women and their infants. Evidence of whether women in Hong Kong who had peer
      counsellors have better breastfeeding outcomes compared to women who had standard care
      however is not available. Prior to undertaking a definitive trial, the investigators need to
      know if women would be willing to be recruited and randomised to an intervention or standard
      care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peer counselling and support has been shown to be effective in improving breastfeeding (BF)
      initiation, duration and exclusiveness. Peer counselling is being introduced into different
      country settings worldwide as an intervention to support women to achieve successful
      commencement and maintenance of breastfeeding, given the range of health benefits for the
      woman and her infant. Findings from one Cochrane review suggested that postnatal contacts in
      the home may reduce infant health service utilisation in the weeks following the birth, and
      that more home visits may encourage more women to exclusively breastfeed.

      The planned study A feasibility randomized controlled trial (RCT) study is proposed in the
      current study as women who had given birth to their first babies recruited to a previous
      project specifically expressed the need for postnatal BF support from peer counsellors at
      home and there is evidence that this could be of benefit for women and their infants.
      Evidence of whether women in Hong Kong who had peer counsellors have better breastfeeding
      outcomes compared to women who had standard care however is not available. Prior to
      undertaking a definitive RCT, the investigators need to know if women would be willing to be
      recruited and randomised to an intervention or standard care.

      This study is important for several reasons. Chinese women are expected to be housebound
      during the first month postnatally due to the tradition of 'doing the month', when problems
      with infant feeding and/or infants failing to thrive due to poor feeding could result in a
      decision to stop breastfeeding. The innovative home-based intervention the investigators will
      undertake will address an important service gap in Hong Kong to promote and sustain exclusive
      breastfeeding, and could be an effective strategy which reflects Chinese culture. The Health
      Care and Promotion Scheme grant review panel recommended that although an evaluation of a
      home-based peer counselling project is a high priority, a small-scale feasibility study was
      needed before a definitive RCT application is submitted.

      Peer counsellors will be recruited from those who passed the UNICEF and La Leche League Peer
      Counselling Training programme. Additional training tailored to issues that they may
      encounter in home-based contacts with women who are breastfeeding, for example solving
      problems of exclusive breastfeeding and correct breastfeeding technique will be needed and
      conducted by team leaders for the peer counsellors. Women planning to breastfeed who meet the
      study's inclusion criteria will be recruited from hospital postnatal ward and randomly
      allocated using opaque, sealed envelopes, by an independent research assistant not involved
      in participant recruitment, data collection or analysis to the intervention group (n=10,
      home-based peer counselling intervention and standard usual care) and control groups (n=10,
      standard usual care).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 5, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 5, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Views on the peer counselling breastfeeding intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>In-depth qualitative interviews</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of exclusive breastfeeding initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1, 2, 4 and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of exclusive breastfeeding rates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exclusive breastfeeding duration</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1, 2, 4 and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Time in weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Women's self-efficacy in breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, 2 and 4 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Breastfeeding Self-efficacy Scale measures maternal breastfeeding self-efficacy. It consists of 14 items measured on a 5-point likert scale. On scale 1 indicates &quot;not at all confident&quot; and 5 indicates &quot;always confident&quot;. Total scores range from 14 to 70 with higher scores indicating greater breastfeeding confidence and self-efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Women's attitude in breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, 2 and 4 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Iowa Infant Feeding Attitude Scale is a measure of attitudes towards feeding. It consists of 17 items that are scored on a 5-point likert scale, which ranges from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree). Eight items are worded in a favourable manner towards breastfeeding, while nine are favourable towards formula feeding. Items favouring formula feeding are reverse-scored (i.e. 1=5, 2=4, 4=2 and 5=1). The total attitude scores range from 17 (indicating positive bottle feeding attitudes) to 85 (reflecting positive breastfeeding attitudes). Total scores are grouped into the following three categories: (1) positive towards breastfeeding (70-85); (2) neutral (49-69); and (3) positive towards formula feeding (17-48).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Breastfeeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based peer counselling intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women planning to breastfeed who meet the study's inclusion criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women planning to breastfeed who meet the study's inclusion criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home-based peer counselling intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists of 5-6 home based visits over 6 months by trained peer counsellors who will focus on breastfeeding among mothers who have already decided to breastfeed and are interested in this programme.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home-based peer counselling intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primiparous mothers

          -  Intention to breastfeed

          -  Singleton pregnancy

          -  Term infant (37-42 weeks gestational)

          -  Cantonese speaking

          -  Hong Kong resident

          -  Mother with no serious medical or obstetrical complications.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  infant is &lt;37 weeks gestation,

          -  infant has an Apgar score &lt;8 at five minutes,

          -  infant has a birthweight &lt;2500 grams,

          -  infant has any severe medical conditions or congenital malformations

          -  infant is placed in the special care baby unit for more than 48 hours after birth

          -  infant is placed in the neonatal intensive care unit at any time after birth
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kris YW Dr Lok, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kris YW Dr Lok, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+852 3917 6690</phone>
    <email>krislok@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yan Shing Dr Chang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)20 7848 3263</phone>
    <email>yan-shing.chang@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kris YW Dr Lok, SRD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+852 3917 6690</phone>
      <email>krislok@hku.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janet Dr Wong, RN, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+852 3917 6641</phone>
      <email>janetyh@hku.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breastfeeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Peer counsellor</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

