<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03706248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CG0013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03706248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paired Analysis of Sensitivity for Colorectal Cancer Using COLVERA : PASCAL</brief_title>
  <acronym>PASCAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Performance and Sensitivity of the Clinical Genomics Colvera Test in Predicting Recurrence of Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinical Genomics Pathology</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinical Genomics Pathology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare the sensitivity and specificity estimates of Colvera with that of a commercially
      available CEA test for detection of recurrent disease in subjects with colorectal cancer that
      have documented recurrence or no evidence of recurrence by CT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be carried out as a single cohort, observational, prospective study to compare
      sensitivity of Colvera to detect recurrent colorectal cancer confirmed by radiology imaging
      (CT) with CEA sensitivity in paired testing. Blood is collected for assay of methylated BCAT1
      and IKZF1 DNA and CEA, from subjects who have undergone curative treatment for primary CRC of
      stages II and III (AJCC) and who are in remission (No evidence of disease). Subjects will
      have recently (within 4 weeks of blood collection) had follow-up radiological imaging as part
      of their surveillance program for recurrence. Participation is for one visit only as part of
      each subject's surveillance-monitoring schedule. Two PAXgene blood tubes (minimum 10 mL,
      maximum 20 mL) will be collected. Any evidence of methylated BCAT1 and/or IKZF1 DNA in blood
      represents a Colvera &quot;positive&quot; result. CEA levels of 5ug/L or higher will represent a
      &quot;positive&quot; result. Sensitivity and specificity of the Colvera and CEA test will be estimated
      and compared in a paired fashion in each case where recurrence status has been investigated
      and determined by the site clinical management team. Blood testing shall be performed and
      analyzed by qualified staff blinded to clinical status. This is a cross-sectional
      observational non-significant risk study, and test results will not be used for clinical
      management, i.e. there will be no interventions in subjects consenting to participate in this
      Research Study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 28, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value and negative predictive value</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Colvera and CEA in recurrent and non-recurrent CRC</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No recurrence</arm_group_label>
    <description>CT scan has confirmed that subjects are without recurrence. Blood can be drawn up to 4 weeks after scan.
Effective Feb 28, 2019, this group is closed to accrual as it has reached the goal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Recurrence</arm_group_label>
    <description>CT scan has confirmed that subjects are have recurrence of their colorectal cancer. Blood can be drawn prior to any treatment for the recurrent disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Draw</intervention_name>
    <description>20 ml of blood will be drawn from subjects via venipuncture</description>
    <arm_group_label>No recurrence</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Recurrence</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      If there is leftover plasma, the plasma or the DNA extracted from the plasma may be stored at
      the sponsor for repeat assays.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This prospective study will enroll 50 subjects with radiologic confirmation of recurrence
        of colorectal cancer and 50 subjects without CRC recurrence (documented by CT scan).
        Eligible study subjects will include men and women (18 years or older) of any race and
        ethnicity who have completed treatment (no further adjuvant chemotherapy or surgery
        currently planned) for primary CRC of stages II and III (AJCC, [2]), and have been
        considered by the site clinical management team for at least 6 months to be in remission. .
        (Concurrent imaging is not required as part of the clinical determination of remission.
        Subjects who have had a recent (within 4 weeks) or prior CT scan for purposes of
        surveillance are eligible.)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is 18 years or older, and capable and willing to provide informed consent.

          2. Subject has undergone curative treatment for primary CRC of stages II and III (AJCC).

          3. Subject was determined to be in remission at the conclusion of primary therapy and has
             been in clinical surveillance for at least 6 months. (No imaging is required for the
             determination of remission. Last treatment was at least 6 months earlier. No
             requirement to complete all of the initial adjuvant treatment plan.)

          4. Subject has had a surveillance CT scan within the past 4 weeks and either has
             recurrent CRC or does not have recurrent CRC based on that CT scan result.

          5. Subject is willing to provide a blood sample. (2 PAXgene tubes)

          6. Definition of recurrence is evidence of local tumor recurrence or metastasis by CT
             scan of chest, abdomen and pelvis or other modalities that confirm recurrent CRC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has other cancer at the time of recruitment.

          2. Subject has prior history of recurrent CRC.

          3. Subject has a diagnosis of End Stage Renal Disease (ESRD), with or without current
             dialysis treatment.

          4. Subject's life expectancy is less than one year based on performance status and
             clinical signs and symptoms.

          5. Subject is receiving chemo- or radiotherapy at the time of blood collection, or
             between radiological imaging and blood collection.

          6. Results of the recent surveillance CT of the chest, abdomen and pelvis are
             inconclusive regarding recurrence of CRC, and further work up (other imaging and/or
             biopsy) is not required at this time.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Torrance Memorial Physician Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Redondo Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90277</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33606</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colon and Rectal Surgery Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Metairie</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Hospital-Ascension Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novi</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48374</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data from each subject is captured without any identifiers in an electronic database.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

