<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03706742</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 072015-022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03706742</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>STOP HCC: Mailed HCV Treatment Outreach Program for HCC Prevention</brief_title>
  <official_title>STOP-HCC Evidence-Based Hepatocellular Cancer Prevention Through Treatment of Hepatitis C Virus Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim 1: The investigators will conduct a randomized controlled trial comparing two strategies
      to promote HCV screening, follow-up testing, and treatment among baby-boomers (i.e. persons
      born between 1945-1965): inreach with electronic medical record alerts and provider education
      vs. combination of inreach and provider education plus mailed outreach and patient
      navigation.

      Aim 2: The investigators will evaluate patient navigation strategies to promote follow-up
      testing and treatment evaluation among non-baby boomer Parkland patients (i.e. born before
      1945 or after 1965) who are either: a) HCV antibody positive but have not completed follow-up
      viral load testing or b) HCV viral load positive and who have not completed in-clinic
      treatment evaluation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 18, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 18, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatitis C Screening</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion with HCV Ab within 3 months of randomization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatitis C Screening</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion with HCV Ab within 12 months of randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatitis C Confirmation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion with HCV Viral Load within 3 months of positive antibody result</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatitis C Linkage to care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion with clinic visit within 6 months of positive HCV Viral Load</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost: Cost-per patient screened</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary measure of costs will be the cost per Ab completion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost: Cost per-HCV diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary measure of costs will be the cost per-patient diagnosed with HCV.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12380</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>HepatoCellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to Group 1 will receive visit-based HCV screening, as offered by clinic providers as part of usual care. Providers must identify at-risk patients who are eligible for HCV screening, understand the benefits of screening in this population, and enter orders for HCV Ab testing. If the HCV antibody is abnormal, providers must order appropriate follow-up tests including HCV viral load to confirm HCV infection. Once HCV is confirmed, providers must refer the patients for fibrosis assessment and treatment evaluation. These efforts are augmented by an established best practice alert and health maintenance reminders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mailed outreach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to Group 2 will receive low literacy, written materials about HCV screening among baby-boomers in English and Spanish. The invitation will include patient-centered educational materials that discuss the risk of HCV in baby boomers and the benefits and risks of HCV screening. The invitation will include a phone number to schedule the HCV antibody blood test. Written materials will be developed and validated in Spanish using the Spanish Language Translation Resource. Once a potential subject is identified and randomized in Group 2, an outreach invitation will be mailed out. Shortly after the letter, a bilingual patient navigator will place a follow-up call to this potential subject. These follow-up calls will occur in the 2nd - 4th week after mailing invitations; up to three attempts in total will be made to reach the patient to facilitate HCC screening completion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mailed outreach</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will randomize all baby boomer patients (~12,000 patients) using a centrally maintained computer-generated list. Patients will be randomly assigned to one of two HCV screening strategies including: visit-based screening as part of usual care (Group 1) or mailed screening invitation outreach and centralized patient navigation (Group 2).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mailed outreach</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  born between 1945 and 1965

          -  ≥ 1 outpatient visit during 12 months prior to randomization at Parkland

          -  no prior HCV screening (prior HCV antibody, viral load, or genotype).

          -  any active medical coverage

          -  speaks Spanish or English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  a life expectancy less than one year including end stage CHF, end stage COPD,
             metastatic cancer, and those who received a palliative care or hospice referral in the
             past year

          -  history of HCC.

          -  non-English or Spanish speakers

          -  no address or phone number on file
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>53 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parkland Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

