<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03708172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100-2016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03708172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>rTMS and Cognitive Training in Youth Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>rTMS and Cognitive Training for Treating Youth Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Youth depression is a highly prevalent disorder with tremendous personal and societal costs.
      Guideline supported treatments are limited in efficacy and associated with side effects.
      Novel, safe, and effective treatments are sorely needed. This study will examine the
      biological targets, and efficacy, of cognitive training in combination with repetitive
      transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) in non-medicated, depressed youth. If positive, the
      investigators will have identified an effective, safe, and acceptable alternative treatment
      for a population with few treatment options. Identifying biological mechanisms of response
      will ultimately enable clinicians to tailor individual interventions for depressed youth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Youth depression affects roughly 10% of the North American population, effecting high costs
      to both individuals and society at large. Unfortunately, few effective treatments exist.
      Antidepressant medications such as selective serotonergic reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) are
      associated with side effects, and possess marginal efficacy in this age group. Black box
      warnings persist for antidepressants used in those under 24, owing to concerns that these
      medications enhance suicidal ideation in this population. While guidelines and randomized
      controlled trials support the use of cognitive behavior therapy (CBT) as a standalone or
      combination treatment for depressed youth, a large proportion of youth do not respond to
      either medication or psychotherapy.

      The study investigators propose to examine the efficacy of repetitive transcranial magnetic
      stimulation (rTMS) in conjunction with cognitive training (CT) for depressed youth. rTMS
      delivered to the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) is a safe and FDA approved treatment
      for adults with treatment-resistant depression, and preliminary studies suggest its safety,
      acceptability, and efficacy in depressed youth. Theta-burst stimulation (TBS) is a new form
      of rTMS that can achieve antidepressant effects in a quarter of the time of conventional
      rTMS. TBS is also thought to enhance neural plasticity. In this study, all participants will
      receive daily (5x a week on weekdays) open-label TBS. In addition, half of the participants
      will receive computer-based CT designed to enhance executive function, while the other half
      will receive placebo CT. This approach may capitalize on rTMS-induced neural plasticity,
      while improving depression associated executive dysfunction.

      Aim:

        1. to investigate the efficacy of combination cognitive training and rTMS applied to the
           DLPFC in youth depression, and

        2. to identify biological targets and predictors of response to combined CT and rTMS
           intervention in youth depression
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open Label for rTMS, Double-Blinded for Cognitive Training</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in symptom severity of depression as measured by the Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression - 17</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (17-item version)
This scale is used to quantify the severity of symptoms of depression
Scale range: 0-52 (total score)
Lower scores indicate lower severity of depressive symptoms (i.e., better outcome)
Higher scores indicate higher severity of depressive symptoms (i.e., worse outcome)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in self-reported symptom severity of depression as measured by the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II) is 21-item self-report instrument intended to assess the existence and severity of symptoms of depression
Items are rated on a 4-point scale ranging from 0 to 3
Scale range: 0-63 (total score)
Lower scores indicate lower severity of depressive symptoms (i.e., better outcome)
Higher scores indicate higher severity of depressive symptoms (i.e., worse outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in symptom severity of depression as measured by the Children's Depression Rating Scale, revised-version (CDRS-R) in youth under 18 years of age</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CDRS-R is a clinician-administered 17-item interview, with item ratings between 1 (=no difficulties) and 5 or 1 and 7(=clinically significant difficulties) (adding up to a total score between 17 to 113). It has been proposed, that a score of ≥40 indicates depressive symptomatology, whereas a score ≤28 was often used as indicative of remission within trials.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS + Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) in an open label fashion. In addition, participants will receive active cognitive training (CT) which consists of completing computer-based tasks designed to enhance executive function.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS + Sham Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) in an open label fashion. In addition, participants will receive sham cognitive training (CT) which consists of completing computer-based tasks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Intermittent TBS (iTBS) rTMS applied to the left Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex (DLPFC) + continuous TBS (cTBS) rTMS applied to the right DLPFC. The order will be counterbalanced. Administration of this treatment takes roughly 10 minutes. This treatment will be applied daily, 5 days/week, for 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS + Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS + Sham Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MagPro rTMS Device (Magventure A/S, Farum, Denmark)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Computer-based cognitive training designed to enhance executive function</description>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS + Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sham Cognitive Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Computer-based inactive sham training</description>
    <arm_group_label>rTMS + Sham Cognitive Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. outpatients

          2. between the ages of 16 and 24

          3. competent to consent to study participation

          4. Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI) confirmed diagnosis of MDD single
             or recurrent

          5. not taking any oral medication for depression or another psychiatric indication 1-week
             prior to screening visit

          6. HRSD-17 score of 20 and higher, to be reviewed on a case by case basis by the study
             psychiatrists

          7. at least one failed/refused/intolerant to antidepressant trial in the current episode
             as determined by ATHF

          8. No safety concerns endorsed on TMS Screening and Information Form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. lifetime MINI diagnosis of bipolar I or II disorder, schizophrenia, schizoaffective
             disorder, delusional disorder, current psychotic symptoms, obsessive compulsive
             disorder, autism spectrum disorder, a history of epilepsy or any other major
             neurological disorder

          2. diagnosis of borderline personality disorder, assessed on a case by case basis

          3. at least 6 answers coded &quot;yes&quot; in both substance abuse and dependence sections
             combined, within the last 3 months as determined by MINI

          4. concomitant major unstable medical illness

          5. acutely suicidal or high risk for suicide as assessed by a study psychiatrist

          6. not eligible to receive TMS or MRI as indicated by TMS Screening and Information Form

          7. medications are considered a confound including selective serotonin reuptake
             inhibitors, benzodiazepines, antipsychotics, mood stabilizers, stimulants and
             anticonvulsants, all to be reviewed on a case by case basis

          8. have failed brain stimulation in the past

          9. cannot be an expert musician
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Z. Jeffrey Daskalakis, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M6J 1H4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.camh.net/research</url>
    <description>Information about research at the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health, Canada's largest mental health and addiction teaching hospital</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Z. J. Daskalakis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chair, Temerty Centre for Therapeutic Brain Intervention</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rTMS</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Youth</keyword>
  <keyword>TBS</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrophysiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

