<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03702231</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>190001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-H-0001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03702231</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Response to the SHINGRIX Varicella Zoster Virus (VZV) Vaccine in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) and CLL Treated With Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor (BTK-I)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Response to the SHINGRIX Varicella Zoster Virus (VZV) Vaccine in Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) Patients That Are Treatment Naive or Receiving Bruton s-Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor (BTK-I) Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      People who have cancer tend to get sick more often. This is in part because of the cancer
      treatments they get. Because of this, they may get shingles. Scientists had thought people
      with chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) should not get the shingles vaccine. Now there is a
      new shingles vaccine that is not live and cannot cause shingles. The new shingles vaccine may
      protect people with weak immune systems from getting shingles. This is currently shown to be
      safe to give people 50 years and older to prevent shingles. Researchers want to test how safe
      the vaccine is and how it works in people with CLL.

      Objective:

      To learn how a new shingles vaccine works in people who have chronic lymphocytic leukemia or
      small lymphocytic lymphoma (SLL).

      Eligibility:

      Adults ages 18 years and older with CLL or SLL who are not being treated for CLL or who are
      getting certain treatments.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with a chart review or through another protocol.

      Visit 1

      At visit 1, participants may have a pregnancy test, blood test, or physical exam.

      Pregnant participants cannot be in the study.

      Eligible participants will get the shingles vaccine as an injection.

      Participants will receive a diary and write down any sumptoms they have for 7 days after the
      vaccines.

      Visit 2

      Visit 2 will be 3 months later. Participants will have blood taken and get another dose of
      the vaccine.

      Participants will receive a diary and write down any symptoms they have for 7 days after the
      vaccines.

      Visit 3

      Visit 3 will be 3 months after visit 2. Participants will have blood taken.

      Participants may be able to get an additional vaccine the same day as the shingles vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to determine the efficacy of the SHINGRIX varicella zoster virus (VZV)
      vaccine in chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) and small lymphocytic lymphoma (SLL) patients
      that are treatment naive or receiving Bruton s-tyrosine kinase inhibitor (BTK-I). (Note:
      Since CLL and SLL are considered the same disease, CLL/SLL will be referred to as CLL
      hereafter, unless otherwise specified).

      Key Eligibility Criteria:

        -  Diagnosis of CLL or SLL

        -  Cohort 1: Treatment naive CLL or SLL patients

        -  Cohort 2: Subjects must be receiving ibrutinib for at least 6 months prior to
           administration of the first vaccine dose

        -  Cohort 3: Subjects must be receiving acalabrutinib for at least 6 months prior to
           administration of the first vaccine dose

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years

        -  ECOG performance status of 0-1

      Design:

      Patients with CLL will enroll on the study for the purpose of determining the SHINGRIX
      vaccine efficacy in patients who are treatment naive or receiving BTK-I therapy. A series of
      2 doses of SHINGRIX will be given at 0- and 3- month schedule by intramuscular injection.
      Subjects will be followed for 6 months and receive assessment of serologic response 6 months
      after the first vaccine dose administration.

      Study Objectives:

      Primary Objective:

      a)Determine the serologic response against VZV after completing the SHINGRIX (RZV) 2-

      dose vaccine series in the following populations:

      -CLL patients that are treatment naive (n=54)

        -  CLL patients receiving treatment with ibrutinib (n=27)

        -  CLL patients receiving treatment with acalabrutinib (n=27)

      Secondary Objective:

      a) Determine the safety and tolerability of the SHINGRIX vaccine among CLL patients who are
      treatment naive or receiving BTK-Is (ibrutinib or acalabrutinib).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 7, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to the SHINGRIX vaccine in untreated CLL patients and CLL patients treated with BTK-inhibitors</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the first vaccine administration</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the rate of varicella zoster virus (VZV) seroprotective titer achievement following completion of the SHINGRIX 2-dose vaccine series in CLL patients that are treatment naive or receiving therapy with a BTK-inhibitor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerabilty of the SHINGRIX vax in CLL pts.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the first vaccine administration</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the safety and tolerability of the SHINGRIXvaccine among CLL patients who are treatment naive or receiving a Bruton s-tyrosine kinase inhibitor (BTK-I) (ibrutinib or acalabrutinib).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">123</enrollment>
  <condition>Safety and Tolerability</condition>
  <condition>Compare SHINGRIX Vaccine Response Rates</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with CLL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zoster VaccineRecombinant, Adjuvanted</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with CLL will enroll on the study for the purpose of determining the SHINGRIX vaccine efficacy in patients who are treatment naive or receiving BTK-I therapy. A series of 2 doses of SHINGRIX will be given on a 0- and 3-month schedule by intramuscular injection. Subjects will be followed for 6 months and receive assessment of serologic response 6- months following the first SHINGRIX vaccine dose. SHINGRIX (Zoster Vaccine Recombinant, Adjuvanted) - A series of 2 doses (0.5 ml each) will be given on a 0- and 3- month schedule via intramuscular injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Diagnosis of CLL/SLL which is made according to the updated criteria of the NCI
             Working Group

          -  Cohort 1:Treatment naive CLL/SLL patients

          -  Cohort 2: Subjects must be receiving treatment ibrutinib for at least 6 months prior
             to administration of the first vaccine dose

          -  Cohort 3: Subjects must be receiving acalabrutinib for at least 6 months prior to
             administration of the first vaccine dose

          -  No active, symptomatic VZV or herpes zoster infection within 12 months prior to
             vaccination

          -  No exposure to the live VZV vaccine (ZOSTAVAX) within 12 months prior to vaccination

          -  No prior exposure to the SHINGRIX vaccine

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-2

          -  Able to comprehend the investigational nature of the protocol and provide informed
             consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Female patients who are currently in pregnancy

          -  Any uncontrolled active systemic infection

          -  Any life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ system dysfunction that, in
             the investigator's opinion, could compromise the subject's safety or put the study
             outcomes at undue risk

          -  Severe allergic reaction to any component of SHINGRIX.

          -  Received intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) within 3 months prior to vaccination.

          -  Concomitant use of immunosuppressive agents (e.g. steroids, radio

        therapy, chemotherapy)

          -  Hereditary or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome unrelated to chronic lymphocytic
             leukemia

          -  Non-English speaking individuals will be excluded from the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher MT Pleyer, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan Soto, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-0797</phone>
    <email>sotos@nhlbi.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2019-H-0001.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 28, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ibrutinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Acalabrutinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Shingles</keyword>
  <keyword>Herpes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chickenpox</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Herpes Zoster</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

