<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03700359</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ES-SCLC 001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03700359</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Lobaplatin/Etoposide With or Without Anlotinib Maintenance Therapy in Patients With ES-SCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-label Study of Lobaplatin/Etoposide as First Line Therapy With or Without Anlotinib Maintenance Therapy in Patients With Extensive-stage Small-cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, open-label and active controlled phase II study. It plans
      to enroll 60 subjects with extensive stage small cell lung cancer (ES-SCLC). All subjects
      will be assigned randomly to the experimental arm or control arm. The primary endpoints would
      be overall survival and progression-free survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Small cell lung cancer (SCLC) accounts for about 20% of lung cancer, has a high degree of
      malignancy, short doubling time, early and widespread metastasis, is sensitive to
      chemotherapy and radiotherapy, and has a high initial response rate, but is prone to
      secondary drug resistance and relapse. The treatment is mainly based on systemic
      chemotherapy.

      SCLC has a more abundant vascular network than NSCLC. Anti-tumor vascular therapy combined
      with chemotherapy is considered the most promising SCLC first-line anti-tumor strategy.
      Anlotinib Hydrochloride has an anti-angiogenic effect and inhibits tumor's growth. It has
      been reported that Anlotinib has the dual benefits of both overall survival and
      progression-free survival in the treatment of multiple tumors, and has initially demonstrated
      its safety and efficacy. The ALTER 0303 study results showed that Anlotinib benefited both
      the overall and progression-free survival of NSCLC patients. However, there is no clinical
      study to probe its relevance to small cell lung cancer, and few studies have examined the
      status of Anlotinib in first-line treatment.

      This randomized, open-label, controlled study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      sequential EL regimen with Anlotinib hydrochloride as first-line treatment for
      extensive-stage SCLC. The study plan to enroll 60 ES-SCLC subjects and will provide evidence
      for the use of Anlotinib for SCLC first-line treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 29, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 29, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to first documented progression, assessed for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival (PFS) is defined as the time from date of randomization to the date of objective disease progression or death due to any cause. Participants were censored at date of last PFS assessment prior to the cutoff date or the date of initiation of subsequent systemic anticancer therapy, whichever was earlier.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With a Complete Response (CR) and Partial Response (PR) (Overall Response Rate)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Response Rate (ORR) is the number of participants with a Complete Response (CR) and Partial Response (PR) divided by the total number of randomized participants per arm, then multiplied by 100. Response is based on the Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.0) criteria. Complete Response (CR) was defined as the disappearance of all target lesions. Partial Response (PR) was defined as at least a 30% decrease in sum of longest diameter of target lesions compared to baseline or the complete disappearance of target lesions, with persistence of 1 or more nontarget lesion(s) and no new lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to death by any cause, assessed for up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) is the duration from date of randomization to date of death from any cause. Participants were censored at the date they were last known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Experiencing an Adverse Event (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participant administered study treatment which does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can be any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of study treatment or protocol-specified procedure, whether or not considered related to the study treatment or protocol-specified procedure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anlotinib/Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>EL regimen for 4 cycles followed by Anlotinib Hydrochloride maintenance therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>EL regimen for 4 cycles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anlotinib Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Anlotinib: Maintenance therapy 12mg/day P.O., day 1-15 every 21 days (2 weeks on, 1 week off) until progressive disease or treatment discontinuation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anlotinib/Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AL3818</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lobaplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Lobaplatin:30 mg/m2 IV every 21 days for up to 4 cycles of 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anlotinib/Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>D-19466</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Etoposide: 60 mg/m2 IV every 21 days for up to 4 cycles of 21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anlotinib/Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lobaplatin/Etoposide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VP16</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histopathologically confirmed patients with extensive small cell lung cancer;

          2. Karnofsky performance status ≥70;

          3. At least one lesion that can measured by CT;

          4. Expected to survive for at least 3 months;

          5. Peripheral blood and liver and kidney function within the following allowable range
             (tested within 7 days before treatment);

               -  White blood cell (WBC) ≥3.0×109/L or Neutrophils (ANC) ≥1.5×109/L;

               -  Hemoglobin (HGB) ≥80 g/L；

               -  Platelet (PLT) ≥100×109/L;

               -  Liver transaminases（AST/ALT）＜3.0 times the normal range limit;

               -  Total bilirubin（TBIL）＜1.5 times the normal range limit;

               -  Creatinine（CREAT）＜1.5 times the normal range limit;

          6. Patients of childbearing age (including female and male patients' partner) must take
             effective contraception methods;

          7. Signed informed consent;

          8. Known history of liver disease: Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) infection and Hepatitis B
             Virus DNA (HBV DNA ≥500 copies or ≥100 IU/ml); or Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) infection;
             or liver cirrhosis, etc.

          9. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV);

         10. Subjects with difficulties in swallowing or known drug malabsorption; Those who meet
             each of the above criteria are included in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Other pathological types of tumor except for small cell lung cancer;

          2. Patients with a history of severe allergies or allergies;

          3. Pregnancy or breastfeeding women;

          4. Patients who have previously participated in other clinical trials and have not yet
             terminated the trial;

          5. Combined with other tumors at the time of initial diagnosis;

          6. Patients who have previously participated in other clinical trials and have not yet
             terminated the trial;

          7. Patients who have acute infection that difficult to control;

          8. Drug abuse, substance abuse, chronic alcohol abuse, and AIDS patients. Those who meet
             any of the above criteria are not included in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jiexia Zhang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jiexia Zhang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>86 20 83062830</phone>
    <email>drzjxcn@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510120</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jiexia Zhang, prof.</last_name>
      <phone>13903056432</phone>
      <email>drzjxcn@126.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jiexia Zhang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Deputy Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>extensive-stage small-cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>lobaplatin/etoposide</keyword>
  <keyword>Anlotinib maintenance therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

