<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03709095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SprintSCI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03709095</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sprint Interval Training During Rehabilitation After Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <acronym>SprintSCI</acronym>
  <official_title>Sprint Interval Training During Rehabilitation After Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hamilton Health Sciences Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Immediately following a spinal cord injury (SCI), patients are admitted to inpatient
      rehabilitation where they undergo physical reconditioning in preparation for a return to home
      setting. The current standard of practice for aerobic training is performing arm-ergometry
      for 25 mins at a frequency of three times per week. Given the move towards shortened length
      of stay during inpatient rehabilitation, performing MICT can consume a considerable amount of
      therapy time. Sprint interval training (SIT) has been shown to elicit similar improvements in
      physical capacity, despite a reduced time commitment to MICT. However, there are no
      controlled trials comparing the effects of SIT to MICT in individuals with SCI undergoing
      inpatient rehabilitation. The primary aim of this study was to investigate the efficacy of a
      five-week, thrice weekly 10 min SIT program and compare outcome measures to a traditional 25
      minute MICT program on the arm-ergometer in individuals with SCI undergoing inpatient
      clinical rehabilitation. It was hypothesized that five weeks of SIT and MICT would induce
      similar changes in maximal and sub-maximal exercise performance, self-efficacy for exercise,
      and exercise enjoyment, despite large differences in training volume and time commitment. It
      was also hypothesized that SIT would be well tolerated and elicit higher levels of
      cardiovascular strain than MICT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants were randomized to one of two groups: (A) sprint interval training (SIT) or (B) moderate intensity continuous training (MICT).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in peak power output</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in peak power output from baseline to 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>maximum amount of power produced during a graded exercise test on the arm-ergometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sub-maximal arm-ergometry</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in sub-maximal arm-ergometry from baseline to 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants performed three 5-minute steady state workloads on the arm-ergometer at power outputs corresponding to RPE's of 8, 10 and 12. Participants were given a minimum of 2 minutes, and a maximum of 5 minutes of rest in between each workload.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout each week of training (Week 1,Week 2, Week 3, Week4, Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>Monitored heart rate throughout each training session</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptual Responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout each week of training (Week 1,Week 2, Week 3, Week4, Week 5)</time_frame>
    <description>Monitored ratings of perceived exertion throughout each training session</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-efficacy for exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in self-efficacy from baseline to 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Using a self-reported questionnaire, participants rated how confident they are with regards to performing and carrying out regular physical activities and exercises.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured only at the end of the intervention (5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants completed the Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale (PACES) in order to asses the level of enjoyment with the training intervention they received.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain perceptions</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured only at the end of the intervention (5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Through a questionnaire, participants rated how much shoulder pain, bodily pain, and physical discomfort they typically experience throughout the day and how much pain they experienced with the intervention they were allocated to.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Rehabilitation</condition>
  <condition>Exercise</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate Intensity Continuous Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Training was performed three times a week for five weeks. Each session began with a 2 minute warm up, and concluded with a 3 minute cool down. Following the warm-up, participants performed 20 minutes of arm cycling at a self-selected cadence at 45-65% of their peak power output. Total training duration was 25 mins.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sprint Interval Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The SIT protocol was adopted from Gillen and colleagues (See Ref), and consisted of 3 x 20 second &quot;all-out&quot; efforts at ≥ 100% of an individuals peak power output. Each sprint was interspersed by 120 seconds of active recovery at 10% of an individuals peak power output. Total training duration was 10 mins.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sprint interval training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants utilized the arm ergometer for improving aerobic exercise capacity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sprint Interval Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>moderate intensity continuous training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants utilized the arm ergometer for improving aerobic exercise capacity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate Intensity Continuous Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with sub-acute spinal cord injury (time since injury: 14 - 182 days)

          -  Undergoing inpatient rehabilitation

          -  Aged 18-65 years

          -  Injury level at the second cervical vertebrae (C2) or below

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Unable to perform arm-ergometry training
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Audrey L Hicks, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McMaster University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McMaster University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8S 4L8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gillen JB, Martin BJ, MacInnis MJ, Skelly LE, Tarnopolsky MA, Gibala MJ. Twelve Weeks of Sprint Interval Training Improves Indices of Cardiometabolic Health Similar to Traditional Endurance Training despite a Five-Fold Lower Exercise Volume and Time Commitment. PLoS One. 2016 Apr 26;11(4):e0154075. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0154075. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27115137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hicks AL, Martin KA, Ditor DS, Latimer AE, Craven C, Bugaresti J, McCartney N. Long-term exercise training in persons with spinal cord injury: effects on strength, arm ergometry performance and psychological well-being. Spinal Cord. 2003 Jan;41(1):34-43.</citation>
    <PMID>12494319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nightingale TE, Metcalfe RS, Vollaard NB, Bilzon JL. Exercise Guidelines to Promote Cardiometabolic Health in Spinal Cord Injured Humans: Time to Raise the Intensity? Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2017 Aug;98(8):1693-1704. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2016.12.008. Epub 2017 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>28089898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Astorino TA, Thum JS. Within-session responses to high-intensity interval training in spinal cord injury. Disabil Rehabil. 2018 Feb;40(4):444-449. doi: 10.1080/09638288.2016.1260648. Epub 2016 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27930890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Inpatient Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Sprint interval training</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal Cord Injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

