<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03700125</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>012543</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>244748</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03700125</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-hospital ECMO in Advanced Resuscitation in Patients With Refractory Cardiac Arrest. ( SUB30 )</brief_title>
  <acronym>SUB30</acronym>
  <official_title>Feasibility Study of a Pre-hospital Extra-corporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO) Capable Advanced Resuscitation Team at Achieving Blood Flow Within 30 Minutes in Patients With Refractory Cardiac Arrest.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Barts &amp; The London NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>London's Air Ambulance</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bodychillz Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maquet Cardiopulmonary GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stryker Nordic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Barts &amp; The London NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To establish whether a pre-hospital advanced physician/ paramedic cardiac arrest team that is
      ECMO capable can establish ECMO flow within 30 minutes of collapse. The Sub30 study will
      investigate the technical and logistical feasibility of instituting pre-hospital
      Extracorporeal Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation (ECPR) within 30 minutes of collapse for
      selected patients (n=6) in a geographical sector of Greater London. It will achieve this
      through a unique collaboration between the primary emergency dispatch and response services
      (London Ambulance Service NHS Trust, LAS), pre-hospital practitioners (LAS and London Air
      Ambulance) and clinicians in ECMO (Barts Health NHS Trust).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Every year, in London, the ambulance service treats over 4,000 patients who have a had a
      cardiac arrest (or their heart has stopped). Less than 1 in 10 patients survive to get home.
      Some of those who survive have severe brain damage since their brains did not receive blood
      and oxygen when their heart was stopped. The ambulance service in London manages to get to a
      patient, on average, 7 minutes following a 999 call. The paramedics are very skilled in
      restarting people's hearts and often manage this in less than 10 minutes. However, sometimes
      it can take much longer or not be possible. The risks of a patient dying or suffering brain
      damage increase the longer it takes to restart the heart, particularly after about 20-30
      minutes. An extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) machine may reduce these risks by
      pumping a patient's blood through an artificial lung and to their vital body organs -
      temporarily replacing the function of the heart and lungs. The ECMO is used in normal care to
      support patients after a cardiac arrest once a patient reaches the hospital, but in this
      study we want to see if the ECMO can be used very soon after the cardiac arrest is reported
      via the 999 call.

      In the Sub30 study, the ECMO team and machine to travel immediately to where the patient
      collapses rather than wait for the patient to be moved to a hospital. The study hypothesis is
      that the ECMO will be started faster and that this may improve patient survival and outcomes.

      The ECMO team consists of three senior doctors and a paramedic. They attend patients who have
      collapsed and start ECMO if standard advanced resuscitation techniques fail to restart the
      heart in 20 minutes. The team will aim to have the ECMO machine started within 30 minutes of
      the 999 call. The team have achieved this in training and the current study will assess
      whether it is possible to do this in six patients in real-life.

      A target of thirty minutes to achieve ECMO flow or return of spontaneous circulation (ROSC)
      is less than in published series to date. This can be achieved by:

        -  integration into an established pre-hospital emergency response services that
           aggressively pursue ROSC through optimised Advanced Life Support

        -  immediate deployment of an ECPR-capable cardiac arrest team as a primary resource, as
           opposed to delayed secondary deployment. Dispatch will be done by the established
           Advanced Paramedic Practitioner (APP) desk of London Ambulance Service, with the
           objective to reach the patient within 8-10 minutes of the 999 call.

        -  early placement of guide-wires into the femoral vessels during on-going conventional
           CPR, a procedure with low complication risk that does not commit the team to ECPR but
           will minimise the delay to ECPR support if conventional resuscitative techniques are not
           successful within 20 minutes

        -  facilitated guide-wire placement through real-time wireless ultrasound delivered to the
           operator through augmented reality smart glasses.

      Some out of hospital cardiac arrests (OHCA) are irreversible in nature and ECPR would not
      provide benefit to these patients. The ECPR team will not be task fixated on providing ECPR,
      but also supportive of the APP primary responders and provide ECPR only in settings of
      refractory cardiac arrest that fulfils the study criteria, that have been chosen based on
      best available evidence to identify those patients in whom ECPR is likely to be of benefit.

      If pre-hospital ECMO is feasible within 30 minutes of chest compressions starting, then a
      larger randomised controlled study of clinical and cost effectiveness is merited.
      Optimisation of the delivery of ECPR is vital, prior to a controlled study, in order to
      maximise any potential benefits for patients.

      Data from Sub30 will inform the design of such studies enabling an estimation of the size of
      any potential outcome benefits and the likely affordability for a healthcare service.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single centre feasibility study of a complex intervention</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients successfully established with pre-hospital ECPR</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 minutes of collapse</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the proportion of patients successfully established with pre-hospital ECPR within 30 minutes of collapse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ambulance dispatch</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 minutes of collapse</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients not dispatched to as travel time too great/team unavailable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful cannulation</measure>
    <time_frame>between 31 and 45 minutes; and 46 and 60 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients successfully cannulated 31 and 45 minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with return of spontaneous circulations (ROSC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 20 minutes of cardiac arrest</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients patients who achieve ROSC prior to the 20 minutes timeout, number of patients in refractory cardiac arrest at 20 minutes in whom ROSC is achieved prior to ECMO flow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency call-out time frame</measure>
    <time_frame>At 30 minutes after cardiac arrest</time_frame>
    <description>The time interval between call to the emergency services and ECPR team arrival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful guide wire placement</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes after cardiac arrest</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of potentially supportable patients in whom guidewire placement is attempted and achieved</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of ECPR-related complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of ECMO run, between 3 - 14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of ECPR-related complications, such as incidence of vascular damage, haemorrhage requiring transfusion and new organ dysfunction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome via FIM at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of functional status at hospital discharge using the Functional Independence Measure - FIM (18 item scale, measure of dependence. The higher the score, the more independent the patient is in performing the task).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome via MRS at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of functional status at hospital discharge using the modified Rankin Scale (MRS) (scale 0-6, measuring the degree of disability or dependence in the daily activities, where 0 is no symptoms and 6 is dead)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of health resources used for the duration of Intensive Care Unit stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of acute hospital admissions post discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of health resources used for further hospital admissions following discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Death, Sudden, Cardiac</condition>
  <condition>Out-Of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <condition>Ventricular Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Cardiopulmonary Arrest With Successful Resuscitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ECMO resuscitation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6 patients who meet the eligibility criteria will be treated by pre-hospital advanced physician/ paramedic cardiac arrest team that is ECMO capable and can establish ECMO flow within 30 minutes of collapse</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ECMO resuscitation</intervention_name>
    <description>Extracorporeal Cardio-Pulmonary Resuscitation (ECPR) using ECMO within 30 minutes of cardiac arrest</description>
    <arm_group_label>ECMO resuscitation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Adult patients who:

          -  have a witnessed out-of-hospital cardiac arrest

          -  a presumed cardiac aetiology to their cardiac arrest

          -  receive bystander chest compressions within 3 minutes

          -  remain in cardiac arrest at 20 minutes following the call to the emergency services or
             fail to sustain ROSC in the pre-hospital setting

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The following patients will not be suitable for entry into the study:

          -  Known or visible advanced pregnancy (when resuscitative hysterotomy should be
             performed)

          -  No signs of life (physical movement or breathing) AND evidence of ineffective chest
             compressions suggested by:

          -  absence of electrical activity at 20 minutes time out OR

          -  end tidal carbon dioxide level of less than 1.3 kPa (10 mmHg)

          -  Evidence from others present at the scene or patient examination that ECMO unlikely to
             benefit patient (e.g. advanced malignancy, severe frailty).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon Finney</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Barts &amp; The London NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ben Singer</last_name>
    <phone>02034656911</phone>
    <email>b.singer@nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vivienne Monk</last_name>
    <phone>0207882 5668</phone>
    <email>v.monk@qmul.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Bartholomew's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>EC1 6BQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ben Singer</last_name>
      <phone>0203 4656911</phone>
      <email>sub30study.bartshealth@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Simon Finney</last_name>
      <email>simon.finney2@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ben Singer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Ambulance Service Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 0BW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.qmul.ac.uk/whri/clinical-activities/cvctu/trials-portfolio/sub-30/</url>
    <description>Bart Cardiovascular Clinical Trials Unit (CVCTU) portfolio - SUB30 study</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced life support (ALS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Extra-corporeal Membrane Oxygenation Resuscitation (ECMO)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death, Sudden, Cardiac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death, Sudden</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share study participant data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

