<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03705182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Epoxy Vision</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03705182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Dermatitis in Epoxy Exposed Workers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevention of Dermatitis in Epoxy Exposed Lamination Workers Producing Wind Turbine Blades: An Intervention Study Using Fluorescence Visualization</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Arbejdsmiljøforskningsfonden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vestas Wind Power</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Siemens Gamesa Renewable Energy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Skane University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Herning Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Research Centre for the Working Environment, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aalborg University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The risk of sensitization and contact dermatitis among workers exposed to epoxy resin systems
      (ERS) is high despite extensive preventive efforts, probably because skin exposure is often
      left unrecognized.

      The main objective of this project is to prevent epoxy-related dermatitis and sensitization,
      caused by working with ERS, by fluorescence visualization of exposure. In cooperation with
      global manufacturers of wind turbines, 450 lamination workers will be allocated to either an
      intervention or a control Group. The risk of dermatitis and sensitization will be compared.
      Skin exposure will be made visible by a fluorescent tracer added to the ERS. UVA-light will
      illuminate the skin of head, neck, arms and hands and the fluorescent areas will be recorded
      and quantified by a computer vision system. The intervention group will be shown the
      fluorescent areas on their skin, while the control group will not have this information. The
      intervention takes place daily for a period of 1 month, 4 times during the 2 year follow up
      period.

      All participants are patch tested, screened for dermatitis and atopy at start and end of
      follow up or at end of employment. The investigators also assess potential determinants for
      ERS exposure including working tasks and procedures. Information on dermatitis diagnoses from
      hospital contacts, medical prescriptions and education will be obtained from registers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives The overarching objective is to reduce the risk of dermatitis and sensitization
      when working with epoxy resin systems.

      Specific aims are:

        -  To identify work procedures at increased risk of dermal exposure to epoxy resins

        -  To examine if fluorescence visualization of dermal exposure to epoxy resins reduces the
           risk of:

             -  subsequent dermal exposure to epoxy resins

             -  dermatitis

             -  sensitization to epoxy resins

        -  To examine the risk of dermatitis following sensitization to ERS components

        -  To examine the course of sensitization to ERS components.

      Materials and methods Study population The study population is 450 employees of two factories
      producing rotor blades for wind turbines. The participants all have daily manual work with
      ERS. Participants will be recruited through the Health Safety and Environment (HSE)
      organizations by oral and written information. Current employees will be followed for 2
      years. Employees employed during the study will continuously be recruited and followed until
      end of follow up, 2 years after study start.

      Measurement of exposure by fluorescent tracer technique The two factories and the
      manufacturers of ERS have tested different fluorescent tracers and decided on a tracer that
      is compatible with the epoxy resin systems. The fluorescence will be recorded and quantified
      by a computer vision system that is currently under development. The system will, for
      milliseconds, illuminate the skin of head, neck, arms and hands with UVA-light that does not
      allow the participants to notice the fluorescent skin areas. Digital images of the
      fluorescent areas will be displayed to the participants on a screen. Participants will record
      skin exposure with the vision system every time a production area is left i.e. for lunch
      breaks, toilet visits and at the end of a work day. At each time, participants will report
      work procedures and use of protective equipment during the preceding few hours and this
      information will be stored and linked with the skin exposure measurements.

      The participants will be able to operate the system themselves; it will register and store
      all data inclusive their identity for later analysis. The system is handy and can be
      transported easily and the procedure will only take a couple minutes. The fluorescence
      measurements will take place daily for a period of 1 month, 4 times during the 2 year follow
      up period.

      Questionnaire At start and end of follow up, participants are asked to fill in a brief
      questionnaire concerning recent and former skin rashes, allergies, atopic dermatitis, asthma
      and life style factors. The questionnaire will be a shortened version of the Nordic
      Occupational Skin Questionnaire and ECRHS.

      Clinical examination and blood samples To test for atopy, participants will provide a blood
      sample for subsequent analysis of specific IgE for standard inhalation allergens.
      Participants reporting skin rash or symptoms from airways will be invited to a clinical
      examination for diagnostic classification.Photo documentation of the skin will be performed.

      Patch testing All participants will be patch tested for ERS components. a specially profiled
      occupational patch test series will be developed as done in former studies of epoxy exposed
      workers. The test materials are diluted according to recommended test concentrations. New
      materials are tested on 20 patients with dermatitis from the Yrkes och Miljödermatologisk
      Afdeling, Skånes Universitetssjukhus. Test concentrations are subsequently adjusted if
      necessary. A dilution series on the 20 test patients will be added in order to evaluate the
      degree of sensitization by positive reactions. All participants are also tested with the
      European standard patch test series.

      Patch testing will be performed at the workplaces at start and end of follow up. Employees
      terminating employment during the study period will be contacted at home for testing. The
      test material will be placed on the back, occluded for 48 hours with readings at day 3, 4 and
      7. The backs of the participants will be photographed prior to application and in connection
      with the readings. Possible skin reactions later than day 7 will be obtained by a
      questionnaire supplemented with photo documentation by the participants.

      Register data Information about prescribed medications, hospital contacts (diagnoses),
      education and other possible confounders or modifying factors will be obtained through
      linkage with national registers. Data will be uploaded and anonymized at Statistics Denmark.

      Intervention The 450 participants will be allocated to an intervention- or a control group,
      around 225 in each. The intervention group will be shown the fluorescent areas on their skin,
      while the control group will not have this opportunity. Work teams of 40 workers will be
      allocated together.

      A group of 600 office workers will be asked to fill in the questionnaire. Of the 600 workers
      100 will be asked to be patch tested and to provide a blood sample.

      Compliance The investigators will on a weekly basis monitor study compliance by checking the
      frequency of the use of the visualization system. The quality of the visualization data
      obtained, will also be monitored. The statistical results will continuously be evaluated
      together with the HSE-responsible of the factories.

      Statistical analyses The investigators will analyze how different work procedures and
      protective equipment predict intensity of skin exposure to epoxy resins in the control group.
      The analytical unit will be exposure registrations and level of fluorescence. Since each
      participant will contribute multiple recordings, data will be analyzed with mixed logistic
      and linear regression.

      The effect of visualization on the risk of subsequent exposure will be analyzed by comparing
      the occurrence of skin exposure in the intervention group with the control group. Data will
      be analyzed with mixed logistic regression for reasons as above.

      The effect of visualization on the risk of dermatitis and sensitization to epoxy resin
      systems will also be accomplished by comparing the intervention with the control group. The
      analytical unit will be the individual participant and data are thus analyzed with
      traditional logistic regression. Participants with dermatitis or sensitization to epoxy resin
      systems at baseline will be excluded from these analyses. All analyses will be adjusted for
      relevant confounders based on Direct Acyclic Graph (DAGs).

      Statistical power Based on the expected incidence of dermatitis in a wind turbine plant,
      around 225 participants in the intervention group and the control group, respectively, a
      follow up of 2 years, and an expected annual incidence of dermatitis of 5 % in the control
      group, the investigators will be able to detect reductions of 75% and 50% in the intervention
      group with a power of 97% and 56%, respectively.

      Perspectives If exposure visualization reduces the risk of dermatitis and sensitization to
      epoxy resin systems, this may have significant impact on the health of the many who work with
      these materials worldwide. Global manufacturers of wind turbines and composite materials are
      involved in the project and this is expected to facilitate the dissemination globally. Follow
      up studies of persistent exposure to potent skin sensitizers with repeated patch testing has
      rarely been done and the study may furthermore provide new insight to the epidemiology of
      allergic dermatitis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The 450 participants will be allocated to an intervention- or a control group, around 225 in each. The intervention group will be shown the fluorescent areas on their skin, while the control group will not have this opportunity. Work teams of approximately 40 workers with comparable work procedures, are allocated together.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sensitization</measure>
    <time_frame>At start and after 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assesed by patch test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in prevalence of dermatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>At start and after 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnosed by clinical examinations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fluorescence levels</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month x 4, over 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of fluorescence, skin area exposed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in number of fluorescence recordings</measure>
    <time_frame>1 months x 4, over 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of recordings during a day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Contact Dermatitis</condition>
  <condition>Sensitization Dermatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventiongroup</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention group will be shown the fluorescent areas on their skin (fluorescence visualization feedback)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will not be shown the fluorescent areas on their skin (no feedback)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluorescence visualization (feedback)</intervention_name>
    <description>UVA-light will illuminate the skin of head, neck, arms and hands and the fluorescent areas will be recorded and quantified by a computer vision system each time the participant leaves a production area. The intervention group will be shown the fluorescent areas on their skin, the control group will not have this opportunity</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventiongroup</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  18 years of age or more

          -  Understand Danish or English

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Severe dermatitis

          -  Epilepsy

          -  Current treatment with prednisolone
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henrik A. Kolstad, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Occupational Medicine, Aarhus University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandra G Christiansen, cand. med</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Occupational Medicine, Aarhus University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandra G. Christiansen, cand. med</last_name>
    <phone>+45 61369475</phone>
    <email>Alexpe@rm.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Henrik A. Kolstad, professor</last_name>
    <phone>+45 78450900</phone>
    <email>Henkol@rm.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Occupational medicine, Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8200</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandra G Christisansen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 61369475</phone>
      <email>Alexpe@rm.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Henrik A. Kolstad, professor</last_name>
      <phone>+45 78450900</phone>
      <email>Henkol@rm.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fluorescence</keyword>
  <keyword>dermal assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>skin exposure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Contact</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

