<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03704922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00026112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03704922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Age of Blood in Sickle Cell Transfusion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Age of Blood in Sickle Cell Transfusion -The Effects of Phosphotidylserine Expression on Older Red Cell Units in Adults With Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Versiti</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Versiti</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Investigators hypothesize that older red cell units trigger phagocytosis and activation
      of circulating macrophages with a downstream immunomodulatory cascade and release of excess
      Non Transferrin Bound Iron(NTBI) that leads to increased rates of infection in adults with
      Sickle Cell Disease(SCD). To test this hypothesis, the study staff will perform a randomized
      prospective clinical trial. In aim 1, the study staff will determine the biochemical
      differences between ≥30 day-old versus ≤10 day-old units. In aim 2, the study staff will
      determine the physiologic effects of the transfused blood in a patient with SCD. Lastly, in
      aim 3, the study staff will explore the clinical implications of receiving older red cells
      over a 3 month period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Investigators assembled a multidisciplinary investigative team to examine the potential
      effects of older red cell units in adults with Sickle Cell Disease(SCD). Study staff have
      preliminary data that show: 1) there is equipoise among blood bank directors about the
      effects of older units in adults with SCD, 2) in our institution, many adults are
      administered older units, 3) older units activate macrophages and 4) this physiology promoted
      by older units is associated with an increased risk of infection. Our team is now poised to
      take the next investigative step: a prospective, randomized study.

      In Milwaukee, 1/3 of units transfused to adults with SCD are &gt;30 days old, but nation-wide
      some restrict the transfusion of older units. About four hundred adults receive care in the
      Adult Sickle Cell Clinic at Froedtert Hospital in Milwaukee, about 23 of who receive chronic
      outpatient transfusions for chronic pain or stroke prophylaxis. Transfusions are administered
      to adults regardless of storage age, except in the case of red cell exchange, for which there
      is a policy to use less than 14 day old units. In a 3-year retrospective review of
      transfusions administered to adults with SCD, 627 units were given via simple transfusion
      over 281 outpatient encounters. The overall median unit storage age was 22 days (range: 2-42
      days), and 25% of the units transfused were stored 33 days or longer.

      To determine the opinions and policies of other hospital blood bank directors about the use
      of older red cell units for patients with SCD, study staff conducted a nation-wide survey
      (n=90). While only 23% of respondents had a storage age restriction policy for patients with
      SCD, 31% thought that older units were not as effective as younger units, and 65% believed
      that evidence-based policies were needed

      Adults with SCD may be susceptible to the effects of an older unit's physiology because they
      are prone to infection, inflamed, and poorly equipped to handle excess iron. In a cohort of
      40 steady-state adults with SCD, we specifically measured markers of inflammation and iron
      excess. High sensitivity C-reactive protein, a marker of systemic inflammation, was found to
      be markedly elevated (median 5.6 mg/L, range 0.4-60 mg/L; reference range &lt;1.0 mg/L), as was
      ferritin, a marker of iron stores (median 2,969 ng/ml, range 20-12,300 ng/ml; reference range
      13-400 ng/ml).

      Forty chronically-transfused adults with SCD will be randomized in a double-blind fashion to
      receive ≥30 day-old or ≤10 day-old units for 3 months. Subjects will be randomized in blocks
      of 5 and stratified by age: at least 10 subjects from each of the age ranges 18-30 and 31-45
      years will be enrolled. Pre-transfusion, sterile samples will be extracted from red cell
      units. Patient peripheral blood will be also obtained 1 month before randomization,
      immediately pre-transfusion, and 2 and 24 hours post-transfusion. Hemoglobin will be measured
      pre-transfusion, 2 and 24 hours post-transfusion, and 2 weeks post transfusion. Participants
      will complete standardized diaries daily to document symptoms of infection, SCD pain,
      medications and Emergency Department(ED) or hospital use. Diaries will be collected and
      participants will be assessed with each transfusion encounter and 4 weeks after the last
      transfusion. To ensure compliance, coordinators will contact subjects weekly to complete the
      diaries.

      Study staff will evaluate red cells pre- and post-transfusion for Phosphatidylserine(PE),
      Phosphatidylethanolamine(PS), and microparticles as above for all blood samples. White cells
      will be isolated with established separation techniques. The white cell populations of
      interest will be defined by their location on a forward scatter/side scatter plot and their
      positivity using key fluorochrome-labeled identity markers (macrophages: CD14, neutrophils:
      CD16). Once the cell populations of interest are identified, the cells will be evaluated for
      various markers of activation. The plasma fraction from each patient and red cell unit will
      be diverted to determine concentrations of free heme/hemoglobin, cytokines, and NTBI,
      respectively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 4, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of biochemically old red cell units</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>We will compare the transfusions provided to the two groups (the proportion of biochemically old units when stored ≥30 days compared to when stored ≤10 days) using a Fisher exact test at an alpha of 0.05. Power: With a total sample size of 40 patients (20 in each group), we will have at least 80% power (α=0.05) to detect a difference of at least 47% between the two randomized groups for biochemically old red cell units (close to a 100% difference is expected). We will compare the secondary endpoints plasma free hemoglobin, heme, and NTBI and also PS, PE, and microparticle concentrations using a two sided two sample t-test at an alpha of 0.05.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the concentration of CD62L positive circulating monocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in CD62Lcirculating monocyte/macrophage MFI at 2 hours post-transfusion compared to the subject pre-transfusion. We will compare the two groups using a two sample two-sided t-test of the log at an alpha of 0.05. Power: In addition, we will use a general(ized) linear model to include biochemically old units transfused, regardless of unit age, as a covariate in our analysis. Other co-variates will include free heme, cell free hemoglobin, and NTBI from the transfused unit. We will similarly compare secondary activation endpoints: activation markers for neutrophils and measured cytokine concentrations. Lastly, as an exploratory aim, we will evaluate the in vivo change in recipient red cell PE/PS positivity at 2 and 24 hours post transfusion. When possible, donor and recipient red cells will be differentiated in S-antigen negative patients who are by chance provided S-positive heterozygous or homozygous donor red cells.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of infections in adults</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the percentage of infections in adults who receive ≥30 day-old units as compared to ≤10 day-old units. The presence of an indwelling catheter will be used as a key co-variate in this analysis.
We will further explore the relationship of blood age and transfusion of biochemically old red cell units on the change in Hb and HbS% over time, daily pain scores, opioid use and dose, ED and hospitalization rate, infection symptoms, new alloantibody formation, and antibiotic use during the 3-month study period. We will compare groups using a Fisher exact test. Power: A difference of 20% will be of clinical interest. We do not expect to have adequate power for this pilot study but at an alpha of 0.05 with 20 subjects in each group we will be able to detect a difference of 47% between the proportions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>≤10 day Blood</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive only blood stored ≤10 days for 3 consecutive transfusion events.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>≥30 day Blood</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group will receive only blood stored ≥30 days for 3 consecutive transfusion events.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transfusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Red cell units for transfusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>≤10 day Blood</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>≥30 day Blood</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. age 16 to 45 years

          2. Hemoglobin SS/Hemoglobin Sβ-thalassemia0

          3. on chronic red cell transfusion therapy

          4. outpatient at the time of transfusion

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. history of reactions to transfusion therapy that cannot be adequately managed by
             antihistamines

          2. ≥2 red cell alloantibodies

          3. participation in another therapeutic trial for SCD

          4. pregnant

          5. HIV positive

          6. uncontrolled inter-current illness, or psychiatric illness/social situations that
             would limit compliance with study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua Field, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Versiti</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew Karafin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>414-937-6809</phone>
    <email>MKarafin@Versiti.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Steven Frymark</last_name>
    <phone>414-937-6814</phone>
    <email>sfrymark@versiti.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hailly Butler, RN</last_name>
      <phone>404-712-8895</phone>
      <email>hailly.butler@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Versiti Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Frymark</last_name>
      <phone>414-937-6814</phone>
      <email>steven.frymark@bcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Versiti</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthew Karafin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transfusion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to make Individual Participant Data (IPD) available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

