<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03707041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMV_P218_17_01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-003004-39</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03707041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability and Chemoprotective Activity of P218 in PfSPZ Challenge Model</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single Centre, Randomised, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Phase Ib Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Chemoprotective Antimalarial Activity of P218 Against Controlled Human Malaria Infection With Plasmodium Falciparum Sporozoite Challenge in Non-immune Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medicines for Malaria Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SGS Life Sciences, a division of SGS Belgium NV</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute of Tropical Medicine, Belgium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss BioQuant A.G., Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PrimeVigilance Ltd., UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biologic LLP, UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanaria Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>FGK Representative Service B.V., The Netherlands</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medicines for Malaria Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single centre, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled Phase Ib study, to
      evaluate the safety, tolerability and chemoprotective activity of P218 in a controlled P.
      falciparum sporozoite infection model.

      Healthy men and women, aged 18 to 45 years will be enrolled in 3 study cohorts and will be
      administered either P218 or placebo twice, 48 hours apart. Subjects in cohorts 2 and 3 will
      be inoculated with P. falciparum sporozoites. Enrolment in cohorts will proceed sequentially,
      to facilitate review of data by a Safety Review Team (SRT) before proceeding with a
      subsequent cohort.

      In cohort 1, safety and tolerability of P218 will be assessed. In cohorts 2 and 3,
      chemoprotective activity of P218 against malaria infection will be assessed, as well as the
      Influence of time of initiation of the P218 treatment on the protective effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single centre, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled Phase Ib study, to
      evaluate the safety, tolerability and chemoprotective activity of P218 in a controlled P.
      falciparum sporozoite infection model.

      32 healthy men and women, aged 18 to 45 years will be enrolled in 3 cohorts of respectively
      8, 12 and 12 subjects. A subject may be enrolled in one cohort only and will be randomised in
      a 3:1 ratio, to receive two consecutive administrations, 48 hours apart, of either P218 or
      placebo. Enrolment in cohorts will proceed sequentially, to facilitate review of data by a
      Safety Review Team (SRT) before populating a subsequent cohort.

      Cohort 1 will consist of 2 subgroups of subjects, to be enrolled sequentially: subgroup 1
      will be composed of 2 subjects: one to receive two 1000 mg doses of P218 and one to receive
      placebo twice. Subgroup 2 will be composed of 6 subjects: five to receive two 1000 mg doses
      of P218 and one to receive placebo twice. Subjects in subgroup 2 will not be treated until 24
      hours after second IMP administration in the last subject of subgroup 1 and only after review
      of the safety data from subgroup 1 by the PI. Duration of each subject treatment and
      follow-up in Cohort 1 is 9 days. Progression to Cohort 2 is subject to review of the safety
      and tolerability data by a SRT.

      Cohort 2 will consist of three subgroups of subjects, to be enrolled sequentially. Subgroup 1
      will be composed of 2 subjects: one to receive two 1000 mg doses of P218 and one to receive
      placebo twice. Subgroups 2 and 3 will be composed of 5 subjects each: four to receive two
      1000 mg doses of P218 and one to receive placebo twice. Subjects in subgroup 2 will not be
      treated until 24 hours after second IMP administration in the last subject of subgroup 1. On
      Day 1, each subject in Cohort 2 will be administered 3200 P. falciparum sporozoites (PfSPZ
      Challenge) by direct venous inoculation (DVI). First administration of 1000 mg of P218 or
      placebo will take place 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge DVI; second administration of 1000 mg
      of P218 or placebo will take place 48 hours later. As of Day 7, parasitemia in every subject
      will be assessed daily until the installation of malarial infection or until Day 28. Overall
      duration of each subject observation in Cohort 2 is 35 days. Progression to Cohort 3 is
      subject to assessment of safety and parasitemia data, as well as malaria signs and symptoms
      by a SRT.

      Cohort 3 will consist of two subgroups each with 6 subjects, to be enrolled sequentially.
      Treatment will be allocated in a ratio of 3 active: 1 placebo. In each subgroup, at least 1
      subject will receive placebo and the remaining subjects will receive two 100 mg doses of P218
      48 hours apart. Subjects in subgroup 2 will not be inoculated until 24 hours after second IMP
      administration in the last subject of subgroup 1. On Day 1, subjects will be administered
      3200 P. falciparum sporozoites by DVI. As of Day 7, parasitemia in every subject will be
      assessed daily until the installation of malarial infection or until Day 28. Overall duration
      of each subject observation in Cohort 3 is 35 days.

      All subjects in Cohorts 2 and 3 will receive antimalarial rescue therapy, either upon
      installation of malarial infection or on Day 28 or if leaving the study prematurely.

      In Cohort 1, safety and tolerability of two 1000 mg doses of P218 administered 48 hours apart
      will be assessed over 9 days of observation. Pharmacokinetic assessments of P218 and its main
      metabolites will take place over 9 days of observation.

      In Cohorts 2 and 3, chemoprotective activity of two doses P218 (1000 mg or 100 mg
      respectively) administered 48 hours apart, will be assessed over 28 days. Safety and
      tolerability of two doses of P218 (1000 mg or 100 mg respectively) administered 48 hours
      apart will be assessed over 35 days of observation. Pharmacokinetic assessments of P218 will
      take place over 9 days of observation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 27, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 27, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In each of the three treatment cohorts, subjects will be randomly allocated to receive either P218 or placebo.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Placebo capsules matched to the drug product with regard to appearance and taste</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: Number of TEAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence, severity and relationship to the treatment of observed or self-reported treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) after two single doses of 1000 mg P218 administered 48 hours apart in healthy adult volunteers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 2: Geometric mean time from PfSPZ Challenge to first quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) outcome equal or greater than 250 asexual parasites per mL of blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of days from PfSPZ Challenge DVI to positive parasitaemia, or 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Chemoprotective activity of two single doses of 1000 mg P218 administered 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge and 48 hours later in healthy adult volunteers</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 3: Geometric mean time from PfSPZ Challenge DVI to first qPCR outcome equal or greater than 250 asexual parasites per mL of blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of days from PfSPZ Challenge to positive parasitaemia, or 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Chemoprotective activity of two single doses of 100 mg P218 administered 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge and 48 hours later in healthy adult volunteers</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 2 and 3: Number of P218 TEAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence, severity and relationship to the P218 treatment of observed or self-reported treatment emergent adverse events in non-immune healthy adult volunteers after two single doses of 1000 mg P218 administered 48 hours apart in a controlled human malaria infection (PfSPZ Challenge)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 2 and 3: Number of PfSPZ Challenge TEAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence, severity and relationship to the PfSPZ Challenge of observed or self-reported treatment emergent adverse events in non-immune healthy adult volunteers before and after P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 2 and 3: Malaria clinical score</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of positive parasitaemia or on Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Malaria clinical score at the time of introduction of rescue therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 1, 2 and 3: P218 AUC[0-48h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218 plasma concentration-time curve from first administration to 48 hours after first administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 1, 2 and 3: P218 AUC[48-96h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218 plasma concentration-time curve from 48 hours after first administration to 96 hours after first administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-OH AUC[0-48h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218-OH plasma concentration-time curve from first P218 administration to 48 hours after first P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-OH AUC[48-96h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218-OH plasma concentration-time curve from 48 hours after first P218 administration to 96 hours after first P218 administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide AUC[0-48h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide plasma concentration-time curve from first P218 administration to 48 hours after first P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide AUC[48-96h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide plasma concentration-time curve from 48 hours after first P218 administration to 96 hours after first P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH AUC[0-48h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH plasma concentration-time curve from first P218 administration to 48 hours after first P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH AUC[48-96h]</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH plasma concentration-time .curve from 48 hours after first P218 administration to 96 hours after first P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 1, 2 and 3: P218 Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed P218 plasma concentration after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohorts 1, 2 and 3: P218 Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to P218 Cmax after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-OH Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed P218-OH plasma concentration after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-OH Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to P218-OH Cmax after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed P218-OH plasma concentration after each P218 .administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide Cmax after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH plasma concentration after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 1: P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to P218-beta-acyl-glucuronide-OH Cmax after each P218 administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P218 1000 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two administrations of 1000 mg P218 (capsules p.o.), 48 hours apart</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsules - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two administrations of P218 placebo (capsules p.o.), 48 hours apart</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P218 1000 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One administration of 1000 mg P218 (capsules p.o.), 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge and one administration of 1000 mg P218 (capsules p.o.), 48 hours after first administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsules - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One administration of P218 placebo (capsules p.o.), 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge and one administration of P218 placebo (capsules p.o.,) 48 hours after first administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P218 100 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One administration of 100 mg P218 (capsules p.o.), 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge and one administration of 100 mg P218 (capsules p.o.), 48 hours after first administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsule - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One administration of P218 placebo (capsules p.o.), 2 hours after PfSPZ Challenge and one administration of P218 placebo (capsules p.o.), 48 hours after first administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>P218 (1000 mg) Oral Capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 mg P218 (4 x 250 mg capsules)</description>
    <arm_group_label>P218 1000 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>P218 1000 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Oral Capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsules matched to the P218 capsules with regard to appearance and taste</description>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsule - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsules - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsules - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>P218 (100 mg) Oral Capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg P218 (2 x 50 mg capsules)</description>
    <arm_group_label>P218 100 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PfSPZ Challenge</intervention_name>
    <description>3200 P. falciparum Sporozoites by direct venous inoculation (DVI)</description>
    <arm_group_label>P218 100 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>P218 1000 mg (Oral Capsules) - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsule - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>P218 Placebo Oral Capsules - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Subjects meeting all of the following criteria are eligible to participate in this study:

          1. Informed Consent Form signed voluntarily before any study-related procedure is
             performed, indicating that the subject understands the purpose of and procedures
             required for the study and is willing to participate in the study, including
             administration of rescue treatment.

          2. Male or female, between 18 and 45 years old (extremes included) at screening.

          3. Body weight of at least 50 kg and a body mass index (BMI) of 19 to 30 kg/m2 (extremes
             included).

          4. Good general health without clinically relevant medical illness, physical exam
             findings including vital signs, and laboratory abnormalities as determined by the
             investigator.

          5. Willing to adhere to the prohibitions and restrictions (see Section 4.3) specified in
             this protocol, including willingness to stay confined to the inpatient unit for
             required duration and willingness to avoid to travel outside of Benelux during the
             study period.

          6. Female subjects should fulfil one of the following criteria:

               1. At least 1 year post-menopausal (amenorrhea &gt;12 months and follicle-stimulating
                  hormone (FSH) &gt;30 mIU/mL) prior to screening;

               2. Surgically sterile (bilateral oophorectomy, hysterectomy or tubal ligation);

               3. Will use contraceptives as outlined in inclusion criteria 7 and 8.

          7. Female subjects of childbearing potential must agree to the use of a highly effective
             method of birth control from screening visit to until 40 days after the last dose of
             IMP (covering a full menstrual cycle of 30 days starting after 5 half-lives of last
             dose of IMP).

             Note: Highly effective birth control methods include: combined (estrogen and
             progestogen containing) oral/intravaginal/transdermal hormonal contraception
             associated with inhibition of ovulation, progestogen-only oral/injectable/implantable
             hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation, intrauterine device,
             intrauterine hormone-releasing system, bilateral tubal occlusion, vasectomised partner
             or sexual abstinence.

          8. Male subjects who are sexually active with a female partner of childbearing potential
             must agree to the use of an effective method of birth control from the day of the
             first IMP dose until 100 days thereafter (covering a full sperm cycle of 90 days
             starting after 5 half-lives of last dose of IMP).

             Note: Medically acceptable methods of contraception that may be used by the subject
             and/or partner include sterilization and vasectomy or a double barrier option
             combining oral contraceptive, contraceptive vaginal ring, contraceptive injection,
             intrauterine device or etonogestrel implant.

          9. Female subject has a negative pregnancy test at screening and upon admission in the
             clinical unit.

             Note: Pregnancy testing will consist of a serum β-human chorionic gonadotropin (β-HCG)
             test at screening and urine β-HCG tests at other visits, in all women.

             Inclusion Criteria - CHMI (controlled human malaria infection) specific:

         10. Different ways of being reachable 24/7 (e.g. by mobile phone, regular phone or
             electronic mail) during the whole study period.

        Subjects meeting any of the following criteria are excluded from participation in this
        study:

          1. Nursing (lactating) women.

          2. Participation in any other clinical drug or vaccine study within 30 days (or five
             half-lives for drugs) preceding the first dose of IMP (whichever is longer), or plans
             to participate in other investigational drug or vaccine research during the study
             period.

          3. Blood product donation to any blood bank during the 8 weeks (whole blood) or 4 weeks
             (plasma and platelets) prior to admission in the clinical unit.

          4. ECG outside normal range and deemed clinically relevant by the investigator. Examples
             of clinically significant ECG abnormalities for this study include:

               1. PR-interval &gt;220 ms;

               2. QRS-complex &gt;120 ms;

               3. QT interval corrected according to Bazett's formula (QTcB) or QT interval
                  corrected according to Fridericia's formula [3] (QTcF) &gt;450 ms;

               4. Pathologic Q wave;

               5. Significant ST-T wave changes;

               6. Left or right ventricular hypertrophy;

               7. Non-sinus rhythm except isolated premature atrial contractions and ventricular
                  extrasystole &lt;2 per 10 s ECG lead;

               8. Incomplete left bundle branch block, or complete or intermittent right or left
                  bundle branch block;

               9. Second or third degree A-V heart block.

          5. Seropositive human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) (antibody and antigen), hepatitis B
             virus (HBV) (hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg]) or hepatitis C virus (HCV)
             (antibody) tests.

          6. History or presence of diagnosed food or known drug allergies (including but not
             limited to allergy to any of the antimalarial rescue medications to be used in the
             study, see Section 5.2), or history of anaphylaxis or other severe allergic reactions.

             Note: Subjects with seasonal allergies/hay fever, house dust mite or allergy to
             animals that are untreated and asymptomatic at the time of dosing can be enrolled in
             the study.

          7. History of convulsion or severe head trauma.

             Note: A medical history of a single febrile convulsion during childhood is not an
             exclusion criteria.

          8. History of serious psychiatric condition that may affect participation in the study or
             preclude compliance with the protocol, including but not limited to past or present
             psychoses, disorders requiring lithium, a history of attempted or planned suicide,
             more than one previous episode of major depression, any previous single episode of
             major depression lasting for or requiring treatment for more than 6 months, or any
             episode of major depression during the 5 years preceding screening.

             Note: The Beck Depression Inventory (Attachment 2) will be used as an objective tool
             for the assessment of depression at screening. In addition to the conditions listed
             above, subjects with a score of 20 or more on the Beck Depression Inventory and/or a
             response of 1, 2 or 3 for item 9 of this inventory (related to suicidal ideation) will
             not be eligible for participation. Subjects with a Beck score of 17 to 19 may be
             enrolled at the discretion of the Investigator if they do not have a history of the
             psychiatric conditions mentioned in this criterion and their mental state is not
             considered to pose additional risk to the health of the volunteer or to the execution
             of the study and interpretation of the data gathered.

          9. A medical, occupational or family problem as a result of alcohol or illicit drug abuse
             during the past 12 months or current alcohol or illicit drug abuse or addiction
             (positive alcohol breath test or positive drug screen for amphetamines, barbiturates,
             benzodiazepines, cannabinoids, cocaine or opiates at screening or upon check-in at the
             clinical unit).

             Note: Excessive use of alcohol is an intake of &gt;21 units per week for males and &gt;14
             units per week for females where one alcohol unit is defined as 10 mL or 8 g of pure
             alcohol. A single unit is equal to one 25-mL (single) measure of whisky (alcohol by
             volume [ABV] 40%), or a third of a pint of beer (190 mL; ABV 5-6%) or half a standard
             (175 mL) glass of wine (ABV 12%).

         10. Subjects are non-smokers or ex-smokers for more than 90 days prior to screening or
             smoke no more than 5 cigarettes per day. If users of nicotine products (i.e. spray,
             patch, e-cigarette, etc.) they should use the equivalent of no more than 5 cigarettes
             per day. Subjects must agree to abstain from smoking while in the unit.

         11. Use of any prescription drugs, herbal supplements (e.g. St John's Wort) or
             over-the-counter medication within 7 days or five half-lives (whichever is longer)
             prior to the first IMP administration, or an anticipated requirement for the use of
             these during the course of the study (See Section 6.2).

             Note: If necessary, the incidental use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs
             (NSAIDs), paracetamol (2g/day, 10 gr/week), vitamins and topical treatments may be
             acceptable after approval by the study Sponsor and will be documented in the eSource
             system. The use of nutritional supplements during this time that are not believed to
             have the potential to affect subject safety nor the overall results of the study, may
             be permitted on a case-by-case basis following approval by the Sponsor in consultation
             with the Investigator.

         12. Any surgical or medical condition possibly affecting drug absorption (e.g.
             cholecystectomy, gastrectomy, bowel disease), distribution, metabolism or excretion.

         13. Any history of gallbladder disease, including cholecystitis and/or cholelithiasis.

         14. History of megaloblastic anaemia or folate deficiency.

         15. Personnel (e.g. investigator, sub-investigator, research assistant, pharmacist, study
             coordinator or anyone mentioned in the delegation log) directly involved in the
             conduct of the study.

         16. Any condition that in the opinion of the investigator would jeopardize the safety or
             rights of a person participating in the trial or would render the person unable to
             comply with the protocol.

             Exclusion Criteria - CHMI specific:

         17. Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency (due to possible hemolysis induced
             by primaquine treatment at study end in G6PD deficient subjects).

         18. Personal history of malaria.

         19. Volunteer has travelled to or lived in a malaria-endemic area for more than 4 weeks
             during the 12 months prior to first IMP administration, or spent any time in an
             endemic area during the 4 weeks prior to first IMP administration.

         20. Plans to travel to malaria-endemic region during the study period up to last follow-up
             visit.

         21. Previous participation in any malaria vaccine or CHMI study.

         22. Falling in moderate or higher risk category for a fatal or non-fatal cardiovascular
             event within 10 years (≥5%) determined by a validated risk estimation system e.g.
             SCORE [13].

         23. Use of medications known to interact with atovaquone-proguanil (Malarone®),
             artemether-lumefantrine (Riamet®) or primaquine (Primaquine®) such as cimetidine,
             metoclopramide or antacids, or an anticipated requirement for the use of these at any
             point during the study period (see Section 6.2).

         24. Use of systemic antibiotics with known antimalarial activity within 30 days (or 5
             half-lives whichever is longer) of first IMP administration (e.g.
             trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole, doxycycline, tetracycline, clindamycin, erythromycin,
             fluoroquinolones or azithromycin) or an anticipated requirement for the use of these
             during the study period (see Section 6.2).

         25. Receipt of blood or blood-derived products (including immunoglobulin) within 3 months
             prior to screening. Receipt of packed red blood cells given for an emergent indication
             in an otherwise healthy person, and not required as ongoing treatment is not
             exclusionary (for example packed red blood cells emergently given during an elective
             surgery).

        Note: In case of an out-of-range clinical laboratory test, vital sign or ECG value that
        will determine a subject's eligibility, or in case of a positive drug screen, a retest or
        expert evaluation can be requested. Results of any retest must be available prior to
        inoculation. The result of the retest will be considered for subject eligibility at the
        investigator's discretion. Subjects can be rescreened at the discretion of the
        investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cristina Donini, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MMV</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pieter-Jan Berghmans, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>SGS Belgium NV</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SGS Belgium NV Clinical Pharmacology Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerpen</city>
        <zip>2060</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>PfSPZ Challenge</keyword>
  <keyword>chemoprotection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 11, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>February 24, 2020</returned>
    <submitted>February 27, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>March 11, 2020</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

