<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03707782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-0337</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03707782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanisms of Immune Deficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanisms of Immune Deficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Colorado Clinical &amp; Translational Sciences Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. The purpose of this study is to learn more about the changes in genes, cells and
           proteins that cause immune deficiency diseases.

        2. The early stages of the study will focus on two groups of patients:

             1. members of families in which several persons have symptoms or medical histories
                that suggest immune deficiency.

             2. Patients who have received treatments with medications or drugs that affect
                functions of the immune system (secondary immune deficiencies).

      It is hoped that studies will provide guidelines for extension of the research to other
      patient groups. Up to 200 patients and family members will be invited to participate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The experiments that are proposed in this portion of the study are intended to:

        1. characterize the significance of the variant form of EZH2 identified in this family.
           They will characterize the degree of methylation of lysine 27 of histone H3 in subjects
           with the variant and members of the same family who have the wild type gene. The
           functional methyltransferase activity of the variant and wild type genes will be
           measured.

        2. characterize the current status of B-cell maturation and function in subjects with
           either the variant gene and the wild type gene.

        3. characterize B-cell function (antibody production) and the quality of antibody produced
           after immunizations in subjects with the wild type gene or the variant gene.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Family-Based</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of Serum immune globulin</measure>
    <time_frame>each year for up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>The clinical definition of &quot;hypogamma-globulinemia is values that are 2 SD below the mean value for the testing laboratory. For this study values that are below the lower limit of abnormal will be scored as abnormal. Chi-square analysis or Fisher's exact test will compare values between subjects with the wild type gene and the variant gene.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody responses</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A four-fold difference or a post-immunization titer of ≥1.3 µg/ml is scored as a true antibody response. Antibody titers and avidity indices are transformed to log2 and evaluated using the Student's T-test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of NK cell function</measure>
    <time_frame>one time</time_frame>
    <description>Spearman correlation will be used to compare the relationship between expression of CD207a by NK cells that are activated with K562 cells or NK cells that are activated with PMA/iono.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DNA sequencing</measure>
    <time_frame>one time</time_frame>
    <description>When indicated, whole exome or whole genome sequencing will be done to identify genetic basis (if any) of the immune deficiency</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>measurement of cellular components of the immune system</measure>
    <time_frame>each year for up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>Flow cytometry will be used to identify numbers of cells of various types (e.g.,subpopulations of B-cells and T-cells) to evaluate changes in various cell populations over time. This is especially important for studies of family members who carry disease-causing or disease-associated genes but are clinically health at the time of the first study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>health outcome measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>each year for up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 form will be used serially to identify changes in health over time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of avidity</measure>
    <time_frame>each year for up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>avidity indices are transformed to log2 and evaluated using the Student's T-test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with immune deficiencies</arm_group_label>
    <description>aged 18 years or older and have an immune deficiency</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Family members</arm_group_label>
    <description>aged 18 years or older and are related to a person who has an immune deficiency</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood lymphocytes, serum and plasma other tissue if availale
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals aged 18 years or older and have an immune deficiency or are related to a person
        who has an immune deficiency.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Immunodeficiency disease; or

          2. family member of individual with immunodeficiency disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Persons with immune deficiencies that are secondary to other diseases such as
             malignancies.

          2. Persons who do not have immune deficiencies, persons who are not meet eligibility
             criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Charles Kirkpatrick</last_name>
    <phone>(303) 724-7197</phone>
    <email>charles.kirkpatrick@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UColorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles H Kirkpatrick, MD</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-7197</phone>
      <email>charles.kirkparick@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonilla FA, Khan DA, Ballas ZK, Chinen J, Frank MM, Hsu JT, Keller M, Kobrynski LJ, Komarow HD, Mazer B, Nelson RP Jr, Orange JS, Routes JM, Shearer WT, Sorensen RU, Verbsky JW, Bernstein DI, Blessing-Moore J, Lang D, Nicklas RA, Oppenheimer J, Portnoy JM, Randolph CR, Schuller D, Spector SL, Tilles S, Wallace D; Joint Task Force on Practice Parameters, representing the American Academy of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology; the American College of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology; and the Joint Council of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology. Practice parameter for the diagnosis and management of primary immunodeficiency. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2015 Nov;136(5):1186-205.e1-78. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2015.04.049. Epub 2015 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26371839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Meara MM, Simon JA. Inner workings and regulatory inputs that control Polycomb repressive complex 2. Chromosoma. 2012 Jun;121(3):221-34. doi: 10.1007/s00412-012-0361-1. Epub 2012 Feb 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22349693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Su IH, Basavaraj A, Krutchinsky AN, Hobert O, Ullrich A, Chait BT, Tarakhovsky A. Ezh2 controls B cell development through histone H3 methylation and Igh rearrangement. Nat Immunol. 2003 Feb;4(2):124-31. Epub 2002 Dec 23.</citation>
    <PMID>12496962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caganova M, Carrisi C, Varano G, Mainoldi F, Zanardi F, Germain PL, George L, Alberghini F, Ferrarini L, Talukder AK, Ponzoni M, Testa G, Nojima T, Doglioni C, Kitamura D, Toellner KM, Su IH, Casola S. Germinal center dysregulation by histone methyltransferase EZH2 promotes lymphomagenesis. J Clin Invest. 2013 Dec;123(12):5009-22. doi: 10.1172/JCI70626. Epub 2013 Nov 8. Erratum in: J Clin Invest. 2014 Apr 1;124(4):1869.</citation>
    <PMID>24200695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bödör C, Grossmann V, Popov N, Okosun J, O'Riain C, Tan K, Marzec J, Araf S, Wang J, Lee AM, Clear A, Montoto S, Matthews J, Iqbal S, Rajnai H, Rosenwald A, Ott G, Campo E, Rimsza LM, Smeland EB, Chan WC, Braziel RM, Staudt LM, Wright G, Lister TA, Elemento O, Hills R, Gribben JG, Chelala C, Matolcsy A, Kohlmann A, Haferlach T, Gascoyne RD, Fitzgibbon J. EZH2 mutations are frequent and represent an early event in follicular lymphoma. Blood. 2013 Oct 31;122(18):3165-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-04-496893. Epub 2013 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24052547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

