<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04188938</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pneumothorax</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04188938</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Occult Pneumothorax in Patients With Blunt or Penetrating Trauma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Occult Pneumothorax in Patients With Blunt or Penetrating Trauma: A Descriptive, Cross-sectional Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European University of Lefke</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European University of Lefke</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pneumothorax is a common life-threatening complication, frequently seen in patients who have
      been admitted to the emergency department and intensive care unit. This study aimed to
      describe the features of patients with pneumothorax due to blunt or penetrating trauma. A
      total of 615 patients admitted to the emergency department between January 2008 and December
      2010 due to multi-trauma, and underwent both chest x-ray and computed chest tomography were
      included in the study. There were 157 patients with a diagnosis of pneumothorax. Fifty-five
      of them were excluded because of the eligible criteria. The final study population included
      105 patients. The computed chest tomography reading was considered as the gold standard for
      the occult pneumothorax diagnosis. Data on patient characteristics, trauma types, accompanied
      traumas, etiology of the chest trauma, and chest x-ray, and computed chest tomography results
      were recorded.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thoracic injuries are the third most common cause of trauma-related morbidity/mortality and
      hospitalization after heart disease and malignancies. At least 25% of blunt traumatic deaths
      are a direct consequence of chest trauma. Additionally, rib fracture and pneumothorax are the
      first two most frequent blunt thoracic traumas, respectively.

      Pneumothorax (PTX) is a common life-threatening complication and frequently seen in patients
      who have been admitted to the Emergency Department (ED) and Intense Care Units (ICU). Some
      traumatic PTXs are clinically and radiologically silent, not identified during the initial
      assessment and cannot be visible on supine chest x-ray (CXR), but later diagnosed by computed
      tomography (CT). This type of PTX is called occult pneumothorax (OPTX) and has been found in
      30-55% of chest trauma cases. The clinical diagnosis of PTX is incorrect in approximately 30%
      of all traumatic cases. Besides, it has been stated that PTX has the potential to elevate the
      mortality rate in patients with trauma if it is not quickly managed.

      On the other hand, small or medium undetected PTX usually is not life-threatening. However,
      delays in the diagnosis and management may result in a rapid progression of OPTX to tension
      PTX and lead to severe dyspnea and even death. Therefore, early detection is crucial and may
      influence the evaluation and management of PTX and probably be a lifesaving action.

      The initial diagnostic screening test of PTX is usually CXR. However, studies reported that
      CXR is an insensitive and unreliable test. When the chest x-ray of the patient is acquired in
      a supine position, even if all of the symptoms related to pneumothorax are present (since the
      air is not located at the apical pulmonary region), there may not be an image consistent with
      PTX. For this reason, although CXR is usually used for many thoracic injuries as a screening
      test, it may miss the diagnosis of some thoracic injuries, including rib fractures, pulmonary
      contusions, and OPTX.

      On the other hand, the role of CT in the assessment of chest injuries has expanded
      considerably in the management of both blunt and penetrating traumas. The increasing use of
      CT in the evaluation and management of patients with chest trauma has led to correct and
      sensitive identification of undetected injuries, including OPTX.

      There are limited, but conflicting data about the ideal management type of OPTX in blunt
      trauma. Some physicians prefer the insertion of a tube thoracostomy (TT) for all OPTX
      patients, while others favor close observation without chest drainage. Physicians who prefer
      to insert a TT claim that an untreated OPTX can rapidly evolve into a tension PTX with
      catastrophic consequences. However, those who favor close observation without TT claim that
      patients should not be subjected to unnecessary invasive processes.

      This study aimed to identify the incidence of OPTX in patients with blunt or penetrating
      trauma.

      This study is a single-center (Emergency Department of Ankara Training and Research Hospital)
      retrospective analysis of trauma registry data. All consecutive participants over the age of
      16 who were admitted to the ED between the 1st of January 2008 and 31st of December 2010 due
      to multi-trauma, consulted by a thoracic surgeon and underwent both CXR and CT were included
      in the study. Files of 615 patients who were admitted to ED with a thoracic trauma were
      reviewed (2008; n=187, 2009; n=168, and 2010; n=260). Patients who had no simultaneous CXR+CT
      or no pathology in their CT were excluded (n=458). Also, patients not referred to a chest
      surgeon, and those referred to some other hospital were excluded (n=52). Data for the
      remaining 105 patients were analyzed. The CT interpretation was considered as the gold
      standard for the PTX diagnosis. Electronic medical records were then searched for patient
      characteristics (age and gender), trauma types (blunt or penetrating), accompanied traumas
      (intra-cerebral and intra-abdominal systems), etiology of the chest trauma (traffic
      accidents, falls, other), and CXR and CT results. Additionally, the intervention types
      (thoracostomy tube insertion, thoracentesis, no intervention) during the early phase of the
      management were recorded. All chest x-rays were performed on the supine position based on the
      trauma protocol of the hospital. Cases missed by the CXR but identified in the CT were
      defined as OPTX. Using the web-based Java applet developed by Russ Lenth
      (https://homepage.divms.uiowa.edu/~rlenth/Power/), a post hoc sample size calculation was
      performed based on a 7% expected prevalence of OPTX. Given an infinite population and a
      margin of error of 5%, a sample size of 100 cases is required to estimate OPTX in the study
      population with a confidence interval of 95%. Statistical analysis was performed with the
      Statistical Package for the Social Sciences version 22 (SPSS, IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). The
      'number (n),' 'percentage (%),' 'mean,' and 'standard deviation (SD)' was given for the
      descriptive statistics. Pearson Chi-Square or Fisher's exact tests used to compare
      categorical data. Age between groups was analyzed using the Mann-Whitney U test. Logistic
      regression analysis was applied to check for independent factors affecting the presence of
      OPTX. The results were evaluated with a confidence interval of 95%, and the level of
      significance, p, was set at &lt;0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 19, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occult Pneumothorax in Patients with Blunt or Penetrating Thoracic Trauma</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Registry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Pneumothorax; Acute</condition>
  <condition>Trauma Chest</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Occult pneumothorax in trauma patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Age&gt;16, multi-trauma, consulted thoracic surgeon, underwent CXR- CT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evaluation of occult pneumothorax in who had a blunt or penetrating chest trauma</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Occult pneumothorax in trauma patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Trauma</other_name>
    <other_name>Pneumothorax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All consecutive participants over the age of 16 who were admitted to the ED between the 1st
        of January 2008 and 31st of December 2010 due to multi-trauma, consulted by a thoracic
        surgeon and underwent both CXR and CT were included in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        &gt;16 years of age consulted by a thoracic surgeon had a multi-trauma underwent both chest x
        ray and computed tomography

        Exclusion Criteria:

        &lt;16 years of age not consulted by a thoracic surgeon did not have a multi-trauma did not
        undergo both chest x ray and computed tomography
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Semra Aslay, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>European University of Lefke</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wilson H, Ellsmere J, Tallon J, Kirkpatrick A. Occult pneumothorax in the blunt trauma patient: tube thoracostomy or observation? Injury. 2009 Sep;40(9):928-31. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2009.04.005. Epub 2009 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19539280</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Soldati G, Testa A, Sher S, Pignataro G, La Sala M, Silveri NG. Occult traumatic pneumothorax: diagnostic accuracy of lung ultrasonography in the emergency department. Chest. 2008 Jan;133(1):204-11. Epub 2007 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17925411</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kunitake RC, Kornblith LZ, Cohen MJ, Callcut RA. Trauma Early Mortality Prediction Tool (TEMPT) for assessing 28-day mortality. Trauma Surg Acute Care Open. 2018 Jan 8;3(1):e000131. doi: 10.1136/tsaco-2017-000131. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29766125</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ding W, Shen Y, Yang J, He X, Zhang M. Diagnosis of pneumothorax by radiography and ultrasonography: a meta-analysis. Chest. 2011 Oct;140(4):859-866. doi: 10.1378/chest.10-2946. Epub 2011 May 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21546439</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ball CG, Kirkpatrick AW, Laupland KB, Fox DL, Litvinchuk S, Dyer DM, Anderson IB, Hameed SM, Kortbeek JB, Mulloy R. Factors related to the failure of radiographic recognition of occult posttraumatic pneumothoraces. Am J Surg. 2005 May;189(5):541-6; discussion 546.</citation>
    <PMID>15862493</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chan YH, Zeng YZ, Wu HC, Wu MC, Sun HM. Effective Pneumothorax Detection for Chest X-Ray Images Using Local Binary Pattern and Support Vector Machine. J Healthc Eng. 2018 Apr 3;2018:2908517. doi: 10.1155/2018/2908517. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29849996</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Holmes JF, Brant WE, Bogren HG, London KL, Kuppermann N. Prevalence and importance of pneumothoraces visualized on abdominal computed tomographic scan in children with blunt trauma. J Trauma. 2001 Mar;50(3):516-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11265032</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee LK, Rogers AJ, Ehrlich PF, Kwok M, Sokolove PE, Blumberg S, Kooistra J, Olsen CS, Wootton-Gorges S, Cooper A, Kuppermann N, Holmes JF; Pediatric Emergency Care Applied Research Network (PECARN). Occult pneumothoraces in children with blunt torso trauma. Acad Emerg Med. 2014 Apr;21(4):440-8. doi: 10.1111/acem.12344.</citation>
    <PMID>24730407</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Akoglu H, Akoglu EU, Evman S, Akoglu T, Denizbasi A, Guneysel O, Onur O, Onur E. Utility of cervical spinal and abdominal computed tomography in diagnosing occult pneumothorax in patients with blunt trauma: Computed tomographic imaging protocol matters. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2012 Oct;73(4):874-9. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e3182569ff2.</citation>
    <PMID>22835995</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Plurad D, Green D, Demetriades D, Rhee P. The increasing use of chest computed tomography for trauma: is it being overutilized? J Trauma. 2007 Mar;62(3):631-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17414339</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Enderson BL, Abdalla R, Frame SB, Casey MT, Gould H, Maull KI. Tube thoracostomy for occult pneumothorax: a prospective randomized study of its use. J Trauma. 1993 Nov;35(5):726-9; discussion 729-30.</citation>
    <PMID>8230337</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ouellet JF, Trottier V, Kmet L, Rizoli S, Laupland K, Ball CG, Sirois M, Kirkpatrick AW. The OPTICC trial: a multi-institutional study of occult pneumothoraces in critical care. Am J Surg. 2009 May;197(5):581-6. doi: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2008.12.007.</citation>
    <PMID>19306978</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ball CG, Kirkpatrick AW, Feliciano DV. The occult pneumothorax: what have we learned? Can J Surg. 2009 Oct;52(5):E173-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19865549</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matsumoto S, Kishikawa M, Hayakawa K, Narumi A, Matsunami K, Kitano M. A method to detect occult pneumothorax with chest radiography. Ann Emerg Med. 2011 Apr;57(4):378-81. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2010.08.012. Epub 2010 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20864214</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ball CG, Kirkpatrick AW, Fox DL, Laupland KB, Louis LJ, Andrews GD, Dunlop MP, Kortbeek JB, Nicolaou S. Are occult pneumothoraces truly occult or simply missed? J Trauma. 2006 Feb;60(2):294-8 discussion 298-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16508485</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Guerrero-López F, Vázquez-Mata G, Alcázar-Romero PP, Fernández-Mondéjar E, Aguayo-Hoyos E, Linde-Valverde CM. Evaluation of the utility of computed tomography in the initial assessment of the critical care patient with chest trauma. Crit Care Med. 2000 May;28(5):1370-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10834680</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kirkpatrick AW, Sirois M, Laupland KB, Liu D, Rowan K, Ball CG, Hameed SM, Brown R, Simons R, Dulchavsky SA, Hamiilton DR, Nicolaou S. Hand-held thoracic sonography for detecting post-traumatic pneumothoraces: the Extended Focused Assessment with Sonography for Trauma (EFAST). J Trauma. 2004 Aug;57(2):288-95.</citation>
    <PMID>15345974</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matsumoto S, Sekine K, Funabiki T, Orita T, Shimizu M, Hayashida K, Kazamaki T, Suzuki T, Kishikawa M, Yamazaki M, Kitano M. Diagnostic accuracy of oblique chest radiograph for occult pneumothorax: comparison with ultrasonography. World J Emerg Surg. 2016 Jan 13;11:5. doi: 10.1186/s13017-016-0061-x. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>26766962</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Neff MA, Monk JS Jr, Peters K, Nikhilesh A. Detection of occult pneumothoraces on abdominal computed tomographic scans in trauma patients. J Trauma. 2000 Aug;49(2):281-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10963540</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rowan KR, Kirkpatrick AW, Liu D, Forkheim KE, Mayo JR, Nicolaou S. Traumatic pneumothorax detection with thoracic US: correlation with chest radiography and CT--initial experience. Radiology. 2002 Oct;225(1):210-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12355007</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Misthos P, Kakaris S, Sepsas E, Athanassiadi K, Skottis I. A prospective analysis of occult pneumothorax, delayed pneumothorax and delayed hemothorax after minor blunt thoracic trauma. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2004 May;25(5):859-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15082295</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moore FO, Goslar PW, Coimbra R, Velmahos G, Brown CV, Coopwood TB Jr, Lottenberg L, Phelan HA, Bruns BR, Sherck JP, Norwood SH, Barnes SL, Matthews MR, Hoff WS, de Moya MA, Bansal V, Hu CK, Karmy-Jones RC, Vinces F, Pembaur K, Notrica DM, Haan JM. Blunt traumatic occult pneumothorax: is observation safe?--results of a prospective, AAST multicenter study. J Trauma. 2011 May;70(5):1019-23; discussion 1023-5. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318213f727.</citation>
    <PMID>21610419</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Patel BH, Lew CO, Dall T, Anderson CL, Rodriguez R, Langdorf MI. Chest tube output, duration, and length of stay are similar for pneumothorax and hemothorax seen only on computed tomography vs. chest radiograph. Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg. 2019 Aug 5. doi: 10.1007/s00068-019-01198-y. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>31384999</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tam MM. Occult pneumothorax in trauma patients: should this be sought in the focused assessment with sonography for trauma examination? Emerg Med Australas. 2005 Oct-Dec;17(5-6):488-93.</citation>
    <PMID>16302942</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barry R, Thompson E. Outcomes after rib fractures in geriatric blunt trauma patients. Am J Surg. 2018 Jun;215(6):1020-1023. doi: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2018.03.011. Epub 2018 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>29548528</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang S, Netterwald J, Wang W, Zhu H. Characterization of the elements and proteins responsible for interferon-stimulated gene induction by human cytomegalovirus. J Virol. 2005 Apr;79(8):5027-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15795288</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Adolfsson E, Wesolowska P, Izewska J, Lund E, Tedgren ÅC. END-TO-END AUDIT: COMPARISON OF TLD AND LITHIUM FORMATE EPR DOSIMETRY. Radiat Prot Dosimetry. 2019 Dec 31;186(1):119-122. doi: 10.1093/rpd/ncy289.</citation>
    <PMID>30929009</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>European University of Lefke</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Semra Aslay</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ass. Prof. (M.D.)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>Thorax</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency</keyword>
  <keyword>Pneumothorax</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumothorax</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All collected individual participating data</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>After published there is no ending time frame</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>All consecutive participants over the age of 16 who were admitted to the ED between the 1st of January 2008 and 31st of December 2010 due to multi-trauma, consulted by a thoracic surgeon and underwent both CXR and CT were included in the study.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

