<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04181996</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB # - 20190355-01H CRRF:1443</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04181996</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Canadian Study of Arterial Inflammation in Patients With Diabetes and Vascular Events: EvaluatioN of Colchicine</brief_title>
  <acronym>CADENCE</acronym>
  <official_title>The Canadian Study of Arterial Inflammation in Patients With Diabetes and Recent Vascular Events: EvaluatioN of Colchicine Effectiveness (CADENCE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular Disease (CVD) is a leading cause of death in the developed world.
      Atherosclerosis causes plaques in the blood vessels and is a common form of CVD. Inflammation
      is now recognized as a major cause of atherosclerosis. Therapies that target inflammation are
      being examined as a potential treatment option. Imaging to detect inflammation may be a
      solution to understand mechanisms and to optimize patient selection and outcomes for these
      drugs. Fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) PET imaging can detect inflammation in the plaque and
      identify patients vulnerable to plaque rupture which cause events such as myocardial
      infarctions (MI) and strokes. The primary objective of this proposal(CADENCE) is to determine
      if the drug colchicine has an effect on plaque inflammation in patients at high risk for
      events (patients with diabetes or pre-diabetes and recent myocardial infarction, stroke or
      transient ischemic attacks (TIAs)). This mechanistic and proof-of-concept study will set the
      stage for future studies that will determine if inflammation imaging can be integrated into
      clinical practice to personalize decisions for anti-inflammation therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inflammation is a key to atherosclerosis and its serious effects (MI, stroke) and represents
      a potentially transformative therapeutic target. Several recent trials have revealed
      potential outcome benefit in patients with cardiovascular disease who are treated with
      anti-inflammatory therapy. The LoDoCo trial showed a reduction in cardiovascular events in
      patients with known coronary artery disease who were treated with colchicine (1). Although
      the LoDoCo trial did show outcome benefit, and in fact reduced the number of acute coronary
      syndromes in the treatment group, colchicine's mechanism of action at the level of the
      atherosclerotic plaque in patients remains unknown. The COLCOT trial was recently published
      which further demonstrated the potential benefit of anti-inflammatory therapy with
      colchicine. Compared with placebo, colchicine significantly reduced the risk of
      cardiovascular events for patients who recently experienced a myocardial infarction (2). It
      is not clear at the present time whether colchicine mainly reduces the systemic inflammatory
      milieu, thus reducing the likelihood of plaque progression and new lesion formation; or
      whether it has a direct effect on local &quot;hot&quot; inflammatory cell activity, thus pacifying the
      inflammatory plaque to reduce events. Insight into colchicine's mechanism of action may help
      identify the most suitable patients for this novel approach.

      Inflammation imaging may represent a solution. 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) PET-CT imaging
      can define plaque inflammation and identify patients and plaques vulnerable to rupture and
      events. Improved FDG uptake occurs with therapies that effectively reduced vascular events
      but not with therapies with no outcome benefit. It is provocative to consider inflammation
      imaging strategies that may positively impact therapy decisions to yield better patient
      selection and outcomes.

      The long term goal of this research is to determine the pathobiological effect of colchicine
      on plaque inflammation and determine if inflammation imaging can be integrated into clinical
      assessment to personalize decisions for anti-inflammation therapies. As the first step for
      this goal, the investigators propose The CADENCE study is the first step towards this goal;
      it is a mechanistic and proof-of-concept study that will be the basis for a future 2nd phase
      definitive RCT integrating inflammation imaging and biomarker strategies.

      The Primary Objective is to determine colchicine's effect on plaque inflammation in the
      carotids and thoracic aorta using FDG PET in patients with diabetes (T2DM) or pre-diabetes
      and recent vascular events (ACS/MI, TIA, stroke).

      Secondary Objectives include defining if baseline inflammation imaging or biomarkers predict
      the inflammation response.

      Exploratory Objectives will define differences in response to colchicine: i) in patients with
      coronary versus cerebral events; ii) in different vascular beds; iii) relationships of
      inflammation imaging to other biomarkers.

      Methods:

      In CADENCE patients with T2DM or pre-diabetes and a recent NonSTEMI, STEMI, stroke or TIA
      will be recruited to one of 2 arms: colchicine 0.6 mg daily; or placebo. At baseline and 6
      months: patients will have FDG PET-CT of carotids and aorta; at 0, 3 and 6 months: clinical
      evaluation and blood sampling for inflammation biomarkers (eg hsCRP, IL-6, IL-1β, TNF-α,
      MCP-1). The primary endpoint will be the change in inflammation over 6 months measured as FDG
      tissue to blood ratio (TBR).

      Expected Outcomes:

      It is expected that colchicine will reduce arterial inflammation measured using FDG PET/CT
      and reduce biomarkers of systemic inflammation. This would validate that colchicine's
      mechanism of action is more than a systemic effect but also a local action at the level of
      the vessel wall and plaque. This would further identify arterial inflammation on imaging as a
      potential novel therapeutic target for those at high risk of CV events. Such proof-of-concept
      data would support a definitive RCT to evaluate and define the potential for new
      biomarker-imaging strategies to direct decisions for novel anti-inflammation therapies in
      this population.

      Current therapies focus on lesion stenosis or ischemia with conflicting results. Use of
      inflammation imaging to direct proven treatments would be a bold practice-changing paradigm
      shift.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double-Blind Placebo controlled trial</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6 month change in FDG uptake TBR (Tissue to Blood Ratio) in the MDS (Maxiumum Disease Segment)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint will be the change over 6 months in the FDG uptake TBR (Tissue-to-blood ratio) as a marker of arterial plaque inflammation in the maximum disease segment (MDS)(the segment with the highest TBR at baseline) in any vasculature imaged whether it be left or right carotid or aorta.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 month change in FDG uptake TBR (Tissue to Blood Ratio) in the MDS of each vascular region: aorta, left and right carotid.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>6 month change in FDG uptake TBR (Tissue to Blood Ratio) in the MDS of each vascular region: aorta, left and right carotid.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 month change in FDG uptake SUV (standard uptake value) in the MDS of each vascular region: aorta, left and right carotid.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>6 month change in FDG uptake SUV (standard uptake value) in the MDS of each vascular region: aorta, left and right carotid.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of high-sensitivity C-Reactive Protein (hs-CRP) (mg/ml) and its change</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of high-sensitivity C-Reactive Protein (hs-CRP) (mg/ml) and its change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of Interleukin-6 (IL-6) (pg/ml) and its change.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of Interleukin-6 (IL-6) (pg/ml) and its change.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory outcomes - Plasma levels of cytokines (pg/ml)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma levels of other cytokines (pg/ml)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory outcomes - Levels of activated monocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of activated monocytes</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory outcomes - plasma levels of inflammation biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma levels of inflammation biomarkers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory outcomes - MACE</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>MACE (multiple adverse CV events (ACS/MI, TIA, stroke, CV death))</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory outcomes - non CV death</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>non-cardiovascular death</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">115</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo: Sugar pill manufactured to mimic colchicine 0.6 mg capsule. Placebo to be taken once a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colchicine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Colchicine: 0.6 mg colchicine capsule to be taken once a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colchicine Oral Product</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to receive either placebo or colchicine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Colchicine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Patents will be randomized to receive either placebo or colchicine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients who have:

          1. Type 2 Diabetes (on diet, oral hypo-glycemic agents and/or insulin) or pre-diabetes
             (defined by Diabetes Canada as HbA1C=6.0-6.45% or increased fasting blood sugar (FBS)
             (6.1-6.9 mmol/L) or impaired glucose tolerance);

          2. suffered a recent cardiovascular event (30-90 days post ACS (i.e. STEMI or nonSTEMI)
             or TIA/stroke with ipsilateral large vessel atherosclerotic disease confirmed on US,
             CT or MRI;

          3. stable symptoms and hemodynamics;

          4. age ≥18 years;

          5. given informed consent. Standard definitions will be used for STEMI, NSTEMI, and for
             ischemic stroke confirmed by CT or MRI and TIA confirmed by a neurologist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who have

          1. planned revascularization of infarct or stroke related artery;

          2. severe uncontrolled diabetes (FBS &gt;11.1 mmol/L or HbA1C &gt;9.0% who require aggressive
             diabetes management);

          3. a recent CV event likely to have been embolic in the opinion of the neurologist or
             cardiologist;

          4. severe LV dysfunction (EF&lt;30%);

          5. severe valve disease requiring intervention;

          6. decompensated heart failure;

          7. active infection;

          8. immune compromise (e.g. recurrent infection; chronic inflammatory bowel disease;
             systemic anti-inflammatory therapy; past cancer);

          9. pregnancy or breastfeeding;

         10. unable to give informed consent;

         11. contrast allergy (will not have CTA but may have PET/CT without CTA);

         12. glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &lt;50 ml/min/1.72m2

         13. Use of p-glycoprotein inhibitor (e.g. cyclosporine, verapamil, or quinidine) or a
             strong CYP3A4 inhibitor (e.g. ritonavir, clarithromycin, or ketoconazole);

         14. Hemoglobin &lt; 105(women) &lt;110 (men) g/L; WBC &lt; 3.0x 10(9)/L, platelet count&lt; 110x
             10(9)/L;

         15. Patient with a history of cirrhosis, chronic active hepatitis or severe hepatic
             disease or with alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels greater than 3 times the upper
             limit of normal.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rob S Beanlands, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Linda M Garrard, BScN</last_name>
    <phone>613-696-7000</phone>
    <phone_ext>14192</phone_ext>
    <email>lgarrard@ottawaheart.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alison D James, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>613-696-7000</phone>
    <phone_ext>10313</phone_ext>
    <email>ajames@ottawaheart.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Linda M Garrard, BScN</last_name>
      <phone>613-696-7000</phone>
      <phone_ext>14192</phone_ext>
      <email>lgarrard@ottawaheart.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alison D James, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>613-696-7000</phone>
      <phone_ext>10313</phone_ext>
      <email>ajames@ottawaheart.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rob S Beanlands, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nidorf SM, Eikelboom JW, Budgeon CA, Thompson PL. Low-dose colchicine for secondary prevention of cardiovascular disease. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Jan 29;61(4):404-410. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2012.10.027. Epub 2012 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23265346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tardif JC, Kouz S, Waters DD, Bertrand OF, Diaz R, Maggioni AP, Pinto FJ, Ibrahim R, Gamra H, Kiwan GS, Berry C, López-Sendón J, Ostadal P, Koenig W, Angoulvant D, Grégoire JC, Lavoie MA, Dubé MP, Rhainds D, Provencher M, Blondeau L, Orfanos A, L'Allier PL, Guertin MC, Roubille F. Efficacy and Safety of Low-Dose Colchicine after Myocardial Infarction. N Engl J Med. 2019 Dec 26;381(26):2497-2505. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1912388. Epub 2019 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>31733140</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Imaging, PET, inflammation, Biomarkers, Colchicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arteritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colchicine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

