<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04182802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STH20679</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04182802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MRI and Lung Function Measures of Benralizumab Response in Asthma</brief_title>
  <acronym>MR BEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Using Benralizumab to Explore Treatment Response Patterns in Functional Lung MRI and Advanced Measures of Lung Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sheffield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Dundee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      New treatments have been developed for asthma that are good at preventing asthma attacks and
      improving day-to-day symptoms. Alongside the development of these new drugs, there are new
      ways of measuring how the lung is affected by asthma. In particular, investigators have
      developed ways of seeing how air moves in the lungs of people with asthma, using MRI
      scanning. This study aims to see how quickly these new drugs result in changes in the way the
      lung is working, as seen in the MRI scans and other breathing tests. This will help
      clinicians in the future to decide who is likely to respond to these new medicines, and once
      patients have started taking the drugs, will help clinicians to decide whether long term
      treatment is likely to benefit the people receiving them.

      In this study, the investigators plan to do extra breathing tests and MRI scans on people who
      are receiving the drug as part of their usual clinical care. The study will not change an
      individual's treatment, but will give the investigators more information about the patients'
      illnesses and the way the patients' bodies respond to treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in percentage ventilated lung volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of lung volume assessed by magnetic resonance imaging</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>eosinophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This is a pragmatic, cohort feasibility study, the primary aim of which is to determine
        which parameters of functional and structural lung MRI change over what time course after
        the introduction of a anti-eosinophil strategy in people with eosinophilic asthma.

        At present, the first-line licensed choice for anti-eosinophil therapies is mepolizumab,
        which has been shown to be effective at reducing exacerbations of asthma. Mepolizumab is
        given every 4 weeks. Benralizumab has two possible advantages over mepolizumab: swifter
        onset, and less frequent administration (it is given 4 weekly for the first three
        injections, then 8 weekly). People who would be eligible for either therapy will be offered
        a choice of participating in this clinical study or receiving mepolizumab through standard
        NHS pathways.

        Candidate patients will be identified in severe asthma clinics at Sheffield Teaching
        Hospitals and through the associated clinics at Rotherham, Doncaster, Barnsley and
        Chesterfield.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  People with eosinophilic asthma meeting the National Institute for Health and Clinical
             Excellence (NICE) criteria for benralizumab therapy based on eosinophil count and
             exacerbation rates will be offered the chance to participate in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any medical illness that in the opinion of the investigator is likely to significantly
             impact on the response to benralizumab or the outcome of the MRI and lung function
             testing.

          -  Non-concordance with routine asthma therapies (this would be assessed as a mandatory
             part of NICE-based criteria).

          -  Any additional significant lung illness that would impact on likelihood of response to
             benralizumab. Of note, trivial stable bronchiectasis that in the opinion of the
             patient's clinician is not clinically significant nor likely to result in either
             recurrent exacerbations or impairment of interpretation of investigation results will
             not be exclusion criteria. Part of the initial inclusion regarding eligibility by NICE
             criteria include an assessment of a likely eosinophilic asthmatic phenotype with
             probability of treatment response, and potential subjects with complex lung disease
             would be unlikely to be eligible.

          -  Current cigarette smoking, or cigarette smoking within the past 6 months

          -  Significant lifetime smoking history of ≥20 pack years

          -  Previous use of another biologic therapy targeting eosinophils within 6 months of
             enrollment

          -  Pregnancy, planning pregnancy, or breast feeding. Women of childbearing potential must
             use effective contraception (concordant use of hormonal contraceptive, intrauterine
             device, total abstinence), and urine pregnancy tests will be performed before scans.

          -  Abnormal renal function (eGFR &lt;30), to avoid risks from Gadolinium chelate MRI
             contrast agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa Watson, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01142265424</phone>
    <email>lisa.watson24@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

