<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04186156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABC-11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04186156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Selective HDAC6 Inhibition With KA2507 in Advanced Biliary Tract Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Selective HDAC6 Inhibition With KA2507 in Advanced Biliary Tract Cancer Previously Treated With Standard of Care Chemotherapy (ABC-11)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karus Therapeutics Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karus Therapeutics Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the preliminary efficacy of KA2507 (an orally active potent and selective HDAC6
      inhibitor) in patients with advanced biliary tract cancer (BTC) previously treated with
      standard of care chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy of KA2507 (an orally active potent and selective HDAC6 inhibitor) in
      patients with advanced biliary tract cancer (BTC) previously treated with standard of care
      chemotherapy.

      ABC-11 is an open-label, multi-centre study of HDAC6 inhibition using KA2507 in patients with
      advanced biliary tract cancer previously treated with standard of care chemotherapy.

      This is a single-arm single-stage phase II study designed using A'Hern's methodology.

      The primary objective of this study is to assess the preliminary efficacy of KA2507 in
      patients with advanced BTC previously treated with standard of care chemotherapy

      A fixed daily dose of KA2507 (800mg BID) will be administered to all patients based on a
      phase I study, KTP-003.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients alive and progression free at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients alive and progression free at 4 months (objective disease progression as per RECIST 1.1)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate tumour response to KA2507 (response rates and duration of response)</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect of KA2507 on overall response rate according to RECIST Version 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to death after study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterise the safety and tolerability profile of KA2507</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events [CTCAE] Version 5.0)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterise the pharmacokinetic profile of KA2507 in a subset of patients</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <description>KA2507 plasma pharmacokinetic parameters in plasma from up to six patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the pharmacodynamic response to KA2507</measure>
    <time_frame>26 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evidence of selective HDAC6 target engagement inferred through measurement of acetylated tubulin and acetylated histone in peripheral blood T cells from up to six patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Biliary Tract Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>KA2507 (HDAC6 inhibitor)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single arm dose escalating study. Patients will be treated with open label KA2507 (HDAC6 inhibitor) capsules.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KA2507</intervention_name>
    <description>KA2507, an orally-active new chemical entity, is a potent and selective inhibitor of the HDAC6 enzyme, with potential clinical utility in the treatment of melanoma and other solid tumors. KA2507 has been shown to display potent in vitro activity in a range of cancer cell lines, including melanoma cell lines. KA2507 exerts potent in vivo efficacy in a syngeneic model of B16 melanoma. Here, the combination of the agent's direct tumor growth inhibition and metastasis suppression, coupled with its immunotherapeutic activity - demonstrated by decreased expression of STAT-3 and PD-L1 and increased expression of acetylated tubulin, gp100 and MHC Class I in tumors - have been observed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>KA2507 (HDAC6 inhibitor)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HDAC6 Inhibitor</other_name>
    <other_name>HDAC6i</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Histological or cytological diagnosis of advanced (i.e. metastatic disease, or
             irresectable locally advanced, or recurrent) biliary tract cancer (to include intra or
             extra hepatic and gall bladder; ampullary cancer will not be included).

          -  Patient must have disease amenable to biopsy at baseline and consent to pre-treatment
             biopsy

          -  Clear evidence of disease progression following standard of care first line therapy
             with at least 1 measurable lesion using CT/MRI as defined by RECIST 1.1, OR clear
             evidence of disease progression based on the emergence of non-measurable disease (e.g.
             new cytologically confirmed ascites, pleural or pericardial effusion)

          -  Previous treatment with any line of chemotherapy for advanced disease (e.g. currently
             gemcitabine/cisplatin) OR radiotherapy

          -  ECOG performance status grade 0-1

          -  Adequate biliary drainage, with no evidence of ongoing infection

          -  Estimated life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          -  Patients intolerant of first-line standard of care chemotherapy will also be eligible
             provided there is evidence of disease progression

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unresolved or unstable serious toxic side-effects of prior chemotherapy or
             radiotherapy, i.e. ≥ grade 2 per CTCAE (common terminology criteria for adverse
             events, v5.0) except fatigue, alopecia and infertility

          -  Clinical evidence of cerebral metastases

          -  History of previous malignancy that could interfere with response evaluation

          -  Concurrent treatment with other investigational drugs within 4 weeks of initiating
             treatment

          -  Inadequate renal, liver, or haematological function defined as any of:

               -  eGFR &lt; 45 ml/min/1.73 m2 using the CKD-EPI (Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology
                  Collaboration) formula

               -  ALT and/or AST &gt; 5 x ULN

               -  Neutropenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1.5 x 109/L)

               -  Platelets &lt;100 x 109/L

               -  Haemoglobin ≤ 9 g/dL). NB the use of transfusion to achieve desired Hb is
                  acceptable

               -  Total bilirubin ≥ 1.5 x ULN (except for patients with known Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Known haemoglobinopathy due to HbS or HbC disease, α or β thalassemia, or
             Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency

          -  Concomitant use of dapsone

          -  Untreated severe hypothyroidism

          -  Significant heart disease defined as any of the following:

               -  NYHA grade 3 or 4 symptomatic heart failure

               -  Unstable angina or acute myocardial infarction within 3 months

               -  cardiac ventricular arrhythmia within 3 months that is not controlled by drug
                  therapy and/or by cardiac ablation

               -  QTcF &gt; 470 ms on screening ECG or history of Torsades de pointes

          -  Any other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical or surgical condition which,
             in the view of the investigator, could compromise the patient's participation in the
             study

          -  Patients with active hepatitis infection (defined as having a positive hepatitis B
             surface antigen [HBsAg] test at screening) or hepatitis C. Patients with past
             hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection or resolved HBV infection (defined as having a
             negative HBsAg test and a positive antibody to hepatitis B core antigen [anti-HBc]
             antibody test) are eligible. Patients positive for hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody
             are eligible only if polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is negative for HCV RNA

          -  Active infection requiring antibiotics within two weeks prior to treatment

          -  Males who are unable to or refuse to use barrier contraception during treatment and
             for 3 months after

          -  Women who are pregnant, breast-feeding or either unable to or refuse to use effective
             means of contraception during treatment

          -  Patients who are unable to swallow capsules and/or have a surgical or anatomical
             condition that precludes swallowing and absorbing oral medication on an ongoing basis

          -  Any other condition that would, in the investigator's judgement, contraindicate the
             patient's participation in the clinical study due to safety concerns or compliance
             with clinical study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Bridgewater</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Research UK &amp; UCL Cancer Trials Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Research UK and UCL Cancer Trials Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W1T 4TJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Biliary Tract Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

