<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04188379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ARGX-113-1801</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-002100-41</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04188379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Efgartigimod in Adult Patients With Primary Immune Thrombocytopenia (ITP).</brief_title>
  <acronym>ADVANCE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Efgartigimod (ARGX 113) 10 mg/kg Intravenous in Adult Patients With Primary Immune Thrombocytopenia (ITP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>argenx BVBA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>argenx BVBA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled multicenter phase 3 trial to evaluate
      the efficacy and safety of ARGX-113 in patients with primary ITP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 6, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of efgartigimod compared to placebo in achieving a sustained platelet count response in patients with chronic primary ITP, sustained platelet count response = platelet counts of at least 50×109/L for at least 4/6 visits between week 19 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five weeks (between visits 19 and 24)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative weeks over the planned 24-week treatment period with platelet counts of at least 50x10^9/L in the chronic ITP population</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks (treatment period)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients in the overall population (chronic and persistent ITP) with a sustained platelet count response defined as achieving platelet counts of at least 50 x 10^9/L for at least 4 of the 6 visits between visit 19 and 24 of the trial.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five weeks (between visits 19 and 24)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of the WHO-classified bleeding events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 31 weeks, at each visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients in the overall population achieving platelet counts of at least 50 x 10^9/L for at least 6 of the 8 visits between week 17 and 24 of the trial.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks (between visits 17 and 24)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Immune Thrombocytopenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>efgartigimod</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient receiving efgartigimod</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>efgartigimod</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous infusion of efgartigimod</description>
    <arm_group_label>efgartigimod</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ARGX-113</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous infusion of placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Ability to understand the requirements of the trial, to provide written informed
             consent (including consent for the use and disclosure of research-related health
             information), and to comply with the trial protocol procedures (including required
             trial visits).

          2. Male or female patient aged ≥18 years.

          3. Confirmed ITP diagnosis, at least 3 months before randomization and according to the
             American Society of Hematology Criteria, and no known other etiology for
             thrombocytopenia.

          4. Diagnosis supported by a response to a prior ITP therapy (other than thrombopoietin
             receptor agonists (TPO-RAs)), in the opinion of the investigator.

          5. Mean platelet count of &lt;30×109/L (and no single platelet count of &gt;35×109/L) from 3
             qualifying counts, 2 during the screening period and the predose platelet count at
             visit 1. The 3 platelet counts must be over the course of 7 to 14 days, with at least
             2 days between any 2 counts.

          6. At the start of the trial, the patient is either on concurrent ITP treatment(s) and
             has received at least 1 prior therapy for ITP in the past, or the patient is not on
             treatment for ITP but has received at least 2 prior treatments for ITP. Patients
             receiving permitted concurrent ITP treatment(s) at baseline, must have been stable in
             dose and frequency for at least 4 weeks prior to randomization. Permitted concurrent
             ITP medications include oral corticosteroids, oral immunosuppressants,
             dapsone/danazol, fostamatinib, and/or oral TPO-RAs.

             Patients not receiving concurrent ITP therapy are also eligible for the trial if they
             have not received prior ITP therapy for at least 4 weeks prior to baseline, and 6
             months in case of prior ITP therapy with an anti-CD20 therapy (eg, rituximab).

          7. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at the
             screening visit and a negative urine pregnancy test at baseline before trial
             medication (infusion) can be administered. Women are considered of childbearing
             potential unless they are post-menopausal (defined by continuous amenorrhea) for at
             least 1 year with a follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) of &gt;40 IU/L or are surgically
             sterilized (ie, women who had a hysterectomy, both ovaries surgically removed, or have
             a documented permanent female sterilization procedure including tubal ligation).
             Follicle-stimulating hormone can be used to confirm postmenopausal status in
             amenorrheic patients not on hormonal replacement therapy.

          8. Women of childbearing potential should use a highly effective method of contraception
             (ie, pregnancy rate of less than 1% per year) during the trial and for 90 days after
             the last administration of the IMP. They must be on a stable regimen, for at least 1
             month:

             combined (estrogen and progestogen containing) hormonal contraception associated with
             inhibition of ovulation

               -  oral

               -  intravaginal

               -  transdermal progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of
                  ovulation:

               -  oral

               -  injectable

               -  implantable intrauterine device (IUD) intrauterine hormone-releasing system
                  bilateral tubal occlusion vasectomized partner (provided that the partner is the
                  sole sexual partner of the trial participant and documented aspermia post
                  procedure) continuous abstinence from heterosexual sexual contact. Sexual
                  abstinence is only allowable if it is the preferred and usual lifestyle of the
                  patient. Periodic abstinence (calendar, symptothermal, post-ovulation methods) is
                  not acceptable.

          9. Non-sterilized male patients who are sexually active with a female partner of
             childbearing potential must use effective double contraception, being a condom for
             male patients and a highly effective form of contraception for the female partner of
             childbearing potential (same as for female patients described in inclusion criterion
             8). Male patients practicing true sexual abstinence (when this is in line with the
             preferred and usual lifestyle of the participant) can be included.

        Sterilized male patients who have had vasectomy with documented aspermia post procedure can
        be included. In addition, male patients are not allowed to donate sperm during this period
        from signing of ICF, throughout the duration of the trial, and for 90 days after the last
        administration of IMP.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. ITP/thrombocytopenia associated with another condition, eg, lymphoma, chronic
             lymphocytic leukemia, viral infection, hepatitis, induced or alloimmune
             thrombocytopenia, or thrombocytopenia associated with myeloid dysplasia.

          2. Use of anticoagulants (eg, vitamin K antagonists, direct oral anticoagulants) within 4
             weeks prior to randomization.

          3. Use of any transfusions within 4 weeks prior to randomization.

          4. Use of Ig (IV, subcutaneous, or intramuscular route) or plasmapheresis (PLEX), 4 weeks
             prior to randomization.

          5. Use of anti-CD20 therapy (eg, rituximab) within 6 months prior to randomization.

          6. Use of romiplostim within 4 weeks prior to randomization.

          7. Undergone splenectomy less than 4 weeks prior to randomization.

          8. Use of any other investigational drug within 3 months or 5 half-lives of the drug
             (whichever is longer) prior to randomization.

          9. Use of monoclonal antibodies or crystallized fragment (Fc) fusion proteins, other than
             those previously indicated, within 3 months prior to randomization.

         10. At the screening visit, clinically significant laboratory abnormalities as below:

             Hemoglobin ≤9 g/dL.

               -  OR - International normalized ratio &gt;1.5 or activated partial thromboplastin time
                  &gt;1.5×ULN.

               -  OR - Total IgG level &lt;6 g/L.

         11. Patients who have a history of malignancy, including malignant thymoma, or
             myeloproliferative or lymphoproliferative disorders, unless deemed cured by adequate
             treatment with no evidence of recurrence for ≥3 years before screening. Patients with
             completely excised non-melanoma skin cancer (such as basal cell carcinoma or squamous
             cell carcinoma) or cervical carcinoma in situ would be permitted at any time.

         12. Uncontrolled hypertension, defined as a repeated elevated blood pressure exceeding 160
             mmHg (systolic) and/or 100 mmHg (diastolic) despite appropriate treatments.

         13. History of any major thrombotic or embolic event (eg, myocardial infarction, stroke,
             pulmonary embolism, deep venous thrombosis) within 12 months prior to randomization.

         14. History of coagulopathy or hereditary thrombocytopenia or a family history of
             thrombocytopenia.

         15. History of a recent or planned major surgery (that involves major organs eg, brain,
             heart, lung, liver, bladder, or gastrointestinal tract) within 4 weeks of
             randomization.

         16. Patients with known serum-positivity or who test positive for an active viral
             infection at screening with: Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) (except patients who are anti-HBs
             Ab positive because of HBV vaccination), Hepatitis C Virus, HIV.

         17. Clinical evidence of significant unstable or uncontrolled acute or chronic diseases
             other than ITP (eg, cardiovascular, pulmonary, hematologic, gastrointestinal,
             endocrine, hepatic, renal, neurological, malignancy, infectious diseases, uncontrolled
             diabetes) despite appropriate treatments which could put the patient at undue risk.

         18. Patients with known medical history of hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients of
             the IMP.

         19. Patients who previously participated in a clinical trial with efgartigimod.

         20. Pregnant or lactating females.

         21. Employees of the investigator or trial center, with direct involvement in the proposed
             trial or other trials under the direction of that investigator or trial center, as
             well as family of the employees or the investigator.

         22. Patients who received a live-attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks before randomization.
             The receipt of any inactivated, sub-unit, polysaccharide, or conjugate vaccine at any
             time prior to randomization is not considered an exclusion criterion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 857-350-4834</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 4</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85711</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ocala</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34474</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 3</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quincy</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>62301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 5</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Wayne</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46804</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 28</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 8</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yvoir</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 29</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Mans</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 20</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 21</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 22</name>
      <address>
        <city>Debrecen</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 9</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nyiregyhaza</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 34</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ravenna</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 23</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reggio Calabria</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 35</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rimini</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 33</name>
      <address>
        <city>Siena</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 30</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hirakata</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 24</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hiroshima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 12</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iruma</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 11</name>
      <address>
        <city>Isehara</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 31</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kashiwa</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 16</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maebashi</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 15</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minato-Ku</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 10</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sapporo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 13</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shibukawa</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 32</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shimotsuke</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 6</name>
      <address>
        <city>Den Haag</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 7</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 25</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chorzów</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 18</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaluga</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 17</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ufa</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 27</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 36</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 26</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 37</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 39</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 14</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma De Mallorca</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator Site 38</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <phone_ext>+1</phone_ext>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigator site 19</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mykolayiv</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Guglietta, MD</last_name>
      <phone>857-350-4834</phone>
      <email>clinicaltrials@argenx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.argenxitpstudy.com</url>
    <description>Website for patients</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic, Idiopathic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

