<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04181775</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060.PHA.2019.A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04181775</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of an ADE-related Hospitalization Risk Prediction Tool for Patients (ADE-RED)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of an ADE-related Hospitalization Risk Prediction Tool for Patients Discharged From the Emergency Department (ADE-RED)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Methodist Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Methodist Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rationale for this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of a risk prediction tool for
      patients who are at high risk for ADEs resulting in hospitalization or ED revisit. The
      ADE-RED score initiates a PLMR that literature has shown reduces medication discrepancies and
      ADEs at hospital admission and discharge. No current system identifies patients presenting to
      the ED that may benefit from PMLR independent of an admission disposition. The ADE-RED
      scoring tool will reduce the incidence of future visits to the ED or future admissions by
      identifying patients who are at high risk for ADE-related readmissions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There has been considerable attention placed on adverse drug events (ADEs) and their effects
      on readmission rates worldwide. Several studies have tried to identify the drugs most
      commonly responsible for ADEs, high-risk patient populations, and the causes of these ADEs.
      Some of the causes that have been postulated include the aging population, increasing number
      of drugs on the market, and a troubling upward trend in polypharmacy. The reported rates of
      ADE-related hospitalizations have varied from study to study. Kongkaew et al. estimated
      around 5% of all hospital admissions are the result of an adverse drug reaction (ADR), which
      is a subtype of ADEs. Meanwhile, Shehab et al. estimated approximately 27.3% of emergency
      department (ED) visits for ADEs result in hospitalization.

      Unfortunately, practitioners may exacerbate the problem by prescribing additional
      pharmacotherapy for conditions caused by an unrecognized ADE. Such circumstances can lead to
      additional cost and harm to patients. However, pharmacists are uniquely qualified to
      recognize and address potential ADEs through pharmacist-led medication reconciliation (PLMR).
      PLMR is the process in which a pharmacist produces an accurate list of medications a patient
      is taking and compares that list against the patient's documented admission, transfer, and/or
      discharge orders. Several years of education and training to learn the pharmacokinetic and
      pharmacokinetic characteristics of a wide variety of medications, as well as any potential
      side effects, have given pharmacists the skills to detect, assess, and understand ADEs. Many
      institutions have implemented PLMRs within specific hospital units, such as the ED, in an
      effort to increase cost savings to the patient and the health care institution.

      A meta-analysis of patients with preventable ADEs found that as much as 52% of ADEs, present
      at the time of hospitalization or an emergency visit, were preventable (8). This highlights
      the need to produce a tool to predict patients at risk for ADE-related hospitalizations.
      There have been several ADE risk prediction initiatives developed to identify high risk
      patients (9-17). Many of these risk prediction tools, such as the Prediction of
      Hospitalization due to ADRs in Elderly Community-Dwelling Patients (PADR-EC) score and the
      Brighton Adverse Drug Reactions Risk (BADRI) model, focused on older patients, hospitalized
      patients, or both. A focus on prediction tools in older adults is reasonable due to
      ADE-related hospitalization rates among adults 65 years or older, being seven times higher
      than adults younger than 65 years old (6). However, there is limited information in risk
      scoring tools for the general public who present to the ED and are at high risk of an ADE. In
      2017, a Transitions of Care pharmacy resident at Methodist Dallas Medical Center (MDMC)
      developed a risk scoring tool to help identify patients in the ED who were at high risk for
      an ADE-related hospitalization. The scoring tool, which was named the ADE-RED score, took
      into account the patient's age, presence of polypharmacy, specific high- risk medications,
      number of previous ED visits, comorbidities, and the reason for their current visit. A score
      of 12 or more alerted ED pharmacists to perform a PLMR and to make necessary interventions
      and recommendations to medical staff. Therefore the ADE-RED program has the opportunity to
      fill a gap in the care for patients who may be hospitalized or return to the ED due to a
      preventable ADE.

      This study will be conducted to determine whether the ADE-RED score can reduce the incidence
      of ADE- related readmissions compared to the incidence of such readmissions as observed from
      sister facilities within the Methodist Health System (MHS) and to determine whether the
      ADE-RED score can predict patients at risk of readmission.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidences of ADE-related readmission within 30 days of prior ED visit.</measure>
    <time_frame>one month period in March 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Incidences of ADE-related readmission within 30 days of prior ED visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients who were readmitted who did or did not have an ADE-RED score at initial ED visit.</measure>
    <time_frame>one month period in March 2019</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients who were readmitted who did or did not have an ADE-RED score at initial ED visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Drug Event</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADE-RED scoring tool</intervention_name>
    <description>The ADE-RED scoring tool will reduce the incidence of future visits to the ED or future admissions by identifying patients who are at high risk for ADE-related readmissions.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients are considered high risk if the score is &gt; 12, moderate risk if the score 6-11,
        and low risk if the score is 0-5. High-risk patients are flagged in the electronic medical
        record of the patient, alerting the pharmacist to complete a medication reconciliation and
        address any issues.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients admitted to the hospital with a prior ED visit within the previous 30 days

          -  Patients presenting to the ED with a prior ED visit within the previous 30 days

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients without PTA medications at the time of initial ED presentation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ilka Ratsaphangthong, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Methodist Dallas Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Crystee Cooper, DHEd</last_name>
    <phone>214-947-1280</phone>
    <email>CrysteeCooper@mhd.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jordania L Lilly, MEd</last_name>
    <phone>214-947-1280</phone>
    <email>JordaniaLilly@mhd.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Crystee Cooper, DHed</last_name>
      <phone>214-947-1280</phone>
      <email>CrysteeCooper@mhd.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jordania L Lilly, MEd</last_name>
      <phone>214-947-1280</phone>
      <email>JordaniaLilly@mhd.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Drug-Related Side Effects and Adverse Reactions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

