<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04187534</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-1143</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04187534</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Critical Care OptimizatIon of Albumin Ordering</brief_title>
  <acronym>RATIONALE</acronym>
  <official_title>Critical Care Optimization of Albumin Ordering</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Strong evidence suggests that human albumin solutions should not be used for fluid
      resuscitation except among patients undergoing therapeutic plasmapheresis and select patients
      with complications of liver cirrhosis (i.e. spontaneous bacterial peritonitis, or large
      volume ascitic fluid removal). Previous work by the investigators reported albumin use
      outside these circumstances as a quality improvement opportunity in Alberta ICUs. In 2017,
      the investigators began a pilot initiative to reduce albumin overuse in 6 ICUs in Alberta.
      The intervention was developed according to the Theoretical Domains Framework, and consisted
      of establishing a clinical champion, educating clinicians, changing the process for albumin
      ordering (albumin-specific order sheet), and providing quarterly audit/feedback data to
      clinicians on albumin utilization. During the intervention, there was a 41% relative
      reduction in albumin utilization. However, follow-up data identified problems with
      sustainability. These sustainability challenges combined with data suggesting high albumin
      use in other ICUs throughout Alberta have led the current project to build on the pilot
      initiative to reduce albumin overuse within all adult ICUs in Alberta.

      The proposed quality improvement intervention will be implemented in 16 adult ICUs using a
      registry-based, stepped-wedge implementation design that will lean heavily on existing
      Provincial healthcare infrastructure. The intervention was developed using the Theoretical
      Domains Framework, and tailored to the unique features of each participating ICU. It will be
      implemented at the level of ICU. Clusters of 2 ICUs will be assigned to receive the
      intervention every month such that all ICUs in Alberta will receive the intervention by the
      end of the implementation period. To evaluate the quality improvement initiative, eCritical
      will serve as a 'registry' and will be used to capture all clinical and outcome data. The
      primary outcome will be the proportion of ICU admissions without an evidence-based indication
      for albumin, prescribed at least 1 unit of albumin (any concentration) during admission to
      ICU. 'Evidence-based indication' will be operationally defined as receipt of therapeutic
      plasmapheresis OR having a diagnosis of liver cirrhosis and being in receipt of a
      paracentesis. This latter criterion enables identification of patients with spontaneous
      bacterial peritonitis or large volume ascitic fluid removal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Strong evidence suggests that human albumin solutions should not be used for
      fluid resuscitation except among patients undergoing therapeutic plasmapheresis and select
      patients with complications of liver cirrhosis (i.e. spontaneous bacterial peritonitis, or
      large volume ascitic fluid removal). Previous work by the investigators reported overuse of
      albumin fluid resuscitation as a stakeholder-identified quality improvement opportunity in
      Alberta ICUs. Audit data from the provincial electronic medical record (EMR) for critical
      care, eCritical, reinforced stakeholder opinion and demonstrated that within Alberta ICUs in
      2016 a considerable amount of albumin use deviated from evidence-based indications. On
      average, 14% of admissions to adult ICUs received at least one albumin unit during their ICU
      admission, with several high-use units providing albumin to between 20% and 35% of
      admissions. In 2017 the investigators began a pilot quality improvement initiative to reduce
      albumin overuse in six ICUs in Alberta. The intervention was developed according to the
      Theoretical Domains Framework. Questionnaires completed by clinicians working in the target
      ICU identified local culture and opinion of clinical leaders as barriers, and education,
      order sets, and clinical champions as facilitators to reducing albumin use. The intervention
      thus consisted of establishing a clinical champion, educating clinicians, changing the
      process for albumin through development of an albumin order sheet, and providing quarterly
      unit-level audit/feedback data to clinicians on albumin utilization. There was a 41%
      reduction in albumin utilization, however follow-up data identified problems with
      sustainability. The current project will build on the pilot initiative to implement a quality
      improvement intervention to reduce albumin overuse within all adult ICUs in Alberta.

      OBJECTIVE: Evaluate albumin reduction within all adult ICUs in Alberta.

      METHODS: This will be a registry-based, stepped-wedge quality improvement initiative.

      Quality Improvement Initiative: Spread to 16 adult ICUs in Alberta will require understanding
      and adapting the investigators pilot intervention to local barriers and facilitators. The
      intervention for this quality improvement initiative will be developed using the Theoretical
      Domains Framework. The research team will develop working groups responsible for tailoring
      the intervention and implementation strategy to each participating ICU. This will be
      conducted as part of the Province-wide quality improvement initiative. The investigators will
      conduct the quality improvement initiative using a registry-based, stepped-wedge,
      implementation trial. Owing to the nature of this design, the interventions will be
      implemented at the level of ICU. Clusters of 2 ICUs will be assigned to receive the
      intervention every month such that all ICUs in Alberta will receive the intervention by the
      end of the implementation period.

      Registry-based data analysis: To evaluate this quality improvement initiative, the Provincial
      EMR for critical care, eCritical, will serve as a 'registry' and will be used to capture all
      clinical and outcome data. Data will be collected until patient death or hospital discharge
      and censored at 60 days. To optimize efficiency and power, data will be collected 3-months
      before and after implementation of the interventions.

      SETTING: 16 adult ICUs in Alberta's critical care strategic clinical network reflecting
      teaching/non-teaching and urban/rural hospitals will participate.

      STUDY POPULATION: All adult patients (&gt;18 years) admitted to the study ICUs during the study
      period (November 2019 to January 2021). Study ICUs will include 14 general medical-surgical
      ICUs, and 2 cardiovascular surgery ICUs.

      OUTCOMES: The primary outcome of this study will be the proportion of ICU patients without an
      evidence-based indication for albumin prescribed at least 1 unit of albumin (any
      concentration) during admission to ICU. Evidence-based indication will be operationally
      defined as receipt of therapeutic plasmapheresis OR having a diagnosis of liver cirrhosis and
      being in receipt of a paracentesis. This latter criterion enables identification of patients
      with either spontaneous bacterial peritonitis or large volume ascitic fluid removal. This
      outcome was selected because: 1) there is precedent within current literature; 2) previous
      experience auditing albumin utilization in Alberta ICUs demonstrate it is available through
      eCritical; 3) it provides a relevant, broadly understandable estimate of the effect of the
      implementation science intervention to change albumin overuse; and 4) it permits assessment
      of the feasibility of implementing the platform to develop and carry out multi-stakeholder
      implementation science interventions to promote evidence-informed clinical practices and
      evaluate the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 21, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 21, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Registry-based, stepped-wedge, implementation trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of ICU admissions receiving albumin</measure>
    <time_frame>During ICU admission</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of ICU admissions without an evidence-based indication for albumin prescribed at least 1 unit of albumin (any concentration) during admission to ICU</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean number of albumin units among those receiving albumin</measure>
    <time_frame>During ICU admission</time_frame>
    <description>Mean number of albumin units prescribed to patients without an evidence-based indication for albumin that received at least 1 unit of albumin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total fluid administration</measure>
    <time_frame>ICU day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Total volume of fluid administered during days 1-7 in ICU</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total crystalloid fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>ICU Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Total volume of crystalloid fluid administered during days 1-7 in ICU</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of vasopressor administration</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of ICU admission to date of discharge, on average 1-6 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days vasopressors administered during ICU length of stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>From date mechanical ventilation commended to date discontinued, on average 0-3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days on mechanical ventilation from time of starting mechanical ventilation during ICU length of stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of ICU admission to date of discharge, on average 1-6 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days admitted to ICU (unique number per admission)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of hospital admission to date of discharge, on average 5-20 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days admitted to hospital (unique number per admission)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of ICU admission to date of discharge, on average 1-6 days</time_frame>
    <description>Survival to discharge from ICU</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of hospital admission to date of discharge, on average 5-20 days</time_frame>
    <description>Survival to discharge from hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8000</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Albumin Fluid Resuscitation Optimization Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Our quality improvement intervention seeking to improve appropriate use and reduce inappropriate use of albumin for fluid resuscitation will consist of establishing a clinical champion, educating clinicians, changing the process for albumin ordering through development of an albumin order sheet, and providing quarterly unit-level audit/feedback data to clinicians on albumin utilization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stepped-wedge roll out of 'Albumin Fluid Resuscitation Optimization Intervention' will permit those ICUs wherein intervention has not yet been implemented to serve as controls. These ICUs will prescribe albumin according to usual practice and not be exposed to any components of the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albumin Fluid Resuscitation Optimization Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Multi-faceted quality improvement intervention to optimize appropriateness of albumin use for fluid resuscitation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Albumin Fluid Resuscitation Optimization Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Practice</intervention_name>
    <description>Albumin fluid resuscitation according to usual practice</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All adult patients admitted to the study ICUs

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel J Niven, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peter Lougheed Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T1Y 6J4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foothills Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 2T9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rockyview General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2V 1P9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Health Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T3M 1M4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mazankowski Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T4N 4E7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T5H 3V9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Misericordia Community Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T5R 4H5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grey Nun's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6L 5X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northern Lights Regional Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort McMurray</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T9H 1P2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth II Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grande Prairie</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T8V 2E8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chinook Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lethbridge</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T1J 1W5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medicine Hat Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medicine Hat</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T1A 4H6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Red Deer Regional Hospital Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Red Deer</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T4N 4E7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sturgeon Community Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Albert</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T8N 6C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sauro K, Bagshaw SM, Niven D, Soo A, Brundin-Mather R, Parsons Leigh J, Cook DJ, Stelfox HT. Barriers and facilitators to adopting high value practices and de-adopting low value practices in Canadian intensive care units: a multimethod study. BMJ Open. 2019 Mar 15;9(3):e024159. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2018-024159.</citation>
    <PMID>30878979</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Calgary</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Niven</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Albumin</keyword>
  <keyword>fluid resuscitation</keyword>
  <keyword>de-adoption</keyword>
  <keyword>de-implementation</keyword>
  <keyword>low-value care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

