<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04183595</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Emera008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04183595</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study of NBMI Treatment in Patients With Mercury Toxicity</brief_title>
  <acronym>NBMI-Hg-COL</acronym>
  <official_title>A Double-blinded, Randomized Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of N1, N3-bis-(2-Mercaptoethyl) Isophthalamide (NBMI) in the Reduction of Mercury Levels, in Subjects Exposed to Mercury in Atlántico, Colombia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EmeraMed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clínica De La Costa Ltda.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EmeraMed</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      NBMI (N1, N3-Bis-(2-Mercaptoethyl) Isophthalamide) is a new metal chelator drug proposed as
      an alternative to the current chelators, and it is widely different; compared to the current
      chelators, consisting of two cysteamine molecules coupled to a single molecule of
      dicarboxybenzoate. It is used as a chelating agent and has the designation of an orphan drug,
      in the EU and USA; in the EU it is used for the treatment of mercury toxicity. It is freely
      soluble in solutions of dimethylformamide (DMF), dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and sodium
      hydroxide diluted NaOH, slightly soluble in methanol and acetone, and insoluble in water.
      Pre-clinical data indicates low to no toxicity, and that it reduces the toxicity associated
      with acute exposure to Hg2+.

      No other chelator has been reported to prevent acute mercury toxicity with only one exposure
      to the chelator. It has the ability to penetrate cell membranes and cross the blood-brain
      barrier and chelate Hg2+ in a complex that eliminates the availability of Hg2+ and
      essentially eliminates toxic effects. The antioxidant properties of NBMI could also reduce
      the toxicity levels of hydroxyl free radicals immediately, upon entering cells suffering from
      oxidative stress. It is possible that the combined chelation of Hg2+ and the elimination of
      hydroxyl free radicals contribute significantly to the protective effects observed with the
      NBMI.

      Previous clinical studies conducted in subjects of the Phase I and Phase II a studies
      conducted, did not show significant adverse events in patients intoxicated with mercury, all
      patients who received the study medication have tolerated it well, with only mild or moderate
      adverse events reported; None of these were considered related to the pharmacological
      treatment of the study. In addition, there is no potential identified with safety problems in
      laboratory tests, or vital signs evaluations.

      The purpose of this Controlled Single-Center Double-Blind Crossover Clinical Trial Phase II b
      is to determine the efficacy, safety and tolerability of a 14 day 400mg / day of NBMI (N1,
      N2-bis-2-mercaptoethyl isophthalamide) Treatment, in the reduction of urinary mercury levels
      versus placebo, in accidentally exposed subjects to mercury in Atlántico, Colombia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Controlled Single-Center Double-Blind Crossover Clinical Trial Phase II b conducted
      in subjects with a history of chronic exposure to mercury in Puerto Colombia,

      Atlántico, and department of Atlántico:

      One hundred and sixteen patients (116) will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio, to either one of
      the two arms of this trial:

      This study will consist of 5 Phases / 5 Visits

        1. Screening

        2. Treatment Period A

        3. Washout Period / Follow-Up Period A

        4. Treatment Period B

        5. Follow-Up Period B.

      After Screening a computer-generated scrambling code will be used for allocation in blocks of
      4 to the two treatments. During enrollment, the proportion of subjects with or without a
      history of previous treatment by chelating will be monitored.

      The identity of patients included in the futility analysis will not be provided to the trial
      team, in order to preserve the blind aspect of the trial.

      The trial will be interrupted if the difference between the groups of treatment in the
      primary assessment is significantly (α = 0.05 unilateral) less than 10% in favor of any of
      the arms.

      A Data Monitoring Committee will be set up to monitor the safety and risk control general
      benefit. The committee's statistician and epidemiologist will carry out the evaluation.

      The identity of the research product associated with each randomization number will be kept
      hidden for the trial team and for the patients.

      The final analysis is planned for when 100% of the patients (116 patients) reach Day 56 of
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>One hundred and sixteen (116) participants will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio, to either one of the two arms of this trial.
This study will consist of 5 Phases / 5 Visits
Screening
Treatment Period A
Washout Period / Follow-Up Period A
Treatment Period B
Follow-Up Period B.
Once Period A is completed, there will be a 2 Weeks Washout Period and the patients will switch arms following a crossover approach.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The research center must assign an unblinded pharmacist or a designated person and a non-blinded CRO monitor, to monitor medication supply and other unblinded documentation of the study.
Masking through identical capsules and blister in the two arms of intervention.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the &quot;Change in the subject's urine mercury levels&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the difference in mercury levels in the urine as percentage of mercury concentration levels will be determined. The percentage is calculated by comparing baseline mercury concentration levels, against the levels observed at 14-day and 28-days follow-up visits. A rule of three is applied to determine the percentage (%) of change. The analysis of total Hg concentration will be done via Cold Vapor Atomic Absorption spectrometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the &quot;Change in the subject's blood iron levels&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the efficacy, the evaluation of the difference in blood iron levels as the percentages of iron concentration, will be calculated. Immunoturbidimetry Test will be used as an indicator of iron reserves to determine serum ferritin (FS) levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the &quot;Change in the subject's blood glucose levels&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To measure efficacy, the evaluation of the difference in blood glucose levels, as percentage of glucose concentration, will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the &quot;Change in the subject's renal function&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The difference in scores derived from the CKD-EPI Equation will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the &quot;Frequency and Severity of Adverse Events&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first dose of study medication until the Day 56 visit.</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and Severity of Adverse Events in the 14 day 400mg / day NBMI Treatment Group. Adverse Events will be encoded using the most recent version of the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure subject's &quot;Variations in Mental Response &quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The European Quality of Life 5 Dimensions 5 Levels (EQ-5D-5L) to evaluate quality of life is an instrument to assess the state of health in multiple dimensions. The questionnaire has five questions with Likert (descriptive system) and an analog visual scale (EQ-VAS). The descriptive system defines health in terms of 5 dimensions: mobility, self-care, habitual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/Depression. Each dimension has 5 response categories: no problem, mild problems, moderate problems, serious problems and extreme problems. The EQ-VAS marked 0 (worst state of health) -100 (best state of health). The combination of the score in each dimension calculates an index value EQus which is equivalent to the QALY (quality-adjusted life year) value. Thus EQus= 1 is equivalent to QALY = 1, that means a year lived with perfect health, an EQus &lt;1 is equivalent to a year lived with a lower level of health and EQus = 0 is equivalent to being dead.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure subject's &quot;Variations in General Clinical examination&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>A general physical examination of systems and organs will be conducted to determine whether there is or there is not a variation of health status (Yes/No scale). The organs and system that will be examined to determine a general health status are Head and Neck, Oral Cavity, Eyes, Ears, Nose, Cardiovascular System, Chest and Lungs, Abdomen, Skin, Lymphatic System, Neurological System, Renal System, Musculoskeletal System, Appearance).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure subject's &quot;Variations in Height&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>As part of general physical examination variations in participants height will be measured in centimeters comparing measurements in the three visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure subject's &quot;Variations in Weight&quot;.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>As part of general physical examination variations in participants weight will be measured in kilograms comparing measurements in the three visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mercury intoxication measured by Medical Intoxication Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the start of treatment, Fourteen (14) days after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The medical intoxication score (MIS) is a tool created to identify mercury poisoning in patients. It is a score of ten points that is evaluated by a medical examination, neuromotor tests and an anamnestic questionnaire evaluating 8 elements: 1. Excessive salivation 2. Tremor during work 3. Problems sleeping at night 4. Bluish discoloration of the gums 5. Ataxic gait 6. Dysdiadocokinesia 7. Heel and chin test 8. Proteinuria. Each can have an assigned value of 0 or 1, specific to whether the symptom is absent (0) or present (1) or if the test result is negative (0) or positive (1). The medical score of mercury poisoning is the sum of the values of the elements.
The worst case of worsening intoxication symptoms would be 10 and a healthy participant will get 0 score. Intoxication will be considered if score is 6 or greater than 6.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Amalgam</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Before) treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of amalgam through digital photos</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Diet</measure>
    <time_frame>The patients will keep a food diary during the study (days 1-56).</time_frame>
    <description>During the course of the protocol, all patients will be given a patient's food diary, in which data like type and amount of food intake is self-reported by participants.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">116</enrollment>
  <condition>Mercury Poisoning</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: NBMI (Study Medication)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>400mg / day N1, N3-BIS- (2-MERCAPTOETHYL) ISOPHTHALAMIDE (NBMI) treatment for 14 days, administered as two capsules of 100 mg of NBMI every 12 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>((Excipients microcrystalline cellulose, silica and magnesium stearate)) capsules will be administered every 12 hours for 14 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>(N1, N3-bis(2- mercaptoethyl)isophthalamide)</intervention_name>
    <description>400mg / day NBMI treatment for 14 days, administered as two capsules of 100 mg of NBMI every 12 hours, at the start of treatment, the principal investigator or his delegate will verify the intake of the first dose and deliver a blister pack corresponding to the remaining NBMI capsules, at visit # 3, research subjects will be asked to return the packaging with the remaining capsules or not, in order to estimate adherence to treatment.
The cross-treatment will be assigned using the same procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: NBMI (Study Medication)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NBMI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Excipients microcrystalline cellulose, silica and magnesium stearate</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules will be administered every 12 hours for 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of exposure to sources of mercury release by a known event of
             direct contact with metallic mercury in Puerto Colombia, Atlántico, and the department
             of Atlántico in Colombia.

          -  All subjects must have signed and dated an informed consent / assent consent form
             approved by the IRB in accordance with regulatory and institutional guidelines. This
             form must be obtained before performing any procedure related to the protocol that is
             not part of the subject's normal regimen.

          -  Under age minors must also have a psychological evaluation and documentation of Assent
             added to the Informed Consent Form.

          -  Patients with detectable urinary mercury levels &gt;5 ug / L at the time of screening.

          -  Patients must be willing and able to comply with clinic visits and all study-related
             procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A history of known or suspected hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reactions to the
             medication or test excipients. Patients with sulfa-drug sensitivity should be excluded
             from this study.

          -  Levels of mercury in urine / blood at the time of baseline measurement that are below
             detection threshold.

          -  Known history of drug addiction and / or alcoholism.

          -  Patients with a known medical condition that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             could increase the risk associated with participation in the study or with the
             administration of the study medication (s) under blinded conditions or interfere with
             the interpretation of the security results.

          -  Patients with major surgery or significant traumatic injury who have not recovered at
             least 14 days before the first dose of the study medications (s) under blind.

          -  Subjects with a condition requiring systemic corticosteroid therapy (&gt; 10 mg daily of
             prednisone equivalent) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14 days before or
             during treatment are excluded.

          -  Women with positive pregnancy test (urine sample) at the time of screening; or women
             who are breastfeeding, or are of childbearing age who disagree with taking
             contraceptives during treatment and until Day 28 after the last dose.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andres Cadena-Bonfanti, MD MS Esp</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinica de la Costa - Barranquilla, Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haley E Boyd, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+1-859-266-92 00 (01)</phone>
    <email>boyd.haley@emeramed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cordy P, Veiga MM, Salih I, Al-Saadi S, Console S, Garcia O, Mesa LA, Velásquez-López PC, Roeser M. Mercury contamination from artisanal gold mining in Antioquia, Colombia: The world's highest per capita mercury pollution. Sci Total Environ. 2011 Dec 1;410-411:154-60. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2011.09.006. Epub 2011 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22000915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erkek N, Senel S, Sarac A, Ertan U, Karacan CD. Being alive after a severe inorganic mercury intoxication. Eur J Pediatr. 2010 May;169(5):625-8. doi: 10.1007/s00431-009-1073-2. Epub 2009 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19802724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan F, Momtaz S, Abdollahi M. The relationship between mercury exposure and epigenetic alterations regarding human health, risk assessment and diagnostic strategies. J Trace Elem Med Biol. 2019 Mar;52:37-47. doi: 10.1016/j.jtemb.2018.11.006. Epub 2018 Nov 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30732897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeitz P, Orr MF, Kaye WE. Public health consequences of mercury spills: Hazardous Substances Emergency Events Surveillance system, 1993-1998. Environ Health Perspect. 2002 Feb;110(2):129-32.</citation>
    <PMID>11836139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schober SE, Sinks TH, Jones RL, Bolger PM, McDowell M, Osterloh J, Garrett ES, Canady RA, Dillon CF, Sun Y, Joseph CB, Mahaffey KR. Blood mercury levels in US children and women of childbearing age, 1999-2000. JAMA. 2003 Apr 2;289(13):1667-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12672735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park JD, Zheng W. Human exposure and health effects of inorganic and elemental mercury. J Prev Med Public Health. 2012 Nov;45(6):344-52. doi: 10.3961/jpmph.2012.45.6.344. Epub 2012 Nov 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23230464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ha E, Basu N, Bose-O'Reilly S, Dórea JG, McSorley E, Sakamoto M, Chan HM. Current progress on understanding the impact of mercury on human health. Environ Res. 2017 Jan;152:419-433. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2016.06.042. Epub 2016 Jul 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27444821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Branco V, Caito S, Farina M, Teixeira da Rocha J, Aschner M, Carvalho C. Biomarkers of mercury toxicity: Past, present, and future trends. J Toxicol Environ Health B Crit Rev. 2017;20(3):119-154. doi: 10.1080/10937404.2017.1289834. Epub 2017 Apr 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28379072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarkson TW, Magos L. The toxicology of mercury and its chemical compounds. Crit Rev Toxicol. 2006 Sep;36(8):609-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16973445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarke D, Buchanan R, Gupta N, Haley B. Amelioration of Acute Mercury Toxicity by a Novel, Non-Toxic Lipid Soluble Chelator N,N'bis-(2-mercaptoethyl)isophthalamide: Effect on Animal Survival, Health, Mercury Excretion and Organ Accumulation. Toxicol Environ Chem. 2012;94(3):616-640.</citation>
    <PMID>22573916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Risher JF, Amler SN. Mercury exposure: evaluation and intervention the inappropriate use of chelating agents in the diagnosis and treatment of putative mercury poisoning. Neurotoxicology. 2005 Aug;26(4):691-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16009427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>George GN, Prince RC, Gailer J, Buttigieg GA, Denton MB, Harris HH, Pickering IJ. Mercury binding to the chelation therapy agents DMSA and DMPS and the rational design of custom chelators for mercury. Chem Res Toxicol. 2004 Aug;17(8):999-1006.</citation>
    <PMID>15310232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bose-O'Reilly S, Bernaudat L, Siebert U, Roider G, Nowak D, Drasch G. Signs and symptoms of mercury-exposed gold miners. Int J Occup Med Environ Health. 2017 Mar 30;30(2):249-269. doi: 10.13075/ijomeh.1896.00715. Epub 2017 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28366955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doering S, Bose-O'Reilly S, Berger U. Essential Indicators Identifying Chronic Inorganic Mercury Intoxication: Pooled Analysis across Multiple Cross-Sectional Studies. PLoS One. 2016 Aug 30;11(8):e0160323. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0160323. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27575533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 3, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exposure to mercury</keyword>
  <keyword>NBMI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Poisoning</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mercury Poisoning</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

