<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04189107</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DexaCup</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04189107</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Postoperative Pain, Why Still in Hospital and DAOH Following TORS for SCCUP</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Investigation of Postoperative Pain, Why Still in Hospital and Days Alive and Out of Hospital Following Transoral Robotic Surgery for Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Candys Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Region Capital Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol investigates the effect of a high dose dexamethasone regimen in the treatment
      of postoperative pain following Transoral Robotic Surgery (TORS). The protocol consists of
      three substudies.

        1. Randomized double-blinded clinical trial assigning half of the participants to a
           high-dose dexamethasone regimen while the other half will receive a low-dose
           dexamethasone dosage and placebo in the first postoperative period.

        2. A investigation of &quot;Why in hospital?&quot; following TORS. From the first postoperative day
           until discharge reasons for continued hospitalization will be registered in order to
           identify clinical and organizational factors contributing to hospitalization

        3. An assessment of &quot;Days Alive and Out of Hospital&quot; following TORS. From the day of
           surgery and the first 12 postoperative months all admissions to a hospital ward will be
           registered along with admission reasons. Any death during the first 12 months will be
           noted with a cause of death.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The morbidity after TORS has not yet been fully investigated, but a recent studies suggest
      that pain is one of the primary causes for unplanned readmission This issue has been
      investigated by Clayburgh D et al who found that a prolonged dexamethasone regime lowered the
      pain scores on day three after surgery. The patients treated with the prolonged dexamethasone
      regime also showed a significant improvement in the food consistency they were capable to
      swallow and had a shortened length of stay (LOS). Recently, a pilot-study showed, that an
      intensified dexamethasone regime among TORS patients reduced the pain level to that of a
      standard tonsillectomy. Besides an analgesic effect glucocorticoids furthermore poses an
      anti-inflammatory quality which can be used to lower the physiological stress and
      inflammatory response following surgery and may prevent organ dysfunctions and complications
      The analgesic effect of dexamethasone has been the topic of many clinical studies, and are
      well described in various surgical fields. However, the optimal dose and regime for
      glucocorticoids prescription has so far not been established. The evidence favoring one
      dosage regime and an optimal prescribed dose is restricted by the variance in the regimes
      used in various clinical trials and the fact that there is a need for clinical trial
      investigating steroids with pain as the primary endpoint Consequently, it is important to
      thoroughly investigate and optimize the analgesic regime after TORS.

      Hospitalization So far when evaluating the long-term consequences of TORS, the main focus has
      been on oncological outcomes and quality of life with attention to functional outcomes, i.e.
      feeding tube dependency and dysphagia while the LOS following TORS and why the patient is
      hospitalized after the procedure have been sparsely studied.

      The reason why TORS patients are still hospitalized after the procedure and which clinical
      and organizational factors contribute to the hospitalization have not yet been examined and
      understood but is highly relevant in order to understand and improve the postoperative care.

      A method to assess the efficiency of a therapy have emerged from the cardiology field and is
      called Days Alive and Out of Hospital (DAOH). This has been used in investigations of heart
      failure patients and myocardial infarction patients. This outcome combines mortality and
      morbidity, and accounts for the number but also duration of several hospitalizations after
      the primary discharge.

      DAOH has only sparse been used in the surgical field, and only in few studies in the cardiac
      surgery area. The measurement is a patient-centered outcome that provide better information
      to the patient and surgeon when planning surgery, and can be used for quality improvement
      studies since it accounts for effective and efficient care.

      Therefore, the DAOH measurement applied to the evaluation of TORS treatment for SCCUP will
      benefit the insight in how the patient's life after treatment is affected.

      The aims of this study comprising patients treated with TORS for SCCUP:

        1. To lower the patients pain intensity after the TORS procedure with an intensified
           dexamethasone regimen.

        2. To investigate the clinical and organizational factors contributing to hospitalization
           after TORS, and with this knowledge to establish an optimized postoperative care
           program.

        3. To measure the efficiency and morbidity after TORS using DAOH as a descriptive
           assessment 12 months postoperatively.

      This project consists of four studies:

      Study 1 - Corresponding to aim A. The investigators hypothesize that an intensified
      dexamethasone regime will lower patients' reported pain intensity following TORS. This will
      be investigated in a randomized (1:1) double-blinded clinical trial among SCCUP patients
      undergoing TORS and extrapolated to the entire TORS population.

        -  A routine surgical complications study will be performed and examine surgical
           complications within the first 30 postoperative days.

      Study 2 - Corresponding to aim B The investigators hypothesize that not much is known about
      the precise reasons for why patients are hospitalized following TORS. Hence, a prospective
      observational study regarding &quot;why still in hospital after TORS?&quot; will be conducted among all
      patients with SCCUP scheduled for TORS.

      Study 3 - Corresponding to aim C The investigators hypothesize that TORS is an efficient
      procedure with a low morbidity. Hence, a prospective observational study regarding DAOH will
      be conducted among all SCCUP patients scheduled for TORS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>1:1 Randomization to either experimental or control treatment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported Pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative day 1 until day 14 postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analog scale (VAS) ranging from 0-10. 0 being no pain and 10 being maximum pain. The patient will twice daily self-assess pain-intensity during both rest and activity (swallowing). The pain-intensity will be noted in a pain-diary</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Why in hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative day 1 until discharge</time_frame>
    <description>A functional discharge criteria scheme will be used twice daily at 9 a.m. and 2 p.m. (± 2 hours) to decide whether the patient can be discharged. The scheme will be filled out by a doctor and/or nurse and used until discharge from the ward. This is an assessment of organizational and clinical factors contributing to hospitalization</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Days Alive and Out of Hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>From the day of surgery and the first 12 postoperative months</time_frame>
    <description>Days alive and out of hospital is a composite patient-centered endpoint. It is calculated by deducting the length of stay of the initial admission as well as any subsequently admissions and days after potential death from the total follow-up period. Days Alive and Out of Hospital will be investigated from the day of surgery with a 12 months follow-up period.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Analgesia</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Cancer of Head and Neck</condition>
  <condition>Oropharyngeal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Carcinoma of Unknown Primary</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High dose Dexamethasone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard dexamethasone dosage and placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>High-dose dexamethasone peroperative and postoperative on day 2 and 4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>High-dose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>low dose dexamethasone peroperative and placebo postoperatively on day 2 and 4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Low-dose dexamethasone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  Ability to provide a written informed consent

          -  ECOG/WHO performance status 0-2

          -  Squamous cell carcinoma of unknown primary

          -  Booked for TORS based on radiologic and clinical assessment by an ENT surgeon

          -  Negative Urine HCG pregnancy test for women in the fertile age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious medical comorbidities (ECOG/WHO performance status &gt;2). Other
             contraindications to surgery

          -  Distant metastasis

          -  Active Herpes zoster

          -  Previous head and neck cancer

          -  Significant trismus, maximum inter-incisal opening 35mm

          -  Insulin dependent diabetes

          -  Allergy to glucocorticoids

          -  Preoperative daily use of systemic glucocorticoids &lt;90 days before the surgery
             Glucocorticoids administered to the patient's routine examination under general
             anesthesia with bilateral biopsies from base of the tongue, adenoidectomy and
             concurrent tonsillectomy are not a part of this exclusion criteria. Only systemic
             daily use &lt;90 prior TORS is an exclusion criterion.

          -  Preoperative use of biological anti-inflammatory medication &lt;90 days before the
             surgery

          -  Active gastric ulcer in the opinion of the investigator

          -  Pregnancy/Breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mikkel Larsen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>35 45 20 71</phone>
    <email>mikkel.hjordt.holm.larsen@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mikkel Hjordt Holm Larsen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Coordinating investigator, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Unknown Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

