<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04184284</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D3250R00053</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04184284</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes in Severe Eosinophilic Asthma Patients Treated With Benralizumab Under Real-life Conditions</brief_title>
  <acronym>imPROve</acronym>
  <official_title>imPROve-asthma - A Prospective, 12-month, Observational Study to Investigate the Change in Patient-Reported Outcomes in Severe Eosinophilic Asthma Patients Treated With Benralizumab Biologic Therapy Under Real-life Conditions in Germany</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main aim of this study is to investigate the change in asthma control after 6 months of
      therapy in patients treated with benralizumab biologic therapy for severe eosinophilic asthma
      under real-life conditions in a pulmonary care setting in Germany. The study also aims to
      investigate Quality-of-Life (QoL), the early treatment response, treatment effectiveness and
      the change in asthma control over time, following benralizumab therapy. This study will also
      describe the physician-chosen reasons for starting beralizumab therapy or switching to
      benralizumab therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in asthma control after 6 months of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in (Asthma Control Test - questionnaire) ACT score after 6 months treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. ACT is a simple, validated, 5-item tool giving a total score from 5 (worst control) to 25 (best control). Scores of 20 to 25 denote well-controlled asthma, scores ≤19 identifies patients with poorly controlled asthma. The minimum clinically important difference (MCID) is reported to be 3 points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The investigator reported treatment effectiveness after 6 months of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator-reported treatment effectiveness using GETE (Global Evaluation of Treatment Effectiveness) after 6 months of treatment. GETE grades overall treatment effectiveness using the following criteria: excellent (complete control of asthma); good (marked improvement of asthma); moderate (discernible, but limited improvement in asthma); poor (no appreciable change in asthma); or worsening (of asthma).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in health-related quality of life (HRQL) in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) total score and domain scores (symptoms, activity and impact score) after 6 months treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. SGRQ is a validated, 50-item questionnaire, giving scores ranging from 0 (best health status) to 100 (worst health status). The SGRQ yields a total score and 3 domain scores (symptoms, activity, and impacts). The total score indicates the impact of disease on overall health status. A difference of four units in the SGRQ total score is considered the MCID.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, day 7, ACQ-6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and day 7 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in ACQ-6 (Asthma-Control-Questionnaire-6) score after 7 days of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients.
ACQ-6 is a validated questionnaire based on 5 symptoms questions (night-time waking, symptoms on waking, activity limitation, shortness of breath, wheezing), and daily rescue bronchodilator use. Each item is scored on a 7-point scale (0=no impairment; 6=maximum impairment), and the ACQ score is the mean of these items. The MCID is greater than or equal to 0.5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, day 7, VAS-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and day 7 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in patient satisfaction, measured on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), after 7 days of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. VAS Scores ranged from &quot;extremly satisfied&quot; (0 mm) to &quot;not at all satisfied&quot; (100 mm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, day 7, VAS-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and day 7 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in patient symptoms, measured on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), after 7 days of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. VAS Scores ranged from &quot;not at all bothersome&quot; (0 mm) to &quot;extremly bothersome&quot; (100 mm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, day 14, ACQ-6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and day 14 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in ACQ-6 (Asthma-Control-Questionnaire-6) score after 14 days of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. ACQ-6 is a validated questionnaire based on 5 symptoms questions (night-time waking, symptoms on waking, activity limitation, shortness of breath, wheezing), and daily rescue bronchodilator use. Each item is scored on a 7-point scale (0=no impairment; 6=maximum impairment), and the ACQ score is the mean of these items. The MCID is greater than or equal to 0.5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, day 14, VAS-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and day 14 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in patient satisfaction, measured on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), after 14 days of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. VAS Scores ranged from &quot;extremly satisfied&quot; (0 mm) to &quot;not at all satisfied&quot; (100 mm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, day 14, VAS-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and day 14 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in patient symptoms, measured on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), after 14 days of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. VAS Scores ranged from &quot;not at all bothersome&quot; (0 mm) to &quot;extremly bothersome&quot; (100 mm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change of asthma control over time and the maintained response after initiation of benralizumab treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment using ACT</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of enrollment until end of follow-up (approx. 12 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in asthma control at each visit during the study period, using ACT in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. ACT is a simple, validated, 5- item tool giving a total score from 5 (worst control) to 25 (best control). Scores of 20 to 25 denote well-controlled asthma, scores ≤19 identifies patients with poorly controlled asthma. The minimum clinically important difference (MCID) is reported to be 3 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change of asthma control over time and the maintained response after initiation of benralizumab treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients initiated with benralizumab treatment using ACQ-6</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of enrollment until end of follow-up (approx. 12 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in asthma control at each visit during the study period, using ACQ-6 in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients. ACQ-6 is a validated questionnaire based on 5 symptoms questions (night-time waking, symptoms on waking, activity limitation, shortness of breath, wheezing), and daily rescue bronchodilator use. Each item is scored on a 7-point scale (0=no impairment; 6=maximum impairment), and the ACQ score is the mean of these items. The MCID is greater than or equal to 0.5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The reasons for biologic treatment change</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of enrollment until end of follow-up (approx. 12 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator-chosen reasons for
Initiation of benralizumab / switching to benralizumab (treatment change from one biologic to another, regardless of the time since the last dose of the previous biologic) at enrolment
discontinuation of benralizumab during the treatment period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The change of physical activity over time in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline until end of follow-up (approx. 12 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in steps per day over 12 months of treatment in anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The change in asthma control after 6 and 12 months of treatment in biologic experienced patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 and 12 months after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in (Asthma Control Test - questionnaire) ACT score at the end of 6 and 12 months of benralizumab treatment in biologic experienced patients. ACT is a simple, validated, 5-item tool giving a total score from 5 (worst control) to 25 (best control). Scores of 20 to 25 denote well-controlled asthma, scores ≤19 identifies patients with poorly controlled asthma. The minimum clinically important difference (MCID) is reported to be 3 points.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The change in asthma control and the maintained response after initiation of benralizumab treatment in biologic experienced patients using ACQ-6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 and 12 months after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in ACQ-6 (Asthma-Control-Questionnaire-6) score at the end of 6 and 12 months of benralizumab treatment in biologic experienced patients.
ACQ-6 is a validated questionnaire based on 5 symptoms questions (night-time waking, symptoms on waking, activity limitation, shortness of breath, wheezing), and daily rescue bronchodilator use. Each item is scored on a 7-point scale (0=no impairment; 6=maximum impairment), and the ACQ score is the mean of these items. The MCID is greater than or equal to 0.5.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The change in HRQL after 6 and 12 months of treatment in biologic experienced patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 and 12 months after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) total score and domain scores (symptoms, activity and impact score) after 6 and 12 months treatment in biologic experienced patients. SGRQ is a validated, 50-item questionnaire, giving scores ranging from 0 (best health status) to 100 (worst health status). The SGRQ yields a total score and 3 domain scores (symptoms, activity, and impacts). The total score indicates the impact of disease on overall health status. A difference of four units in the SGRQ total score is considered the MCID.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in biologic experienced patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, ACQ-6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 7 and day 14 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in ACQ-6 (Asthma-Control-Questionnaire-6) score after 7 and 14 days of treatment in biologic experienced patients. ACQ-6 is a validated questionnaire based on 5 symptoms questions (night-time waking, symptoms on waking, activity limitation, shortness of breath, wheezing), and daily rescue bronchodilator use. Each item is scored on a 7-point scale (0=no impairment; 6=maximum impairment), and the ACQ score is the mean of these items. The MCID is greater than or equal to 0.5.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in biologic experienced patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, patient satisfaction, VAS-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 7 and day 14 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in patient satisfaction, measured on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), after 7 and 14 days of treatment in biologic experienced patients. VAS Scores ranged from &quot;extremly satisfied&quot; (0 mm) to &quot;not at all satisfied&quot; (100 mm).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The early treatment response in biologic experienced patients initiated with benralizumab treatment, patient symptoms, VAS-2</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 7 and day 14 after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in patient symptoms, measured on Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), after 7 and 14 days of treatment in biologic experienced patients. VAS Scores ranged from &quot;not at all bothersome&quot; (0 mm) to &quot;extremly bothersome&quot; (100 mm).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The investigator reported treatment effectiveness after 6 months of treatment in biologic experienced patients initiated with benralizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after first treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Investigator-reported treatment effectiveness using GETE (Global Evaluation of Treatment Effectiveness) after 6 months of treatment. GETE grades overall treatment effectiveness using the following criteria: excellent (complete control of asthma); good (marked improvement of asthma); moderate (discernible, but limited improvement in asthma); poor (no appreciable change in asthma); or worsening (of asthma).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Study Cohort - Anti-IL5/IL5R naïve patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Severe eosinophilic asthma patients who have never received anti-Interleukin-5 / anti-Interleukin-5-receptor (anti-IL-5/anti-IL-5R) biologic treatment for severe eosinophilic asthma, for whom the investigator had decided to initiate benralizumab biologic treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Secondary Study Cohort - Biologic experienced patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients that previously received a biologic treatment for severe asthma (at least one dose).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        approximately 350 to 500 patients in 40 pulmonology sites (hospitals and outpatient
        practices) in Germany Primary study cohort: approximately 250 patients Secondary study
        cohort: approximately 100 to 250 patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients aged 18 years or older with confirmed diagnosis of severe
             asthma according to the ATS/ERS and local German guidelines

          -  Decision was made by the investigator (regardless of this NIS) to start treating the
             patient with benralizumab according to severe eosinophilic asthma indication (NB: can
             include patients that are switched from another EU approved biologic treatment if
             required for a medical reason).

          -  Patients must be able and willing to read and comprehend written instructions, and
             comprehend and complete the questionnaires required by the protocol

          -  After full explanation, patients must have signed an informed consent document
             indicating that they understand the purpose of and the procedures required for the
             study and are willing to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concomitant treatment with any other biologic for any indication

          -  Patients already treated with benralizumab

          -  Clinically important pulmonary disease other than asthma including: chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease (as main diagnosis), bronchiectasis, idiopathic
             pulmonary fibrosis, pulmonary hypertension, alpha-1-antitrypsin-deficiency, and
             malignancy of any kind (NB: the following conditions are permitted: nasal polyposis,
             allergic rhinitis, atopic dermatitis, non-idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis).

          -  An acute or chronic condition that, in the investigator's opinion, would limit the
             patient's ability to complete questionnaires or participate in this study or impact
             the interpretations of results.

          -  Concurrent biologics for asthma are not allowed except for stable allergen
             immunotherapy (defined as a stable dose and regimen at the time of enrolment).
             Acceptable wash-out periods for other asthma biologics: ≥30 days from last dose of
             previous biologic

          -  Pregnancy or lactation period

          -  Participation in an observational trial that might, in the investigator's opinion,
             influence the assessment for the current study, or participation in a randomized
             clinical trial in the last 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca Clinical Study Information Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-877-240-9479</phone>
    <email>information.center@astrazeneca.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aschaffenburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augsburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bamberg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beelitz</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bonn</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cottbus</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darmstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dortmund</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duesseldorf</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dusseldorf</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Flensburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fuerstenwalde</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gelsenkirchen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gerlingen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halberstadt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halle</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hemer</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hettstedt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ibbenbueren</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Konstanz</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Magdeburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Markkleeberg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Neu-Isenburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Peine</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regensburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reinfeld</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rheine</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostock</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roth</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saalfeld</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Schleswig</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warendorf</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wedel</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wiesbaden</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Witten</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>benralizumab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Eosinophilia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

