<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04189224</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR-6372</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04189224</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Reusable Silicone Hydrogel Multifocal Contact Lens</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Evaluation of a Reusable Multifocal Optical Design in a Presbyopic Population Phase II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Vision Care, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Vision Care, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized, single-masked, crossover clinical trial. There are two study
      lenses. Each lens will be dispensed for 3 ± 1 days and then an optimization visit will occur.
      The final lens pair will be dispensed for 12 ± 2 days and the follow-up on the final lens
      pair will occur. The second study lenses will then be fit and the above sequence repeated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 10, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Performance (Distance, Bright Illuminance)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Visual performance will be evaluated binocularly under high luminance high contrast and high luminance low contrast conditions at 4 meters using Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) charts. Letter-by-letter results will calculate the visual performance score for each chart read. LogMAR scores closer to zero, or below zero, indicate a better visual acuity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Performance (Intermediate, Bright Illuminance)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Visual performance will be evaluated binocularly under high luminance high contrast and high luminance low contrast conditions at 64cm using reduced Guillon-Poling charts. Letter-by-letter results will calculate the visual performance score for each chart read. LogMAR scores closer to zero, or below zero, indicate a better visual acuity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Performance (Near, Bright Illuminance)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Visual performance will be evaluated binocularly under high luminance high contrast and high luminance low contrast conditions at 40cm using reduced Guillon-Poling charts. Letter-by-letter results will calculate the visual performance score for each chart read. LogMAR scores closer to zero, or below zero, indicate a better visual acuity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Performance (Distance, Dim Illuminance)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Visual performance will be evaluated binocularly under dim luminance high contrast conditions at 4 meters using Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) charts. Letter-by-letter results will calculate the visual performance score for each chart read. LogMAR scores closer to zero, or below zero, indicate a better visual acuity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Performance (Intermediate, Dim Illuminance)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Visual performance will be evaluated binocularly under dim luminance high contrast conditions at 64 cm using reduced Guillon-Poling charts. Letter-by-letter results will calculate the visual performance score for each chart read. LogMAR scores closer to zero, or below zero, indicate a better visual acuity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Performance (Near, Dim Illuminance)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Visual performance will be evaluated binocularly under dim luminance high contrast conditions at 40 cm using reduced Guillon-Poling charts. Letter-by-letter results will calculate the visual performance score for each chart read. LogMAR scores closer to zero, or below zero, indicate a better visual acuity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CLUE Vision</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Overall quality of vision is assessed using the Contact Lens User Experience (CLUE™) Questionnaire. CLUE™ is a validated patient-reported outcomes questionnaire developed to measure general and throughout the day comfort/vision, as well as symptoms of discomfort/poor vision, lens handling and packaging. Derived CLUE scores using Item Response Theory (IRT) follow a normal distribution with a population average score of 60 (Standard Deviation 20), where higher scores indicate a more favorable / positive response. A 5 point increase in an average CLUE score translates into 10% shift in the distribution in the distribution of scores for population of soft contact lens wearers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CLUE Comfort</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Overall comfort is assessed using the Contact Lens User Experience (CLUE™) Questionnaire. CLUE™ is a validated patient-reported outcomes questionnaire developed to measure general and throughout the day comfort/vision, as well as symptoms of discomfort/poor vision, lens handling and packaging. Derived CLUE scores using Item Response Theory (IRT) follow a normal distribution with a population average score of 60 (Standard Deviation 20), where higher scores indicate a more favorable / positive response. A 5 point increase in an average CLUE score translates into 10% shift in the distribution in the distribution of scores for population of soft contact lens wearers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject reported ocular symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will respond to a verbal open-ended symptoms questionnaire to determine whether or not ocular symptoms and problems are present.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Slit Lamp Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A slit lamp will be used to determine the level of corneal edema, and other complications in each eye using the FDA Slit Lamp Findings Classification Scale: Grade 0 - None; Grade 1 - Trace; Grade 2 - Mild; Grade 3 - Moderate; Grade 4 - Severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Presbyopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test/Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hyperopic subjects that are habitual soft contact lens wearers and have presbyopia will be randomized to sequence, Test/Control.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control/Test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hyperopic subjects that are habitual soft contact lens wearers and have presbyopia will be randomized to sequence, Control/Test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JJV Investigational Multifocal Contact Lens</intervention_name>
    <description>TEST</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control/Test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test/Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1-Day Acuvue® Moist Brand Multifocal Contact Lens</intervention_name>
    <description>CONTROL</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control/Test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Test/Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Potential subjects must satisfy all of the following criteria to be enrolled in the
             study:

               1. The subject must read, understand, and sign the STATEMENT OF INFORMED CONSENT and
                  receive a fully executed copy of the form.

               2. The subject must appear able and willing to adhere to the instructions set forth
                  in this clinical protocol.

               3. The subject must be at least 40 years of age and not greater than 70 years of age
                  at the time of consent.

               4. Subjects must own a wearable pair of spectacles if required for their distance
                  vision.

               5. The subject must be an adapted soft contact lens wearer in both eyes (i.e. worn
                  lenses a minimum of 2 days per week for at least 8 hours per wear day, for 1
                  month or more duration).

               6. The subject must either already be wearing a presbyopic contact lens correction
                  (e.g., reading spectacles over contact lenses, multifocal or monovision contact
                  lenses, etc.) or if not respond positively to at least one symptom on the
                  &quot;Presbyopic Symptoms Questionnaire&quot; (Appendix E).

               7. The subject's distance spherical equivalent refraction must be in the range of
                  +1.25 D to +3.75 D in each eye.

               8. The subject's refractive cylinder must be ≤0.75 D in each eye.

               9. The subject's ADD power must be in the range of +0.75 D to +2.50 D.

              10. The subject must have distance best corrected visual acuity of 20/20-3 or better
                  in each eye.

                  Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Potential subjects who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from
             participating in the study:

               1. Currently pregnant or lactating.

               2. Any active or ongoing ocular or systemic allergies that may interfere with
                  contact lens wear.

               3. Any active or ongoing systemic disease, autoimmune disease, or use of medication,
                  which may interfere with contact lens wear. This may include, but not be limited
                  to, diabetes, hyperthyroidism, Sjögren's syndrome, xerophthalmia, acne rosacea,
                  Stevens- Johnson syndrome, and immunosuppressive diseases or any infectious
                  diseases (e.g. hepatitis, tuberculosis).

               4. Any previous, or planned, ocular or intraocular surgery (e.g. radial keratotomy,
                  PRK, LASIK, lid procedures, cataract surgery, retinal surgery, etc.).

               5. A history of amblyopia, strabismus or binocular vision abnormality.

               6. Use of any of the following medications within 1 week prior to enrollment: oral
                  retinoid isotretinoin (e.g. Accutane), oral tetracyclines, oral phenothiazines,
                  oral/topical/inhaled anticholinergics, systemic/topical corticosteroids.

               7. Use of any ocular medication, with the exception of rewetting drops.

               8. History of herpetic keratitis.

               9. History of irregular cornea.

              10. History of pathological dry eye.

              11. Participation in any contact lens or lens care product clinical trial within 30
                  days prior to study enrollment.

              12. Employee or immediate family member of an employee of clinical site (e.g.,
                  Investigator, Coordinator, Technician).

              13. Any known hypersensitivity or allergic reaction to Optifree®Replenish®
                  multipurpose care solution, sodium fluorescein or non-preserved rewetting drop
                  solutions.

              14. Clinically significant (Grade 2 or greater) corneal edema, corneal
                  vascularization, corneal staining, tarsal abnormalities or bulbar injection, or
                  any other corneal or ocular abnormalities which would contraindicate contact lens
                  wear.

              15. Entropion, ectropion, extrusions, chalazia, recurrent styes, glaucoma, history of
                  recurrent corneal erosions.

              16. Any current ocular infection or inflammation.

              17. Any current ocular abnormality that may interfere with contact lens wear.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maitland Vision Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maitland</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32751</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Advanced Eyecare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Raytown</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64133</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ProCare Vision Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granville</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43023</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Frazier Vision Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75703</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Presbyopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Johnson &amp; Johnson Medical Device Companies have an agreement with the Yale Open Data Access (YODA) to serve as the independent review panel for evaluation of requests for clinical study reports and participant level data from investigators and physicians for scientific research that will advance medical knowledge and public health. Requests for access to the study data can be submitted through the YODA Project site at http://yoda.yale.edu</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>http://yoda.yale.edu</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

