<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04189900</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMIMFTCL/TRIPTO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04189900</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Generation of Biological Samples Positive to Triptorelin for Anti-doping Control</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRIPTO</acronym>
  <official_title>Generation of Biological Samples Positive to Triptorelin for Anti-doping Control</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Parc de Salut Mar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Parc de Salut Mar</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Androgens are used for doping purpose because they can increase muscle mass and strength.
      These drugs are included in the list of prohibited substances of the World Anti-Doping Agency
      (WADA). The prohibition of its use has given rise to a great variety of strategies of
      indirect androgenic doping, whose purpose is to produce a sustained increase in endogenous
      testosterone.

      Triptorelin acetate is a gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) agonist. Daily subcutaneous
      administration of triptorelin causes an initial increase in circulating levels of luteinizing
      hormone (LH) and follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), producing a transient increase in
      testosterone levels. However, prolonged daily administration results in a paradoxical
      decrease in LH and FSH levels due to desensitization of GnRH receptors, decreasing
      testosterone production to levels similar to castration.

      Thus, the initial flare reaction produced by triptorelin administration could be used by
      athletes as an indirect androgenic doping method to stimulate the synthesis of endogenous LH
      and testosterone with the aim of improving physical performance.

      Hypothesis:

      Subcutaneous administration of triptorelin in healthy subjects allows obtaining positive
      urine samples that will be used to identify analytical strategies for doping detection.
      Triptorelin concentrations and its metabolites can be measured in urine.

      Objectives:

      Primary objective: To measure triptorelin concentrations in urine samples for anti-doping
      control.

      Secondary objectives: To identify triptorelin metabolites in urine. To explore the time
      window in which the drug or its metabolites can be detected in urine after administration.

      Methods:

      Phase I, open, non-randomized, uncontrolled clinical trial, with a treatment condition
      (triptorelin) administered subcutaneously in a single dose to 2 subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study model consists on a single group of subjects who receive the treatment condition (triptorelin)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin</measure>
    <time_frame>0-4 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin in urine sample (Fraction 1)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin in urine sample (Fraction 2)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin</measure>
    <time_frame>8-12 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin in urine sample (Fraction 3)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin</measure>
    <time_frame>12-24 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin in urine sample (Fraction 4)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin</measure>
    <time_frame>24-48 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin in urine sample (Fraction 5)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>0-4 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin metabolites in urine sample (Fraction 1)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin metabolites in urine sample (Fraction 2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>8-12 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin metabolites in urine sample (Fraction 3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>12-24 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin metabolites in urine sample (Fraction 4)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentration of triptorelin metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>24-48 hours post-administration</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of triptorelin metabolites in urine sample (Fraction 5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Triptorelin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The subjects in this group receive a single dose treatment. Biologic sample collection (urine) from 48 hours pre-administration to 48 hours post administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triptorelin</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects receive a single subcutaneous dose of 0,1 mg of Triptorelin acetate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Triptorelin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male volunteers aged between 18 and 45 years.

          -  Able to understand and accept the trial procedures and able to sign an informed
             consent.

          -  History and physical examination that demonstrate not presenting organic or
             psychiatric disorders.

          -  ECG, blood and urine tests performed at screening should be within normal limits.
             Minor or punctual variations of these limits of normality are admitted if, in the
             opinion of the Principal Investigator, they have no clinical significance, do not pose
             a risk to the subject and do not interfere with the evaluation of the product. These
             variations and their non-relevance will be justified in writing specifically.

          -  Body mass index (weight/size^2) between 19 and 25 kg/m2, and weight between 50 and 90
             kg. BMI between 25 and 27 kg/m2 may be included at the discretion of the Principal
             Investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Failure to meet the inclusion criteria.

          -  History of allergy, idiosyncrasy, hypersensitivity or adverse reactions to the active
             substance or similar nonapeptides and to any of the excipients.

          -  Serious adverse reactions to other medications.

          -  Subjects with contraindications to treatment with the study drug (according to Summary
             of Product Characteristics).

          -  Background or clinical evidence of psychiatric disorders, alcoholism, drug abuse or
             addiction to other substances (except for nicotine) or regular consumption of
             psychoactive drugs.

          -  Having participated in another clinical trial with medication in the three months
             prior to the start of the study.

          -  Having donated blood during the two months prior to the start of the study.

          -  Having suffered an organic disease or major surgery in the six months prior to the
             start of the study.

          -  Background or clinical evidence of cardiovascular, respiratory, renal, hepatic,
             endocrine, gastrointestinal, hematological, neurological or other acute or chronic
             diseases that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator or the collaborators
             designated by him, may pose a risk to the subjects or interfere with the objectives of
             the study. Especially epileptic seizures or history of epilepsy.

          -  Have taken medication regularly in the month prior to the study sessions, with the
             exception of vitamins, herbal remedies or dietary supplements that, in the opinion of
             the Principal Investigator or the collaborators designated by him, do not pose a risk
             to the subjects and do not interfere with the objectives of the study. Treatment with
             single doses of symptomatic medication in the week prior to the study session will not
             be exclusive if it is assumed that it has been completely eliminated on the day of the
             experimental session.

          -  Smokers of more than 20 cigarettes daily the 3 months prior to the study.

          -  Consumption of more than 40 g of alcohol daily.

          -  Consumers of more than 5 coffees, teas, cola drinks and/or other stimulant drinks
             (xanthines) per day in the 3 months prior to the start of the study.

          -  Being unable to understand the nature of the trial and the procedures requested to
             follow.

          -  Positive serology for hepatitis B, C or HIV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ana M Aldea Perona, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>IMIM (Hospital del Mar Medical Research Institute)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IMIM (Hospital del Mar Medical Research Institute)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Triptorelin</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-doping control</keyword>
  <keyword>Athletic performance</keyword>
  <keyword>Gonadotropin-releasing hormone</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Triptorelin Pamoate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

