<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00046059</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000058</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-HG-0058</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00046059</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Analysis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic Analysis of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is the most common behavioral disorder in
      childhood, affecting 3-5% of children between the ages of 7 and 17. Family studies suggest
      that there is a genetic component to ADHD. Scientists believe that it is a complex disorder
      in which two or more genes may be involved.

      Potentially eligible families will be asked to give written consent to participate and will
      be asked to complete questionnaires for each member in the family. In addition, an interview
      will be administered to the parent of minors enrolled in the study to determine their
      eligibility for being in the study. This screening tool is computerized and will take
      approximately 45 minutes to administer per child.

      Once screenings are completed, a blood collection kit will be sent to the family to take to
      their local medical care provider, have blood samples drawn and sent to NIH. There is no cost
      to the family to participate. We would like to enroll entire families, with both parents and
      all children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is one of the most common childhood

      disorders and the most common childhood neurodevelopmental behavioral disorder. Symptoms
      include difficulty staying focused (inattention), difficulty controlling behavior
      (impulsivity), and hyperactivity. Symptoms typically develop between six and 12 years of age,
      and frequently persist into adulthood, with serious life-long health and social consequences.
      Affected children are at increased risk for poor educational achievement, low income,
      underemployment, legal difficulties, and impaired social relationships. The general belief is
      that ADHD is caused by a combination of genetic and environmental factors.

      The main objective of the study is to conduct genetic and behavioral studies that will
      closely

      characterize the genetic influences in diagnosis, prognosis, severity, and pharmacological

      response in ADHD patients. Since the start of the study in 2000, research has contributed to
      the understanding of the innate susceptibility of ADHD and associated comorbidities; the
      interaction of genetic, demographic, and environmental factors underpinning the risk of
      developing ADHD; the extent to which these factors shape the response of ADHD patients to
      pharmacological interventions (pharmacogenetics); the over-representation of functional and
      ontological genebased networks implicated in determining synapse structure; and the use of
      advanced geneticepidemiological models with potential for use in clinical practice
      (translational genomics). The most significant research finding occurred in 2010, when the
      study team identified LPHN3, a key gene involved in the etiology of ADHD and comorbid
      conditions in one of the previously identified regions of strong genetic signal in chromosome
      4q13.2.

      In order to provide power for the study s statistical analyses, the upper enrollment goal is
      4,000 participants. Although the study has several small and genetically distinct cohorts,
      the majority of subjects come from the United States of America population through outreach
      recruitment efforts. Recruitment has been very successful and the large cohort numbers
      provide support for identification of genetic components related to the diagnosis of ADHD.
      Recent efforts have focused on identifying new areas of the genome associated with ADHD, and
      identifying genetic (coding and non-coding) variations implicated in the etiology and
      clinical manifestations of ADHD. A primary aim of the study is to correlate genetic and
      biological markers for diagnosis and prognosis of ADHD identified through the use of state of
      the art genomics, which includes enome-wide association studies, linkage analysis, whole
      genome and exome sequencing, and targeted gene capture in cosmopolitan and isolated
      populations. As the current diagnosis of ADHD is based on subjective observations, one of the
      main goals of the study is to develop a more definitive system to diagnose ADHD and to assess
      and predict prognosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 8, 2000</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ADHD</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>The main objective of the study is to conduct genetic and behavioral studies that will closely characterize the genetic influences in diagnosis, prognosis, severity, and pharmacological response in ADHD patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3481</enrollment>
  <condition>ADHD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADHD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children aged 7-17 with ADHD and their families.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1. Families with children, seven through 17 years of age, diagnosed with ADHD (defined as
        the proband for the study).@@@2. The probands siblings, either affected with ADHD
        (concordant) or unaffected (discordant), seven years of age and above, including adult
        siblings.@@@3. The parents, both mothers and fathers, of enrolled probands.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        This study will enroll families with the following characteristics:

          1. Families with children, seven through 17 years of age, diagnosed with ADHD (defined as
             the proband for the study).

          2. The probands siblings, either affected with ADHD (concordant) or unaffected
             (discordant), seven years of age and above, including adult siblings.

          3. The parents, both mothers and fathers, of enrolled probands.

          4. The study will enroll both male and female probands of any ethnic background and race.
             The prevalence of ADHD is higher in males than in females, so we would expect to have
             a higher number of male probands than female probands. Both male and female siblings
             and male and female parents of probands will be enrolled.

          5. Adults who are or may be unable to provide informed consent will be excluded.

          6. Probands with one parent affected with ADHD or with neither parent affected with ADHD
             are eligible. Probands from bilineal families, families with both parents affected
             with ADHD, will be excluded for statistical reasons.

        Additional inclusion criteria for the study include:

        1. Ability to read and understand spoken English, since the questionnaires, scales, and
        interviews that we have license to use in this study are in English.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Some conditions can confound the diagnosis of ADHD. Probands with the following conditions
        will be excluded from enrollment or will be withdrawn from the study if the condition is
        discovered subsequent to enrollment:

          -  Prematurity

          -  Neurological conditions

          -  Cardiac surgery

          -  Prenatal drug exposure

          -  Hydrocephaly

          -  Mental Retardation (IQ&lt;80)

          -  Known genetic syndromes

          -  Known CNS disorders

          -  Known lead toxicity

          -  Tourette Disorder

          -  Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder

          -  Major Depression on both proband and affected sibling

          -  Pervasive Developmental Disorder

          -  Age under 7 years old

          -  Autism

          -  Other Psychoses

          -  Post Traumatic Stress Disorder

          -  Language Disorder (if known)

          -  Severe Sensory Impairment (visual and hearing)

        Probands with the following conditions may be included, but the conditions will be noted
        during statistical analysis:

          -  Oppositional Defiant Disorder

          -  Conduct Disorder

          -  Tic Disorder

          -  Obsessive/Compulsive Symptoms

          -  Anxiety/Phobias

          -  Learning Disabilities
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria T Acosta, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Irvine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92668</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2000-HG-0058.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson JC, Williams S, McGee R, Silva PA. DSM-III disorders in preadolescent children. Prevalence in a large sample from the general population. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1987 Jan;44(1):69-76.</citation>
    <PMID>2432848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biederman J, Faraone S, Milberger S, Guite J, Mick E, Chen L, Mennin D, Marrs A, Ouellette C, Moore P, Spencer T, Norman D, Wilens T, Kraus I, Perrin J. A prospective 4-year follow-up study of attention-deficit hyperactivity and related disorders. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1996 May;53(5):437-46.</citation>
    <PMID>8624187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faraone SV, Biederman J, Chen WJ, Milberger S, Warburton R, Tsuang MT. Genetic heterogeneity in attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD): gender, psychiatric comorbidity, and maternal ADHD. J Abnorm Psychol. 1995 May;104(2):334-345. doi: 10.1037/0021-843X.104.2.334.</citation>
    <PMID>7790635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 10, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 18, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 18, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 19, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Linkage</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Identification</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperactivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

