<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03633318</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2000023035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03633318</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Establishing Muscle Impedance Parameters With Electrical Impedance Myography</brief_title>
  <official_title>Application of Electrical Impedance Myography (EIM) to Establish Muscle Impedance Parameters as a Potential Biomarker of Inclusion Body Myositis (IBM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this study is to assess the changes in the impedance parameters of muscles
      in inclusion body myositis (IBM) through electrical impedance myography (EIM), an emerging
      non-invasive electrodiagnostic technology. Muscle impedance parameters can potentially serve
      as an objective biomarker reflecting disease progression and severity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this pilot study, the electrical impedance myography (EIM) parameters of individuals with
      inclusion body myositis (IBM) will be compared with age and sex matched normal data. Along
      with EIM parameters, clinical outcome measures will be obtained to understand how EIM data
      correlates with these parameters. A focused study to assess muscle health in IBM patients
      through EIM is essential to gather further insight into the potential application of this
      technology as a disease biomarker. Additionally, this investigation will provide critical
      data for the design of a subsequent biomarker validation study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants with IBM will be compared with a group matched on sex and age.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>IBM-Functional Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>45 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Physical functioning in daily life will be measured using the IBM-Functional rating scale (IBM-FRS). IBM-FRS will be obtained for both IBM participants and healthy controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Grip Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>45 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength will be assessed using the Jamar hand dynamometer and will be obtained by the physician from both IBM participants and healthy controls. The best of three attempts will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Stand</measure>
    <time_frame>45 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Time to stand will be measured using the &quot;Get-up-and-go test&quot;. Time will be measured for a participant to stand up from a chair (using arms if necessary), walk 3 meters, turn around, return to the chair, and sit down. The better of two trials will be used. These results will be obtained by the physician from both IBM participants and healthy controls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>45 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Distance walked by a participant in 6 minutes will be measured. Given the general disability of many IBM participants, rather than utilizing two trials, a 2-minute &quot;practice&quot; walk will be performed before the actual test, to familiarize the participant with the task to be performed. Both IBM participants and healthy controls will undergo this procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Manual Muscle Testing (MMT) Global Score</measure>
    <time_frame>45 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This is a hands-on assessment that will use the Medical Research Council muscle scales (MRC) to score the strength of the following muscle groups that may be involved in IBM: neck flexor, extensor, deltoid, biceps, triceps, wrist extensor, wrist flexors, finger long and short flexors, finger extensors, hip flexors, hip adductors, hip abductors, knee extensors, knee flexors, ankle dorsi and planti flexors. MRC scores will be obtained by the physician from both IBM participants and healthy controls. A global score can be calculated and will be used. 0 (none) = no contraction, 1 (trace) = visible contraction with no motion, 2 (poor) = full range of motion, gravity eliminated, 3 (fair) = full range of motion against gravity, 4 (good) = full range of motion against gravity, moderate resistance, 5 (normal) = full range of motion against gravity, maximum resistance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">31</enrollment>
  <condition>IBM</condition>
  <condition>Inclusion Body Myositis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IBM Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will have Inclusion Body Myositis (IBM). All patients will have EIM measurements of selected muscles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will be healthy controls. All participants will have EIM measurements of selected muscles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>electrical impedance myography (EIM)</intervention_name>
    <description>EIM is a measure of impedance. EIM is a measure of the obstruction of flow of current through the tissue. It is a completely painless assessment of muscle health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IBM Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinico-pathologically defined IBM in the absence of any other significant
             neurological problem or cognitive dysfunction.

          -  Healthy controls will be age and gender-matched to the enrolled IBM patients.

        Exclusion Criteria for both IBM and control group:

          -  Patients with decompensated congestive heart failure

          -  Patients with chronic kidney disease on hemodialysis

          -  Patients with active cancer on chemotherapy or radiotherapy

          -  Patients with severe disease who are already wheel-chair bound
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>46 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bhaskar Roy, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale School of Medicine: Department of Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard J Nowak, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale School of Medicine: Department of Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale Physicians Building</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06519</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>electrical impedance myography</keyword>
  <keyword>EIM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myositis, Inclusion Body</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

