<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03635970</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIBIUG-P14-2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03635970</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cell Therapy for Peripheral Arterial Disease and Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Microvascular Effect After the Application of Cell Therapy With a Hematopoietic Stem Cell Concentrate in Patients With Peripheral Arterial Disease With Non-critical Ischemia and Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Regional de Alta Especialidad del Bajio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Regional de Alta Especialidad del Bajio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled trial with blinding (for the observer who evaluates treatment
      goals).

      With two groups to study. A group of patients with conventional therapy for the treatment of
      PAD (Platelet antiaggregant, statin, cilostazol in case of claudication) and the other group
      of patients with conventional therapy for treatment of PAD plus cell therapy with objective
      to evaluate the microvascular effect after the application of cell therapy with a
      hematopoietic stem cell concentrate in patients with PAD with non-critical ischemia and
      Diabetes. Perform evaluations of the microcirculation by means of TcPO2 at 30, 60, 90 and 180
      days after the experimental maneuver (cell therapy) and conventional therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION: Peripheral arterial disease (PAD) is defined as arterial occlusion of the lower
      extremities. Based on epidemiological studies using the Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI), the
      prevalence of PAD (defined as an ABI &lt;0.9) in diabetic patients ranges from 20% to 30%.
      Diabetic patients with PAD have a higher mortality and death rate at a younger age than
      patients without diabetes. The appropriate medical treatment for EAP in patients with
      diabetes is based on the control of cardiovascular risk factors. Revascularization is
      indicated in particular situations in PAD in the context of critical chronic ischemia (ABI
      &lt;0.6), however, anatomical factors, operative risk, technical difficulties or patient
      preferences may limit its use in patients with PAD and diabetes. Therapeutic angiogenesis is
      an experimental approach to restore perfusion and cell therapy can provide a continuous
      source of growth factors and structural elements for therapeutic angiogenesis. The
      transcutaneous oxygen pressure (TcPO2) is defined as a microvascular evaluation system. The
      microvascular effect of cell therapy at an earlier stage of PAD has not been analyzed as
      non-critical ischemia in patients with diabetes.

      OBJECTIVE: To evaluate the microvascular effect after the application of cell therapy with a
      concentrate of hematopoietic stem cell in patients with PAD with non-critical ischemia and
      Diabetes.

      MATERIAL AND METHODS: Randomized controlled clinical trial with blinding (for the observer
      who evaluates treatment goals). With two groups for your study. A group of patients with
      conventional therapy for the treatment of PAD (Platelet antiaggregant, statin, cilostazol in
      case of claudication) and the other group of patients with conventional therapy for treatment
      of PAD plus cell therapy, to be carried out in patients entitled to the Mexican Institute of
      the Social Security of the Guanajuato Delegation, with diagnosis of Diabetes Mellitus type 2
      of more than 10 years of detection and with diagnosis of peripheral arterial disease with an
      ABI between 0.6 and 0.9 that agree to participate in the study. Cell therapy will consist of
      hematopoietic progenitor cells identified as a fraction of cells identified by flow cytometry
      as CD34 + obtained by peripheral blood harvesting procedure, prior mobilization process with
      filgrastim.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 18, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 18, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Treatment for peripheral arterial disease plus diabetes with 2 arms of study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>the evaluator of the treatment goals does not know the treatment that each patient received</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TcPO2</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change is being assessed, through the transcutaneous pressure of oxygen, after the application of the therapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>receive the best conventional therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>experimental treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The best medical treatment possible plus celular therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>celular therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>application of cell therapy with a concentrate of hematopoietic progenitor cells or celular therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>conventional treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>experimental treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with affiliation to the Mexican Institute of Social Security.

          2. Patients older than 35 years.

          3. Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus over 10 years of detection.

          4. Patients with Peripheral Arterial Disease with ABI between 0.6 and 0.9.

          5. Signature of informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with a history of uncontrolled oncological disease in the last 5 years.

          2. Presence of Chronic Renal Insufficiency with a calculated creatinine clearance using a
             Cockcroft formula less than 15ml / min.

          3. Ulcer that defines diabetic foot or tissue necrosis that requires partial or total
             amputation of a limb.

          4. Serious active infectious process anywhere in the body.

          5. Have restrictions with the use of filgrastim such as treatment with lithium,
             chemotherapy or radiotherapy, as well as a history of autoimmune thrombocytopenia,
             vasculitis, previous cardiovascular disease, Sweet's syndrome or Steven-Johnson
             syndrome.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>B MURILLO, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>IMSS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto Mexicano Del Seguro Social</name>
      <address>
        <city>León</city>
        <state>Guanajuato</state>
        <zip>37660</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

