<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03633214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BK070-2016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03633214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of An Online Intervention In Improving General Practitioners' Practice In Prostate Cancer Screening</brief_title>
  <acronym>ProCaSS</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of An Online Intervention In Improving General Practitioners' Practice In Prostate Cancer Screening</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Malaya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Malaya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of prostate cancer has been rising steadily both globally and in Malaysia.
      Besides an ageing population, another reason cited to explain the increase, is the
      corresponding increase in the prostate cancer screening rates, especially using non-invasive
      tests like the prostate specific antigen (PSA).

      General practitioners, being front liners in medicine, play an important role in helping men
      make an informed decision on prostate cancer screening. In Malaysia, about 50% of GPs would
      routinely screen asymptomatic men and 95% of them would use PSA as a screening tool. Despite
      this, the evidence for screening is inconclusive, as evidenced from two major trials on
      screening [The European Randomised Study of Screening for Prostate Cancer (ERSPC) and
      Prostate, Lung, Colorectal and Ovarian Cancer Screening trial (PLCO)]. Furthermore, clinical
      practice guidelines globally provide conflicting recommendations on this subject, and none
      has been published in Malaysia to date.

      Therefore, our study aims to determine the effectiveness of an online training module in
      helping GPs' better understand the controversies surrounding prostate cancer screening, and
      in so doing, improve their practice of screening. The investigators hypothesise that GPs who
      are randomised to receive their online module will be less inclined to screen unnecessarily
      for prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design: Randomised controlled trial

      Setting: This trial will involve GPs in the Klang Valley, encompassing the Petaling district
      and Kuala Lumpur.

      The healthcare system in Malaysia is divided into public and private sectors. Patients pay a
      standard minimal fee for public healthcare system whereas the private sector charges patients
      based on the services provided. The study will be conducted in private GP clinics as PSA
      testing is readily available compared to the public primary care setting. In public primary
      care clinics, PSA screening is not offered as part of a routine screening programme.

      Sample size:

      With 80% power and 5% (two-sided) significance, with an estimated 40% reduction in PSA
      screening from baseline in the intervention group and 10% in the control group, the number of
      participants needed for each group is 38 (total 76). Therefore, a total of 96 GPs in the
      Klang Valley will be recruited for this study, assuming a non-response rate of 20 GPs.

      Intervention:

      The intervention consists of two phases.

      Phase 1 The research team will develop 3 self-administered, online surveys, with the input of
      family physicians and urologists. The surveys will capture basic demographic information
      about the participating GPs (but not any identifiable information), and also their overall
      knowledge and perception towards prostate cancer screening. In addition, all 3 surveys will
      also contain 5 clinical vignettes that will relate to prostate cancer screening. After
      reading the vignettes, the GPs will be asked whether or not they would recommend screening
      for the particular patient in the given scenario; and should they choose to screen, which
      screening method they would use (PSA, DRE, or both).

      GPs will then be randomised to either receive an online training module (intervention) or
      none (control).

      Phase 2:

      Upon successful receipt of the GPs' response to the first survey, a second survey will be
      sent to all the GPs via email. The participants will once again be invited to read and
      respond to another set of vignettes of similar nature to those in phase 1.

      GPs who have been randomised to the intervention arm will also receive a link in the second
      email that will enable them to download an online training module. The participants will be
      asked to view the training module prior to answering the second survey.

      GPs in the control group will only receive the second survey and not the training module.

      A third and final email will be sent to all the GPs who have successfully answered the second
      survey, 3 months after the date of receipt of their second survey response. This final survey
      will likewise, contain five clinical vignettes of similar nature to those of the two previous
      surveys. The responses of GPs in the intervention group will then be compared before and
      immediately after the online training video and also 3-months later; as well as to the
      control group.

      Recruitment:

      The research team will recruit the GPs from an existing GP database which has been created
      from previous studies conducted in the Petaling District and Kuala Lumpur. A researcher and a
      research assistant will be responsible for identifying and recruiting eligible participants.
      An invitation letter, a study summary, a participant information sheet and consent form will
      be sent via email to each GP. Consenting participants will be remunerated for their time and
      effort spent in participating in the study. In the event response is poor, a research
      assistant may need to arrange an appointment to visit the GPs at their clinics'.

      Analysis:

      The McNemar test will be used to determine the phase differences in the proportion of GPs who
      perform screening unnecessarily and the differences between the intervention and control
      group. Chi square test will be used to compare the difference in proportions between the
      intervention and control groups. GPs' characteristics associated with unnecessary screening
      practice will be explored using logistic regression models using phase 1 data. Logistic
      regression will be used for binary outcomes and the analyses will be adjusted for baseline
      data. SPSS will be used to manage the data sets
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 25, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of effectiveness of online training module among general practitioners in prostate cancer screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the change in proportions of appropriate prostate cancer screening from baseline by GPs between intervention (online training module) and control (no online training module) groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-online training module knowledge in prostate cancer screening</measure>
    <time_frame>An average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the post-online training module knowledge and attitudes towards prostate cancer screening between the intervention and control groups.
GPs' characteristics that are associated with prostate cancer screening</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer Screening</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training module (Intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Responses of GPs in the intervention group will then be compared before and immediately after the online training video and also 3-months later</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No training module (Control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online training module</intervention_name>
    <description>Responses of GPs in the intervention group will then be compared before and immediately after the online training video and also 3-months later; as well as to the control group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training module (Intervention)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Full time general practitioners in the Klang valley (Petaling district and Kuala
             Lumpur)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  GPs who do not see male patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tun Firzara Abdul Malik</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Malaya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Primary Care Medicine, University of Malaya Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuala Lumpur</city>
        <state>Lembah Pantai</state>
        <zip>59100</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://globocan.iarc.fr</url>
    <description>Cancer Incidence and Mortality Worldwide: IARC CancerBase</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schröder FH, Hugosson J, Roobol MJ, Tammela TL, Ciatto S, Nelen V, Kwiatkowski M, Lujan M, Lilja H, Zappa M, Denis LJ, Recker F, Páez A, Määttänen L, Bangma CH, Aus G, Carlsson S, Villers A, Rebillard X, van der Kwast T, Kujala PM, Blijenberg BG, Stenman UH, Huber A, Taari K, Hakama M, Moss SM, de Koning HJ, Auvinen A; ERSPC Investigators. Prostate-cancer mortality at 11 years of follow-up. N Engl J Med. 2012 Mar 15;366(11):981-90. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1113135. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2012 May 31;366(22):2137.</citation>
    <PMID>22417251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andriole GL, Crawford ED, Grubb RL 3rd, Buys SS, Chia D, Church TR, Fouad MN, Gelmann EP, Kvale PA, Reding DJ, Weissfeld JL, Yokochi LA, O'Brien B, Clapp JD, Rathmell JM, Riley TL, Hayes RB, Kramer BS, Izmirlian G, Miller AB, Pinsky PF, Prorok PC, Gohagan JK, Berg CD; PLCO Project Team. Mortality results from a randomized prostate-cancer screening trial. N Engl J Med. 2009 Mar 26;360(13):1310-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0810696. Epub 2009 Mar 18. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2009 Apr 23;360(17):1797.</citation>
    <PMID>19297565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Malaya</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Tun Firzara Abdul Malik</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostatic neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Mass screening</keyword>
  <keyword>General practitioners</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary health care</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>It is not yet known if there will be a plan to make IPD available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

