<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03632707</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MRIOMMPRT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03632707</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging of Medial Meniscal Posterior Root Tear</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Magnetic Resonance Imaging in the Diagnosis of Posterior Medial Meniscal Root Tear of the Knee</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate and analyze the role of magnetic resonance imaging in
      the diagnosis of medial meniscal posterior root tears, including the normal variations in
      meniscal anatomy that may resemble a meniscal tear, and identifying the causes or nature of
      posterior medial meniscal root tear(degenerative versus traumatic) and correlate the results
      with the standard reference knee Arthroscopy.In addition to identifying and estimating the
      suspected cases of meniscal extrusion by making MRI with stress varus overloading simulating
      weight bearing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The knee joint is one of the most important joints in the human body responsible for
      weight-bearing and a group of complex movements during ordinary life activities and even in
      vigorous sports making it susceptible to different traumatic injuries.Knee pain is considered
      as one of the most common complaints of patients presenting to clinical practitioners.There
      are many structures within the knee which can cause pain. By far, one of the most common
      causes of knee pain is a meniscus tear.The meniscus is the most important cushion in the
      knee; It plays an important bio mechanical role in axial load distribution of the knees. If
      the meniscus is injured and the cushioning is lost, arthritis and pain can occur.Menisci can
      tear due to traumatic injury or degenerative wear, meniscal root tears are a type of meniscal
      tear in the knee where the tear extends to either the anterior or posterior meniscal root
      attachment to the central tibial plateau. They often tend to be radial tears extending into
      the root.The medial meniscal posterior root tear can occur especially in middle-aged or older
      patients who have a single event of posteromedial painful popping sensation during light
      activities.Magnetic resonance imaging is well established as the best imaging modality for
      evaluating a patient with suspected meniscal pathology, involving the medial meniscal
      posterior horn root.In recent years, posterior meniscal root tears have received increasing
      attention in both Arthroscopic and Magnetic resonance study. All sequences of Magnetic
      resonance imaging should be reviewed, but T2 weighted coronal sections should provide the
      best visualization of the posterior roots. The Magnetic resonance findings of a medial
      meniscal posterior radial root tear are shortening or absence of the root (ghost sign) on
      sagittal images and a vertical fluid cleft with truncation sign and features of meniscal
      extrusion on coronal images.

      It is very important to avoid errors in diagnosing meniscal root tears. So interpreting
      Magnetic resonance examinations of the knee need to be aware of the attachments of the
      menisci and to understand the normal variations in meniscal anatomy that may resemble a
      meniscal tear.

      Tears of the meniscal root are relatively uncommon, occurring in 2.2% - 9.8% of patients
      undergoing Magnetic resonance imaging of the knee.However, it is important that these tears
      be diagnosed as several complications of meniscal root tear, including meniscal extrusion,
      secondary osteoarthritis, and subchondral insufficiency fracture.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients complain of painful knee joint associated with popping sounds and clinically suspected of medial meniscal posterior root tear will examined by Magnetic Resonance Imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation the results of Magnetic Resonance Imaging with gold standard knee Arthroscopy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Medial Meniscus, Posterior Horn Derangement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Magnetic resonance imaging of the knee</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients complain of painful knee with clinical suspicious of medial meniscus posterior root tear of the knee will be examined by all Magnetic Resonance Imaging sequences including sagittal, coronal and axial PD,T2 and PD-SPIR weighted images, and correlate the results with Knee Arthroscopy.while the suspected cases of meniscal extrusion will make MRI using the knee coil for varus stress Overloading simulating weight bearing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic Resonance Imaging of the knee</intervention_name>
    <description>After clinical assessment, all the patients will examined by Magnetic Resonance Imaging to diagnose the medial meniscal posterior root tear,and the suspected cases of meniscal extrusion will make MRI using the knee coil for varus stress Overloading simulating weight bearing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Magnetic resonance imaging of the knee</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Knee Arthroscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlate all the magnetic resonance imaging results with the Knee Arthroscopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Magnetic resonance imaging of the knee</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of either sex from more than 16 years, having acute or chronic painful knee
             associated with popping sounds are included in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are contraindicated to Magnetic Resonance Imaging examination as those
             who have artificial cardiac pacemaker or metallic prosthesis not compatible with
             Magnetic Resonance Imaging or those with severe claustrophobia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nisreen A. Abbas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Afaf A. Kader, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00201095229303</phone>
    <email>Drafaf.kader@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hosam E. Deen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00201014269335</phone>
    <email>h.elmalah@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barile A, Conti L, Lanni G, Calvisi V, Masciocchi C. Evaluation of medial meniscus tears and meniscal stability: weight-bearing MRI vs arthroscopy. Eur J Radiol. 2013 Apr;82(4):633-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ejrad.2012.10.018. Epub 2012 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23199751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Park HJ, Kim SS, Lee SY, Choi YJ, Chung EC, Rho MH, Kwag HJ. Medial meniscal root tears and meniscal extrusion transverse length ratios on MRI. Br J Radiol. 2012 Nov;85(1019):e1032-7. doi: 10.1259/bjr/26261821.</citation>
    <PMID>23091292</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carreau JH, Sitton SE, Bollier M. Medial Meniscus Root Tear in the Middle Aged Patient: A Case Based Review. Iowa Orthop J. 2017;37:123-132.</citation>
    <PMID>28852346</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Costa CR, Morrison WB, Carrino JA. Medial meniscus extrusion on knee MRI: is extent associated with severity of degeneration or type of tear? AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2004 Jul;183(1):17-23.</citation>
    <PMID>15208101</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>AAQardash</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

