<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03636763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-29</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03636763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dipeptidyl Peptidase-IV Inhibitors, Risk Factor for Development of Bullous Pemphigoid?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dipeptidyl Peptidase-IV Inhibitors, Risk Factor for Development of Bullous Pemphigoid? : Multicenter Retrospective Study in France and Switzerland</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bullous pemphigoid (BP) is the most common autoimmune bullous dermatosis. It mainly affects
      the elderly, and its cutaneous manifestations are extremely varied. Since the publication of
      the first case of PB associated with sulfasalazine in 1970, several drugs have been reported
      for their potential link with the development of PB. Recently, cases of PB associated with
      dipeptidyl peptidase-IV (DPP4) inhibitors, also known as gliptins, have been reported. DPP4
      inhibitors are oral antidiabetic agents prescribed to patients with type 2 diabetes, as
      monotherapy, in combination with other oral antidiabetic agents or with insulin.

      In recent years, an increasing number of cases have been published, describing the potential
      role of gliptins in PB induction. All these clinical cases and pharmacovigilance analyzes
      tend to show an increased risk of developing BP in case of gliptin exposure.

      The main objective is to evaluate the risk of developing a PB under DPP4 inhibitor treatment,
      comparing cases of diabetic patients with BP, to matched diabetic controls for sex and age,
      from French departments. Endocrinology in a retrospective study from 1 January 2014 to 31
      July 2016.

      The study will be conducted using databases of clinical and histological records. The
      investigators will perform a retrospective 1: 2 case-control study comparing cases with type
      2 diabetes and BP to matched diabetic controls for sex and age, randomly drawn from French
      endocrinology departments (Marseille La Conception ) and Switzerland (Bern), between January
      1, 2014 and July 31, 2016. the investigators will compare gliptin exposure in the
      case-control group versus the control group, adjusting for potential confounding bias using
      models. logistic regression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bullous pemphigoid (BP) is the most common autoimmune bullous dermatosis. It mainly affects
      the elderly, and its cutaneous manifestations are extremely varied. Since the publication of
      the first case of PB associated with sulfasalazine in 1970, several drugs (spironolactone,
      furosemide, chloroquine, beta-blockers and various antibiotics) have been reported for their
      potential link with the development of PB. Recently, cases of PB associated with dipeptidyl
      peptidase-IV (DPP4) inhibitors, also known as gliptins, have been reported. DPP4 inhibitors
      are oral antidiabetic agents prescribed to patients with type 2 diabetes, as monotherapy, in
      combination with other oral antidiabetic agents or with insulin.

      Problem raised:

      In recent years, an increasing number of cases have been published, describing the potential
      role of gliptins in PB induction. All these clinical cases and pharmacovigilance analyzes
      tend to show an increased risk of developing BP in case of gliptin exposure, but this
      hypothesis has not yet been confirmed by a quality controlled study.

      Goal:

      The main objective is to evaluate the risk of developing a PB under DPP4 inhibitor treatment,
      comparing cases of diabetic patients with BP, to matched diabetic controls for sex and age,
      from French departments. Endocrinology (Marseille La Conception) and Dermatologie (Marseille
      North, Marseille La Timone) and Swiss (Bern), in a retrospective study from 1 January 2014 to
      31 July 2016.

      Material and methods:

      The study will be conducted in three university departments of Dermatology (Marseille North,
      Marseille La Timone, Bern), using databases of clinical and histological records. The
      investigators will perform a retrospective 1: 2 case-control study comparing cases with type
      2 diabetes and BP to matched diabetic controls for sex and age, randomly drawn from French
      endocrinology departments (Marseille La Conception ) and Switzerland (Bern), between January
      1, 2014 and July 31, 2016. The investigators will compare gliptin exposure in the
      case-control group versus the control group, adjusting for potential confounding bias using
      models. logistic regression.

      Criteria for inclusion:

        -  Case: Patients from three university departments of Dermatology (Marseille North,
           Marseille La Timone, Bern) with type 2 diabetes, and a diagnosis of PB diagnosed for the
           first time between January 1, 2014 and July 31, 2016. The diagnosis of PB is based on
           compatible clinical presentation, compatible histology, positive direct
           immunofluorescence (IFD), and in some cases positive indirect immunofluorescence (IFI)
           and / or the presence of autoantibodies (BP180 and / or BP230) by ELISA.

        -  Witnesses: Patients from two university departments of Endocrinology (Marseille La
           Conception and Bern) with type 2 diabetes, and matched 1: 2 to cases for sex and age.

      Exclusion criteria:

        -  Case: Patients with another bullous dermatosis, not meeting the inclusion criteria.
           Patients biopsied before consultation in University Hospital, or patients seen in
           private dermatology practices.

        -  Witnesses: Patients suffering at the time of inclusion of a chronic dermatosis, in
           particular of a bullous dermatosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>numbers of patients exposed to gliptin</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>numbers of patients exposed to gliptin developing a Bullous pemphigoid</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">183</enrollment>
  <condition>Bullous Pemphigoid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bullous pemphigoid and diabetes 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with Bullous pemphigoid and diabete type 2 data report about gliptin exposure will be performed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diabete type 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with diabetes type 2 data report about gliptin exposure will be performed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>data report</intervention_name>
    <description>the information &quot;gliptin exposure&quot; will be reported</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bullous pemphigoid and diabetes 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>diabete type 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>gliptin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients from three university departments of Dermatology with type 2 diabetes and a
        diagnosis of PB diagnosed for the first time between January 1, 2014 and July 31, 2016
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Case: Patients from three university departments of Dermatology (Marseille North, Marseille
        La Timone, Bern) with type 2 diabetes, and a diagnosis of PB diagnosed for the first time
        between January 1, 2014 and July 31, 2016. The diagnosis of PB is based on compatible
        clinical presentation, compatible histology, positive direct immunofluorescence (IFD), and
        in some cases positive indirect immunofluorescence (IFI) and / or the presence of
        autoantibodies (BP180 and / or BP230) by ELISA.

        - Witnesses: Patients from two university departments of Endocrinology (Marseille La
        Conception and Bern) with type 2 diabetes, and matched 1: 2 to cases for sex and age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Case: Patients with another bullous dermatosis, not meeting the inclusion criteria.
        Patients biopsied before consultation in University Hospital, or patients seen in private
        dermatology practices.

        Witnesses: Patients suffering at the time of inclusion of a chronic dermatosis, in
        particular of a bullous dermatosis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>EMILIE GARRIDO PRADALIE</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>APHM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Joseph BENZAQUEN</last_name>
    <phone>+33 491964962</phone>
    <email>MICHAEL.BENZAQUEN@ap-hm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance Publique Des Hopitaux de Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <state>Paca</state>
        <zip>13354</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MICHAEL BENZAQUEN</last_name>
      <phone>+33 491964962</phone>
      <email>MICHAEL.BENZAQUEN@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pemphigoid, Bullous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

