<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03632278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSEARS20180531001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03632278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mindfulness Psychoeducation Program for Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effectiveness of a Mindfulness Psychoeducation Program on Emotional Regulation for People With Schizophrenia: A Pilot Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New Life Psychiatric Rehabilitation Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is the first pilot randomised controlled trial (RCT) to explore the feasibility and
      efficacy of Mindfulness-based psychoeducation in emotion regulation and related depressive
      and anxiety symptoms in people with schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is increasing evidence to demonstrate the safety and effectiveness of mindfulness-based
      psychoeducation programme (MBPP) for Chinese people with schizophrenia. A single-blind,
      multi-site, pragmatic randomised controlled trial conducted in Hong Kong, mainland China, and
      Taiwan with 300 participants consistently demonstrated significant improvement in regard to
      insight of illness, functioning, mental state and the length of re-hospitalisations when
      compared with conventional psychoeducation and Treatment As Usual (TAU) groups (Chien, 2017).

      The study hypothesises that:

        1. Participants receiving MBPP will decrease their use of rumination and expressive
           suppression, and increase the use of cognitive reappraisal compared to a control group
           after completion of the intervention.

        2. Participants receiving MBPP attain a reduction in depressive/anxiety symptoms compared
           to a control group after completion of the intervention.

        3. These effects are expected to be maintained through 3-month follow up with regular
           self-practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants referred to the study will be assessed at a screening examination to ensure eligibility and obtain written consent from a research assistant.
Eligible participants will be randomly assigned to receive Mindfulness psychoeducation programme (MBPP) plus TAU or TAU.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Emotion regulation questionnaire (ERQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clients will be followed up and assessed at baseline, immediately after 8 weeks of MBI intervention (post-intervention), and 3 months post-intervention by the assessor who will be blind to participant allocation</time_frame>
    <description>This is a self-report questionnaire that measures two different emotion regulation patterns: cognitive reappraisal and expressive suppression. The questionnaire has 10 items: six items reflect the reappraisal factor and four items reflect the suppressive factor. The 10 items are rated on a scale from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short Ruminative Response Scale (SRRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clients will be followed up and assessed at baseline, immediately after 8 weeks of MBI intervention (post-intervention), and 3 months post-intervention by the assessor who will be blind to participant allocation</time_frame>
    <description>It comprises 10 items that are symptom-focused, self-focused, or focused on the possible causes and consequences of the depressive mood. Participants will be asked to rate on a four-point Likert scale, resulting in a possible range of scores from 22 to 88, with a higher score implying a higher level of rumination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS-21)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clients will be followed up and assessed at baseline, immediately after 8 weeks of MBI intervention (post-intervention), and 3 months post-intervention by the assessor who will be blind to participant allocation</time_frame>
    <description>This instrument comprises three subscales including Depression, Anxiety, and Stress. The Depression scale assesses dysphoria, hopelessness, devaluation of life, self-deprecation, lack of interest or involvement, anhedonia and inertia. The Anxiety scale assesses autonomic arousal, skeletal muscle effects, situational anxiety and subjective experience of anxious affect. The stress scale is sensitive to levels of chronic non-specific arousal. Each subscale consists of seven items. The severity ratings are made on a series of 4-point (0 to 3) scales (0 = did not apply to me at all, 3 = applied to me very much, or most of the time). The higher the subscale scores the more severe the symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Chinese version of the Psychotic Symptom Rating Scale (C-PSYRATS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clients will be followed up and assessed at baseline, immediately after 8 weeks of MBI intervention (post-intervention), and 3 months post-intervention by the assessor who will be blind to participant allocation</time_frame>
    <description>C-PSYRATS consists of 17 items assessing the specific dimensions of hallucinations and delusions, with each item being rated on a 5-point scale from 0 (Absent) to 4 (Severe/Often/Extreme). There are two subscales including the auditory hallucinations subscale (AHS) consisting of 11 items, and the delusions subscale (DS) composed six items. The scale measures the subjective characteristics of AHS and DS including their nature, persistence, amount, distress, disruption and controllability toward the symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Social and Occupational Functioning Assessment Scale (SOFAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clients will be followed up and assessed at baseline, immediately after 8 weeks of MBI intervention (post-intervention), and 3 months post-intervention by the assessor who will be blind to participant allocation</time_frame>
    <description>It is a single-item scale ranging from 1 to 100, with higher scores indicating higher functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire - Short form (FFMQ-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clients will be followed up and assessed at baseline, immediately after 8 weeks of MBI intervention (post-intervention), and 3 months post-intervention by the assessor who will be blind to participant allocation</time_frame>
    <description>The FFMQ-SF is a 20-item questionnaire that measures five facets of mindfulness including observing, describing, acting with awareness, nonjudging, and non-reacting (Baer, Smith, Hopkins, Krietemeyer, &amp; Toney, 2006). Items are scored on a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (never/very rarely true) to 5 (very often/always true). Higher scores indicate greater levels of mindfulness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophreniform Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness psychoeducation programme</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A MBPP will be conducted for 2 hours for each session, one a week for ten weeks, with 13-15 participants per group. The protocol has been developed based on the model of mindfulness-based stress reduction proposed by Kabat-Zinn (1994) and Tong et al. (2015), and the psychoeducation programmes by Chien and Lee, and Lehman and colleagues (Chien &amp; Lee, 2010; Kabat-Zinn et al., 1992; Lehman et al., 2004; Tong et al., 2015).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The usual care group will receive routine psychiatric outpatient services, including monthly psychiatric consultation and treatment by a psychiatrist, psychiatric nursing advice and brief education according to the patient's psychosocial needs. There will be community mental health services, social welfare or financial assistance supported by medical social workers, whenever necessary.
Participants in this control may be aware that they are receiving no extra treatment which may result in negative expectancies and inflation of the treatment effect (Stoney &amp; Johnson, 2012). To eliminate the time effect and artificially inflated intervention effect, patients in the control group will receive telephone contact once a week to discuss their disease process and daily issues.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness psychoeducation Programme</intervention_name>
    <description>A MBPP will be conducted for 2 hours for each session, one a week for eight weeks. The protocol has been developed based on the model of mindfulness-based stress reduction proposed by Kabat-Zinn (1994) and Tong et al. (2015), and the psychoeducation programmes by Chien and Lee, and Lehman and colleagues (Chien &amp; Lee, 2010; Kabat-Zinn et al., 1992; Lehman et al., 2004; Tong et al., 2015).
The programme will be integration of mindfulness and psychoeducation to cultivate the client's mindfulness attitude. The clients will learn to apply the mindfulness in illness management and daily difficulties.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness psychoeducation programme</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 years to 65 years old

          -  Diagnosis with schizophrenia-spectrum disorders according to the criteria of the
             Diagnostic and Statistical Manual for Mental Disorders DSM-IV-TR (and the latest
             DSM-V) or International Classification of Diseases (ICD-10)-Classification of Mental
             Disorders

          -  Able to communicate in written and conversational Chinese/Cantonese

          -  Able to understand the concepts of the study and to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Comorbid organic brain disorders or substance abuse

          -  Participation in any forms of cognitive therapy

          -  Participation and/or practice of mindfulness (in the forms of Tai Chi, Qi Gong, etc.)
             more than twice a week during the previous three months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ho Yan Lam</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ho Yan Lam</last_name>
    <phone>852 3917 6975</phone>
    <email>angielam@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New Life Assocation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheang Detty</last_name>
      <phone>2778 4503</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henry JD, Rendell PG, Green MJ, McDonald S, O'Donnell M. Emotion regulation in schizophrenia: affective, social, and clinical correlates of suppression and reappraisal. J Abnorm Psychol. 2008 May;117(2):473-478. doi: 10.1037/0021-843X.117.2.473.</citation>
    <PMID>18489225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aldao A, Nolen-Hoeksema S, Schweizer S. Emotion-regulation strategies across psychopathology: A meta-analytic review. Clin Psychol Rev. 2010 Mar;30(2):217-37. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2009.11.004. Epub 2009 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20015584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chien WT, Lee IY, Wang LQ. A Chinese version of the Psychotic Symptom Rating Scales: psychometric properties in recent-onset and chronic psychosis. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2017 Mar 8;13:745-753. doi: 10.2147/NDT.S131174. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28331325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chien WT, Thompson DR. Effects of a mindfulness-based psychoeducation programme for Chinese patients with schizophrenia: 2-year follow-up. Br J Psychiatry. 2014 Jul;205(1):52-9. doi: 10.1192/bjp.bp.113.134635. Epub 2014 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24809397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crawford JR, Henry JD. The Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS): normative data and latent structure in a large non-clinical sample. Br J Clin Psychol. 2003 Jun;42(Pt 2):111-31.</citation>
    <PMID>12828802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hou J, Wong SY, Lo HH, Mak WW, Ma HS. Validation of a Chinese version of the Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire in Hong Kong and development of a short form. Assessment. 2014 Jun;21(3):363-71. doi: 10.1177/1073191113485121. Epub 2013 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23596271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norton PJ. Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS-21): psychometric analysis across four racial groups. Anxiety Stress Coping. 2007 Sep;20(3):253-65.</citation>
    <PMID>17999228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Driscoll C, Laing J, Mason O. Cognitive emotion regulation strategies, alexithymia and dissociation in schizophrenia, a review and meta-analysis. Clin Psychol Rev. 2014 Aug;34(6):482-95. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2014.07.002. Epub 2014 Jul 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25105273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang H, &amp; Xu Y. Reliability and Validity of the Chinese Short Ruminative Responses Scale (SRRS) in Chinese Undergraduates. Psychological research(3):34-39. 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao X, Zhang BR, Zhang HP, Pan L, &amp; Zhou RL. Reliability and validity of emotion regulation questionnaire in middle school students. Chinese Journal of Clinical Psychology(1). 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lam AHY, &amp; Chien WT. The effectiveness of mindfulness-based intervention for people with schizophrenia: a systematic review. Neuropsychiatry (London), 6(5): 208-222. 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chien WT, Bressington D, Yip A, Karatzias T. An international multi-site, randomized controlled trial of a mindfulness-based psychoeducation group programme for people with schizophrenia. Psychol Med. 2017 Sep;47(12):2081-2096. doi: 10.1017/S0033291717000526. Epub 2017 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28374661</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>LAM Ho Yan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

