<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03630224</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P160919J</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-004206-17</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03630224</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plasmalyte Versus Saline in Trauma Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASTRAU</acronym>
  <official_title>Renal Effects of Fluid Resuscitation With Plasmalyte Viaflo Versus Saline in Trauma Patients (the ASTRAU Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fluid resuscitation remains the cornerstone for the care of severe trauma patients to
      compensate for blood loss, to compensate for capillary leak induced by systemic inflammation
      but also to prevent the detrimental consequences of traumatic rhabdomyolysis. Isotonic saline
      (NaCl 0.9%), called &quot;physiological serum&quot; is the standard fluid for the resuscitation of
      severely injured patients. However, the formulation of NaCl 0.9% is not really physiological
      since its chloride concentration is 1.5 higher than the one of human plasma. This excessive
      chloride concentration leads to hyperchloremic acidosis and to a drop in renal perfusion
      after isotonic saline infusion. For this reason, we wonder whether fluid resuscitation with
      Plasmalyte would be beneficial for renal function of trauma patients in comparison with NaCl
      0.9%. Our research question is:

      In a population of trauma patients at high risk of acute kidney injury, does a fluid
      resuscitation with Plasmalyte Viaflo lower the incidence of severe acute kidney injury (stage
      2 or 3 according to the KDIGO classification) compared with a resuscitation with isotonic
      saline (NaCl 0.9%)?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fluid resuscitation remains the cornerstone for the care of severe trauma patients to
      compensate for blood loss, to compensate for capillary leak induced by systemic inflammation
      but also to prevent the detrimental consequences of traumatic rhabdomyolysis. Isotonic saline
      (NaCl 0.9%), called &quot;physiological serum&quot; is the standard fluid for the resuscitation of
      severely injured patients. However, the formulation of NaCl 0.9% is not really physiological
      since its chloride concentration is 1.5 higher than plasma. This excessive chloride
      concentration leads to hyperchloremic acidosis and to a drop in renal perfusion after
      isotonic saline infusion. A retrospective study conducted in the perioperative setting
      (abdominal surgery) reported a significant decrease in mortality and acute kidney injury in
      926 patients receiving balanced crystalloid solution compared to a propensity-matched
      population of 2778 patients receiving isotonic saline. Yunos et al. conducted a prospective
      sequential period study including 760 patients receiving chloride-rich solution during the
      first 6-month period and 773 patients receiving chloride-poor solution during the next
      6-month period. They reported a decrease in severe acute kidney injury (I or F in the RIFLE
      classification) in the group receiving chloride-poor solution. Large retrospective studies in
      intensive care confirmed a beneficial effect of the use of chloride-poor solutions on
      survival compared to chloride-rich solutions. A recent meta-analysis including 5 small size
      randomized controlled trials, 1 controlled trial and two retrospective studies, reported also
      a decrease in acute kidney injury. A recent multicenter study randomized 2778 patients to
      receive either Plasmalyte 148 or NaCl 0.9% during their ICU stay. No AKI or mortality
      differences were reported. However, this study included patients with low ICU severity score
      (mean APACHE II = 14) and at low risk of severe AKI (severe AKI incidence = 9%). Moreover,
      they received a median amount of fluid of 2000 mL during their ICU stay. This small fluid
      volume may not be enough to show any difference between rich-chloride and poor-chloride
      solutions on AKI in this population with low ICU severity scores.

      Trauma patients are particularly at risk of AKI during the acute phase of trauma because of
      hypovolemia (bleeding), rhabdomyolysis and systemic inflammation (traumatic tissue injuries
      and emergency surgeries). AKI is reported in 18 to 26 % of trauma patients. In our database
      (TraumaBase®, traumabase.eu) that included at the time of the study the 6 trauma centers of
      the Paris area (France), we reported a 24% incidence of severe AKI (stage I or F of the RIFLE
      classification) in the subpopulation of patients needing at least one red blood cell unit
      transfusion in the 6 first hours of care. Moreover, this subpopulation receives an average
      amount of 6000 mL of fluid during the first 24 hours of care. We postulate that trauma
      patients at high risk of AKI receiving high volume of fluid can be the best population target
      to demonstrate a beneficial effect of Plasmalyte vs isotonic saline on severe AKI occurrence
      in a prospective, blinded, randomized manner.

      Thus, we formulate the following hypothesis:

      In a population of trauma patients, at high risk of AKI, a fluid resuscitation with
      Plasmalyte Viaflo during the 5 first days of care will lower decrease the incidence of severe
      acute kidney injury (stage 2 or 3 according to the KDIGO classification) compared with a
      resuscitation with isotonic saline (NaCl 0.9%)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 24, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 7, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Acute Kidney Injury (stage 2 or 3 according to KDIGO classification) over the 5 first days after trauma</measure>
    <time_frame>over the 5 first days after trauma</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients requiring renal replacement therapy (during 28 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>during 28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of transfused blood product units (during the first 5 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>during the first 5 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days alive without free of mechanical ventilation (during 28 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>during 28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days spent alive outside the ICU (during 28 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>during 28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>at 28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between the serum creatinine peak in the 5 first days of ICU stay and the baseline creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>during the 5 first days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">622</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Trauma Patients</condition>
  <condition>Acute Kidney Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plasmalyte Viaflo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention type: drug (Plasmalyte Viaflo) Intervention name: plasmalyte Intervention description: fluid resuscitation using exclusively Plasmalyte up to 20L during the first 5 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NaCl 0.9%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention type: drug (NaCl 0.9%) Intervention name: NaCl 0.9% Intervention description: fluid resuscitation using exclusively NaCl 0.9% up to 20L during the first 5 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plasmalyte Viaflo</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention description: fluid resuscitation using exclusively Plasmalyte up to 20L during the first 5 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Plasmalyte Viaflo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NaCl 0.9%</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention name: NaCl 0.9% Intervention description: fluid resuscitation using exclusively NaCl 0.9% up to 20L during the first 5 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>NaCl 0.9%</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe trauma defined by at least one Vittel criteria

          -  Indication for at least one red blood cell unit transfusion within 6 hours after
             trauma

          -  Delay between trauma and study randomization ≤ 6 hours

          -  Patient able to give consent or included in emergency situation

          -  Patient affiliated to Health security system

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years

          -  Chronic kidney disease needing requiring renal replacement therapy

          -  Participation to another interventional trial

          -  Fluid resuscitation &gt; 4000 mL before inclusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacques DURANTEAU</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacques DURANTEAU, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33(0)145213441</phone>
    <email>jacques.duranteau@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anatole HARROIS, MD</last_name>
    <email>harroisanatole@yahoo.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Département d'Anesthésie Réanimation - Kremlin Bicêtre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Kremlin-Bicêtre</city>
        <zip>94270</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacques DURANTEAU, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chowdhury AH, Cox EF, Francis ST, Lobo DN. A randomized, controlled, double-blind crossover study on the effects of 2-L infusions of 0.9% saline and plasma-lyte® 148 on renal blood flow velocity and renal cortical tissue perfusion in healthy volunteers. Ann Surg. 2012 Jul;256(1):18-24. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e318256be72. Erratum in: Ann Surg. 2013 Dec;258(6):1118.</citation>
    <PMID>22580944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw AD, Bagshaw SM, Goldstein SL, Scherer LA, Duan M, Schermer CR, Kellum JA. Major complications, mortality, and resource utilization after open abdominal surgery: 0.9% saline compared to Plasma-Lyte. Ann Surg. 2012 May;255(5):821-9. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31825074f5.</citation>
    <PMID>22470070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yunos NM, Bellomo R, Hegarty C, Story D, Ho L, Bailey M. Association between a chloride-liberal vs chloride-restrictive intravenous fluid administration strategy and kidney injury in critically ill adults. JAMA. 2012 Oct 17;308(15):1566-72. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.13356.</citation>
    <PMID>23073953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw AD, Raghunathan K, Peyerl FW, Munson SH, Paluszkiewicz SM, Schermer CR. Association between intravenous chloride load during resuscitation and in-hospital mortality among patients with SIRS. Intensive Care Med. 2014 Dec;40(12):1897-905. doi: 10.1007/s00134-014-3505-3. Epub 2014 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>25293535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raghunathan K, Shaw A, Nathanson B, Stürmer T, Brookhart A, Stefan MS, Setoguchi S, Beadles C, Lindenauer PK. Association between the choice of IV crystalloid and in-hospital mortality among critically ill adults with sepsis*. Crit Care Med. 2014 Jul;42(7):1585-91. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000000305.</citation>
    <PMID>24674927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw AD, Schermer CR, Lobo DN, Munson SH, Khangulov V, Hayashida DK, Kellum JA. Impact of intravenous fluid composition on outcomes in patients with systemic inflammatory response syndrome. Crit Care. 2015 Sep 12;19:334. doi: 10.1186/s13054-015-1045-z. Erratum in: Crit Care. 2016;20:17.</citation>
    <PMID>26370823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krajewski ML, Raghunathan K, Paluszkiewicz SM, Schermer CR, Shaw AD. Meta-analysis of high- versus low-chloride content in perioperative and critical care fluid resuscitation. Br J Surg. 2015 Jan;102(1):24-36. doi: 10.1002/bjs.9651. Epub 2014 Oct 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25357011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young P, Bailey M, Beasley R, Henderson S, Mackle D, McArthur C, McGuinness S, Mehrtens J, Myburgh J, Psirides A, Reddy S, Bellomo R; SPLIT Investigators; ANZICS CTG. Effect of a Buffered Crystalloid Solution vs Saline on Acute Kidney Injury Among Patients in the Intensive Care Unit: The SPLIT Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA. 2015 Oct 27;314(16):1701-10. doi: 10.1001/jama.2015.12334. Erratum in: JAMA. 2015 Dec 15;314(23):2570.</citation>
    <PMID>26444692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagshaw SM, George C, Gibney RT, Bellomo R. A multi-center evaluation of early acute kidney injury in critically ill trauma patients. Ren Fail. 2008;30(6):581-9. doi: 10.1080/08860220802134649.</citation>
    <PMID>18661407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bihorac A, Delano MJ, Schold JD, Lopez MC, Nathens AB, Maier RV, Layon AJ, Baker HV, Moldawer LL. Incidence, clinical predictors, genomics, and outcome of acute kidney injury among trauma patients. Ann Surg. 2010 Jul;252(1):158-65. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181deb6bc.</citation>
    <PMID>20562612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute kidney injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluid resuscitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Sodium chloride</keyword>
  <keyword>Plasmalyte</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plasma-lyte 148</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

