<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03632785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FAPESP 2014/01021-4 - Subp. 1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03632785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laboratory Implications of Non Obstructive Atherosclerotic Plaques Identified by Multiple Detector Coronary Angiotomography</brief_title>
  <official_title>Laboratory Implications of Non Obstructive Atherosclerotic Plaques Identified by Multiple Detector Coronary Angiotomography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 50% of coronary events occur in previously asymptomatic patients. Thus, the
      early detection of the individuals at higher risk became an important research target within
      the current cardiology. The various clinical scores used present a predictive accuracy for
      ischemic events, evaluated by the ROC curve, which ranges from 0.73 to 0, 79. Therefore, the
      introduction of new non-invasive techniques for the detection of atherosclerosis aims to
      allow a more adequate classification of risk. The development of radiological techniques,
      fundamentally coronary angiotomography of multiple detectors (CAMD) and electron beam
      computed tomography-EBCT‖, demonstrated that the degree of coronary calcification correlates
      with endothelial lesion and individual prognosis in the long term. Notably, the calcium score
      has a weak correlation with the severity of coronary stenosis per se, possibly due to
      variations in arterial remodeling due to coronary calcification. On the other hand, the CAMD
      allows the detection of a small magnitude atheromatous disease, not diagnosed clinically, nor
      by tests provoking ischemia, or even by coronary catheterization.

      The clinical relevance of the small magnitude atheromatous disease diagnosed by the ACMD and
      its correlation with plaque vulnerability markers, mainly platelet aggregation, vascular
      reactivity, and inflammation are still not well determined.

      This is a case and control study and we will enrolled 90 patients with low and medium risk of
      cardiovascular event whose cases should present discrete plaques in the CAMD e controls
      should present none plaque in coronary stenosis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Coronary atherosclerotic disease often begins in the transition from childhood to
      adolescence, progressing slowly and quietly. Its clinical manifestation occurs in the
      majority of cases from the 4th decade of life. However, it is important to remember that
      necropsy studies conducted in the 1970s identified the presence of non-obstructive
      atherosclerotic plaques in the aorta of individuals from the second decade of life.

      From its first description to the present day, the subject has been deeply studied, providing
      reliable information on several mechanisms involved in atherogenesis, disease progression and
      plaque unstabilization, which may occur in a silent manner or lead to a clinical picture of
      unstable myocardial ischemic syndrome (UMIS). In this period, classic risk factors for
      coronary artery disease (age, sex, diabetes mellitus, systemic arterial hypertension,
      hypercholesterolemia and smoking, among others) were described, and risk scores were
      developed that aid in the individual prediction of the probability of disease manifestation
      coronary artery disease (CAD).

      The most widespread of these scores is that developed from the population of Framingham,
      which was started in the United States of the same name after 1948. Subjects with no evidence
      of cardiovascular disease were followed prospectively with biannual evaluations. The data
      obtained allowed the elaboration of an algorithm of prediction of individual risk that is
      included in the most recent recommendations of evaluation of cardiovascular risk.

      However, these traditional clinical assessment scores tend to underestimate cardiovascular
      risk in some populations, especially in women and young individuals. In the global
      population, the various clinical scores used have a predictive accuracy for ischemic events,
      as assessed by the ROC (Receiver Operating Characteristic) curve, ranging from 0.73 to 0.79.

      In this way, the concept of &quot;detection interval&quot; is proposed. Defined by the difference
      between cases of coronary disease or cardiovascular events detected and the actual total
      prevalence of atherosclerotic disease in the population, such detection interval opens a new
      field for the introduction of new non-invasive atherosclerosis investigation techniques.

      Taking into account that approximately 50% of coronary events occur in previously
      asymptomatic patients, the early detection of these individuals at greater risk has become an
      important research target within the current cardiology.

      More recently, the development of radiologic techniques, fundamentally coronary angiography
      of multiple detectors (CAMD) and electron beam computed tomography (EBCT), have demonstrated
      that the degree of coronary calcification correlates with endothelial lesion and individual
      prognosis in the long term, allowing to refine the clinical classification of a patient's
      risk for a greater or lesser chance of fatal and non-fatal events. Notably, the calcium score
      has a weak correlation with the severity of coronary stenosis per se, possibly due to
      variations in the arterial remodeling due to coronary calcification.

      On the other hand, calcification of the coronary arteries is known to be associated with
      lower myocardial blood flow even in the absence of significant stenosis. This means that
      calcification is not merely a marker of obstructive coronary disease and may predispose
      patients to myocardial ischemia by mechanisms other than those traditionally known and may
      therefore be a marker of endothelial dysfunction.

      On the other hand, the application of CAMD allowed the detection of a small magnitude
      atheromatosis , not diagnosed clinically by the tests provoking ischemia or even by
      contrast-enhanced coronary angiography. The clinical relevance of these alterations,
      evaluated by their correlation with the presence of plaque vulnerability markers, mainly
      platelet aggregation, vascular reactivity, and inflammation, is still very little studied,
      being the main objective of this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 27, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet aggregation by VerifyNow System - P2Y12®</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing platelet aggregation by VerifyNow System - P2Y12® (An equipment from Accriva Diagnostics that evaluates platelet aggregation) in case and control groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet aggregation by Multiplate-ADP®, Multiplate-ASPI®</measure>
    <time_frame>1day</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing platelet aggregation by Adenosine Diphosphate pathway (ADP test) and by Arachidonic Acid pathway (ASPI test). Theses methods will be analyzed in case and control groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endothelial function</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing endothelial function by ENDOPAT 2000 method (is the leading medical device for noninvasive endothelial function assessment. It was developed and is distributed by Itamar Medical, Caesarea, Israel) in case and control groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet-reticulated</measure>
    <time_frame>1day</time_frame>
    <description>comparing platelet-reticulated analysis in the case and control groups;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory activity</measure>
    <time_frame>1day</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the inflammatory activity by Interleukin 6 (IL-6) and by Ultra-Sensitive C-Reactive Protein (us-CRP) in the case and control groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic polymorphisms</measure>
    <time_frame>1day</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the presence of genetic polymorphisms in the case and control groups;</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Transport of lipids to HDL</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing Transport of lipids to HDL in the case and control group</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlate results</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Correlate platelet aggregability with inflammatory markers and presence of polymorphisms; and. Comparing platelet aggregation among patients with or without calcium (in the ACMD) of the case group</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing platelet aggregation in subgroups</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing platelet aggregation in the case and control groups in the following subgroups:
Diabetics and non-diabetics;
Elderly (≥65 years) and not elderly;
Feminine and masculine genres;
With renal dysfunction (Clearance Creatinine &lt;60) and without renal dysfunction;
With statin and without statin.
Obese (IMC≥30) and non-obese
Smoking / non-smoking</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Global Risk Score</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing Global Risk Score (global risk of coronary heart disease - is a calculation of the absolute risk of having a coronary heart disease event in 10 years. Some variables are analyzed: Age (40-79 years), Gender (male or female), Total cholesterol (130-320mg/dL), HDL cholesterol(20-100mg/dL), Systolic blood pressure (90-200mmHg), Diastolic blood pressure (30-140mmHg), Treated for high blood pressure (Yes ou Not), Diabetes (Yes or Not) and Smoker (Yes or Not). After calculation we have a final number and its respective risk (%) of developing cardiovascular disease. With this, we classify the patient in Low risk(&lt; 5% to have coronary disease in 10 years), Moderate Risk ( Men ≥ 5% e ≤ 20% and Woman ≥ 5% e ≤ 10%) and High risk ( Men &gt;20% and Woman &gt; 10%). We will compare this Global Risk Score in case and control group.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Discrete Coronary Artery Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Angiography of Multiple Detectors</condition>
  <condition>Platelet Aggregation, Spontaneous</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood, plasma
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients older than 18 years, male and female with low and medium risk of cardiovascular
        disease without atherosclerotic disease manifest.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Low or Medium Risk of cardiovascular disease assessed by the Framingham criteria;

          -  That agrees to sign the Consent Form;

          -  Absence of known atherosclerotic disease;

          -  Patients in the case group should additionally present discrete plaques (s) evaluated
             by coronary angiotomography of multiple detectors (CAMD). Patients in the control
             group should be absent from any coronary atherosclerotic process to CAMD.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known atherosclerotic disease manifest;

          -  Previous acute coronary syndrome (ACS);

          -  Use of antiplatelet agents and / or anticoagulants;

          -  Use of NSAIDs and/or corticosteroids

          -  Known platelet dysfunction or platelets &lt;100,000 / μL or&gt; 450,000 / μL

          -  Hematocrit &lt;33% and &gt; 52%

          -  Hematological diseases;

          -  Liver disease;

          -  Known malignant neoplasm;

          -  Refusal to sign free and informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>José Carlos Nicolau</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>Sao Paulo</state>
        <zip>05403-900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lavi S, Bae JH, Rihal CS, Prasad A, Barsness GW, Lennon RJ, Holmes DR Jr, Lerman A. Segmental coronary endothelial dysfunction in patients with minimal atherosclerosis is associated with necrotic core plaques. Heart. 2009 Sep;95(18):1525-30. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2009.166017. Epub 2009 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19497916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Deanfield JE, Halcox JP, Rabelink TJ. Endothelial function and dysfunction: testing and clinical relevance. Circulation. 2007 Mar 13;115(10):1285-95. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17353456</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ross R, Harker L. Hyperlipidemia and atherosclerosis. Science. 1976 Sep 17;193(4258):1094-100.</citation>
    <PMID>822515</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wilson PW, D'Agostino RB, Levy D, Belanger AM, Silbershatz H, Kannel WB. Prediction of coronary heart disease using risk factor categories. Circulation. 1998 May 12;97(18):1837-47.</citation>
    <PMID>9603539</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Greenland P, Alpert JS, Beller GA, Benjamin EJ, Budoff MJ, Fayad ZA, Foster E, Hlatky MA, Hodgson JM, Kushner FG, Lauer MS, Shaw LJ, Smith SC Jr, Taylor AJ, Weintraub WS, Wenger NK, Jacobs AK, Smith SC Jr, Anderson JL, Albert N, Buller CE, Creager MA, Ettinger SM, Guyton RA, Halperin JL, Hochman JS, Kushner FG, Nishimura R, Ohman EM, Page RL, Stevenson WG, Tarkington LG, Yancy CW; American College of Cardiology Foundation; American Heart Association. 2010 ACCF/AHA guideline for assessment of cardiovascular risk in asymptomatic adults: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Dec 14;56(25):e50-103. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.09.001.</citation>
    <PMID>21144964</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nasir K, Michos ED, Blumenthal RS, Raggi P. Detection of high-risk young adults and women by coronary calcium and National Cholesterol Education Program Panel III guidelines. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2005 Nov 15;46(10):1931-6. Epub 2005 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16286182</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Akosah KO, Schaper A, Cogbill C, Schoenfeld P. Preventing myocardial infarction in the young adult in the first place: how do the National Cholesterol Education Panel III guidelines perform? J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 May 7;41(9):1475-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12742284</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kappagoda CT, Amsterdam EA. Assessment of risk for developing coronary heart disease in asymptomatic individuals. J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. 2009 Jul-Aug;29(4):207-19. doi: 10.1097/HCR.0b013e3181af6be5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19628986</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>O'Rourke RA, Brundage BH, Froelicher VF, Greenland P, Grundy SM, Hachamovitch R, Pohost GM, Shaw LJ, Weintraub WS, Winters WL Jr. American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Expert Consensus Document on electron-beam computed tomography for the diagnosis and prognosis of coronary artery disease. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 Jul;36(1):326-40. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10898458</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Expert Panel on Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Cholesterol in Adults. Executive Summary of The Third Report of The National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Expert Panel on Detection, Evaluation, And Treatment of High Blood Cholesterol In Adults (Adult Treatment Panel III). JAMA. 2001 May 16;285(19):2486-97.</citation>
    <PMID>11368702</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wang L, Jerosch-Herold M, Jacobs DR Jr, Shahar E, Detrano R, Folsom AR; MESA Study Investigators. Coronary artery calcification and myocardial perfusion in asymptomatic adults: the MESA (Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis). J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006 Sep 5;48(5):1018-26. Epub 2006 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>16949496</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Myerburg RJ, Interian A Jr, Mitrani RM, Kessler KM, Castellanos A. Frequency of sudden cardiac death and profiles of risk. Am J Cardiol. 1997 Sep 11;80(5B):10F-19F. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9291445</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Raggi P, Callister TQ, Cooil B, He ZX, Lippolis NJ, Russo DJ, Zelinger A, Mahmarian JJ. Identification of patients at increased risk of first unheralded acute myocardial infarction by electron-beam computed tomography. Circulation. 2000 Feb 29;101(8):850-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10694523</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Raggi P, Cooil B, Callister TQ. Use of electron beam tomography data to develop models for prediction of hard coronary events. Am Heart J. 2001 Mar;141(3):375-82.</citation>
    <PMID>11231434</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goldstein JA, Chinnaiyan KM, Abidov A, Achenbach S, Berman DS, Hayes SW, Hoffmann U, Lesser JR, Mikati IA, O'Neil BJ, Shaw LJ, Shen MY, Valeti US, Raff GL; CT-STAT Investigators. The CT-STAT (Coronary Computed Tomographic Angiography for Systematic Triage of Acute Chest Pain Patients to Treatment) trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Sep 27;58(14):1414-22. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.03.068.</citation>
    <PMID>21939822</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cheng VY, Lepor NE, Madyoon H, Eshaghian S, Naraghi AL, Shah PK. Presence and severity of noncalcified coronary plaque on 64-slice computed tomographic coronary angiography in patients with zero and low coronary artery calcium. Am J Cardiol. 2007 May 1;99(9):1183-6. Epub 2007 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17478137</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gurbel PA, Erlinge D, Ohman EM, Neely B, Neely M, Goodman SG, Huber K, Chan MY, Cornel JH, Brown E, Zhou C, Jakubowski JA, White HD, Fox KA, Prabhakaran D, Armstrong PW, Tantry US, Roe MT; TRILOGY ACS Platelet Function Substudy Investigators. Platelet function during extended prasugrel and clopidogrel therapy for patients with ACS treated without revascularization: the TRILOGY ACS platelet function substudy. JAMA. 2012 Nov 7;308(17):1785-94. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.17312.</citation>
    <PMID>23117779</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Price MJ, Berger PB, Teirstein PS, Tanguay JF, Angiolillo DJ, Spriggs D, Puri S, Robbins M, Garratt KN, Bertrand OF, Stillabower ME, Aragon JR, Kandzari DE, Stinis CT, Lee MS, Manoukian SV, Cannon CP, Schork NJ, Topol EJ; GRAVITAS Investigators. Standard- vs high-dose clopidogrel based on platelet function testing after percutaneous coronary intervention: the GRAVITAS randomized trial. JAMA. 2011 Mar 16;305(11):1097-105. doi: 10.1001/jama.2011.290. Erratum in: JAMA. 2011 Jun 1;305(21);2174. Stillablower, Michael E [corrected to Stillabower, Michael E].</citation>
    <PMID>21406646</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Collet JP, Cuisset T, Rangé G, Cayla G, Elhadad S, Pouillot C, Henry P, Motreff P, Carrié D, Boueri Z, Belle L, Van Belle E, Rousseau H, Aubry P, Monségu J, Sabouret P, O'Connor SA, Abtan J, Kerneis M, Saint-Etienne C, Barthélémy O, Beygui F, Silvain J, Vicaut E, Montalescot G; ARCTIC Investigators. Bedside monitoring to adjust antiplatelet therapy for coronary stenting. N Engl J Med. 2012 Nov 29;367(22):2100-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1209979. Epub 2012 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23121439</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tantry US, Bonello L, Aradi D, Price MJ, Jeong YH, Angiolillo DJ, Stone GW, Curzen N, Geisler T, Ten Berg J, Kirtane A, Siller-Matula J, Mahla E, Becker RC, Bhatt DL, Waksman R, Rao SV, Alexopoulos D, Marcucci R, Reny JL, Trenk D, Sibbing D, Gurbel PA; Working Group on On-Treatment Platelet Reactivity. Consensus and update on the definition of on-treatment platelet reactivity to adenosine diphosphate associated with ischemia and bleeding. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Dec 17;62(24):2261-73. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.07.101. Epub 2013 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24076493</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kuvin JT, Patel AR, Sliney KA, Pandian NG, Sheffy J, Schnall RP, Karas RH, Udelson JE. Assessment of peripheral vascular endothelial function with finger arterial pulse wave amplitude. Am Heart J. 2003 Jul;146(1):168-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12851627</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hamburg NM, Benjamin EJ. Assessment of endothelial function using digital pulse amplitude tonometry. Trends Cardiovasc Med. 2009 Jan;19(1):6-11. doi: 10.1016/j.tcm.2009.03.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19467447</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jose Carlos Nicolau</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, PhD.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Platelet</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary angiography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plaque, Atherosclerotic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

