<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03634098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P171105j</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-A00311-54</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03634098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Identification and Validation of Noninvasive Biomarkers of the Diagnosis and Severity of NASH in Type 2 Diabetics</brief_title>
  <acronym>Quid-Nash</acronym>
  <official_title>Identification and Validation of Noninvasive Biomarkers (Virtual Biopsy) of the Diagnosis and Severity of NASH in Type 2 Diabetics: a Cross-sectional Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic diseases of the liver are silent affections whose morbidity is important. About 70%
      of patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D) are concerned. Of these, 50% develop clinically
      significant lesions (including non-alcoholic steatohepatitis or NASH) as they are associated
      with an increased risk of complications; and 15% progress to severe fibrosis or cirrhosis.
      These diseases are slowly progressive and asymptomatic. Their pathophysiology is poorly
      known. Management is hampered by the absence of a specific diagnostic marker, the need for
      invasive diagnostic procedures (liver biopsy), and the lack of established treatment.

      QUID-NASH aims to develop a virtual liver biopsy in T2D participants, based on the
      identification of single or combined, multimodal, non-invasive biomarkers obtained by new
      quantitative imaging techniques (magnetic resonance and ultrafast ultrasound UFUS); and /or
      extensive clinical-biological phenotyping data; and/or data obtained by different omic
      approaches (metabolomics, targeted genetics, transcriptomics). Extracellular vesicle and
      immune cell profiling will complement these phenotyping data. This approach will also enable
      us to improve our understanding of pathophysiology (new signaling pathways, new therapeutic
      targets).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic diseases of the liver are silent affections whose morbidity is important. About 70%
      of patients with type 2 diabetes (T2D) are concerned. Of these, 50% develop clinically
      significant lesions (including non-alcoholic steatohepatitis or NASH) as they are associated
      with an increased risk of complications; and 15% progress to severe fibrosis or cirrhosis.
      These diseases are slowly progressive and asymptomatic. Their pathophysiology is poorly
      known. Management is hampered by the absence of a specific diagnostic marker, the need for
      invasive diagnostic procedures (liver biopsy), and the lack of established treatment.
      Non-invasive methods (&quot;first-generation&quot; tests) have recently seen significant growth:
      commercialization of FibroTest as a marker of fibrosis; FibroTest, Fibrometer and FibroScan,
      for the initial assessment of adult chronic hepatitis C; FibroTest, Fibrometer, and Enhanced
      Liver Fibrosis test (ELF-test) for diagnosis of metabolic liver disease and diagnosis of
      fibrosis; SteatoTest (APHP patent) for the diagnosis of steatosis. The ActiTest (APHP patent)
      is widely used in evaluating the necrotic-inflammatory activity of chronic viral hepatitis C
      and B. For the diagnosis of NASH alone the ActiTest is validated. The NashTest (APHP patent)
      is little used. Several biomarkers of imaging (liver ultrasound, FibroScan Controller
      Attenuated Parameter (CAP), elastography and nuclear magnetic resonance) are widely used for
      the diagnosis of steatosis. Two new &quot;second generation&quot; blood tests (APHP patents) are under
      development, Non Invasive Test-NASHr (NIT-NASHr), and NIT-A2F2. NIT-NASHr is a new
      combination of the components of SteatoTest and NASH-Test to assess the severity of NASH.
      NIT-A2F2 is a combination of NIT-NASHr and FibroTest for the diagnosis of clinically
      significant liver metabolic disease. These tests will be the subject in the project of a
      validation of their performances in the context of use (T2D without other liver disease). At
      the same time, significant progress has been made in integrating omic data to characterize
      various pathologies and to identify their mechanisms. The transcriptomics and metabolomics of
      body fluids are particularly promising for the construction of &quot;third generation&quot; tests.

      QUID-NASH aims to develop a virtual liver biopsy in T2D participants, based on the
      identification of single or combined, multimodal, non-invasive biomarkers obtained by new
      quantitative imaging techniques (magnetic resonance and ultrafast ultrasound UFUS); and / or
      extensive clinical-biological phenotyping data; and / or data obtained by different omic
      approaches (metabolomics, targeted genetics, transcriptomics). Extracellular vesicle and
      immune cell profiling will complement this data. This approach will also enable us to improve
      knowledge of the pathology (new signaling pathways, new therapeutic targets).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 25, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To study in type 2 diabetic participants with liver biopsy, the performance of a composite biomarker (3rd generation test) for the diagnosis of NASH</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Histological diagnosis of NASH (as established by centralized re-reading of liver biopsy slides), blinded to omic results and imaging.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study in type 2 diabetic participants with or without liver biopsy, performance of a composite biomarker for the diagnosis of clinically significant metabolic liver diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>diagnosis of clinically significant liver metabolic disease (SAF-Score ≥A2 or ≥F2) adjudicated by an independent committee</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study in type 2 diabetic participants with liver biopsy, the performance of a single or composite biomarker for the diagnosis of NASH elemental lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>histological diagnosis of elementary lesions of NASH (lobular inflammation, ballooning, steatosis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study inter-center and intra-participants reproducibility of imaging measurements. a graphical evaluation will be conducted using a representation of Bland-Altman.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>By MRI: steatosis, biomechanical properties, T1, diffusivity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study inter-center and intra-participants reproducibility of imaging measurements.a graphical evaluation will be conducted using a representation of Bland-Altman.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>By AixPlorer ultrasound: steatosis, biomechanical properties, vascular properties</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study in type 2 diabetic participants the performance of second-generation tests for the diagnosis of metabolic liver diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>metabolic liver disease (adjudicated by an independent committee)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constitution of a bio-collection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>stool</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constitution of a bio-collection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constitution of a bio-collection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constitution of a bio-collection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>serum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constitution of a bio-collection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>mononuclear cells of peripheral blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constitution of a bio-collection</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Liver tissue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">820</enrollment>
  <condition>Type2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Exams performed on volunteers with other purpose than liver disease or diabetes in two centers:
MRI
Ultrasound AixPlorer These examinations are carried out in 2 differents centers at 1month intervals</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T2D liver test abnormalities's participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Exams performed on type 2 diabetic patients with liver test abnormalities :
sample for analysis and biocollection
MRI
Ultrasound AixPlorer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T2D participants without liver test abnormality</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>type 2 diabetic participants without liver test abnormality and not undergoing liver biopsy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>new quantitative imaging techniques</intervention_name>
    <description>magnetic resonance and ultrafast ultrasound UFUS</description>
    <arm_group_label>T2D liver test abnormalities's participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood sample</intervention_name>
    <description>extensive clinical-biological phenotyping data; and / or data obtained by different omic approaches (metabolomics, targeted genetics, transcriptomics). Extracellular vesicle and immune cell profiling will complement this data</description>
    <arm_group_label>T2D liver test abnormalities's participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>second generation tests</intervention_name>
    <description>second generation tests NIT-NASHr et NIT-A2F2</description>
    <arm_group_label>T2D liver test abnormalities's participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Pilot phase : Volunteers (for reproducibility study) Inclusion criteria

          -  Voluntary

          -  Person aged 18 or over

        Criteria for non-inclusion

          -  Refusal or inability to sign consent

          -  Vulnerable person according to article L1121-6 of the CSP

          -  Protected person of age

        Clinical Study of Clinically Significant NASH or NASH Markers Performance with Standard
        NASH Criteria (patient with liver biopsy) Inclusion criteria

          -  Participant aged 18 or over

          -  Diabetic type 2 (ADA / WHO criteria mentioned in section 20.5)

          -  Liver biopsy planned in day hospital (HDJ) as part of routine care (indication of
             biopsy: or ALT&gt; 30 IU for men or&gt; 20 IU for women less than 1 month old) and/or
             steatosis on ultrasound )

          -  Hemoglobin&gt; 7g / dL (or&gt; 10 g / dL in case of cardiovascular or respiratory pathology)

        Criteria for non-inclusion

          -  Refusal or inability to sign consent

          -  Vulnerable person: person deprived of liberty by a judicial or administrative
             decision, or subject to psychiatric care, and person admitted to a health or social
             institution for purposes other than that of research

          -  Protected person of age

          -  No affiliation or non-beneficiary of a social security scheme

          -  Pregnant or lactating woman

          -  Contraindication to MRI according to the French Society of Radiology (mentioned in
             section 20.4)

          -  Corpulence incompatible with the realization of an MRI

          -  Disease related to other etiologies

               -  Alcoholic liver disease

               -  Current infection of hepatitis B virus

               -  Current infection of hepatitis C virus

               -  Autoimmune hepatitis according to AASLD and EASL oTransferrin saturation&gt;50%

               -  Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency ZZ or SZ

               -  Wilson's disease

               -  Obstruction of the blood vessels or bile ducts on ultrasound (on routine
                  ultrasound If nothing is mentioned on the report, it is considered that there is
                  no obstruction of the vessels blood or bile ducts)

        Clinical study of the performance of second-generation tests for the diagnosis of metabolic
        liver disease: border population Inclusion criteria

          -  Consecutive patients aged 18 years or over

          -  Diabetic Type 2 (ADA / WHO criteria mentioned in section 20.5)

        Criteria for non-inclusion

          -  Refusal or inability to sign consent

          -  Vulnerable person: person deprived of liberty by a judicial or administrative
             decision, person under psychiatric care and person admitted to a health or social
             institution for purposes other than research

          -  Protected person of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laurent Castera</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>APHP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fadila Amerali</last_name>
    <phone>+33 1 44 84 17 17</phone>
    <email>fadila.amerali@ahph.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Beaujon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clichy</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurent Castera</last_name>
      <phone>1 40 87 50 00</phone>
      <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
      <email>laurent.castera@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dominique Valla</last_name>
      <phone>1 40 87 50 00</phone>
      <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patients</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

