<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03636880</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016H0451</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03636880</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heart Failure Insomnia Treatment Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>H-FITS</acronym>
  <official_title>Insomnia, Cognitive Impairment, and Decision Making Among Patients With Heart Failure:A Randomized Study of Brief Behavioral Treatment for Insomnia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare a short, behavioral treatment for insomnia with sleep
      monitoring to determine whether these approaches are effective in reducing insomnia and
      improving sleep quality among patients with heart failure (HF). This study will also examine
      the relationship between insomnia and cognitive functioning in HF and the effects of the
      behavioral treatment on cognitive functioning, self-care, distress, HF symptoms, and
      functional status.

      Participants will be randomly assigned to four-sessions of a behavioral treatment (Brief
      Behavioral Treatment for Insomnia; BBTI) or sleep monitoring.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Comorbid insomnia is prevalent among heart failure (HF) patients and associated with poorer
      mental and physical functioning, including possible exacerbation of cognitive deficits.
      Initial investigations document the effectiveness of cognitive-behavioral therapy for the
      treatment of insomnia in HF. However, the high symptom burden of HF necessitates alternative
      interventions for these patients with fewer time and physical endurance demands.

      Brief Behavioral Treatment for Insomnia (BBTI) is a four-session behavioral intervention that
      emphasizes stimulus control and sleep restriction techniques, along with providing education
      to patients about healthy sleep practices and behaviors that adversely affect sleep. The
      efficacy of BBTI has been previously documented in samples of older adults with insomnia, but
      the intervention has yet to be applied to a disease-specific patient population.

      This study was designed to 1) evaluate the treatment effects of BBTI on insomnia among HF
      patients, 2) examine the relationship between insomnia, cognitive function, and
      decision-making in HF patients at baseline, and 3) evaluate the effects of BBTI on relevant
      correlates of insomnia in HF patients, including cognitive functioning, decision-making,
      distress, self-care, quality of life, and functional status.

      Participants will be randomized to either the four-session behavioral intervention (BBTI) or
      a sleep monitoring condition. Measures of sleep (insomnia, sleep efficiency, sleep quality),
      cognitive functioning (memory, attention, executive functioning, and decision making),
      distress (anxiety and depression), HF-related quality of life, HF self-care, and functional
      status will be obtained from participants at baseline, post-intervention, and 6 months
      post-intervention. Repeated measures multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) will serve as
      the primary mode of data analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Baseline assessment is completed prior to randomization. Assessments conducted at 2 weeks and 6 months post-intervention are completed by an assessor blinded to participants' assigned condition.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insomnia severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Insomnia symptoms will be measured with the 7-item self-report Insomnia Severity Index (ISI). This measure assesses the severity of sleep-onset and sleep maintenance difficulties, sleep satisfaction, as well as associated daytime dysfunction and distress over the prior two weeks. Items are answered on a 5-point Likert-scale from 0 'not at all' to 4 'extremely'. Total scores range from 0 to 28, with higher scores reflective of greater insomnia severity. Scores of 8 or greater indicate the presence of at least mild clinical insomnia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality assessed by the PSQI</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality will be measured with the 19-item self-report Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). Seven component scores (subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbance, use of sleep medication, and daytime dysfunction) are derived from the instrument which can then be summed to produce a total 'global' PSQI score ranging from 0 to 21. Total PSQI scores greater than 5 indicate poor sleep quality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep efficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep efficiency (SE) will be measured with two-week sleep diaries where participants log their daily bed and wake times, as well as the number of hours of sleep each night. SE will be calculated as the percentage of sleep time divided by time spent in bed, with higher percentages indicative of more efficient sleep.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insomnia severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Insomnia symptoms will be measured with the 7-item self-report Insomnia Severity Index (ISI). This measure assesses the severity of sleep-onset and sleep maintenance difficulties, sleep satisfaction, as well as associated daytime dysfunction and distress over the prior two weeks. Items are answered on a 5-point Likert-scale from 0 'not at all' to 4 'extremely'. Total scores range from 0 to 28, with higher scores reflective of greater insomnia severity. Scores of 8 or greater indicate the presence of at least mild clinical insomnia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Executive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Executive function will be measured with the Trail Making Test (TMT), a paper-and-pencil neuropsychological instrument comprised of two parts, A and B. Time taken to complete each part is calculated in seconds, with longer times indicative of poorer performance. To minimize practice effects, comparable alternative forms will be used for post-intervention assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Memory will be measured with the Verbal Paired Associates I and II (VPAI and VPAII) tasks, subtests included in the Wechsler Memory Scale - Fourth Edition (WMS-IV) neuropsychological battery. VPAI assesses immediate recall of verbally-presented associated word pairs and VPAII measures delayed, long-term memory. Performance is evaluated by comparing the number of correctly recalled word pairs with age-based norms, with higher scores indicative of better verbal memory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attention and psychomotor performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Attention and psychomotor performance will be measured with the Coding task, a subtest included in the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale - Fourth Edition (WAIS-IV). Participants use a key to match as many numbers to corresponding nonsense symbols as possible within a two-minute time limit. Performance is evaluated by comparing the total number of correct matches to age-based norms, with higher scores indicative of better attention and psychomotor functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the IGT</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Iowa Gambling Task (IGT) produces a score representative of risky decision making by assessing participants' tendency to choose more disadvantageous over advantageous selections. For this measure, lower scores represent greater risky decision making.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the MCQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Monetary Choice Questionnaire (MCQ) is a measure of delay-discounting designed to assess preferences for smaller, more immediate rewards over larger, delayed rewards. An average score is produced based on participant responses to 27 trials, with higher values indicative of steeper discounting of delayed rewards and greater impulsivity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the GDT</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Game of Dice Task (GDT) produces a score representative of risky decision making by assessing participants' tendency to choose more disadvantageous over advantageous selections. For this measure, lower scores represent greater risky decision making.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety symptoms will be measured with the 14-item self-report Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). This instrument assesses symptoms of anxiety and depression specifically among patients with physical illnesses. Seven items assess symptoms of anxiety, while the remaining 7 items assess symptoms of depression. Each item is scored on a 4-point Likert-scale ranging from 0 to 3. Subscale scores, ranging from 0 to 21, can be calculated for anxiety and for depression, with higher scores indicative of greater symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Depressive symptoms will be measured with the 14-item self-report Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). This instrument assesses symptoms of anxiety and depression specifically among patients with physical illnesses. Seven items assess symptoms of anxiety, while the remaining 7 items assess symptoms of depression. Each item is scored on a 4-point Likert-scale ranging from 0 to 3. Subscale scores, ranging from 0 to 21, can be calculated for anxiety and for depression, with higher scores indicative of greater symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HF-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>HF-related quality of life will be measured with the 23-item self-report Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ), a HF-specific measure designed to quantify physical limitations, symptoms, and HF-related quality of life. The measure includes 9 subscales that can be combined into an overall summary score ranging from 0-100, with higher scores indicative of better functioning and fewer symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HF self-care</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>HF self-care will be measured with the 15-item self-report Self Care of Heart Failure Index (SCHFI). This instrument assesses patient's adherence to specific HF dietary and symptom monitoring guidelines, their confidence in adhering to these guidelines, and the steps they take when they notice changes in their symptom status. Three subscales (Management, Maintenance, and Confidence) are scored out of 100, with higher scores representing better self-care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Executive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Executive function will be measured with the Trail Making Test (TMT), a paper-and-pencil neuropsychological instrument comprised of two parts, A and B. Time taken to complete each part is calculated in seconds, with longer times indicative of poorer performance. To minimize practice effects, comparable alternative forms will be used for post-intervention assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Memory will be measured with the Verbal Paired Associates I and II (VPAI and VPAII) tasks, subtests included in the Wechsler Memory Scale - Fourth Edition (WMS-IV) neuropsychological battery. VPAI assesses immediate recall of verbally-presented associated word pairs and VPAII measures delayed, long-term memory. Performance is evaluated by comparing the number of correctly recalled word pairs with age-based norms, with higher scores indicative of better verbal memory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attention and psychomotor performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Attention and psychomotor performance will be measured with the Coding task, a subtest included in the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale - Fourth Edition (WAIS-IV). Participants use a key to match as many numbers to corresponding nonsense symbols as possible within a two-minute time limit. Performance is evaluated by comparing the total number of correct matches to age-based norms, with higher scores indicative of better attention and psychomotor functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the MCQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Monetary Choice Questionnaire (MCQ) is a measure of delay-discounting designed to assess preferences for smaller, more immediate rewards over larger, delayed rewards. An average score is produced based on participant responses to 27 trials, with higher values indicative of steeper discounting of delayed rewards and greater impulsivity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the GDT</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Game of Dice Task (GDT) produces a score representative of risky decision making by assessing participants' tendency to choose more disadvantageous over advantageous selections. For this measure, lower scores represent greater risky decision making.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Status</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 2 weeks post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Functional status will be measured with the Sixty-Foot Walk Test (60ftWT), an ambulatory measure that requires patients to walk four laps of 15 feet. Time needed to walk each of the four laps, as well as the total duration, is recorded in seconds, with higher completion times indicative of poorer functional status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insomnia severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Insomnia symptoms will be measured with the 7-item self-report Insomnia Severity Index (ISI). This measure assesses the severity of sleep-onset and sleep maintenance difficulties, sleep satisfaction, as well as associated daytime dysfunction and distress over the prior two weeks. Items are answered on a 5-point Likert-scale from 0 'not at all' to 4 'extremely'. Total scores range from 0 to 28, with higher scores reflective of greater insomnia severity. Scores of 8 or greater indicate the presence of at least mild clinical insomnia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality assessed by the PSQI</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality will be measured with the 19-item self-report Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). Seven component scores (subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbance, use of sleep medication, and daytime dysfunction) are derived from the instrument which can then be summed to produce a total 'global' PSQI score ranging from 0 to 21. Total PSQI scores greater than 5 indicate poor sleep quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep efficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep efficiency (SE) will be measured with two-week sleep diaries where participants log their daily bed and wake times, as well as the number of hours of sleep each night. SE will be calculated as the percentage of sleep time divided by time spent in bed, with higher percentages indicative of more efficient sleep.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety symptoms will be measured with the 14-item self-report Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). This instrument assesses symptoms of anxiety and depression specifically among patients with physical illnesses. Seven items assess symptoms of anxiety, while the remaining 7 items assess symptoms of depression. Each item is scored on a 4-point Likert-scale ranging from 0 to 3. Subscale scores, ranging from 0 to 21, can be calculated for anxiety and for depression, with higher scores indicative of greater symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Depressive symptoms will be measured with the 14-item self-report Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). This instrument assesses symptoms of anxiety and depression specifically among patients with physical illnesses. Seven items assess symptoms of anxiety, while the remaining 7 items assess symptoms of depression. Each item is scored on a 4-point Likert-scale ranging from 0 to 3. Subscale scores, ranging from 0 to 21, can be calculated for anxiety and for depression, with higher scores indicative of greater symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HF-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>HF-related quality of life will be measured with the 23-item self-report Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ), a HF-specific measure designed to quantify physical limitations, symptoms, and HF-related quality of life. The measure includes 9 subscales that can be combined into an overall summary score ranging from 0-100, with higher scores indicative of better functioning and fewer symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HF self-care</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>HF self-care will be measured with the 15-item self-report Self Care of Heart Failure Index (SCHFI). This instrument assesses patient's adherence to specific HF dietary and symptom monitoring guidelines, their confidence in adhering to these guidelines, and the steps they take when they notice changes in their symptom status. Three subscales (Management, Maintenance, and Confidence) are scored out of 100, with higher scores representing better self-care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Executive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Executive function will be measured with the Trail Making Test (TMT), a paper-and-pencil neuropsychological instrument comprised of two parts, A and B. Time taken to complete each part is calculated in seconds, with longer times indicative of poorer performance. To minimize practice effects, comparable alternative forms will be used for post-intervention assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attention and psychomotor performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Attention and psychomotor performance will be measured with the Coding task, a subtest included in the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale - Fourth Edition (WAIS-IV). Participants use a key to match as many numbers to corresponding nonsense symbols as possible within a two-minute time limit. Performance is evaluated by comparing the total number of correct matches to age-based norms, with higher scores indicative of better attention and psychomotor functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Memory will be measured with the Verbal Paired Associates I and II (VPAI and VPAII) tasks, subtests included in the Wechsler Memory Scale - Fourth Edition (WMS-IV) neuropsychological battery. VPAI assesses immediate recall of verbally-presented associated word pairs and VPAII measures delayed, long-term memory. Performance is evaluated by comparing the number of correctly recalled word pairs with age-based norms, with higher scores indicative of better verbal memory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the MCQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Monetary Choice Questionnaire (MCQ) is a measure of delay-discounting designed to assess preferences for smaller, more immediate rewards over larger, delayed rewards. An average score is produced based on participant responses to 27 trials, with higher values indicative of steeper discounting of delayed rewards and greater impulsivity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision making assessed by the GDT</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decision making will be measured with three self-administered computerized tasks. The Game of Dice Task (GDT) produces a score representative of risky decision making by assessing participants' tendency to choose more disadvantageous over advantageous selections. For this measure, lower scores represent greater risky decision making.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Status</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from pre-intervention to 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Functional status will be measured with the Sixty-Foot Walk Test (60ftWT), an ambulatory measure that requires patients to walk four laps of 15 feet. Time needed to walk each of the four laps, as well as the total duration, is recorded in seconds, with higher completion times indicative of poorer functional status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Failure</condition>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Insomnia</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Disorders of Initiating and Maintaining Sleep</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brief treatment for insomnia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brief Behavioral Treatment for Insomnia (BBTI) is a manualized, individual intervention designed to modify sleep patterns to reduce insomnia and improve sleep quality and efficiency. Participants complete two in-person meetings and two booster telephone calls over a four-week period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sleep Monitoring is an active comparator condition where participants track their sleep patterns for two weeks prior to the baseline and post-intervention assessments. They receive no contact from study staff during the intervening four-week period, except for a reminder call to begin completing the second sleep diary and to schedule the post-intervention assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brief treatment for Insomnia</intervention_name>
    <description>This behavioral intervention provides participants with an individualized plan to modify sleep patterns contributing to insomnia, as well as education about sleep hygiene and habits that help and hurt sleep.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brief treatment for insomnia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BBTI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sleep Monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention involves using sleep diaries to track daily aspects of sleep, including bed time, wake time, hours of sleep, nighttime awakenings, daytime naps, and sleep quality.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Fluent in English

          -  Diagnosis of heart failure

          -  At least mild chronic insomnia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Restless legs syndrome

          -  Narcolepsy

          -  Perform night or rotating shift work

          -  Seizure disorder

          -  Excessive daytime sleepiness

          -  Current or past diagnosis of Bipolar disorder or psychotic disorder

          -  Significant cognitive impairments

          -  Untreated moderate to severe sleep apnea or high risk for sleep apnea
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Emery, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Schiele, M.A.</last_name>
    <phone>614-688-3895</phone>
    <email>schiele.6@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristie Harris, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>614-688-3895</phone>
    <email>harris.1815@osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Schiele, M.A.</last_name>
      <phone>614-688-3895</phone>
      <email>schiele.6@osu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristie Harris, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>614-688-3895</phone>
      <email>harris.1815@osu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Emery, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charles Emery PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>insomnia</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>memory</keyword>
  <keyword>attention</keyword>
  <keyword>executive functioning</keyword>
  <keyword>decision making</keyword>
  <keyword>self-care</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>functional status</keyword>
  <keyword>walk test</keyword>
  <keyword>sleep monitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Wake Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

