<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03638895</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UoL001379</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03638895</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Energy Expenditure From ECAL Indirect Calorimeter in a Multicomponent Weight Management Service</brief_title>
  <acronym>ECAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Trial to Evaluate Impact of Energy Expenditure Information From Indirect Calorimeter on the Outcome of Weight Loss During a Standardised Multicomponent Weight Management Intervention in Non-diabetic &amp; Pre-diabetic Obese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Liverpool</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Metabolic Health Solutions UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Liverpool</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Whether greater weight loss is as a result of a smaller reduction in energy expenditure with
      caloric restriction is not known. Resting energy expenditure and 24-hour energy expenditure
      vary substantially between individuals. In some cases, relatively reduced rates of 24h EE
      predict weight gain in some populations who have high prevalence of obesity. Obese
      individuals that lose weight experience a decrease in 24-h EE and resting energy expenditure
      that is lower than predicted based on changes in body composition. Most weight loss studies
      have found a large individual variation in the amount of weight change, and whether an
      individual's response to an intervention can be predicted is not clear. Measurements of
      24-hour EE in response to fasting may help predict weight loss. The ECAL indirect calorimeter
      (ECAL) is a validated device purpose-built to provide the practitioner and patient with
      energy information that allows for more accurate, reliable method of establishing an obese
      individuals' metabolic profile. The aim of this study is to determine whether providing
      energy information from ECAL indirect calorimeter as an adjunct to the multicomponent weight
      management intervention in non-diabetic obese and severely obese individuals would help
      predict the response of weight loss.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Weight loss is important to improve overall health and reduce risk of obesity-related
      comorbidities such as diabetes. Numerous studies performed on individuals with predisposed
      genetic propensity to obesity who are deemed to be metabolically 'thrifty', require further
      structured intensification of caloric restriction and change in physical activity in order to
      achieve weight loss. Whether greater weight loss is as a result of smaller reduction in
      energy expenditure with calorie restriction is not known. Resting energy expenditure and
      24-hour energy expenditure vary substantially between individuals. Obese individuals that
      lose weight experience a decrease in 24-h EE and resting energy expenditure that is lower
      than predicted based on changes in body composition. Most weight loss studies have found a
      large individual variation in the amount of weight change, and whether an individual's
      response to an intervention can be predicted is not clear. Measurements of 24-hour EE in
      response to fasting may help predict weight loss. The ECAL indirect calorimeter (ECAL) is a
      validated device purpose-built to provide the practitioner and patient with energy
      information that allows for more accurate, reliable method of establishing an obese
      individuals' metabolic profile. The ECAL device also measures the respiratory quotient (RQ)
      which is the ratio of the volume of carbon dioxide expired to that of oxygen consumed by the
      individual for every breath. Previous studies demonstrated variability in role of RQ in
      predicting weight loss, but individuals who demonstrated an RQ in the lower range (&lt;0.72)
      were more likely to maintain the weight-loss achieved on a caloric restriction and avoid a
      weight loss rebound as compared to those with RQ in the higher range (&gt;0.75). This suggests
      that RQ could prove useful in clinical practice as a prognostic marker for long-term
      effectiveness of low- and very-low-calorie diets used to induce weight loss. Baltimore
      Longitudinal Study on Aging shared a similar finding that fasting RQ or respiratory exchange
      ratio adjusted for age, BMI, and fat free mass was positively related to weight change. The
      aim of this study is to determine whether providing energy information from ECAL indirect
      calorimeter as an adjunct to the multicomponent weight management intervention in
      non-diabetic obese and severely obese individuals would help predict the response of weight
      loss.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double (Participant, Practitioner) Energy expenditure information (resting energy expenditure &amp; respiratory quotient) is withheld from participant and practitioner providing care to participants in the control group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Magnitude of weight loss (in kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resting metabolic rate (RMR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The measurement of number of calories that the body burns at rest in 24 hours, expressed as kcal/day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory Quotient (RQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The ratio of carbon dioxide production to oxygen consumption and reflects the relative contribution of fat, carbohydrate, and protein in the oxidation fuel mixture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secretion of gut hormones (GLP-1, GIP, PYY)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secretion of appetite regulating gut hormone (GLP-1, GIP, PYY) in fasting and post-prandial phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycaemic variability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in the swings in blood glucose levels, expressed as the mean amplitude of glycaemic excursion (MAGE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in the measure of insulin rise in response to blood sugar levels, expressed as the homeostasis model assessment (HOMA). HOMA estimates steady state beta cell function and insulin sensitivity as percentages of the normal reference population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensory Neuropathy Testing in Prediabetic Obese Individuals</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in vibration perception threshold measurement using the neurothesiometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Douleur Neuropathique en4 Questions (DN4)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in Douleur Neuropathique en4 Questions (DN4) using seven interview questions and three physical tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analogue score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in visual analogue score of pain, expressed as Units on a scale of 0 to 100. where 0 is worst possible health and 100 is the best possible health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>modified Total Neuropathy Score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in modified Total Neuropathy Score (mTNS) questionnaire expressed as the average of the five components</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory Short Form</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in brief pain inventory short form (BPI-SF) scored as the mean of the seven interference items.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Severe Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Apnoea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ECAL group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention group (ECAL) - practitioners and participants receive measured energy information from ECAL indirect calorimeter including resting energy expenditure and respiratory quotient to diagnose, manage and advise on modification of caloric restriction and physical activity level. Energy information also allows participant and practitioner to monitor and compare changes to their metabolic health throughout the duration of intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SC group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care (SC) - participants receive standard care (diet, exercise &amp; behaviour modification therapy) as part of the multicomponent weight management intervention within the tier 3 weight management service. Practitioners will rely on standard predictive equations to provide dietary advice and intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ECAL Indirect Calorimeter</intervention_name>
    <description>The ECAL is an open-circuit portable indirect calorimeter that measures both volume of CO2 expired and O2 consumed using a small mixing chamber. Participants will breathe through a mouthpiece with a nose clip applied whilst lying in a restful and comfortable position for 15 minutes. ECAL device will provide breath-by-breath measurements of the resting energy expenditure and respiratory quotient which will allow both practitioners and participants to monitor their metabolic health and compare the effect of dietary and physical activity intervention over the course of the structured intensive lifestyle intervention (24-weeks).</description>
    <arm_group_label>ECAL group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet, exercise &amp; behaviour modification therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard care (SC) - participants receive standard care (diet, exercise &amp; behaviour modification therapy) as part of the multicomponent weight management intervention within the tier 3 weight management service. Practitioners will rely on standard predictive equations to provide dietary advice and intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SC group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI &gt; or equivalent to 30 kg/m2 to - 60 kg/m2

          -  Stable weight (change of &lt;5% within 12 weeks before screening based on medical
             history)

          -  Subjects are well-motivated, capable and willing to learn how to undergo indirect
             calorimetry testing

          -  Willing and able to adhere to prohibitions and restrictions specified within this
             protocol

        For Subjects participating in the glycaemic variability sub-study:

          -  Subject understands instructions on the use of continuous glucose monitor sensor and
             is willing to undergo appropriate training and testing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking weight loss medication within 12 weeks prior to randomisation

          -  Previous or planned bariatric surgery

          -  History of Type 1, Type 2 diabetes mellitus, DKA or diabetes secondary to pancreatitis

          -  Has HbA1c &gt; or equal to 6.5% or Fasting Plasma Glucose &gt; or equal to 7.0 mmol/L at
             screening.

        NOTE: a one-time repeat measurement is allowed, if value of HbA1c and/or FPG is not
        consistent with prior values

          -  History of obesity with a known secondary cause (Cushing's disease/syndrome)

          -  Oral corticosteroid use (except in the short term use of a 7-10 day course)

          -  Ongoing, inadequately controlled thyroid disorder defined as thyroid-stimulating
             hormone &gt; 6 mIU/litre or &lt; 0.4 mIU/litre

          -  History of malignancy within 3 years before screening (or diagnosis of malignancy
             within this period)

          -  estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 ml/min/1.73m2 on serum testing

          -  Alanine aminotransferase level is &lt;2.0 times the upper limit of normal or total
             bilirubin is &gt;1.5 times the upper limit of normal at screening

          -  Other major illness likely to preclude participation in the trial

          -  History of glucagonoma

          -  A myocardial infarction, unstable angina, revascularisation procedure (stent or bypass
             graft surgery) or cerebrovascular accident within 12 weeks before screening
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Wilding, DM FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Liverpool</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John PH Wilding, DM FRCP</last_name>
    <phone>0151 529 5885</phone>
    <phone_ext>5885</phone_ext>
    <email>j.p.h.wilding@liverpool.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jonathan ZM Lim, MBChB</last_name>
    <phone>0151 529 5917</phone>
    <phone_ext>5917</phone_ext>
    <email>j.z.lim@liverpool.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang X, Wang Y, Ding Z, Cao G, Hu F, Sun Y, Ma Z, Zhou D, Su B. Relative validity of an indirect calorimetry device for measuring resting energy expenditure and respiratory quotient. Asia Pac J Clin Nutr. 2018;27(1):72-77. doi: 10.6133/apjcn.032017.02.</citation>
    <PMID>29222882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Das SK, Saltzman E, McCrory MA, Hsu LK, Shikora SA, Dolnikowski G, Kehayias JJ, Roberts SB. Energy expenditure is very high in extremely obese women. J Nutr. 2004 Jun;134(6):1412-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15173405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melo CM, Tirapegui J, Ribeiro SM. [Human energetic expenditure: concepts, assessment methods and relationship to obesity]. Arq Bras Endocrinol Metabol. 2008 Apr;52(3):452-64. Review. Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>18506270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lam YY, Ravussin E. Indirect calorimetry: an indispensable tool to understand and predict obesity. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2017 Mar;71(3):318-322. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2016.220. Epub 2016 Nov 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27848941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McLay-Cooke RT, Gray AR, Jones LM, Taylor RW, Skidmore PML, Brown RC. Prediction Equations Overestimate the Energy Requirements More for Obesity-Susceptible Individuals. Nutrients. 2017 Sep 13;9(9). pii: E1012. doi: 10.3390/nu9091012.</citation>
    <PMID>28902175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alves VG, da Rocha EE, Gonzalez MC, da Fonseca RB, Silva MH, Chiesa CA. Assessement of resting energy expenditure of obese patients: comparison of indirect calorimetry with formulae. Clin Nutr. 2009 Jun;28(3):299-304. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2009.03.011. Epub 2009 Apr 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19398250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Liverpool</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. John Wilding</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine &amp; Honorary Consultant Physician, Obesity and Endocrinology Research, Theme Lead for Metabolism and Nutrition</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>weight management</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>severe obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>structured dietary intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>calorie restriction</keyword>
  <keyword>indirect calorimetry</keyword>
  <keyword>resting energy expenditure</keyword>
  <keyword>resting metabolic rate</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory quotient</keyword>
  <keyword>substrate oxidation</keyword>
  <keyword>glycemic variability</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>peripheral neuropathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Morbid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

