<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04082871</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1IRB/2016/04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04082871</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Medication Review in Women With Depression and Anxiety</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing the Impact of Medication Management Review Service for Females Diagnosed With Depression and Anxiety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Applied Science Private University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Applied Science Private University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study sought to assess the impact of the MMR service on identifying and resolving TRPs,
      improving adherence, depression and anxiety scores in females diagnosed with depression and
      anxiety in Jordan
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants were recruited into this single-blind parallel randomized controlled trial and
      randomized into active and control groups. A clinical pharmacist identified TRPs for all
      participants. Adherence, depression and anxiety scores were assessed. Active group patients
      received the MMR service: pharmacist-delivered counseling and a letter with recommended
      changes in the patient's treatment plan was sent to the patient's psychiatrist to be applied.
      Control group participants did not receive the intervention. Follow-up assessments were
      completed for all patients at 3 months from baseline. Main outcome measures were TRPs,
      adherence, depression and anxiety scores.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 10, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Following recruitment, participants were randomized into two groups (1:1 randomization), active and control, using the computer-generated randomization program (www.randomization.com). The researcher generated the allocation sequence, and assigned the participants to their group. Participant who came into the clinic during the clinic's working hours (Sunday to Thursday, from 9 am to 1 pm) were approached consecutively and allocated to the active or control group. Participants were not aware of which study group they were assigned to; only the researcher was aware of each patient's group assignment.
Participants in the active and control groups completed a baseline and follow-up (3 months from baseline) visits at the same outpatient psychiatric clinic with the researcher conducting the interview using the study tool to complete the MMR process.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>This single-blind parallel randomized controlled trial</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effect of the medication management review service delivered to females living in Jordan and diagnosed with depression and anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>the medication management review service will be measured by the reduction of treatment related number after providing the service</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's satisfaction with the medication management review service</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>satisfaction will be measured by the willingness of patients to pay for the provided services</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">73</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression, Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Adherence, Patient</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All pharmacist level counseling and education regarding treatment, adherence and self-care activities were delivered to the active group patients only (planned to take 15 minutes). Patient level TRPs (any TRP that could be resolved via patient education and counseling) were resolved directly with the patient by the clinical pharmacist.
A letter with the identified TRPs (prioritized from most important to least important) for each patient in the active group was sent to the patient's psychiatrist by the researcher in sealed envelopes. The psychiatrist either accepted or rejected the recommendations. In case the recommendations were accepted, the psychiatrist implemented the recommended changes. Patients were informed by a phone call by the pharmacist to visit their psychiatrist soon after the recommendations were approved for the changes to be applied.
If the recommendations were rejected, the psychiatrist stated the reason of rejection and discussed it with the pharmacist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group patients also underwent the baseline interview with the researcher at the psychiatric clinic, TRPs were identified and documented. No intervention was provided by the pharmacist and no letter was sent to the patients' psychiatrists. In case a patient was found to have a life-threatening TRP, the patient was excluded from the study and reported to the psychiatrist due to ethical considerations.
After study completion, all patients in the control group received the MMR service, and a letter with their TRPs and recommendations to resolve them was sent by the pharmacist to their psychologist</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medication management review</intervention_name>
    <description>The researcher screened each completed an MMR template and verified that all information in each patient template was complete. A classification system was then used to identify the TRPs which either actually or potentially interfered with the clinical outcomes for each patient.[19] This system was explained in detail and applied successfully in many previous studies.[10, 14, 20] The researcher then identified TRPs for each patient in both groups using evidence-based medicine. The TRPs including unneeded drug treatment, untreated condition/s, efficacy/effectiveness issues, safety issues, inadequate knowledge, inappropriate adherence to pharmacological therapy, inappropriate adherence to self-care activities and miscellaneous problems.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Jordanian females or residents in Jordan for the last 12 months and planning to stay
             in Jordan for 6 months (the study follow-up period),

          -  above the age of 18 years

          -  diagnosed with depression and/or anxiety for at least 4 weeks duration

          -  taking medications for depression and/or anxiety

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  presence of a cognitive problem or sensory impairment which may prevent communication
             with the patient (reported by the patient's psychiatrist)

          -  being not able to speak or write Arabic (reported by the patient)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Females diagnosed with depression and/or anxiety and attending the psychiatric clinics at Jordan University Hospital (JUH)</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Medication management review service</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmaceutical care</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical pharmacist</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

