<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04080037</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01-QALM-2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04080037</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing Opioid Care Practices Using CPV Patient Simulation Modules</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing Opioid Care Practices Using CPV Patient Simulation Modules to Improve Alignment With CDC Guidelines</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Qure Healthcare, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ascend Learning</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Qure Healthcare, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the quality of opioid-related physician care decisions using a
      patient-simulation based measurement and feedback approach that combines multiple-choice care
      decisions with real-time, personalized scoring and feedback. The cases and feedback have been
      designed to align with the latest CDC opioid guidelines. The study will also measure the
      impact of gaming-inspired competition and motivation, including a weekly leaderboard, to
      improve evidence-based care decisions. The quality of care decisions will be measured in the
      simulations and in a multiple-choice assessment administered before and after the patient
      simulations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary care providers (PCPs) are often on the front lines of helping patients manage acute
      and chronic pain. These pain management decisions have become especially important in light
      of the national opioid crisis that has seen an unsettling rise in opioid dependency,
      over-doses and fatalities. The Centers for Disease Control has developed specific
      evidence-based guidelines to help clinicians make more informed decisions about appropriate
      use of opioids as well as identifying and managing patients at risk for opioid-use disorder
      and overdose.

      The investigators' previous work has shown that patient simulations can rapidly and reliably
      measure unwarranted practice variation among providers. In addition, published work shows
      that patient simulations, when administered serially and combined with customized feedback on
      improvement opportunities can reduce practice variation and improve performance on
      patient-level quality measures. Given the challenge of the current opioid crisis and the
      large scope of unwarranted variation in medical practice, there is a need for scalable
      approaches to measure care decisions, provide feedback on improvement opportunities and
      benchmark performance to peers.

      This study seeks to evaluate the impact of personalized measurement and feedback on
      evidence-based care decisions made by primary care providers across the country concerning
      opioid care. The study, a prospective cohort trial, will enroll primary care physicians
      (PCPs) practicing in the U.S. Upon enrollment, eligible providers will be asked to complete a
      questionnaire detailing their practice and professional background. They will then be asked
      to complete the following:

      Pretest: Pre-project, participants will take a multiple-choice assessment test. These
      assessments measure CDC Opioid Guidelines knowledge and adherence. Study administrators will
      randomize half of providers to take Assessment A pre-intervention, and half to take
      Assessment B pre-intervention, and have attempted to make these two assessments of equal
      difficulty.

      Intervention: All providers will then care for 1 online CPV QualityIQ patient simulation each
      week over the course of 6 weeks. The simulated patients will be adults aged 18-75 and present
      with clinical conditions commonly seen by PCPs, such as chronic or acute pain, for whom
      opioids are currently in use or may be considered. In the patient simulations, participants
      will make work-up, diagnostic and treatment decisions relevant to the patient's pain
      management and will receive real-time feedback on how those decisions align with the CDC
      recommendations. Each week, participants will receive an email notification with their case
      score from the previous week, how their care compares to their PCP peers, and a link their
      new case to be completed.

      Posttest: Recruits will take the remaining assessment as described above after completion of
      the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 29, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 29, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study will enroll practicing PCPs in the US. All eligible and consented participants will complete a multiple-choice pre-assessment, the complete 6 weekly patient simulations with feedback and peer benchmarking, then complete a multiple-choice post-assessment.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in provider scores on pre- and post-intervention assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>At the beginning and end of the study, participants with complete a 20 multiple-choice question assessment to measure familiarity with the latest CDC opioid guidelines. The assessment scales are known as the &quot;QURE-Ascend Learning Modules: Opioids, Assessment A&quot; and &quot;QURE-Ascend Learning Modules: Opioids, Assessment B,&quot; both of which measure familiarity with the latest CDC guidelines via multiple-choice questions. Scores on the scales range from 0 to 100%, with a higher score representing greater familiarity with evidence-based care. There are no subscales within the measures.
Between the assessment, they will care for online simulated patients and receive feedback on their care decisions. A primary outcome in the study will be to measure whether performance on the assessments improves after caring for the simulated patients and receiving feedback. Higher scores on the second assessment represent a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the overall and the diagnostic and treatment quality scores in the CPV QualityIQ patient simulations.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>In each case, participants will answer multiple-choice questions about their preferred course of action to work-up, diagnose and treat patients in the primary care setting. Each question has specific evidence-based scoring criteria identifying necessary and unnecessary care decisions. Each provider will get a score for each case, ranging from 0 to 100 percentage based on the care decisions they make in the case. Over the course of the project, the investigators will track the percentage of correct, evidence-based care decisions made by participants, with the hypothesis that serial measurement and feedback on evidence-based care decisions will lead to increases in appropriate decisions over time. Higher scores represent a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction as measured by post-evaluation survey</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will measure participant satisfaction as measured by post-evaluation survey. On a scale of 1 to 5 (with 5 being the highest), participants will be asked about the overall quality of the material, the relevance to their practice and the educational content. Higher scores represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician engagement throughout the study</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will track the percentage of enrolled participants who stay engaged in the study and complete at least 80% of their patient simulation cases.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Acute</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Neuropathic</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Abuse and Addiction</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Withdrawal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All eligible and consented participants will be asked complete a multiple-choice opioid assessment based on the latest CDC opioid guidelines, then care for 6 online QualityIQ patient simulations and receive feedback on their care decisions. They will then all complete an other multiple-choice assessment at the conclusion of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality IQ Patient Simulations</intervention_name>
    <description>Online patient cases designed to simulate typical patients seen in a primary care practice. In each case, providers will answer multiple-choice questions about their preferred course of action to work-up, diagnose and treat patients in the primary care setting. After each question, providers will receive evidence-based feedback, including references, on the appropriateness of each of their care decisions. Feedback will be supported with relevant reference to evidence-based guidelines, with a specific focus on the CDC opioid guidelines.
Cases will cover typical primary care patients presenting with acute and chronic pain, who may or may not be already taking opioid medication.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Participants</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clinical Performance and Value Vignettes</other_name>
    <other_name>CPVs</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Board-certified in internal medicine or family medicine

          2. Minimum patient panel size of 1,000 patients

          3. At least 5% of their patients currently or previously using opioid medications

          4. English-speaking

          5. Access to the internet

          6. Informed, signed and voluntarily consented to be in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Not board certified in either internal medicine or family medicine

          2. Patient panel size less than 1,000 patients

          3. Less than 5% of their patients currently or previously using opioid medications

          4. Non-English speaking

          5. Unable to access the internet

          6. Do not voluntarily consent to be in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Peabody, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>QURE Healthcare</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>QURE Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burgon TB, Cox-Chapman J, Czarnecki C, Kropp R, Guerriere R, Paculdo D, Peabody JW. Engaging Primary Care Providers to Reduce Unwanted Clinical Variation and Support ACO Cost and Quality Goals: A Unique Provider-Payer Collaboration. Popul Health Manag. 2019 Aug;22(4):321-329. doi: 10.1089/pop.2018.0111. Epub 2018 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30328782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weigel PA, Ullrich F, Shane DM, Mueller KJ. Variation in Primary Care Service Patterns by Rural-Urban Location. J Rural Health. 2016 Spring;32(2):196-203. doi: 10.1111/jrh.12146. Epub 2015 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26376210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peabody JW, Luck J, Glassman P, Dresselhaus TR, Lee M. Comparison of vignettes, standardized patients, and chart abstraction: a prospective validation study of 3 methods for measuring quality. JAMA. 2000 Apr 5;283(13):1715-22.</citation>
    <PMID>10755498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peabody JW, Luck J, Glassman P, Jain S, Hansen J, Spell M, Lee M. Measuring the quality of physician practice by using clinical vignettes: a prospective validation study. Ann Intern Med. 2004 Nov 16;141(10):771-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15545677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schieber LZ, Guy GP Jr, Seth P, Young R, Mattson CL, Mikosz CA, Schieber RA. Trends and Patterns of Geographic Variation in Opioid Prescribing Practices by State, United States, 2006-2017. JAMA Netw Open. 2019 Mar 1;2(3):e190665. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.0665. Erratum in: JAMA Netw Open. 2019 May 3;2(5):e194307.</citation>
    <PMID>30874783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No individual participant data will be shared with other researchers. Analysis will be conducted at the aggregate group level.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

