<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04080752</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108655</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-001683-29</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>61393215MDD2001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04080752</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of JNJ-61393215 in the Treatment of Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Multi-Center Study Investigating the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of JNJ-61393215 as Adjunctive Treatment in Adults With Major Depressive Disorder With Anxious Distress With Suboptimal Response to Standard Antidepressants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of JNJ-61393215 as adjunctive treatment
      compared to adjunctive placebo, as assessed by the change from baseline to week 6 on a
      17-item Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS-17) in participants with major depressive
      disorder (MDD) with anxious distress with a score greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 2 on item 26
      or 27 of the Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology, Clinician Rating -30 (IDS-C30), who have
      a suboptimal response to current treatment with a standard antidepressant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 24, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 24, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Hamilton Depression Rating Scale-17 (HDRS-17) Total Score up to Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>HDRS-17 is a Clinician-Administered rating scale designed to assess the severity of symptoms in participants diagnosed with depression with a total score range of 0 to 52 with higher scores indicting greater severity of depressive symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (HAM-A) Total Score up to Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>HAM-A scale measures the severity of a participant's anxiety, based on 14 parameters, including anxious mood, tension, fears, insomnia, somatic complaints and behavior at the interview. Each of the 14 items is rated by the clinician on a 5-point scale ranging from 0 (not present) to 4 (severe). The total score ranges from 0 to 56, where higher score indicates worsening. In this study, the Structured Interview Guide version of the HAM-A (SIGH-A) will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (HAM-A) Total Score up to Weeks 2 and 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>HAM-A scale measures the severity of a participant's anxiety, based on 14 parameters, including anxious mood, tension, fears, insomnia, somatic complaints and behavior at the interview. Each of the 14 items is rated by the clinician on a 5-point scale ranging from 0 (not present) to 4 (severe). The total score ranges from 0 to 56, where higher score indicates worsening. In this study, the SIGH-A will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in HDRS-17 Total Score in Participants with a Baseline HAM-A Score Greater than or Equal to (&gt;=) 20 up to Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>HDRS-17 is a Clinician-Administered rating scale designed to assess the severity of symptoms in participants diagnosed with depression with a total score range of 0 to 52 with higher scores indicting greater severity of depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in HAM-A Total Score in Participants with a Baseline HAM-A Score &gt;=20 up to Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>HAM-A scale measures the severity of a participant's anxiety, based on 14 parameters, including anxious mood, tension, fears, insomnia, somatic complaints and behavior at the interview. Each of the 14 items is rated by the clinician on a 5-point scale ranging from 0 (not present) to 4 (severe). The total score ranges from 0 to 56, where higher score indicates worsening. In this study, the SIGH-A will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7) Total Score up to Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>GAD-7 is a self-administrated test to assess generalized anxiety disorder. GAD-7 has 7 items, which measure severity of various signs of GAD according to reported response categories with each item is rated on a 4-point scale (0=not at all; 1=several days; 2=more than half the days; 3=nearly every day). Item responses are summed to yield a total score (range of 0 to 21), with higher scores indicating more anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) Total Score up to Weeks 2, 4 and 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Weeks 2, 4 and 6</time_frame>
    <description>PHQ-9 will be used as a participant-reported measure of depressive symptomatology. The PHQ-9 is a 9-item scale, where each item is rated on a 4-point scale (0=not at all, 1=several Days, 2=more than half the days, and 3=nearly every day), with a total score range of 0 to 27. The recall period is 2 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in HDRS-17 Total Score up to Weeks 2 and 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Weeks 2 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>HDRS-17 is a Clinician-Administered rating scale designed to assess the severity of symptoms in participants diagnosed with depression with a total score range of 0 to 52 with higher scores indicting greater severity of depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical event that occurs in a participant administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve (AUC) of JNJ-61393215</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Baseline), Days 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <description>AUC is the area under the plasma concentration-time curve observed during a dosing interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trough Plasma Concentration (Ctrough) of JNJ-61393215</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Baseline), Days 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <description>Ctrough is defined as the observed plasma concentration before dosing or at the end of the dosing interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of JNJ-61393215</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Baseline), Days 15, 29 and 43</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax is the maximum observed plasma concentration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Protein Binding (PPB) of JNJ-61393215</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6 (Day 43)</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma protein binding (PPB) of JNJ-61393215 will be determined by using a liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry/mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">218</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder With Anxious Distress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-61393215 135 milligram (mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive JNJ-61393215 135 mg (3*45 mg capsules) orally once daily for 6 weeks along with the prescribed standard oral antidepressants (without dose change) throughout the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive matching placebo for 6 weeks along with the prescribed standard oral antidepressants (without dose change) throughout the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-61393215</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-61393215 will be administrated orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-61393215 135 milligram (mg)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Orexin-1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo will be administered orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have a body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 36 kilogram per meter
             square (kg/m^2)

          -  Participants must have a primary diagnostic and statistical manual of mental
             disorders, 5th edition (DSM-5) diagnosis of major depressive disorder (MDD) with
             anxious distress, as assessed by the mini international neuropsychiatric inventory
             7.0. Plus (MINI). Participants with a diagnosis of comorbid generalized anxiety
             disorder (GAD), post-traumatic stress disorder, persistent depressive disorder,
             attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), social anxiety disorder or
             nicotine/caffeine dependence may be included, if MDD is primary diagnosis

          -  Participants must have an inventory of depressive symptomatology, clinician rating-30
             (IDS-C30) total score greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 35 (moderate to severe depression)

          -  Participant must not have received more than 3 failed antidepressant treatments (of
             adequate dose and duration), including their current treatment, in the current episode
             of depression, as documented by the massachusetts general hospital antidepressant
             treatment history questionnaire (MGH-ATRQ)

          -  Participant must be currently receiving 1 of the following antidepressants for at
             least 6 weeks duration at screening, at an adequate therapeutic dose, as determined by
             the MGH-ATRQ and should remain on a stable dose throughout the study: bupropion,
             citalopram, escitalopram, sertraline, paroxetine, venlafaxine, desvenlafaxine,
             duloxetine, fluoxetine, vilazodone, vortioxetine, mirtazapine, agomelatine,
             nortriptyline, imipramine, amitriptyline and levomilnacipran

          -  Participants must have a suboptimal response (improvement &lt;50%) to the antidepressant
             used as their current treatment, as measured by the MGH-ATRQ

          -  A woman of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening and a negative urine pregnancy test before the first dose

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has any other psychiatric condition including but not limited to: MDD with
             current psychotic features, bipolar disorder (including lifetime diagnosis),
             obsessive-compulsive disorder, borderline personality disorder, eating disorder
             (example: bulimia, anorexia nervosa), or schizophrenia (lifetime)

          -  Age of onset of depression is after 55 years of age

          -  Participant has a history of alcohol or substance use disorder (abuse/dependence)
             within 6 months prior to screening (nicotine and caffeine dependence are not
             exclusionary)

          -  Participant has a current or recent (within the past year) history of clinically
             significant suicidal ideation (corresponding to a score of &gt;= 3 for ideation) or any
             suicidal behavior within the past year, as validated on the Colombia suicide severity
             rating scale (C-SSRS) at screening or baseline

          -  Length of current major depressive episode &gt;60 months

          -  Participant has organic brain disease or dementia or has known or suspected
             intellectual development disorder

          -  Participant has been treated with at least one of the following treatments: (a)
             electroconvulsive therapy in the current episode; (b) deep brain stimulation
             (lifetime); (c) repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation within 4 weeks prior to
             baseline visit

          -  Participant has any clinically relevant medical condition that could potentially alter
             the absorption, metabolism, or excretion of the study intervention, such as liver
             disease or renal disease

          -  Participant has a relevant history of any significant and/or unstable cardiovascular,
             respiratory, neurological (including seizures - uncomplicated childhood febrile
             seizures with no sequelae are not exclusionary) or significant cerebrovascular, renal,
             hepatic, dermatologic, hematologic, gastrointestinal or endocrine diseases

          -  Participant has a clinically significant abnormal physical examination, vital signs or
             12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening or baseline

          -  Participant has a history of known demyelinating diseases such as multiple sclerosis
             or optic neuritis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Contact</last_name>
    <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Collaborative NeuroScience Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Garden Grove</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92845</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pacific Clinical Research Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Upland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91785</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alpharetta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30022</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta Center for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30331</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richmond Behavioural Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Staten Island</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10312</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43220</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IPS Research Company</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ARENSIA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chisinau</city>
        <zip>MD2025</zip>
        <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Clinical Psychiatric Hopsital 3</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>107076</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nizny Novgorod clinical psychiatric hospital 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nizny Novgorod</city>
        <zip>603155</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orenburg Regional Clinical Psychiatric Hospital #1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orenburg</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical and Rehabilitation Research Center Phoenix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostov-on-Don</city>
        <zip>344010</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Engels psychiatric hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov Region</city>
        <zip>413124</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saratov Regional Psychiatric hospital named after St. Sofia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <zip>410060</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychoneurological dispensary 10</name>
      <address>
        <city>St-Petersburg</city>
        <zip>190121</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Psychiatric hospital 7 named after I.P.Pavlov</name>
      <address>
        <city>St-Petersburg</city>
        <zip>199034</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychoneurological dispensary 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>St-Petersburg</city>
        <zip>199178</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychoneurological Dispensary #4</name>
      <address>
        <city>St.Peterburg</city>
        <zip>197110</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute of Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tomsk</city>
        <zip>634014</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MNCE of Kyiv RC Regional Psychiatric and Narcological Medical Association</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glevakha</city>
        <zip>8630</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE'Precarpathian Regional Clinical Mental Health Center Ivano-Frankivsk RC'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ivano-Frankivsk</city>
        <zip>76011</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SI Institute of Neurology, Psychiatry and Narcology of NAMSU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kharkiv</city>
        <zip>61068</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNPE'Kherson Regional Institution of Mental Care'of Kherson Regional Council</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kherson</city>
        <zip>73488</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyiv Railway Station Clinical Hospital #2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyiv</city>
        <zip>03049</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyiv Psychiatry Hospital #2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyiv</city>
        <zip>2660</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE 'Cherkasy Regional Psychiatric Hospital of Cherkasy Regional Council'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Smila</city>
        <zip>20708</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE 'Vinnytsya RC Psychoneurological Hospital n.a. O.I. Yushchenko Vinnytsya RC'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vinnytsia</city>
        <zip>21005</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barnsley</city>
        <zip>S75 3DL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L341BH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kings College London</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 8AZ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M139NQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR108655</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data sharing policy of the Janssen Pharmaceutical Companies of Johnson &amp; Johnson is available at www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency.
As noted on this site, requests for access to the study data can be submitted through Yale Open Data Access (YODA) Project site at yoda.yale.edu</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>https://www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

