<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04083157</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IBDHepBVaccine</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04083157</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intra-dermal With Topical Imiquimod Pretreatment Versus Intra-muscular Hepatitis B Vaccination in IBD Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intra-dermal With Topical Imiquimod Pretreatment Versus Intra-muscular Hepatitis B Vaccination in IBD Patients - a Double-blind Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) has witnessed a rising incidence globally and in Hong Kong,
      an area where chronic hepatitis B (CHB) remains endemic. IBD patients are usually
      immunocompromised due to the disease itself and secondary to the use of medications including
      immunosuppressants and biologics, predisposing them to various opportunistic infection
      including hepatitis. Vaccination against hepatitis B virus (HBV) is recommended to prevent
      CHB and its related complications including flare up of acute hepatitis, cirrhosis and
      hepatocellular carcinoma. However, it is reported that efficacy with conventional
      intramuscular hepatitis B vaccination in IBD patients is suboptimal, especially among those
      receiving biologic therapies. Various strategies in boosting vaccine immunogenicity including
      the utilization of higher vaccination dose, shorter dosing interval, or alternate route of
      vaccine administration have been studied.6

      Intradermal route of vaccination has been recently shown to be an effective way in augmenting
      immune response in specific patient groups who are known poor responders, including elderly
      and immunocompromised patients. In addition, topical imiquimod, a synthetic agonist of
      toll-like receptor 7 (TLR7), has been shown to further boost up the immunogenicity response
      when applied to the site before intradermal vaccination. The proposed study is the first
      clinical trial comparing the efficacy of intradermal hepatitis B vaccination with adjuvant
      topical application of imiquimod cream with the conventional intramuscular hepatitis B
      vaccination in IBD patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim of study To compare the efficacy of intradermal hepatitis B vaccination with adjuvant
      topical imiquimod with conventional intramuscular hepatitis B vaccination in IBD patients.

      Methodology Patient recruitment IBD patients newly referred to or currently followed up at
      Department of Medicine, Queen Mary Hospital will be screened for CHB status
      (HBsAg/Anti-HBs/Anti-HBc). Patients without CHB infection and evidence of prior HBV
      vaccination i.e. HBsAg -ve /Anti-HBc-ve/ Anti-HBs -ve will be recruited into the study.
      Eligible patients will be randomized to receive either intradermal vaccination with Engerix B
      with topical imiquimod or intramuscular vaccination with Engerix-B with topical aqueous cream
      as the control arm.

      Randomization Eligible patients will be randomized in 1:1 ratio to receive intradermal
      hepatitis B vaccination (Engerix B) with topical imiquimod cream (as the study arm) or
      intramuscular hepatitis B vaccination (Engerix-B) with topical aqueous cream (as the control
      arm). Computer generated random number is used for randomization. Randomization sequences
      will be kept in opaque envelope and kept by a research staff not directly involved in this
      study. Once the patient has consented to the study, that research staff will open the
      envelope and notified the study nurse only of the vaccine allocation. In case of medical
      emergency or severe adverse reaction to the study medication, unblinding can be performed
      after notification of the principal investigator who will break the randomization code by
      revealing the randomization sequence assigned to the concerned study subject.

      Vaccine administration Vaccination schedule is identical between the two arms with 3 doses
      given at 0, 1, 6 month. Participants in the study arm will receive 20 mcg intradermal
      Engerix-B at two separate sites (10 mcg/0.5 ml) with topical imiquimod ointment pre-treatment
      5 minutes before injection. Participants in the control arm will receive 20 mcg intramuscular
      Engerix-B at two separate sites (10 mcg/ 0.5 ml) with topical placebo aqueous cream
      pretreatment 5 minutes before injection. The topical treatment will be given in a 4x4cm2
      marked at the deltoid on each arm. Vaccination will be administered at clinic by dedicated
      study nurse, who is not involved in subsequent management of the participants. Both the
      investigators and the participants will be blinded to the result of randomization as only the
      study nurse know the route of administration.

      Follow up Follow up visits will be arranged at 1,6,12 month after first dose of vaccine.
      Blood will be taken during each follow up visits for anti-HBs titres.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sero-protection rate to HBV</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after first dose of vaccine</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of recruited subjects with anti-HBs titre ≥ 10 IU/L</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Injection site adverse effect of intradermal hepatitis B vaccine in IBD patients</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days after each dose of vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Injection site adverse effect recorded as following, with left and right arm recorded separately:
Pain - 0 = no pain / 1 = pain on touch / 2 = pain during arm raising / 3 = pain on arm movement Presence or absence of the following Itching Swelling Hot sensation Bruise</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic adverse effect of intradermal hepatitis B vaccine in IBD patients</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days after each dose of vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of absence of systemic adverse effect recorded as following:
Fever Malaise Headache Myalgia Arthralgia Nausea Diarrhoea</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sero-protection rate to HBV at 1 and 6 months after dose of vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 6 month after first dose of vaccine</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of good responder defined as anti-HBs ≥ 100 IU/L</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month after first dose of vaccine</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean concentration of anti-HBs at 1, 6 and 12 months after first dose of vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6 and 12 month after first dose of vaccine</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intradermal hepatitis B vaccine with imiquimod</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the study arm will receive 20 mcg intradermal Engerix-B at two separate sites (10 mcg/0.5 ml) with topical imiquimod ointment pre-treatment 5 minutes before injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intramuscular hepatitis B vaccine with aqueous cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the control arm will receive 20 mcg intramuscular Engerix-B at two separate sites (10 mcg/ 0.5 ml) with topical placebo aqueous cream pretreatment 5 minutes before injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intradermal hepatitis B vaccine with imiquimod</intervention_name>
    <description>Intradermal hepatitis B vaccine with topical imiquimod pretreatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intradermal hepatitis B vaccine with imiquimod</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intramuscular hepatitis B vaccine with aqueous cream</intervention_name>
    <description>Intramuscular hepatitis B vaccine with topical aqueous cream pretreatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intramuscular hepatitis B vaccine with aqueous cream</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults aged over 18 years old

          -  Confirmed IBD diagnosis (Ulcerative colitis, Crohns disease or IBD-Unclassified)

          -  HBsAg -ve / anti-HBs / antiHBc -ve

          -  Subjects must give written informed consent

          -  Subjects must be available to complete the study and comply with study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability or unwilling to follow all required study procedures

          -  History of allergy or severe adverse reaction to the study vaccines, their components,
             topical imiquimod or aqueous cream

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  HBsAg / anti-HBs / anti-HBc +ve

          -  Confirmed hepatitis C virus (HCV) (anti-HCV +ve) infection

          -  Fever (axillary temperature ≥ 38°C or oral temperature ≥ 38.5°C within 3 days of
             intended study vaccination, subjects can be recruited after the febrile episode
             subsides

          -  Have an active neoplastic disease

          -  Have any condition which the investigator believes may prevent successful completion
             of the study or interfere with results of the study

          -  Received an experimental agent (vaccine, drug, biologic, medication) within 1 month
             prior to vaccination or expect to receive an experimental agent during the study
             period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wai Keung Leung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wai Keung Leung, MD</last_name>
    <phone>85222553750</phone>
    <email>waikleung@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kwan Lung Ko, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>85222553111</phone>
    <email>kkl516@ha.org.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wai Keung Leung, MD</last_name>
      <phone>85222553750</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Imiquimod</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

