<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04085094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-01971</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04085094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gender Differences in Renal Functioning and Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>GenderBOLD</acronym>
  <official_title>Gender Differences in Renal Disease Progression: an Analysis of Potential Mechanisms Using Modern Radiological Techniques</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Geneva</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the GenderBOLD study is to shed light on the mechanisms responsible for
      women's lower susceptibility to developing and progressing chronic renal disease, using
      modern imaging techniques, and applying different diets. We postulate that oxygenation and
      renal perfusion are better conserved and change less in women than in men in different
      dietary situations (high salt-low salt), possibly because they are able to store excess salt
      in their skin and muscles. We postulate that these differences are independent of their
      menstrual cycle. Finally, we will analyze the renal functional reserve and changes in renal
      perfusion through an oral protein load and after sublingual nitroglycerin to assess whether
      potential différences exist between genders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic kidney disease (CKD) affects about 10% of the adult population in Switzerland.

      Despite decades of research, the mechanisms involved in the development and progression of
      CKD remain unclear, and there is a lack of preventative therapies. Women are relatively
      protected against CKD, but this topic has been little studied.

      The kidney is very sensitive to hypoxia and its chronic oxygen depravation is the final step
      in the pathogenesis of CKD. A special MRI application, called BOLD-MRI, has the ability to
      measure renal tissue oxygenation in humans. In a recent BOLD-MRI study, we demonstrated that
      cortical oxygenation is significantly higher in women than in men, which may explain women's
      lower susceptibility to declining renal function. However, whether this is true under
      different dietary conditions (high salt-low salt), and whether renal oxygenation changes
      throughout the menstrual cycle is unknown and will be assessed in this study.

      Renal oxygenation depends on its perfusion. Renal micro-perfusion can be measured with
      contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS) and is expressed as PI (perfusion index). CEUS is a
      recent imaging technique that combines conventional ultrasound with the administration of a
      microbubble contrast agent (a lipid or albumin-enveloped gas compound). The microbubbles are
      inert and eliminated by pulmonary and hepatic systems within one hour of administration. They
      are not nephrotoxic and have no major side effects. Whether there are differences in renal
      perfusion as measured with CEUS between men and women with and without CKD will be also
      assessed in this study.

      Oxygenation of the kidneys does not only depend on their perfusion, but also on their
      consumption, mainly related to tubular active sodium transport. Thus, their oxygenation is
      lower in the case of a high salt diet compared to a low salt diet. This has been proven in
      men, but not in women.

      Recently, another MRI technique called 23Na MRI was used to measure the amount of salt stored
      in the skin and muscles. It is possible that the cutaneous and muscular capacity of storing
      salt according to dietary salt intake is lower in men, but this has not, at present, been
      examined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in renal microperfusion according to dietary salt intake in healthy and CKD</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month (5 days high salt- two weeks wash out- 5 days low salt)</time_frame>
    <description>Renal perfusion is measured with the contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in renal oxygenation after salty/unsalted diets in women compared to men</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Renal oxygenation is measured by Blood Oxygen Level Dependent (BOLD-IRM)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in skin and muscle storage of sodium according to salt intake</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in cutaneous and muscle sodium storage measured by 23Na-MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in renal perfusion measured with CEUS after SL nitroglycerine</measure>
    <time_frame>before-5 minutes after NTG</time_frame>
    <description>Renal perfusion is measured with the contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>5</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">135</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Renal Failure</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Controls</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. Healthy and pre-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <description>A total of 45 healthy and pre-menopausal women (&lt;50 years old) will be recruited. Thirty of them are not on oral anticonception; 15 will be examined at each visit during their follicular phase, 15 during their luteal phase. Fifteen are on oral contraception.
Three visits will take place:
V1: after 5 days of a high salt diet (adding 6g of salt/day on top of regular diet), patients will undergo renal ultrasound (Doppler and CEUS), renal functional MRI (BOLD and phase contrast) and Na23 muscle and skin MRI.
V2: after 5 days of low salt diet (dietary instructions), the same exams mentioned above will be repeated
V3: renal CEUS will be performed before and after an oral protein load (1g/kg) or after SL nitroglycerin (0.2mg).
The day before each visit, a 24h urine collection will be performed in order to measure renal salt excretion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pre-menopausal women with CKD</arm_group_label>
    <description>A total of 30 women with CKD will be recruited and undergo the same visits as outlined above</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3. Post-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Fifteen post-menopausal women will undergo the same exams as outlined above</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4. Healthy men</arm_group_label>
    <description>A total of thirty age-and sex-matched men (15 below and 15 above 50 years old) will undergo the same exams as above.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>5.Men with CKD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Fifteen men with CKD will undergo the same exams as outlined above</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>high-salt diet (V1) and low salt diet (V2)</intervention_name>
    <description>Before the first visit, the participant will follow a five-day high salt diet (addition of 6g/day of salt to their regular diet followed at home). Before the second visit (V2), the participant will follow for five days a low-salt diet, according to dietary instructions followed provided during the screening visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Healthy and pre-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pre-menopausal women with CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3. Post-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4. Healthy men</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Renal ultrasound with use of a contrast product (SonoVue®), perfusion rate 0.015ml/kg/min. Four destruction-reperfusion sequences are performed in order to measure the Perfusion Index (PI) of the renal cortex.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Healthy and pre-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pre-menopausal women with CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3. Post-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4. Healthy men</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>5.Men with CKD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>functional MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Measurement of renal oxygenation with the Blood Oxygenation Level Dependant-MRI technique (BOLD-MRI) on Siemens Prisma 3T scanner before and 15minutes after 0.03mg/kg of IV furosemide. Assessment of the amount of salt stored in the skin and muscles with the 23Na MRI technique.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Healthy and pre-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pre-menopausal women with CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3. Post-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4. Healthy men</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>5.Men with CKD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pilocarpine test</intervention_name>
    <description>Assessment of sweat salt and potassium concentrations in healthy volunteers according to slat intake. Two electrodes are placed on the forearm. The electric current between the two electrodes will induce perspiration which will be collected with the Macroduct system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Healthy and pre-menopausal women without CKD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4. Healthy men</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Collection of blood samples (all), urine (all) and sweat in some.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy volunteers will be recruited by way of advertisement at CHUV. Patients with CKD
        will be recruited via the ambulatory nephrology consultation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion/exclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria for healthy pre-menopausal women:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old and &lt;50 years old.

          -  No drugs (psychoactive substances used for non-medical purposes) /medicine.

          -  Blood pressure &lt;135/85mmHg.

          -  Renal function (eGFR &gt;90ml/min/1.73m2) and absence of albuminuria.

          -  Regular menstrual cycle.

          -  No pregnancy.

          -  Understanding and signature of the informed consent.

        Inclusion criteria for pre-menopausal women with a chronic renal failure:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old and &lt;50 years old.

          -  Possibility to stop the treatment during the day of the study.

          -  Reduced renal function (eGFR 15-60 ml/min/1.73m2) or eGFR 60-90 ml/min/1.73m2 with the
             presence of albuminuria &gt;300 mg/j.

          -  Understanding and signature of the informed consent.

        Inclusion criteria for post-menopausal women:

          -  Age ≥ 50 years old.

          -  Absence of menstruation.

          -  No drugs consumption.

          -  No medicine, or possibility to stop it two days before the study.

          -  Blood pressure &lt;135/85mmHg.

          -  Renal function (eGFR &gt;90ml/min/1.73m2) and absence of albuminuria.

          -  Understanding and signature of the informed consent.

        Inclusion criteria for men:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old, but matched with the age of pre- aor post-menopausal women

          -  No drugs consumption.

          -  No medicine, or possibility to stop it two days before the study.

          -  Blood pressure &lt;135/85mmHg.

          -  Renal function (eGFR &gt;90ml/min/1.73m2) and absence of albuminuria.

          -  Understanding and signature of the informed consent.

        Exclusion criteria for all:

          -  Contra-indication for Magnetic Resonance Imaging (Pacemaker, implanted metallic
             device, claustrophobia,..)

          -  Known allergy to one of the study compounds (furosemide, Sonovue).

        Exclusion criteria for persons with chronic renal failure:

          -  Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease.

          -  Ingestion of corticosteroids or other immunosuppressants.

          -  Volume overload or heart failure.

          -  eGFR &lt; 15ml/min/1.73m2 or dialysis.

        Exclusion criteria for men and women receiving sublingual nitroglycerin:

          -  Hypersensitivity to nitrous derivatives or to one of the excipients present in the
             composition.

          -  History of heart disease (ischemic heart disease, valve and/or rhythmic).

          -  Low blood pressure (systolic blood pressure &lt;100mmHg)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>The study is characterized by several groups which contain only men or only women.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Menno Pruijm, PD MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHUV</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Menno Pruijm, MD PD</last_name>
    <phone>+41795565946</phone>
    <email>Menno.Pruijm@chuv.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wendy Brito, Rad technician</last_name>
    <phone>+4179 556 73 61</phone>
    <email>wendy.brito@chuv.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUV, nephrology service</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <state>Vaud</state>
        <zip>1011</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Menno Pruijm, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+41795565946</phone>
      <email>Menno.Pruijm@chuv.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>PD Dr. Grégoire Wuerzner</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PD Dr. Grégoire Wuerzner</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BOLD-RMI</keyword>
  <keyword>Contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Salt storage</keyword>
  <keyword>Perfusion index</keyword>
  <keyword>Resistance index</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal functional reserve</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal oxygenation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pilocarpine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

