<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04082468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-500-440-30-10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04082468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VALIDATE: Factor VIII Trending for MS Relapse</brief_title>
  <official_title>Observational Trial Evaluating Whether Elevated Factor VIII Activity During Multiple Sclerosis Relapses Serves as a Marker for Solumedrol-Resistance and Incomplete Relapse Recovery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center, Phoenix</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center, Phoenix</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple sclerosis (MS) patients hospitalized with an acute motor or visual relapse will be
      consented. Factor VIII-related labs will be systematically drawn for six months. During this
      time, patients will be followed with clinical assessments including: Expanded Disability
      Status Scale (EDSS), Multiple Sclerosis Functional Composite (MSFC), Low Contrast Sloan
      Letter Chart Testing, Symbol Digital Modality Test (SDMT), and NeuroQol. MRIs of the brain,
      cervical spine, and thoracic spine with and without contrast will be obtained. All patients
      will be treated with 1 gram IV solumedrol daily for five days per standard care. Clinical,
      imaging, and Factor VIII-related lab data individually or in aggregate will be correlated
      with relapse presence, severity, and extent of recovery following standard intravenous (IV)
      solumedrol treatment
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The identification of blood tests that detect patients having Multiple Sclerosis (MS)
      relapses in real time could lead to a new era of MS relapse treatment. Accidental, anecdotal
      clinical observations suggest that transient upregulation of the intrinsic coagulation
      pathway, namely with elevated von Willebrand Factor antigen levels (vWF) and increased Factor
      VIII activity, occur with some MS relapses and that the higher the elevated plasma values,
      the more glucocorticoid therapy required to achieve clinical improvement.

      Ten adult patients with relapsing remitting MS with or without secondary progression will be
      consented and enrolled in this longitudinal clinical trial. As a standard of care all
      patients will be treated daily with one gram IV solumedrol for five days, and all patients
      will have performed standard MRI's of the brain, cervical spine, and thoracic spine with and
      without IV contrast during hospital admission, which may occur after Solumedrol treatment.

      In addition to this standard of care, patients will have a panel of labs drawn on Days: 1
      (prior to any solumedrol treatment), 7, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 135, and 180. Neurological
      clinical assessments, comprising of assessing the EDSS score, the MSFC index (that looks at
      ambulation, hand/arm coordination, and cognitive function, comprised of the 25 foot timed
      walking tests, with and without any assistive devices if possible), LCSLC test, SDMT, and
      Neuro QoL will be conducted on Days: 1, 7, 30, 90, 180. Individual and aggregate laboratory
      values, neurological clinical assessment results, and MRI findings will be correlated for the
      presence of a MS relapse, severity of relapse, and extent of recovery from the relapse.
      Patients and evaluators will be blinded to the lab results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MS relapse recovery time with elevated lab values.</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Extent of relapse recovery across a variety of measures will be correlated with collected lab values and neurological assessments in an attempt to identify a positive correlation between incomplete recovery and solumedrol resistance with abnormally elevated lab values involving the vWF antigen and Factor VIII pathways</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood sample collection for coagulation profile</intervention_name>
    <description>Factor VIII Activity Level, Factor VIII Antigen Level, Interleukin 6, vWF Antigen Level, Thrombin Activity, Protein C Activity, Protein C Antigen Level, CRP, PT/PTT/INR ,T &amp; B lymphocyte panel at above time points</description>
    <other_name>Clinical data collection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Acute MS relapse patients hospitalized at St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center in
        Phoenix, Arizona
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients aged 18-65 with an established diagnosis of relapsing remitting
             multiple sclerosis (RRMS);

          2. Patients with RRMS hospitalized at St. Joseph's Hospital and Medical Center in
             Phoenix, Arizona for an acute relapse affecting strength or vision;

          3. Patients may or may not be on disease modifying treatment;

          4. Entry EDSS score up to 7.0.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients unable to have an MRI;

          2. Patients taking any heparin products, warfarin (Coumadin), apixiban (Eliquis),
             dabigatran (Pradaxa), or rivaroxaban (Xarelto);

          3. If stroke, tumor or other non-MS related cause is identified as the source of the
             patient's neurological issues.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amiee Borazanci, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Joseph's Hospital/Barrow Neurological Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary Thornton, RN</last_name>
    <phone>602-406-6287</phone>
    <email>mary.thornton@dignityhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stacey Lent</last_name>
    <phone>602-406-6291</phone>
    <email>Stacey.lent@dignityhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barrow Neurological Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Thornton, RN</last_name>
      <phone>602-406-6287</phone>
      <email>mary.thornton@dignityhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stacy Lent</last_name>
      <phone>602-406-6291</phone>
      <email>Stacey.lent@dignityhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aimee Borazanci, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dolly Roy, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Relapsing remitting Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

