<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04087785</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Rev/06/15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04087785</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>microRNA Profile in Early-stage Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>microRNA Profile Associated With Positive Lymph Node Metastasis in Early-stage Cervical Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Cancerología</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Cancerología</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Persistent infections with high-risk subtypes of the human papillomavirus (HPV) are
      recognized as the etiological factor for developing cervical cancer. The aim od this study
      was to identify a miRNA profile in patients with early-stage cervical cancer with positive
      lymph node metastasis treated. Formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissue samples of
      patients with a diagnosis of early-stage cervical cancer treated by radical hysterectomy with
      lymphadenectomy were collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cervical carcinoma (CC) is one of the most common cancers in women from countries with
      emerging economies; in Mexico, CC has the second highest incidence and mortality rate.
      Several studies have demonstrated that the most important prognostic factor is lymph node
      metastasis in early-stage CC patients prior to radical hysterectomy (RH) with bilateral
      pelvic lymphadenectomy (BPL), in which positive lymph node metastasis decreasing overall
      survival (OS) from 80% to 53% at 5 years.

      MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are single-strand RNAs comprising approximately 21-23 nucleotides. miRNAs
      regulate gene expression through the inhibition of posttranscriptional events and, in some
      cases, induce the degradation of their target messenger RNA. In cancer, miRNAs can function
      as both oncogenes and/or as tumor suppressor genes depending on the function of their target
      genes.

      Formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissue blocks from CC patients diagnosed between
      January 2006 and December 2013 at the Department of Oncologic Gynecology of the National
      Cancer Institute (Mexico City) were analyzed with the intention of selecting those with a
      confirmed histopathological diagnosis of stages IB1 or IIA1 CC treated with RH and BPL. Total
      RNA was extracted from 5 (10-µm) sections for selected tissues.For the clinical correlation
      analysis, the samples were divided into 2 groups: 1 with positive occult lymph node
      metastasis pathology and 1 without lymph node metastasis pathology. For both groups, patients
      were matched for age, tumor size and presence of lymphovascular permeation.

      The identification of global miRNA profiles was performed using GeneChip miRNA 3.0 Array
      (Affymetrix, Cat. 902018) following the manufacturer's instructions. the microarray was
      hybridized and washed using the Affymetrix Fluidics Station 450 and scanned with the
      Affymetrix GeneChip Scanner 3000. After processing the images, the raw data were processed.
      To obtain the miRNA profile, the processed samples were divided into 2 groups, samples with
      lymph node metastasis and samples without lymph node metastasis. Differentially expressed
      miRNAs were identified using a cutoff value of p &lt;0.01 and a fold change (FC) of 1.5. miRNAs
      that met these criteria were classified as over-expressed or under-expressed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prognostic miRNAs</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identify a subset of miRNAs with prognostic value associated with early-stage CC patients treated with RH and BPL with positive lymph node metastasis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Positive metastasis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Positive occult lymph node metastasis pathology</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Negative metastasis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Without lymph node metastasis pathology</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tissue blocks.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients diagnosed with cervical cancer between January 2006 and December 2013 at the
        Department of Oncologic Gynecology of the National Cancer Institute (Mexico City).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cervical cancer histopathological diagnosis

          -  Clinical stage IB1 or IIA1 CC

          -  Treated with radical hysterectomy (RH) with bilateral pelvic lymphadenectomy (BPL)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Double primary tumors

          -  Treatment regimens other than standard treatment

          -  Poor quality formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tissue blocks
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David F Cantú-deLeón, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute of Mexico</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://gco.iarc.fr</url>
    <description>GLOBOCAN 2012 v1.0, Cancer Incidence and Mortality Worldwide: IARC CancerBase. No. 11 [Internet]., Lyon, Fr. Int. Agency Res. Cancer. 11 (2013)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomison J 3rd, Thomas LK, Shroyer KR. Human papillomavirus: molecular and cytologic/histologic aspects related to cervical intraepithelial neoplasia and carcinoma. Hum Pathol. 2008 Feb;39(2):154-66. doi: 10.1016/j.humpath.2007.11.002. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18206494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koh WJ, Greer BE, Abu-Rustum NR, Apte SM, Campos SM, Chan J, Cho KR, Cohn D, Crispens MA, DuPont N, Eifel PJ, Gaffney DK, Giuntoli RL 2nd, Han E, Huh WK, Lurain JR 3rd, Martin L, Morgan MA, Mutch D, Remmenga SW, Reynolds RK, Small W Jr, Teng N, Tillmanns T, Valea FA, McMillian NR, Hughes M; National Comprehensive Cancer Network. Cervical cancer. J Natl Compr Canc Netw. 2013 Mar 1;11(3):320-43.</citation>
    <PMID>23486458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lea JS, Lin KY. Cervical cancer. Obstet Gynecol Clin North Am. 2012 Jun;39(2):233-53. doi: 10.1016/j.ogc.2012.02.008. Epub 2012 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22640713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delgado G, Bundy B, Zaino R, Sevin BU, Creasman WT, Major F. Prospective surgical-pathological study of disease-free interval in patients with stage IB squamous cell carcinoma of the cervix: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. Gynecol Oncol. 1990 Sep;38(3):352-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2227547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suprasert P, Charoenkwan K, Khunamornpong S. Pelvic node removal and disease-free survival in cervical cancer patients treated with radical hysterectomy and pelvic lymphadenectomy. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2012 Jan;116(1):43-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgo.2011.08.001. Epub 2011 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21978816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Togami S, Kamio M, Yanazume S, Yoshinaga M, Douchi T. Can pelvic lymphadenectomy be omitted in stage IA2 to IIB uterine cervical cancer? Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2014 Jul;24(6):1072-6. doi: 10.1097/IGC.0000000000000163.</citation>
    <PMID>24905616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tanaka Y, Sawada S, Murata T. Relationship between lymph node metastases and prognosis in patients irradiated postoperatively for carcinoma of the uterine cervix. Acta Radiol Oncol. 1984;23(6):455-9.</citation>
    <PMID>6099039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bartel DP. MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function. Cell. 2004 Jan 23;116(2):281-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14744438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedroza-Torres A, López-Urrutia E, García-Castillo V, Jacobo-Herrera N, Herrera LA, Peralta-Zaragoza O, López-Camarillo C, De Leon DC, Fernández-Retana J, Cerna-Cortés JF, Pérez-Plasencia C. MicroRNAs in cervical cancer: evidences for a miRNA profile deregulated by HPV and its impact on radio-resistance. Molecules. 2014 May 16;19(5):6263-81. doi: 10.3390/molecules19056263. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24840898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JW, Choi CH, Choi JJ, Park YA, Kim SJ, Hwang SY, Kim WY, Kim TJ, Lee JH, Kim BG, Bae DS. Altered MicroRNA expression in cervical carcinomas. Clin Cancer Res. 2008 May 1;14(9):2535-42. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-07-1231.</citation>
    <PMID>18451214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institute of Cancerología</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Cantu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of clinical trials department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>miRNAs</keyword>
  <keyword>cervical cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>lymph node metastasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

