<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04086901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DART</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04086901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Escalated Adaptive RadioTherapy in Definitive Chemo-radiotherapy for Esophageal Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>DART</acronym>
  <official_title>Dose Escalated Adaptive RadioTherapy - a Randomised Phase II Study of Definitive Chemo-radiotherapy in Locally Advanced Esophageal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital Skejby</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Denmark, 1000 new cases of esophageal and gastro-esophageal junction cancer occur every
      year. Surgery is the primary treatment for patients with localized disease who are considered
      medically and technically operable. For patients deemed non-resectable, definitive
      chemoradiotherapy is the treatment of choice, but despite treatment with curative intent,
      these patients have a poor prognosis, with a median survival of less than 20 months and a
      5-year survival at 15-25% in clinical studies

      This study will examine the effect of escalation of increasing the radiation dose to the most
      Positron Emissions Tomografi (PET) avid part of the tumour and lymph nodes compared to a
      standard uniform dose distribution.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Denmark, there are almost 900 new cases of oesphageal and gastro-esophageal junction (GEJ)
      cancer per year, with a 5-year survival rate below 20% for the entire group and a 5-year
      survival rate of approximately 40% for the curatively treated patients.

      Surgery is the primary treatment for patients with localized disease who are considered
      medically and technically operable. For patients deemed non-resectable, definitive
      chemoradiotherapy is the treatment of choice, but despite treatment with curative intent,
      these patients have a poor prognosis, with a median survival of less than 20 months and a
      5-year survival at 15-25% in clinical studies.

      Survival is affected by several factors like stage, gender and comorbidity, but also by lack
      of local and regional tumour control. Several studies examined pattern of failure in patients
      with oesophageal cancer treated with definitive chemoradiotherapy. Most patients experience
      local failure, and most local failures were located in the Gross Tumor volume (GTV). These
      findings imply that future therapeutic strategies should focus on improving local control in
      order to increase successful treatment outcome, although care should be taken to ensure that
      this does not come at the cost of excess treatment related toxicity.

      Strategies to overcome in-GTV failures include radiotherapy-sensitizing agents and dose
      escalation, the latter has been evaluated in several studies with heterogeneous results.

      The role of Positron Emissions Tomografi/ComputerTomografi (PET/CT) in radiotherapy planning
      has been examined and the diagnostic value of PET/CT in oesophageal cancer is widely
      accepted, whereas the role in assessing tumour response to treatment is less well
      established. Flour-Deoxy-Glucose (FDG)-PET scans allow for measurement of changes in tumour
      cell metabolism that precede changes in tumour size, and reduction in FDG uptake during
      neoadjuvant therapy has been correlated with favourable outcomes in patients with oesophageal
      cancer.

      PET-positive areas have been suggested as suitable targets for dose-escalation strategies,
      since studies suggested that high FDG uptake on pre-treatment PET/CT identifies tumour
      sub-volumes that are at greater risk of recurrence after chemoradiotherapy in patients with
      locally advanced oesophageal cancer.

      The major concern in a dose escalation study is severe and potentially lethal normal tissue
      complications. Oesophageal cancer irradiation usually results in irradiation of the
      oesophagus, lungs and heart due to the anatomical tumour location, which may result in acute
      toxicities dominated by radiation pneumonitis and esophagitis (leading to inappropriate
      nutricial intake). Late toxicities include oesophageal fistula/ulcers, cardiac events,
      pulmonary fibrosis, or even deaths related to radiation exposure. Dose gradients between the
      target and normal tissue may be sharp, in order to limit the norml tissue dose and hence the
      risk of unacceptable toxicity, while maintaining high doses to the tumour.

      Current study Previous studies have suggested that escalating the radiation dose to the GTV
      may provide improved local control, but requires great caution in relation to normal tissue
      irradiation to avoid unacceptable side effects. The investigators propose a study approach
      where both requirements will be met. FDG-PET scans will be used to identify and delineate the
      tumour sub-volumes with the highest tracer uptake to guide the dose-escalation. The dose to
      the GTV will be escalated to a high dose (63Gray (Gy) in the FDG-PET avid areas in the
      primary tumour and 60 Gy in the lymph nodes) while Clinical target volume (CTV) and Planning
      target volume (PTV) will be treated with standard dose. The patients will be randomized
      between this dose-escalated arm and a standard arm with 50Gy in 25 fractions. The total
      number of fractions will be 25 in both arms. Dose escalation will be limited by normal
      tissues constraints.

      The study will be conducted with modern state-of-the-art radiotherapy techniques, including
      advanced dose calculation algorithms, daily image guidance, and adaptation of the treatment
      plan during treatment if needed. The participating centres must implement and comply with a
      quality assurance program in order to maintain high treatment quality in the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Loco-regional control</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Loco-regional control evaluated with Flour-Deoxy-Glucose /Positron Emissions Tomografi (FDG-PET)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute and late toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Acute and late toxicity during and after treatment and at follow-up visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients surviving</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Survival without disease progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time spent at hospital and number of hospitalizations due to radiation-induced toxicity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean and maximum dose distributions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean and maximum doses for all organs at risk will be compared between proton therapy (in silico) and (clinical) IMRT/VMAT photon therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose distributions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>V5, V10, V15, V20, V25, V30, V35, V40, V45 and V50 for all organs at risk will be compared between proton therapy (in silico) and (clinical) IMRT/VMAT photon therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of failure in GTV-T</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with failure in the Gross tumor volume-tumor (GTV-T)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of failure in GTV-N</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with failure in the Gross tumor volume-nodes (GTV-N)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of failure in GTV-PET</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with failure in Gross tumor volume-PET avid (GTV-PET)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of failure in CTV</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with failure in the clinical target volume (CTV)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of failure in PTV</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with failure in the Planning target volume (PTV)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of failure outside PTV</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with failure in the outside the Planning target volume (PTV)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stability of the FDG-PET signal, intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in FDG-PET signal measured in terms of intensity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stability of the FDG-PET signal, shape</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in FDG-PET signal measured in terms of shape</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stability of the FDG-PET signal, heterogeniety</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in FDG-PET signal measured in terms of heterogeniety</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between loco-regional progression after treatment and changes in FDG-PET uptake pattern during standard and dose-escalated radiotherapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Response will be measured based on PERCIST and using radiomics characterizing the tumour in terms of uptake intensity, shape, and volumes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment completion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients completing all radiotherapy treatments and receiving at least one cycle of chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">211</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chemo-radiotherapy with radiotherapy dose escalation based on Flour-Deoxy-Glucose /Positron Emissions Tomografi (FDG/PET) scans</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard chemo-radiotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy dose escalation</intervention_name>
    <description>Flour-Deoxy-Glucose /Positron Emissions Tomografi (FDG-PET) scans will be used to identify and delineate the tumour sub-volumes with the highest tracer uptake to guide the dose-escalation. The dose to the Gross tumor volume (GTV) will be escalated to a high dose while clinical target volume (CTV) and planning target volume (PTV) will be treated with standard dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The patients must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be included in the study:

          -  Patients with histologically verified squamous cell or adenocarcinoma (including
             signet cell carcinoma) of the oesophagus or GEJ.

          -  Multi-Disciplinary Team (MDT) assessment and treatment recommendation; deemed
             nonresectable and/or inoperable.

          -  TNM stage (8th edition): cT1-4a or cN+, cM0-1 (M1 disease limited to metastatic lymph
             nodes)

          -  Age ≥18 years.

          -  Performance status ≤2.

          -  Adequate cardiac, lung and renal function measured according to local guidelines.

          -  Adequate laboratory findings:

               -  haematological: haemoglobin &gt; 90 g/L, absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,5 x
                  109/L, platelets ≥ 75 x 109/L

               -  hepatic: bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN, ALAT ≤ 3 x ULN

               -  renal: creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

          -  Suitability to undergo curatively intended chemoradiation therapy.

          -  Ability to adhere to procedures for study and follow-up.

          -  Women must present a negative pregnancy test. Fertile men and women must use effective
             contraception. Fertile women included in the study must use oral contraceptives,
             intrauterine devices, depot injection of progestin subdermal implantation, a hormonal
             vaginal ring, or transdermal patch during the study treatment and one month after.

          -  Signed informed consent to participate in the study, including acceptance that dose
             plan and scans will be stored in a national dose plan bank, and the remaining data
             stored in a central database.

          -  A standard plan for radiotherapy with homogenous 50 Gy / 25 fractions, meeting all
             dose constraints for normal tissue, must be achievable.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who will meet one or more of the following exclusion criteria cannot be included
        in this study:

          -  Prior oncological treatment or surgical resection for the present disease

          -  Broncho-pulmonary fistula verified by bronchoscopy

          -  Any other active malignancies which may compromise study protocol or endpoints except
             for basal or squamous cell skin cancer

          -  Any unstable systemic disease (including clinically significant cardiovascular
             disease, unstable angina, New York Heart Association (NYHA) grade III-IV congestive
             heart, severe hepatic, renal or metabolic disease or active inflammatory bowel
             disease)

          -  Symptomatic peripheral neuropathy greater than grade 1 (CTCAE version 4.03)

          -  Any other serious or uncontrolled illness which in the opinion of the investigator
             makes it undesirable for the patient to enter the trial

          -  Severely decreased lung function
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hanna R Mortensen, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aarhus University Hospital and Aarhus University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hanna R Mortensen, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 92432382</phone>
    <email>hanna.mortensen@auh.rm.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marianne Nordsmark, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 91167246</phone>
    <email>marianne.nordsmark@auh.rm.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense Universityhospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <state>Fyn</state>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eva Holtved, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <state>Hovedstaden</state>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Signe N Risum, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <state>Midtjylland</state>
        <zip>8200</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hanna R Mortensen, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 91167262</phone>
      <email>hanna.mortensen@auh.rm.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marianne Nordsmark, Md PhD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hanna R Mortensen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marianne Nordsmark, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizaveta Tabaksblat, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose escalation</keyword>
  <keyword>Definitive chemo-radiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will not be shared</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

