<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04083209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04083209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Preoperative Counseling on Postoperative Opioid Use Following Knee Arthroscopy.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Preoperative Counseling on Postoperative Opioid Use Following Knee Arthroscopy. A Randomized Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Our study looks to evaluate the effect of brief preoperative counseling on opioid use
      following knee arthroscopy. We aim to quantify the effect we have as providers in changing
      patient behavior postoperatively in terms of the type and amount of pain medication that is
      utilized.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Amid a national opioid epidemic, providers are looking for ways to minimize the utilization
      of narcotic and addictive pain medications while adequately treating acute and postoperative
      pain, all the while maintaining patient satisfaction. Much effort has been dedicated to
      studying non-narcotic alternative medications such as acetaminophen, NSAIDs, toradol,
      ketamine, ect., as well as multimodal strategies such as periaxial and perineural blockades.
      Little attention, however, has been given to the role we play as providers to help minimize
      the use of these addictive medications and the potential effect we have on changing patient
      behaviors. Alter et al1 published in the Journal of Hand Surgery their success of minimizing
      opioid use by simple preoperative counseling of patients undergoing carpal tunnel release
      surgery. They provided brief educational materials about the opioid epidemic and risks of
      these medications, as well as encouraging patients to utilize non-narcotic alternatives to
      control pain postoperatively. They saw a decrease in the amount of opioids used with no
      difference in pain scores in the group receiving this preoperative counseling.

      There are roughly 750,000 knee scopes performed each year in the United States. The incidence
      of chronic opioid use stemming from a short course of narcotics after elective knee
      arthroscopy has been shown to be up to 30%.2-4 The high volume of these procedures presents a
      unique opportunity to study trends in opioid use and pain control in the postoperative period
      in a prospective fashion.

      Study Design

      Patients scheduled to undergo knee arthroscopy by a single surgeon will be randomized into
      preoperative counseling or no counseling by simple randomization methods (computer generated
      &quot;coin flip&quot;). Those in the counseling group will receive a two minute talk during their
      preoperative appointment covering the risks of opioid medications, current public health
      situation regarding opioids, and alternative methods for pain control. They will also receive
      a one page document summarizing the Pennsylvania Orthopedic Society recommendations regarding
      opioid use that was used in previous research1. All patients will be prescribed the same pain
      medication and quantity (hydrocodone-acetaminophen 5-325 mg, 40 pills, 0 refills).
      Postoperatively, patients will be contacted via telephone on postoperative day three, asking
      what medication and how many pills they are taking daily for pain, as well as rating their
      daily pain level on a scale from 0-10. At their first postoperative follow-up appointment,
      they will again be asked about the quantity of pain medications used and pain level. After
      the first postoperative phone call, all data collection will be obtained at their regularly
      scheduled postoperative office visits, which occur at two and four weeks postoperatively.
      During all postoperative data collection time points we will also inquire and note all pain
      control measures, including ice, heat, compression, elevation, or other medications not
      commonly thought of as &quot;pain medications&quot;. Data collection from each patient will be
      concluded at their one month postoperative visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be randomized into a treatment and control group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantity of opioid pain medication used</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be tracked for the amount of opioid pain medication that is used during their postoperative course using a pill log.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will also be surveyed on their pain level postoperatively using the VAS pain scale. The scale is from 0-10 with 10 being the highest amount of pain. 0 representing no pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Counseling group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized into the &quot;counseling group&quot; will be given a 1-2 minute presentation over the risks of opioid pain medications during their preoperative visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will undergo the standard preoperative evaluation by the senior author without any additional formal opioid counseling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Opioid counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>The formal opioid counseling will involve reading the recommendations for postoperative opioid use established by the Pennsylvania Orthopedic Society.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Counseling group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged 18-60, undergoing knee arthroscopic meniscectomy surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-english speaking, prisoners, those who cannot provide consent on their own,
             previous history of chronic opioid use, prior history of surgery on the ipsilateral
             knee, and those undergoing additional surgical procedures on the same knee at the time
             of the surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mitch Beckert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mitch Beckert, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5633407212</phone>
    <email>mbeckert@iu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert Klitzman, MD</last_name>
    <email>RKlitzman@IUHealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IU Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mitch Beckert, MD</last_name>
      <phone>563-340-7212</phone>
      <email>mitch.beckert@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tepolt FA, Bido J, Burgess S, Micheli LJ, Kocher MS. Opioid Overprescription After Knee Arthroscopy and Related Surgery in Adolescents and Young Adults. Arthroscopy. 2018 Dec;34(12):3236-3243. doi: 10.1016/j.arthro.2018.07.021. Epub 2018 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>30396797</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rozet I, Nishio I, Robbertze R, Rotter D, Chansky H, Hernandez AV. Prolonged opioid use after knee arthroscopy in military veterans. Anesth Analg. 2014 Aug;119(2):454-9. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000000292.</citation>
    <PMID>24977636</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alter TH, Ilyas AM. A Prospective Randomized Study Analyzing Preoperative Opioid Counseling in Pain Management After Carpal Tunnel Release Surgery. J Hand Surg Am. 2017 Oct;42(10):810-815. doi: 10.1016/j.jhsa.2017.07.003. Epub 2017 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>28890331</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mitchell Beckert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We plan to share all data collected from the study including non-identifiable patient demographics, pain scores, opioid medication utilization, complications, and study design.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

