<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04081818</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Nutritious_Mushrooms_61100</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04081818</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study on the Effects of Nutritious Mushrooms in Adults With Metabolic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study on the Effects of Nutritious Mushrooms in Adults With Metabolic Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Harokopio University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Harokopio University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity, characterized by an increase in body weight that results in excessive fat
      accumulation, is a global health problem. Recently, it has also been shown that obesity is
      associated with low-grade chronic systemic inflammation in adipose tissue. This condition is
      mediated by activation of the innate immune system in adipose tissue that promotes
      inflammation and oxidative stress and triggers a systemic acute-phase response.

      Previous research points towards the potential of phytochemicals in food as part of
      nutritional strategies for the prevention of obesity and associated inflammation, as well as,
      increase in insulin sensitivity in diabetic patients.

      In addition, there is strong evidence that obesity is inversely associated with vitamin D
      levels. The major cause of vitamin D deficiency in humans is the lack of adequate sun
      exposure. Unfortunately, very few foods, i.e. mushrooms, naturally contain vitamin D and
      foods that are fortified with vitamin D are inadequate to satisfy vitamin D requirements.

      The last decade, mushrooms have attracted the research interest as functional foods with
      desirable health benefits in several metabolic disorders without the side effects of
      pharmacological treatment. Edible mushrooms are highly nutritious and exhibit beneficial
      effects on several inflammatory diseases such as cancer, heart disease, diabetes,, high blood
      pressure.

      Thus, the purpose of this study is to determine the effects of nutritious mushrooms in adults
      with Metabolic Syndrome. More specifically, 100 participants will be allocated to two groups,
      namely intervention group (N=50) and control group (N=50). Vitamin D2-enhanced mushrooms by
      UV-B will be provided as a snack to the intervention group, whereas the control group will
      not consume the snack. The intervention will last 3 months.The effects of the intervention
      will be evaluated via clinical and laboratory markers. Personal and family history,
      anthropometric, demographic data, body composition, dietary habits, physical activity and
      smoking status will be assessed pre- and post- intervention. Biochemical profile, oxidative
      stress and inflammation, as well as metabolomic profiles will be assessed in blood samples
      pre- and post- intervention. Both groups will receive standard nutritional counselling
      throughout the intervention and will be encouraged to report any adverse effects they may
      experience during the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin sensitivity change pre- and post- intervention in each arm, measuring fasting blood sugar levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin sensitivity change pre- and post- intervention in each arm, measuring Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vitamin D levels change pre- and post- intervention in each arm</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group (Nutritious Mushrooms)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nutritious Mushrooms</intervention_name>
    <description>The Intervention group will consume antioxidant rich and Vitamin D2-enhanced mushrooms as a snack daily for 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group (Nutritious Mushrooms)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  30 years &lt; Age &lt; 65 years

          -  BMI &gt; 25 kg/ m2

          -  Metabolic Syndrome

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hepatotoxic Medication

          -  Diabetes Mellitus

          -  Dysthyroidism, hypopituitarism, Cushing syndrome / disease

          -  Pregnancy, lactation

          -  Psychiatric or mental disorder

          -  Any use of antioxidant-phytochemical rich supplement, vitamin D supplement, nti-, pre-
             or pro-biotics within 3 months pre-intervention
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andriana C Kaliora, Ass. Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+30 2109549226</phone>
    <email>akaliora@hua.gr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Andriana Kaliora</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>17671</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andriana C Kaliora, Ass. Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+30 2109549226</phone>
      <email>akaliora@hua.gr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andriana C Kaliora, Ass. Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marseglia L, Manti S, D'Angelo G, Nicotera A, Parisi E, Di Rosa G, Gitto E, Arrigo T. Oxidative stress in obesity: a critical component in human diseases. Int J Mol Sci. 2014 Dec 26;16(1):378-400. doi: 10.3390/ijms16010378. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25548896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardwell G, Bornman JF, James AP, Black LJ. A Review of Mushrooms as a Potential Source of Dietary Vitamin D. Nutrients. 2018 Oct 13;10(10). pii: E1498. doi: 10.3390/nu10101498. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30322118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdali D, Samson SE, Grover AK. How effective are antioxidant supplements in obesity and diabetes? Med Princ Pract. 2015;24(3):201-15. doi: 10.1159/000375305. Epub 2015 Mar 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25791371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duggan C, de Dieu Tapsoba J, Mason C, Imayama I, Korde L, Wang CY, McTiernan A. Effect of Vitamin D3 Supplementation in Combination with Weight Loss on Inflammatory Biomarkers in Postmenopausal Women: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Cancer Prev Res (Phila). 2015 Jul;8(7):628-35. doi: 10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-14-0449. Epub 2015 Apr 23.</citation>
    <PMID>25908506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norman PE, Powell JT. Vitamin D and cardiovascular disease. Circ Res. 2014 Jan 17;114(2):379-93. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.113.301241. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24436433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holick MF, Chen TC. Vitamin D deficiency: a worldwide problem with health consequences. Am J Clin Nutr. 2008 Apr;87(4):1080S-6S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18400738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutt SJ, Hyppönen E, Saarnio J, Järvelin MR, Herzig KH. Vitamin D and adipose tissue-more than storage. Front Physiol. 2014 Jun 24;5:228. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2014.00228. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25009502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Urbain P, Singler F, Ihorst G, Biesalski HK, Bertz H. Bioavailability of vitamin D₂ from UV-B-irradiated button mushrooms in healthy adults deficient in serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D: a randomized controlled trial. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2011 Aug;65(8):965-71. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2011.53. Epub 2011 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21540874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>El Khoury D, Cuda C, Luhovyy BL, Anderson GH. Beta glucan: health benefits in obesity and metabolic syndrome. J Nutr Metab. 2012;2012:851362. doi: 10.1155/2012/851362. Epub 2011 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22187640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ganesan K, Xu B. Anti-Obesity Effects of Medicinal and Edible Mushrooms. Molecules. 2018 Nov 5;23(11). pii: E2880. doi: 10.3390/molecules23112880. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30400600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Harokopio University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andriana C Kaliora</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor in Foods and Human Nutrition</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

