<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04085042</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Esenfc</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04085042</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of a Multimodal Intervention on Peripheral Venous Catheterization of Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>MultiCat</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of a Multimodal Intervention on Peripheral Venous Catheterization of Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Escola Superior de Enfermagem de Coimbra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Português Oncologia de Coimbra Francisco Gentil E. P. E.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Escola Superior de Enfermagem de Coimbra</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral intravenous catheterization (PIVC) is the most frequent invasive clinical
      procedure in a hospital setting, associated with significant complication rates for the
      patient, compromising their well-being, as well as the quality, safety, and efficacy of the
      care provided. The traditional approach to PIVC is considered reactive and ineffective,
      resulting in the exhaustion of the patients' peripheral venous access prior to consideration
      of other access methods and options (Moureau et al., 2012).

      Evidence suggests that the safety and effectiveness of patients with a peripheral catheter
      are also intrinsically associated with the adequacy of materials and technologies used in
      clinical contexts for vein selection, as well as for catheter insertion and maintenance care
      (Marsh, Webster, Mihala &amp; Rickard, 2017). Several studies point to the inadequacy of the
      technologies and medical devices used in this area, enhancing the occurrence of complications
      such as infection, phlebitis, occlusion and accidental catheter removal (Braga, 2017; Costa,
      2017; Nobre &amp; Martins, 2018).

      The project investigators aim to determine whether the use of a PIVC pack will significantly
      reduce associated complications when compared with the usual care. Additionally, the research
      team aims to determine if the use of a PIVC pack will reduce the number of insertion attempts
      and overall procedure time, as well as improving patient and provider satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PIVC-related complications</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome will be assessed immediately following intervention, an average of 5 minutes. This outcome will be assessed through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated through a self-report scale where the nurse identifies a set of indicators associated to the occurrence of immediate complications during the procedure (extravasation, puncture of proximal anatomical structures, hematoma, etc.)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful intravenous catheterization on the first attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome will be assessed immediately following intervention, an average of 5 minutes. This outcome will be assessed through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Successful attempt is defined through the clear flush of the catheter with 5 mL of normal saline without extravasation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of attempts to successful intravenous catheter placement</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately following intervention, an average of 5 minutes. This outcome will be assessed through study completion, an average of 6 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to successful placement (in minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of randomization until the time of successful intravenous catheter placement, assessed through study completion, an average of 6 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome will be assessed immediately following intervention, an average of 20 minutes. This outcome will be assessed through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated through a self-report scale where the participant identifies a set of indicators associated to their satisfaction with the intervention, when compared to previous experiences.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nurse satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome will be assessed immediately following intervention, an average of 20 minutes. This outcome will be assessed through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated through a self-report scale where the nurse identifies a set of indicators associated to their satisfaction with the intervention, when compared to previous experiences.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Catheterization, Peripheral</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care during peripheral venous catheterization. Nurses will continue with the normal routine practice, by preparing all needed material individually.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PIVC pack</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nurses will use a sterile pack that includes all needed devices for peripheral intravenous catheterization according to the latest evidence (eg, cannula, swabs, disposable tourniquet, antiseptic).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PIVC pack</intervention_name>
    <description>The PIVC pack is a sterile container that includes inside all the need devices to perform peripheral catheterization. The pack is color-coded to inform healthcare professionals about the catheter caliber inside.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PIVC pack</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who require peripheral intravenous catheterization as part of their
             therapeutic plan (caliber 20G or 22G);

          -  Participants whose primary nurse agrees to participate in the study;

          -  Participants who are able to give written assent or oral assent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Confused and/or disoriented participants;

          -  Participants who are unable to communicate orally and/or in writing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paulo Costa, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Health Sciences Research Unit: Nursing</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paulo Costa, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>00351967405475</phone>
    <email>paulocosta.15@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>João Graveto, PhD</last_name>
    <email>jgraveto@esenfc.pt</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moureau NL, Trick N, Nifong T, Perry C, Kelley C, Carrico R, Leavitt M, Gordon SM, Wallace J, Harvill M, Biggar C, Doll M, Papke L, Benton L, Phelan DA. Vessel health and preservation (Part 1): a new evidence-based approach to vascular access selection and management. J Vasc Access. 2012 Jul-Sep;13(3):351-6. doi: 10.5301/jva.5000042.</citation>
    <PMID>22307471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marsh N, Webster J, Mihala G, Rickard CM. Devices and dressings to secure peripheral venous catheters: A Cochrane systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Nurs Stud. 2017 Feb;67:12-19. doi: 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2016.11.007. Epub 2016 Nov 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27889585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nobre A., Martins M. Prevalência de flebite da venopunção periférica: fatores associados. Revista de Enfermagem Referência 4(16): 127-138, 2018.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Braga L. Práticas de enfermagem e a segurança do doente no processo de punção de vasos e na administração da terapêutica endovenosa (Doctoral Thesis). Universidade de Lisboa, 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Costa P. Gestão de Material Clínico de Bolso por Enfermeiros: fatores determinantes e diversidade microbiológica (Masters' Dissertation). Escola Superior de Enfermagem de Coimbra, 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Escola Superior de Enfermagem de Coimbra</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paulo Costa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MSc, RN</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Catheterization, Peripheral</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will not be shared with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

