<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04084535</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSEULS - PI - 215/2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04084535</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT) vs. Inspiratory Muscle Training on the Recovery After a Maximal Apnea.</brief_title>
  <acronym>(HIIT)</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Inspiratory Muscle Training vs. High Intensity Interval Training Program on the Recovery Capacity After a Maximal Dynamic Apnea in Breath-hold Divers. A Randomized Crossover Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro Universitario La Salle</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro Universitario La Salle</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this randomized cross-over controlled study was to assess the effects of an 4-week
      exercise program on the recovery capacity after a voluntary maximal apnea. Participants will
      be randomly allocated to receive either a high intensity interval training (HIIT), or an
      inspiratory muscle training (IMT) using an inspiratory resistance device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is a multi-center study. 3 different Spanish Freedivers Centres are included in the study
      (Madrid, Zaragoza, and Barcelona).

      For each participant, exercise program started with one or the other program. Hence, both
      interventions were applied once with the participant randomly allocated to receive the same
      intervention. The trial included four study visits. Each exercise training program will be
      applied sessions per week during 4 weeks. Participants received baseline assessments at the
      beginning of nay intervention, and post-intervention assessments at the end of the fourth
      week. The wash-out period will be two weeks. After these two weeks participants switched
      intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen Saturation recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after training intervention (after 4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Oxygen Saturation recovery will be record by the experimenters every 5 seconds by a handheld pulse-oximeter during the 1 min recovery time after a maximal dynamic apnea. The outcome represents the time it takes to get a 95% of saturation during these 1 minute.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung function (forced spirometry)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after training intervention (after 4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The Spirometry will be perform according to American Thoracic Society criteria and was measured in litres. The maneuver will be perform 3 times and recording the best one.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Respiratory Pressures</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after training intervention (after 4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum respiratory pressures (MIP and MEP) will be measure with a device. This device applies an inspiratory/expiratory load which provides a resistance. The maneuver will be perform in a sitting position. Measuring a minimum of 3 times will be perform, recording the highest value.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lactic acid recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after training intervention (after 4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The level of lactic acid in the blood will be measure by a device that used a blood lactic acid measurement that you've gotten by the finger-stick method. It will be record by the experimenters 3 times: immediately after the maximal dynamic apnea, after 3 min and after 10 min of the maximal dynamic apnea.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Rate recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after training intervention (after 4 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Heart Rate will be record by the experimenters every 5 seconds by a handheld pulse-oximeter during the 1 min recovery time after a maximal dynamic apnea. The outcome represents how long does it take before the participant periodic Heart Rate is stabilized during these 1 minute.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Exercise Training</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Muscle Training</condition>
  <condition>High-Intensity Interval Training</condition>
  <condition>Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High intensity interval training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>It will apply a HIIT program for 4 weeks, with 3 sessions per week of 30 min per session, including warm-up, recovery between intervals and return to calm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inspiratory muscle training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>It will apply an inspiratory muscle training for 4 weeks, with 3 sessions per week of 30 min per session, including warm-up, recovery between intervals and return to calm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High intensity interval training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will perform 3 HIIT sessions per week, involving 10 min of intense exercise within a time commitment of 30 min per session, including warm-up, recovery between intervals and cool down.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High intensity interval training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inspiratory muscle training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will perform 3 inspiratory resistance training sessions per week, involving 30 min per session, including warm-up, recovery between intervals</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inspiratory muscle training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Absence of pain or illness

          -  No changes in cognitive ability

          -  Over 18 years old.

          -  Member of the Spanish Federation of Underwater Activities.

          -  Positive medical examination that allows the diver to practice voluntary apnea.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  People with systemic diseases, tumors, infections, pacemakers, history of epilepsy,
             hydrophobia, pregnancy women, pharmacological treatment.

          -  To be participating in other physical activities during the experimental research
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Madrid FREEDIVERS association</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersson JP, Linér MH, Rünow E, Schagatay EK. Diving response and arterial oxygen saturation during apnea and exercise in breath-hold divers. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2002 Sep;93(3):882-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12183481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centro Universitario La Salle</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fran de Asís Fernández</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

