<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04089254</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PCS-2018C1-11111</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04089254</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Suicide Treatment Alternatives for Teens</brief_title>
  <acronym>START</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multi-Site Study to Compare the Outcomes of Psychiatric Treatment of Suicidal Adolescents in Different Treatment Settings</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized trial to compare inpatient care versus outpatient crisis intervention clinic. This
      study plans to enroll up to 1,000 participants across 4 sites in a 5 years period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To address the unmet need of optimizing the treatment and management for adolescent
      suicidality, the investigators propose to evaluate if Outpatient Crisis Intervention Clinic
      (OCIC) leads to better treatment outcomes than inpatient treatment. To achieve this goal, the
      investigators propose a multi- site study to evaluate if OCIC, compared with inpatient care,
      can lead to a lower risk of a suicidal event (primary outcome) as well as higher treatment
      satisfaction (TS) and satisfaction with life (SL) (secondary outcomes) of both the legal
      guardians/parents and patients. Furthermore, the investigators will assess which clinical and
      socioeconomic factors at baseline may affect the treatment outcomes. With the results from
      the proposed study, the investigators will be able to reduce the family and clinician
      decisional uncertainty about the best treatment setting for suicidal adolescents in the
      target population. The results will significantly help patients, families, and clinicians
      with this decision-making process and improve outcomes for suicidal adolescents. The study
      has been designed to accomplish the following Specific Aims (SA):

      SA1: Measure the differences between OCIC and inpatient treatment in the time to first
      recurrence of a suicidal event (a suicide attempt, interrupted attempt, hospitalization
      because of suicidal risk, an emergency/urgent evaluation because of suicidal risk, and a
      death by suicide) and the number of suicidal events over 90 days and 180 days for suicidal
      adolescents after their baseline Emergency Department (ED) visits.

      Hypothesis (H) 1.1: Assignment with randomization to OCIC from the ED will lead to a longer
      time to the first recurrence of a suicidal event compared to inpatient treatment after 90
      days and 180 days from the baseline ED visit for suicidality. H1.2 Assignment with
      randomization to OCIC will lead to a lower number suicidal events over 90 days and 180 days
      when compared to inpatient treatment. H1.3 Heterogeneity of Treatment Effects [HTE]: The
      investigators will examine to what degree the following specific clinical features and
      sociodemographic features differ for patients who respond to OCIC or inpatient psychiatry
      treatment. Response is defined by a delay in first recurrence of a suicidal event and a lower
      number of suicidal events over 90 days and 180 days. Clinical features: 1) Severity of
      suicidal ideation at baseline and over 180 days; 2) number of suicidal events at baseline
      only; 3) Substance use at baseline and over 180 days. Sociodemographic features at baseline:
      1) Age 2) Gender 3) Gender Identity 4) Type of Insurance (public insurance/no
      insurance/private) 5) Ethnicity (Hispanic/Non); 6) Race (African-American (AA) versus
      non-African American); 7) Living with one biological parent, two biological parents, a
      stepparent, a relative, or other SA2: Assess the treatment satisfaction (TS) and satisfaction
      with life (SL) across OCIC and inpatient treatment.

      H2.1: Overall, patients and legal guardians/parents in the OCIC group will have higher TS (at
      the completion of treatment in OCIC or inpatient psychiatry) and better SL than the inpatient
      treatment group over 90 and 180 days.

      SA3: As an exploratory aim, assess the demographics and potential barriers to treatment for a
      third comparator of the &quot;no show&quot; group who were randomized to OCIC or inpatient treatment
      but never showed up or left the inpatient unit against medical advice (AMA).

      H3.1: The no show group (the third comparator) who did not arrive for any OCIC appointments
      or left AMA from inpatient treatment will differ from the other comparators with respect to
      the following barriers to treatment: 1) Age 2) Gender 3) Type of Insurance (public
      insurance/no insurance/private) 4) Ethnicity (Hispanic/Non) 64; 5) Race (African-American
      (AA) versus non-African American) ; 6) Living with one biological parent, two biological
      parents, a stepparent, a relative, or other H3.2: The no show group will have significantly
      shorter time to first recurrence of a suicidal event and a larger number of suicidal events
      over 90 days and 180 days in comparison to the other patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first recurrence of a suicide event</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the differences between OCIC and inpatient treatment in the time to first recurrence of a suicidal event (a suicide attempt, interrupted attempt, hospitalization because of suicidal risk, an emergency/urgent evaluation because of suicidal risk, and a death by suicide).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of suicide events after treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the difference between OCIC and inpatient treatment in the number of suicidal events (a suicide attempt, interrupted attempt, hospitalization because of suicidal risk, an emergency/urgent evaluation because of suicidal risk, and a death by suicide) over 180 days for suicidal adolescents after their baseline ED visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Satisfaction as assessed using the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire-Adapted (CSQ).</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the rate of client treatment satisfaction (TS) across OCIC and inpatient treatment. This will be measured by patient completing the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire-Adapted (CSQ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic factors as assessed using the START demographics form.</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>As an exploratory aim, assess the demographic influences that may impact treatment outcomes for all groups (inpatient, OCIC, and no show group).This will be measured by the patient and parent completing the START demographics form, including information on race, ethnicity, patient sexual orientation, patient sexual identify, household education level and income, family makeup (number of parents and/or guardians in the home), and other socio-economic factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Satisfaction as assessed using the PROMIS® (Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System) Item Bank v1.0 - General Life Satisfaction - Short Form 5a</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assess and compare the patient's life satisfaction following treatment in either OCIC or inpatient using the PROMIS® (Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System) Item Bank v1.0 - General Life Satisfaction - Short Form 5a.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Satisfaction as assessed using the PROMIS Pediatric Item Bank v1.0 - Life Satisfaction - Short Form 4a</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assess and compare the patient's life satisfaction following treatment in either OCIC or inpatient using the Quality of Life Satisfaction as assessed using the PROMIS Pediatric Item Bank v1.0 - Life Satisfaction - Short Form 4a.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Satisfaction as assessed using PROMIS Parent Proxy Item Bank v1.0 - Life Satisfaction - Short Form 8a</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assess and compare the patient's life satisfaction following treatment in either OCIC or inpatient using the : Quality of Life Satisfaction as assessed using PROMIS Parent Proxy Item Bank v1.0 - Life Satisfaction - Short Form 8a.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Suicidal Ideation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inpatient Psychiatry</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Child and adolescent inpatient treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Outpatient Crisis Intervention Clinic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>OCIC is outpatient crisis intervention clinic</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inpatient Psychiatry</intervention_name>
    <description>Inpatient hospitalization to treat and stabilize suicidal thoughts and behavior.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inpatient Psychiatry</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Outpatient Crisis Intervention Clinic</intervention_name>
    <description>Outpatient psychiatric clinic that provides crisis intervention to treat and stabilize suicidal thoughts and behavior.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Outpatient Crisis Intervention Clinic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adolescents (12 to 18 years old) who were brought to the ED due to suicidal thoughts
             or behaviors and require a higher level of care (OCIC or inpatient)

          -  The presence of a legal guardian

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adolescents with suicidal thoughts that place themselves at a serious imminent risk of
             suicide based on clinical judgment and/or responses on the Concise Health Risk
             Tracking Self-Report (CHRT-SR) (a score of 23 or higher on the 14 item CHRT-SR) 70-72

          -  Adolescents who require 24 hour/day supervision but no adult can provide 24 hour/day
             supervision outside of the hospital

          -  Adolescents with suicidal thoughts who had prior OCIC treatment in the past 12 months
             will be excluded

          -  Adolescents without the ability to answer survey questions will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Drew Barzman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Drew Barzman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(513) 636-0807</phone>
    <email>drew.barzman@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jennifer Combs, MSSA</last_name>
    <phone>(513) 803-0007</phone>
    <email>jennifer.combs@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwell Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glen Oaks</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11004</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Victor Fornari, MD</last_name>
      <phone>718-470-3510</phone>
      <email>vfornari@northwell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victor Fornari, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vera Feuer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital and Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Drew Barzman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>513-636-0807</phone>
      <email>drew.barzman@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer Combs, MSSA</last_name>
      <phone>513-803-0007</phone>
      <email>jennifer.combs@cchmc.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Bridge, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>614-722-3066</phone>
      <email>jeff.bridge@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Bridge, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Axelson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center/Children's Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Graham Emslie, MD</last_name>
      <phone>844-424-4537</phone>
      <email>graham.emslie@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Graham Emslie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Beth Kennard, PsyD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cdc.gov/injury/wisqars/index.html</url>
    <description>CDC, Web-based Injury Statistics Query and Reporting System</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Suicide</keyword>
  <keyword>Suicidal</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Suicidal Ideation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

