<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04089163</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Tg 511-19-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04089163</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Toca 511 &amp; Toca FC in Patients With Recurrent High Grade Non-Muscle Invasive Bladder Cancer (Toca 8)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Toca 8: A Multicenter, Open-Label, Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of Toca 511, a Retroviral Replicating Vector, Combined With Toca FC in Patients With Recurrent High Grade Non-Muscle Invasive Bladder Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tocagen Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tocagen Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, multicenter, open-label study of intravesical Toca 511 followed by oral
      Toca FC in patients with high grade (HG) non-muscle invasive bladder cancer (NMIBC), with
      cohort expansion at the recommended Phase 2 dose. Patients with recurrent HG NMIBC who are
      undergoing planned transurethral resection of bladder tumor (TURBT) will be enrolled into the
      study, subject to meeting all entry criteria.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Sponsor decision.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>3+3 dose escalation design with expansion at recommended Phase 2 dose.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Any treatment-related Grade 3 or higher non-hematologic toxicity, excluding nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea that are controllable with appropriate medical measures (eg, antiemetics, antimotility drugs)
Any treatment-related Grade 4 or higher hematologic toxicity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in viral transduction of Toca 511 at each dose level, based on quantitation of viral RNA and DNA in tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks (+/- 1 week)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance of viral RNA in plasma and urine, based on real-time quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR), and of viral DNA in whole blood and urine, based on quantitative PCR (qPCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week for plasma, 4 weeks for urine</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline in immune activity in tumor, peripheral blood, and urine</measure>
    <time_frame>21 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate at 6 and 12 months in patients with carcinoma in situ (CIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Proportion of patients with CIS with complete response at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>High-grade recurrence-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Event free survival overall and at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of cystectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>The proportion of patients who undergo cystectomy</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of disease progression at 6 and 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>The proportion of patients with disease progression at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential Dose Cohorts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Doses of Toca 511 will be evaluated in sequential cohorts. Toca 511 will be administered as a single intravesical instillation. Following Toca 511 administration, Toca FC will be administered orally at a dose of 220 mg/kg/day for 7 days every 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Toca 511</intervention_name>
    <description>Toca 511 consists of a purified retroviral replicating vector encoding a modified yeast cytosine deaminase (CD) gene. The CD gene converts the antifungal drug, flucytosine (5-fluorocytosine; 5-FC) to the anticancer drug 5-fluorouracil (5-FU) in cancer cells that have been infected by the Toca 511 vector.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential Dose Cohorts</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>vocimagene amiretrorepvec</other_name>
    <other_name>retroviral replicating vector (RRV)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Toca FC (extended-release formulation of flucytosine)</intervention_name>
    <description>Toca FC is an extended-release formulation of flucytosine and is supplied as 500 mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential Dose Cohorts</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>flucytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>5-fluorocytosine (5-FC)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provide written informed consent to participate

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Recurrent HG NMIBC, with HG tumor on previous histopathology

          -  Undergoing planned TURBT and biopsy of CIS suspicious areas

          -  No imaging findings consistent with T2 or greater disease, hydronephrosis,
             extravesical disease, nodal involvement, metastases, or other malignancies.

          -  Able and willing to wait at least 2 weeks following intravesical administration of
             Toca 511 to undergo TURBT

          -  If patient is a candidate for standard of care (SOC) intravesical therapy, able and
             willing to wait at least 2 weeks post-TURBT for initiation of such treatment

          -  Patient is able to be catheterized and is anticipated to be able to retain Toca 511
             for approximately 2 hours

          -  Estimated life expectancy of at least 12 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 0 or 1

          -  Patient has adequate organ function, as indicated by the following laboratory values

               -  Complete blood count: hemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL, platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm^3,
                  absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/ mm^3, absolute lymphocyte count ≥ 500/ mm^3

               -  Liver: total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN; unless known
                  Gilbert's syndrome); alanine aminotransferase ≤ 2.5 × ULN

               -  Kidney: estimated glomerular filtration rate (GFR: Cockcroft-Gault) ≥ 50 mL/min

          -  Women of childbearing potential (defined as not postmenopausal [ie, ≥ 12 months of
             non-therapy-induced amenorrhea] or not surgically sterile) must have a negative serum
             pregnancy test within 7 days prior to administration of Toca 511, and be willing to
             use an effective means of contraception in addition to barrier methods (condoms) for
             the duration of the study.

          -  Patient and partner are willing to use condoms for 12 months after receiving Toca 511
             and/or 30 days after the last dose of Toca FC, and/or until there is no evidence of
             the virus in his/her blood or urine, whichever is longer.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of urothelial cancer in the upper tract or urethra; muscle invasive bladder
             cancer; or metastatic bladder cancer

          -  History of bladder tumors other than urothelial carcinoma (ie, neuroendocrine,
             adenocarcinoma, or squamous cell carcinoma)

          -  Treatment with intravesical agents within 28 days prior to Toca 511 administration

          -  TURBT within 12 weeks prior to planned Toca 511 administration

          -  History of pelvic radiation

          -  Bladder tumor located within a bladder diverticulum

          -  Genitourinary procedures (eg, prostate surgery; treatment of ureteral stones or
             moderate to extensive urethral stricture disease) prior to, during, or planned within
             the 4 weeks following TURBT, other than procedures for treatment of bladder tumors

          -  Severe lower urinary tract dysfunction clinically manifest as poor capacity, disabling
             incontinence, chronic catheter use, or chronic infections or stones

          -  Presence of suprapubic catheter

          -  History of other malignancy, unless the patient has been disease-free for at least 5
             years. Adequately treated basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell skin cancer is
             acceptable regardless of time, as well as cervical carcinoma in situ or localized
             prostate carcinoma, after curative treatment. (Note: Men with very low or low risk
             prostate cancer on active surveillance are acceptable candidates for this study.)

          -  Active infection requiring antibiotic, antifungal, or antiviral therapy within 2 weeks
             prior to administration of Toca 511

          -  Investigational treatment within 2 weeks or immunotherapy or antibody therapy within
             28 days prior to Toca 511 administration, and/or has not recovered from toxicities
             associated with such treatment

          -  Chronic treatment with autoimmune medications

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositive

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Bleeding diathesis, or required to take anticoagulants or antiplatelet agents,
             including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, that cannot be stopped for surgery

          -  Severe pulmonary, cardiac, or other systemic disease, specifically:

               -  New York Heart Association &gt; Class II congestive heart failure that is not
                  controlled on standard therapy within 6 months prior to Toca 511 administration

               -  Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease, clinically significant
                  ventricular arrhythmia (such as ventricular tachycardia, ventricular
                  fibrillation, or torsades de pointes), clinically significant pulmonary disease
                  (such as ≥ Grade 2 dyspnea)

               -  Any other serious medical, social, or psychological condition that, based on
                  Investigator assessment, may affect the patient's compliance or place the patient
                  at an increased risk of potential treatment complications

          -  History of allergy or intolerance to flucytosine

          -  Presence of a condition that would prevent the patient from being able to swallow Toca
             FC tablets
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-muscle invasive bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>high grade non-muscle invasive bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>HG NMIBC</keyword>
  <keyword>NMIBC</keyword>
  <keyword>high grade NMIBC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Flucytosine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

