<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04083859</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00060382</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00060382</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04083859</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Digital Outreach Intervention for Lung Cancer Screening</brief_title>
  <acronym>mPATH-Lung</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pragmatic Randomized-Controlled Trial of a Digital Outreach Intervention for Lung Cancer Screening: mPATH-Lung (Mobile Patient Technology for Health-Lung)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      mPATH-Lung (mobile Patient Technology for Health - Lung) is an innovative digital outreach
      program that identifies patients who qualify for lung cancer screening and helps them get
      screened. The study will: 1) Determine the effect of mPATH-Lung on receipt of lung cancer
      screening in a pragmatic randomized-controlled trial conducted with primary care patients in
      two large health networks, 2) Elucidate the drivers of patients' screening decisions and
      screening behavior; and 3) Explore implementation outcomes that will impact the
      sustainability and dissemination of mPATH-Lung using program data, surveys, and interviews.

      This project will determine how mPATH-Lung affects patients' screening decisions and their
      completion of screening.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective: Determine the effectiveness of mPATH-Lung on receipt of LCS in a
      randomized pragmatic clinical trial of 1318 patients recruited from two large health
      networks, Wake Forest Baptist Health and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  Elucidate the drivers of patients' decisions to receive or forgo LCS through a values
           clarification exercise embedded within mPATH-Lung and supplemental semi-structured
           interviews of at least 60 patients.

        -  Assess several critical implementation outcomes (reach, acceptability, and
           appropriateness) to inform the sustainability and scalability of mPATH-Lung across
           diverse primary care settings
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion of a lung cancer screening CT scan</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 16 weeks of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Completed low-dose chest CT for lung cancer screening within 16 weeks of study randomization, as determined by electronic health record review</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge of LCS among patients who indicate a strong preference for or against screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks after day of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Mean number of lung cancer screening knowledge items answered correctly</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge of LCS among all patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks after day of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Mean number of lung cancer screening knowledge items answered correctly</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intention to receive LCS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks after day of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Patient intention to receive LCS as measured by a survey item</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung cancer screening decision</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks after day of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Patient decision to receive or forego lung cancer screening in the mPATH-Lung group only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with LCS clinic visits scheduled</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients in each arm who have scheduled a LCS clinic visit, whether or not the visit is completed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with LCS clinic visits completed</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients in each arm who have completed a LCS clinic visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with LCS scans ordered</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients in each arm for whom a LCS scan was ordered</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung cancer screening test results</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The results of a completed lung cancer screening CT, reported using the Lung-RADS classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of LCS false positives</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>A Lung-RADS 3 or 4 result with a negative completed work-up for lung cancer or no diagnosis of lung cancer within 12 months of the scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Invasive procedures following LCS scan</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients in each arm who undergo an invasive procedure following a LCS scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with complications following LCS</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients in each arm who experience a complication from an invasive procedure following a LCS scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overscreening</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients with screen diagnosed lung cancer who are deemed too ill for potentially curative surgery by blinded chart review.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reach of digital outreach strategy</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients sent a digital invitation who complete the eligibility questions on the study website.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reach of mPATH-Lung program</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients randomized to mPATH-Lung who complete the mPATH-Lung program to the point of indicating their screening decision.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of mPATH-Lung program</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 16 weeks after day of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Patient mean score on the program acceptability survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Appropriateness of mPATH-Lung program</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after the last enrolled patient</time_frame>
    <description>Primary care provider mean score on the program appropriateness survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1320</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mPATH-Lung</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the mPATH arm will complete a self-survey and a brief video decision aid, and then invites them to estimate their personal risks and benefits of screening by completing 8 survey items needed to calculate their predicted risk of developing lung cancer based on the validated Prostate, Lung, Colorectal and Ovarian Cancer Screening Trial Model 2012.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care (CONTROL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the control arm will see an animated video about exercise for lung health based on recommendations from the European Lung Foundation. They will not be offered the opportunity to estimate their predicted benefits and harms of screening or to request a lung cancer screening visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mPATH-Lung</intervention_name>
    <description>A web-based program that determines patients eligibility for lung cancer screening (LCS), informs them of LCS, presents them with personalized risk-benefit information, helps them make a screening decision, and helps them schedule a LCS clinic appointment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mPATH-Lung</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lung health video</intervention_name>
    <description>Web-based video about guideline recommended exercise for lung health</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care (CONTROL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meet the Medicare criteria for lung cancer screening:

               -  Age 55 - 77 years

               -  Smoked at least 30 pack years

               -  Current smoker or quit smoking within the past 15 years

          -  Be scheduled to see a primary care provider within the health network in the next 3-4
             weeks

          -  Have a patient portal account, cellphone number, or email address listed in the EHR

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients flagged as needing a language interpreter in the EHR

          -  Those for whom LCS would be inappropriate:

               -  Prior history of lung cancer

               -  Chest CT within the last 12 months

               -  Those with medical conditions predicting shorter life expectancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>77 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David P Miller, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Diana E Flores</last_name>
    <phone>336-713-3103</phone>
    <email>dflores@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina- Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teri L Malo</last_name>
      <phone>919-445-6217</phone>
      <email>malotl@email.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alison T Brenner, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dan Reuland, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arlene Chung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teri L Malo, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diana E Flores</last_name>
      <phone>336-713-3103</phone>
      <email>dflores@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David P Miller, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristie Foley, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ajay Dharod, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christina Bellinger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Cancer Society. Cancer Facts &amp; Figures 2019. Atlanta: American Cancer Society; 2019.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Lung Screening Trial Research Team, Aberle DR, Adams AM, Berg CD, Black WC, Clapp JD, Fagerstrom RM, Gareen IF, Gatsonis C, Marcus PM, Sicks JD. Reduced lung-cancer mortality with low-dose computed tomographic screening. N Engl J Med. 2011 Aug 4;365(5):395-409. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1102873. Epub 2011 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21714641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinsky PF, Church TR, Izmirlian G, Kramer BS. The National Lung Screening Trial: results stratified by demographics, smoking history, and lung cancer histology. Cancer. 2013 Nov 15;119(22):3976-83. doi: 10.1002/cncr.28326. Epub 2013 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24037918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moyer VA; U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Screening for lung cancer: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement. Ann Intern Med. 2014 Mar 4;160(5):330-8. doi: 10.7326/M13-2771.</citation>
    <PMID>24378917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wender R, Fontham ET, Barrera E Jr, Colditz GA, Church TR, Ettinger DS, Etzioni R, Flowers CR, Gazelle GS, Kelsey DK, LaMonte SJ, Michaelson JS, Oeffinger KC, Shih YC, Sullivan DC, Travis W, Walter L, Wolf AM, Brawley OW, Smith RA. American Cancer Society lung cancer screening guidelines. CA Cancer J Clin. 2013 Mar-Apr;63(2):107-17. doi: 10.3322/caac.21172. Epub 2013 Jan 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23315954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaklitsch MT, Jacobson FL, Austin JH, Field JK, Jett JR, Keshavjee S, MacMahon H, Mulshine JL, Munden RF, Salgia R, Strauss GM, Swanson SJ, Travis WD, Sugarbaker DJ. The American Association for Thoracic Surgery guidelines for lung cancer screening using low-dose computed tomography scans for lung cancer survivors and other high-risk groups. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2012 Jul;144(1):33-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2012.05.060.</citation>
    <PMID>22710039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services. Final National Coverage Determination on Screening for Lung Cancer with Low Dose Computed Tomography (LDCT) (CAG-00439N).; 2015. https://www.cms.gov/medicare-coverage-database/details/nca-decision-memo.aspx?NCAId=274. Accessed November 10, 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Fedewa SA. Lung Cancer Screening With Low-Dose Computed Tomography in the United States-2010 to 2015. JAMA Oncol. 2017 Sep 1;3(9):1278-1281. doi: 10.1001/jamaoncol.2016.6416.</citation>
    <PMID>28152136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach PB, Mirkin JN, Oliver TK, Azzoli CG, Berry DA, Brawley OW, Byers T, Colditz GA, Gould MK, Jett JR, Sabichi AL, Smith-Bindman R, Wood DE, Qaseem A, Detterbeck FC. Benefits and harms of CT screening for lung cancer: a systematic review. JAMA. 2012 Jun 13;307(22):2418-29. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.5521. Review. Erratum in: JAMA. 2012 Oct 3;308(13):1324. JAMA. 2013 Jun 5;309(21):2212.</citation>
    <PMID>22610500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris RP, Sheridan SL, Lewis CL, Barclay C, Vu MB, Kistler CE, Golin CE, DeFrank JT, Brewer NT. The harms of screening: a proposed taxonomy and application to lung cancer screening. JAMA Intern Med. 2014 Feb 1;174(2):281-5. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.12745. Review. Erratum in: JAMA Intern Med. 2014 Mar;174(3):484.</citation>
    <PMID>24322781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Veronesi G, Maisonneuve P, Bellomi M, Rampinelli C, Durli I, Bertolotti R, Spaggiari L. Estimating overdiagnosis in low-dose computed tomography screening for lung cancer: a cohort study. Ann Intern Med. 2012 Dec 4;157(11):776-84. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-157-11-201212040-00005.</citation>
    <PMID>23208167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patz EF Jr. Lung cancer screening, overdiagnosis bias, and reevaluation of the Mayo Lung Project. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2006 Jun 7;98(11):724-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16757691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kovalchik SA, Tammemagi M, Berg CD, Caporaso NE, Riley TL, Korch M, Silvestri GA, Chaturvedi AK, Katki HA. Targeting of low-dose CT screening according to the risk of lung-cancer death. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jul 18;369(3):245-254. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1301851.</citation>
    <PMID>23863051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner A, Howard K, Lewis C, Sheridan S, Crutchfield T, Hawley S, Reuland D, Kistler C, Pignone M. Comparing 3 values clarification methods for colorectal cancer screening decision-making: a randomized trial in the US and Australia. J Gen Intern Med. 2014 Mar;29(3):507-13. doi: 10.1007/s11606-013-2701-0. Epub 2013 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>24272830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reuland DS, Cubillos L, Brenner AT, Harris RP, Minish B, Pignone MP. A pre-post study testing a lung cancer screening decision aid in primary care. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2018 Jan 12;18(1):5. doi: 10.1186/s12911-018-0582-1.</citation>
    <PMID>29325548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fagerlin A, Pignone M, Abhyankar P, Col N, Feldman-Stewart D, Gavaruzzi T, Kryworuchko J, Levin CA, Pieterse AH, Reyna V, Stiggelbout A, Scherer LD, Wills C, Witteman HO. Clarifying values: an updated review. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2013;13 Suppl 2:S8. doi: 10.1186/1472-6947-13-S2-S8. Epub 2013 Nov 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24625261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elwyn G, O'Connor A, Stacey D, Volk R, Edwards A, Coulter A, Thomson R, Barratt A, Barry M, Bernstein S, Butow P, Clarke A, Entwistle V, Feldman-Stewart D, Holmes-Rovner M, Llewellyn-Thomas H, Moumjid N, Mulley A, Ruland C, Sepucha K, Sykes A, Whelan T; International Patient Decision Aids Standards (IPDAS) Collaboration. Developing a quality criteria framework for patient decision aids: online international Delphi consensus process. BMJ. 2006 Aug 26;333(7565):417. Epub 2006 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>16908462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards A, Elwyn G. Shared Decision-Making in Health Care: Achieving Evidence-Based Patient Choice. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter-Harris L, Brandzel S, Wernli KJ, Roth JA, Buist DSM. A qualitative study exploring why individuals opt out of lung cancer screening. Fam Pract. 2017 Apr 1;34(2):239-244. doi: 10.1093/fampra/cmw146.</citation>
    <PMID>28122849</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ali N, Lifford KJ, Carter B, McRonald F, Yadegarfar G, Baldwin DR, Weller D, Hansell DM, Duffy SW, Field JK, Brain K. Barriers to uptake among high-risk individuals declining participation in lung cancer screening: a mixed methods analysis of the UK Lung Cancer Screening (UKLS) trial. BMJ Open. 2015 Jul 14;5(7):e008254. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-008254.</citation>
    <PMID>26173719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lillie SE, Fu SS, Fabbrini AE, Rice KL, Clothier B, Nelson DB, Doro EA, Moughrabieh MA, Partin MR. What factors do patients consider most important in making lung cancer screening decisions? Findings from a demonstration project conducted in the Veterans Health Administration. Lung Cancer. 2017 Feb;104:38-44. doi: 10.1016/j.lungcan.2016.11.021. Epub 2016 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28212998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quaife SL, Marlow LAV, McEwen A, Janes SM, Wardle J. Attitudes towards lung cancer screening in socioeconomically deprived and heavy smoking communities: informing screening communication. Health Expect. 2017 Aug;20(4):563-573. doi: 10.1111/hex.12481. Epub 2016 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27397651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jonnalagadda S, Bergamo C, Lin JJ, Lurslurchachai L, Diefenbach M, Smith C, Nelson JE, Wisnivesky JP. Beliefs and attitudes about lung cancer screening among smokers. Lung Cancer. 2012 Sep;77(3):526-31. doi: 10.1016/j.lungcan.2012.05.095. Epub 2012 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22681870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter-Harris L, Ceppa DP, Hanna N, Rawl SM. Lung cancer screening: what do long-term smokers know and believe? Health Expect. 2017 Feb;20(1):59-68. doi: 10.1111/hex.12433. Epub 2015 Dec 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26701339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roth JA, Carter-Harris L, Brandzel S, Buist DSM, Wernli KJ. A qualitative study exploring patient motivations for screening for lung cancer. PLoS One. 2018 Jul 5;13(7):e0196758. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0196758. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29975709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Triplette M, Kross EK, Mann BA, Elmore JG, Slatore CG, Shahrir S, Romine PE, Frederick PD, Crothers K. An Assessment of Primary Care and Pulmonary Provider Perspectives on Lung Cancer Screening. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2018 Jan;15(1):69-75. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201705-392OC.</citation>
    <PMID>28933940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanodra NM, Pope C, Halbert CH, Silvestri GA, Rice LJ, Tanner NT. Primary Care Provider and Patient Perspectives on Lung Cancer Screening. A Qualitative Study. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2016 Nov;13(11):1977-1982.</citation>
    <PMID>27676369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajupet S, Doshi D, Wisnivesky JP, Lin JJ. Attitudes About Lung Cancer Screening: Primary Care Providers Versus Specialists. Clin Lung Cancer. 2017 Nov;18(6):e417-e423. doi: 10.1016/j.cllc.2017.05.003. Epub 2017 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>28648531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henderson LM, Jones LM, Marsh MW, Brenner AT, Goldstein AO, Benefield TS, Greenwood-Hickman MA, Molina PL, Rivera MP, Reuland DS. Opinions, practice patterns, and perceived barriers to lung cancer screening among attending and resident primary care physicians. Risk Manag Healthc Policy. 2018 Jan 22;10:189-195. doi: 10.2147/RMHP.S143152. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>29403320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simmons VN, Gray JE, Schabath MB, Wilson LE, Quinn GP. High-risk community and primary care providers knowledge about and barriers to low-dose computed topography lung cancer screening. Lung Cancer. 2017 Apr;106:42-49. doi: 10.1016/j.lungcan.2017.01.012. Epub 2017 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28285693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ersek JL, Eberth JM, McDonnell KK, Strayer SM, Sercy E, Cartmell KB, Friedman DB. Knowledge of, attitudes toward, and use of low-dose computed tomography for lung cancer screening among family physicians. Cancer. 2016 Aug 1;122(15):2324-31. doi: 10.1002/cncr.29944. Epub 2016 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27294476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raz DJ, Wu GX, Consunji M, Nelson RA, Kim H, Sun CL, Sun V, Kim JY. The Effect of Primary Care Physician Knowledge of Lung Cancer Screening Guidelines on Perceptions and Utilization of Low-Dose Computed Tomography. Clin Lung Cancer. 2018 Jan;19(1):51-57. doi: 10.1016/j.cllc.2017.05.013. Epub 2017 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>28652090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis JA, Petty WJ, Tooze JA, Miller DP, Chiles C, Miller AA, Bellinger C, Weaver KE. Low-Dose CT Lung Cancer Screening Practices and Attitudes among Primary Care Providers at an Academic Medical Center. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2015 Apr;24(4):664-70. doi: 10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-14-1241. Epub 2015 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25613118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raz DJ, Wu GX, Consunji M, Nelson R, Sun C, Erhunmwunsee L, Ferrell B, Sun V, Kim JY. Perceptions and Utilization of Lung Cancer Screening Among Primary Care Physicians. J Thorac Oncol. 2016 Nov;11(11):1856-1862. doi: 10.1016/j.jtho.2016.06.010. Epub 2016 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>27346412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter-Harris L, Tan AS, Salloum RG, Young-Wolff KC. Patient-provider discussions about lung cancer screening pre- and post-guidelines: Health Information National Trends Survey (HINTS). Patient Educ Couns. 2016 Nov;99(11):1772-1777. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2016.05.014. Epub 2016 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>27241830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner AT, Malo TL, Margolis M, Elston Lafata J, James S, Vu MB, Reuland DS. Evaluating Shared Decision Making for Lung Cancer Screening. JAMA Intern Med. 2018 Oct 1;178(10):1311-1316. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2018.3054.</citation>
    <PMID>30105393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volk RJ, Linder SK, Leal VB, Rabius V, Cinciripini PM, Kamath GR, Munden RF, Bevers TB. Feasibility of a patient decision aid about lung cancer screening with low-dose computed tomography. Prev Med. 2014 May;62:60-3. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2014.02.006. Epub 2014 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24518006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Housten AJ, Lowenstein LM, Leal VB, Volk RJ. Responsiveness of a Brief Measure of Lung Cancer Screening Knowledge. J Cancer Educ. 2018 Aug;33(4):842-846. doi: 10.1007/s13187-016-1153-8.</citation>
    <PMID>27966194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellinger C, Pinsky P, Foley K, Case D, Dharod A, Miller D. Lung Cancer Screening Benefits and Harms Stratified by Patient Risk: Information to Improve Patient Decision Aids. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2019 Apr;16(4):512-514. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201810-690RL.</citation>
    <PMID>30620619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dharod A, Bellinger C, Foley K, Case LD, Miller D. The Reach and Feasibility of an Interactive Lung Cancer Screening Decision Aid Delivered by Patient Portal. Appl Clin Inform. 2019 Jan;10(1):19-27. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1676807. Epub 2019 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>30625501</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller DP Jr, Weaver KE, Case LD, Babcock D, Lawler D, Denizard-Thompson N, Pignone MP, Spangler JG. Usability of a Novel Mobile Health iPad App by Vulnerable Populations. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2017 Apr 11;5(4):e43. doi: 10.2196/mhealth.7268.</citation>
    <PMID>28400354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katki HA, Kovalchik SA, Petito LC, Cheung LC, Jacobs E, Jemal A, Berg CD, Chaturvedi AK. Implications of Nine Risk Prediction Models for Selecting Ever-Smokers for Computed Tomography Lung Cancer Screening. Ann Intern Med. 2018 Jul 3;169(1):10-19. doi: 10.7326/M17-2701. Epub 2018 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29800127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinsky PF, Bellinger CR, Miller DP Jr. False-positive screens and lung cancer risk in the National Lung Screening Trial: Implications for shared decision-making. J Med Screen. 2018 Jun;25(2):110-112. doi: 10.1177/0969141317727771. Epub 2017 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28929865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fagerlin A, Zikmund-Fisher BJ, Ubel PA. Helping patients decide: ten steps to better risk communication. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2011 Oct 5;103(19):1436-43. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djr318. Epub 2011 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21931068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hawley ST, Zikmund-Fisher B, Ubel P, Jancovic A, Lucas T, Fagerlin A. The impact of the format of graphical presentation on health-related knowledge and treatment choices. Patient Educ Couns. 2008 Dec;73(3):448-55. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2008.07.023. Epub 2008 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18755566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffman AS, Hempstead AP, Housten AJ, Richards VF, Lowenstein LM, Leal VB, Volk RJ. Using a Patient Decision Aid Video to Assess Current and Former Smokers' Values About the Harms and Benefits of Lung Cancer Screening With Low-Dose Computed Tomography. MDM Policy Pract. 2018 Apr 19;3(1):2381468318769886. doi: 10.1177/2381468318769886. eCollection 2018 Jan-Jun.</citation>
    <PMID>30288444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pignone MP, Howard K, Brenner AT, Crutchfield TM, Hawley ST, Lewis CL, Sheridan SL. Comparing 3 techniques for eliciting patient values for decision making about prostate-specific antigen screening: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2013 Mar 11;173(5):362-8. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.2651.</citation>
    <PMID>23400279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiner BJ, Lewis CC, Stanick C, Powell BJ, Dorsey CN, Clary AS, Boynton MH, Halko H. Psychometric assessment of three newly developed implementation outcome measures. Implement Sci. 2017 Aug 29;12(1):108. doi: 10.1186/s13012-017-0635-3.</citation>
    <PMID>28851459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lowenstein LM, Richards VF, Leal VB, Housten AJ, Bevers TB, Cantor SB, Cinciripini PM, Cofta-Woerpel LM, Escoto KH, Godoy MC, Linder SK, Munden RF, Volk RJ. A brief measure of Smokers' knowledge of lung cancer screening with low-dose computed tomography. Prev Med Rep. 2016 Jul 26;4:351-6. doi: 10.1016/j.pmedr.2016.07.008. eCollection 2016 Dec.</citation>
    <PMID>27512650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bangor A, Kortum PT, Miller JT. An Empirical Evaluation of the System Usability Scale. Int J Human-Computer Interact. 2008;24(6):574-594. doi:10.1080/10447310802205776</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henderson LM, Marsh MW, Benefield TS, Jones LM, Reuland DS, Brenner AT, Goldstein AO, Molina PL, Maygarden SJ, Rivera MP. Opinions and Practices of Lung Cancer Screening by Physician Specialty. N C Med J. 2019 Jan-Feb;80(1):19-26. doi: 10.18043/ncm.80.1.19.</citation>
    <PMID>30622199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mass screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Early detection of cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Digital health interventions</keyword>
  <keyword>Decision making, computer assisted</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will share de-identified individual participant data that underlie our published or presented results with researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal. Use of the data will be limited to achieve the aims in their submitted proposal. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>We will make the de-identified data available within one year of the publication of the relevant results. Data will remain available for at least 5 years from the last publication of results.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Researchers desiring data access must provide a methodologically sound proposal to the study principal investigator. Use of the data will be limited to achieve the aims in their submitted proposal. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

