<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04087369</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCDnyaya</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04087369</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrated NCD Intervention in Rural Nepal</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Integrated Intervention for Chronic Care Management in Rural Nepal: a Type 2 Hybrid Effectiveness-implementation Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Possible</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nyaya Health Nepal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Government of Nepal, Ministry of Health and Population</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Possible</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We will test an NCD intervention bundle incorporating the World Health Organisation (WHO)'s
      Package for Essential Non-Communicable Disease Interventions (PEN) within an approximate
      population of 300,000 people in rural Nepal. This intervention integrates three
      evidence-based approaches for both facility- and community-based NCD care focused on the key
      areas of Clinical Practice, Counseling, and Technology for two tiers of non-physician
      healthcare worker - Mid-Level Providers and Community Health Workers: 1) Task-shifting of
      evidence-based medicine algorithms and clinical skills from PEN protocols to non-physician
      healthcare workers; 2) Delivering quality counseling based on the Motivational Interviewing
      Model to drive behavior change with respect to both treatment adherence (defined as
      medication adherence and follow-up completion) and risk factor modification (alcohol,
      tobacco, diet, physical activity); 3) Employing a facility- and community-based clinical
      decision support tool for effective integration of PEN protocols into non-physician
      healthcare worker workflow. This five-year study will initial test the acceptability and
      feasibility of the intervention (two years) followed by a type 2 hybrid
      effectiveness-implementation research trial (three years) to which we will apply the RE-AIM
      implementation evaluative framework of both outcomes and process indicators. Co-primary
      outcomes for the intervention bundle will be: a) disease-specific, evidence-based control
      metrics that measures clinical efficacy; b) qualitative evaluation of acceptability and
      feasibility that incorporates perspectives of patients, providers, and government
      stakeholders; and c) an implementation checklist of key intervention process measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Type II diabetes mellitus control measure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled type II diabetes patients achieving &quot;at goal&quot; status, at the completion of the study period (type II diabetes mellitus: Hemoglobin A1c &lt; 7.5 OR fasting blood sugar &lt;130 mg/dL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypertension control measure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled hypertension patients achieving &quot;at goal&quot; status, at the completion of the study period (hypertension: blood pressure &lt;130/80mm Hg or patient-tailored goal per risk stratification)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>COPD control measure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled COPD patients achieving &quot;at goal&quot; status, at the completion of the study period (COPD: exacerbation status ≤1/3 Anthonisen criteria)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tobacco use</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients who were using tobacco at enrollment who are non-users or who have reduced by &gt;50% their tobacco intake, at the completion of the study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol use</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients who were alcohol drinkers at enrollment who are non-drinkers or who have reduced by &gt;50% alcohol intake, at the completion of the study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Home visit coverage (Reach)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients having a CHW home visit</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Clinic visit coverage (Reach)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients having an MLP visit at the clinic, measured monthly according to the patients indicated to be seen that month based on protocol-based guidelines</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic, geographic barriers and facilitators</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients whose CHW has GPS-mapped their households, describing barriers/facilitators to individuals' access, and identifying contributors to variation/inequities</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Loss to follow-up (Reach)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients, stratified by demographic data and NCD conditions, that are lost-to-follow-up after enrollment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Monthly patient touch-points (Effectiveness)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Number of monthly per-patient touch-points, including interactions by both MLPs and CHWs</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence-based hypertension management (Effectiveness)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled hypertension patients in accordance with evidence-based recommendations, as prescribed by clinical algorithms, assessed quarterly by EHR audits</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence-based diabetes management (Effectiveness)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled diabetes patients in accordance with evidence-based recommendations, as prescribed by clinical algorithms, assessed quarterly by EHR audits</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence-based COPD management (Effectiveness)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled COPD patients in accordance with evidence-based recommendations, as prescribed by clinical algorithms, assessed quarterly by EHR audits</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Village cluster adoption (Adoption)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of intended village clusters receiving intervention</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Timely adoption (Adoption)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of intended village clusters rolling-out intervention within 3 months of schedule, according to local governance decisions to roll-out the intervention</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CHW training adoption (Adoption)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of CHWs trained in intervention implementation within first six months</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CHW retention adoption (Adoption)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of of trained CHWs retained in their positions at the completion of the study period</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>MLP training adoption (Adoption)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of MLPs trained in intervention implementation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>MLP retention adoption (Adoption)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of of trained MLPs retained in their positions at the completion of the study period</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Care integration (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of all NCD patients enrolled at the facilities seen by CHWs at home within first month</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CHW supervision completion (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of scheduled CHW supervision field visits completed, stratified by CHN and district</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CHW supervision review meeting completion (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of scheduled quarterly data review meetings held with CHWs and CHNs</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CHW home visit completion (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients with 100% of algorithm-indicated home visits received</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CHW home visit fidelity (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of of topics included at each session as dictated by the condition-specific algorithms, assessed during the CHW supervision field visits by CHNs</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Referral fidelity (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients appropriately referred to MLP care as indicated by the clinical algorithms, assessed during the CHW supervision field visits by CHNs</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Referral completion (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of % of patients referred by CHWs seen by MLPs within the prescribed time window according to the clinical algorithms (e.g. 24hours, 72 hours, 1 week)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>MLP supervision model (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled NCD patients appropriately referred to see a physician by MLPs as indicated by the clinical algorithms, assessed during monthly physician supervision sessions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>MLP visit fidelity (Implementation)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of of enrolled NCD patients with 100% of algorithm-indicated facility visits received, assessed during monthly physician supervision sessions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Total intervention cost (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cost of each intervention component and total costs using the Joint Learning Network costing methodology</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention initiation costs (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage breakdown of initial (one-time) costs for intervention (training, equipment, etc)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention maintenance costs (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage breakdown of maintenance (recurring) costs (on-going training, personnel, materials, and other)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Facility vs. community costs (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of costs of health care divided between facility level and community level</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Geographic cost variation (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variance in costs between village clusters and districts within the intervention catchment area</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Out-of-pocket patient costs (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of costs of health care divided between facility level and community level</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Integrated intervention cost-effectiveness analysis (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pre/post intervention marginal effectiveness for primary outcomes</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost per unit patient (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention cost per enrolled patient</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost per capita (Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention cost per capita</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Projected scale cost(Maintenance)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Projected cost to scale intervention nationally</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Noncommunicable Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bundled NCD WHO PEN Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mixed-methods type 2 hybrid effectiveness-implementation study to evaluate an integrated NCD care management intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bundled NCD WHO PEN Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>In the intervention includes the planned roll-out of the World Health Organization's Package of essential noncommunicable disease interventions (WHO PEN) for primary care in low resource settings by the Government of Nepal, Ministry of Health and Population. In addition, this intervention will include three evidence-based components: 1) non-communicable disease (NCD) care integration using mid-level practitioners (MLPs) and community healthcare workers (CHWs); 2) clinical decision support (CDS) tools to ensure quality care in accordance with best practices; and 3) training and supervision of MLPs to provide motivational interviewing (MI) techniques for modifiable risk factor optimization, with a specific focus on tobacco and alcohol use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bundled NCD WHO PEN Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients aged 18 or older that screen into Nyaya Health Nepal/Possible's chronic
             disease program for the following conditions: Hypertension, Type II Diabetes Mellitus,
             COPD, and Asthma OR

          2. Adult patients aged 18 or older with end-organ pathology resulting from the
             aforementioned conditions including the following: Chronic Kidney Disease, Ischemic
             Heart Disease, Cerebrovascular Disease AND

          3. Healthcare staff; mid-level providers serving at district/primary health center-level
             facility; community health workers serving village clusters, Nyaya Health
             Nepal/Possible and Government of Nepal/Ministry of Health and Population employees
             involved in study design, program implementation, data collection, or data analysis
             processes.

               -  Note, study populations 1 and 2 must reside in either Achham or Dolakha (Nepal)
                  districts.

                    -  Patients must have a noncommunicable note in electronic medical record
                       system at least twice (indicating at least one follow-up visit) and must
                       have minimum 12 weeks in between baseline/endline clinical measures
                       (indicating patients have been followed up for at least 3 months and have 3
                       months of exposure to intervention).

                         -  Patients do not need to have been in study for all 3 years. Duration of
                            exposure to intervention will depend on stepped implementation design.

        Patients may be identified at Bayalpata Hospital (Achham, Nepal) or Charikot Primary Health
        Center (Dolakha, Nepal) by facility clinicians. Community health workers can also identify
        hypertensive patients and refer them to the facility for diagnosis confirmation. Patient
        enrollment will not be restricted by economic status or caste. Patients will not be
        recruited exclusively to participate in the study but will undergo routine evaluations,
        entering the final diagnosis in electronic health record system, tracking progress at each
        patient contact, the frequency for which is determined by the clinician's recommendation
        per World Health Organization Package of Essential Noncommunicable disease intervention
        protocols and the patient's availability. Patients will receive longitudinal care via the
        community health workers at their homes and at the hospitals by mid-level providers and
        staff physicians. Their receipt of care is not contingent upon their enrollment in the
        study; they receive care per routine service delivery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients migrate from the study are before completion of any of the Package of
             Essential Noncommunicable disease interventions

          2. Patients explicitly request exclusion from the study and decline to consent to the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sabitri Sapkota, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Possible/Nyaya Health Nepal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Duncan Maru, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>2128247950</phone>
    <email>duncan@possiblehealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Citrin, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <email>david@possiblehealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bayalpata Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sanfebagar-10</city>
        <state>Achham/Province 7</state>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sabitri Sapkota, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <email>sabitri.sapkota@possiblehealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charikot Primary Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charikot</city>
        <state>Dolakha/Province 3</state>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sabitri Sapkota, MD, MPH</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>implementation research</keyword>
  <keyword>low- and middle-income countries</keyword>
  <keyword>Nepal</keyword>
  <keyword>Package of Essential Noncommunicable disease interventions for primary care in low-resource settings</keyword>
  <keyword>task-shifting</keyword>
  <keyword>non-physician health workers</keyword>
  <keyword>digital tools</keyword>
  <keyword>motivational interviewing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Noncommunicable Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

