<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04083027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Breast MRI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04083027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-mass Enhancement in Breast MRI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patterns of Non-mass Enhancement of Breast MRI Using the BI-RADS Lexicon Fifth Edition With Histopathologic Correlation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) has been proven to be the most sensitive method in
      detection of breast cancer with sensitivity reaching 68-100%. The most frequent indication
      for breast MRI is screening for high-risk patients with a 20% or greater lifetime risk of
      developing breast cancer. Other indications include; assessment of extent of disease and
      screening of the contralateral breast in patients who are newly diagnosed with primary breast
      cancer. Evaluation of residual disease post Breast Conserving Surgery (BCS) with positive
      margins, loco-regional recurrence detection, as well as response to neoadjuvant chemotherapy
      are also well visualized by breast MRI. Furthermore, assessment of inconclusive mammography
      finding without a sonographic correlate, suspicious nipple discharge without a
      sono-mammographic or galacto-graphic correlate and evaluation of metastatic axillary
      lymphadenopathy in case of unknown primary tumor are all indications in which breast MRI has
      shown high sensitivity.

      Breast MRI also helps in identifying multifocal/multicentric or contralateral breast
      malignancies which was not detected by conventional imaging. Moreover, MRI gives more
      accurate data about local extension of invasive breast cancer and in situ tumors than other
      conventional modalities. In some patients newly diagnosed to have cancer breast, breast MRI
      is able to detect additional lesions that has not been found in mammography or breast
      ultrasound in 6 - 34% in the ipsilateral breast and 3 - 5% in the contralateral breast. These
      additional breast lesions are classified into focus, mass, and non-mass enhancement (NME) on
      MRI.

      Non-mass enhancement (NME) is defined as an enhancing abnormality that is not associated with
      the three-dimension volume of a mass, shape and outlining, and they are separate from the
      Background Parenchymal Enhancement (BPE). The fifth edition of the American College of
      Radiology (ACR) Breast Imaging-Reporting and Data System (BI-RADS) lexicon has erased some
      ambiguities, and modified terminologies from the fourth edition to provide more precise
      evaluation in descriptions of the distribution and Internal Enhancement Patterns (IEPs) of
      NME, contributes in quality assurance, better communication with physicians, and enhances
      patient care.

      For morphological assessment of NME, distribution is described as focal, linear, segmental,
      regional, multiple regions, and diffuse. And the IEPs are characterized as homogeneous,
      heterogeneous, clumped, and clustered ring. NME may be benign as Pseudoangiomatous Stromal
      Hyperplasia (PASH), apocrine metaplasia and radiation effect; high risk such as Atypical
      Ductal Hyperplasia (ADH), flat epithelial atypia, intraductal papilloma, radial scar or
      complex sclerosing lesion, or malignant as Ductal Carcinoma in-situ (DCIS), Invasive Ductal
      Carcinoma (IDC), and Invasive Lobular Carcinoma (ILC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patterns of non-mass enhancement on breast MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Within one year; from March 2020 to March 2021</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the various patterns of NME using the BI-RADS lexicon fifth edition with histopathologic correlation; to evaluate their clinical significance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasm</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Breast MRI</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Female patients with mean age 50 ± 17
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all female with mean age 50 ± 17 having breast MRI

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications of MRI as pacemakers, aneurysmal clipping, retained metallic foreign
             bodies, or claustrophobic patients

          -  Pregnant women especially in the first trimester.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>33 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara Mohamed</last_name>
    <phone>+201098349966</phone>
    <email>sara011222@med.au.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eman Abo Elhamd, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+201001980793</phone>
    <email>dr.eman_08@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park SY, Han BK, Ko ES, Ko EY, Cho EY. Additional lesions seen in magnetic resonance imaging of breast cancer patients: the role of second-look ultrasound and imaging-guided interventions. Ultrasonography. 2019 Jan;38(1):76-82. doi: 10.14366/usg.18002. Epub 2018 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>30103597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shin K, Phalak K, Hamame A, Whitman GJ. Interpretation of Breast MRI Utilizing the BI-RADS Fifth Edition Lexicon: How Are We Doing and Where Are We Headed? Curr Probl Diagn Radiol. 2017 Jan - Feb;46(1):26-34. doi: 10.1067/j.cpradiol.2015.12.001. Epub 2015 Dec 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26826797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ha GW, Yi MS, Lee BK, Youn HJ, Jung SH. Clinical outcome of magnetic resonance imaging-detected additional lesions in breast cancer patients. J Breast Cancer. 2011 Sep;14(3):213-8. doi: 10.4048/jbc.2011.14.3.213. Epub 2011 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22031803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho YH, Cho KR, Park EK, Seo BK, Woo OH, Cho SB, Bae JW. Significance of Additional Non-Mass Enhancement in Patients with Breast Cancer on Preoperative 3T Dynamic Contrast Enhanced MRI of the Breast. Iran J Radiol. 2016 Jan 23;13(1):e30909. doi: 10.5812/iranjradiol.30909. eCollection 2016 Jan.</citation>
    <PMID>27127579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SM, Nam KJ, Choo KS, Kim JY, Jeong DW, Kim HY, Kim JY. Patterns of malignant non-mass enhancement on 3-T breast MRI help predict invasiveness: using the BI-RADS lexicon fifth edition. Acta Radiol. 2018 Nov;59(11):1292-1299. doi: 10.1177/0284185118759139. Epub 2018 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29758996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang QX, Ji X, Feng LL, Zheng L, Zhou XQ, Wu Q, Chen X. Significant MRI indicators of malignancy for breast non-mass enhancement. J Xray Sci Technol. 2017;25(6):1033-1044. doi: 10.3233/XST-17311.</citation>
    <PMID>29154312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Machida Y, Shimauchi A, Tozaki M, Kuroki Y, Yoshida T, Fukuma E. Descriptors of Malignant Non-mass Enhancement of Breast MRI: Their Correlation to the Presence of Invasion. Acad Radiol. 2016 Jun;23(6):687-95. doi: 10.1016/j.acra.2016.01.014. Epub 2016 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26976623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Orsi CJ, Sickles EA, Mendelson EB, Morris EA, et al. ACR BI-RADS Atlas, Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System. Reston, VA, American College of Radiology; 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chadashvili T, Ghosh E, Fein-Zachary V, Mehta TS, Venkataraman S, Dialani V, Slanetz PJ. Nonmass enhancement on breast MRI: review of patterns with radiologic-pathologic correlation and discussion of management. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2015 Jan;204(1):219-27. doi: 10.2214/AJR.14.12656. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25539260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sara Mohamed Gamal Hassan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

