<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04088916</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Nº OAIC 986/18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04088916</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Proviral DNA as a Target for HIV-1 Resistance Analysis</brief_title>
  <acronym>HIV</acronym>
  <official_title>Proviral DNA as a Target for HIV-1 Resistance Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chile</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ViiV Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chile</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In summary, in this project the investigators propose to study the proviral DNA genotyping to
      implement a lower cost and wider than the commercial systems currently in use, in order to
      analyze all HIV genes that are therapeutic targets of antiretroviral drugs. Using HIV
      proviral DNA we can obtain information for: HIV-1 Viral Tropism, Mutations associated to
      Integrase Inhibitors, Mutations associated to Transcriptase reverse Inhibitors, Mutations
      associated to Protease Inhibitors, and Mutations associated to GP41 Inhibitors.

      Along with this the investigators propose to validate the proviral DNA as starting material
      for genotyping which is independent of the patient's viral load and achieve a greater number
      of patients living with HIV have access to this important test that is essential in
      monitoring the HIV infection.

      3.2 RESEARCH QUESTIONs Is proviral DNA a genetic compartment suitable for carrying out a
      genotypic resistance test in patients with low or undetectable viral load? Does proviral DNA
      have the same clinical validity that RNA? 3.3.- HYPOTHESIS A resistance genotyping test
      carried out by Proviral DNA detects the same mutations associated to resistance that viral
      RNA.

      3.4.- OBJECTIVES: General/Specific General objective Develop a methodology to assess the
      proviral HIV-1 DNA or RNA as the genetic material for genotyping assays in genes that are
      targets of pharmacological interest as TR reverse transcriptase and protease (PRO), Integrase
      or GP41 Inhibitors and HIV tropism. Specific Objectives

      1. Carry out genotyping by proviral DNA and compare it with the same genes genotyping
      performed with viral RNA. 2. Once the correlation between proviral DNA and RNA has shown,
      standardize a method to use the technique for clinical use in monitoring HIV patients
      according to each patient's needs. RNA for patients with viral load above 1,000 copies/mL.
      Proviral DNA for patients with low or undetectable viral load.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective longitudinal observational study, the objective is to observe and describe the
      prevalence of INRT, INNRT, Protease and INIS mutations detected by proviral DNA in patients
      with virologic failure and low level viremia.

      Inclusion/Exclusion: Our Study will include only patients with HIV that had been confirmed by
      &quot;Instituto de Salud Pública de Chile&quot; (ISP-Chile). Children less than 18 years are excluded.

      Number of Patients: A total of 1,200 patients will be included in a period of three years
      (Including statistical justification, if appropriate).

        1. - Only patients who have signed informed consent will be admitted to our study.

        2. - The admitted patients will have a blood sample taken for an HIV genotypic resistance
           test.

        3. - from the clinical record of each patient admitted, some relevant clinical data will be
           taken to interpret the results such as CD4 T lymphocyte count, Viral Load, date of HIV
           diagnosis, date of initiation of therapy in addition to number and type of treatments
           antiretrovirals

        4. - By way of genotype control, a second blood sample will be taken every year.

      Detailed Description

      Detection of Resistance Mutations in Proviral DNA in HIV-1 Infection

      Background The genetic test HIV proviral DNA (HPD) for resistance to antiretroviral drugs is
      very useful to detect mutations in patients under antiretroviral therapy who has failed to
      achieve undetectable viral loads levels or with low level viremia (LLV).

      HPD allows the detection of circulating resistant variants and archived which could not be
      detected in the plasma.

      HPD is independent of the viral load of patients. This makes it very useful for studies of
      primary resistance as it can detect resistance mutations in recently diagnosed patients with
      low baseline viral loads (&lt;1,000 copies/mL).

      HPD is recommended by the European AIDS Clinical Society EACS for cases where there is not
      HIV RNA for analysis (Barcelona, October 2015).

      HPD is able to analyze resistance to all antiretroviral drugs currently available in the
      market. Therefore, with the HPD innovation we can carry out the following genetic resistance
      tests: HIV Tropism (Maraviroc), resistance to Integrase Inhibitors (Dolutegravir) and
      resistance to Transcriptase reversa/Proteasa (Abacavir).

      Size Sample and Methodology

      During a period of two years, we will study a population of 1,200 patients. These include all
      patients we have analyzed in our HIV center until December 2012. The methodology includes
      nucleic acid extraction, amplification of HIV-1 genes that are targets of therapeutic
      interest and sequencing by traditional and new generation sequencing methods.

      Patient Recruitment: a Total of 1.200 (400 by year)

      Obtaining blood samples: two samples: sample to the start and one sample to the end after one
      year

      DNA and viral RNA extraction:

      RT-PCR amplification:

      Electrophoresis visualization in agarose gels

      Sending samples to Macrogen for sequencing services

      Automatic sequencing by Sanger method in Macrogen USA

      Sequencing by deep sequencing (NGS) in Chile or Macrogen USA

      Sequence Analysis

      Quality Analysis and assemble of raw sequences in software ReCall

      Registry of mutations of clinical interest

      Report on resistance to antiretroviral drugs

      Biostatistical analysis

      Results Report and Publications

      Preliminary results Preliminary analysis of 100 patients with viral load &lt;1,000 copies/mL,
      detected 10% of patients with mutations of resistance to drugs that inhibit reverse
      transcriptase and viral protease. This valuable information enabled earlier therapeutic
      intervention by changing the drug scheme before they reach higher levels of viral load with
      consequent improvement in the clinical management.

      Projections Project Due to the success and immediate application of this preliminary study,
      we believe it become very important to validate this technique as a daily routine genetic
      testing for HIV clinic patients in the public health system. Permanent financing for this
      genetic HIV test for HIV proviral DNA should be given by the Ministry of Health, Government
      of Chile.

      In conclusion, at present HPD is very useful tool to study virologic failure and LLV in order
      to an early change of the antiretroviral therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 8, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proviral DNA as a Target for HIV-1 Resistance Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Develop a methodology to assess the proviral HIV-1 DNA or RNA as the genetic material for genotyping assays in genes that are targets of pharmacological interest as TR reverse transcriptase and protease (PRO), Integrase or GP41 Inhibitors and HIV tropism</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>HIV Seropositivity</condition>
  <condition>Viral Infection</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      HIV ADN proviral
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion/Exclusion: Our Study will include only patients with HIV that had been confirmed
        by &quot;Instituto de Salud Pública de Chile&quot; (ISP-Chile). Children less than 18 years are
        excluded.

        Number of Patients: A total of 1,200 patients will be included in a period of three years
        (Including statistical justification, if appropriate)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Clinical diagnosis of HIV

        viral load &lt;1.000 copies/mL

        under antiretroviral tratment

        Exclusion Criteria:

        HIV negative

        viral load &gt;1.000 copies/mL
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pablo Ferrer, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Clínico Universidad de Chile</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Immunology, HIV and Allergy Section</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <state>Metropolitana</state>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>pablo ferrer, phd</last_name>
      <phone>+56950269199</phone>
      <email>pferrer@hcuch.cl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Molecular Medicine Laboratory</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <state>Metropolitana</state>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>pablo ferrer, phd</last_name>
      <phone>+56950269199</phone>
      <email>pferrer@hcuch.cl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Chile</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>PABLO ANDRES FERRER CAMPOS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADNproviral</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>genotyping</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Seropositivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

