<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04083586</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>frequency involuntary movement</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04083586</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pattern and Frequency of Non-epileptic Involuntary Movements</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pattern and Frequency of Non-epileptic Involuntary Movements. Hospital-based Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We will perform a medical record review of all patients seen in Assiut University hospital,
      Egypt, to determine the frequency of movement disorders seen, disease characteristics,
      diagnostic evaluations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Movement disorders are conventionally divided into major categories: 1) Hyperkinetic movement
      disorders (also called dyskinesias) refer to excessive, often repetitive, involuntary
      movements that intrude into the normal flow of motor activity. This category includes chorea,
      dystonia, myoclonus, stereotypies, tics, and tremor. 2) Hypokinetic movement 3) Ataxia.

      Hyperkinetic movements any unwanted excess movement. Together with hypertonia (abnormally
      increased resistance to externally imposed movement) and negative signs (insufficient muscle
      activity or insufficient control of muscle activity).

      Tremor: Tremor is a rhythmic back-and-forth or oscillating purposeless involuntary movement
      about a joint axis. Tremor occurs at rest (the pill-rolling tremor of Parkinsonism). Postural
      tremor (the fine tremor of hyperthyroidism), Action tremor (intention tremor) occurs near the
      end of a goal-directed movement.

      Chorea : is a series of brief, jerky, explosive ongoing random-appearing sequence of one or
      more discrete involuntary movements, or &quot;fidgeting; there are different causes of chorea,
      Sydenham's chorea. Lesions in the sub thalamic nucleus. Encephalitis with diffuse
      gray-matter. Motor impersistence is a common association.

      Athetosis is a slow, continuous, writhing, sinuous movement, especially marked in the digits
      and extremities, prevents maintenance of a stable posture.

      Myoclonus consists of sequence of repeated, often non-rhythmic sudden brief twitches or jerks
      or involuntary contraction or relaxation of one or more muscles as seen in metabolic
      encephalopathies such as uremic encephalopathy. It can be categorized as &quot;action myoclonus&quot;,
      &quot;postural myoclonus&quot;, or &quot;rest myoclonus&quot; based on the condition when it is observed
      Asterixis :is an intermittency of sustained posture, illustrated by &quot;flapping&quot; of the hands
      when the arms are outstretched and wrists dorsiflexed, as in hepatic encephalopathy.

      Stereotypies are repetitive, simple movements that can be voluntarily suppressed.
      Stereotypies do not necessarily hold the person's attention.

      Tics are repeated, individually recognizable, intermittent movements that are almost always
      briefly suppressible and are usually associated with awareness of an urge to perform the
      movement.

      Dystonia: a movement disorder in which involuntary sustained or intermittent muscle
      contractions cause twisting and repetitive movements, abnormal postures, or both. Dystonic
      postures are often triggered by attempts at voluntary movement or voluntary posture, as may
      occur in task-specific dystonia.

      Hypokinetic movements: include bradykinesia (slowness of movement) and hypokinesia (poverty
      of movement, and movements that are smaller than intended), but also crucially and
      fundamentally the progressive fatiguing and decrement of repetitive alternating movements
      seen during finger or foot tapping. The best known cause and example is Parkinson's disease.

      Ataxia: Ataxia is a degenerative disorder affecting the brain, brainstem or spinal cord. This
      can result in clumsiness, inaccuracy, instability, imbalance, tremor or a lack of
      coordination while performing voluntary movements. Ataxia also can affect speech and movement
      of the eyes.

      Previous epidemiological studies in Egypt showed that the Overall the recorded Crude
      Prevalence Rate (CPR) of Parkinson's disease in Egypt was varied in different governorates
      and ranged from 53 to 557/105 inhabitants Another study was planned to estimate the
      prevalence and to study the aetiological factors of chorea, dystonia, athetosis and
      hemiballismus in Assiut. The prevalence rate for rheumatic chorea was 62/100,000 population,
      whereas Huntington's chorea had a prevalence rate of 21/100,000. The other two common types
      of chorea were reported with prevalence rates of 12/100,000 for the encephalitic type and
      17/100,000 for the atherosclerotic type. No single case of generalized dystonia was recorded
      and all cases were of the focal type of dystonia with a prevalence rate of 26/100,000
      population, but there's no available data about other movement disorders in Egypt
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Crossover</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>•Detect pattern and clinical characteristics of patients with different forms of movement disorders attending Assiut University neurology outpatient clinic and internal department as parkinson's disease</measure>
    <time_frame>from Sep 15th 2019 to March15th 2020.</time_frame>
    <description>Using MDS- Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) (Goetz et al., 2008) for PD. (parts 3) III: Motor Examination, The investigator should &quot;rate what you see.concurrent medical problems and orthopedic problems may interfere with individual items in the motor examination. In situations where it is absolutely impossible to test use the notation &quot;UR&quot; for Unable to Rate. Otherwise, rate the performance of each task as the patient performs in the context of co-morbidities.Do higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>•Detect pattern and clinical characteristics of patients with different forms of movement disorders attending Assiut University neurology outpatient clinic and internal department as dystonia</measure>
    <time_frame>from Sep 15th 2019 to March15th 2020.</time_frame>
    <description>using Fahn-Marsden rating scale (FMRS), for dystonia. The FMDRS is composed of two clinician-rated subscales: a movement subscale, based on patient examination, and a disability subscale, based on the patient's report of disability in activities of daily living.The movement subscale rates dystonia severity and provoking factors in nine body areas, All items have a 5-point score. The provoking factor rates the relation of dystonia to action, from 0 (no dystonia at rest or with action) to 4 (dystonia at rest).The maximal total FMDRS score is 120. The disability subscale is composed of 7 items for activities of daily living,providing a maximum disability sub- score of 30. Do higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>•Detect pattern and clinical characteristics of patients with different forms of movement disorders attending Assiut University neurology outpatient clinic and internal department as essential tremors</measure>
    <time_frame>from Sep 15th 2019 to March15th 2020.</time_frame>
    <description>Using • Tremor assessment form (TAF) for tremor: A questionnaire related to hand tremor consisting of 12 items was prospectively applied to patients with PD or ET in three movement-disorder clinics. Each question was analyzed, and a query-based scoring system was evaluated for differentiating hand tremors between PD and ET</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Involuntary Movements</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>All investigations; laboratory and radiological, needed for diagnosis</intervention_name>
    <description>mri brain, ct brain, drug screening</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with movement disorders attending Assiut University neurology outpatient clinic
        and internal department, from Sep 15th 2019 to March15th 2020.

        sample size: regarding previously estimated prevalence in (kwon KY et al,2019), was 292, so
        our sample size as calculated: Sample Size(n) for Various Confidence Levels
        ________________________________________ Confidence Level(%) Sample Size 95% 167 80% 106
        90% 141 97% 181 99% 203 99.9% 231 99.99% 245

        ________________________________________ Equation Sample size n = [DEFF*Np(1-p)]/
        [(d2/Z21-α/2*(N-1)+p*(1-p)]

        Results from OpenEpi, Version 3, open source calculator--SSPropor
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with movement disorders attending Assiut University neurology outpatient
             clinic and internal department, from Sep 15th 2019 to March15th 2020.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1) involuntary movements epileptic in origin 2) refusal of patient to give consent to
             join the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hamdy El-Tallawy, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Neurology Faculty of Medicine, Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ali Shalash, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Neurology Faculty of Medicine, Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>mohamed abdelhameed, assist prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assistant professor of Neurology Faculty of Medicine, Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>roaa elsabrout, postgraduate</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Resident at neuropsychiatry department Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>roaa elsabrout, postgraduate</last_name>
    <phone>00201064982780</phone>
    <email>rosana6@ymail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>mohamed abdelhameed, assist prof</last_name>
    <phone>00201002629734</phone>
    <email>moh78_abdelhamed@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanger TD, Delgado MR, Gaebler-Spira D, Hallett M, Mink JW; Task Force on Childhood Motor Disorders. Classification and definition of disorders causing hypertonia in childhood. Pediatrics. 2003 Jan;111(1):e89-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12509602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanger TD, Chen D, Delgado MR, Gaebler-Spira D, Hallett M, Mink JW; Taskforce on Childhood Motor Disorders. Definition and classification of negative motor signs in childhood. Pediatrics. 2006 Nov;118(5):2159-67.</citation>
    <PMID>17079590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swedo SE. Sydenham's chorea. A model for childhood autoimmune neuropsychiatric disorders. JAMA. 1994 Dec 14;272(22):1788-91.</citation>
    <PMID>7661914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benabid AL, Benazzouz A, Limousin P, Koudsie A, Krack P, Piallat B, Pollak P. Dyskinesias and the subthalamic nucleus. Ann Neurol. 2000 Apr;47(4 Suppl 1):S189-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10762147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janavs JL, Aminoff MJ. Dystonia and chorea in acquired systemic disorders. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1998 Oct;65(4):436-45. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9771763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardoso F, Eduardo C, Silva AP, Mota CC. Chorea in fifty consecutive patients with rheumatic fever. Mov Disord. 1997 Sep;12(5):701-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9380051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morris JG, Jankelowitz SK, Fung VS, Clouston PD, Hayes MW, Grattan-Smith P. Athetosis I: historical considerations. Mov Disord. 2002 Nov;17(6):1278-80.</citation>
    <PMID>12465068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caviness JN, Brown P. Myoclonus: current concepts and recent advances. Lancet Neurol. 2004 Oct;3(10):598-607. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15380156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy CH, Meyer KA, Knowles T, Shukla S. Analyzing the multiple functions of stereotypical behavior for students with autism: implications for assessment and treatment. J Appl Behav Anal. 2000 Winter;33(4):559-71.</citation>
    <PMID>11214031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swedo SE, Leonard HL, Garvey M, Mittleman B, Allen AJ, Perlmutter S, Lougee L, Dow S, Zamkoff J, Dubbert BK. Pediatric autoimmune neuropsychiatric disorders associated with streptococcal infections: clinical description of the first 50 cases. Am J Psychiatry. 1998 Feb;155(2):264-71. Erratum in: Am J Psychiatry 1998 Apr;155(4):578.</citation>
    <PMID>9464208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meierkord H, Fish DR, Smith SJ, Scott CA, Shorvon SD, Marsden CD. Is nocturnal paroxysmal dystonia a form of frontal lobe epilepsy? Mov Disord. 1992;7(1):38-42.</citation>
    <PMID>1557065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>El-Tallawy HN, Farghaly WM, Shehata GA, Rageh TA, Hakeem NM, Hamed MA, Badry R. Prevalence of Parkinson's disease and other types of Parkinsonism in Al Kharga district, Egypt. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2013;9:1821-6. doi: 10.2147/NDT.S48318. Epub 2013 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24379673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Roaa Almoataz Abdelrazik Zohni Elsabrout</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>post graduate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyskinesias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

