<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04080141</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>981/b</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04080141</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Termination of Pregnancy and Psychiatric Implications</brief_title>
  <acronym>TTOP_PSY</acronym>
  <official_title>Therapeutic Termination of Pregnancy: Maternal and Paternal Mental Health Before and in the Long-term</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Milano Bicocca</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Milano Bicocca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      25 parental couples, with a prenatal diagnosis of fetal abnormality, had psychiatric
      evaluation for eligibility before TToP and after one year from the procedure. Women and
      unborn's fathers were also subjected to different psychometric questionnaires (HAM-D, HAM-A,
      BDI-II, PCL-5, IPDS, CTQ, CD-RISC-10).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The therapeutic interruption of pregnancy (TTOP) may have psychiatric outcomes like
      depression, anxiety and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD). Personality issues, childhood
      traumas and paternal consequences are too little investigated in current Literature.

      The investigator's aim is exploring the contribution of maternal personality disorders and
      maternal history of childhood traumas to psychiatric outcomes after a TToP, paternal
      psychiatric outcomes and their role on their partner's psychopathological and psychiatric
      outcomes.

      25 couples, with a prenatal diagnosis of fetal abnormality, had psychiatric evaluation for
      eligibility before TToP and after one year from the procedure. Women and unborn's fathers
      were also subjected to different psychometric questionnaires (HAM-D, HAM-A, BDI-II, PCL-5,
      IPDS, CTQ, CD-RISC-10).

      At the time of first contact (T0) only women were subjected to a psychiatric clinical
      examination in order to evaluate their legal eligibility to TToP, according to Italian Law n.
      194/78. At T0 women were also subjected to Hamilton's rating scale for depression (HRSD or
      HAM-D), Hamilton's rating scale for anxiety (HRSA or HAM-A), Beck Depression Inventory
      (BDI-II). At the follow up after 1 year from the first examination (T1) the parental couples
      were subjected to a questionnaire with multiple psychometric tests for mother and her
      partner. The female version included Post-traumatic stress disorder checklist (PCL-5), Iowa
      Personality Disorder Screen (IPDS), Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II), Connor-Davidson
      Resilience Scale 10 (CD-RISC 10) and Short-Form Questionnaire on childhood trauma (CTQ-SF).
      The male version included Post-traumatic stress disorder checklist (PCL-5), Iowa Personality
      Disorder Screen (IPDS), Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale 10 (CD-RISC 10) and Short-Form
      Questionnaire on childhood trauma (CTQ-SF).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms in women</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in number of women with depressive symptoms at 1 year after TToP assessed with the Beck Depression Inventory, which measure the severity of depressive symptoms. The long form of the Beck Depression Inventory is composed of 21 questions or items, each with four possible responses. Each response is assigned a score ranging from zero to three, indicating the severity of the symptom. The sum of all item scores indicates the severity of depression. Scores from 0 to 9 represent minimal depressive symptoms, scores of 10 to 16 indicate mild depression, scores of 17 to 29 indicate moderate depression, and scores of 30 to 63 indicate severe depression. So, a higher value at the Beck Depression Inventory represent a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-traumatic stress disorder in women</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in number of women with post-traumatic symptoms at 1 year after TToP assessed with the PTSD Checklist 5, which is a 20-item self-report measure that assesses the presence and severity of PTSD symptoms. Responders are asked to rate how bothered they have been by each item in the past month on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 0-4. Items are summed to provide a total score. PCL-5 cut-point of 33 appears to be a reasonable value to use for provisional PTSD diagnosis. Severity can be determined adding scores of each item together to determine a total score. The range is 0-80 and a higher value represent a worse outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms after TToP in men</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in number of men with depressive symptoms at 1 year after TToP assessed with the Beck Depression Inventory, which measure the severity of depressive symptoms. The long form of the Beck Depression Inventory is composed of 21 questions or items, each with four possible responses. Each response is assigned a score ranging from zero to three, indicating the severity of the symptom. The sum of all item scores indicates the severity of depression. Scores from 0 to 9 represent minimal depressive symptoms, scores of 10 to 16 indicate mild depression, scores of 17 to 29 indicate moderate depression, and scores of 30 to 63 indicate severe depression. So, a higher value at the Beck Depression Inventory represent a worse outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-traumatic stress disorder after TToP in men</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in number of men with post-traumatic symptoms at 1 year after TToP assessed with the PTSD Checklist 5 (PCL-5), which is a 20-item self-report measure that assesses the presence and severity of PTSD symptoms. Responders are asked to rate how bothered they have been by each item in the past month on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 0-4. Items are summed to provide a total score. PCL-5 cut-point of 33 appears to be a reasonable value to use for provisional PTSD diagnosis. Severity can be determined adding scores of each item together to determine a total score. The range is 0-80 and a higher value represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants with personality disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with personality disorder assessed with the Iowa Personality Disorder Screen, which is a 11-item screening instrument used to evaluate the presence of a personality disorder. Each item is scored dichotomously by Yes/No, giving individual IPDS scores ranging from 0 to 11. A cut off&gt;4 positive items indicates the presence of a personality disorder. A higher value represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants with childhood trauma</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with a childhood trauma assessed with the Childhood Trauma Questionnaire, which is a standardized, retrospective 28-item self-report inventory that measures the severity of different types of childhood trauma, producing five clinical subscales each comprised of five items: Emotional Abuse, Physical Abuse, Sexual Abuse, Emotional Neglect, Physical Neglect. Participants respond to each item in the context of &quot;when you were growing up&quot; and answer according to a five-point Likert scale ranging from &quot;never&quot; = 1 to &quot;very often&quot; = 5, producing scores of 5 to 25 for each trauma subscale. A cut off&gt;5 points in every subscale indicates the presence of that particular traumatic experience. A higher score in every subscale represent a worse outcome and a more severe type of childhood trauma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Role of personality disorders on depressive symptoms after TToP</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in number of patients with depressive symptoms assessed with the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI, previously described) between participants with a personality disorder (PD+ group) and participants without a personality disorder (PD- group). This difference will be assessed with a statistical analysis. A higher number of patients with depressive symptoms in one of the two groups represent a worse outcome in that group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Role of personality disorders on post-traumatic symptoms after TToP</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in number of patients with post-traumatic symptoms assessed with the PTSD Checklist 5 (PCL-5, previously described) between participants with a personality disorder (PD+ group) and participants without a personality disorder (PD- group). This difference will be assessed with a statistical analysis. A higher number of patients with post-traumatic symptoms in one of the two groups represent a worse outcome in that group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Therapeutic Abortion With Complications</condition>
  <condition>Personality Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Trauma, Psychological</condition>
  <condition>Reproductive Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Depression, Reactive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD+</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with personality disorder</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD-</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects without personality disorder</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multiple psychometric questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>At the time of first contact (T0) only women were subjected to Hamilton's rating scale for depression (HRSD or HAM-D), Hamilton's rating scale for anxiety (HRSA or HAM-A), Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II). At the follow up after 1 year from the first examination (T1) they were subjected to a questionnaire with multiple psychometric tests for mother and her partner. The female version included Post-traumatic stress disorder checklist (PCL-5), Iowa Personality Disorder Screen (IPDS), Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II), Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale 10 (CD-RISC 10) and Short-Form Questionnaire on childhood trauma (CTQ-SF). The male version included Post-traumatic stress disorder checklist (PCL-5), Iowa Personality Disorder Screen (IPDS), Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale 10 (CD-RISC 10) and Short-Form Questionnaire on childhood trauma (CTQ-SF).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PD-</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical psychiatric examination</intervention_name>
    <description>At the time of first contact (T0) only women were subjected to psychiatric clinical examination</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PD-</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        45 parental couples (90 subjects: 45 women and 45 men) with a prenatal diagnosis of fetral
        abnormality followed by Obstetrical Department of ASST Monza
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Prenatal diagnosis of fetal abnormality

          -  Adequate comprehension

          -  Legal eligibility to TToP procedure after psychiatric clinical evaluation

          -  Acceptance on a voluntary basis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Incapacity

          -  Acute psychosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.salute.gov.it/imgs/C_17_normativa_845_allegato.pdf</url>
    <description>Gazzetta Ufficiale della Repubblica Italiana. Legge 22 maggio 1978, n. 194. Norme per la tutela sociale della gravidanza e della maternità e sull'interruzione volontaria della gravidanza</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rasch V, Gammeltoft T, Knudsen LB, Tobiassen C, Ginzel A, Kempf L. Induced abortion in Denmark: effect of socio-economic situation and country of birth. Eur J Public Health. 2008 Apr;18(2):144-9. Epub 2007 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18065434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uria M, Mosquera C. Legal abortion in Asturias (Spain) after the 1985 law: sociodemographic characteristics of women applying for abortion. Eur J Epidemiol. 1999 Jan;15(1):59-64.</citation>
    <PMID>10098997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dehlendorf C, Harris LH, Weitz TA. Disparities in abortion rates: a public health approach. Am J Public Health. 2013 Oct;103(10):1772-9. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2013.301339. Epub 2013 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23948010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taft AJ, Watson LF. Termination of pregnancy: associations with partner violence and other factors in a national cohort of young Australian women. Aust N Z J Public Health. 2007 Apr;31(2):135-42.</citation>
    <PMID>17461004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dehlendorf C, Weitz T. Access to abortion services: a neglected health disparity. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2011 May;22(2):415-21. doi: 10.1353/hpu.2011.0064.</citation>
    <PMID>21551921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pérez G, Ruiz-Muñoz D, Gotsens M, Cases MC, Rodríguez-Sanz M. Social and economic inequalities in induced abortion in Spain as a function of individual and contextual factors. Eur J Public Health. 2014 Feb;24(1):162-9. doi: 10.1093/eurpub/ckt104. Epub 2013 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23902666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taft AJ, Watson LF, Lee C. Violence against young Australian women and association with reproductive events: a cross-sectional analysis of a national population sample. Aust N Z J Public Health. 2004 Aug;28(4):324-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15704695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Major B, Appelbaum M, Beckman L, Dutton MA, Russo NF, West C. Abortion and mental health: Evaluating the evidence. Am Psychol. 2009 Dec;64(9):863-90. doi: 10.1037/a0017497. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19968372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinberg JR, Finer LB. Examining the association of abortion history and current mental health: A reanalysis of the National Comorbidity Survey using a common-risk-factors model. Soc Sci Med. 2011 Jan;72(1):72-82. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2010.10.006. Epub 2010 Oct 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21122964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mota NP, Burnett M, Sareen J. Associations between abortion, mental disorders, and suicidal behaviour in a nationally representative sample. Can J Psychiatry. 2010 Apr;55(4):239-47.</citation>
    <PMID>20416147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Munk-Olsen T, Laursen TM, Pedersen CB, Lidegaard O, Mortensen PB. First-time first-trimester induced abortion and risk of readmission to a psychiatric hospital in women with a history of treated mental disorder. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2012 Feb;69(2):159-65. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2011.153.</citation>
    <PMID>22310504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Ditzhuijzen J, ten Have M, de Graaf R, van Nijnatten CH, Vollebergh WA. Psychiatric history of women who have had an abortion. J Psychiatr Res. 2013 Nov;47(11):1737-43. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2013.07.024. Epub 2013 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23941742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallin Lundell I, Sundström Poromaa I, Frans O, Helström L, Högberg U, Moby L, Nyberg S, Sydsjö G, Georgsson Öhman S, Östlund I, Skoog Svanberg A. The prevalence of posttraumatic stress among women requesting induced abortion. Eur J Contracept Reprod Health Care. 2013 Dec;18(6):480-8. doi: 10.3109/13625187.2013.828030. Epub 2013 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23978220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simoila L, Isometsä E, Gissler M, Suvisaari J, Sailas E, Halmesmäki E, Lindberg N. Schizophrenia and induced abortions: A national register-based follow-up study among Finnish women born between 1965-1980 with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder. Schizophr Res. 2018 Feb;192:142-147. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2017.05.039. Epub 2017 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>28615119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Brien KM, Whelan DR, Sandler DP, Hall JE, Weinberg CR. Predictors and long-term health outcomes of eating disorders. PLoS One. 2017 Jul 10;12(7):e0181104. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0181104. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28700663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roller CG. Sexually compulsive/addictive behaviors in women: a women's healthcare issue. J Midwifery Womens Health. 2007 Sep-Oct;52(5):486-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17826712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Genna NM, Feske U, Larkby C, Angiolieri T, Gold MA. Pregnancies, abortions, and births among women with and without borderline personality disorder. Womens Health Issues. 2012 Jul-Aug;22(4):e371-7. doi: 10.1016/j.whi.2012.05.002.</citation>
    <PMID>22749198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bleil ME, Adler NE, Pasch LA, Sternfeld B, Reijo-Pera RA, Cedars MI. Adverse childhood experiences and repeat induced abortion. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Feb;204(2):122.e1-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2010.09.029. Epub 2010 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21074137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niswander KR, Singer J, Singer M. Psychological reaction to therapeutic abortion. II. Objective response. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1972 Sep 1;114(1):29-33.</citation>
    <PMID>4404655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen L, Roth S. Coping with abortion. J Human Stress. 1984 Fall;10(3):140-5.</citation>
    <PMID>6520395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freeman EW, Rickels K, Huggins GR, Garcia CR, Polin J. Emotional distress patterns among women having first or repeat abortions. Obstet Gynecol. 1980 May;55(5):630-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7366922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zolese G, Blacker CV. The psychological complications of therapeutic abortion. Br J Psychiatry. 1992 Jun;160:742-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1617354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith EM. A follow-up study of women who request abortion. Am J Orthopsychiatry. 1973 Jul;43(4):574-85.</citation>
    <PMID>4716675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharma V, Sommerdyk C, Sharma S. Post-abortion mania. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2013 Apr;16(2):167-9. doi: 10.1007/s00737-013-0328-0. Epub 2013 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23381493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahé V, Dumaine A. Oestrogen withdrawal associated psychoses. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2001 Nov;104(5):323-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11722312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drower SJ, Nash ES. Therapeutic abortion on psychiatric grounds. Part I. A local study. S Afr Med J. 1978 Oct 7;54(15):604-8.</citation>
    <PMID>741260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kersting A, Kroker K, Steinhard J, Hoernig-Franz I, Wesselmann U, Luedorff K, Ohrmann P, Arolt V, Suslow T. Psychological impact on women after second and third trimester termination of pregnancy due to fetal anomalies versus women after preterm birth--a 14-month follow up study. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2009 Aug;12(4):193-201. doi: 10.1007/s00737-009-0063-8. Epub 2009 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19266250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Therapeutic Abortion</keyword>
  <keyword>Personality Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Childhood Trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Personality Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychological Trauma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adjustment Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

