<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04081311</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H2019:298</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04081311</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparison of the Efficacy of Interdental Floss to Water Flosser Around Dental Implants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of the Efficacy of Interdental Floss to Water Flosser Around Dental Implants in Maintenance Patients: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this trial is to determine the effectiveness of a waterfloss system compared to
      flossing in reducing the bleeding on probing (BOP) index around dental implants
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled clinical trial will involve 40 adult patients with previously
      placed and restored dental implants. Patients of the Dr. Sam Borden Graduate Periodontics
      Clinic, Dr. Gerald Niznick College of Dentistry, University of Manitoba with at least a
      single implant with a screw retained crown and a diagnosis of peri-implant health or
      peri-implant mucositis and with Probing Depths (PD) less than 5mm. Patients will receive
      initial periodontal examination (baseline) and then they will be randomly divided in 2
      groups, group 1 with water flosser (experiment) and group 2 with conventional flossing
      (control). All clinical measurements will be taken by a single blinded investigator
      (Periodontal Resident) while a single dental hygienist is responsible for prophylaxis and
      delivery of oral hygiene instructions to the study participants. At each appointment 5
      clinical parameters will be recorded: Full Mouth Plaque Score (FMPS) and Quigley-Hein plaque
      index (QHI) of the implants after the use of a disclosing solution, Probing Depth (PD),
      Bleeding on Probing (BOP) of the study implants recorded at 6 sites (distobuccal, mid-buccal,
      mesiobuccal, distolingual, mid-lingual and mesiolingual) using a UNC 12 Colorvue probe and
      the width of the keratinized tissue (KT) at the buccal surface of the study implants.

      Randomization will be achieved using computerized randomization scheme. Patients meeting
      inclusion criteria will be assigned to one of two groups and allocated by means of sealed
      envelope opened on the day of the examination by the examiner.

      Group A (control): patient will be instructed to floss with TePe Bridge and Implant Floss
      once a day, preferably at nighttime.

      Group B (test): patient will be provided with Waterpik Water Flosser and instructed to water
      floss around the implant once a day, preferably at nighttime.

      To standardize the study, both groups will receive a research bag comprising a manual tooth
      brush and a toothpaste.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This randomized controlled clinical trial will involve 40 adult patients with previously placed and restored dental implants. Patients with at least a single implant with a screw retained crown and a diagnosis of peri-implant health or peri-implant mucositis and with Probing Depths (PD) less than 5mm. Patients will receive initial periodontal examination (baseline) and then they will be randomly divided in 2 groups, group 1 with water flosser (experiment) and group 2 with conventional flossing (control).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>All clinical measurements will be taken by a single blinded investigator (Periodontal Resident) while a single dental hygienist is responsible for prophylaxis and delivery of oral hygiene instructions to the study participants</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in BOP (bleeding on probing) index around dental implants</measure>
    <time_frame>All participants will be seen every 3 months for a one year period: baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>to determine the effectiveness of a waterfloss system compared to flossing in changing the bleeding on probing (BOP) index around dental implants. BOP is a sign of inflammation and is recorded as yes/no (yes for bleeding, no for absence of bleeding). BOP is a percentage calculated by dividing the number of bleeding sites divided by the total number of sites of each implant. A lower percentage indicates lower inflammation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Full Mouth Plaque Score (FMPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>All participants will be seen every 3 months for a one year period: baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>to determine the differences between water flosser compared to flossing in changing the Full Mouth Plaque Score (FMPS). FMPS is a percentage calculated by dividing the number of plaque containing surfaces divided by the total number of available surfaces of each tooth/implant. A lower percentage indicates lower total plaque and means better plaque control</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quigley-Hein plaque index (QHI) around dental implants</measure>
    <time_frame>All participants will be seen every 3 months for a one year period: baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>to determine the differences of a waterfloss system compared to flossing in (QHI) around dental implants. Quigley-Hein plaque index (QHI) is a scale 0 to 5.
0 no plaque.
separate flecks of plaque at the cervical margin of the tooth.
a thin continuous band of plaque (up to one mm) at the cervical margin of the tooth.
a band of plaque wider than one mm but covering less than one-third of the crown of the tooth.
plaque covering at least one-third but less than two-thirds of the crown of the tooth.
plaque covering two-thirds or more of the crown of the tooth.
A lower number indicates better plaque control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing Depth (PD) around dental implants</measure>
    <time_frame>All participants will be seen every 3 months for a one year period: baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>to evaluate the differences of a waterfloss system compared to flossing in Probing Depth (PD) around dental implants. PD is the measurement of the depth of a sulcus by measuring in millimeters the distance from a gingival margin to the base of the sulcus with a calibrated periodontal probe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>keratinized tissue (KT) around dental implants</measure>
    <time_frame>All participants will be seen every 3 months for a one year period: baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>to evaluate the differences of a waterfloss system compared to flossing in the width of keratinized tissue (KT) around dental implants. KT is the stratified, squamous epithelium, that lines the vestibular and oral surfaces of the gingiva.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Implant Site Bleeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>water flosser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>patient will be provided with Waterpik Water Flosser and instructed to water floss around the implant once a day, preferably at nighttime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dental floss</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patient will be instructed to floss with TePe Bridge and Implant Floss once a day, preferably at nighttime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>comparing interdental floss to water flosser around dental implants</intervention_name>
    <description>to determine the effectiveness in reducing the bleeding on probing (BOP) index around dental implants</description>
    <arm_group_label>dental floss</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>water flosser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients that present with at least a single implant with a screw-retained crown

          -  Patients with general good health that do not have a condition contra-indicating
             routine dental treatment

          -  Patients that are compliant with the research protocol and methods

          -  Patients that have read, understood and signed the informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with implants with cemented crowns

          -  Patients with any contact hypersensitivity to the related materials used in the study

          -  Tobacco users (vaping included)

          -  Patients unwilling to sign the informed consent form or follow the protocol of the
             study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carlo Sgarbanti, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>4313730061</phone>
    <email>sgarbanc@myumanitoba.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anastasia Cholakis, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>2042978862</phone>
    <email>anastasia.cholakis@umanitoba.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Manitoba</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winnipeg</city>
        <state>Manitoba</state>
        <zip>R3E 0W2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carlo Sgarbanti, DDS</last_name>
      <phone>4313730061</phone>
      <email>sgarbanc@myumanitoba.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Testori T, Del Fabbro M, Feldman S, Vincenzi G, Sullivan D, Rossi R Jr, Anitua E, Bianchi F, Francetti L, Weinstein RL. A multicenter prospective evaluation of 2-months loaded Osseotite implants placed in the posterior jaws: 3-year follow-up results. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2002 Apr;13(2):154-61.</citation>
    <PMID>11952735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Velzen FJ, Lang NP, Schulten EA, Ten Bruggenkate CM. Dental floss as a possible risk for the development of peri-implant disease: an observational study of 10 cases. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2016 May;27(5):618-21. doi: 10.1111/clr.12650. Epub 2015 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26261052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montevecchi M, De Blasi V, Checchi L. Is Implant Flossing a Risk-Free Procedure? A Case Report with a 6-year Follow-up. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2016 May-Jun;31(3):e79-83. doi: 10.11607/jomi.4263.</citation>
    <PMID>27183086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Worthington HV, MacDonald L, Poklepovic Pericic T, Sambunjak D, Johnson TM, Imai P, Clarkson JE. Home use of interdental cleaning devices, in addition to toothbrushing, for preventing and controlling periodontal diseases and dental caries. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2019 Apr 10;4:CD012018. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD012018.pub2.</citation>
    <PMID>30968949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelekis-Cholakis A, Rothney J. Maintenance of Implant Patients: A Narrative Review. Implant Dent. 2019 Apr;28(2):161-172. doi: 10.1097/ID.0000000000000837. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30601226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magnuson B, Harsono M, Stark PC, Lyle D, Kugel G, Perry R. Comparison of the effect of two interdental cleaning devices around implants on the reduction of bleeding: a 30-day randomized clinical trial. Compend Contin Educ Dent. 2013 Nov-Dec;34 Spec No 8:2-7.</citation>
    <PMID>24568169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dental implants</keyword>
  <keyword>water flosser</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

