<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04082390</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GOLO 1704</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04082390</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of the GOLO for Life System Diet With and Without GOLO Release Supplement on Glycemic Control and Insulin Resistance</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study Evaluating the Effects of the GOLO for Life System Diet With and Without GOLO Release Supplement on Glycemic Control and Insulin Resistance in Overweight and Obese Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Golo</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Golo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled study is intended to observe the short-term
      effects of the GFL System Diet with Release supplement versus GFL System Diet with placebo on
      glycemic metabolism and insulin resistance in patients with Type 2 DM.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fasting Blood Glucose (FBG) at approximately 4 weeks of the GFL System Diet with Release supplement versus GFL System Diet with placebo supplement</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Fructosamine between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in HGB A1C between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Insulin Levels between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in HOMA-IR between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Weight between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Body Mass Index between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Hip Circumference between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Waist Circumference between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Blood Pressure between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Heart Rate between the 2 groups</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RELEASE Supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RELEASE</intervention_name>
    <description>Dietary supplement</description>
    <arm_group_label>RELEASE Supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years and ≤ 80 years

          -  Body mass index (BMI) ≥ 27 and ≤ 60 kg/m2

          -  Have the ability to engage in at least 15 minutes of moderate physical activity such
             as brisk walking

          -  A1C greater than or equal to 6.5% at screening

          -  Willing to comply with study procedures described herein

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current diagnosis of type 1 diabetes

          -  Subjects with a history of hypoglycemia

          -  A history of an eating disorder as defined by the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
             Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5)

          -  Known allergy to any of the components in the Release supplement

          -  A history of prior surgery for weight loss within one year from screening

          -  Currently taking injectable medications to control diabetes, including insulin and
             GLP-1 agonists

          -  Currently pregnant or breastfeeding or have had a baby within the last six weeks

          -  Planning to become pregnant in the next three months. Women of child-bearing potential
             must be willing and able to use adequate and reliable contraception throughout the
             study (e.g. abstinence or barrier with additional spermicidal foam or jelly, or the
             use of intrauterine device or hormonal contraception).

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension at screening defined as Systolic blood pressure greater than
             180 mmHG or Diastolic blood pressure greater than 110 mmHG

          -  Current clinical diagnosis or signs and symptoms of unstable (in the opinion of the
             principle investigator) heart, kidney or liver disease, cancer, or chronic
             neurological disease.

          -  Current participation in any other weight loss or weight management program

          -  Currently taking weight loss medications, or medications or supplements known to be
             associated with significant weight loss or weight gain

          -  Has any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would make participation
             in this study not in the best interest of the subject or that could prevent, limit or
             confound the protocol-specified assessments. Examples include: history of diabetic
             ketoacidosis; active chronic liver disease or cirrhosis; chronic autoimmune disease;
             inflammatory bowel disease, colonic ulceration, partial intestinal obstruction,
             subjects predisposed to intestinal obstruction; chronic intestinal diseases associated
             with marked disorders of digestion or absorption
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert Buynak, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2194648302</phone>
    <email>RBUYNAK@ATT.NET</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

