<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04084379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ETMIplus ChC/SiC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04084379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementation Strategy of Bio-molecular Techniques for Early Diagnose of Congenital Syphilis and Chagas Diseases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Implementation Strategy of Bio-molecular Techniques for Early Diagnose of Congenital Syphilis and Chagas Diseases in Context of ETMIplus Program, OPS/OMS. Multicentric Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Niños R. Gutierrez de Buenos Aires</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Niños R. Gutierrez de Buenos Aires</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chagas disease and syphilis are considered a mayor public health problem worldwide. Both
      pathologies affect socio-economic vulnerable population and they are both transmitted
      congenitally, causing an alarming increasing number of infected newborns. The current
      diagnostic methods for these diseases are based on serology follow-up until 8 to 10 months
      from birth, which considering the population usually involved and their scarce resources,
      usually translates in loosing continuity in their controls and follow-up.

      Chagas prevalence in pregnant women is 4% with an incidence of Congenital Chagas disease of
      1500 annual cases. From those, only 1 third are diagnosed. In the investigators and other
      authors experience, the detection of DNA of Trypanosoma cruzi by PCR shows an elevation of
      parasitemia at birth, with a peak at the first month of life.

      Syphilis is a re-emergent pathology, preventable and curable when diagnose is achieved early
      at the beginning of pregnancy.. The cost-effectiveness of performing screening for this
      infection is widely demonstrated, preventing high morbi-mortality for children when applied
      to pregnant women.

      For both syphilis and Chagas diagnosis, there are some studies comparing PCR follow-up with
      conventional serology, but none were validated and there is still need to bring more evidence
      in order to modify current practice. The investigators propose a sequential study of PCR for
      Tryipanosoma cruzi and Treponema pallidum from birth, believing this will increase
      sensitivity of congenital Chagas and syphilis diagnose and improve follow-up of these
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation of Bio-molecular Techniques (PCR) for Early Diagnose of Congenital Syphilis and Chagas Diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate PCR sensitivity, specificity, PPV and NPP in diagnose of congenital syphilis and congenital Chagas diseases and compare it with current methods. The investigators will measure PCR titles during one year in each patient, and then compare results with serologies, in order to assess if PCR positivization and negativization occurs earlier than current methods. This may allow physicians to shorten time required for follow-up in these patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation of Bio-molecular Techniques (PCR) as terapeutic response biomarker for Congenital Syphilis and Chagas Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will evaluate the utility of PCR as an early biomarker of terapeutic response and compare it to serology for T.pallidum and T. cruzi during and after treatment. This could prevent unnecessary prolonged treatments, and could also allow early diagnose for treatment failures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of different genotypes of T.pallidum in samples to create a database of T.pallidum genotypes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of different genotypes of T.pallidum in samples taken from active skin lessions and blood samples, in order to create a data base of T.pallidum genotypes causing congenital syphilis and acquired syphilis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">560</enrollment>
  <condition>Chagas Disease</condition>
  <condition>Syphilis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Population of this study are children born from mother positive for syphilis or Chagas
        diseases, with congenital infection suspected and children with acquired syphilis.

        They will be recruited at five centers from different geographical areas of Argentina
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Child under 1 year of age, born from mother positive for syphilis not treated or
             inadequately treated during pregnancy

          -  Patients with acquired syphilis

          -  Child under 1 year of age, born from mother with positive serology test for Chagas

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who had received treatment for syphilis or Chagas previously

          -  Patients who are not able to complete scheduled visits

          -  Other diseases that could difficult implementation of this protocol or results
             interpretation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parasitology Division, Children's Hospital &quot;R Gutierrez&quot; of Buenos Aires</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buenos Aires</city>
        <zip>1425</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Altcheh, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>54-11-4964-3093</phone>
      <email>jaltcheh@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jaime Altcheh, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital de Niños R. Gutierrez de Buenos Aires</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Jaime Altcheh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>congenital chagas disease</keyword>
  <keyword>congenital syphilis</keyword>
  <keyword>Chagas PCR diagnose</keyword>
  <keyword>Syphilis PCR diagnose</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syphilis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syphilis, Congenital</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chagas Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

