<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04083755</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-003714-40</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-003714-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04083755</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Intravenous Iron Treatment of Preoperative Anemia in Patients With LEAD (IRONPAD)</brief_title>
  <acronym>IRONPAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Intravenous Iron Treatment of Preoperative Anemia in Patients With Lower Extremity Peripheral Artery Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asociación Instituto de Investigación Sanitaria BioCruces</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asociación Instituto de Investigación Sanitaria BioCruces</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Anaemia due to iron and vitamin deficiency among patients with critical limb
      ischemia is high (&gt;50%). The prevalence of a higher rate of anaemia extends into the three
      months prior to revascularization surgery, it is associated with longer hospital stays and
      more transfusions in addition to being a factor in poor prognoses. Study and treatment of
      anaemia within the perioperative period could improve the surgical outcomes, including the
      recovery and the quality of patients' lives. There are several types of intravenous iron
      preparations with different administration protocols, but there is not a consensus on the
      timing and type of the appropriate iron therapy. To the best of our knowledge, there is no
      data on the performance of intravenous iron in the management of preoperative anaemia in
      patients with peripheral artery disease (PAD) in vascular surgery.

      Methods and analysis: The IRONPAD Study is a phase IV randomised controlled trial with two
      branches of treatment on the efficacy of intravenous iron therapy for the optimisation of
      blood use and prognosis in the perioperative period of patients with anaemia undergoing
      revascularisation for chronic lower limb ischemia. The study randomises 230 patients with
      anaemia to: treat with a single intravenous dose of ferric carboxymaltose (1000 mg) or no
      treatment vs oral iron supplements (if severe anaemia) a minimum of seven days prior to lower
      limb revascularisation surgery. The primary outcome is to reduce the incidence of transfusion
      from randomisation up to 15-45 days after the main surgery. The secondary outcomes will be
      included to establish the optimal preoperative moment of increased intravenous iron
      administration, to raise haemoglobin levels; to study the evolution of haemoglobin from
      inclusion to 15-45 days after surgery; and to determine the impact of anaemia and its
      treatment on the length of hospital stay, morbidity and mortality, as well as the quality of
      life in this period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The IRONPAD Study is a phase IV randomised controlled trial with two branches of treatment on
      the efficacy of intravenous iron therapy for the optimisation of blood use and prognosis in
      the perioperative period of patients with anaemia undergoing revascularisation for chronic
      lower limb ischemia.

      Patients admitted to hospital with anaemia and indication of elective revascularisation
      surgery for chronic ischemia of the lower limbs will be eligible for screening. Anaemia in
      this study is established following the WHO criteria with haemoglobin (Hb) &lt;130 g/L in men
      and &lt;120 g/L in women 21.

      Patients will be selected according to the usual practice, without excluding patients because
      of comorbidity or other reasons that may affect results (selection bias).

      Prior to inclusion, freely given written informed consent will be obtained from all patients.
      Once included, each patient will be masked into a unique identity number (correlative
      according to inclusion), as a reference of patient ID in the registry.

      Each patient will be randomised to a line A or line B of treatment.

        -  Line A: a single, ferric carboxymaltose (Ferinject®) 1000 mg IV iron dose
           administration. The infusion will be according to product specifications with an
           approximate duration of 15 minutes during hospitalisation and will not require an
           additional site visit or extended period of hospitalisation.

        -  Line B: control. The control group will not receive specific treatment. In case of
           severe iron deficiency anaemia, oral iron supplements (iron sulphate dihydrate) will be
           given.

      Both lines may be followed in addition to taking vitamin B12 and folic acid, if indicated.

      The patient, once included in the study, may receive a blood transfusion if the following
      criteria are met:

      - Absolute indication: Hemodynamic instability Active bleeding Hb &lt;7 g/dl

      - Relative indications: in case of Hb &lt;8.5 g/dL or haematocrit &lt;28% following the clinical
      criteria of the medical specialist.

      Interventions to be measured:

      The data collected at baseline will include patients' past medical history, medications,
      blood tests (including hemogram, iron tests and renal function), comorbidity index (Charlson
      Scale), lower limbs chronic ischemia category and the limb scheduled for revascularisation
      (including registry of any trophic lesions and if they have signs of active infection),
      height, weight and body-mass index of the patient. In addition, already validated quality of
      life questionnaire, the Short Form-36 Health Survey (SF-36) will be completed.

      Procedure data will record: date of IV iron treatment, if received, dose and any adverse
      events during or after administration; ASA (American Society of Anaesthesiologists) risk
      level; type of surgery performed for revascularisation of lower limbs, information on
      clinical success and complications of the intervention. Blood records will include
      haemoglobin before and first day after surgery and number of red blood cell units of or any
      other blood component transfused during the surgical procedure. If surgery does not finally
      take place, data from the 30 days after inclusion will be registered for analysis with
      intention to treat.

      The hospital discharge visit will record: date of discharge; last hemogram; number of blood
      transfusions from the postoperative period until discharge; days in intensive care; adverse
      events such as medical and surgical complications as well as mortality.

      The final follow-up visit will take place 30 days after the main surgery (with +/- 15-day
      window) it would be performed by telephone, in the outpatient consultation or in the hospital
      if the patient continues to be hospitalised; in that case, the discharge visit and final
      visit will be made simultaneously. It will record: blood tests (including hemogram, iron
      tests), clinical success, serious adverse events (SAE) and mortality, which may have occurred
      between hospital discharge and the visit in addition to Short Form-36 Health Survey (SF-36).
      See Fig. 1 for Assessment flow diagram.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To reduce the incidence of transfusion (receiving any volume of 1 unit or more than 1 unit of packed red cells) from randomisation up to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of red blood cell units of or any other blood component transfused during the surgical procedure and from the postoperative period until discharge. If surgery does not finally take place, data from the 30 days after inclusion will be registered for analysis with intention to treat.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes and evolution of hemoglobin during admission; difference in hemoglobin (Hb) between inclusion, intervention and discharge.</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after surgical procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The data collected at baseline will include patients blood tests (including hemogram). Blood records during surgical period will include haemoglobin (g/dL) before and first day after surgery. (If surgery does not finally take place, data from the 30 days after inclusion will be registered for analysis with intention to treat).The final follow-up visit will take place 30 days after the main surgery it would be performed by telephone, in the outpatient consultation or in the hospital if the patient continues to be hospitalised; in that case, the discharge visit and final visit will be made simultaneously. It will record: blood tests (including hemogram).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish the optimal preoperative moment of increased intravenous iron yield to increase Hb</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Best time before surgery for treatment anemia with ferric carboxymaltose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of anemia and its treatment on the length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between both groups in days of hospitalization after main surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of anemia and its treatment on morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Serious adverse events such, as medical and surgical complications during hospitalization and at final follow-up visit (which may have occurred between hospital discharge and final the visit).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of anemia and its treatment on mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Death and cause, if known, during hospitalization and at the final follow-up visit (which may have occurred between hospital discharge and final the visit).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of anemia and its treatment on quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>From inclusion date to 30 days (with +/- 15-day window) after the main surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Form-36 Health Survey (SF-36) will be completed at inclusion and at the final visit that will take place 30 days after the main surgery (with +/- 15-day window). It would be performed by telephone, in the outpatient consultation or in the hospital if the patient continues to be hospitalized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Arterial Occlusive Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Line A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One dose of Ferric carboxymaltose (1000mg) intravenous. Duration of administration 15 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Line B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>No treatment or treatment oral with iron supplementation if iron-deficiency anemia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferric Carboxymaltose Injection [Injectafer]</intervention_name>
    <description>1000mg intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Line A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferinject</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>no treatment or oral iron supplementation</intervention_name>
    <description>No treatment or treatment oral with iron supplementation if iron-deficiency anemia</description>
    <arm_group_label>Line B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of both sexes over 18 years

          -  Patients diagnosed with anemia, considered as Hb &lt;13.0 g/dL in mens and Hb&lt;12g/dL in
             women

          -  Patients diagnosed with symptomatic chronic lower limb ischemia (degrees 2-5 by
             Rutherford-Baker, both included, Fontaine II-IV), who will undergo surgical
             revascularization (endovascular or open) and accept treatment

          -  Revascularization surgery scheduled in the approximate minimum period of one week, (&gt;
             7 days) from the inclusion,

          -  They are able and willing to give written informed consent at the time of selection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with acute ischemia will be excluded

          -  Severe anemia &lt; 8 gr/dL

          -  Arterial hypertension not controlled with antihypertensive medication (considered with
             systolic blood pressure&gt; 180mmHg or diastolic&gt; 100mmHg)

          -  Acute renal failure or renal failure with creatinine clearance &lt;30mmHg

          -  Patient with documented intolerance or allergy to iron or its derivatives

          -  Unstable angina, defined as electrocardiographic changes with chest pain that indicate
             resting myocardial ischemia

          -  History of stroke in the previous 6 months

          -  Patients with thrombocytopenia less than 50,000ug/dl or alterations in coagulation

          -  That you are simultaneously participating in a clinical trial that conditions or
             modifies the registry

          -  Patients already diagnosed with iron-deficiency anemia in oral iron treatment in their
             usual medication

          -  Pregnancy or lactation (pregnancy tests in women of childbearing age according to
             usual practice)

          -  Rejection of treatment or inclusion in the registry by the patient

          -  Patients who refuse to receive transfusions of blood products (for example, Jehovah's
             Witnesses)

          -  Patients with criteria of SEPSIS

          -  Patients with Ferritin &lt;30 ng/ml that will be directed for digestive study

          -  Patients with active neoplasia

          -  Patients who are not able to give their informed consent or understand the study
             procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ana Apodaka Diez, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vascular Surgeon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose Manuel Rodriguez Chinesta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Internal Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ana Apodaka, MD</last_name>
    <phone>34946006000</phone>
    <email>ANA.APODAKADIEZ@osakidetza.eus</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio de Angiología y Cirugía vascular del Hospital Universitario Cruces</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baracaldo</city>
        <state>Biscay</state>
        <zip>48903</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Apodaka, MD</last_name>
      <phone>34610471636</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esteban Gracia C, Escudero Rodríguez JR, Preciado Mora MJ, et al. Prevalencia de anemia en pacientes sometidos a cirugía vascular electiva y su influencia en el postoperatorio. Angiologia 2016;68:396-404. doi:10.1016/j.angio.2016.01.015</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vega de Céniga M, Bravo E, Izagirre M, Casco C, Estallo L, Esteban M, Barba A. Anaemia, iron and vitamin deficits in patients with peripheral arterial disease. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2011 Jun;41(6):828-30. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2011.01.017. Epub 2011 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21353606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>González ZM, Barrasa AG, Renau AR. [Anaemia, iron, transfusion and therapeutic alternatives. A review from a surgical perspective]. Cir Esp. 2010 Dec;88(6):358-68. doi: 10.1016/j.ciresp.2010.03.014. Epub 2010 May 11. Review. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>20462573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Musallam KM, Tamim HM, Richards T, Spahn DR, Rosendaal FR, Habbal A, Khreiss M, Dahdaleh FS, Khavandi K, Sfeir PM, Soweid A, Hoballah JJ, Taher AT, Jamali FR. Preoperative anaemia and postoperative outcomes in non-cardiac surgery: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2011 Oct 15;378(9800):1396-407. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61381-0. Epub 2011 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21982521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muñoz M, Gómez-Ramírez S, Martín-Montañez E, Pavía J, Cuenca J, García-Erce JA. Perioperative intravenous iron: an upfront therapy for treating anaemia and reducing transfusion requirements. Nutr Hosp. 2012 Nov-Dec;27(6):1817-36. doi: 10.3305/nh.2012.27.6.6087. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23588429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baron DM, Hochrieser H, Posch M, Metnitz B, Rhodes A, Moreno RP, Pearse RM, Metnitz P; European Surgical Outcomes Study (EuSOS) group for Trials Groups of European Society of Intensive Care Medicine; European Society of Anaesthesiology. Preoperative anaemia is associated with poor clinical outcome in non-cardiac surgery patients. Br J Anaesth. 2014 Sep;113(3):416-23. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeu098. Epub 2014 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24829444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fowler AJ, Ahmad T, Phull MK, Allard S, Gillies MA, Pearse RM. Meta-analysis of the association between preoperative anaemia and mortality after surgery. Br J Surg. 2015 Oct;102(11):1314-24. doi: 10.1002/bjs.9861. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26349842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glance LG, Dick AW, Mukamel DB, Fleming FJ, Zollo RA, Wissler R, Salloum R, Meredith UW, Osler TM. Association between intraoperative blood transfusion and mortality and morbidity in patients undergoing noncardiac surgery. Anesthesiology. 2011 Feb;114(2):283-92. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3182054d06.</citation>
    <PMID>21239971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zollo RA, Eaton MP, Karcz M, Pasternak R, Glance LG. Blood transfusion in the perioperative period. Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol. 2012 Dec;26(4):475-84. doi: 10.1016/j.bpa.2012.10.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23351234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kougias P, Orcutt S, Pak T, Pisimisis G, Barshes NR, Lin PH, Bechara CF. Impact of postoperative nadir hemoglobin and blood transfusion on outcomes after operations for atherosclerotic vascular disease. J Vasc Surg. 2013 May;57(5):1331-7; discussion. doi: 10.1016/j.jvs.2012.10.108. Epub 2013 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23384496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunkelgrun M, Hoeks SE, Welten GM, Vidakovic R, Winkel TA, Schouten O, van Domburg RT, Bax JJ, Kuijper R, Chonchol M, Verhagen HJ, Poldermans D. Anemia as an independent predictor of perioperative and long-term cardiovascular outcome in patients scheduled for elective vascular surgery. Am J Cardiol. 2008 Apr 15;101(8):1196-200. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2007.11.072. Epub 2008 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18394458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desormais I, Aboyans V, Bura A, Constans J, Cambou JP, Messas E, Labrunie A, Lacroix P. Anemia, an independent predictive factor for amputation and mortality in patients hospitalized for peripheral artery disease. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2014 Aug;48(2):202-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2014.04.005. Epub 2014 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24935912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toor IS, Jaumdally RJ, Moss MS, Babu SB. Preprocedural hemoglobin predicts outcome in peripheral vascular disease patients undergoing percutaneous transluminal angioplasty. J Vasc Surg. 2009 Aug;50(2):317-21. doi: 10.1016/j.jvs.2009.03.041.</citation>
    <PMID>19631867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Preciado Mora MJ, Azparren Cabezón G, Escudero Rodríguez JR, et al. La anemia como factor de riesgo quirúrgico en cirugía vascular. Algoritmos de diagnóstico y tratamiento. Angiologia 2017;69:242-9. doi:10.1016/j.angio.2016.08.007</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar A. Perioperative management of anemia: limits of blood transfusion and alternatives to it. Cleve Clin J Med. 2009 Nov;76 Suppl 4:S112-8. doi: 10.3949/ccjm.76.s4.18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19880828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cuenca J, García-Erce JA, Martínez AA, Solano VM, Molina J, Muñoz M. Role of parenteral iron in the management of anaemia in the elderly patient undergoing displaced subcapital hip fracture repair: preliminary data. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2005 Jun;125(5):342-7. Epub 2005 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>15789233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serrano-Trenas JA, Ugalde PF, Cabello LM, Chofles LC, Lázaro PS, Benítez PC. Role of perioperative intravenous iron therapy in elderly hip fracture patients: a single-center randomized controlled trial. Transfusion. 2011 Jan;51(1):97-104. doi: 10.1111/j.1537-2995.2010.02769.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20630042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Froessler B, Palm P, Weber I, Hodyl NA, Singh R, Murphy EM. The Important Role for Intravenous Iron in Perioperative Patient Blood Management in Major Abdominal Surgery: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Ann Surg. 2016 Jul;264(1):41-6. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000001646.</citation>
    <PMID>26817624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallet J, Hanif A, Callum J, Pronina I, Wallace D, Yohanathan L, McLeod R, Coburn N. The impact of perioperative iron on the use of red blood cell transfusions in gastrointestinal surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Transfus Med Rev. 2014 Oct;28(4):205-11. doi: 10.1016/j.tmrv.2014.05.004. Epub 2014 Jun 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24997001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng O, Keeler BD, Mishra A, Simpson A, Neal K, Brookes MJ, Acheson AG. Iron therapy for pre-operative anaemia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 Dec 22;(12):CD011588. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD011588.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2019 Dec 7;12:CD011588.</citation>
    <PMID>26694949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nutritional anaemias. Report of a WHO scientific group. World Health Organ Tech Rep Ser 1968;405:5-37.http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4975372 (accessed 27 Aug 2019).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esteban C, Rodríguez P, Escudero JR, Clarà A, Fernández A, Fernández S, Agúndez I. Anaemia in patients who underwent vascular surgery: a significant predictor of amputation and death. Med Clin (Barc). 2019 Jan 4;152(1):6-12. doi: 10.1016/j.medcli.2018.01.029. Epub 2018 Apr 9. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>29650265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muñoz M, Gómez-Ramírez S, Besser M, et al. Current misconceptions in diagnosis and management of iron deficiency. Blood Transfus 2017;15:422-37. doi:10.2450/2017.0113-17</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dignass AU, Gasche C, Bettenworth D, Birgegård G, Danese S, Gisbert JP, Gomollon F, Iqbal T, Katsanos K, Koutroubakis I, Magro F, Savoye G, Stein J, Vavricka S; European Crohn’s and Colitis Organisation [ECCO]. European consensus on the diagnosis and management of iron deficiency and anaemia in inflammatory bowel diseases. J Crohns Colitis. 2015 Mar;9(3):211-22. doi: 10.1093/ecco-jcc/jju009. Epub 2014 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>25518052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodnough LT, Shander A, Spivak JL, Waters JH, Friedman AJ, Carson JL, Keating EM, Maddox T, Spence R. Detection, evaluation, and management of anemia in the elective surgical patient. Anesth Analg. 2005 Dec;101(6):1858-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16301274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kotzé A, Harris A, Baker C, Iqbal T, Lavies N, Richards T, Ryan K, Taylor C, Thomas D. British Committee for Standards in Haematology Guidelines on the Identification and Management of Pre-Operative Anaemia. Br J Haematol. 2015 Nov;171(3):322-31. doi: 10.1111/bjh.13623. Epub 2015 Sep 6. Review. Erratum in: Br J Haematol. 2016 Jan;172(1):148.</citation>
    <PMID>26343392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards TJ, Noble EJ, Durran A, Mellor N, Hosie KB. Randomized clinical trial of preoperative intravenous iron sucrose to reduce blood transfusion in anaemic patients after colorectal cancer surgery. Br J Surg. 2009 Oct;96(10):1122-8. doi: 10.1002/bjs.6688.</citation>
    <PMID>19731228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim YH, Chung HH, Kang SB, Kim SC, Kim YT. Safety and usefulness of intravenous iron sucrose in the management of preoperative anemia in patients with menorrhagia: a phase IV, open-label, prospective, randomized study. Acta Haematol. 2009;121(1):37-41. doi: 10.1159/000210062. Epub 2009 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19332985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rognoni C, Venturini S, Meregaglia M, Marmifero M, Tarricone R. Efficacy and Safety of Ferric Carboxymaltose and Other Formulations in Iron-Deficient Patients: A Systematic Review and Network Meta-analysis of Randomised Controlled Trials. Clin Drug Investig. 2016 Mar;36(3):177-94. doi: 10.1007/s40261-015-0361-z. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26692005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedrisch JR, Cançado RD. Intravenous ferric carboxymaltose for the treatment of iron deficiency anemia. Rev Bras Hematol Hemoter. 2015 Nov-Dec;37(6):400-5. doi: 10.1016/j.bjhh.2015.08.012. Epub 2015 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26670403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asociación Instituto de Investigación Sanitaria BioCruces</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ana Apodaka Diez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vascular Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>iron</keyword>
  <keyword>surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>PAD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ferric Compounds</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Study protocol will be send to publication in the next months</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>open access to read as soon as published</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>open</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

