<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04087434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N00014-18-C-2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04087434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Health Outcomes for Acute Concussion</brief_title>
  <acronym>HOAC</acronym>
  <official_title>HOAC: Improving Health Outcomes for Acute Concussion Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kendra Jorgensen-Wagers</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Defense and Veterans Brain Injury Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Office of Naval Research (ONR)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this prospective observational trial is to validate the Brain Gauge
      device as an objective tool for concussion assessment and treatment in order to determine if
      a method that has proven successful in 18-22 year old collegiate student-athletes will be
      applicable for military personnel. Overall aims of the study include:

        1. Demonstration that the Brain Gauge can objectively measure concussion in this population
           and thus improve concussion identification and coding.

        2. Demonstration of stronger screening for and tracking of acute concussion and
           documentation of concussion diagnoses, including improved tracking of recovery and
           greater adherence to DOD/VA Clinical Practice Guidelines for acute concussion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this prospective observational trial is to validate the Brain Gauge
      device as an objective tool for concussion assessment and treatment in order to determine if
      a method that has proven successful in 18-22 year old collegiate student-athletes will be
      applicable for military personnel. Overall aims of the study include: Demonstration that the
      Brain Gauge can objectively measure concussion in this population and thus improve concussion
      identification and coding; Demonstration of stronger screening for and tracking of acute
      concussion and documentation of concussion diagnoses, including improved tracking of recovery
      and greater adherence to DOD/VA Clinical Practice Guidelines for acute concussion.

      A retrospective cohort of 300 anonymized patients from Landstuhl Regional Medical Center will
      be used as historical controls to assess diagnosis and recovery patterns, while a comparison
      cohort of 100 healthy active duty members from Fort Bragg, NC, will be used as uninjured
      controls to establish baseline Brain Gauge metrics in this population.

      For the prospective cohort, all participants will receive comprehensive standard of care
      medical assessment and treatment as determined by their clinical team and as appropriate to
      their injury and course of recovery. In addition to standard assessments, participants will
      complete the Brain Gauge assessments at home or in the clinic at selected time points from
      initial assessment through 90 days post-study entry. The Brain Gauge system is designed for
      use by the patient at home and is easily incorporated in a remote, tele-health based patient
      monitoring system.

      Data will be analyzed for compliance with current military Clinical Practice Guidelines
      (CPGs) for mTBI, both with the use of the Brain Gauge system and prior to its implementation.
      Objective cortical neurofunctional measures from the Brain Gauge instrument will be compared
      to standardized clinical measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 10, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validate Brain Gauge to detect clinical/ statistically significant change in reaction time, reaction time variability, temporal order judgment, accuracy,fatigue and stimulus discrimination between concussed and healthy controls..</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Brain Gauge is a health assessment system that takes advantage of the relationship between the sensory nerves in the fingers and the projection of those nerves to the corresponding regions in the brain. The system is composed of a mouse sized test device that uses novel fingertip vibration patterns to probe cortical connectivity and utilize that connectivity to gain more sensitive and specific detection of neural function. In sports concussion studies using this technology has established efficacy for detecting mild traumatic brain injury and tracking its recovery for differentiating individuals with and without traumatic brain injury with no baseline measures required.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine utility of remote telehealth clinical oversight for TBI recovery to improve accountability, and responsibilities for tracking concussion recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>over the course of a year</time_frame>
    <description>Prove efficacy of assessment via remote capability with synchronous and asynchronous Telehealth clinical oversight from TBI trained staff. This trial utilizes a symptom tracking application that patients can deploy on their own phones and complete the neurobehavioral symptom inventory. Mild traumatic brain injuries are difficult to diagnose or assess and are particularly difficult to assess in circumstances were triage decisions are necessary. Use of the Brain Gauge device as well as a patient centered commercial off the shelf software is hypothesized to not only increase patient compliance in treatment but also significantly personalize treatment to foster stronger recovery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Injury, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Retrospective</arm_group_label>
    <description>retrospective review of 300 records of patients following concussive diagnosis to track recovery and adherence to progressive return to activity recommendations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prospective</arm_group_label>
    <description>300 prospective patients enrolled following concussive diagnosis to track recovery, clinical diagnosis and brain gauge performance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>75-100 Healthy Controls recruited by Fort Bragg to assess performance in a healthy population for brain gauge performance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brain Gauge Prospective and Healthy Control</intervention_name>
    <description>The Brain Gauge is a brain health assessment system that takes advantage of the well-documented relationship between the sensory nerves in the fingers and the projection of those nerves to corresponding regions in the brain. The system is composed of a test device (the Brain Gauge) that uses novel fingertip vibration patterns to probe cortical complexity and utilize that complexity to gain more sensitive and specific detection of compromised neural function.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prospective</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Active duty service members with or without a concussion diagnosis within the past 7 days.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Active duty military aged 18-60 stationed within local catchment area.

          -  Confirmed concussion within the last 72 hours

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  a sensory, motor or central neurological disorder such as seizures, ADD/ADHD, autism
             or neuropathy in the hands.

          -  Subtest test records incomplete for key variables such as symptom report inventories.

          -  Current MEB in process.

          -  Pregnant women as there are parts of the Clinical practice guide that cannot be
             implemented as a part of standard clinical care due to pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kendra L Jorgensen-Wagers, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Defense and Veterans Brain Injury Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kendra L Jorgensen-Wagers, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+49637194644995</phone>
    <email>kendra.l.jorgensen-wagers.ctr@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wesley R Cole, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>9109077709</phone>
    <email>wesley.r.cole.civ@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Landstuhl Regional Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Landstuhl</city>
        <state>Rheinland Pfalz</state>
        <zip>09180</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dawn M Collins, MA</last_name>
      <phone>49637194645601</phone>
      <email>dawn.m.collins48.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anna M Komitov, MS</last_name>
      <phone>94637194645601</phone>
      <email>anna.m.komitov.ctr@mail.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Office of Naval Research (ONR)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kendra Jorgensen-Wagers</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Clinical Research Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>concussion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

