<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04404101</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-1854</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04404101</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Pancreatic Cystic Lesions Via EUS-guided Fine Needle Aspiration With and Without Micro Forceps Biopsies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Pancreatic Cystic Lesions Via EUS-Guided Fine Needle Aspiration With and Without Micro Forceps Biopsies: A Multi-Center Prospective Randomized Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pancreatic cystic lesions (PCLs) are a common incidental finding in cross sectional imaging
      (up to 27% on CT scan and 41% on MRI ) and pose a management challenge to physicians.
      According to society guidelines, PCLs with specific features should prompt additional workup
      with endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) for cyst characterization as well as cyst sampling. This can
      help determine if the cyst is mucinous or non-mucinous which has implications for its
      malignant potential. Cyst fluid has traditionally been sampled using EUS with FNA
      (Fine-Needle Aspiration) and sent for fluid analysis (CEA and amylase) and cytology. More
      recently, the adjunctive use of the through-the-scope micro forceps (Moray micro forceps, US
      Endoscopy, Mentor, OH) biopsy (EUS-MFB) has shown promise for diagnosis of PCLs. This
      technology utilizes a micro forceps through a 19-gauge needle to biopsy the cyst wall for
      histology, in addition to collecting cyst fluid for CEA level and cytology. The results of
      this study will hopefully help increase diagnostic yield by obtaining a histopathologic
      diagnosis of these PCLs, and potentially affect practice patterns of the endoscopic
      community, specifically those physicians who perform EUS in these patients. Furthermore, the
      results will help determine whether there is reason to continue this line of research to
      obtain a definite histologic tissue diagnosis of PCLs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pancreatic cystic lesions (PCLs) are a common incidental finding in cross sectional imaging
      (up to 27% on CT scan and 41% on MRI ) and pose a management challenge to physicians.
      According to society guidelines, PCLs with specific features should prompt additional workup
      with endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) for cyst characterization as well as cyst sampling. This can
      help determine if the cyst is mucinous or non-mucinous which has implications for its
      malignant potential. Cyst fluid has traditionally been sampled using EUS with FNA
      (Fine-Needle Aspiration) and sent for fluid analysis (CEA and amylase) and cytology. However,
      despite use of a cyst fluid carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) level cutoff of 192 ng/mL and
      cytology, accuracy of diagnosis for PCLs is poor. As the spectrum ranges from benign to high
      risk for neoplasm, precise diagnosis is critical. More recently, the adjunctive use of the
      through-the-scope micro forceps (Moray micro forceps, US Endoscopy, Mentor, OH) biopsy
      (EUS-MFB) has shown promise for diagnosis of PCLs. This technology utilizes a micro forceps
      through a 19-gauge needle to biopsy the cyst wall for histology, in addition to collecting
      cyst fluid for CEA level and cytology. Only a few small retrospective reports have been
      published regarding the use of MFB. Pancreatic cysts continue to pose a management dilemma
      for practicing clinicians, especially with the increased use of radiologic imaging modalities
      identifying incidental pancreatic cystic lesions with higher frequency. This leads to patient
      anxiety and increased costs due to radiologic surveillance and even surgery. The results of
      this study will hopefully help increase diagnostic yield by obtaining a histopathologic
      diagnosis of these PCLs, and potentially affect practice patterns of the endoscopic
      community, specifically those physicians who perform EUS in these patients. Furthermore, the
      results will help determine whether there is reason to continue this line of research to
      obtain a definite histologic tissue diagnosis of PCLs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical Success of EUS-FNA plus MFB, with EUS-FNA alone for evaluation of PCLs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedural</time_frame>
    <description>(1) Technical success for MFB will be defined as the ability to puncture the cyst with the FNA needle under EUS guidance, advance the micro forceps into the cyst and perform cyst biopsies. For the FNA alone group, technical success will be defined as the ability to puncture the cyst with the FNA needle under EUS guidance and aspirate fluid for analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Success of EUS-FNA plus MFB, with EUS-FNA alone for evaluation of PCLs.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>(2) Clinical success will be defined as the ability to obtain a pathologic tissue diagnosis (diagnostic yield) of the PCL with MFB. Based on prior experience, expected diagnoses include pseudocyst, serous cystadenoma, mucinous cyst (mucinous cystic neoplasm, intra-ductal papillary mucinous neoplasm), adenocarcinoma, and neuroendocrine tumor, to name a few.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of EUS-FNA plus MFB with that of EUS-FNA by recording adverse events per published ASGE (American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy) criteria.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-4 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Intraprocedural and post-procedural adverse events (e.g. bleeding, infection, perforation, pancreatitis, etc.)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical ease in performing FNA and MFB</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedural</time_frame>
    <description>Ease of passage of FNA needle
Ease of passage of Micro Forceps
Ease of EUS visualization of Micro Forceps Technical ease will be scored on a predetermined 5-point Likert scale (1 = best, 5 = worst)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time taken for FNA and time for MFB</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraprocedural</time_frame>
    <description>Time for FNA will defined as time when FNA needle is introduced into the channel of the echoendoscope to the time cyst fluid is collected in the specimen tube/jar.
Time for MFB will be defined as the time when micro forceps is introduced into the FNA needle for the first pass to the time when last tissue fragment is collected into the specimen jar after the last pass.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cyst</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1). EUS-FNA plus MFB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 19-G needle plus micro-forceps will be used for FNA plus MFB.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2). EUS-FNA Alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 19-G needle will be used for FNA alone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1). EUS-FNA plus MFB</intervention_name>
    <description>The cyst will be punctured using a 19-G EUS-FNA needle (endoscopic ultrasound-fine needle aspiration) with a stylet. A transgastric approach will be used for PCLs located in body/tail region, and a transduodenal approach for PCLs in the head/neck region. The stylet will be removed and at least 1 mL of cyst fluid will be aspirated and sent for CEA, and cytology. The entire cyst will not be collapsed by aspiration so as to allow subsequent MFB under direct EUS visualization. If the cyst is noted to collapse (after aspiration of cyst fluid), 1-2 mL sterile saline may be instilled into the cyst at the discretion of the endoscopist to allow MFB. The wall of the cyst will be biopsied using the micro forceps passed through the 19 G needle under direct EUS visualization. Multiple passes with the micro forceps will be performed leaving the 19 G EUS needle in the cyst between micro forceps passes, so as to obtain 4 visible tissue fragments with the micro forceps.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1). EUS-FNA plus MFB</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2). EUS-FNA Alone</intervention_name>
    <description>The cyst will be punctured using an EUS-FNA needle (endoscopic ultrasound-fine needle aspiration) with a stylet. The gauge of the FNA needle (fine needle aspiration) will be decided by the performing endoscopist as per standard practice. A transgastric approach will be used for PCLs located in body/tail region, and a transduodenal approach for PCLs in the head/neck region. Cyst fluid will be aspirated and sent for CEA, and cytology. The entire cyst will be aspirated to collapse the cyst, if feasible. Any separate associated solid mass will be sampled separately with standard EUS-FNA/FNB (endoscopic ultrasound-fine needle aspiration/fine needle biopsy) as per clinical practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2). EUS-FNA Alone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients &gt;18 years old

          -  Cysts &gt; 20 mm in size deemed appropriate for FNA by the endoscopist, based on clinical
             presentation, radiologic imaging features, associated solid mass or nodules, and
             patient anxiety about the diagnosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Inability to provide informed consent

          -  Thrombocytopenia (Platelets &lt; 50,000) or coagulopathy (INR &gt; 1.8)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Post-surgical anatomy where the cyst is not accessible for FNA

          -  Presence of intervening blood vessels on EUS precluding FNA
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mihir Wagh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mihir Wagh, MD</last_name>
    <phone>720-848-2777</phone>
    <email>mihir.wagh@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Janelle M Medernach, MS, RDN</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-6070</phone>
    <email>janelle.medernach@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moris M, Bridges MD, Pooley RA, Raimondo M, Woodward TA, Stauffer JA, Asbun HJ, Wallace MB. Association Between Advances in High-Resolution Cross-Section Imaging Technologies and Increase in Prevalence of Pancreatic Cysts From 2005 to 2014. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2016 Apr;14(4):585-593.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2015.08.038. Epub 2015 Sep 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26370569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tanaka M, Fernández-del Castillo C, Adsay V, Chari S, Falconi M, Jang JY, Kimura W, Levy P, Pitman MB, Schmidt CM, Shimizu M, Wolfgang CL, Yamaguchi K, Yamao K; International Association of Pancreatology. International consensus guidelines 2012 for the management of IPMN and MCN of the pancreas. Pancreatology. 2012 May-Jun;12(3):183-97. doi: 10.1016/j.pan.2012.04.004. Epub 2012 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22687371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vege SS, Ziring B, Jain R, Moayyedi P; Clinical Guidelines Committee; American Gastroenterology Association. American gastroenterological association institute guideline on the diagnosis and management of asymptomatic neoplastic pancreatic cysts. Gastroenterology. 2015 Apr;148(4):819-22; quize12-3. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2015.01.015.</citation>
    <PMID>25805375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Del Chiaro M, Verbeke C, Salvia R, Klöppel G, Werner J, McKay C, Friess H, Manfredi R, Van Cutsem E, Löhr M, Segersvärd R; European Study Group on Cystic Tumours of the Pancreas. European experts consensus statement on cystic tumours of the pancreas. Dig Liver Dis. 2013 Sep;45(9):703-11. doi: 10.1016/j.dld.2013.01.010. Epub 2013 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23415799</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brugge WR, Lewandrowski K, Lee-Lewandrowski E, Centeno BA, Szydlo T, Regan S, del Castillo CF, Warshaw AL. Diagnosis of pancreatic cystic neoplasms: a report of the cooperative pancreatic cyst study. Gastroenterology. 2004 May;126(5):1330-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15131794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Attili F, Pagliari D, Rimbaș M, Inzani F, Brizi MG, Costamagna G, Larghi A. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided histological diagnosis of a mucinous non-neoplastic pancreatic cyst using a specially designed through-the-needle microforceps. Endoscopy. 2016;48 Suppl 1:E188-9. doi: 10.1055/s-0042-108194. Epub 2016 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>27213974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mittal C, Obuch JC, Hammad H, Edmundowicz SA, Wani S, Shah RJ, Brauer BC, Attwell AR, Kaplan JB, Wagh MS. Technical feasibility, diagnostic yield, and safety of microforceps biopsies during EUS evaluation of pancreatic cystic lesions (with video). Gastrointest Endosc. 2018 May;87(5):1263-1269. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2017.12.025. Epub 2018 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>29309781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang ML, Arpin RN, Brugge WR, Forcione DG, Basar O, Pitman MB. Moray micro forceps biopsy improves the diagnosis of specific pancreatic cysts. Cancer Cytopathol. 2018 Jun;126(6):414-420. doi: 10.1002/cncy.21988. Epub 2018 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>29660844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basar O, Yuksel O, Yang DJ, Samarasena J, Forcione D, DiMaio CJ, Wagh MS, Chang K, Casey B, Fernandez-Del Castillo C, Pitman MB, Brugge WR. Feasibility and safety of microforceps biopsy in the diagnosis of pancreatic cysts. Gastrointest Endosc. 2018 Jul;88(1):79-86. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2018.02.039. Epub 2018 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>29510146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barresi L, Crinò SF, Fabbri C, Attili F, Poley JW, Carrara S, Tarantino I, Bernardoni L, Giovanelli S, Di Leo M, Manfrin E, Tacelli M, Bruno MJ, Traina M, Larghi A. Endoscopic ultrasound-through-the-needle biopsy in pancreatic cystic lesions: A multicenter study. Dig Endosc. 2018 Nov;30(6):760-770. doi: 10.1111/den.13197. Epub 2018 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29808529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cotton PB, Eisen GM, Aabakken L, Baron TH, Hutter MM, Jacobson BC, Mergener K, Nemcek A Jr, Petersen BT, Petrini JL, Pike IM, Rabeneck L, Romagnuolo J, Vargo JJ. A lexicon for endoscopic adverse events: report of an ASGE workshop. Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Mar;71(3):446-54. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2009.10.027.</citation>
    <PMID>20189503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Cyst</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 20, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/01/NCT04404101/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 10, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/01/NCT04404101/Prot_SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

