<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04408105</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-3052.cc</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04408105</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Survey Study on Barrett's Esophagus Screening</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCREEN-BE</acronym>
  <official_title>Study of Compliance, Practice Patterns, and Barriers REgarding Established National Screening Programs for Barrett's Esophagus: SCREEN-BE</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American College of Gastroenterology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to optimize Barrett's Esophagus (BE) screening to reduce the
      incidence, morbidity, and mortality of Esophageal Adenocarcinoma (EAC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The initial step to achieve this goal is to study shortcomings of the current BE screening
      referral processes in the United States. These shortcomings will be identified through
      completion of two synergistic aims that assess:, (1) provider knowledge, attitudes, and
      barriers to BE screening referral and (2) patient knowledge, attitudes, and barriers to
      completion of BE screening. The central hypothesis is that there are patient- and
      provider-level factors that can be modified to improve BE screening adherence. This
      hypothesis was formulated based on strong preliminary data demonstrating significant
      single-mindedness among gastroenterologists regarding BE screening criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To define provider-level knowledge, attitudes, and barriers to BE screening.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>This investigator will conduct a survey study among primary care providers and gastroenterologists at 7 large health systems in the U.S.—including 4 tertiary care referral centers and 3 safety-net health systems. Based on constructs from Social Cognitive Theory and Theory of Reasoned Action, the survey will assess provider knowledge, attitudes, and barriers to BE screening among at-risk individuals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the association between patient-level knowledge, attitudes, and barriers regarding BE screening.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>This investigator will conduct a survey study among patients at 7 large health systems in the U.S. Based on constructs from the Health Behavior Framework, the survey will assess patient knowledge, attitudes, and barriers to BE screening. To accomplish these study aims, this investigator has assembled a strong and diverse team with complementary areas of expertise in Barrett's esophagus, and survey research.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease</condition>
  <condition>Barrett's Esophagus</condition>
  <condition>Esophagus Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Care Providers</arm_group_label>
    <description>400 eligible primary care providers (PCPs) will be recruited across the 7 participating sites to complete an anonymous survey. The survey will be distributed to eligible PCPs by the study site research coordinator via anonymous REDCap internet survey with 2 additional automated electronic reminders. There will also be opportunities for providers to complete a paper survey at PCP clinic meetings which will be collected by only the site research coordinator to maintain response anonymity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gastroenterologists</arm_group_label>
    <description>100 eligible gastroenterologists (GIs) will be recruited across the 7 participating sites to complete an anonymous survey. The survey will be distributed to eligible GIs by the study site research coordinator via anonymous REDCap internet survey with 2 additional automated electronic reminders. There will also be opportunities for GIs to complete a paper survey at provider clinic meetings which will be collected by only the site research coordinator to maintain response anonymity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>500 eligible patients will be recruited across the 7 participating sites to complete a survey. The survey will be distributed to eligible patients at the time of a clinic appointment, via telephone, or via a REDCap internet survey that will allow for 2 additional electronic phone call reminders and 1 email reminder.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Primary Care Provider Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>To assess PCP demographics, attitudes, and perceived barriers to BE screening, we have developed a PCP survey using a theoretical model of physician behavior based on Social Cognitive Theory and the Theory of Reasoned Action. This approach has proven effective in colorectal cancer and hepatocellular carcinoma screening. This model includes domains of provider background and experience, screening practices, perceptions of screening, physician influences, and practice environment and practice patterns. To assess PCP knowledge of BE screening, we have designed 9 clinical vignettes that will categorize provider responses into under-, appropriate, and over-use of BE screening. Survey questions and vignettes have been adapted from earlier validated surveys. Prior to distribution, the survey and vignettes will be pretested and refined based on a cognitive interview about the survey among a convenience sample of 10 PCPs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Care Providers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gastroenterologist Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>To assess GI demographics, attitudes, and perceived barriers to BE screening, we have developed a GI survey using a theoretical model of physician behavior based on Social Cognitive Theory and the Theory of Reasoned Action. This approach has proven effective in colorectal cancer and hepatocellular carcinoma screening. This model includes domains of provider background and experience, screening practices, perceptions of screening, physician influences, and practice environment and practice patterns. To assess GI knowledge of BE screening, we have designed 9 clinical vignettes that will categorize provider responses into under-, appropriate, and over-use of BE screening. Survey questions and vignettes have been adapted from earlier validated surveys. Prior to distribution, the survey and vignettes will be pretested and refined based on a cognitive interview about the survey among a convenience sample of 10 GIs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gastroenterologists</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>To assess patient knowledge, attitudes, and barriers to completion of BE screening, we will use a theoretical model of patient behavior on the Health Behavior Framework to guide selection of relevant variables for survey development including 4 domains: knowledge about BE and EAC, potential barriers to BE screening completion, patient attitudes and demographic information. Prior to distribution, the survey will be refined and pretested among a sample of 10 patients with each participant completing a cognitive interview prior to distribution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1. We will include patients with a diagnosis of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD)
             who have at least one outpatient clinic visit at a participating site. Patients will
             be identified through an administrative query of the electronic medical record by
             ICD-10 codes for GERD (K21.0 and K21.9) as well as through a review of the upcoming
             clinic schedule. Patients with prior diagnosis of BE/EAC or language other than
             English will be excluded. Across the 7 sites, we plan to enroll 500 patients.

          2. This study will include PCPs and gastroenterologists at participating sites. Across
             the 7 participating centers, we plan to enroll 100 gastroenterologists and 400 PCPs.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Patient Eligibility Criteria

             Inclusion Criteria:

               -  Patients identified by ICD-10 codes for GERD (K21.0 and K21.9) AND

               -  Have had at least one outpatient clinic visit at a participating site

             Exclusion Criteria:

               -  Prior diagnosis of BE/EAC

               -  Non-English speaking

          2. Provider Eligibility Criteria

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provider must be a PCP and/or gastroenterologist AND

          -  Must be at a participating site
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sachin Wani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erica Miles</last_name>
    <phone>3037246670</phone>
    <email>erica.miles@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sachin Wani</last_name>
    <phone>7208482786</phone>
    <email>sachin.wani@cuanschutz.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Denver Health Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erica Miles, MA</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-6670</phone>
      <email>erica.miles@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sachin Wani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Kolb, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frank Scott, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erica Miles, MA</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-6670</phone>
      <email>erica.miles@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sachin Wani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Kolb, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frank Scott, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ravy Vajravelu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-760-2310</phone>
      <email>ravy.vajravelu@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ravy Vajravelu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Falk, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennsylvania Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ravy Vajravelu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-760-2310</phone>
      <email>ravy.vajravelu@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ravy Vajravelu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennsylvania Presbyterian Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ravy Vajravelu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-760-2310</phone>
      <email>ravy.vajravelu@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ravy Vajravelu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Falk, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parkland Health and Hospital System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mobolaji Odewole</last_name>
      <phone>214-645-8300</phone>
      <email>mobolaji.odewole@UTsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amit Singal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Tavakkoli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mobolaji Odewole</last_name>
      <phone>214-645-8300</phone>
      <email>mobolaji.odewole@UTsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amit Singal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Tavakkoli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dubecz A, Solymosi N, Stadlhuber RJ, Schweigert M, Stein HJ, Peters JH. Does the Incidence of Adenocarcinoma of the Esophagus and Gastric Cardia Continue to Rise in the Twenty-First Century?-a SEER Database Analysis. J Gastrointest Surg. 2013 Nov 15. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>24234242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conio M, Cameron AJ, Romero Y, Branch CD, Schleck CD, Burgart LJ, Zinsmeister AR, Melton LJ 3rd, Locke GR 3rd. Secular trends in the epidemiology and outcome of Barrett's oesophagus in Olmsted County, Minnesota. Gut. 2001 Mar;48(3):304-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11171817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mendes de Almeida JC, Chaves P, Pereira AD, Altorki NK. Is Barrett's esophagus the precursor of most adenocarcinomas of the esophagus and cardia? A biochemical study. Ann Surg. 1997 Dec;226(6):725-33; discussion 733-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9409571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lagergren J, Bergström R, Lindgren A, Nyrén O. Symptomatic gastroesophageal reflux as a risk factor for esophageal adenocarcinoma. N Engl J Med. 1999 Mar 18;340(11):825-31.</citation>
    <PMID>10080844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ASGE STANDARDS OF PRACTICE COMMITTEE, Qumseya B, Sultan S, Bain P, Jamil L, Jacobson B, Anandasabapathy S, Agrawal D, Buxbaum JL, Fishman DS, Gurudu SR, Jue TL, Kripalani S, Lee JK, Khashab MA, Naveed M, Thosani NC, Yang J, DeWitt J, Wani S; ASGE Standards of Practice Committee Chair. ASGE guideline on screening and surveillance of Barrett's esophagus. Gastrointest Endosc. 2019 Sep;90(3):335-359.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2019.05.012.</citation>
    <PMID>31439127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hachem C, Shaheen NJ. Diagnosis and Management of Functional Heartburn. Am J Gastroenterol. 2016 Jan;111(1):53-61; quiz 62. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2015.376. Epub 2016 Jan 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26729546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Gastroenterological Association, Spechler SJ, Sharma P, Souza RF, Inadomi JM, Shaheen NJ. American Gastroenterological Association medical position statement on the management of Barrett's esophagus. Gastroenterology. 2011 Mar;140(3):1084-91. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2011.01.030.</citation>
    <PMID>21376940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peery AF, Crockett SD, Murphy CC, Lund JL, Dellon ES, Williams JL, Jensen ET, Shaheen NJ, Barritt AS, Lieber SR, Kochar B, Barnes EL, Fan YC, Pate V, Galanko J, Baron TH, Sandler RS. Burden and Cost of Gastrointestinal, Liver, and Pancreatic Diseases in the United States: Update 2018. Gastroenterology. 2019 Jan;156(1):254-272.e11. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2018.08.063. Epub 2018 Oct 10. Review. Erratum in: Gastroenterology. 2019 May;156(6):1936.</citation>
    <PMID>30315778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhat SK, McManus DT, Coleman HG, Johnston BT, Cardwell CR, McMenamin U, Bannon F, Hicks B, Kennedy G, Gavin AT, Murray LJ. Oesophageal adenocarcinoma and prior diagnosis of Barrett's oesophagus: a population-based study. Gut. 2015 Jan;64(1):20-5. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2013-305506. Epub 2014 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24700439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spechler SJ, Katzka DA, Fitzgerald RC. New Screening Techniques in Barrett's Esophagus: Great Ideas or Great Practice? Gastroenterology. 2018 May;154(6):1594-1601. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2018.03.031. Epub 2018 Mar 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29577931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menezes A, Tierney A, Yang YX, Forde KA, Bewtra M, Metz D, Ginsberg GG, Falk GW. Adherence to the 2011 American Gastroenterological Association medical position statement for the diagnosis and management of Barrett's esophagus. Dis Esophagus. 2015 Aug-Sep;28(6):538-46. doi: 10.1111/dote.12228. Epub 2014 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24849246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thrift AP. Barrett's Esophagus and Esophageal Adenocarcinoma: How Common Are They Really? Dig Dis Sci. 2018 Aug;63(8):1988-1996. doi: 10.1007/s10620-018-5068-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29671158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubenstein JH, Shaheen NJ. Epidemiology, Diagnosis, and Management of Esophageal Adenocarcinoma. Gastroenterology. 2015 Aug;149(2):302-17.e1. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2015.04.053. Epub 2015 May 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25957861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kramer JR, Shakhatreh MH, Naik AD, Duan Z, El-Serag HB. Use and yield of endoscopy in patients with uncomplicated gastroesophageal reflux disorder. JAMA Intern Med. 2014 Mar;174(3):462-5. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.13015.</citation>
    <PMID>24474391</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qumseya BJ, Bukannan A, Gendy S, Ahemd Y, Sultan S, Bain P, Gross SA, Iyer P, Wani S. Systematic review and meta-analysis of prevalence and risk factors for Barrett's esophagus. Gastrointest Endosc. 2019 Nov;90(5):707-717.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2019.05.030. Epub 2019 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>31152737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaheen NJ, Falk GW, Iyer PG, Gerson LB; American College of Gastroenterology. ACG Clinical Guideline: Diagnosis and Management of Barrett's Esophagus. Am J Gastroenterol. 2016 Jan;111(1):30-50; quiz 51. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2015.322. Epub 2015 Nov 3. Erratum in: Am J Gastroenterol. 2016 Jul;111(7):1077.</citation>
    <PMID>26526079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spechler SJ, Sharma P, Souza RF, Inadomi JM, Shaheen NJ; American Gastroenterological Association. American Gastroenterological Association technical review on the management of Barrett's esophagus. Gastroenterology. 2011 Mar;140(3):e18-52; quiz e13. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2011.01.031. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21376939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wani S, Falk G, Hall M, Gaddam S, Wang A, Gupta N, Singh M, Singh V, Chuang KY, Boolchand V, Gavini H, Kuczynski J, Sud P, Reddymasu S, Bansal A, Rastogi A, Mathur SC, Young P, Cash B, Lieberman DA, Sampliner RE, Sharma P. Patients with nondysplastic Barrett's esophagus have low risks for developing dysplasia or esophageal adenocarcinoma. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2011 Mar;9(3):220-7; quiz e26. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2010.11.008. Epub 2010 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21115133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wani S, Falk GW, Post J, Yerian L, Hall M, Wang A, Gupta N, Gaddam S, Singh M, Singh V, Chuang KY, Boolchand V, Gavini H, Kuczynski J, Sud P, Bansal A, Rastogi A, Mathur SC, Young P, Cash B, Goldblum J, Lieberman DA, Sampliner RE, Sharma P. Risk factors for progression of low-grade dysplasia in patients with Barrett's esophagus. Gastroenterology. 2011 Oct;141(4):1179-86, 1186.e1. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2011.06.055. Epub 2011 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21723218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Standards of Practice Committee, Wani S, Qumseya B, Sultan S, Agrawal D, Chandrasekhara V, Harnke B, Kothari S, McCarter M, Shaukat A, Wang A, Yang J, Dewitt J. Endoscopic eradication therapy for patients with Barrett's esophagus-associated dysplasia and intramucosal cancer. Gastrointest Endosc. 2018 Apr;87(4):907-931.e9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2017.10.011. Epub 2018 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29397943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wani S, Rubenstein JH, Vieth M, Bergman J. Diagnosis and Management of Low-Grade Dysplasia in Barrett's Esophagus: Expert Review From the Clinical Practice Updates Committee of the American Gastroenterological Association. Gastroenterology. 2016 Nov;151(5):822-835. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2016.09.040. Epub 2016 Oct 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27702561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vajravelu RK, Mamtani R, Scott FI, Waxman A, Lewis JD. Incidence, Risk Factors, and Clinical Effects of Recurrent Diverticular Hemorrhage: A Large Cohort Study. Gastroenterology. 2018 Nov;155(5):1416-1427. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2018.07.026. Epub 2018 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>30056095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott FI, Vajravelu RK, Bewtra M, Mamtani R, Lee D, Goldberg DS, Lewis JD. The benefit-to-risk balance of combining infliximab with azathioprine varies with age: a markov model. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2015 Feb;13(2):302-309.e11. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2014.07.058. Epub 2014 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>25117775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vajravelu RK, Osterman MT, Aberra FN, Roy JA, Lichtenstein GR, Mamtani R, Goldberg DS, Lewis JD, Scott FI. Indeterminate QuantiFERON-TB Gold Increases Likelihood of Inflammatory Bowel Disease Treatment Delay and Hospitalization. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2017 Dec 19;24(1):217-226. doi: 10.1093/ibd/izx019.</citation>
    <PMID>29272482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farvardin S, Patel J, Khambaty M, Yerokun OA, Mok H, Tiro JA, Yopp AC, Parikh ND, Marrero JA, Singal AG. Patient-reported barriers are associated with lower hepatocellular carcinoma surveillance rates in patients with cirrhosis. Hepatology. 2017 Mar;65(3):875-884. doi: 10.1002/hep.28770. Epub 2016 Oct 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27531684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simmons OL, Feng Y, Parikh ND, Singal AG. Primary Care Provider Practice Patterns and Barriers to Hepatocellular Carcinoma Surveillance. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2019 Mar;17(4):766-773. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2018.07.029. Epub 2018 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>30056183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dalton-Fitzgerald E, Tiro J, Kandunoori P, Halm EA, Yopp A, Singal AG. Practice patterns and attitudes of primary care providers and barriers to surveillance of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with cirrhosis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2015 Apr;13(4):791-8.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2014.06.031. Epub 2014 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25019694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wani S, Williams JL, Komanduri S, Muthusamy VR, Shaheen NJ. Over-Utilization of Repeat Upper Endoscopy in Patients with Non-dysplastic Barrett's Esophagus: A Quality Registry Study. Am J Gastroenterol. 2019 Aug;114(8):1256-1264. doi: 10.14309/ajg.0000000000000184.</citation>
    <PMID>30865017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wani S, Williams JL, Komanduri S, Muthusamy VR, Shaheen NJ. Endoscopists systematically undersample patients with long-segment Barrett's esophagus: an analysis of biopsy sampling practices from a quality improvement registry. Gastrointest Endosc. 2019 Nov;90(5):732-741.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2019.04.250. Epub 2019 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>31085185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bandura A. Health promotion by social cognitive means. Health Educ Behav. 2004 Apr;31(2):143-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15090118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michels TC, Taplin SM, Carter WB, Kugler JP. Barriers to screening: the theory of reasoned action applied to mammography use in a military beneficiary population. Mil Med. 1995 Sep;160(9):431-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7478025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yabroff KR, Klabunde CN, Yuan G, McNeel TS, Brown ML, Casciotti D, Buckman DW, Taplin S. Are physicians' recommendations for colorectal cancer screening guideline-consistent? J Gen Intern Med. 2011 Feb;26(2):177-84. doi: 10.1007/s11606-010-1516-5. Epub 2010 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20949328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beatty P, Willis G. Research synthesis: the practice of cognitive interviewing. Publ Opin Q 2007;71:287-311.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willis G. Cognitive interviewing: a tool for improving questionnaire design. Thousands Oaks, CA: Sage Publications 2004.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoddinott SN, Bass MJ. The dillman total design survey method. Can Fam Physician. 1986 Nov;32:2366-8.</citation>
    <PMID>21267217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bastani R, Glenn BA, Taylor VM, Chen MS Jr, Nguyen TT, Stewart SL, Maxwell AE. Integrating theory into community interventions to reduce liver cancer disparities: The Health Behavior Framework. Prev Med. 2010 Jan-Feb;50(1-2):63-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2009.08.010. Epub 2009 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19716379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maxwell AE, Bastani R, Chen MS Jr, Nguyen TT, Stewart SL, Taylor VM. Constructing a theoretically based set of measures for liver cancer control research studies. Prev Med. 2010 Jan-Feb;50(1-2):68-73. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2009.10.015. Epub 2009 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19883680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Barrett's Esophagus</keyword>
  <keyword>Upper Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Barrett's Esophagus Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>GERD</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>BE</keyword>
  <keyword>EAC</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophageal Adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Barrett Esophagus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

