<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04466410</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XT-150-1-0102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04466410</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of XT-150 for Treatment of Neuropathic Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preliminary Evaluation of Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of XT-150 for the Treatment of Neuropathic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xalud Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xalud Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Preliminary Evaluation of Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of XT-150 for the Treatment of
      Neuropathic Pain. Intrathecally administered, single injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      XT-150 has been safe and well tolerated in clinical studies of intra-articular knee
      injections for osteoarthritis.

      This is the initial study of XT-150 for treatment of neuropathic pain. For this indication
      XT-150 must be administered by intrathecal injection. Doses used in the osteoarthritis
      studies will be studied for neuropathic pain.

      Upon safety reviews, doses will be increased by cohorts.

      The study is placebo controlled and blinded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Dose escalation by cohort following safety reviews</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Placebo and active drug are identical in appearance. Randomization will be provided to an unblinded pharmacist. Dosing and clinical assessments will be blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale of Pain Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline score, 0 to 100 worst pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>West Haven-Yale Multidimensional Pain Inventory (WHYMPI/MPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measures the impact of pain on patients' lives</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Pain Scale (MPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline in pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropathic Pain Symptom Inventory (NPSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluates the relative component of neuropathic and nociceptive pain symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuropathic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose XT-150</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lowest dose of XT-150. Cohort 1 of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Middle dose XT-150</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Middle dose of XT-150. Cohort 2 of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose XT-150</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Highest dose of XT-150. Cohort 3 of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PBS for injection. 4 of 16 subjects randomly assigned in each experimental drug cohort</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>XT-150</intervention_name>
    <description>Single bolus intrathecal injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose XT-150</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose XT-150</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Middle dose XT-150</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IL-10 transgene plasmid DNA injected intrathecally</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female, between 18 and 80 years of age, inclusive

          2. Clinical indication: Lumbar disk disease with no prior lumbar surgery with /radicular
             pain symptoms and/or signs of compressive neuropathy.

          3. Inadequate pain relief (visual analog scale of pain intensity [VASPI] score ≥70 mm on
             a 0-100 mm scale) lasting &gt; 3 months.

          4. Medically stable as determined by the Principal Investigator in consultation with the
             Sponsor's Medical Monitor, based on pre-study medical history, physical examination,
             and clinical laboratory tests

          5. In the judgment of the Investigator, acceptable vital signs: blood pressure; resting
             heart rate; respirations, and oral temperature.

          6. Body mass index of 18 to 35 kg/m2 , (maximum weight 250kg, maximum girth 420cm)

          7. Life expectancy &gt;6 months

          8. Female subjects of child-bearing potential, and those &lt;1 year post-menopausal, must be
             practicing highly effective methods of birth control such as hormonal methods (e.g.,
             combined oral, implantable, injectable, or transdermal contraceptives), double barrier
             methods (e.g., condoms, sponge, diaphragm, or vaginal ring plus spermicidal jellies or
             cream), or total abstinence from heterosexual intercourse for a minimum of 1 full
             cycle before study drug administration and agree to continue abstinence for 1 full
             cycle after the study is completed

          9. Male subjects who are heterosexually active and not surgically sterile must agree to
             use effective contraception for the duration of the study and for 1 month after the
             study is completed

         10. Stable medical regimen for ≥2 months before participation (excluded medications are
             listed in Exclusion Criteria #12-16)

         11. Have suitable lumbar anatomy for intrathecal injection

         12. Willing and able to return for the follow-up (FU) visits

         13. Able to reliably provide pain assessment

         14. Successfully complete the Focused Analgesia Selection Test (Analgesic Solutions,
             Wayland, MA), which will be used to determine whether patients can report pain with
             sufficient consistency to enter the clinical trial

         15. Able to read and understand study instructions, and willing and able to comply with
             all study procedures

         16. Adequately informed of the nature and risks of the study and give written informed
             consent before receiving any study specific assessments or procedures

         17. Stable use of non-prescription pain therapy, including massage, TENS, physiotherapy
             osteopathy, chiropractic and acupuncture for 2 months prior and throughout the study
             period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must NOT meet any of the following exclusion criteria:

          1. Hypersensitivity, allergy, or significant reaction to any ingredient of the study drug

          2. Any spinal deformity preventing intrathecal injection or making intrathecal injection
             unsafe

          3. Prior history of lumbar surgery, including fusion and microdiscectomy.

          4. History of epidural block or facet block or steroid injection in the last 6 months.

          5. Current unstable angina, uncontrolled congestive heart failure, or &gt;1+ pitting edema
             of lower extremities

          6. History of acute myocardial infarction, transient ischemic attack, stroke, or seizure
             within 3 months of screening visit

          7. Severe chronic obstructive or restrictive pulmonary disease

          8. Current insulin dependent diabetes mellitus

          9. Current autoimmune conditions or documented immunodeficiency

         10. History of immunosuppressive therapy; high-potency systemic steroids in the last 3
             months

         11. Current treatment with systemic immunosuppressive (systemic corticosteroid therapy
             [equivalent to &gt;10mg/day prednisone] or other strong immunosuppressant)

         12. Current or history of central nervous system cancer

         13. Any malignancy (EXCEPTION: localized non-melanoma skin cancers) within 5 years before
             the screening visit or currently receiving systemic chemotherapy, radiation therapy,
             or a surgical stabilization procedure

         14. Significant hepatic disease as indicated by clinical laboratory results ≥3 times the
             upper limit of normal for any liver function test (e.g., aspartate aminotransferase,
             alanine aminotransferase, lactate dehydrogenase)

         15. Severe anemia, uncontrolled coagulopathy, or bleeding diathesis

         16. Significant renal disease as indicated by creatinine ≥1.5 times the upper limit of
             normal or creatinine clearance &lt;80 mL/minute (Cockcroft-Gault formula estimate)

         17. Positive serology for human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis B virus, or hepatitis C
             virus

         18. Significant psychological conditions; dementia, major depression, or altered mental
             state that in the opinion of the Investigator will interfere with study participation

         19. Current treatment with systemic antibiotics or antivirals (EXCEPTION: topical
             treatments)

         20. Current treatment with anticoagulant or antiplatelet medications (EXCEPTION: aspirin
             and other NSAIDs)

         21. Current use of systemic corticosteroids (equivalent to &gt;10mg/day prednisone)

         22. Known or suspected history of active alcohol or illicit drug abuse within 1 year
             before the screening visit

         23. Women who are pregnant or nursing

         24. Use of any investigational drug or device within 1 month before randomization or
             current participation in a trial that included intervention with a drug or device; or
             currently participating in an investigational drug or device study.

         25. Any condition that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, could compromise the
             safety of the subject, the subject's ability to communicate the study staff, or the
             quality of the data

         26. Presence of an implanted intrathecal infusion system or peripheral neurostimulator.

         27. Presence of a generalized pain disorder such as fibromyalgia or complex regional pain
             syndrome that in the opinion of the PI may impact on evaluation of response to the
             study drug.

         28. Diagnosis of peripheral neuropathy of the lower extremities which in the opinion of
             the PI, might interfere with the subject's ability to assess the effect of the study
             drug on the radicular signs and/or symptoms.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Collins, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Xalud Therapeutics, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elspeth Hutton, MBBS,PhD,FRACP</last_name>
    <phone>+61 3 9903 0781‬</phone>
    <email>elspeth.hutton@monash.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mahima Kapoor</last_name>
    <email>M.Kapoor@alfred.org.au</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alfred Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jack Germaine</last_name>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2029</phone>
      <email>j.germaine@alfred.org.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elspeth Hutton, MBBS PhD FRACP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mahima Kapoor</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>XT-150</keyword>
  <keyword>Plasmid Gene Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-10</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

