<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04463108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108760</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>54135419MDD4002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04463108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Describe Routine Treatment Pathways in Participants With Major Depression and Active Suicidal Ideation With Intent in Italy</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARIANNA</acronym>
  <official_title>A Description of Routine Treatment Pathways in a Cohort of Patients With Major Depression and &quot;Active Suicidal Ideation With Intent&quot; in Italy: the Arianna Observational Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen-Cilag S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen-Cilag S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to describe the pharmacological and non-pharmacological treatment
      utilization pathways in Italian routine clinical practice of participants with Major
      Depressive Disorder (MDD) and active suicidal ideation with intent.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of Comprehensive Treatment for Major Depression Disorder (MDD) and Active Suicidal Ideation with Intent</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Type of comprehensive treatment for MDD and active suicidal ideation with intent (for example, psychopharmacotherapy; psychosocial treatment; somatic therapy) will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Psychiatric Drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of psychiatric drugs (that is, polypsychopharmacy versus monotherapy) will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of treatment for MDD and suicidal ideation with intent will be evaluated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sequence of Treatments in Participants with MDD and Suicidal Ideation with Intent</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment sequences for participants with MDD and suicidal ideation with intent (for exapmple, administration of first-line antidepressant) will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Care Setting</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Care setting (that is, in-patient and out-patient) will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a clinician-rated scale designed to measure changes in depression severity due to antidepressant treatment.The MADRS consists of 10 items, each of which is scored from 0 (item not present or normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of the symptoms) for a total possible score of 60. Higher scores represent a more severe condition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Quality of Life (EuroQol) 5-Dimension 5-Level Questionnaire (EQ-5D-5L) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D-5L is a generic measure of health status. The EQ-5D-5L is a 5-item questionnaire that assesses 5 domains including mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression plus a visual analog scale rating &quot;health today&quot; with anchors ranging from 0 (worst imaginable health state) to 100 (best imaginable health state).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with AEs and SAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of visit)</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event (AE) is any untoward medical event that occurs in a participant administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product. A Serious (AE) is an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; congenital anomaly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Resource Utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 104 (End of Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Health Care Resource Utilization (HCRU) will be measured through the number of hospitalization visits, visits to the emergency department, inpatient hospitalization, specialist outpatient visits, number of day care visits, laboratory tests, instrumental and other diagnostic tests related to MDD with active suicidal ideation with intent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Suicidal ideation and behavior as Assessed by Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of study)</time_frame>
    <description>Suicidal ideation or behavior will be measured using C-SSRS score. C-SSRS is a clinician rated assessment of suicidal behavior and/ or intent. Scale consists of 28 items in 4 sections: suicide behavior, actual attempts, suicidal ideation, and intensity of ideation. Suicidal ideation consists of 5 yes/no items: wish to be dead, non-specific active suicidal thoughts, active suicidal ideation with any methods (not plan) without intention to act, active suicidal ideation with some intent to act without specific plan, active suicidal ideation with specific plan and intent. Worsening of suicidal ideation will be an increase in severity of suicidal ideation from baseline.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Hopelessness Scale (BHS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of visit)</time_frame>
    <description>BHS is paper-based self-reported measure to assess one's level of negative expectations or pessimism regarding future. The scale consists of 20 true-false items that examine the respondent's attitude over past week by either endorsing a pessimistic statement or denying an optimistic statement; 9-items are keyed false and 11 are keyed true. Items fall within 3 domains: feelings about future; loss of motivation; future expectations. Each response is assigned a score of 0 or 1. Total BHS score is sum of item responses, with range from 0 to 20, with a higher score representing higher level of hopelessness. Total scores that range from 0 to 3 are (normal range), scores 4 to 8 (mild hopelessness, scores 9 to 14 (moderate hopelessness), scores &lt;14 (severe hopelessness). Negative change in score indicates improvement.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale Suicide Ideation: item 10 (MADRS-SI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>MADRS is clinician-rated scale designed to measure depression severity, and to detect changes due to antidepressant treatment. MADRS item 10, or MADRS-SI evaluates apparent sadness, reported sadness, inner tension, sleep, appetite, concentration, lassitude, interest level, pessimistic thoughts, and suicidal thoughts; scored from 0 (item is not present or is normal) to 6 (severe or continuous presence of symptoms), summed for a total possible score of 0 to 60. Higher scores represent more severe condition.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Involvement Evaluation Questionnaire (IEQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 104 (End of Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>The 31-item Involvement Evaluation Questionnaire measures caregiver burden. It has been validated for caregivers of individuals with schizophrenia, covers a broad domain of caregiving consequences and refers to burden experienced within the past 4 weeks. Mean scores are calculated for the total scale and sub-scales. Total scores can range from 29 to 145 with sub-scale domains ranging - tension, 9-45; supervision, 6-30; worrying, 6-30; and urging, 8-40. Lower total and subscale scores indicate less burden and higher scores greater level of caregiver burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <condition>Suicidal Ideation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with MDD and Active Suicidal Ideation with Intent</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and active suicidal ideation with intent as defined/confirmed by Investigator will be enrolled and treated in accordance with routine clinical practice. The primary data source for this study will be the medical records of each participant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention will be administered as a part of this study. Both retrospective and prospective data will be collected. The retrospective data will be collected through medical chart review.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with MDD and Active Suicidal Ideation with Intent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population consists of participants with confirmed Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)
        and active suicidal ideation with intent as per physician's opinion.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant must meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (5th
             edition) (DSM-5) diagnostic criteria for single episode or recurrent Major Depressive
             Disorder (MDD), based upon clinical assessment

          -  In the physician's opinion the current depressive episode is moderate-to-severe in
             terms of severity.

          -  In the physician's opinion, acute psychiatric hospitalization is clinically warranted
             due to participant's current active suicidal ideation with intent

          -  Participant must be capable of discernment

          -  Participant must be able to read and write in the Italian language

          -  Participant must have signed the informed consent form (ICF) indicating that he/she
             understands the study purpose and is willing to participate in the study

          -  Participant is in the site's catchment area, as evaluated by the Investigator

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Participant currently (that is, at the time of enrolment and based upon clinical
             assessment) meets DSM-5 criteria for psychotic disorder, bipolar or related disorders,
             antisocial personality disorder, borderline personality disorder, intellectual
             disability, autism spectrum disorder, dementia

          -  Participant meets the DSM-5 severity criteria for moderate or severe substance or
             alcohol use disorder (except for nicotine or caffeine) within the 6 months before
             enrolment, based upon clinical assessment

          -  Participant has participated in or is currently enrolled in any clinical trial with
             experimental treatments within the current major depressive episode
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen-Cilag S.p.A., Italy Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen-Cilag S.p.A.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Contact</last_name>
    <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST Spedali Civili Brescia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <zip>25123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Santissima Trinità</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cagliari</city>
        <zip>00000</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Sant'Antonio Abate</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cantu'</city>
        <zip>22063</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Vittorio Emanuele</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <zip>95124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Parodi Delfino</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colleferro</city>
        <zip>00034</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedali Riuniti Foggia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Foggia</city>
        <zip>71122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale San Giovanni di Dio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frattamaggiore</city>
        <zip>80027</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria San Martino di Genova</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <zip>16132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Az. USL 12 di Viareggio Ospedale Versilia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lido Di Camaiore</city>
        <zip>53041</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H.U. Santa Lucía</name>
      <address>
        <city>Macerata</city>
        <zip>62100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST Fatebenefratelli Sacco</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20157</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Ca Granda - Niguarda</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20162</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dipartimento di Salute Mentale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Modena</city>
        <zip>41126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale S. Francesco d'Assisi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oliveto Citra</city>
        <zip>84020</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aou San Luigi Gonzaga</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano</city>
        <zip>10043</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Salute Mentale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Padova</city>
        <zip>35124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AOU Policlinico P.Giaccone</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <zip>90127</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>P.O. Putignano</name>
      <address>
        <city>Putignano</city>
        <zip>70017</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Infermi Rimini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rimini</city>
        <zip>47923</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Sant Andrea</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00196</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale G. Mazzini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Teramo</city>
        <zip>64100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>A.O.U. Città della Salute e della Scienza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <zip>10126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Sanitaria Universitaria Integrata di Udine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Udine</city>
        <zip>33100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ulss 8 Berica- Ospedale Di Vicenza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vicenza</city>
        <zip>36100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR108760</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicidal Ideation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

