<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04460235</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HEMATOVAC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04460235</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity of an Anti-pneumococcal Combined Vaccination in Acute Leukemia or Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEMATOVAC</acronym>
  <official_title>Immunogénicité de la Vaccination Anti-pneumococcique Dans la leucémie aiguë et le Lymphome Chez l'Adulte</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Poitiers University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Poitiers University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The French Public Health Council recommended pneumococcal vaccination combined strategy for
      all immunocompromised patients in 2012. This strategy consisted in conjugated 13-valent
      pneumococcal injection followed 2 months later by polysaccharide 23-valent vaccine injection.
      General practitioners are usually in charge of this vaccination. Conjugated pneumococcal
      vaccine enhances the immunogenicity of the polysaccharide vaccine. Acute leukemia and
      lymphoma are treated with multiple courses of chemotherapy, impairing the immune system and
      potentially the response to vaccination. These patients are more at risk for developing
      pneumococcal invasive diseases than the general population. However, efficacy of pneumococcal
      vaccination is poorly documented in this setting. We assume that 70% of the patients are
      non-responders to vaccination, according to their anti-pneumococcal immunoglobulin G titers
      and the opsonophagocytic activity. To assess the immunogenicity of the pneumococcal
      vaccination combined strategy in adult population of acute leukemia and lymphoma, the
      investigator will measure anti-pneumococcal serotype-specific immunoglobulin G titers and
      opsonophagocytic activity at different time-points after completion of the combined vaccine
      strategy. The primary objective is to assess the immunogenicity of pneumococcal vaccination
      combined strategy at 3 months after the 13-valent pneumococcal injection (corresponding to 1
      month after the end of the combined strategy) using immunoglobulin G titers and
      opsonophagocytic activity. At different time points (day 0, 1 month after the 13-valent
      pneumococcal injection, the day of the injection of the polysaccharide 23-valent vaccine, one
      month after the injection of the polysaccharide 23-valent vaccine, 3-6 months after the
      polysaccharide 23-valent vaccine,9-12 months after the polysaccharide 23-valent vaccine), the
      immunological response to vaccination will be monitored using specific-serotype
      immunoglobulin G titers, opsonophagocytic activity, and total anti-pneumococcal
      Immunoglobulin. The investigator will determine predictive factors of non-response to
      vaccination by comparing demographic data, biological data and treatment received by both
      acute myeloblastic leukemia and lymphoma patients. The tolerance and safety of the
      vaccination strategy will also be assessed in this specific hematological population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients having a good response to combined strategy</measure>
    <time_frame>39 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients having a good response to combined strategy at 4 weeks after the end of the combined strategy. A good response to vaccination is defined by 4/7 tested serotypes responding to these 4 criteria: a serotype-specific immunoglobulin G titer ≥ 1μg/L (WHO threshold), a two-fold increase of this immunoglobulin G titer compare to baseline before vaccination, a serotype-specific opsonophagocytic activity ≥1/8, and a four-fold increase of functional antibodies compare to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaccine</condition>
  <condition>Streptococcus Pneumoniae</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccination</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients will be vaccinated</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients with hematological malignancies like acute myeloblastic leukemia or non
        Hodgkin lymphoma
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient ≥ 18 year-old.

          -  AND medical follow-up in hematology unit

          -  AND had received a first course of chemotherapy for acute myeloblastic leukemia
             without ProMyelogenousLeukemia-RetinoicAcidReceptor alpha and no planned allogeneic
             hematopoietic stem cell transplantation or for diffuse large B cell lymphoma or for
             follicular lymphoma

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 6 months

          -  Having signed the consent form.

          -  Having an health insurance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving monoclonal antibodies or biotherapies altering the immune response, other
             than anti-Cluster of differentiation number 20 antibodies in the chemotherapy
             protocol.

          -  Previous vaccination with 13-valent pneumococcal vaccine or polysaccharide 23-valent
             vaccine (unless 13-valent pneumococcal vaccine was administered in childhood. The last
             injection must be performed at least five years ago).

          -  Preexisting condition that altered the immune response: splenectomy, HIV, primary or
             secondary immune deficiency, nephrotic syndrome, sickle cell anemia, autoimmune
             disorder, solid organ transplantation, immunosuppressive drugs or biotherapy not
             included in the chemotherapy.

          -  Patient who already received chemotherapy for malignancy in the previous 2 years
             before the inclusion.

          -  Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation planned in the following 3 months
             after the first chemotherapy course.

          -  Curative anticoagulation within 7 days before vaccination.

          -  Major blood clotting disorders preventing intramuscular injection.

          -  Medical history of anaphylactic reaction to vaccination.

          -  Known allergy to one of the vaccine components.

          -  Involvement to another vaccine biomedical research.

          -  Protected person.

          -  Pregnant women or women of childbearing age without appropriate contraceptive
             measures.

          -  Perfusion of polyvalent immunoglobulins during follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mathieu Puyade, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0033 5 49 44 32 76</phone>
    <email>mathieu.puyade@chu-poitiers.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fanny Abriat</last_name>
    <phone>0033 5 49 44 37 96</phone>
    <email>fanny.abriat@chu-poitiers.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Undecided</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

