<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04467216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZB1H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04467216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VR Motor-cognitive Training for Cognitive Frailty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Virtual Reality Motor-cognitive Training for Older People With Cognitive Frailty: A Pilot Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive frailty is a clinical syndrome in which cognitive impairment (e.g., poor memory,
      visuospatial function) and physical frailty (e.g., slowness, poor muscle strength, physical
      inactivity) co-exist. It is prevalent in community-dwelling older people. The progressive
      decline of cognitive and physical functions restricts older people from participating in
      activities (e.g., social get-togethers). Reduced participation further jeopardizes their
      life-space mobility (e.g., ability to travel to areas far away from home). Therefore, those
      with cognitive frailty are at risk of developing dementia and becoming dependent.

      Simultaneous motor-cognitive training is more effective at promoting optimal functioning in
      older people than motor or cognitive training alone. Gaming is effective at promoting the
      motivation to participate. The contents of games in the market are unrelated to the context
      or daily living of the elderly. Currently, available training is non-simultaneous. This makes
      the training less transferable to the daily life of the elderly and reduces its effects.

      Virtual reality (VR) technology can provide a virtual space that mimics the real environment.
      This allows clients to participate in daily activities in a virtual space. Older people can
      be trained to improve their cognitive and physical skills in a painless, fun way. However,
      the effect and feasibility of employing simultaneous motor-cognitive training launching on a
      VR platform mimicking the daily living environment in older people with cognitive frailty is
      poorly known. This pilot trial aims to examine the preliminary effects on cognitive function
      and frailty syndrome, as well as examine the feasibility.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the intervention, VR will be employed to simulate a daily living environment familiar to
      older people. Participants will wear a commercially available head-mounted VR system with
      hand-held controllers to experience the participation of daily activities in a virtual
      environment. Simultaneous physical and cognitive training will be embedded in the training
      system to promote optimal function. Participants will attend physical training in a sitting
      position through cycling on an ergometer and moving the hand-held controllers. Motion sensors
      built into the VR system and ergometer will track these movements to control everyday tasks
      in the virtual environment (e.g., moving around the city). Simultaneously, participants will
      undergo cognitive training by participating in various tasks demanding cognitive functions,
      such as visual-spatial (e.g., wayfinding) and problem-solving (e.g., wallet loss) functions.
      Gamification will be employed to promote the motivation to participate. All training
      activities will be gamified by blending in fun elements, such as difficulty-levelling,
      competition, and e-tokens. Co-participation is allowed to promote interpersonal interactions.
      The prototype enables real-time co-viewing among participants. Other elderly centre members
      and the activity facilitators can share the view of the participants in the game on either a
      large-screen monitor or a tablet computer. They can simultaneously talk about and share their
      gaming experiences.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A total of 16 subjects with cognitive frailty will be assigned into 2 groups. Eight participants will be assigned to the intervention group in which they will undertake VR simultaneous motor-cognitive training and eight participants will be assigned to the control group in which existing forms of non-VR sequential motor-cognitive training will be provided.
Both intervention and control groups will employ the same intervention dosage including course, session duration and frequency. The following dosage is employed because they are also the same dosage used in the VR simultaneous motor-cognitive training that we proposed. I.e.,
Course: eight weeks
Session duration: 30 minutes
Frequency: twice per week</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcome assessors at both pre- and post-observations will be blinded to the group label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change is being assessed: &quot;baseline&quot; and &quot;immediately after the completion&quot; (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>MoCA (score)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Selective attention</measure>
    <time_frame>Change is being assessed: &quot;baseline&quot; and &quot;immediately after the completion&quot; (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Stroop test (score)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual-spatial perception</measure>
    <time_frame>Change is being assessed: &quot;baseline&quot; and &quot;immediately after the completion&quot; (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Object Space Perception test (score)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>Change is being assessed: &quot;baseline&quot; and &quot;immediately after the completion&quot; (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Fried Frailty Phenotype (score)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking</measure>
    <time_frame>Change is being assessed: &quot;baseline&quot; and &quot;immediately after the completion&quot; (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Timed up and go test (seconds)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Change is being assessed: &quot;baseline&quot; and &quot;immediately after the completion&quot; (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength by dynamometer (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Frailty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will undertake VR simultaneous motor-cognitive training in 30 minutes session, twice a week for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be doing existing forms of motor-cognitive training in 30 minutes session, twice a week for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computerised cognitive training using virtual reality</intervention_name>
    <description>Immersive VR training system tailor-made for the daily living experiences in the Hong Kong context to provide interactive experiences for older people in Hong Kong.The VR systems available in the market for older people are only for non-interactive activities (e.g., watching movies) to provide unusual experiences for disabled older people who cannot travel too far from home.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          1. Age ≥ 60 years,

          2. Community dwelling, as defined by living at home without staying in long-term care
             facilities (e.g., nursing home) in the last 12 months, and

          3. Cognitive frailty, as defined by co-existence of mild cognitive impairment and
             physical frailty,

               1. Mild cognitive impairment, measured by Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) ≤ 25
                  and Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) = 0.5, and

               2. Frailty status from pre-frail to frail, measured by Fried Frailty Phenotype score
                  ≥ 1.

        Exclusion criteria

          1. Diagnosed dementia, according to subjects' medical record, or

          2. Probable dementia, as defined by MoCA ≤ 18, or

          3. Mobility restriction, as defined by Modified Functional Ambulatory Classification
             (MFAC) &lt; Category 7 (i.e., Outdoor walker), or
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rick Kwan</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rick Kwan</last_name>
    <phone>96690420</phone>
    <phone_ext>6456</phone_ext>
    <email>rick.kwan@polyu.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pok Oi Hospital Neighbourhood Elderly Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olive Sin</last_name>
      <phone>98519917</phone>
      <email>khkic@pokoi.org.hk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruan Q, Yu Z, Chen M, Bao Z, Li J, He W. Cognitive frailty, a novel target for the prevention of elderly dependency. Ageing Res Rev. 2015 Mar;20:1-10. doi: 10.1016/j.arr.2014.12.004. Epub 2014 Dec 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25555677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nasreddine ZS, Phillips NA, Bédirian V, Charbonneau S, Whitehead V, Collin I, Cummings JL, Chertkow H. The Montreal Cognitive Assessment, MoCA: a brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2005 Apr;53(4):695-9. Erratum in: J Am Geriatr Soc. 2019 Sep;67(9):1991.</citation>
    <PMID>15817019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeung PY, Wong LL, Chan CC, Leung JL, Yung CY. A validation study of the Hong Kong version of Montreal Cognitive Assessment (HK-MoCA) in Chinese older adults in Hong Kong. Hong Kong Med J. 2014 Dec;20(6):504-10. doi: 10.12809/hkmj144219. Epub 2014 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25125421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fried LP, Tangen CM, Walston J, Newman AB, Hirsch C, Gottdiener J, Seeman T, Tracy R, Kop WJ, Burke G, McBurnie MA; Cardiovascular Health Study Collaborative Research Group. Frailty in older adults: evidence for a phenotype. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56(3):M146-56.</citation>
    <PMID>11253156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosanna Chau MW, Chan SP, Wong YW, Lau MYP. Reliability and validity of the Modified Functional Ambulation Classification in patients with hip fracture. Hong Kong Physiotherapy Journal. 2013;31(1):41-44.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelaiditi E, Cesari M, Canevelli M, van Kan GA, Ousset PJ, Gillette-Guyonnet S, Ritz P, Duveau F, Soto ME, Provencher V, Nourhashemi F, Salvà A, Robert P, Andrieu S, Rolland Y, Touchon J, Fitten JL, Vellas B; IANA/IAGG. Cognitive frailty: rational and definition from an (I.A.N.A./I.A.G.G.) international consensus group. J Nutr Health Aging. 2013 Sep;17(9):726-34. doi: 10.1007/s12603-013-0367-2.</citation>
    <PMID>24154642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desjardins-Crépeau L, Berryman N, Fraser SA, Vu TT, Kergoat MJ, Li KZ, Bosquet L, Bherer L. Effects of combined physical and cognitive training on fitness and neuropsychological outcomes in healthy older adults. Clin Interv Aging. 2016 Sep 19;11:1287-1299. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27698558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lauenroth A, Ioannidis AE, Teichmann B. Influence of combined physical and cognitive training on cognition: a systematic review. BMC Geriatr. 2016 Jul 18;16:141. doi: 10.1186/s12877-016-0315-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27431673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tait JL, Duckham RL, Milte CM, Main LC, Daly RM. Influence of Sequential vs. Simultaneous Dual-Task Exercise Training on Cognitive Function in Older Adults. Front Aging Neurosci. 2017 Nov 7;9:368. doi: 10.3389/fnagi.2017.00368. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29163146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Vries AW, Faber G, Jonkers I, Van Dieen JH, Verschueren SMP. Virtual reality balance training for elderly: Similar skiing games elicit different challenges in balance training. Gait Posture. 2018 Jan;59:111-116. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2017.10.006. Epub 2017 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29028622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Rick Kwan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive frailty</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor-cognitive training</keyword>
  <keyword>Virtual reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Gamification</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Frailty</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

