<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04463654</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>213+983</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04463654</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zero Self-Harm - a Mobile Phone Application to Reduce Non-suicidal Self-injury: A Randomized Clinical Superiority Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Zero Self-Harm - a Mobile Phone Application to Reduce Non-suicidal Self-injury: A Randomized Clinical Superiority Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mental Health Services in the Capital Region, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TrygFonden, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mental Health Services in the Capital Region, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Non-suicidal self-injury (NSSI), the deliberate, self-inflicted destruction of body tissue
      without suicidal intent and for purposes not socially sanctioned, is an increasing health
      care problem in Denmark. Approximately 20 % of Danish adolescents report a history of NSSI at
      some point in their lives. Individuals with NSSI have an increased risk of suicidality.
      Therefore, it is of great importance to develop and investigate the effectiveness of a
      low-cost app in reducing NSSI.

      The purpose is to investigate whether treatment as usual (TAU) and the Zero Self-Harm app is
      superior to TAU in reducing 1) frequency of NSSI-episodes and 2) suicide ideation,
      hopelessness, and depressive symptoms in individuals with NSSI. As people with NSSI, without
      a comorbid psychiatric diagnosis, are not eligible to receive psychiatric treatment in
      Denmark, TAU includes many different treatments and counseling services, i.e. counseling at
      non-profit organizations, service centers in the municipalities, outpatient treatment
      services for psychiatric disorders, and care, information and attention at emergency
      departments. Common to them all is that they do not offer specialized treatment focused on
      NSSI.

      The trial is designed as a 2-arm, parallel group, 6 months, randomized clinical superiority
      trial. A total of 366 participants, 183 in each arm, will be included. One group will receive
      TAU, the other will receive TAU and the Zero Self-Harm App. Participants will be recruited
      through non-profit organizations, service centers in the municipalities, outpatient treatment
      services, and psychiatric and somatic emergency departments in Denmark.

      Inclusion criteria are engagement in two or more episodes of NSSI in the past month, no
      further planned treatment, have a smartphone, fluent in Danish, provide an informed written
      consent, age above 15 years.

      Primary outcome is the mean monthly difference in frequency of NSSI-episodes at 6-month.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Deliberate Self Harm Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>17-item self-report questionnaire that assesses various aspects of self harm(defined as the deliberate, direct self-destruction of body tissue without suicidal intent) over specified time periods, including frequency (continuous range) and type of self-harm behavior (e.g. cutting, burning etc.). The DSHI demonstrates adequate test-retest reliability and construct, discriminant validity among non-clinical and patient samples</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Becks Suicide Ideation Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Becks Suicide Ideation Scale is a 21-item self-report questionnaire measuring suicidal thinking. The outcome is considered as a proxy measure for suicide attempt.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Becks Hopelessness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>The Becks Hopelessness Scale consists of 20 true-false items pertaining to future outlook.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>The Major Depression Inventory is a short questionnaire consisting of 12 items capturing depressive symptoms. It can be scored as a diagnostic tool, but also according to severity by a simple sum of the item scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WHO Well-being Index</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>The WHO Well-being Index (WHO-5), a widely used short questionnaire to measure quality of life, consisting of 5 simple and non-invasive questions. It is among the most widely used questionnaires assessing subjective psychological well-being.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rosenberg's Self-Esteem scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>The Rosenberg's Self-Esteem scale consists of 10 items and is a Likert scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">366</enrollment>
  <condition>Self-Injurious Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zero Self-Harm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>When randomized to the Zero Self-Harm app the participants will receive an introduction to the app, reviewing previous crisis situations and possible strategies, using an instruction manual and/or a YouTube instruction video. This will ensure the navigation and knowledge of the technicalities of the app.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will continue their present course of treatment and/or counseling at non-profit organizations, in service centers in the municipalities, at outpatient treatment services for psychiatric disorders and/or care, information and attention at emergency departments. They will receive no treatment on the nature of NSSI. Participants in the control group will be offered a possibility to download the Zero Self-Harm app after they have completed the last questionnaire at six months, which will be stressed at the initial appointment as well as after collection of all data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zero Self-Harm application</intervention_name>
    <description>Safety plan application for smartphones</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zero Self-Harm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Engagement in two or more episodes of NSSI in the past month.

          -  No further planned treatment focused on NSSI.

          -  Have a smartphone (IPhone or Android phone).

          -  Fluent in Danish.

          -  Skills sufficient to enable use of the Zero Self-Harm app.

          -  Provide an informed written consent.

          -  Age ≥ 15 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lack of informed consent.

          -  High suicide risk (Becks suicide ideation scale (BSS) &gt; 24).

          -  Forced care.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Merete Nordentoft, MD, Ph.D MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mental Health Center Copenhagen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lene Qvist Larsen</last_name>
    <phone>004560395772</phone>
    <email>lene.qvist.larsen.01@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kate Aamund, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <email>kate.aamund@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Self-Injurious Behavior</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

