<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04466384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MDT19049SONORA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04466384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bispectral Index and Levels of Sedation With Propofol With/Without Remifentanil in Healthy Volunteers (SONORA)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SONORA</acronym>
  <official_title>Bispectral Index and Levels of Sedation With Propofol With/Without Remifentanil in Healthy Volunteers (SONORA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medtronic - MITG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medtronic - MITG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is investigate the relationship between BIS™ and propofol
      with/without remifentanil across a wide range of hypnotic states.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, prospective, non-randomized, cross-over study to collect data to
      evaluate the relationship between BIS™ and anesthetic regimens. The subjects will receive two
      regimens of anesthesia with different drug combinations, with at least a 1-week washout
      period between regimens. Subjects will be sequentially assigned to start with either Propofol
      (P) or Propofol with 4 ng/ml of Remifentanil (R) regimens while BIS™ bilateral sensor placed
      on the subject's forehead. The Modified Observer's Assessment of Alertness/Sedation (MOAA/S)
      scale, refer to Appendix A, will be used to measure the level of alertness in sedated
      subjects with Tetanic Electrical Stimulation (TES) being used once subjects reach a MOAA/S
      score &lt;2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The subjects will receive two regimens of anesthesia with different drug combinations, with at least a 1-week washout period between regimens. Subjects will be sequentially assigned to start with either propofol or propofol with remifentanil regiments.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BIS50</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determine BIS50 (BIS™ value at which 50% of patients will be unresponsive at given drug concentrations) and other dose-response parameters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BIS95</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determine BIS95 (BIS™ value at which 95% of patients will be unresponsive at given drug concentrations) and other dose-response parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Anesthesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Propofol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be sequentially assigned to start with propofol or propofol with remifentanil. Propofol will be started at a concentration of 0.5 µg/ml followed by incremental increases in the target effect-site concentrations of 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, and 8 µg/ml until a MOAA/S score less than 2 is reached.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Propofol with Remifentanil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be sequentially assigned to start with propofol or propofol with remifentanil. Approximately 2 minutes before starting propofol, to attain an effect-site targeted concentration of remifentanil of 4 ng/ml, remifentanil will be given by a continuous infusion. Within approximately 7 minutes, the infusion rate of Remifentanil may be adjusted to maintain the effect-site concentration of remifentanil of 4 ng/ml throughout the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BIS</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be sequentially assigned to the propofol or propofol and remifentanil group. The purpose is to capture the BIS value in association with these anesthetics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Propofol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Propofol with Remifentanil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy (ASA physical status 1), male or female subjects between the ages of 18 to 60
             years;

          2. Completion of a health screening for a medical history by a licensed physician, nurse
             practitioner or physician assistant;

          3. Vital signs must be within the following ranges to be included: Vital signs measured
             sitting after 3 minutes rest; heart rate: 45-90 bpm; systolic blood pressure: 110-140;
             diastolic blood pressure: 50-90. Out-of-range vital signs may be repeated once.
             [Pre-dose vital signs will be assessed by the Principal Investigator or designee
             (e.g., a medically qualified sub-investigator) before study drug administration. The
             Principal Investigator or designee will verify the eligibility of each subject before
             dosing];

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has severe contact allergies that may cause a reaction to standard adhesive materials
             found in pulse oximetry sensors, ECG electrodes, respiration monitor electrodes, or
             other medical sensors [self-reported];

          2. Known neurological disorder (e.g., epilepsy, the presence of a brain tumor, a history
             of brain surgery, hydrocephalic disorders, depression needing treatment with
             anti-depressive drugs, a history of brain trauma) [self-reported and assessment by PI
             or delegate];

          3. Known cardiovascular disease (e.g., hypertension, coronary artery disease, prior acute
             myocardial infarction, any valvular and/or myocardial disease involving a decrease in
             ejection fraction, arrhythmias, which are either symptomatic or require continuous
             medication/ pacemaker/ automatic internal cardioverter defibrillator), current
             implanted pacemaker or automatic internal cardioverter defibrillator [self-reported
             and assessment by PI or delegate];

          4. Has a clinically significant abnormal finding on medical history, physical
             examination, clinical laboratory tests, or ECG at the screening [self-reported and
             assessment by PI or delegate];

          5. Recent use of psychoactive medication (e.g., benzodiazepines, antiepileptic drugs,
             ADHD medication, Parkinson's medication, anti-depressant drugs, opioids)
             [self-reported and assessment by PI or delegate];

          6. Subjects with known gastric diseases [self-reported and assessment by PI or delegate];

          7. Has a positive urine cotinine test or urine drug screen or oral ethanol test [POC
             testing];

          8. Known history of allergic or adverse response to drugs to be administered
             [self-reported];

          9. Known history of complications relating to previous general anesthesia or conscious
             sedation [self-reported and assessment by PI or delegate];

         10. Known history of malignant hyperthermia [self-reported and assessment by PI or
             delegate];

         11. Has a room air saturation less than 95% by pulse oximetry [measurement by PI or
             delegate];

         12. Has a clinically significant abnormal ECG [assessment by PI or delegate];

         13. Has a clinically significant abnormal pulmonary function test via spirometry
             [assessment by PI or delegate];

         14. Pregnant or lactating women [assessed by urine test and self-reported];

         15. Subjects with tattooed skin specific to the sensor placement areas (forehead, fingers,
             chest) [self-reported and assessment by PI or delegate];

         16. The subject must not take any prescription medication, except female hormonal
             contraceptives or hormone replacement therapy, from 146 days before the dosing until
             the end-of-study visit without evaluation and approval by the Investigator. Subjects
             who participated in a previous clinical trial who received a required FDA approved
             concomitant medication, for example, naltrexone, but were not randomized may be
             considered for participation in this study if they meet the washout requirement
             [assessment by PI or delegate];
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephanie Monza, BS</last_name>
    <phone>303-763-0813</phone>
    <email>stephanie.r.monza@medtronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stacy Osborn, BS</last_name>
    <phone>720-503-3073</phone>
    <email>stacy.osborn@medtronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

