<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04460560</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>834744</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04460560</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Terlipressin for HRS-AKI in Liver Transplant Candidates (INFUSE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>INFUSE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multi-Center, Open Label, Collaborative Research Study to Treat HRS-AKI Patients With Continuous Terlipressin Infusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hepatorenal syndrome-acute kidney injury (HRS-AKI), a potentially reversible renal failure,
      is a serious, rapidly progressing, often fatal, complication of decompensated cirrhosis.
      Terlipressin is a synthetic vasopressin analogue that acts as a systemic vasoconstrictor via
      the vascular vasopressin V1 receptors. In HRS-AKI patients the strong V1 receptor-mediated
      vasoconstrictor activity of terlipressin, particularly in the splanchnic area, increases
      effective intravascular volume and mean arterial pressure (MAP), ameliorates
      renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system and sympathetic nervous system hyperactivity, and
      improves renal blood flow. The INFUSE trial will evaluate the use of continuous terlipressin
      infusion in patients on the liver transplant waiting list with HRS-AKI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of renal function (SCr) from Day 1 thru end of treatment, repeated measure analysis. SCr will be collected daily, from Day 1 thru end of treatment. Baseline SCr will also be entered.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days or reversal of HRS-AKI, whichever occur first</time_frame>
    <description>SCr will be collected daily, from Day 1 thru end of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatorenal Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Terlipressin</intervention_name>
    <description>For the first dose of terlipressin, each vial will be reconstituted with 5 mL of sterile 0.9% sodium chloride solution and administered intravenously as a bolus injection and given over 1 minute at a dose of 0.5 mg.
For continuous infusion, the dose of terlipressin is to be dissolved in 50 mL of a 0.9% sodium chloride solution and infused with a pump</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent by subject or legally authorized representative.

          2. At least 18 years of age.

          3. Cirrhosis and ascites.

          4. No sustained improvement in renal function (less than 20% decrease in SCr) at least 48
             hours after diuretic withdrawal and after plasma volume expansion with albumin (given
             daily for two days - 48 hours minimum from 1st dose).

          5. Increase in SCr by at least ≥ 0.3 mg/dl OR 1.5-2 fold above baseline (AKI stage 1 and
             above), to a SCr of ≥ 1.5 mg/dl at the time of initiating treatment. Baseline SCr is
             defined as the most recent, lowest SCr within last 6 months before date of current
             admission.

          6. On liver transplant wait list or liver transplant eligible with anticipation of being
             placed on the liver transplant wait list within seven days of screening.

             -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Serum creatinine level greater than 7.0 mg/dL.

          2. Uncontrolled sepsis and/or uncontrolled bacterial infection (e.g., persisting
             bacteremia, persisting ascitic fluid leukocytosis, fever, increasing leukocytosis with
             vasomotor instability).

          3. Shock.

          4. Current or recent (within 4 weeks) treatment with or exposure to nephrotoxic agents:
             eg, aminoglycosides, amphotericin, cyclosporine A, cisplatin, nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs: e.g., ibuprofen, naproxen, diclofenac), significant
             exposure to radiographic contrast agents (large doses or multiple injections of
             iodinated contrast media; e.g., during coronary or abdominal angiogram).

          5. Estimated life expectancy of less than 7 days.

          6. Superimposed acute liver injury due to drugs (e.g., acetaminophen), dietary
             supplements, herbal preparations, viral hepatitis, or toxins (e.g., Amanita toxin with
             mushroom poisoning carbon tetrachloride), with the exception of acute alcoholic
             hepatitis.

          7. Evidence of obstructive uropathy or parenchymal renal disease. Renal ultrasound or
             other imaging not required but should be taken if suspicious.

          8. Tubular epithelial casts, heme granular casts (range of 1-3 granular casts
             acceptable), hematuria or microhematuria on urinalysis that is indicative of acute
             tubular necrosis and/or intrinsic renal disease.

          9. Subjects known to be pregnant; all women of child-bearing age and potential must have
             a negative pregnancy test.

         10. Severe cardiovascular disease, including, but not limited to, unstable angina,
             pulmonary edema, congestive heart failure, or persisting symptomatic peripheral
             vascular disease, myocardial infarction or stable chronic angina within the past 12
             months, or any other cardiovascular disease judged by the investigator to be severe
             and creates a risk to subject with concurrent terlipressin use.

         11. Current or recent (within 4 weeks) renal replacement therapy (RRT) or anticipation of
             RRT within 3 days on enrollment.

         12. Participation in other clinical research involving investigational medicinal products
             that would adversely affect participation in this or the current trial.

         13. Transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunt (TIPS) within 30 days of starting study
             drug.

         14. Ongoing use of vasopressors. Any vasopressors must be stopped prior to treatment with
             terlipressin in the Prospective Terlipressin Group and also were not concomitantly
             taking any norepinephrine or vasopressors during the two weeks prior to treatment with
             terlipressin.

         15. Known allergy or sensitivity to terlipressin. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tracey Sikora</last_name>
    <phone>215-615-3238</phone>
    <email>tsikora@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Grace Kim-Lee</last_name>
    <phone>215-360-0836</phone>
    <email>gracekim.lee@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatorenal Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Terlipressin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

