<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04467060</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3571-CPK-1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04467060</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single Ascending Dose Pharmacology Study of Anaprazole in Healthy Chinese Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-center, Randomized, Double-blinded, Placebo Parallel Controlled Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety and Pharmacology of Single Ascending Dose Administration of Anaprazole in Healthy Chinese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sihuan Pharmaceutical Holdings Group Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sihuan Pharmaceutical Holdings Group Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A single-center, randomized, open-labeled, 2×2 crossover phase 1 study to evaluate the
      pharmakinetics effect of high fat food to single dose administration of Anaprazole in healthy
      Chinese male subjects. 14 health male subjects is divided to A group (n=7) and B group (n=7).
      2 periods (7 days) cross-over design, anaprazole 40mg single dose, one is fasting oral
      administration before breakfast, the other is oral administration 30 minutes after breakfast
      with high fat food.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 14, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 25, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 25, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events and serious adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v5.0</measure>
    <time_frame>From signing informed consent to study completion, 8 days post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events will be monitored in each subject</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Male Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anaprazole Sodium enteric-coated tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single ascendinng dose (2.5mg, 5mg, 10mg, 20mg, 40mg, 80mg, 120mg, 160mg), fasting oral administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>single dose, fasting oral administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anaprazole Sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>2.5mg, 5mg, 10mg, 20mg, 40mg, 80mg, 120mg, 160mg，fasting oral administration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anaprazole Sodium enteric-coated tablet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>single dose, fasting oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject is capable of understanding and complying with protocol requirements, and
             signed and dated a written informed consent form voluntarily;

          2. The subject is a Chinese health adult, aged 18 to 45 years, inclusive;

          3. The subject weighed at least 50.0 kg and had a body mass index (BMI) between 19.0
             kg/m^2 and 25.0 kg/m^2, inclusive;

          4. Has clinical laboratory evaluations, vital signs and ECG testing within the reference
             range, and medical history and physicial examination results are normal. Participants
             with evaluations outside the reference range that are deemed not clinically
             significant by the investigator may be included at investigator discretion

          5. No medical history of allergy to proton pump inhibitors and no any other drug allergy
             history;

          6. The subjects have a good lifestyle and can keep good communication with the
             investigators and comply with the requirements of clinical trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has postural hypotension, gastrointestinal disease (gastric ulcer, gastritis and etc),
             liver disease, renal disease (nephritis, pyelonephritis and etc), and other disease or
             medical history of any other system (cardiovascular, respiratory, psychoneural,
             hematology, endocrinology and etc) ;

          2. Has clinical significant abnormal electrolytes (especially hypopotassemia) in
             screening examination;

          3. Has clinical significant ECG abnormal history or family history of long QT
             syndrome(Grandparents, parents and siblings);

          4. Has rhinitis, allergic rhinitis, recurrent hemorrhinia, nasal deformity and abnormal
             nasal septum；

          5. With positive result of drug screening test;

          6. With positive result of nicotine test;

          7. Female participants who are pregnant, breast-feeding or menstral period, or
             participants has no effective contraception method, or has pregnancy plan in 6 months;

          8. Has received any drugs: acid-inhibitors, any priscription drug, herb medicine,
             non-prescription drugs and/or food suppliments (including vitamine) within 2 weeks
             before randomization;

          9. Blood donation / blood loss ≥400 mL within 3 months, or participated any other
             clinical trials within 3 months;

         10. Known Human immunodeficiency virus antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C
             antibody, and Treponema pallidum specific antibody test results were positive at
             screening;

         11. Frequent alcoholics (drink more than 2 units of alcohol per day, 1 unit = 330 mL beer
             or 25 mL liquor or 125 mL wine), or took food or drinks with alcoholics 72 hours
             before randomization;

         12. Has taken foods or drinks with xanthine(cafeine) or intensive excercise. Has taken
             foods or drinks that affect CYP3A4 (such as grapefruit or beverages containing
             grapefruit) within 14 days before administration of investigational drugs;

         13. Smoke more than 5 pieces per week;

         14. Any conditions in which considered by investigator not be appropriate to participate
             in this trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

