<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03541655</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100-CIP01-P</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03541655</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Activity of F14 for Management of Pain Following Total Knee Replacement</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Randomized, Single-Blind, Active-Control, Parallel Group Study to Evaluate Safety and Activity of a Single Administration of F14 for Management of Postoperative Pain in Participants Undergoing Unilateral Total Knee Replacement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arthritis Innovation Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arthritis Innovation Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The safety and activity of a single, 3.5 mL dose of F14 (celecoxib) concurrent with standard
      of care analgesia administered following total knee replacement will be compared to standard
      of care analgesia alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, single-blind, active control study in participants undergoing primary
      unilateral total knee replacement (TKR). Fifty (50) participants will be randomized 1:1 to
      receive either a single, 3.5 mL dose of F14 (celecoxib) concurrent with standard of care
      analgesia, or only standard of care analgesia. F14 will be administered into the joint space
      at the end of surgery and just prior to wound closing. Safety will be evaluated through
      recording of adverse events, vital signs, ECG, physical and knee-specific examinations,
      laboratory blood tests and standing x-rays of the TKR obtained at 3 and 12 months.
      Post-operative pain will be assessed using visual analog scores (VAS) and Western Ontario and
      McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) questionnaires and the Timed Up and Go
      test. Concomitant medication usage including MSO4 equivalents will be monitored daily for 3
      months with participant drug diaries, and at the 12-month visit. Perceived benefit of
      analgesia will be compared using the Overall Benefit of Analgesic Score (OBAS). The
      pharmacokinetic profile of celecoxib in plasma will be assessed up to 3 months. Standardized
      physical therapy will be implemented post-operatively. Follow-up study visits will occur at
      1, 2, 3, 4 (phone) and 6 weeks, 3 and 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak pain intensity measured by visual analog scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve (AUC) of visual analog scale (VAS) pain intensity scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 72 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Summed pain intensity difference (SPID) of visual analog scale (VAS) pain intensity scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 72 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional improvement by Timed Up and Go test</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total post-surgical opioid consumption (in MSO4 equivalents)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak pain intensity by visual analog score (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain, stiffness, and physical function by the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC Parts A, B, C)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first rescue medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants using rescue medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Benefit of analgesia by Overall Benefit of Analgesic Score (OBAS) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Celecoxib concentration in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Total Knee Replacement</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.25% Bupivacaine HCl administered following total knee replacement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>F14 (celecoxib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3.5 mL dose of F14 (celecoxib) concurrent with 0.25% Bupivacaine HCl administered following total knee replacement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacaine HCl</intervention_name>
    <description>0.25% Bupivacaine HCl</description>
    <arm_group_label>F14 (celecoxib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Marcaine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F14 (celecoxib)</intervention_name>
    <description>Celecoxib in novel drug delivery system (BEPO™)</description>
    <arm_group_label>F14 (celecoxib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and/or female indicated for primary, unilateral TKR

          -  Between 45-80 years of age inclusive at the time of signing the informed consent

          -  Capable of giving signed informed consent and complying with requirements and
             restrictions listed in the informed consent form (ICF) and in this protocol

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) ≤ 40 kg/m²

          -  Medically stable as determined by the Investigator based on pre-study medical history,
             physical examination, clinical laboratory tests, and 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG)
             findings

          -  Absence of fixed flexion deformity exceeding 15°

          -  Absence of varus or valgus deformity exceeding 15°

          -  Minimum pre-operative flexion arc of 100°

          -  Absence of steroid, hyaluronic acid, platelet rich plasma, or any other type of
             therapeutic injection(s) in the index knee within 3 months before scheduled surgery

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Status Classification System (ASA-PSC)
             score ≤ 3

          -  Females of childbearing potential with a negative pregnancy test at screening, who
             agree to employ adequate birth control measures for the full duration of the study

          -  Has undergone scheduled total knee replacement surgery of the index knee, which in the
             opinion of the Investigator, will not affect the participant's study follow-up

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy or hypersensitivity to active ingredient celecoxib. When an allergy to
             celecoxib is unknown,allergy or hypersensitivity to sulfonamide antibiotics or sulfa
             containing drugs

          -  Active or past infection in the index knee

          -  Previous total or partial knee arthroplasty in either knee within the past 6 months

          -  Prior arthroscopy in the index knee in the last 6 months; knee surgery other than
             arthroscopy (including cruciate ligament, cartilage or osteotomy) in the index knee in
             the last 12 months; knee surgery in the contralateral knee in the last 12 months
             (excluding total or partial knee replacement)

          -  Documented osteonecrosis or arthrotomy within previous 12 months

          -  Prior or current presence of hardware in index knee other than screws from previous
             ligament repair that do not require manipulation or removal for TKR surgery

          -  Other planned major surgery within 12 months of scheduled surgery

          -  Concurrent painful physical condition that may require analgesic treatment (such as an
             NSAID or opioid) in the postsurgical period for pain that is not strictly related to
             the TKR surgery emanating from other lower body joints in the ipsilateral (hip, ankle)
             or contralateral (hip, knee, ankle) or back (by body diagram)

          -  Current or historical evidence of any clinically significant disease or condition,
             especially cardiovascular, pulmonary or neurological conditions that, in the opinion
             of the Investigator, may increase the risk of surgery or complicate or affect the
             participant's study follow-up

          -  Strong narcotic use (e.g. Oxycontin®, Vicodin®, Percocet®) before scheduled study
             surgery for a prolonged period exceeding 30 days within the last 2 years

          -  History of alcohol abuse within previous 12 months (score of 4 on CAGE questionnaire)

          -  Known or suspected history of illicit drug abuse within 1 year before randomization,
             or history of opioid dependence within 2 years before scheduled surgery (score
             exceeding 5 on DAST-10 questionnaire)

          -  Participation in another clinical study involving an investigational product (IP) or
             device within 30 days before screening or scheduled participation in another clinical
             study involving an IP or device during the course of this study

          -  Use of pregabalin or gabapentin, or other drugs for neuropathic pain unless willing to
             discontinue at least 7 days prior to study surgery

          -  Current patient-reported seizure disorder

          -  Current peripheral neuropathy

          -  Current depression, mood or anxiety disorder (score exceeding 14 on PHQ-9
             questionnaire)

          -  History of complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS)

          -  Diagnosis of clinically significant liver and/or renal abnormalities within previous 2
             years

          -  Diagnosis of diabetes with HbA1c exceeding 7

          -  Current inflammatory arthritides (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, lupus erythematosus,
             ankylosing spondylitis, psoriatic arthritis), or traumatic bone injuries within 12
             months before scheduled surgery, but excepting clinically stable/non-active gout that
             does not affect the knee and does not interfere with walking

          -  Treatment with immunosuppressants, antipsychotics, anticholinergics, or
             anticonvulsants within 1 month of randomization

          -  Diagnosis of skin disorders including psoriasis, vascular insufficiency ulcers, and
             chronic venous stasis

          -  Participants with sleep apnea associated with a history of postoperative delirium. If
             symptomatic sleep apnea is currently treated with continuous positive airway pressure
             (CPAP) or bilevel positive airway pressure (BIPAP), use must be continued
             postoperatively

          -  History of coronary or vascular stent placed within 3 months (may be extended to 1
             year if medically indicated per physician discretion).

          -  Participation in active or pending personal injury or workers' compensation litigation
             related to index knee

          -  Current or planned use of medical marijuana or cannabidiol (CBD), unless willing to
             discontinue at least 10 days prior to study surgery and for 3 months following study
             surgery

          -  Unwilling or unable to discontinue use of NSAIDs within 7 days of scheduled surgery
             and for 3 months following study surgery, including low-dose aspirin for cardiac
             prophylaxis

          -  Has an allergy or contraindication to opioids

          -  Had a malignancy in the last year, except for non-metastatic basal cell or squamous
             cell carcinoma of the skin or localized carcinoma in situ of the cervix

          -  Positive urine drug screen for disallowed medication at screening or preoperatively on
             day of study surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jared Foran, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Panorama Orthopedics &amp; Spine Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Panorama Orthopedics &amp; Spine Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dayton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endeavor Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>July 7, 2020</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>total knee replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>celecoxib</keyword>
  <keyword>intra-articular</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Celecoxib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

