<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03547479</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TW010592-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03547479</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VDOT and Mobile Payments in Cambodia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combined Phone Based Video DOT and Mobile Payments for TB Treatment in Cambodia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Operation ASHA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National University, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project proposes to develop and pilot a novel smart phone-based intervention to improve
      tuberculosis (TB) treatment adherence in Cambodia, which integrates video-enabled Directly
      Observed Treatment (vDOT) with an automated rewards system that transfers mobile money and
      eventual phone ownership to compliant patients. The results will be of immediate relevance to
      Cambodia's National TB Control Program (which is partnering with us), the major implementing
      field partner Operation ASHA (a leading TB-focused nonprofit organization), as well as other
      TB control programs seeking new alternatives to improving adherence, especially where
      traditional DOT may be infeasible or costly, and outside the area of TB where adherence to
      treatment is critical, such as HIV, and will provide key insights into mobile health
      (mHealth) programs in a setting relevant to other developing countries. The project will
      involve building new capacity in Cambodia for behavioral research, mHealth,and communications
      through hands-on training for study staff in-country, and through general training sessions
      for internal and external stakeholders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tuberculosis (TB) remains one of the leading causes of death from infectious disease
      worldwide, and treatment adherence a persistent challenge. This is particularly pressing in
      high-burden, low-resource settings such as Cambodia, where approximately two-thirds of people
      carry the TB bacterium, one of the highest rates in the world. The investigators propose to
      develop and pilot a novel smart phone-based intervention to improve TB treatment adherence,
      integrating video-enabled Directly Observed Therapy (VDOT) with transfers of mobile money and
      phone ownership to compliant patients. This intervention aims to directly address two of the
      key barriers to TB treatment adherence in low resource settings where DOT is costly or
      impractical. First, the video component has the potential to substitute direct in-person
      observation with time-stamped videos of patients taking their medication. Second, the
      proposed intervention incorporates incentives to patients for treatment adherence and
      equipment preservation in the form of mobile money and eventual phone ownership upon
      treatment completion.

      In partnership with the National Tuberculosis Program (NTP), the investigators will assess
      the feasibility of this intervention and of a future randomized study in two districts of
      Cambodia. First, the team will extend and adapt an existing platform for video-enabled
      medication monitoring (Mobile Interactive Supervised Therapy (MIST)) to incorporate mobile
      cash payments conditional upon compliance. Outstanding technical and usability issues with
      the platform will be identified and addressed by conducting an initial 1-month test of the
      intervention with 10 TB patients. Finally, the investigators will conduct an 8-month
      demonstration study among 50 households in our study locations to assess the acceptability,
      implementation, and potential for scale up of the intervention. We also aim to assess the
      practicalities and challenges of a future randomized controlled effectiveness and
      cost-effectiveness trial.

      To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to examine a mHealth intervention for
      TB that integrates both adherence monitoring and patient incentives into a single platform.
      The results will be of immediate relevance to the NTP as well as other TB control programs
      seeking new alternatives to improving adherence, especially where traditional DOT may be
      infeasible or costly. These results will also be of interest outside the area of TB where
      adherence to treatment is critical, such as HIV. More generally, the study will provide key
      insights into mHealth programs in a setting relevant to other developing countries. This
      project will involve building new capacity in Cambodia for behavioral research, mHealth, and
      communications through training to the study personnel and general training on conducting TB
      and/or mHealth research to study partners and other stakeholders in the country.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study design consists of (a) 4 qualitative focus groups (b) a pretest of 10 patient (c) a pilot randomised study of 60 patients and (d) interviews of stakeholders including healthcare professionals and policymakers</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility: % patients correctly using the system</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>% patients correctly using the system without phone theft, breakages or discrepancies in incentive distribution</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Missed treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Any missed treatment for 10 subsequent days or more</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of pills taken relative to total prescribed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment default</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Missed treatment for 2 subsequent months or more</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cure</measure>
    <time_frame>5 and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sputum smear-conversion at month 5 and 8</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive current standard of care (DOTS)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VDOT only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive daily DOTS treatment with video-enabled mobile monitoring, but also maintain regular supervisory checks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VDOT + mobile money incentives</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive daily DOTS treatment with video-enabled mobile monitoring supplemented with mobile money incentives, but also maintain regular supervisory checks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VDOT</intervention_name>
    <description>In VDOT, reminder notifications are sent x minutes prior to the scheduled pill time, and continue every y minutes until the user sends a video of themselves taking their pill via the app. Instructions will be provided in Khmer. The web system has an administrator component whereby a healthcare provider can log in via the Internet to monitor and validate all the videos received that day, and reasons for non-submission.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VDOT only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VDOT + mobile money</intervention_name>
    <description>The VDOT intervention above will be paired with financial incentives in the form of mobile payments in one of the experimental arms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VDOT + mobile money incentives</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        PROPOSED PATIENT INCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Age 21 years or more;

          2. Diagnosis of TB at healthcare facility (Clinical symptoms consistent with pulmonary TB
             and sputum test positive);

          3. Willing to comply with the study procedures;

          4. Resident at a fixed address within feasible travelling distance to the site and likely
             to remain resident there for the foreseeable future;

          5. Willing to have directly observed therapy;

          6. Willing and able to provide written informed consent in English/Khmer.

        PROPOSED PATIENT EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Extra-pulmonary TB or suspected rifampicin resistance;

          2. Underlying serious chronic diseases (such as liver or kidney disease, active
             malignancy, poorly-controlled diabetes);

          3. History of myocardial infarction, congestive cardiac failure, cardiac arrhythmias or
             family history of Long QT Syndrome;

          4. Current alcohol or drug abuse;

          5. Pregnancy;

          6. Inability to take oral medication or known allergy to one or more of the study drugs.

          7. Any other significant condition that would, in the opinion of the investigator,
             compromise the patient's safety or outcome in the trial or lead to poor compliance
             with study visits and protocol requirements;

             -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joanne Yoong</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joanne Yoong, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+6583327955</phone>
    <email>jyoong@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lila Rabinovich, MPhil</last_name>
    <phone>+12138210537</phone>
    <email>lilarabi@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joanne S. Yoong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Program Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

