<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03540953</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NP549/14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03540953</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endoscopic Injection of Mitomycin C for the Treatment of Pharyngoesophageal Stenosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endoscopic Injection of Mitomycin C for the Treatment of Pharyngoesophageal Stenosis Refractory to Endoscopic Treatment With Dilatation in Patients With Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fauze Maluf Filho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto do Cancer do Estado de São Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Management of pharyngoesophageal stenosis (PES) in patients after head and neck cancer (HNC)
      treatment remains a challenge. There are some cases of strictures refractory to dilation
      sessions. This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy of Mitomycin C (MMC) endoscopic injection
      for the treatment of refractory pharyngoesophageal stenosis.

      Patients and methods: This is a prospective study in patients with dysphagia following head
      and neck cancer treatment, without evidence suggestive of tumor recurrence, and refractory to
      endoscopic treatment. Theses undergo endoscopic dilation of the stenotic segment with
      thermoplastic bougies, followed by the injection of MMC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Management of pharyngoesophageal stenosis (PES) after cancer treatment in patients with head
      and neck cancer (HNC) remains a challenge. The etiology of PES in this group of patients is
      probably multifactorial, being associated with surgical manipulation, ischemic effects of
      radiotherapy and even cancer recurrence. It is estimated that up to 50% of patients treated
      for advanced HNC will present some degree of dysphagia. PES is a frequent cause of post
      treatment dysphagia of HNC patients. Although the exact prevalence is unknown, several
      retrospective series estimate that upper cervical stricture is present in 1% to 23% of the
      cases. The initial approach to PES is endoscopic dilation with a reported success rate
      ranging from 76% to 96%. In patients with refractory strictures to dilation sessions,
      endoscopic corticosteroid injection, such as triamcinolone, is usually added to the dilation
      sessions, which may increase the success of the endoscopic treatment. A relatively small
      group of patients will be refractory to the association of dilation and corticosteroid
      injection treatment. Metal stents may be considered in this scenario, but in the case of
      pharyngoesophageal stenosis, this approach is limited by cervical pain and foreign body
      sensation. Surgical reconstruction for pharyngoesophageal stenosis refractory to endoscopic
      treatment is the last therapeutic option (2). Previous radiotherapy, eventual reconstruction
      with cutaneous flaps make a surgical manipulation of the cervical region a real challenge,
      with increased adverse event rate, including restenosis.(2) Because of such difficulties,
      this prospective study aimed to evaluate the efficacy of Mitomycin C (MMC) endoscopic
      injection for the treatment of pharyngoesophageal stenoses in patients who were treated for
      head and neck cancer, refractory to endoscopic dilation treatment. There are descriptions of
      the use of Mitomycin C for scar prevention after ophthalmologic and otorhinolaryngological
      interventions (8). Its use in endoscopy has previously been described for the treatment of
      laryngeal and tracheal stenosis as well as refractory esophageal stenosis. Mitomycin C is a
      substance isolated from the bacterium Streptomyces caespitosus, which is used as a
      chemotherapeutic agent and has antiproliferative effects on fibroblasts, reducing fibroblast
      proliferation and collagen formation. Some studies demonstrated the ability to decrease
      fibroblast activity and consequent scar formation after the application of Mitomycin C on
      culture of fibroblasts in low concentrations (0.1 to 0.4 mg / ml) for 5 to 10 minutes,
      affecting their proliferation for over 3 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    adverse events was observed in all of them, with intense neck pain and ulcer evelopment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 5, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 5, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 5, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>dysphagia</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>dysphagia score (0 = able to eat normal diet / no dysphagia;1 = able to swallow some solid foods; 2 = able to swallow only semi solid foods; 3 = able to swallow liquids only; 4 = unable to swallow anything / total dysphagia)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of sessions of endoscopic dilations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>decrease in the number of sessions of endoscopic dilations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Deglutition Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Head and Neck Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endoscopic injection of Mitomycin C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endoscopy injection of Mitomycin C will be perform to the treatment of pharyngoesophageal stenosis refractory to endoscopic treatment with dilatation in patients with head and neck cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic injection of Mitomycin C</intervention_name>
    <description>administration included dilation of the stenotic segment with thermoplastic bougies, followed by the injection of 3mg of Mitomycin C, divided into 4 aliquots of 0.75mg, injected in the four quadrants, at the stenosis level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endoscopic injection of Mitomycin C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with dysphagia following head and neck cancer treatment

          -  Patients without endoscopic or radiological evidence suggestive of tumor recurrence

          -  Patients refractory to endoscopic treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Endoscopic or radiological signs suggestive of tumor recurrence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto do Câncer do Estado de São Paulo - ICESP</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <zip>01246-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Instituto do Cancer do Estado de São Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fauze Maluf Filho</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endoscopic injection of Mitomycin C</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mitomycins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitomycin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

