<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03549715</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEMIO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03549715</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NEoadjuvant Dose-dense MVAC In cOmbination With Durvalumab and Tremelimumab in Muscle-invasive Urothelial Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEMIO</acronym>
  <official_title>NEoadjuvant Dose-dense MVAC In cOmbination With Durvalumab (MEDI4736) and Tremelimumab in Muscle-invasive Urothelial Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Association Pour La Recherche des Thérapeutiques Innovantes en Cancérologie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Association Pour La Recherche des Thérapeutiques Innovantes en Cancérologie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, phase I/II clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of 2
      cycles of durvalumab without (Arm A) or with (Arm B) tremelimumab in association with ddMVAC
      as neoadjuvant therapy in patients with MIUC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Population:

      Patients with MIUC fit to receive cisplatin.

      Study Design:

      The trial is designed as a non-comparative, open-label phase I/II study.

      Divided in two phases:

      The run In phase (I) and a phase II study. During the run-in phase, a limited number of
      patients (n=12-18) will be treated with durvalumab + ddMVAC or durvalumab + tremelimumab +
      ddMVAC (6-9 patients each). If the toxicity rate is acceptable (not higher than 2 out of 6 or
      3 out of 9 patients per arm) the study will continue as a randomized phase II study. During
      phase II, the efficacy and safety of durvalumab + ddMVAC and durvalumab + tremelimumab +
      ddMVAC

      Research hypothesis:

      Combination of checkpoint inhibitors (CPI), durvalumab ± tremelimumab, with neoadjuvant
      ddMVAC will improve the pathological complete response (pCR) rate in patients with
      muscle-invasive urothelial carcinoma (MIUC). No additional toxicity of the combination CPI +
      ddMVAC is expected.

      Investigational Product(s):

      Durvalumab: 1500 mg IV D1 every 28 days Durvalumab will be administered at the hospital every
      28 days prior to administration of ddMVAC on D1.

      Tremelimumab 75 mg IV D1 every 28 days Tremelimumab will be administered first, with
      durvalumab infusion starting approximately 1 hour (maximum 2 hours) after the end of the
      tremelimumab infusion.

      Translational research:

      Mechanism of response/resistance to neoadjuvant treatment will be assessed by comparing
      molecular and immunological tumor profiles before treatment (transurethral resection tumor
      samples) and after treatment (cystectomy samples). In addition, circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA)
      and urine tumor DNA (utDNA) will be analysed during treatment (ctDNA and utDNA) and after
      surgery (ctDNA).

      Immunological profiles will be established using a specific metagene signature for major cell
      types of the tumor microenvironment and chemokines, cytokines and regulatory molecules , and
      will be validated using relevant markers by immunohistochemistry (IHC) on formalin-fixed
      paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor sections.

      Metabolomic profiling will also be conducted by analyzing metabolites present in urinary
      samples with a Proton-based nuclear magnetic resonance (1H-NMR), and correlations with
      prognosis, molecular profile or/and with immunological signature determined.

      Finally, correlations between tumor pathological factors (e.g., pTNM, nuclear grade, variant
      squamous differentiation or sarcomatoid dedifferentiation) and prognosis will be evaluated
      using IHC on FFPE tissue sections.

      Sample Size: Approximately 120 patients are planned to be included.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The sample size will be balanced between 2 arms. Initially, 12 patients (6 in each arm) will be included and randomized between durvalumab + ddMVAC (ARM A) or durvalumab + tremelimumab + ddMVAC (ARM B)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity Grade</measure>
    <time_frame>38 months</time_frame>
    <description>Grade ≥ 3 treatment related toxicity rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pathologic complete response</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>pCR rate after ddMVAC + durvalumab ± tremelimumab period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-Free Survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the 1-year disease-free survival (DFS) rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the 1-year overall survival (OS) rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events (AEs).</measure>
    <time_frame>38 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the incidence of adverse events (AEs).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic downstaging</measure>
    <time_frame>During procedure</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the pathologic downstaging rate (defined as the presence of residual tumor ≤T1 on cystectomy, excluding T0).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular profile</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine changes in the molecular profile and immunological signature of the tumor after treatment compared with before treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Factors of pCR</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To identify predictive factors of pCR response to treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological signature</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine changes in the immunological signature of the tumor after treatment compared with before treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Infiltrating Bladder Urothelial Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A: durvalumab + ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Durvalumab + ddMVAC Durvalumab 1500 mg IV D1 every 28 days Durvalumab will be administered at the hospital every 28 days prior to administration of ddMVAC on D1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: durvalumab + tremelimumab+ ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>durvalumab + tremelimumab + ddMVAC Tremelimumab 75 mg IV D1 every 28 days Tremelimumab will be administered first, with durvalumab infusion starting approximately 1 hour (maximum 2 hours) after the end of the tremelimumab infusion.
Infusion of ddMVAC will start approximately 1 hour after completion of durvalumab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>1500 mg IV D1 every 28 days (2 doses for each patient)</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A: durvalumab + ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: durvalumab + tremelimumab+ ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MEDI4736</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tremelimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>75 mg IV D1 every 28 days ((2 doses for each patient)</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: durvalumab + tremelimumab+ ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CP-675,206</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MVAC Protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>Methotrexate 30 mg/m2 IV D1
Vinblastine 3 mg/m2 IV D1
Adriamycin (doxorubicin) 30 mg/m2 IV D1
Cisplatin 70 mg/m2 IV D1</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM A: durvalumab + ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ARM B: durvalumab + tremelimumab+ ddMVAC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ddMVAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent and any locally required authorization (e.g., EU Data Privacy
             Directive in the EU) obtained from the patient prior to performing any
             protocol-related procedures, including screening evaluations

          2. Age ≥18 years at time of study entry

          3. Histologically confirmed MIUC (also termed TCC) of the bladder. Patients with mixed
             histologies are required to have a dominant transitional cell pattern (urothelial
             carcinoma must be &gt; 50%)

          4. Localized MIUC of the bladder with clinical stage T2−T4a and ≤N1 disease ( the single
             lymph node must be &lt; 15 mm (short axis) on imaging

          5. Patients with urothelial carcinoma of the prostatic urethra

          6. Bodyweight &gt;45kg

          7. Patients eligible for cisplatin-based neoadjuvant chemotherapy, including:

               -  Creatinine clearance (CL) &gt;60 mL/min based on the Modification of Diet in Renal
                  Disease Study (MDRD) formula

               -  Cardiac left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥50%

          8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          9. Absence of metastasis, as confirmed by a negative baseline CT or MRI scan of the
             pelvis, abdomen, and chest no more than 4 weeks prior to randomization. Patients with
             clinical stage N1 disease are eligible if the single lymph node measures ≤2 cm in
             greatest dimension.

         10. Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below (obtained within 14 days prior to
             the first study treatment):

               -  Hemoglobin ≥10.0 g/dL (patients may be transfused to meet this criterion)

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1500 cells/μL (without G-CSF support within 2
                  weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1)

               -  WBC counts &gt;2500/µL

               -  Platelet count ≥100,000/µL (without transfusion within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1,
                  Day 1)

               -  Serum bilirubin ≤1.0 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN). Patients with
                  known Gilbert disease who have serum bilirubin level ≤3 x ULN may be enrolled.

               -  AST, ALT, and alkaline dehydrogenase ≤2.5 x ULN

               -  Partial thromboplastin time/prothrombin time (PTT/PT) ≤1.5 x ULN or international
                  normalized ratio (INR) &lt;1.7 x ULN

         11. Evidence of post-menopausal status or negative urinary or serum pregnancy test for
             female pre-menopausal patients. Women will be considered post-menopausal if they have
             been amenorrheic for 12 months without an alternative medical cause. The following
             age-specific requirements apply:

               -  Women &lt;50 years of age would be considered post-menopausal if they have been
                  amenorrheic for 12 months or more following cessation of exogenous hormonal
                  treatments and if they have luteinizing hormone and follicle-stimulating hormone
                  levels in the post-menopausal range for the institution or underwent surgical
                  sterilization (bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy)

               -  Women ≥50 years of age would be considered post-menopausal if they have been
                  amenorrheic for 12 months or more following cessation of all exogenous hormonal
                  treatments, had radiation-induced menopause with last menses &gt;1 year ago, had
                  chemotherapy-induced menopause with last menses &gt;1 year ago, or underwent
                  surgical sterilization (bilateral oophorectomy, bilateral salpingectomy or
                  hysterectomy).

         12. Women of childbearing potential and non-sterilized males who are sexually active with
             a female partner of childbearing potential must be willing to use contraceptive
             methods during the treatment period and for at least 6 months after the last dose of
             treatment

         13. Patient is willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study
             including undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and examinations including follow
             up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Urothelial carcinoma of the upper tract

          2. Any approved anti-cancer therapy for urothelial carcinoma, including chemotherapy, or
             immunotherapy prior to initiation of study treatment. Of note, previous intravesical
             BCG injections are allowed if administered for non-muscle invasive urothelial
             carcinoma

          3. Primary chemoradiation for bladder preservation for urothelial carcinoma of the
             bladder

          4. Impaired renal function (glomerular filtration rate (GFR)&lt;60 mL/min); GFR should be
             assessed by calculation from serum/plasma creatinine (MDRD formula)

          5. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness, including but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, interstitial lung disease, serious chronic
             gastrointestinal conditions associated with diarrhea, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirement, substantially increase
             risk of incurring AEs or compromise the ability of the patient to give written
             informed consent

          6. Grade 2 or greater hearing loss that contraindicates cisplatin use. Threshold shift of
             &gt;25 decibel averaged at 2 contiguous test frequencies in least one ear.

          7. Grade 2 or greater peripheral neuropathy

          8. Oral anticoagulation treatment (vitamin K antagonist should be replaced by
             low-molecular-weight heparin)

          9. Treatment with any other investigational agent or participation in another clinical
             trial with therapeutic intent within 28 days or five half-lives of the drug

         10. Concurrent enrolment in another clinical study, unless it is an observational
             (non-interventional) clinical study or during the follow-up period of an
             interventional study

         11. Any concurrent chemotherapy, investigational product, biologic, or hormonal therapy
             for cancer treatment. Concurrent use of hormonal therapy for non-cancer-related
             conditions (e.g., hormone replacement therapy) is acceptable

         12. Major surgical procedure (as defined by the Investigator) other than for diagnosis
             within 28 days prior to Cycle 1

         13. History of prior organ transplantation, including stem cell allografting

         14. History of autoimmune disease, including, but not limited to, myasthenia gravis,
             myositis, autoimmune hepatitis, systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis,
             inflammatory bowel disease, vascular thrombosis associated with antiphospholipid
             syndrome, Wegener's granulomatosis, Sjogren's syndrome, Guillain-Barré syndrome,
             multiple sclerosis, vasculitis, or glomerulonephritis. Patients with a history of
             autoimmune-related hypothyroidism on a stable dose of thyroid replacement hormone and
             type I diabetes mellitus on stable dose of insulin may be eligible for this study

         15. Severe infections within 4 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1, including but not limited to
             hospitalization for complications of infection, bacteremia, or severe pneumonia

         16. Signs or symptoms of infection within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1

         17. Receipt of therapeutic oral or IV antibiotics within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1

         18. Significant cardiovascular disease, such as New York Heart Association cardiac disease
             (Class II or greater), myocardial infarction within the previous 6 months, unstable
             arrhythmias, or unstable angina

         19. History of another primary malignancy within 3 years prior to Cycle 1, Day 1, except
             for:

               -  Localized low-risk prostate cancer (defined as Stage ≤T2b, Gleason score ≤7, and
                  prostate-specific antigen [PSA] at prostate cancer diagnosis ≤20 ng/mL [if
                  measured]) treated with curative intent and without PSA recurrence

               -  Low-risk prostate cancer (defined as Stage T1/T2a, Gleason score &lt;7, and PSA ≤10
                  ng/mL) who are treatment-naive and undergoing active surveillance

               -  Patients with malignancies of a risk of metastasis/death (e.g., risk of
                  metastasis or death &lt;5% at 5 years) are eligible after investigator's approval if
                  they meet both of the following criteria: Malignancy treated with expected
                  curative intent, and no evidence of recurrence or metastasis by follow-up imaging
                  and any disease-specific tumor markers

         20. History of leptomeningeal carcinomatosis

         21. History of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, organizing pneumonia

         22. Serum albumin &lt;25 g/L

         23. LVEF &lt;50%

         24. Mean QT interval corrected for heart rate using Fridericia's formula (QTcF) ≥470 ms
             calculated from 3 electrocardiograms (ECGs) within 15 minutes at 5 minutes apart

         25. Active infection including tuberculosis (clinical evaluation that includes clinical
             history, physical examination and radiographic findings, and TB testing in line with
             local practice), hepatitis B (known positive HBV surface antigen (HBsAg) result),
             hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency virus (positive HIV 1/2 antibodies). Patients
             with a past or resolved HBV infection (defined as the presence of hepatitis B core
             antibody [anti-HBc] and absence of HBsAg) are eligible. Patients positive for
             hepatitis C (HCV) antibody are eligible only if PCR is negative for HCV RNA

         26. Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 14 days before the first
             dose of durvalumab or tremelimumab. The following are exceptions to this criterion:

               -  Intranasal, inhaled, topical steroids, or local steroid injections ( intra
                  articular injection)

               -  Systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses not to exceed 10 mg/day of
                  prednisone or its equivalent

               -  Steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity reactions (CT scan premedication)

         27. Receipt of live attenuated vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of study
             treatment. Note: Patients, if enrolled, should not receive live vaccine whilst
             receiving study treatment and for up to 30 days after the last dose of study treatment

         28. Female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding, or male or female patients of
             reproductive potential who are not willing to employ effective birth control from
             screening to 90 days after the last dose of durvalumab monotherapy or180 days after
             the last dose of durvalumab + tremelimumab combination therapy

         29. Known allergy or hypersensitivity to chimeric or humanized antibodies or fusion
             proteins, or to any of the study drugs or study drug excipients

         30. Prior randomisation or treatment in a previous durvalumab and/or tremelimumab clinical
             study regardless of treatment arm assignment

         31. Any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition that, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, makes the patient unsuitable for participation in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Constance THIBAULT, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpital Européen Georges Pompidou, Oncology department of Pr Stéphane OUDARD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reza ELAIDI, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00 33 1 56 09 23 40</phone>
    <email>reza-thierry.elaidi-ext@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mouna ROUABAH</last_name>
    <phone>00 33 1 56 09 50 16</phone>
    <email>mouna.rouabah-ext@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Européen Georges Pompidou</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <state>Ile De France</state>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Constance THIBAULT, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00 33 1 56 09 59 92</phone>
      <email>constance.thibault@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Constance THIBAULT, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint André, CHU de Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33075</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sasu Roc37</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chambray Les Tours</city>
        <zip>37170</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pierre COMBE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Henri-Mondor</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <zip>94000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Leon Berard</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69008</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aude FLECHON, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Paoli Calmettes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13009</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gwaenaelle Gravis, MD</last_name>
      <email>GRAVISG@marseille.fnclcc.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Antoine Lacassagne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Delphine BORCHIELLINI, MD</last_name>
      <email>Delphine.BORCHIELLINI@nice.unicancer.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Pitié-Salpetrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aurelien Gobert, MD</last_name>
      <email>aurelien.gobert@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Mutualiste Montsouris</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mostefa Bennamoun, MD</last_name>
      <email>Mostefa.Bennamoun@imm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75679</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olivier HUILLARD, MD</last_name>
      <email>olivier.huillard@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Eugene Marquis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <zip>35042</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hia Begin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Mandé</city>
        <zip>94160</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpitaux universitaires de Strasbourg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <zip>67000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philippe BARTHELEMY, MD</last_name>
      <email>philippe.barthelemy@chru-strasbourg.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Claudius Regaud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Damien POUESSEL, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Gustave Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yohann LORIOT, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Durvalumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tremelimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

