<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03543033</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03543033</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preoperative Corticosteroid Epidural Injection and Lumbar Decompression Surgery Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Control Trial Comparing Pain and Functional Outcome Following Single Level Lumbar Nerve Decompression Surgery With or Without Preoperative Corticosteroid Epidural Injection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lahey Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lahey Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized control trial will compare opioid use, pain, and functional outcomes
      following decompression surgery for single-level lumbar radiculopathy in patients who undergo
      placement of corticosteroid epidural injection within 2 weeks prior to surgery compared to
      those who do not. The hypothesis of this study is that patients who receive the preoperative
      corticosteroid injection will have less reduced postoperative opioid use, as well as earlier
      mobilization, reduced length of stay, and faster return to work compared to control patients
      who do not receive the injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized control study that will be completed within the Department of
      Neurosurgery at Lahey Hospital &amp; Medical Center. Patients will undergo their recommended
      surgery to treat single-level lumbar radiculopathy. Patients who are randomized to and
      consent to receiving a preoperative corticosteroid injection will report to clinic within 2
      weeks prior to date of surgery to receive a corticosteroid injection. These subjects will
      first receive a topical anesthesia to the skin and underlying tissue in a maximum amount of 5
      ml of 1% Lidocaine. Following this application, an 18-20 gauge epidural needle will be used
      to inject a solution containing 80 mg Depo-Medrol in 1 ml of 1% PF Lidocaine and 5ml of
      sterile PF saline. To assure the injection is epidural, we will be using loss of resistance
      technique under fluoroscopy and epidural placement will be confirmed with the live-image
      instillation in the AP and lateral positions of dye, with pattern confirming epidermal needle
      placement.

      All patients will complete health outcome questionnaires (VAS, EQ-5D, ODI) at baseline
      (treatment cohort: prior to injection, control cohort: prior to spine surgery), 1 week
      post-op, 1 month post-op, and 3 months post-op. Patients will be instructed to bring all
      condition-related pain medication containers to each follow-up for research measuring
      purposes. Research personnel will record number of pills remaining in container, number of
      opioid prescription refills, and respective dates. Opioid usage for each subject will be
      tracked and converted to mg oral morphine equivalents using a standard table. Research
      personnel will capture additional clinic information such as length of stay, length of time
      before ambulation, and occurrence of any complications (i.e. DVT, infection). Opioid use,
      muscle relaxants, and other pain medication use will be followed for 3 months. At baseline
      and at each post-op follow up, patients will be asked to define their use of illicit drugs
      over the past 6 months (heroin, cocaine, marijuana, methamphetamine, other). Return to work
      date and work status will be captured out to 3 months. Patients will submit a health-cost
      diary at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months, and this data will be combined with hospital-based
      cost information to generate a cost analysis. This diary will capture costs such as
      medication costs, copayments, travel, etc. Additionally, all patient surgery cancelations as
      well as reason for cancelation will be recorded. No additional medical testing will be
      required by the patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The study was closed by the investigators due to lack of study population to enroll.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Control Trial with randomization ratio 1:1</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Use - conversion to oral morphine equivalents using standard table</measure>
    <time_frame>Primary endpoint is 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Following spine surgery, # of prescription opioid pills used will be recorded and converted to oral morphine equivalents using a standard table. Information collected will include # of pills taken, # of prescription refills, and respective dates.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disability - Oswestry Disability Index (ODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 week post-op, 1 month post-op, and 3 months post-op</time_frame>
    <description>Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) will be used to measure disability associated with their spinal condition. The ODI contains 10 questions; each with 6 choices and each answer choice ranges from 0 to 5 points. The minimum score is 0 and maximum score is 50; the higher the score, the greater the disability indicated. Each question is 5 points each and is summed then divided by total possible point. Scores from each cohort will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain - Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 week post-op, 1 month post-op, and 3 months post-op</time_frame>
    <description>VAS will be used to measure pain and discomfort. The scale is a horizontal line numbered 0 through 10 with &quot;0&quot; indicating no pain, &quot;5&quot; indicating moderate pain, and 10 indicating worst pain. Patients will be instructed to mark an &quot;X&quot; on the number corresponding to their level of back pain over the past week. They will also be asked to indicate their leg pain on a similar, but separate scale. Scores from each cohort will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life - EuroQol-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 week post-op, 1 month post-op, and 3 months post-op</time_frame>
    <description>EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D) will be used to measure quality of life. The EQ-5D includes 5 multiple-choice questions with 3 choices each; each choice corresponding to a value of 1,2,or 3. Each value is entered into an algorithm that computes a score. The score can range from &quot;1&quot; = high quality of life&quot; and &quot;0&quot; = poor quality of life. Scores will be compared between both cohorts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost Analysis - Health Resource Diary</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week post-op, 1 month post-op, 3 months post-op</time_frame>
    <description>A self-administered health resource diary will be completed by the patient. Information on co payments, travel costs, medical devices, and medical tests will be collected. Along with their estimated costs or receipts.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Lumbar Radiculopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive a corticosteroid epidural injection within 2 weeks of their scheduled lumbar surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will not receive a corticosteroid injection within 2 weeks of their scheduled lumbar surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Corticosteroid injection</intervention_name>
    <description>These subjects will first receive a topical anesthesia to the skin and underlying tissue in a maximum amount of 5 ml of 1% Lidocaine. Following this application, an 18-20 gauge epidural needle will be used to inject a solution containing 80 mg Depo-Medrol in 1 ml of 1% PF Lidocaine and 5ml of sterile PF saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients 30-75 years of age

          2. Patients diagnosed with diagnoses with single level unilateral lumbar radiculopathy

          3. Patients diagnosed with spinal stenosis or disc herniation

          4. Patients who have a history of &gt; 6 weeks of at least 1 conservative treatment

          5. ASA &lt; III

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have undergone previous lumbar spinal surgery at index level

          2. Patients diagnosed with spondylolisthesis at index level

          3. Patients currently taking anti-coagulant therapy

          4. Active treatment of major psychiatric condition such as major depression and/or
             anxiety disorder.

          5. Patients currently seeking or receiving workers compensation

          6. Patients who have undergone previous corticosteroid injection at index level

          7. Morbid obesity defined as BMI &gt; 40

          8. Patients with history of chronic opioid use

          9. Patients with a contrast dye allergy

         10. Extruded disc fragment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erica J Bial, M.D., M.S.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lahey Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert G Whitmore, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lahey Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lahey Hospital &amp; Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lumbar radiculopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>corticosteroid epidural injection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Radiculopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

