<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03548116</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-0859</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03548116</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biological Effects of Ultrasound Insonification of the Spleen</brief_title>
  <official_title>Biological Effects of Ultrasound Insonification of the Spleen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>John Pellerito</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>General Electric</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwell Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a six-cohort, double-blinded, randomized, sham-controlled feasibility trial to
      determine whether organ-specific biological effects are achievable through selective
      ultrasound of the spleen utilizing low-energy insonification.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will consist of three study visits. At the screening visit, individuals will be
      asked to undergo a physical and neurological examination, a blood draw of 4 teaspoons, and a
      urine pregnancy test if of childbearing potential.

      The participants that clear study screening will be randomized to one of six groups. The
      groups consist of: sham insonification at the hilum; half-powered insonification at the
      hilum; full-powered insonification at the hilum; sham insonification at the lower, middle,
      and upper spleen; half-powered insonification at the lower, middle, and upper spleen; and
      full-powered insonification at the lower, middle, and upper spleen.

      At the baseline visit, individuals will be asked to undergo a physical and neurological
      examination and a blood draw of 7 teaspoons before receiving ultrasound as per their assigned
      group. These individuals will then be asked to undergo a blood draw of 5 teaspoons at 1-hour
      and 2-hours after the ultrasound.

      Individuals will be asked to return 24 hours later for the follow-up visit, which will
      include a physical and neurological examination and a blood draw of 9 teaspoons.

      Upon completion of the study, participants will receive compensation for their time and
      travel expenses for the baseline and follow-up visits.

      The blood samples collected before insonification, one hour after insonification, two hours
      after insonification, and twenty-four hours after insonification will be assessed for changes
      in biomarkers (substances in the body that indicate the status of a biological process or
      condition). These biomarkers include cytokines (proteins involved in the immune response),
      norepinephrine (chemical in the body that transmits signals), glucose (sugar in the blood),
      and blood cells that are involved in breathing, clotting, and the immune response.

      The study will be considered complete after completion of enrollment (10 participants in each
      group, for a study total of 60 participants), completion of study procedures by all
      participants, and the completion of analysis of identifiable study data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>After a screened individual is deemed eligible for continued participation, a study investigator will enter the participant's information into a randomization portal in order to receive the group assignment.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>The study participants will be blinded to their group assignment for the entire duration of the study. The study investigators will also be blinded to participant assignments on this study, except for the investigators performing the ultrasound procedure, co-investigators randomizing the participants, and co-investigators involved in the study's monitoring.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-inflammatory Response</measure>
    <time_frame>The primary outcome will be assessed before ultrasound and at 1-hour, 2-hours, and 24-hours after receiving ultrasound.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome to determine whether diagnostic-level ultrasound to the spleen has a biological effect is measured as a statistically significant change in the level of biomarkers associated with the inflammatory response following delivery of ultrasound.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transient Tissue Displacement</measure>
    <time_frame>The secondary outcome will be assessed approximately every 15 seconds during the approximately 10-minute ultrasound.</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcome to determine whether ultrasound delivery to the spleen leads to transient tissue displacement that is correlated to organ-specific biological effects is measured as a statistically significant correlation between the magnitude of transient displacement and the biological effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will receive sham non-imaging mode ultrasound (control group) delivered to just the spleen's hilum (area of spleen that allows passage of blood vessels, lymphatic vessels, and nerves).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will receive half-powered non-imaging mode ultrasound delivered to just the spleen's hilum (area of spleen that allows passage of blood vessels, lymphatic vessels, and nerves).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will receive full-powered non-imaging mode ultrasound delivered to just the spleen's hilum (area of spleen that allows passage of blood vessels, lymphatic vessels, and nerves).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will receive sham non-imaging mode ultrasound (control group) delivered to the lower, middle, and upper spleen based on the spleen's size.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will receive half-powered non-imaging mode ultrasound delivered to the lower, middle, and upper spleen based on the spleen's size.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will receive full-powered non-imaging mode ultrasound delivered to the lower, middle, and upper spleen based on the spleen's size.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>This study involves a specially designed ultrasound being placed against the abdomen of an individual in order to administer low levels of insonification to the spleen as specified by the individual's assigned study group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 6</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>This study involves a specially designed ultrasound being placed against the abdomen of an individual in order to administer sham insonification to the spleen as specified by the individual's assigned study group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals between 18 and 45 years of age

          -  Individuals without physical disabilities or conditions/diseases that may make them
             incapable of undergoing the study procedures or otherwise places them at a greater
             risk of harm

          -  Individuals without significant past medical or surgical histories that would render
             them at a greater risk of harm

          -  Individuals that are considered English Proficient due to the study requirements to
             follow verbal commands during the ultrasound session

          -  Individuals that are considered active as assessed by type of activity (i.e., walking,
             running, etc.) and number of hours a week performing the various activities

          -  Individuals able to attend all study visits at approximately the same time of day
             (i.e., 8 - 12 pm)

          -  Individuals that are able to comprehend the study goals and procedures, and are able
             to provide informed consent for participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals participating in another research study that may affect the conduct or
             results of this study

          -  Individuals considered substantially overweight or obese via body mass index (≥ 29)

          -  Individuals having or exhibiting any of the following:

               -  surgery in the past 90 days

               -  previous surgery of the spleen or splenectomy, esophagus, lungs, stomach,
                  duodenum, or liver

               -  recent traumatic injury, including intracerebral hemorrhage and visceral injury

               -  end stage renal disease and/or uremia

               -  active malignancy

               -  previous leukemia and/or lymphoma

               -  human immunodeficiency virus infection or AIDS

               -  rheumatoid arthritis or other immune-mediated diseases (e.g. inflammatory bowel
                  disease)

               -  arrhythmias, including but not limited to, atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter,
                  clinically significant bradycardia, ventricular arrhythmias, and A-V block

               -  implanted pacemaker or cardioverter/defibrillator (AICD)

               -  a history of stable or unstable angina, myocardial infarction, angioplasty or
                  coronary arterial by-pass grafting surgery

               -  history of stroke or TIA

               -  history of deep venous thrombosis (DVT) and/or pulmonary embolism (PE)

               -  previous episodes of pancreatitis

               -  spinal disorders

               -  chronic pain syndromes

               -  history of thrombosis or bleeding disorders

               -  stage III-IV pressure ulcers

               -  sickle cell anemia or other anemia syndromes

               -  monocytosis

               -  thrombocytopenia

               -  diagnosed with fever of unknown origin (FUO)

               -  previously or currently implanted vagus nerve stimulator

               -  previously or currently implanted spinal cord stimulator

               -  other chronically-implanted electronic medical device

               -  history of seizures

               -  history of cancer

          -  Individuals who have taken any of the following medications within one week of
             receiving ultrasound delivery:

               -  anti-coagulant (Coumadin, Xarelto)

               -  anti-platelet (aspirin, Plavix)

               -  anti-inflammatory (aspirin, NSAIDs)

               -  anti-hypertensive (α-methyldopa)

               -  epinephrine-related drugs, norepinephrine-related drugs, and drugs that stimulate
                  release of epinephrine and/or norepinephrine (Micronefrin, Asthmanefrin)

               -  immunosuppressive agents (steroids, newer immunomodulatory drugs)

               -  alpha and/or beta adrenoceptor blocking agents

               -  anti-seizure medications

               -  other medications, supplements, etc. that may interfere with the ultrasound
                  delivery or study results

          -  Individuals with a substance abuse (alcoholism or other) problem

          -  Individuals that consumed alcohol within 4 days of the baseline visit

          -  Individuals currently using or have used tobacco or nicotine products within the past
             1 month

          -  Individuals currently using or have used recreational drugs within the past 1 month

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Pellerito, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwell Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard D Ramdeo</last_name>
    <phone>516-562-3634</phone>
    <email>rramdeo1@northwell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwell Health's The Feinstein Institute for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhasset</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Ramdeo</last_name>
      <phone>516-562-3634</phone>
      <email>rramdeo1@northwell.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://commonfund.nih.gov/sparc</url>
    <description>Stimulating Peripheral Activity to Relieve Conditions (SPARC)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.darpa.mil/program/electrical-prescriptions</url>
    <description>Electrical Prescriptions</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1742-6596/581/1/012003/meta</url>
    <description>Ultrasonic Stimulation of Peripheral Nervous Tissue</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koopman FA, Chavan SS, Miljko S, Grazio S, Sokolovic S, Schuurman PR, Mehta AD, Levine YA, Faltys M, Zitnik R, Tracey KJ, Tak PP. Vagus nerve stimulation inhibits cytokine production and attenuates disease severity in rheumatoid arthritis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2016 Jul 19;113(29):8284-9. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1605635113. Epub 2016 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27382171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeng W, Pirzgalska RM, Pereira MM, Kubasova N, Barateiro A, Seixas E, Lu YH, Kozlova A, Voss H, Martins GG, Friedman JM, Domingos AI. Sympathetic neuro-adipose connections mediate leptin-driven lipolysis. Cell. 2015 Sep 24;163(1):84-94. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2015.08.055.</citation>
    <PMID>26406372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker JL, Cameron T. Technology for Peripheral Nerve Stimulation. Prog Neurol Surg. 2015;29:1-19. doi: 10.1159/000434651. Epub 2015 Sep 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26394391</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birk DM, Yin D, Slavin KV. Regulation of Peripheral Nerve Stimulation Technology. Prog Neurol Surg. 2015;29:225-37. doi: 10.1159/000434674. Epub 2015 Sep 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26394389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tracey KJ. Physiology and immunology of the cholinergic antiinflammatory pathway. J Clin Invest. 2007 Feb;117(2):289-96. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17273548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martelli D, McKinley MJ, McAllen RM. The cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway: a critical review. Auton Neurosci. 2014 May;182:65-9. doi: 10.1016/j.autneu.2013.12.007. Epub 2013 Dec 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24411268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juan EJ, González R, Albors G, Ward MP, Irazoqui P. Vagus Nerve Modulation Using Focused Pulsed Ultrasound: Potential Applications and Preliminary Observations in a Rat. Int J Imaging Syst Technol. 2014 Mar 1;24(1):67-71.</citation>
    <PMID>25165410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwell Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Pellerito</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice Chairman of Education, Department of Radiology; Director, Peripheral Vascular Laboratory and the Body Imaging Fellowship Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>Ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Insonification</keyword>
  <keyword>Spleen</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Currently, there are no plans to make individual participant data available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

