<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03548129</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>phosphomycin</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03548129</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>the Use of Fosfomycin as a Single Dose Oral Treatment of Asymptomatic Bacteriuria</brief_title>
  <official_title>Empirical Use of Fosfomycin as a Single Dose Oral Treatment of Asymptomatic Bacteriuria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Urinary tract infections (UTIs) are the most commonly occurring bacterial infections in
      women, Asymptomatic bacteriuria (AB) is a common complication during pregnancy, with a
      prevalence of 2-10%. It has been associated with a greater incidence of symptomatic urinary
      tract infection (UTI), as well as foetal and obstetric complications. Appropriate treatment
      reduces the incidence of UTI by 80-90%, as well as the risk of a premature birth and
      low-birth-weight baby Fosfomycin trometamol (Monuril) is approved in numerous countries
      worldwide, including various European countries and the USA, mainly for the treatment of
      uncomplicated UTIs
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to compare between the efficacy of empirical use of fosfomycin trometamol and
      the use of selected antimicrobials according to urinary culture and sensitivity in curing
      asymptomatic bacteriuria.

      All women included in the study will be counseled regarding mode of intervention and informed
      consent will be obtained. All cases will be subjected to complete history taking, routine
      antenatal examination and investigations including complete blood picture, kidney functions
      and urine analysis, treatment of genital infection if diagnosed. Routine obstetric ultrasound
      examination.

      Patients will be randomized into two groups:

        1. Group (A): Fosfomycin group (FG); where all patients will receive empirical 3 gm oral
           fosfomycin fosfomycin will be taken by mouth on an empty stomach i.e. 2-3 hours after
           meals preferably in the evening before bed time after emptying the bladder.

           The contents of 1 packet of Monuril will be dissolved in a glass of water or another
           non-alcoholic drink and drink immediately. Do not mix with hot water. Do not take
           fosfomycin in its dry form.

           Nature: also known as phosphomycin, phosphonomycin, is a broad-spectrum antibiotic,
           produced by certain Streptomyces species, although it can now be made by chemical
           synthesis.

           Trade name: Monuril Company: Zambon, Pharma Con Company, Switzerland

        2. Group (B): Culture specific group (CG): where all patients will receive oral antibiotic
           according to urine culture and sensitivity, oral antibiotics will be given in the form
           of five days regimen.

      How the urine sample will be collected? The caregiver will give the patient a sterile cup and
      lid, and advice her to wash herself completely then clean the perineal area from anterior to
      posterior by water and in standing position as male begin to urinate then stop urinating put
      the sterile cup and catch the rest of urine in it. Do not touch the inside of the cup or the
      lid. Put the lid on the cup.

      One week after completing the course of treatment all patients included in the study will be
      subjected to colony count evaluation, to figure out the need for:

        1. Urine culture in fosfomycin group in case of inadequate response to treatment and to
           give antibiotic according.

        2. The change of duration or the type of antibiotic in case of inadequate response to
           initial treatment in the culture group.

      Outcomes

      Primary:

        -  Resolution of asymptomatic bacteriuria as measured by colony count.

        -  Time frame: 1 week

      Secondary:

        1. Side effects of fosfomycin as, nausea, diarrhea, headache, vaginal itching, runny nose,
           back pain Side effects from other antibiotics in culture and sensitivity group

        2. Need for further treatment, either extending the course of treatment into 5 or 7 days
           regimen or changing the antibiotic in case of inadequate initial response.

        3. Need for further investigations, as urine culture and sensitivity for fosfomycin group
           in case of inadequate response on empirical treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Resolution of asymptomatic bacteriuria</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Decline in colony forming unit (CFU)/mL or absence of bacterial growth after treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for further treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Either extending the course of treatment into 5 or 7 days regimen or changing the antibiotic in case of inadequate initial response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for further investigations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Need for urine culture and sensitivity in fosfomycin group in case of inadequate response on empirical treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse drug reactions .</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse drug reactions as nausea, diarrhea, headache, vaginal itching, runny nose, back pain Side effects from other antibiotics in culture and sensitivity group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fosfomycin group (FG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-treatment Urine culture will be done then all patients will receive empirical 3 gm oral phosphomycin fosfomycin will be taken by mouth on an empty stomach i.e. 2-3 hours after meals preferably in the evening before bed time after emptying the bladder.
The contents of 1 packet of Monuril will be dissolved in a glass of water or another non-alcoholic drink and drink immediately. Do not mix with hot water. Do not take fosfomycin in its dry form.
Response to treatment will be assessed by post-treatment urine culture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Culture specific group (CG):</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-treatment Urine culture and antimicrobial sensitivity testing will be done then all patients will receive oral culture specific antibiotic therapy in the form of five days regimen.
Response to treatment will be assessed by post-treatment urine culture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>phosphomycin</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose 3 gm oral fosfomycin will be taken by mouth on an empty stomach</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fosfomycin group (FG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Culture specific antibiotic therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Culture-specific antibiotic treatment for 5 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Culture specific group (CG):</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre-treatment Urine Culture</intervention_name>
    <description>Mid-stream urine sample will be cultured and number of CFU per mL will be determined.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Culture specific group (CG):</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fosfomycin group (FG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antimicrobial sensitivity testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Susceptibility of urinary pathogens to various antimicrobials</description>
    <arm_group_label>Culture specific group (CG):</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Post-treatment urine culture</intervention_name>
    <description>Mid-stream urine sample will be cultured and number of CFU per mL will be determined.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Culture specific group (CG):</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fosfomycin group (FG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant patients from 13 weeks to 36 weeks gestation.

          2. Pus cells in urine analysis &gt;5/HPF.

          3. ≥ 105 colony-forming units (CFU) per millilitre of the same microorganisms in two
             consecutive cultures.

          4. No symptoms or sings suggestive of urinary tract infection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of any urinary symptoms as burning micturition, hesitancy

          2. Fever and loin pain.

          3. Diabetes mellitus.

          4. Known to be allergic from any of the antimicrobial ingredients.

          5. Not using any antimicrobial during the course of treatment for any other infection.

          6. Not known to have any congenital urinary anomalies.

          7. If the patient is taking medications that interact with fosfomycin as:

               -  Anorexiants (eg, phentermine) or certain sympathomimetics (eg, albuterol,
                  amphetamine, pseudoephedrine) because the risk of their side effects may be
                  increased by fosfomycin.

               -  Lithium or tetracyclines because their effectiveness may be decreased by
                  fosfomycin.

               -  Metoclopramide because it may decrease fosfomycin's effectiveness.

          8. Impaired kidney functions (creatinine's clearance is &lt;80 ml/min.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed Samy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M Samy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>mohammed mahmoud samy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lecturer in Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bacteriuria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fosfomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Infective Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

