<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03541460</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0312-14-RMB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03541460</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Israeli Multi Ethnic Centenarian Project</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMECP</acronym>
  <official_title>Detection of Epigenome Variation Associated With Longevity Among the Multi Ethnic Centenarian Population in Israel</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rambam Health Care Campus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Israel Science Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rambam Health Care Campus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will systematically assess epigenome methylation changes in participants of the
      Israel multi-ethnic centenarian study cohort, which includes citizens of Israel aged 95 years
      and older, compared to their offspring and younger controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The number of men and women reaching advanced age is rapidly increasing in developed
      countries and life expectancy has already doubled since the beginning of the last century. In
      parallel, the proportion of those who have survived to advanced old age without major health
      complications has become increasingly common. This phenomenon has led to concerted research
      efforts to understand the correlates and mechanisms of extended human longevity and healthy
      aging. For decades the public health perspective has emphasized environmental and life style
      factors as having beneficial effects on health and disease prevention in the general
      population. Important biological insights have been reached by examining the genetic basis of
      longevity and healthy aging, especially among individuals who demonstrate a favorable healthy
      aging phenotype. Epigenetics, defined as heritable changes in gene function or phenotypes, in
      the absence of DNA sequence changes, has revolutionized the concept of how genetics affect
      disease risk. Epigenetics have been shown to be associated with cancer risk and autoimmunity
      disorders. Moreover, epigenetic changes at specific sites appear to increase with age, hence
      they may serve as indices for chronological age. This background has led us to our central
      hypotheses that: i) epigenetic changes associated with healthy aging could serve as markers
      for a healthy life span, and ii) the epigenetic changes may represent one of the central
      mechanisms by which aging predisposes to many age-related diseases, and therefore affects
      healthy aging. We propose to test these hypotheses within the Israel multi-ethnic centenarian
      study cohort (which includes all citizens of Israel&gt;95 years old; an estimated 1 in 5000 of
      the population). We will systematically assess genomic methylation changes in three major
      sub-groups which signifies three major points in human lifespan: Age 60±5 years (leading age
      of onset of age associated diseases and also considered to represent the beginning of old
      age, age 80±5 years (average life expectancy in the western world), and age 100±5 years
      (exceptional longevity). Our centenarians includes 3 subgroups: SURVIVORS: those who survive
      and become centenarians in spite of early onset of cognitive impairment, functional
      disability or major age associated diseases, such as diabetes, vascular disease or cancer, at
      the beginning of old age, i.e., age of 60±5 years (thus long life span but short healthy
      lifespan). DELAYERS: those who develop age related diseases or cognitive/physical disability
      much later than the control population i.e., at the age of 80±5 years instead of 60 years
      (therefore have a longer healthy life span). DODGERS: those who fail to develop age-related
      illnesses or cognitive/physical disability throughout their life span. We will compare these
      groups to healthy controls with no family history of longevity in two reference groups,
      namely 60±5 years and 80±5 years, comparing them to the survivors and delayers groups,
      respectively. We predict that subjects will exhibit differences in methylation at sites
      distinct from each other, in contrast to healthy subjects.

      Accordingly our proposed goals are:

        1. To characterize the Israel multi-ethnic centenarian study cohort (I-MECS).

        2. To screen, catalog and annotate epigenome methylation variants in five different groups
           (a. Survivors, b. Delayers, c. Dodgers, d. 60±5YO healthy control, and e. 80±5YO healthy
           controls).

        3. To validate differential methylated loci by ranking and prioritizing using Sequenom's
           MassARRAY.

        4. Exploratory goal (depend on time and funding availability) - To establish expression
           patterns using a qRT-PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction) Roche light-cycler of the candidate
           epigenetic loci identified in Aims 1, 2 and 3 as well as specific genes (such as
           deoxyribonucleic acid methyltransferase and tumor suppressor genes) in blood cells of
           the initially screened population.

      To test our hypotheses, we propose to employ a novel high-throughput genome-wide methylation
      assay, namely HELPtag. Additionally, we will utilize a combination of epigenome-wide
      association studies (EWAS) to identify the most distinctive epigenetic loci that show
      greatest differential methylation. We will then perform multi-locus validation for
      methylation status using MassARRAY.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of alleles in genes across the genome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variations of frequency of alleles in study groups using dedicated software for genomic analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>LONGEVITY 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Older Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Demographic, health and functional data will be collected from subjects 95 years and older by means of a structured interview. Blood will be collected for laboratory and genetic testing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Younger Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Demographic, health and functional data will be collected from the children of the older subjects and other aged-matched controls by means of a structured interview. Blood will be collected for laboratory and genetic testing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Three 10 ml blood samples will be drawn into vacutainer tubes (Yellow top with anticoagulant;
      speckled top without anticoagulant). Blood samples will be analyzed for the levels of
      hemoglobin, hematocrit, white blood cell counts, and levels of glucose, insulin, albumin,
      inflammatory markers, and plasma lipids. CD34+Lin- cells will be isolated from the peripheral
      blood specimen using immuno-magnetic separation technique, followed by cell sorter.
      Mononuclear cells are separated by Ficoll-Paque density gradient, and CD34+ cells obtained by
      positive immuno-magnetic bead selection, using Macs columns (Miltenyi Biotech). The purified
      cells are then subjected to a cell sorter following immunostaining. The isolated cells will
      be cryopreserved in 10% DMSO by controlled rate freezing.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects aged 95 years and older will form the study cohort. Control group will comprise
        children of the older subjects and age-matched controls.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 95 years and older.

          -  Provide verbal consent for participation in the study.

          -  Cognitively able to provide consent and answer a structured questionnaire.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not able to provide consent for participation in the study.

          -  Impaired consciousness.

          -  Unable to communicate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>95 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tzvi Dwolatzky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tzvi Dwolatzky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>972-502061183</phone>
    <email>tzvidov@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elad Rubin</last_name>
    <phone>972-524685038</phone>
    <email>e_rubin@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rambam Health Care Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <state>North</state>
        <zip>3109601</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tzvi Dwolatzky</last_name>
      <phone>502061183</phone>
      <email>tzvidov@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elad Rubin</last_name>
      <phone>972-524685038</phone>
      <email>e_rubin@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brooks-Wilson AR. Genetics of healthy aging and longevity. Hum Genet. 2013 Dec;132(12):1323-38. doi: 10.1007/s00439-013-1342-z. Epub 2013 Aug 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23925498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evert J, Lawler E, Bogan H, Perls T. Morbidity profiles of centenarians: survivors, delayers, and escapers. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2003 Mar;58(3):232-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12634289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wojdacz TK, Hansen LL. Techniques used in studies of age-related DNA methylation changes. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2006 May;1067:479-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16804030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 10, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tzvi Dwolatzky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Geriatric Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>centenarians</keyword>
  <keyword>epigenome</keyword>
  <keyword>longevity</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy aging</keyword>
  <keyword>epigenetic</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual Participant Data (IPD) will not be shared</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

