<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03549377</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>44065</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03549377</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neural Correlates of Self-regulation on Academic Functioning</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neural Correlates of the Associations Between Sleep Functioning, Self-regulation, Academic Functioning, and Problem Behaviors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alexander Vazsonyi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objectives of the study include: 1. What are the differences in self-regulation and
      its neurophysiological and neuroanatomical correlates between college students with poor and
      excellent sleep functioning? 2. Does sleep functioning (assessed both by questionnaires and
      actigraphy), and self-control/self-regulation (questionnaire and imaging data) predict
      academic achievement and problem behaviors in college students?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Based on the Self-Control Theory, individual differences in characteristics such as
      impulsivity, risk-seeking, and self-regulation consistently predict health-compromising and
      problem behaviors as well as academic functioning and success in adolescents and young
      adults.[1] Although suboptimal self-regulation is normative in adolescence and young
      adulthood, [2] it might result in negative consequences for adolescents' and young adults'
      health and well-being, including substance use, school/college dropout, or troubles with law.
      A recent line of research suggested that self-regulation problems are associated with
      insufficient and poor sleep.[3] As adolescents and young adults frequently report poor sleep
      functioning,[4] their self-regulation abilities might be further compromised by unfavorable
      sleep functioning with consequences for youths' problem behaviors and academic success. To
      mitigate this problem, some efforts have followed to ensure that adolescents get enough
      quality sleep (e.g., delayed school start times). However, the associations between sleep
      functioning, self-regulation, academic functioning, and problem behaviors were established
      predominantly using questionnaire data. Neurophysiological correlates of these associations
      have not been extensively studied. In the proposed study, this gap in scholarship will be
      addressed by linking sleep functioning to self-regulation indicated by neuropsychological and
      neuroanatomical data, and predicting academic achievement and problem behaviors with sleep
      and self-regulation. This explorative, pilot study is a first step in efforts to understand
      the issue; it will be carried out with a college student sample (N = 48, 50% female) which
      will also have implications for future research focused on adolescents (middle and high
      school students). Pilot data will inform the development of a larger study that will include
      adolescents (middle and high school students) and will support grant applications. Results
      will have a potential for prevention /intervention programs and policy targeting youth, such
      as school start times setting. This study will be carried out as a collaboration between the
      Department of Family Sciences at the University of Kentucky and the Department of Human
      Development and Family Studies at the Texas Tech University. Data will be collected following
      the same procedures described in this application both at the University of Kentucky and
      Texas Tech campuses. Research team at the Texas Tech University has submitted their own
      Institutional Review Board (IRB) application that is now being reviewed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) Blood oxygenation level dependent (BOLD) responses for Stop Signal Reaction Time Task (SSRT) Stop Signals</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of functional magnetic resonance imaging reactivity of the whole brain while performing a Stop Signal Reaction Time Task</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of fMRI BOLD responses for a Go-NoGo Continuous Performance Task (CPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of functional magnetic resonance imaging reactivity of the whole brain while performing a Go-NoGo Continuous Performance Task</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of brain structural connectivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of brain structural connectivity as measured by diffusion tensor imaging and analyzed using tract-based spatial statistics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of brain structure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences of brain structure as determined by voxel based morphometry of structural magnetic resonance imaging data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in sleep time preferences</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Morningness-eveningness Questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in hours of sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional studyUp to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quantity</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in low self-control</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Low Self-Control Scale (LSC)
Low self-control scale (24 items) measures low self-control.
The total score ranges from 1 to 5.
Five subscales called impulsivity, simple tasks, risk seeking, physical activities, self-centered, and temper, each provide subscale score ranging from 1 to 5.
Higher values indicate higher lower self-control, in other words, worse outcomes.
A total score is developed by averaging all 24 items across all subscales. Subscale scores also represent the averaged responses to their corresponding items.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in sensation seeking and impulsivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Zuckerman Impulsivity and Sensation Seeking Scale
Impulsivity and Sensation Seeking Scale (19 items) measures impulsivity and sensation seeking.
Total score ranges from 0 to 19. Impulsivity (i.e., one of the two subscales) score ranges from 0 to 8 (8 items), whereas Sensation Seeking score ranges from 0 to 11 (11 items).
For total as well as for each subscale scores, higher values indicate more impulsivity and sensation seeking, respectively.
Total and subscale scores are computed by summing the responses (19, 11, and 8 items respectively).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in internalizing behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Weinberger Adjustment Inventory</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in deviance/externalizing subscales</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Normative Deviance Scale, Short Form
Normative Deviance Scale-Short Form (21 items); the scale measures involvement in deviant and norm-violating behaviors.
Total scores range from 1 to 5. Seven subscale scores (i.e., vandalism, alcohol use, drug use, school misconduct, general deviance, theft, assault) each range from 1 to 5, 3 items each.
Higher scores indicate greater deviance (more frequent involvement), in other word, worse outcome.
A total score, as well as subscale scores, are computed by averaging responses of the corresponding items.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in GPA/SAT/ACT Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Grade point average (GPA)/Scholastic Aptitude Test (SAT)/American College Test (ACT) Score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Academic Dishonesty Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in school attitudes</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in academic concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Academic Concentration Measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in academic aspirations and expectations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Academic Expectations and Aspirations</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in school attitudes</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>School Attitudes Assessment Survey</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in Flanker Inhibitory Control and Attention Test, Dimensional Change Card Sort Test, List Sorting Working Memory Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 45 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>NIH toolbox Cognition Battery</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in Flanker Inhibitory Control and Attention Test, Dimensional Change Card Sort Test, Picture Sequence Memory Test,</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>NIH toolbox Cognition Battery</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in commission errors in Balloon Analogue Risk Task (BART), , omission errors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Balloon Analogue Risk Task (BART)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rested versus sleep deprived group differences in commission errors in a Go-NoGo CPT, omission errors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following selection for inclusion based on prescreen, cross-sectional study</time_frame>
    <description>Go/NoGo continuous performance task (CPT)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Self-Control</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rested</arm_group_label>
    <description>Based on Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, participants scoring in the top 10-20% will be assigned to the rested group and will experience deception as part of the delayed gratification task</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep-deprived</arm_group_label>
    <description>Based on Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, participants scoring in the bottom 10-20% will be assigned to the sleep-deprived group and will experience deception as part of the delayed gratification task</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deception</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be deceived during delayed gratification task.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rested</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep-deprived</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study sample will consist of 24 healthy college students (12 males and 12 females)
        between ages 18 - 24 years.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy college-age youth between the ages of 18 and 24 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Gross impairment of vision or hearing

          -  Inability to read and follow written instructions

          -  Physical, neurological, or concurrent psychiatric impairments

          -  Regular intake of psychotropic medication (such as methylphenidate used to treat
             Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), antidepressants, or anti-anxiety
             medication)

          -  A history of head injury that resulted in loss of consciousness/a history of brain
             surgery/or seizures

          -  A current/past history of smoking and/or alcohol or drug abuse (i.e., five or more
             drinks in one sitting or 15 drinks or more during a week for men, and four drinks on
             one occasion or eight drinks over the course of a week for women; additionally,
             regular drug use, including marijuana)

          -  Current pregnancy

          -  Any metallic objects in your body (such as braces, pacemakers, surgical devices,
             piercings that cannot be removed etc.) Enrollment of the subjects will start in May
             2018 and will be finished by the end of December 2018.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander T Vazsonyi, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottfredson MR, Hirschi T. A general theory of crime. Stanford: Stanford University Press; 1990.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinberg L, Albert D, Cauffman E, Banich M, Graham S, Woolard J. Age differences in sensation seeking and impulsivity as indexed by behavior and self-report: evidence for a dual systems model. Dev Psychol. 2008 Nov;44(6):1764-78. doi: 10.1037/a0012955.</citation>
    <PMID>18999337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Owens JA, Dearth-Wesley T, Lewin D, Gioia G, Whitaker RC. Self-Regulation and Sleep Duration, Sleepiness, and Chronotype in Adolescents. Pediatrics. 2016 Dec;138(6). pii: e20161406. Epub 2016 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27940688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wheaton AG, Jones SE, Cooper AC, Croft JB. Short Sleep Duration Among Middle School and High School Students - United States, 2015. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2018 Jan 26;67(3):85-90. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6703a1.</citation>
    <PMID>29370154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alexander Vazsonyi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Endowed Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sleep</keyword>
  <keyword>Academic functioning</keyword>
  <keyword>Problem behaviors</keyword>
  <keyword>College age youth</keyword>
  <keyword>Self-regulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Problem Behavior</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan at this time</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

