<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03546049</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-PUMa-3-12-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03546049</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound-guided Percutaneous Biliary Drainage Versus Endoscopic Ultrasound-guided Biliary Drainage</brief_title>
  <acronym>PUMa</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Multi-site Study of Ultrasound-guided Percutaneous Biliary Drainage and Endoscopic Ultrasound-guided Biliary Drainage With Implantation of a Self-expanding Metal Stent in Patients With Malignant, Distal Bile Duct Obstruction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Theresienkrankenhaus und St. Hedwig-Klinik GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Heidelberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Theresienkrankenhaus und St. Hedwig-Klinik GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective multi-site study of ultrasound-guided percutaneous biliary drainage and
      endoscopic ultrasound-guided biliary drainage with implantation of a self-expanding metal
      stent in patients with malignant, distal bile duct obstruction (PUMa-study)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In a recent systematic review and meta-analysis about the efficacy and safety of endoscopic
      ultrasound-guided biliary drainage (EUBD) in comparison with percutaneous transhepatic
      biliary drainage (PTBD), there was no difference in technical success between the two
      procedures, but PTBD was associated with a lower level of clinical success, a higher level of
      post-procedural adverse events and a higher rate of re-interventions. The authors concluded
      that EUBD should be favored for biliary drainage when endoscopic retrograde
      cholangiopancreaticography (ERCP) failed or wasn´t possible to perform due to anatomical
      reasons.

      The hypothesis of this prospective multicenter study is that PTBD wasn´t performed in an
      appropriate way to compare it adequately with EUBD. The following improvements should be
      done. First, color Doppler ultrasound-guidance for cannulating the bile duct should be used
      in PTBD. The transgression of blood vessels with the risk of severe intrahepatic bleedings or
      hemobilia can be avoided, which are common adverse events in PTBDs when it is performed by
      fluoroscopic guidance. Second, the access to the bile duct from the left side of the liver
      should be favored. The access from the right liver side causes more adverse events such as
      biliary effusion or pneumothorax, as well as more patient discomfort and pain. Third,
      implantation of the self-expanding metal stent should be performed in the first session as a
      one-step procedure. This has the advantage that no further re-intervention is necessary after
      insertion of an external or an external/internal drainage, an outcome which can cause further
      adverse events such as bile duct leak along the catheter, biliary ascites or catheter
      dislocation. Fourth, stent release should be performed under endoscopic luminal guidance. In
      this way, the positioning and the correct expansion of the distal tip of the metal stent can
      be observed directly in comparison with the stent release which is only controlled by
      fluoroscopic guidance.

      On the other hand, EUBD should be performed in its best manner (special metal stents
      included) with the three techniques that are usually necessary to perform a successful EUBD:
      EUS-guided antegrade transpapillary drainage, EUS-guided transhepatic drainage and EUS-guided
      choledochal drainage.

      The study focuses on patients with malignant distal (infra-hilar) bile duct obstruction.

      It is presumed that the technical and clinical success rate is equal (non-inferiority) but
      the adverse event rate, the number of re-interventions and the number of days of
      hospitalization may differ between the two interventions. An adequate number of cases (106
      patients in each intervention, drop outs included) should be recruited to calculate relevant
      statistical differences.

      Furthermore, patients will be followed over six months after the intervention to calculate an
      estimated survival analysis (with and without palliative chemotherapy).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>prospective, non-randomized multicenter study (each center performs the intervention which can do best)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical success</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute after injection of a radiocontrast agent into the expanded metal stent</time_frame>
    <description>Successful implantation of a self-expanding metal stent to drain the obstructed bile duct, measured by the successful drainage of the radiocontrast agent by the metal stent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical success</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease of bilirubin level on more than a half of the initial value</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events caused by the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after successful implantation of the metal stent</time_frame>
    <description>Number of re-interventions (PTBD or EUBD) that are necessary in the follow up (for example due to due stent occlusion or stent migration) after successful stent implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>The day of the performed procedure (24 h), usually from 10 minutes up to 180 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of biliary drainage procedure (US-guided percutaneous biliary drainage or EUS-guided biliary drainage) in minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>The day of the first PTBD or EUBD is counted as day 1 of hospital stay. The day of the discharge from the hospital is counted as the last day of hospital stay. An average 7 to 14 days is estimated.y.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay from the day of the first intervention (PTBD or EUBD) to the the day of discharge (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival time</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow up of six months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from the day of intervention to the death of the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">216</enrollment>
  <condition>Bile Duct Obstruction, Extrahepatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>US-guided percutaneous biliary drainage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The initial percutaneous transhepatic puncture of the bile duct is performed by ultrasound guidance with a Chiba-needle (0.7 mm). After injection of a radiopaque contrast media into the bile duct system, the malignant extrahepatic bile duct stenosis can be visualized by fluoroscopic guidance (digital remote-controlled fluoroscopy device). Then a 0.018 inch guide wire is introduced and proceeded beyond the tumor stenosis into the duodenum. Next, the Chiba needle is exchanged by a 5 F catheter and the 0.018 inch guide wire is exchanged by a 0.035 inch guide wire. After dilatation of the hepatic access route with bougies up to 12 F, a self-expandable metal stent is introduced. The placement of the metal stent is controlled by endoscopic luminal guidance (gastroscope or duodenoscope).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-guided biliary drainage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The initial transluminal puncture of the bile duct is performed by endoscopic ultrasound guidance (longitudinal echoendoscope) with an 19 G access needle. After injection of a radiopaque contrast media into the bile duct system, the malignant extrahepatic bile duct stenosis can be visualized by fluoroscopic guidance. Then, a 0.035 inch guide wire is introduced into the bile duct. After dilatation of the transluminal access route with a balloon catheter, a self-expandable metal stent is introduced as an antegrade biliary drainage, a transhepatic biliary drainage or a choledochal biliary drainage. The placement of the metal stent is controlled by fluoroscopic and endoscopic luminal guidance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>US-guided percutaneous biliary drainage</intervention_name>
    <description>Device: metal stent. The self-expandable metal stent is implanted percutaneously by a transhepatic access route.
The metal stent is partially covered or non-covered (in cases in which the gallbladder is not removed).
Length: 6-10 cm. Diameter: 8-10 mm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>US-guided percutaneous biliary drainage</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WallFlex™ Biliary RX Stents Boston Scientific</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS-guided biliary drainage</intervention_name>
    <description>Device: metal stent. The transluminal (transgastric, transduodenal or transenteric) implanted self-expandable metal stent is released via echoendoscope.
The metal stent is partially covered or non-covered (in cases in which the gallbladder is not removed) or mixed covered (one half covered, one half non-covered). The mixed covered stent is used for the transhepatic access.
Length: 6-10 cm. Diameter: 8-10 mm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-guided biliary drainage</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WallFlex™ Biliary RX Stents Boston Scientific</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inoperable, malignant disease with extrahepatic bile duct obstruction (infra- hilar)

          -  ERCP was not successful or wasn´t possible due to anatomical reasons (for example
             status post-gastrectomy)

          -  At least twofold elevated bilirubin level (&gt; 2mg/dl)

          -  Histologically verified malignant disease

          -  Abdominal ultrasound was performed

          -  Computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging of the abdomen was performed

          -  A written consent was given

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Relevant blood coagulation disorder (Quick &lt; 50%, Partial thromboplastin time &gt; 50
             sec., thrombocytes &lt; 50/nl)

          -  Extrahepatic cholangiocellular carcinoma (Klatskin tumor) Bismuth II-IV or
             intrahepatic cholangiocellular carcinoma

          -  Operable, malignant disease or disease which can be cured by chemotherapy (for example
             aggressive Non Hodgkin-lymphoma)

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Participation in another trial concerning PTBD or EUBD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anja Sander, Dr.M.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institut für Medizinische Biometrie und Informatik Abteilung Medizinische Biometrie, Heidelberg University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Schmitz, Dr.med.</last_name>
    <phone>00496214245575</phone>
    <email>d.schmitz@theresienkrankenhaus.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jochen Rudi, Prof.Dr.med.</last_name>
    <phone>00496214244631</phone>
    <email>j.rudi@theresienkrankenhaus.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tertiary referral hospital: Theresienkrankenhaus und St. Hedwig Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <zip>68165</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Schmitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00496214245575</phone>
      <email>d.schmitz@theresienkrankenhaus.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jochen Rudi, MD PD</last_name>
      <phone>00496214245937</phone>
      <email>j.rudi@theresienkrankenhaus.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel Schmitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharaiha RZ, Khan MA, Kamal F, Tyberg A, Tombazzi CR, Ali B, Tombazzi C, Kahaleh M. Efficacy and safety of EUS-guided biliary drainage in comparison with percutaneous biliary drainage when ERCP fails: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Gastrointest Endosc. 2017 May;85(5):904-914. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2016.12.023. Epub 2017 Jan 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28063840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bapaye A, Dubale N, Aher A. Comparison of endosonography-guided vs. percutaneous biliary stenting when papilla is inaccessible for ERCP. United European Gastroenterol J. 2013 Aug;1(4):285-93. doi: 10.1177/2050640613490928.</citation>
    <PMID>24917973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Artifon EL, Aparicio D, Paione JB, Lo SK, Bordini A, Rabello C, Otoch JP, Gupta K. Biliary drainage in patients with unresectable, malignant obstruction where ERCP fails: endoscopic ultrasonography-guided choledochoduodenostomy versus percutaneous drainage. J Clin Gastroenterol. 2012 Oct;46(9):768-74. doi: 10.1097/MCG.0b013e31825f264c.</citation>
    <PMID>22810111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khashab MA, Valeshabad AK, Afghani E, Singh VK, Kumbhari V, Messallam A, Saxena P, El Zein M, Lennon AM, Canto MI, Kalloo AN. A comparative evaluation of EUS-guided biliary drainage and percutaneous drainage in patients with distal malignant biliary obstruction and failed ERCP. Dig Dis Sci. 2015 Feb;60(2):557-65. doi: 10.1007/s10620-014-3300-6. Epub 2014 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>25081224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharaiha RZ, Kumta NA, Desai AP, DeFilippis EM, Gabr M, Sarkisian AM, Salgado S, Millman J, Benvenuto A, Cohen M, Tyberg A, Gaidhane M, Kahaleh M. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided biliary drainage versus percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage: predictors of successful outcome in patients who fail endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography. Surg Endosc. 2016 Dec;30(12):5500-5505. Epub 2016 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27129552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee TH, Choi JH, Park do H, Song TJ, Kim DU, Paik WH, Hwangbo Y, Lee SS, Seo DW, Lee SK, Kim MH. Similar Efficacies of Endoscopic Ultrasound-guided Transmural and Percutaneous Drainage for Malignant Distal Biliary Obstruction. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2016 Jul;14(7):1011-1019.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2015.12.032. Epub 2015 Dec 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26748220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sportes A, Camus M, Greget M, Leblanc S, Coriat R, Hochberger J, Chaussade S, Grabar S, Prat F. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided hepaticogastrostomy versus percutaneous transhepatic drainage for malignant biliary obstruction after failed endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography: a retrospective expertise-based study from two centers. Therap Adv Gastroenterol. 2017 Jun;10(6):483-493. doi: 10.1177/1756283X17702096. Epub 2017 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>28567118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmitz D, Grosse A, Hallscheidt P, Roseneck A, Niemeyer J, Rudi J. Color Doppler ultrasound-guided PTBD with and without metal stent implantation by endoscopic control: prospective success and early adverse event rates. Z Gastroenterol. 2015 Nov;53(11):1255-60. doi: 10.1055/s-0041-104225. Epub 2015 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26562399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu YS, Lin CY, Chuang MT, Tsai YS, Wang CK, Ou MC. Success and complications of percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage are influenced by liver entry segment and level of catheter placement. Abdom Radiol (NY). 2018 Mar;43(3):713-722. doi: 10.1007/s00261-017-1258-5.</citation>
    <PMID>28741168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Theresienkrankenhaus und St. Hedwig-Klinik GmbH</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Schmitz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical doctor, assistant medical director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ultrasound-guided percutaneous transhepatic biliary drainage</keyword>
  <keyword>endoscopic ultrasound-guided antegrade biliary drainage</keyword>
  <keyword>endoscopic ultrasound-guided transhepatic biliary drainage</keyword>
  <keyword>endoscopic ultrasound-guided choledochal biliary drainage</keyword>
  <keyword>self-expandable metal stent</keyword>
  <keyword>malignant bile duct obstruction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholestasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholestasis, Extrahepatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

