<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03549299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LSC2-II-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03549299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Allogeneic ABCB5-positive Limbal Stem Cells for Treatment of LSCD</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Interventional, Open-label, Multicenter Phase I/IIa Clinical Trial to Investigate the Safety and Efficacy of Ascending Doses of Allogeneic ABCB5-positive Limbal Stem Cells (LSC2) for the Treatment of Limbal Stem Cell Deficiency (LSCD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RHEACELL GmbH &amp; Co. KG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>FGK Clinical Research GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ticeba GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Granzer Regulatory Consulting &amp; Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RHEACELL GmbH &amp; Co. KG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this clinical trial is to investigate the efficacy (by monitoring
      neovascularization and epithelial defects) of up to four doses of the investigational
      medicinal product (IMP) LSC2 topically administered on the target eye of patients with LSCD.
      Further, safety of the IMP during and after application will be investigated (by monitoring
      adverse events [AEs]).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an interventional, open-label, phase I/IIa clinical trial to investigate the efficacy
      and safety of up to four doses of the IMP topically administered on the target eye of
      patients with LSCD. Patients will be treated in up to four ascending dose groups.

      The allogeneic investigational product LSC2 contains ABCB5-positive limbal stem cells (from
      corneal rims of cadaveric donors, expanded ex vivo, isolated and stored in a donor cell
      bank).

      The IMP will be applied on the target eye. Prior to application, the conjunctival pannus will
      be removed under general or local anesthesia.

      Patients will be followed up for efficacy for 1 year. Efficacy of the IMP will be monitored
      by assessing neovascularization and epithelial defects.

      To assess long-term safety of LSC2 one follow-up visit at Month 24 post IMP application is
      included.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be treated in up to four ascending dose groups. After the first treated patient of the first dose group (Group A) was followed for 2 weeks, a safety and tolerability assessment of the applied IMP dose will be conducted by an internal committee. The same approach applies to the second subject.
Dose escalation and recruitment of additional patients into the second dose group (Group B) will depend on the safety and tolerability of the IMP in Group A. A safety and tolerability assessment will be conducted after the last treated patient of the first dose group (Group A) was followed for 12 weeks.
The same approach applies to Group C and D.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate at 12 months after IMP application</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate at 12 months after IMP application, where response is defined as:
no or mild corneal neovascularization (no vessel penetration or vessel penetration up to 1 quadrant, without central cornea) AND
no or mild epithelial defects (no corneal erosion or ulcer are present (corneal wounds are closed) or minimal superficial staining)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of adverse event (AE) occurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>All AEs occurring during the clinical trial will be registered, documented and evaluated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate at 3 months after IMP application</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate at 3 months after IMP application, where response is defined as:
no or mild corneal neovascularization (no vessel penetration or vessel penetration up to 1 quadrant, without central cornea) AND
no or mild epithelial defects (no corneal erosion or ulcer are present (corneal wounds are closed) or minimal superficial staining)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neovascularization</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 12, month 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>Corneal neovascularization will be assessed as &quot;none&quot; (no blood vessel penetration), &quot;mild&quot; (blood vessel penetration of 1 quadrant, without central cornea involvement), &quot;moderate&quot; (blood vessel penetration of 1 quadrant, with central cornea involvement or blood vessel penetration of 2 or 3 quadrants, with or without central cornea involvement) or &quot;strong&quot; (blood vessel penetration of all quadrants, with or without central cornea involvement).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epithelial defects</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2, 4, 6, month 3, 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>Epithelial defects will be assessed as &quot;none&quot; (no corneal erosion or ulcer are present (corneal wounds are closed)) or &quot;mild&quot; (minimal superficial staining) or &quot;moderate&quot; (dense coalescent staining up to 2 mm in diameter) or &quot;strong&quot; (dense coalescent staining greater than 2 mm in diameter) by means of fluorescein staining.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ocular symptoms of pain, photophobia, burning</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2, 4, 6, 12, month 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>Photophobia and burning will be assessed as &quot;no complaint&quot; (grade 0), &quot;mild&quot; (grade 1), &quot;moderate&quot; (grade 2) or &quot;severe&quot; (grade 3).
Pain assessment will be done by the patient using a 11-point numerical rating scale ranging between no pain (zero) and worst imaginable pain (ten).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ocular inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2, 4, 6, 12, month 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>The assessment of inflammation will be categorized as present (yes) or nonexistent (no).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Corneal opacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2, 4, 6, 12, month 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>Corneal opacification will be assessed as &quot;none&quot; (no corneal opacification), &quot;mild&quot; (corneal opacification in up to 1 quadrant, without central cornea involvement), &quot;moderate&quot; (corneal opacification in 1 quadrant, with central cornea involvement or corneal opacification in 2 or 3 quadrants, with or without central cornea involvement) or &quot;strong&quot; (corneal opacification in all quadrants, with or without central cornea involvement).
Additional densitometric Pentacam® measurements are optional. Opacity values of the following ring-shaped corneal segments will be record:
0 - 2 mm, 2 - 6 mm, 6 - 10 mm, 10 - 12 mm (anterior, central and posterior corneal layer for each segment)
0 - 2 mm, 2 - 6 mm, 6 - 10 mm, 10 - 12 mm (full thickness average for each segment)
Anterior layer of the complete cornea (0 - 12 mm)
Central layer of the complete cornea (0 - 12 mm)
Posterior of the complete cornea (0 - 12 mm)
Overall cornea (0 - 12 mm, full thickness)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2, 4, 6, 12, month 6 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>Clarity of vision.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life (visual function questionnaire-25 [VFQ-25]) questionnaire to be answered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, month 12</time_frame>
    <description>A full physical examination will be performed at week 12 and abnormal physical examination results will be evaluated and reported as AEs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tonometry</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline,week 1, 3, 7 and 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs: Body temperature at Baseline, week 12, month 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Body temperature at Baseline, week 12 and month 12 will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs: Blood pressure at Baseline, week 12, month 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure at Baseline, week 12 and month 12 will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs: Heart rate at Baseline, week 12, month 12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 12, month 12</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate at Baseline, week 12 and month 12 will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Limbal Stem Cell Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 7.5 x 10^4 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of LSC2, 7.5 x 10^4 cells per patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 3.0 x 10^5 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of LSC2, 3.0 x 10^5 cells per patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 8.0 x 10^5 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of LSC2, 8.0 x 10^5 cells per patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 1.2 x 10^6 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of LSC2, 1.2 x 10^6 cells per patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LSC2</intervention_name>
    <description>Topical application of IMP on target eye</description>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 1.2 x 10^6 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 3.0 x 10^5 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 7.5 x 10^4 cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>LSC2; 8.0 x 10^5 cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Suspension of ABCB5-positive limbal stem cells in pre-filled syringe</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female patients aged 18 to 85 years

          2. Patients with secondary bilateral or unilateral LSCD (injury that caused LSCD at least
             6 months prior to inclusion)

          3. Neovascularization: Vessel penetration of at least 2 quadrants, with central cornea
             involved

          4. Patients understand the nature of the procedure and are providing written informed
             consent prior to any clinical trial procedure

          5. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative blood pregnancy test at Visit 1

          6. Women of childbearing potential must be willing to use highly effective contraceptive
             methods during the course of the clinical trial

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Compromised eyelid mobility and/or symblepharon; patient can be re-screened after
             appropriate treatment

          2. Presence of eyelid malposition; patient can be re-screened after appropriate treatment

          3. Active local ocular or systemic infection and/or inflammation. Patient can be
             re-screened after infection and/or inflammation is resolved.

          4. Tumor diseases or history of tumor disease

          5. Active ocular neoplastic disease (exclusion will be based on investigator's
             assessment)

          6. Corneal erosion or ulcer is bigger than 4 mm2; corresponding to less than 95% of
             continuous corneal epithelium. Patient can be re-screened after erosion or ulcer is
             resolved (≤ 4 mm2).

          7. Positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) 1 and/or 2 (diagnosed by serologic
             testing)

          8. Clinically significant or unstable concurrent disease or other clinical
             contraindications to stem cell transplantation

          9. History of glaucoma

         10. Contraindications to trial related procedures/substances including

               1. The surgical procedure (e.g. removing of the conjunctival pannus)

               2. Contact lens complications due to contact lens use in the proposed trial (based
                  on the Efron Grading scale for standard clinical reference for contact lens
                  complications)

               3. Tear secretion deficiency determined by Schirmer's test

               4. Allergy, sensitivity or intolerance to components/excipients of the IMP/ per
                  protocol pre-planned concomitant medications

               5. Conjunctival scarring with fornix shortening

               6. General anesthesia (in case general anesthesia is required) or local anesthesia

               7. Immunosuppression (being mandatory concomitant therapy)

         11. Intraocular pressure (IOP) of ≥30 mm Hg

         12. History or clinical signs of stroke or transient ischemic attacks

         13. Active or suspected ocular or periocular infections

         14. Active or suspected intraocular inflammation

         15. Further clinical contraindications to IMP application (exclusion will be based upon
             investigator's judgment)

         16. Current or previous (within 30 days of enrollment) treatment with another IMP, or
             participation and/or under follow-up in another clinical trial

         17. Previous participation in this clinical trial (except screening failure due to
             inclusion criterion 2 and/or exclusion criterion 1 and/or 2 and/or 3 and/or 6)

         18. Known abuse of alcohol, drugs, or medicinal products

         19. Patients unwilling or unable to comply with the requirements of the protocol

         20. Lactating women

         21. Evidence of any other medical conditions (such as psychiatric illness, physical
             examination, or laboratory findings) that may interfere with the planned treatment,
             affect the patient's compliance, or place the patient at high risk of complications
             related to the treatment

         22. Employees of the sponsor, or employees or relatives of the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gerd U. Auffarth, Prof.Dr.med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitäts-Klinikum Heidelberg, Kopfklinik, Heidelberg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christoph Ganss, Dr. med</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6221 71833</phone>
    <phone_ext>0</phone_ext>
    <email>office@rheacell.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathrin Dieter</last_name>
    <phone>+49 6221 71833</phone>
    <phone_ext>0</phone_ext>
    <email>kathrin.dieter@rheacell.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts Eye and Ear Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James Chodosh, MD, MPH</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitäts-Klinikum Heidelberg, Kopfklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gerd U. Auffarth, Prof.Dr.med.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitäts-Klinikum Jena, Augenklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <zip>07747</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Meller, Prof.Dr.med.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitäts-Klinikum Köln, Augenklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Köln</city>
        <zip>50937</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claus Cursiefen, Prof.Dr.med.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin der Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz, Augenklinik und Poliklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <zip>55131</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Norbert Pfeiffer, Prof.Dr.med.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>limbal stem cell deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>ABCB5</keyword>
  <keyword>Limbal stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>LSCs</keyword>
  <keyword>LSC</keyword>
  <keyword>allogeneic</keyword>
  <keyword>tissue engineered product</keyword>
  <keyword>phase I/IIa</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

