<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03544034</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00175392</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03544034</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Partnering With Patients for Improving Medication Safety During Transitions of Care: Implications for Work System Design</brief_title>
  <official_title>Partnering With Patients for Improving Medication Safety During Transitions of Care: Implications for Work System Design</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Texas-Arlington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project is to develop, implement, pilot evaluate, and disseminate a medication safety
      program (HomeTeam) that consolidates strategies to help patients by partnering with patients
      and their informal caregivers during transitions from hospital to home. Care transitions,
      especially from hospital to home, are high-risk periods for medication errors, and are
      frequently associated with serious adverse drug events (ADEs) and preventable readmissions.
      Older adults with multi-morbid conditions who have complex medication regimes are especially
      prone to these risks. Patients and family caregivers may experience a dramatic transition in
      roles and responsibilities immediately after hospital discharge. Patients and family
      caregivers are relatively passive recipients in their care and medication management in the
      hospital, but when patients arrive at home, patients have the primary responsibility for
      their care and medication use (with professional care providers switching to a 'supporting'
      function). Although this significant transition in the nature and intensity of patient work
      needs to be managed actively, often patients and family members are not adequately engaged
      and prepared in the hospital, and not effectively supported for safe medication use after
      hospital discharge. More specifically, patients and family members may not understand
      essential steps in the management of their condition, and have difficulty contacting
      appropriate health care practitioners for guidance. Although most organizations deploy
      multiple layers of interventions for improving care transitions, reducing postdischarge
      adverse drug events (ADEs), 30-day readmissions and emergency department (ED) visits, their
      impact to date has been small, and there remains significant and urgent need to fundamentally
      redesign the hospital-to-home care transition process. Investigators believe that one
      practical and potentially effective way for this 'much-needed' redesign is through engaging
      and supporting patients and families in safe medication use. Investigators' proposed program
      'HomeTeam' will contain evidence-based tools and methods for engaging patients and shifting
      culture towards a truly patient-centered care for medication safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The 'HomeTeam will be developed and evaluated by completing 3 specific aims:

      Aim #1: Develop components of a multi-faceted program (HomeTeam) that consolidates
      evidence-based practices in patient and family activation and engagement related to
      medication safety, with the goal to adequately and reliably support transitions from the
      hospital to the patient home &quot;work system&quot; for medication management. Inpatient stays and the
      hospital discharge periods will be targeted as opportunities in activating, engaging, and
      enabling patients and family members to improve medication safety.

      (1a) Identify evidence-based practices in patient and family activation and engagement
      related to medication safety during care transitions.

        1. b) Develop program components (e.g., action-oriented patient/ family education, improved
           medication reconciliation, patient-centered rounds, learning systems through systematic
           feedback from home care professionals)-including tools to assess, prioritize,
           streamline, and integrate existing practices- aimed at engaging patients and families
           and supporting medication use safety during care transitions from hospital to home with
           a participatory design (PD) approach.

           Aim #2: Refine and implement the HomeTeam program in two organizations (one academic,
           one community hospital), with a peer-to-peer assessment methodology to identify and
           refine patient and family engagement practices for transitional care medication safety.

        2. a) Refine HomeTeam program through participatory design approach and peer-to-peer
           assessment

      (2b) Implement and pilot test HomeTeam in all participating sites

      Aim #3: Evaluate the implementation process and the impact of the toolkit 'HomeTeam' on
      medication safety after hospital discharge. Investigators will use a pre-post design to
      evaluate the impact of the toolkit over a one year period, focusing on 65 years of age and
      older medicine patients. The primary outcome is preventable and ameliorable adverse drug
      events (ADEs) after discharge. Secondary outcomes include 30-day post-discharge readmissions
      and ED visits due to medication-related issues process improvement assessment,
      patient-reported outcomes, and toolkit adoption assessment (e.g., acceptability,
      feasibility). Qualitative methods (post-implementation interviews with clinicians and
      patient/ family members) will be used as part of the evaluation.

      Hypothesis: Investigators hypothesize that the HomeTeam Medication Safety Program will reduce
      preventable and ameliorable post-discharge 30-day ADEs in the following subpopulations: older
      adults with at least 5 medications discharged from hospital to home on (H01) anticoagulants,
      (H0b) opioids, (H0c) diabetes agents.

      The project will be conducted in two hospitals: Bayview Medical Center (academic) and Howard
      County Medical Center (community). Dissemination plans include national medication safety
      organizations (e.g., Institute for Safe Medication Practices), patient safety organizations
      (e.g., Batz Patient Safety Foundation), and professional societies (e.g., Society of Hospital
      Medicine). Different dissemination modalities are planned, including story-telling through
      social media and short videos targeted for patients and clinicians.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    not funded
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A pre-post study in two hospitals. Implementation will be done at the organization level (for all 65 and older patients admitted to hospitalist service in these two hospitals.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>No masking</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Preventable adverse drug events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Preventable ADEs are injuries that could have bee n avoided, that is, an injury judged to probably be the result of an error or a system design flaw.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ameliorable adverse drug events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Ameliorable ADEs are injuries whose severity could have been substantially reduced if different actions or procedures had been performed or followed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Patient Safety</condition>
  <condition>Adverse Drug Event</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Routine/ standard care and retrospective chart review for identifying preventable and ameliorable Adverse drug events as baseline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hometeam toolkit interventions (including improved discharge education, proactive medication safety assessment in daily rounds and handoffs, safety briefings) applied in all hospitalist services.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HomeTeam Toolkit</intervention_name>
    <description>A multi-component intervention (8S's)
Safety at home through partnership.
Safety risk assessment at the admission
Safety agenda setting for coordinating efforts among professionals to prepare patient/ family for self-management
Safety tools. Cognitive tools to support patient/family after discharge
Safety education. Enhanced Patient/ family medication safety education
Safety briefings with patient/family A mechanism to proactively address common and patient/family specific risks.
Safety through learning routines across the care continuum
Safety assessment after discharge</description>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  65 and older

          -  medicine patients

          -  hospitalized from home

          -  English speaking

          -  no cognitive problems/ can consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  surgery patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ayse Gurses</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Univ Armstrong Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Drug-Related Side Effects and Adverse Reactions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

