<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03540433</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PCI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03540433</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Observational Study on Perioperative Cognitive Trajectories (POCD Census International/PCI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of POCD-Census Prospective, International Observation Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this international, multi-centre observational study is to describe
      perioperative cognitive changes (pre-existing neurocognitive disorder [NCD], postoperative
      delirium [POD] and Postoperative Cognitive Dysfunction [POCD]) up to five years after
      elective surgery in a mixed cohort. Measurements and definitions of cognitive outcomes will
      be based on current consensus and used for further harmonization in future clinical studies
      on perioperative cognitive trajectories. This is a feasibility approach to identify an
      effective screening procedure and estimate loss to follow up rates for the planning of future
      intervention studies. Data from this trial may also serve to facilitate and implement time
      effective cognitive screening and risk stratification concerning postoperative cognitive
      decline in the anaesthesiological preoperative assessment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This international observational study on perioperative cognitive trajectories (POCD census
      international/PCI) has been designed as a pilot study to allow a peer reviewed process of
      four international test centres on measurement of perioperative acute and long-term cognitive
      outcome. Data from standard clinical treatment of 500 patients age ≥ 70 years scheduled for
      elective surgery (stratified according to preoperative assessment of frailty and monitored by
      intraoperative depth of anaesthesia) will be supplemented by guideline conform delirium-
      analgesia- and sedation screening until day 5 after surgery, I-Pad based neuropsychological
      testing [Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery - CANTAB connect]
      pre-operatively, 3 months, 1- 2- and 5 years after surgery, a paper-based verbal fluency test
      (animal naming test from Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination Revised (ACE-R)), a paper based
      test on executive function (Trailmaking Test), cognitive screening tests (Montreal Cognitive
      Assessment (MOCA) and Mini-Cog), and concomitant questionnaires to assess functional status,
      self- and by proxy rating of cognitive performance, psychological factors (depression,
      perioperative anxiety, stress, resilience and coping), social support, perioperative anxiety,
      stress, resilience and coping, as well as risk consumption of alcohol and tobacco.

      A non-surgical control group of 100 study participants who are not scheduled for surgery will
      be followed up at the same time points as the surgical cohort for scaling of cognitive data
      and definition of cut off values to define significant cognitive decline.

      Secondary outcome measures of this trial comprise levels and changes in molecular biomarkers
      involved in Alzheimer's dementia etiology sampled from spinal fluid on induction of spinal
      anaesthesia and sampled from blood in all patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 8, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative cognitive dysfunction (POCD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Neuropsychological testing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative cognitive dysfunction (POCD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Neuropsychological testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive cognitive screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Short neuropsychological testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mild Neurocognitive Disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>Definition according to DSM-V as proposed in Evered L et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of cognitive change associated with anaesthesia and surgery. Br J Anaesth, Anesthesiology, Can J Anesth, Anesth Analg, J Alz Dis, acta scandinavica anaesthesiologica (Joint Publication) 2017; Accepted, In Press. We will use an I-pad based neuropsychological test battery (CANTAB connect), and cognitive screening instruments (MOCA, Mini-Cog™ and Animal naming test on verbal fluency from ACE-R) for assessment of cognitive function, MMQ and IQ-code for self- or by proxy reported cognitive concern and ADL/IADL for assessment of functional status. Mild/major Neurocognitive Disorder measured at baseline (pre-existing NCD) 3 months and 1 year (with specifier 'POCD'), 2- and 5 years after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Neurocognitive Disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>Definition according to DSM-V as proposed in Evered L et al. Recommendations for the nomenclature of cognitive change associated with anaesthesia and surgery. Br J Anaesth, Anesthesiology, Can J Anesth, Anesth Analg, J Alz Dis, acta scandinavica anaesthesiologica (Joint Publication) 2017; Accepted, In Press. We will use an I-pad based neuropsychological test battery (CANTAB connect), and cognitive screening instruments (MOCA, Mini-Cog™ and Animal naming test on verbal fluency from ACE-R) for assessment of cognitive function, MMQ and IQ-code for self- or by proxy reported cognitive concern and ADL/IADL for assessment of functional status. Mild/major Neurocognitive Disorder measured at baseline (pre-existing NCD) 3 months and 1 year (with specifier 'POCD'), 2- and 5 years after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerobrospinal fluid biomarker for diagnosing dementia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients for spinal anesthesia who consented on lumbar puncture receive biomarkers analysis from spinal fluid (beta Amyloid 1-40, beta-Amyloid 1-42, beta-Amyloid Ratio (42/40*10), phospho-TAU, Protein 14-3-3, PRPSc, TAU (Gesamt-Tau)).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood biomarker for diagnosing dementia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients consented on blood sampling receive biomarker analysis from blood (Apolipoprotein E).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Findings of memory consultation session</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>Comorbidities will be quantified by use of Charlson Comorbidity index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Malnutrition 1</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Malnutrition is measured by the Mini Nutritional Assessment - Short Form (MNA®-SF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Malnutrition 2</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Malnutrition is measured by the Body mass index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obesity 1</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Obesity is measured by the Body mass index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obesity 2</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Obesity is measured by waist to hip ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Physical activity is evaluated by interviewing the Patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical risk</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed up during surgery, an estimated duration of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Surgical risk will be described by type and length of surgery and perioperative cardiac risk estimation as described in Anästh Intensivmed 2017; 58:349-364.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anaesthesiological Risk 1</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Anaesthesiological risk will be described by American Society of Anesthesiologists Classification (ASA Class)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anaesthesiological Risk 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed up during surgery, an estimated duration of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Anaesthesiological risk will be measured by length of anesthesia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anaesthesiological Risk 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed up during surgery, an estimated duration of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Anaesthesiological risk will be measured by type of anaesthesia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative depth of anaesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed up during surgery, an estimated duration of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Intraoperative depth of sedation will be monitored with changes in the pattern and power spectrum of EEG-raw data measured with the Masimo SedLine® brain function monitoring for Root®, Narcotrend®, BIS™ and additionally quantified by indices [e.g. PSI or BIS-index] and burst suppression ratio.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depth of sedation on the Intensive Care Unit</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of intensive care unit stay, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Sedation is measured by Richmond Agitation Sedation Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sedation on the peripheral ward</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Sedation is measured by Richmond Agitation Sedation Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Agitation on the peripheral ward</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Agitation describes a clinical state in which the patient may be impulsive and attempt to get out of bed, to wander, and to fall (which may lead to further injury or death) and attempt to remove IV lines, tubes, or catheters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative delirium rate, defined according to Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V), CAM/CAM-ICU, Nu-DESC and Chart Review.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of postoperative delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative delirium rate, defined according to Confusion assessment method - severity(CAM-S); Delirium Rating Scale Revised (DSR-R-98), Intensive Care Delirium Screening Checklist (ICDSC) and Nursing Delirium Screening Scale (Nu-DESC).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scale for patients able of pain self-assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to hospital discharge, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pain during hospital stay will be measured with the Numeric Rating Scale (NRS-V).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scales for patients unable of pain self-assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to hospital discharge, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>For patients unable of pain self-assessment (e.g. ventilated patients, patients in delirious state or patients with stroke affecting language skills) observer-rated pain scales will be applied: Behavioural Pain Scale (BPS for ventilated) and BPS-NI (for non-ventilated) patients, Critical-Care Pain Observation Tool (CPOT) during hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive care unit length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of intensive care unit stay, an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Intensive care unit length of stay describes every day spent in an ICU bed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital length of stay describes every day spent in an hospital.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perioperative Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Perioperative anxiety will be measured with APAIS preoperatively and the Faces Anxiety Scale (FAS) and during hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalized anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety will be measured with the Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-Item Scale (GAD-7)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Depression is measured by PHQ-8. Scores represent:0-5 = mild, 6-10 = moderate, 11-15 = moderately severe, 16-20 = severe depression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of sleep is measured by the Insomnia Severity Index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Routine laboratory</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to hospital discharge, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ dysfunctions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to hospital discharge, an expected average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Organ dysfunctions are evaluated according to the Clavien-Dindo classification of surgical complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective/By proxy assessment of cognitive impairment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Prescribed regular drug intake from baseline at all follow ups including perioperative application of drugs, infusions and transfusions will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be measured with the EQ-5D-5L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of dependency</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Level of dependency will be measured with with ADL/IADL, single items concerning patients' living situation and the BSSS-17 (Berlin Social Support Scales).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plausibility check variables</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Variables affecting performance of cognitive testings</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-admission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital readmission is an episode when a patient who had been discharged from a hospital is admitted again within a specified time interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Revison surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Surgery performed to replace or compensate for a failed implant or to correct undesirable sequelae of previous surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outpatient treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment outside of the hospital in an associated facility for diagnosis or treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The number of deaths in a given period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dementia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Dementia reported as clinical diagnosis based on DSM-5 criteria for major NCD either through neuropsychological evaluation at a memory clinic or as a research diagnosis based on neuropsychological test values (CANTAB/MOCA), cognitive concern (MMQ/IQCODE) and functionality (ADL/IADL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motivational incongruence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>The incongruence questionnaire (Der Inkongruenzfragebogen)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Leisure behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire on frequency of cognitively stimulating leisure activities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic variables</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Living conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to five years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Variables of adjusting</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Reading / writing weakness, hendedness, native speaker</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Frailty will be measured by Fried's criteria (Physical Frailty Phenotype), Fried et al: Frailty in older adults: evidence for a phenotype. J.Gerontol.A Biol.Sci.Med.Sci. 2001; 56: M146-M156 and evaluated in a short comprehensive geriatric assessment as decribed by Birkelbach, O. et al. Warum und wie sollte ich Frailty erfassen? - ein Ansatz für die Anästhesieambulanz. Anasthesiol. Intensivmed. Notfallmedizin Schmerztherapie 52, 765-776 (2017).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Reserve</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Level of education (years of formal training, last occupation, ISCED-2011 and crystalline intelligence [IQ-variable calculated with NART/MWT-A or other national equivalent ] will be used to evaluate cognitive reserve.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Crystalline Intelligence</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Mehrfachwahl-Wortschatz-Intelligenztest (MWT-A) and National Adult Reading Test (NART)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Previous professional activity</measure>
    <time_frame>At the beginning of the observation</time_frame>
    <description>Interview guide employment situation and previous professional activity adapted to Engstler (2017); Classification according to ISCO 08; Workload indices according to Kroll (2011)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Cognitive Deficit (POCD)</condition>
  <condition>Neurocognitive Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Surgical patients aged ≥70 years</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy subjects, aged ≥70 years, American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) I+II+III, no surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Surgical patients aged ≥70 years
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Surgical patients at Campus Virchow- Klinikum and Campus Charité Mitte

          -  Aged ≥ 70 years

          -  Informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Manifest dementia

          -  Lack of willingness to store and disseminate pseudonymized disease data as part of the
             clinical trial

          -  Lack of readiness to participate in the follow-up examinations and contact to make an
             appointment

          -  Placement in an institute under judicial or official orders (according to German drug
             Law §40 (1) 4)

          -  Persons without a permanent residence or other circumstances that call into question
             the availability by telephone or post for postoperative examination

          -  Employees of the respective study centers

          -  illiteracy

          -  Patients with a neuropsychiatric condition that limits the performance of
             neurocognitive testing

          -  Patients with hearing and / or vision problems that limit the performance of
             neuro-cognitive testing

          -  Simultaneous participation in a prospective clinical intervention study (apart from
             the desired parallel participation in the anaesthesiological study Praep-Go,
             EA1/225/19)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 30 450 55 10 01</phone>
    <email>claudia.spies@charite.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anaesthesia, St. Vincents`s Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fitzroy</city>
        <state>Melbourne</state>
        <zip>VIC 3065</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisbeth Anne Evered, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+61 407 345 540</phone>
      <email>lisbeth.evered@unimelb.edu.au</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesiology and Operative Intensive Care Medicine Berlin (CCM/CVK), Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13353</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0) 30 450 55 10 01</phone>
      <email>claudia.spies@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claudia Spies, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Friedrich Borchers, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anesthesiology and Critical Care Department, Hospital Río Hortega of Valladolid</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <zip>CP 2.47012</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>César Aldecoa Álvarez-Santullano, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+34 (0) 983420400</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anesthesiology and Intensive Care at the Department of Physiology and Pharmacology, Section for Trauma and Acute Anesthesiology at Karolinska Institute, Karolinska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Huddinge</city>
        <state>Stockholm</state>
        <zip>14186</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lars Erikkson, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+46 (0) 8-524 872 41</phone>
      <email>Lars.I.Eriksson@ki.se</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Claudia Spies</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of the Department of Anesthesiology and Operative Intensive Care Medicine (CCM/CVK)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurocognitive Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

