<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03543592</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3081987</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03543592</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Three-dimensional Power Doppler in the Diagnosis of Endometrial Lesions in Patients With Postmenopausal Bleeding</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Accuracy of Three-dimensional Power Doppler Ultrasound in the Diagnosis of Endometrial Lesions in Patients With Postmenopausal Bleeding Compared With the Endometrial Histopathology.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      100 women suffering post-menopausal bleeding will be included in the study. All the
      participants will undergo 3D Transvaginal Ultrasound to assess the endometrium and myometrium
      (for the presence of any focal lesions e.g. polypi) followed by 3D Power Doppler ultrasound
      assessment of the vascular indices: vascularization index (VI), flow index (FI) and
      vascularization-flow index (VFI) and endometrial volumes.

      The results of the ultrasound and Doppler indices will be correlated to the histopathological
      examination of specimens collected following fractional curettage or hysterectomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      100 women suffering post-menopausal bleeding (occurred after at least 12 months of
      amenorrhea) will be included in the study.

      After obtaining an informed consent entailing the explanation of the study and its aim, all
      participants will undergo the following; full history taking (including full menstrual
      history and the date of menopause), complete physical examination, laboratory investigations
      (complete blood count, liver function tests, kidney function tests and a coagulation
      profile). Baseline 2D transvaginal ultrasound will be done to measure endometrial thickness
      and to detect presence of any endometrial and myometrial focal lesions. 3D-transvaginal
      ultrasonography will be done to acquire multi-planner view of the uterine cavity and detect
      presence or absence of any cavitary or myometrial lesions and acquire endometrial volumes.
      This will be followed by 3D Power Doppler Ultrasound assessment of the vascular indices
      namely; vascularization index (VI), flow index (FI) and vascularization-flow index (VFI).

      Transvaginal sonography will be performed for all patients using Voluson 730 PRO V
      transvaginal volumetric probe transducer with frequency range of 5-8 MHz equipped with color,
      power and pulsed Doppler capabilities. First, conventional gray-scale sonography will be
      performed to obtain longitudinal and transverse sections of the uterus. Maximum endometrial
      thickness (double-layer) will be measured in the longitudinal plane with the detection of any
      focal lesions.

      For Three-Dimensional Ultrasound: Once the B - mode had been completed, three-dimensional
      images will be recorded. The volumes will be generated by the automatic rotation of the
      mechanical transducer 360 degrees. The probe will be kept steady, the patient will be asked
      to hold breath and volume mode will be switched on. With the use of the medium line density,
      the typical acquisition time will be between 4 and 10 seconds. Visualization of the
      endometrium in the three planes will be done to detect endometrial cavity. Endometrial
      margin, echogenicity and presence of intrauterine fluid will be examined to notice the
      presence of any heterogenic pattern, irregularity, asymmetry in the margin or local
      thickening denoting the presence of polyp, endometrial hyperplasia, or carcinoma. The
      myometrium will be also examined in the three planes to detect any other focal lesion e.g.
      Fibroid or Adenomyosis.

      For Power Doppler Study, the power Doppler gate will be activated for blood flow mapping of
      the endometrium and endometrial-myometrial interface (sub-endometrial area). Power Doppler
      settings will be set to achieve maximum sensitivity for detecting low velocity flow without
      noise. Once the vessels have been identified, the pulsed Doppler sample volume will be
      activated to obtain a flow velocity waveform (FVW). Vascularization index (VI), flow index
      (FI) and vascularization-flow index (VFI) will be automatically calculated from three
      consecutive FVWs. Only endometrial and endometrial-myometrial interface vessels were
      included.

      The patient will then be admitted for either a D and C operation (Endometrial curettage) or
      for Total Abdominal Hysterectomy. All removed tissues will be sent for histopathological
      examination of the endometrium or of any pathological uterine lesion. Pathological
      examination results will be correlated to ultrasound (2D and 3D) and Doppler findings,
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic performance of Vascularization index in detecting endometrial carcinoma</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours before the surgical procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Vascularization index (VI) will be correlated to pathology report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic performance of the endometrial volumes acquired by Three-Dimensional Ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours before the surgical procedure</time_frame>
    <description>endometrial volumes will be correlated to pathology report</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic performance of flow index (FI) in detecting endometrial carcinoma.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours before the surgical procedure</time_frame>
    <description>flow index will be correlated to pathology report</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the diagnostic performance of vascularization-flow index (VFI) in detecting endometrial carcinoma.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 hours before the surgical procedure</time_frame>
    <description>vascularization-flow index (VFI) will be correlated to pathology report</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Postmenopausal Bleeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 dimensional power Doppler</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 women suffering post-menopausal bleeding (occurred after at least 12 months of amenorrhea) will be included in the study and 3 dimensional ultrasonography and Doppler will be done for them</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3 dimensional ultrasonography and Doppler</intervention_name>
    <description>Three-Dimensional images will be recorded. The volumes will be generated by the automatic rotation of the mechanical transducer 360 degrees. Visualization of the endometrium and myometrium in the three planes will be done to detect endometrial cavity and any lesions. The power Doppler gate will be activated for blood flow mapping of the endometrium and endometrial-myometrial interface (sub-endometrial area). The pulsed Doppler sample volume will be activated to obtain a flow velocity waveform (FVW). Vascularization index (VI), flow index (FI) and vascularization-flow index (VFI) will be automatically calculated from three consecutive FVWs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3 dimensional power Doppler</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Post-menopausal bleeding (occurred after at least 12 months of amenorrhea)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of hormone administration in the last 6 months.

          -  Systemic diseases causing abnormal uterine bleeding as hematologic diseases and
             chronic medical diseases.

          -  Women who experienced artificial or induced menopause because of the use of tamoxifen
             or any type of hormone replacement therapy.

          -  Patients who take any anticoagulant drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>moutaz elsherbini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+2 01001588300</phone>
    <email>mizosherbini@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sally El-Attar, MSc</last_name>
    <email>dr_sally_elattar@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>kasr elaini hospital (Cairo university)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>115431</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MOUTAZ ELSHERBINI, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(+2)01001588300</phone>
      <email>mizosherbini@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>MOUTAZ ELSHERBINI, md</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Moutaz Sherbini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>assistant professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>postmenopausal bleeding</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>power doppler</keyword>
  <keyword>endometrium</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

