<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03546712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMDU/IEC/1188</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1214-2489</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03546712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Estimating Error in Locating Touch Sensation on Forearm in Healthy Middle School Going Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Standard References Norms for Tactile Localization Acuity in Upper Limb Among the Asymptomatic Middle School Children: A Normative Research</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maharishi Markendeswar University (Deemed to be University)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maharishi Markendeswar University (Deemed to be University)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tactile localization stimuli are fundamental in forearm to the somatosensory
      perception.Tactile localization reverse the touch internal organization of the forearm and in
      the normal development of children.It is helpful in quick estimation of tactile localization
      among the children in the age group, eight to thirteen years.Study design is cross-sectional
      study it is conducted from September 2017 to April 2019 and use stratified random sampling.
      subject recruitment is healthy school going children of age group between eight and thirteen
      year will be included in this study.The procedure will be explained to the children's before
      starting the test. Ascent will be obtained from the participant. Anthropometrics will be
      measured before beginning the procedure. The acuity of TL will be determined by the
      point-to-point tactile localization (PPTL) technique. For performing PPTL, the child will be
      seated and the examiner will locate a point on the participants forearm of the blinded child
      by a black pen marker. Then the child will be asked to relocate the point with the help of
      red pen marker in blindfolded state. The distance between black point and red point (in cm)
      will be noted this distance will be measure by measuring tape as the acuity of tactile
      localization. Mean of three readings will be used for estimating the normative reference
      value of tactile localization by PPTL technique.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For performing Point to Point Tactile Localization, the child will be seated and the examiner
      will locate a point on the forearm of the blinded child by a black marker pen. Then the child
      will be asked to relocate the point with the help of red marked in blindfolded state. The
      distance between black point and red point (in cm) will be noted as the acuity of tactile
      localization. 15 areas in upper limb will be selected and PPTL will be performed on them. The
      fifteen areas are, phalanges of the palmer area of the little finger (palm 1), phalanx of the
      middle finger of the Palmer area (palm 2), phalanx of the thumb area of palm (palm 3), first
      dorsal interosseous (palm 4), mid last part of the forearm (forearm 1), middle of the medial
      forearm (forearm 2), medial side of the forearm (forearm 3), the lower portion of the arm
      (arm 1), middle posterior of arm (arm 2), lateral side of upper arm (arm 3), lower portion of
      medial arm (arm 4), middle portion of arm (arm 5), the median upper arm (arm 6), lower side
      arm (arm 7), and upper side of arm (arm 8). Mean of three readings will be used for
      estimating the normative reference value of tactile localization by PPTL technique.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 4, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 3, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>distance in millimeter</measure>
    <time_frame>3 times</time_frame>
    <description>distance between black pen marker and red pen marker point measure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">365</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tactile Localization</intervention_name>
    <description>tactile localization is help to assess touch sensation</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy school going children age between eight and thirteen years without any neurological
        disease. healthy school children is able to follow commands and able to understand.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: healthy school going children, Male and female, Age between eight-13
        years, Able to understand commands, Obey simple comments

        Exclusion Criteria: neurological diseases, disease of the skin, skin rashes, Non
        cooperative child, other medical conditions that prevent the from participating in the
        study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>13 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Krati Omar, BPT, (MPT)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maharishi Markandeshwar Institute of physiotherapy and Rehabilitation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asir John Samuel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ambala</city>
        <state>Haryana</state>
        <zip>133207</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maharishi Markandeshwar Institute of physiotherapy and Rehabilitation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ambala</city>
        <state>Haryana</state>
        <zip>133207</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msksp.2017.07.007</url>
    <description>Tactile acuity testing at the neck: A comparison of methods</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinto JM, Kern DW, Wroblewski KE, Chen RC, Schumm LP, McClintock MK. Sensory function: insights from Wave 2 of the National Social Life, Health, and Aging Project. J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci. 2014 Nov;69 Suppl 2:S144-53. doi: 10.1093/geronb/gbu102.</citation>
    <PMID>25360015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ackerley R, Carlsson I, Wester H, Olausson H, Backlund Wasling H. Touch perceptions across skin sites: differences between sensitivity, direction discrimination and pleasantness. Front Behav Neurosci. 2014 Feb 19;8:54. doi: 10.3389/fnbeh.2014.00054. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24600368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Croy I, Sehlstedt I, Wasling HB, Ackerley R, Olausson H. Gentle touch perception: From early childhood to adolescence. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2019 Feb;35:81-86. doi: 10.1016/j.dcn.2017.07.009. Epub 2017 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28927641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rigato S, Banissy MJ, Romanska A, Thomas R, van Velzen J, Bremner AJ. Cortical signatures of vicarious tactile experience in four-month-old infants. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2019 Feb;35:75-80. doi: 10.1016/j.dcn.2017.09.003. Epub 2017 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28942240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harvie DS, Kelly J, Buckman H, Chan J, Sutherland G, Catley M, Novak J, Tuttle N, Sterling M. Tactile acuity testing at the neck: A comparison of methods. Musculoskelet Sci Pract. 2017 Dec;32:23-30. doi: 10.1016/j.msksp.2017.07.007. Epub 2017 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28800436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chai G, Sui X, Li S, He L, Lan N. Characterization of evoked tactile sensation in forearm amputees with transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation. J Neural Eng. 2015 Dec;12(6):066002. doi: 10.1088/1741-2560/12/6/066002. Epub 2015 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>26401550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maharishi Markendeswar University (Deemed to be University)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Asir John Samuel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor of institute of physiotherapy and rehabilitation</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acuity</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>forearm</keyword>
  <keyword>perception</keyword>
  <keyword>touch location</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>undecided</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

