<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03546322</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P30HS023558-1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30HS023558</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03546322</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Customized Registry Tool for Tracking Adherence to Clinical Guidelines for Head and Neck Cancers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Customized Registry Tool for Tracking Adherence to Clinical Guidelines for Head and Neck Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To implement and evaluate a health information technology platform designed to support the
      management of patients with head and neck cancer in an urban, publicly-funded outpatient
      setting. This is an observational study; researchers will not assign specific interventions
      to study participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to implement and evaluate a health information technology (HIT)
      registry at an urban, public delivery system. The investigators will not assign specific
      interventions to the study participants, but rather observationally assess the effect of the
      HIT registry, designed to support routine medical care, on participants.

      The investigators will use systems engineering methodologies to design, develop, and
      implement the platform. The platform will be implemented in the Otolaryngology - Head and
      Neck Surgery clinic that cares for patients with head and neck cancers. The study will assess
      patient outcomes and evaluate the time it takes for patients to progress through key
      treatment and post-treatment milestones before and after the HIT tool is implemented. The
      investigators will use models controlling for secular trend to estimate the effect of the
      tool on improving timely and successful completion of guideline-based care processes.

      The HIT platform seeks to improve the monitoring and alerting functionality of existing
      systems. Specifically, it replaces paper-based systems previously used by the clinic to
      monitor its head and neck cancer patients. It will be implemented clinic-wide for all
      patients being treated for head and neck cancers. The investigators are not assigning a
      specific intervention to patients, but rather supporting the clinic and health system in the
      development of a population management platform that improves routine care processes. The
      platform is approved for clinical use and research by the San Francisco Health Network and
      the University of California, San Francisco.

      The HIT platform users are clinicians who are responsible for monitoring patients with head
      and neck cancer and agree to partner with the investigators to improve monitoring processes.
      The clinicians involved may be asked to voluntarily participate in surveys, interviews, focus
      groups, and program evaluations. Patient medical records will be reviewed, but patients
      monitored on the registry will not be contacted by researchers.

      Procedures are in place to monitor the registry. First, quality assurance is performed by the
      research team, information technology analysts, and software engineers. This includes
      checking that data in the platform matches source data, such as data entered in the
      electronic health record. In addition, the platform users are audited on a weekly basis. A
      data dictionary defining variables used in the platform exists and is updated as needed.
      Patients will be added to the registry by a clinician if they are diagnosed with head and
      neck cancer. The research team will support the clinicians in data analysis, although this
      will be performed with population-level, de-identified data. However, if unmediated adverse
      events are identified by the research team, the research team will alert the clinicians
      immediately. The HIT platform is designed to supplement, but not replace, the existing
      electronic health record. Data on the registry will be validated with source data and users
      will still engage with the source data and electronic health record as appropriate clinically
      and operationally.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Workup and Treatment Planning - Primary Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of diagnosis to first date of treatment, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from diagnosis to initiation of treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment - Primary Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients that complete tumor board treatment recommendations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Workup and Treatment Planning - Secondary Outcome #1</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of diagnosis to presentation at tumor board, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from diagnosis to presentation at tumor board</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Workup and Treatment Planning - Secondary Outcome #2</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of diagnosis to date of dental evaluation for patients undergoing radiation treatment, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from diagnosis to dental evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Workup and Treatment Planning - Secondary Outcome #3</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of diagnosis to date of first visit with oncology clinic, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from diagnosis to first visit in oncology clinics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment - Secondary Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who complete post-treatment radiation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Loss to follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who are lost to follow-up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">802</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Registry</arm_group_label>
    <description>Head and neck cancer patients monitored on registry</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Registry</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who are diagnosed with head and neck cancer and monitored by the Otolaryngology - Head and Neck Surgery clinic at Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital and Trauma Center will be included in this group. The intervention is the implementation of a registry, designed to replace existing paper-based systems for tracking patients. All head and neck cancer patients monitored by the clinic will be included.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Registry</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with head and neck cancer monitored by the Otolaryngology - Head and Neck Surgery
        clinic at the Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital and Trauma Center
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with head and neck surgery monitored by the Otolaryngology - Head and Neck
             Surgery Clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  N/A
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Urmimala Sarkar, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital and Trauma Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>head and neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>health information technology</keyword>
  <keyword>patient safety</keyword>
  <keyword>adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>ambulatory</keyword>
  <keyword>outpatient</keyword>
  <keyword>human factors</keyword>
  <keyword>vulnerable populations</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

