<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03548298</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R-2018-3601-014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03548298</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antireflux Ablation Therapy (ARAT) for Gastroesophageal Reflux Treatment</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Antireflux Ablation Therapy (ARAT) With Hybrid-APC (Argon Plasma Coagulation) for GERD Treatment in Patients Without Hiatal Hernia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Coordinación de Investigación en Salud, Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Coordinación de Investigación en Salud, Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD) is defined as the rise of gastric or gastroduodenal
      contents above the esophagogastric junction (EGJ), generating symptoms and/or esophageal
      lesions. It is estimated a failure to treatment with PPI(proton pump inhibitor) between
      10%-40% of patients with GERD. The main disadvantages of surgical treatment include
      perforation (0-4%), bleeding (&lt;1%) and pneumothorax (0-10%), the most common late
      complication is gastric fullness, which occurs in almost all patients, approximately 25% of
      patients may experience persistent dysphagia 3 months after surgery and the most worrisome
      late complication is the need of a new surgical intervention. The aims of treatment at EGJ is
      to reduce gastroesophageal reflux contents into the esophagus. Hybrid-APC with ablation of
      EGJ (ARAT) is a new technique with could generate a scar remodeling this region and
      consequently reducing reflux disease. Our objective is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of
      ARAT in a group of patients with GERD without hiatal hernia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gastroesophageal reflux disease is a condition in which there is a rise of gastroduodenal
      contents into the esophageal lumen, causing mucosal damage. Among treatments, medications are
      the most common used ones but up to 10%-40% doesn't respond to this type of treatment.
      Surgical treatment has been considered as the gold standard; however, with complications such
      as bleeding, perforation, or dysphagia after surgery. Moreover, not all patients are
      candidates to receive this type of treatment. Based on these data, new techniques have been
      explored in order to reduce morbidity, mortality and costs in the treatment of these
      patients.

      Among different endoscopical treatments, ablation of EGJ is a new promising technique which
      can be used to perform a closure at this level throughout the scar secondary to hybrid-APC
      treatment, consequently decreasing gastroesophageal reflux. So, the aim of this study is to
      evaluate safety and efficacy of ARAT in a group of patients with confirmed GERD.

      This is a quasi experimental study that will be conducted in a tertiary care center in Mexico
      city, Mexico. In an endoscopy department at the Mexican Institute of Social Security between
      January 2018 and July 2019. Those patients diagnosed with gastroesophageal reflux who are
      candidates and who accept this type of treatment will be evaluated. Patients who meet the
      inclusion criteria will be the definitive candidates. The risks and benefits of this type of
      endoscopic treatment will be explained as well as the potential scope of this endoscopic
      alternative. We will evaluate safety and efficacy of this new procedure.

      The technique of the procedure involves ablation of the mucosa of the EGJ using Hybrid-APC
      (ARAT). The ablation field is initially marked with a Hybrid-APC. Subsequently, saline
      solution mixed with indigo-carmine is injected at the submucosa level to raise a submucosal
      bleb, followed by ablation of the mucosa along the lesser curvature. The approximate duration
      of the procedure is 40min.

      Follow-up will include objective evaluation of reflux disease with: upper endoscopy,
      manometry, pHmetry, reflux questionnaire, and need of PPI (proton-pump inhibitor) dose
      quantification.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 10, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Men and women with diagnosis of GERD confirmed by endoscopy or pHmetry, GERD questionnaire and that accept this new treatment.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of ARAT with Hybrid-APC in patients with GERD without hiatal hernia</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>The efficacy of this treatment will be defined as: The decrease of ≥ 50 percent of the total percentage of acid exposure at 24 hrs (DeMeester Score)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of ARAT with hybrid-APC in patients with GERD without hiatal hernia</measure>
    <time_frame>One Year</time_frame>
    <description>We will document any adverse event presented during or after application of ARAT therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastro Esophageal Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GERD without hiatal hernia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with GERD without hernia hiatal will receive ARAT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ARAT</intervention_name>
    <description>After confirmation of GERD, participants will undergo to ablation with Hybrid-APC (ARAT). Participant will be admitted to hospital 24 hrs before procedure. Technique consist in ablation with hybrid-APC, submucosal injection of saline solution with methylene blue at 3-4 cm from 60-70% cardias and 1 cm esophageal. After procedure they will be kept on surveillance and will be followed-up with clinical, endoscopic, esophageal manometry and pHmetry up to 1 year after procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GERD without hiatal hernia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of both sexes of age with a diagnosis of GERD and who are under medical
             treatment and who do not wish to undergo surgical treatment

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of GERD in the following way:

          -  Positive pHmetry

          -  Positive endoscopy (GERD with esophagitis of any degree) or negative

          -  Positive symptoms questionnaire for GERD

          -  Manometry without evidence of esophageal motor disorder

          -  Total or partial response to proton pump inhibitors

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who do not accept the signature of the informed consent

          -  Patients previously treated by surgery for GERD

          -  Pregnant women.

          -  Patients with hiatal hernia greater than 3 cm or Hill type IV

          -  Patients with esophageal motility disorders

          -  Patients in whom, for any reason, any antireflux surgery or endoscopic treatment has
             been contraindicated.

          -  Patients who want to undergo surgical treatment as an initial option.

          -  Patients with portal hypertension and the presence of esophageal varices

          -  Patients with hemophilia or a haematological disorder that is difficult to control
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Oscar V Hernández Mondragón, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IMSS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Medico Nacional Siglo XXI, Hospital de Especialidades</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ciudad de mexico</city>
        <zip>06720</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mezerville Cantillo Ld, Cabas Sánchez J, Contreras F, Castellanos Garcia LF, Dondis JE, Galdámez J, García-Maradiaga R, Grullón Dickson F, Jerez González LE, Mayo DiBello M, Mejía Rivas MA, Moreno Padilla P, Sánchez Hernández MA, Velasco SR, Vela MF, Valdovinos-Diaz MA, Remes-Troche JM. [Practice guideline of the Centroamerican and Carribean Association of Gastroenterology and Gastrointestinal Endoscopy for the management of gastroesophageal reflux disease]. Acta Gastroenterol Latinoam. 2014 Jun;44(2):138-53. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>25199309</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Katz PO, Gerson LB, Vela MF. Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of gastroesophageal reflux disease. Am J Gastroenterol. 2013 Mar;108(3):308-28; quiz 329. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2012.444. Epub 2013 Feb 19. Erratum in: Am J Gastroenterol. 2013 Oct;108(10):1672.</citation>
    <PMID>23419381</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bolier EA, Kessing BF, Smout AJ, Bredenoord AJ. Systematic review: questionnaires for assessment of gastroesophageal reflux disease. Dis Esophagus. 2015 Feb-Mar;28(2):105-20. doi: 10.1111/dote.12163. Epub 2013 Dec 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24344627</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hansdotter I, Björ O, Andreasson A, Agreus L, Hellström P, Forsberg A, Talley NJ, Vieth M, Wallner B. Hill classification is superior to the axial length of a hiatal hernia for assessment of the mechanical anti-reflux barrier at the gastroesophageal junction. Endosc Int Open. 2016 Mar;4(3):E311-7. doi: 10.1055/s-0042-101021. Epub 2016 Feb 10.</citation>
    <PMID>27004249</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Villa N, Vela MF. Impedance-pH testing. Gastroenterol Clin North Am. 2013 Mar;42(1):17-26. doi: 10.1016/j.gtc.2012.11.003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23452628</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wileman SM, McCann S, Grant AM, Krukowski ZH, Bruce J. Medical versus surgical management for gastro-oesophageal reflux disease (GORD) in adults. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Mar 17;(3):CD003243. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD003243.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;11:CD003243.</citation>
    <PMID>20238321</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nabi Z, Reddy DN. Endoscopic Management of Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease: Revisited. Clin Endosc. 2016 Sep;49(5):408-416. Epub 2016 Sep 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27744659</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inoue H, Ito H, Ikeda H, Sato C, Sato H, Phalanusitthepha C, Hayee B, Eleftheriadis N, Kudo SE. Anti-reflux mucosectomy for gastroesophageal reflux disease in the absence of hiatus hernia: a pilot study. Ann Gastroenterol. 2014;27(4):346-351.</citation>
    <PMID>25330784</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Manner H, Neugebauer A, Scharpf M, Braun K, May A, Ell C, Fend F, Enderle MD. The tissue effect of argon-plasma coagulation with prior submucosal injection (Hybrid-APC) versus standard APC: A randomized ex-vivo study. United European Gastroenterol J. 2014 Oct;2(5):383-90. doi: 10.1177/2050640614544315.</citation>
    <PMID>25360316</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Manner H, May A, Kouti I, Pech O, Vieth M, Ell C. Efficacy and safety of Hybrid-APC for the ablation of Barrett's esophagus. Surg Endosc. 2016 Apr;30(4):1364-70. doi: 10.1007/s00464-015-4336-1. Epub 2015 Jun 24. Erratum in: Surg Endosc. 2016 Apr;30(4):1371.</citation>
    <PMID>26104794</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GERD, Hybrid-APC, efficacy, safety</keyword>
  <keyword>ARAT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

