<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03549845</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHAP052018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03549845</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cardiovascular Health Awareness Program (CHAP) in Subsidized Social Housing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pragmatic Randomized Controlled Trial of the Cardiovascular Health Awareness Program (CHAP) in Subsidized Social Housing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to improve the cardiovascular health of seniors living in subsidized
      housing by implementing the successful community-based Cardiovascular Health Awareness
      Program (CHAP). CHAP is a patient-centred, interdisciplinary, multi-pronged, community-led
      CVD and stroke prevention and management program designed to prevent and reduce the impact of
      cardiovascular disease in older adults. The program addresses common cardiovascular disease
      risk factors, such as smoking, physical activity and poor diet by raising awareness of health
      and community resources available to encourage self-care and appropriate management of
      cardiovascular disease. A randomized controlled trial will be used to evaluate the impact of
      CHAP on healthcare utilization by older adults living in subsidized housing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to improve the cardiovascular health of seniors living in subsidized
      housing by implementing the successful community-based Cardiovascular Health Awareness
      Program (CHAP). Residents in subsidized housing are considered to be a vulnerable population
      because of their low income and tend to be in poorer health; with a multitude of chronic
      illnesses, such as cardiovascular disease (CVD) and diabetes.

      This project will build on the success of CHAP in other provinces. The program has been shown
      to reduce blood pressure and CVD-related hospitalization costs. CHAP is a patient-centred,
      interdisciplinary, multi-pronged, community-led CVD and stroke prevention and management
      program designed to prevent and reduce the impact of cardiovascular disease in older adults.
      The program addresses common cardiovascular disease risk factors, such as smoking, physical
      activity and poor diet by raising awareness of health and community resources available to
      encourage self-care and appropriate management of cardiovascular disease.

      Taking the form of a randomized controlled trial, the sample will be subsidized housing
      buildings (low income) for those aged 55 years and over. During CHAP monthly assessment
      sessions, participants will 1) complete a consent form, 2) complete a cardiovascular risk
      profile form, 3) undergo blood pressure measurement using an automated blood pressure
      measuring device, 4) receive targeted healthy lifestyle and preventive care materials, 5) be
      invited to participate in group health education sessions. Those patients identified at high
      risk will be assessed by a health professional and referred to a family physician for timely
      and appropriate follow-up.. The impact this program will have on health care utilization
      (emergency visits, cardiovascular hospitalization rates) will be measured using
      administrative databases.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 17, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pragmatic cluster randomized controlled trial with parallel intervention and control groups.
Randomization will occur at the building level (clusters) and the intervention is open to all building residents.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization Composite - Change in CVD-related emergency department visits and hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly from 1 year pre-intervention to 1 year post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Change in rate of CVD-related emergency department visits and hospitalizations by postal code from administrative databases (Building-level analysis)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization - Change in all-cause emergency department visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly from 1 year pre-intervention to 1 year post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Change in rate of all-cause emergency department visits by postal code from administrative</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization - Change in all-cause hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly from 1 year pre-intervention to 1 year post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Change in all-cause hospitalization rates by postal code from administrative data (building-level)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using EQ-5D-5L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality-Adjusted Life Years (QALYs)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year (post-intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated from EQ-5D-5L at two time points and Canadian value sets</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year (post-intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated from program cost data and health outcomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant experience of the CHAP intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year (post-intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Participant experience of the intervention will be evaluated through qualitative individual interviews and focus groups of residents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Risk - Change in blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in measured blood pressure (automated, validated device)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Risk - Change in body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in body mass index calculated from height and weight (self-reported)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Risk - Change in waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in waist circumference (measured with measuring tape)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Risk - Change in diabetes risk score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in diabetes risk score (CANRISK questionnaire)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2742</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHAP Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Cardiovascular Health Awareness Program (CHAP) intervention is an on-site drop-in, monthly, cardiovascular risk assessment program run by trained volunteers with community-led group health sessions that deliver education and information about access to community health resources. The education sessions will be delivered by national and provincial and local community organizations utilizing already developed material as much as possible, but maintaining consistency across both provinces. Health education sessions will include topics such as: Physical Activity, Healthy Eating, Stress, Tobacco Use, High Blood Pressure, Role of Pharmacist: How they can assist people, and Appropriate use of 9-1-1. This intervention will be held in a common room in selected subsidized housing buildings.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control buildings will receive usual care which will be wellness programs already present in the building prior to the RCT if these are present. Not all control buildings will have wellness programs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiovascular Health Awareness Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Cardiovascular disease prevention and health promotion</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHAP Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Building Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Approximately 50-200 apartment units

          -  Majority of residents are 55 years of age or older.

          -  Unique postal code

          -  Availability of at least one building with similar characteristics for
             matching/randomization

        Individual Inclusion Criteria

          -  Resides in a study building

          -  Aged 55 years or older

          -  Speaks and reads English or French

        Note: Younger residents will be allowed to take part in the program but their data will not
        be included in the analysis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gina Agarwal</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McMaster University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janusz Kaczorowski</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHUM (Université de Montréal)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de recherche du CHUM</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2X 0A9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthcare Utilization</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency Department</keyword>
  <keyword>Hospitalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Income</keyword>
  <keyword>Social Housing</keyword>
  <keyword>Older Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is currently no plan for individual participant data to be shared. Aggregate data will be shared upon request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

