<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03549169</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UNColombia</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03549169</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Decision Making for the Management the Symptoms in Adults of Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <acronym>TOMAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Decision Making for the Management for the Symptoms in Adults of Heart Failure: Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction. Heart failure (HF) is the most prevailing chronic illness in the world. In
      Colombia, high morbidity and mortality rates because of HF are registered, as well as a
      significant burden of symptoms, frequent hospitalizations, poor quality of life, significant
      consumption of health resources and early mortality. It is necessary to propose novel
      strategies that can change the current picture.

      Objective: determine the efficacy of an intervention centered in decision taking for the
      handling of symptoms in adults with HF who live in the department of Cordoba, Colombia.

      Hypothesis

      Primary hypothesis: the intervention Decision taking for the handling of symptoms in adults
      with HF: 1) Increases self-care.

      Secondary hypothesis: 1) reduces clinical events: emergency care and hospitalizations, 3)
      Improves quality of life related to health.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intervention: The theoretic approach of the Theory of the Specific Situation Self-care in HF
      was used for the design of the intervention.

      Supplier/dosage/duration. The intervention was given by the researcher (nurse trained in the
      intervention protocol) in three doses, each contact lasts 60 minutes. Frequency: sessions are
      given once a week during a one-month period (duration). Nurse controls are implemented after
      the intervention after one month and three months. There is also telephonic accompaniment on
      application of the participant.

      Delivery method/environment. Verbal: Individual face to face. Printed educational written
      material type brochure, outpatient clinic of a health institution.

      Methodology

      Participants: inclusion criteria: adults (over the age of 18 years), more than two months of
      having been diagnosed; functional New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II - III, left
      ventricular ejection fraction reduced (&lt;40%). Cognitive state conservation (Lobo cognitive
      mini exam - MEC-35). Absence or low co-morbidity (Charlson index). Exclusion criteria: acute
      HF, advanced HF

      Sample: The study was designed to have a 90% output, (alpha = 0.05), an expected difference
      of 0.5 in the outcome score of the management and maintenance evaluation in both groups, a
      standard deviation of outcome scores of 1.0, a correlation average between the first and the
      second evaluation of 0.2 and a rate of wear of 20%. Therefore, the required final sample size
      was 124 (62 per group - theoretic sample).

      Pilot study: 176 adults with HF were recruited. 114 entered the study. 62 were excluded (did
      not meet the inclusion criteria (n=39), did not want to participate (=14), other reasons
      (n=9)).

      Randomization. Table of random numbers without repetition. The Participants randomly assigned
      to the control group CG (n=57) received the standard attention, including standard education
      given by attention providers, and the ones assigned to the intervention group IG (n=57)
      received the intervention protocol.

      Information collection (research assistant). The study registers information in the following
      time points: beginning (base line), follow up after a month (outpatient appointment), follow
      up after 3 months (outpatient appointment). The study is classified as simple blind; the
      research assistant, who is in charge of applying the instrument measuring the effect of the
      intervention, will remain blinded during the whole study regarding the group assigned to each
      participant.

      Risk control. Compliance with methodological recommendations used to guarantee reliability
      and validity of the research studies proving a clinic intervention for behavioral changes. A
      plan is being contemplated that includes goals and strategies to monitor and counter possible
      threats to internal and external validity.

      Ethical aspects. Compliance with universal ethical principles for research on humans,
      according to international ethical guidelines - CIOMS, national regulations, informed consent
      and deontological Nursing responsibilities in Colombia.

      Analysis framework Excel database - SPSS Program analysis

        1. Descriptive analysis of the total sample and by groups (intervention and control):
           absolute and relative frequency distributions; median and standard deviation.

        2. Data normality analysis: Kolmogorov-Smirnov test Statistical analysis for independent
           samples a) difference of proportions: X2, b) difference of means: t for student, c)
           difference of medians: U test of Mann - Whitney. In all cases a statistic significance
           will be assumed if the value p &lt; 0.05.

        3. Intrasubject and intergroup analysis: ANOVA with repeated measurements.

        4. Hypothesis proof: W of Mauchly test. When the sphericity premise is fulfilled, test F
           will be used.

        5. Analysis of possible confusion and/or interaction effect.

             1. Stratified analysis: X2 of Mantel-Haenszel (M-H),

             2. Logistic regression analysis. Stepwise method. Minimum change % considered as
                favorable (≥20=1, ≤19=0).

        6. Analysis of the magnitude of the intervention's effect. Improvement of at least 20% of
           the score on the scale, with the analysis principle of the intention of trying. The
           absolute increase in benefit and the necessary number for treatment (NNT) will be
           calculated afterwards.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 4, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The participants are assigned to two groups during the duration of the study. A group receives the standard attention and the intervention protocol and the other group only the standard attention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A research assistant (nurse trained in the measurement instruments) applies the instruments that allow the evaluation of the outcomes of interest: self-care, quality of life regarding health and follow up of clinical events: emergency attention, hospitalization, death by HF.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-care of heart failure index</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline self-care for heart failure index at 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Self-Care of Heart Failure Index is a measure of self-care defined as a naturalistic decision making process involving the choice of behaviors that maintain physiologic stability and the response to symptoms when they occur. A score of ≥70 can be used as the cut-point to judge self-care adequacy.
We strongly discourage users from calculating a total, combined SCHFI score. Instead, the data will be far more useful if the scales (maintenance, management, confidence) are used individually. Each scale is standardized to a score of 100.
Use the following formula to compute a standardized:
Maintenance: (sum of Section A items - 10) * 3.333 Management: (sum of Section B items - 4) * 5 Confidence: (sum of Section C items - 6) * 5.56</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Results in health</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline results in health at 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Emergency admissions, hospitalization, death by heart failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life related to health</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baselineQuality of life related to health punctuation at 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire is one of the most widely used health-related quality of life questionnaires for patients with heart failure (HF). It provides scores for two dimensions, physical and emotional, and a total score. Comprising 21 items rated on six-point Likert scales, representing different degrees of impact of HF on quality of life related to health, from 0 (none) to 5 (very much). It provides a total score (range 0-105, from best to worst HRQoL), as well as scores for two dimensions, physical (8 items, range 0-40) and emotional (5 items, range 0-25). The other eight items (of the totalof 21) are only considered for the calculation of the total score.
The Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire has been translated into and validated in Spanish - Colombia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TOMAS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention centered on taking decisions for management of symptoms in adults with Heart Failure. Includes 3 doses (self-care maintenance, symptom perception and symptom management) and 4 strategies are developed: knowledge of the situation, experience and abilities in decision taking and compatibility with personal values.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard or regular attention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Regular attention is centered on education for therapeutic adherence</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TOMAS</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention focused on decision making for the management of symptoms aimed at adults with heart failure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TOMAS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Regular attention</intervention_name>
    <description>Regular attention focused on education for therapeutic adherence</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard or regular attention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Adults (over 18 years of age).

          -  More than two months of having been diagnosed.

          -  Conserves cognitive state.

          -  Absence or low co-morbidity.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Confirmed diagnose of acute HF.

          -  Confirmed diagnose of advanced HF.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>EUGENIA HERRERA GUERRA, NURSE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eugenia Herrera Guerra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montería</city>
        <state>Córdoba</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://doi.org/10.1097/JCN.0b013e3181b4baa0</url>
    <description>Riegel, B., Lee, C. S., Dickson, V. V., &amp; Carlson, B. (2009). An Update on the Self-Care of Heart Failure Index. The Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing, 24(6), 485-497</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://journals.lww.com/jcnjournal/Abstract/2016/05000/The_Situation_Specific_Theory_of_Heart_Failure.7.aspx</url>
    <description>Riegel, B., Dickson, V., &amp; Faulkner., K. (2016). The Situation-Specific Theory of Heart Failure Self-Care: Revised and Updated. The Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing, 31(3), 226-235. doi: 10.1097/JCN.0000000000000244</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eugenia Del Pilar Herrera Guerra</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Nurse</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptoms management</keyword>
  <keyword>Selft-care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Publication of articles derived from the main study</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>They will be available when the main study ends</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>They will be available when the main study ends It can be requested by email</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

