<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02103270</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AADCRC-STAN-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02103270</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Peanut Oral Immunotherapy Study: Safety, Efficacy and Discovery</brief_title>
  <acronym>POISED</acronym>
  <official_title>Single Center, Placebo Controlled Clinical Study in Desensitization vs Tolerance Induction in Peanut Allergy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Determine whether peanut oral immunotherapy (OIT) induces clinical tolerance as assessed
      after the initial 3 month avoidance period

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  Identify the basic immune mechanisms which can explain the differences in the effects of
           OIT in desensitized vs. tolerant individuals.

        -  Determine whether immune monitoring measurements reflecting underlying mechanisms during
           OIT can be used to predict responses to OIT in individual subjects and, ultimately, to
           improve the safety and efficacy outcomes in peanut OIT protocols.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All arms will undergo an Initial Dose Escalation (IDE) Day and updosing regimen with a
      maintenance phase of OIT or placebo to a maximum of 4,000 mg protein daily, as peanut flour,
      in the OIT groups, and to a maximum of an equivalent amount of oat flour for the placebo
      group. After maintenance is achieved, all subjects will begin performing DBPCFCs (staged so
      as to ensure safety) at Week 104 and every 13 weeks thereafter. At Week 104, individuals that
      reach criteria will, based on the randomization that was done at the start of the study,
      either stop therapy with peanut and be switched to oat flour, or will be maintained on 300 mg
      peanut protein per day and all placebo subjects will decrease to the equivalent volume of oat
      flour (approximately 600 mg oat flour) to optimize the blind. All subjects will be evaluated
      every 13 weeks thereafter with DBPCFCs until the end of study.

      Individuals in Arm A will be defined as &quot;clinically tolerant&quot; if there is no clinical
      reactivity at the Week 104 and Week 117 DBPCFC. Clinical reactivity is defined as any
      reaction ≥ Grade 1 based on the Bock's Criteria. Individuals in Arm A who meet the definition
      of &quot;clinically tolerant&quot; will continue to avoid peanut protein (i.e. continue on 600 mg per
      day of oat flour) as long as each subsequent DBPCFC (performed every 13 weeks until end of
      study) shows no clinical reactivity.

      Individuals in Arm B will be defined as &quot;desensitized&quot; to a minimum of 300 mg per day of
      peanut protein if they show no clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).

      Individuals in Arm C will be defined as &quot;natural loss of responsiveness&quot; if they show no
      clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).

      We plan to identify the basic immune mechanisms which can explain the differences in the
      effects of OIT in individuals who do or do not become clinically tolerant and to determine
      whether immune monitoring can predict the safety and efficacy outcomes in peanut OIT
      protocols.

      After initial screening and enrollment, there are three phases of the study:

        -  Dose escalation and Build up Phase

        -  Maintenance phase

        -  Tolerance and Desensitization Testing phase Overall, 120 subjects who are eligible will
           undergo the Initial Dose Escalation Day. Subsequent updosing visits will occur every 2
           weeks as a part of the build-up phase. They will continue to updose until they reach
           4,000 mg protein daily, which is the maximum maintenance amount of protein. We expect
           active OIT treatment subjects to reach 4,000 mg of peanut protein between 44-78 weeks.

      Treatment and Desensitization Failures:

      A treatment failure will be defined as a) failure to reach 1.5 mg peanut protein (single
      dose) during the Initial Dose Escalation Day or b) failure to reach 1,000 mg peanut protein
      by week 104.

      Subjects who do not meet the criteria at Week 104 and who demonstrate clinical reactivity
      will be considered desensitization failures.

      If Arm B subjects demonstrate clinical reactivity in any DBPCFC from Week 117 to end of
      study, they will be considered desensitization failures.

      If Arm A subjects demonstrate clinical reactivity (≥Grade 1, in any DBPCFC from Week 117 to
      end of study, they will be considered tolerance failures.

      Treatment failures, desensitization failures, and tolerance failures will be unblinded (both
      participant and research staff) and will be followed until the end of the study at the
      specified study visits but will not undergo DBPCFCs. They will be considered in statistical
      analyses of the intent-to-treat population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 25, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Passing the Week 117 DBPCFC to Peanut</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 117 - Number of participants with no clinical reactivity to peanuts</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants with No Clinical Reactivity to Peanuts</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Passing the DBPCFC to Peanut at Week 130</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 130</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary endpoint: Passing the DBPCFC to peanut at 130 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Peanut Allergy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oat Flour 600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm C that is maintained on placebo (oat flour) throughout the study; this arm will receive 600 mg oat flour beginning on week 104. This will be true even if a subject in the placebo group meets criteria at week 104</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein 4,000mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm A on peanut OIT until week 104 (maintenance) and once meeting criteria [i.e. 1) on OIT treatment for minimum 104 weeks, 2) taking daily maintenance dose of 4,000 mg protein for at least 13 weeks, 3) no severe reactions to home dosing from Week 91-Week 104, and 4) no reactions at the Week 104 DBPCFC] will be assigned to avoid peanut (i.e. will consume 600 mg oat flour daily) and will proceed to tolerance and desensitization phase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm B on peanut OIT until week 104 and once meeting criteria specified in description of Arm A, will be assigned to be maintained on 300 mg peanut protein (i.e. 600 mg peanut flour) daily and will proceed to the tolerance and desensitization testing phase.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peanut Protein 4,000mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm A will be defined as &quot;clinically tolerant&quot; if there is no clinical reactivity at the Week 104 and Week 117 DBPCFC. Clinical reactivity is defined as any reaction ≥ Grade 1 based on the Bock's Criteria (Appendix 4). Individuals in Arm A who meet the definition of &quot;clinically tolerant&quot; will continue to avoid peanut protein (i.e. continue on 600 mg per day of oat flour) as long as each subsequent DBPCFC (performed every 13 weeks until end of study) shows no clinical reactivity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein 4,000mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Peanut Flour</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oat Flour</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm C will be defined as &quot;natural loss of responsiveness&quot; if they show no clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oat Flour 600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein 4,000mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peanut Protein 300 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm B will be defined as &quot;desensitized&quot; to a minimum of 300 mg per day of peanut protein if they show no clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peanut Protein 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Peanut Flour</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject and/or parent guardian must be able to understand and provide informed consent
             and/or assent as applicable.

          -  Peanut-allergic subjects between the ages of 7-55 years old.

          -  Sensitivity to peanut allergen as documented by a positive skin prick test result (5
             mm or greater diameter wheal relative to negative control) within 10 months preceding
             enrollment.

          -  Allergy to peanut based on a double-blind placebo-controlled oral food challenge
             (DBPCFC) (see Appendix 4 for scoring details) failed at a dose ≤500 mg with peanut
             protein within 10 months preceding enrollment.

          -  All female subjects of child-bearing potential will be required to provide a blood or
             urine sample for pregnancy testing that must be negative one week before being allowed
             to participate in the study.

          -  Subjects must plan to remain in the study area during the trial.

          -  Subjects must be trained on the proper use of the EpiPen (see Appendix 6) to be
             allowed to enroll in the study.

          -  Subjects with other food allergies must agree to eliminate these other food items from
             their diet so as not to confound the safety and efficacy data from the study.

          -  Use of birth control by female subjects of child-bearing potential

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability or unwillingness of a participant to give written informed consent or comply
             with study protocol

          -  History of cardiovascular disease

          -  History of other chronic disease (other than asthma, atopic dermatitis, or rhinitis)
             requiring therapy (e.g., heart disease, diabetes) that, in the opinion of the
             Principal Investigator, would represent a risk to the subject's health or safety in
             this study or the subject's ability to comply with the study protocol

          -  History of eosinophilic gastrointestinal disease

          -  Current participation in any other interventional study

          -  Subject is on 'build-up phase&quot; of immunotherapy to another allergen (i.e., has not
             reached maintenance dosing)

          -  Severe asthma (2007 NHLBI Criteria Steps 5 or 6) at time of enrollment

          -  • Use of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) treatment modalities (e.g.,
             herbal remedies) for atopic and/or non-atopic disease within 90 days preceding Initial
             Dose Escalation Day (IDED) or at any time after the IDED

          -  Inability to discontinue antihistamines for the initial day of escalation, skin
             testing or OFCs

          -  Use of omalizumab within the past six months, or current use of other non-traditional
             forms of allergen immunotherapy (e.g., oral or sublingual) or immunomodulator therapy
             (not including corticosteroids)

          -  Use of β-blockers (oral), angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors,
             angiotensin-receptor blockers (ARB) or calcium channel blockers

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  History of sensitivity to oat

          -  History of severe anaphylaxis to peanut with symptoms including hypotension requiring
             fluid resuscitation and/or the need for mechanical ventilation

          -  Use of investigational drugs within 24 weeks of participation

          -  Past or current medical problems or findings from physical assessment or laboratory
             testing that are not listed above, which, in the opinion of the investigator, may pose
             additional risks from participation in the study, may interfere with the participant's
             ability to comply with study requirements or that may impact the quality or
             interpretation of the data obtained from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kari C Nadeau, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sean N. Parker Center for Allergy Research at Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mountain View</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>April 2, 2019</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kari Christine Nadeau, MD PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peanut Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 24, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/70/NCT02103270/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 9, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/70/NCT02103270/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 1, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/70/NCT02103270/SAP_002.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>All arms undergo an Initial Dose Escalation (IDE) Day and updosing regimen with a maintenance phase of OIT or placebo to a maximum of 4,000 mg protein daily, as peanut flour, in the OIT groups, and to a maximum of an equivalent amount of oat flour for the placebo group.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>At Week 104, individuals that reach criteria will, based on the randomization, either stop therapy with peanut and be switched to oat flour or will maintain on 300 mg peanut protein per day and all placebo subjects decreased to the equivalent volume of oat flour to optimize the blind. All subjects were evaluated every 13 weeks with DBPCFCs.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Peanut-4000</title>
          <description>Oral immunotherapy with peanut discontinuation arm</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Peanut-300</title>
          <description>Oral immunotherapy with low dose peanut continuation arm</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Placebo Comparator: Oat Flour 600 mg</title>
          <description>Placebo received oat flour</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="60"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="35"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="25"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="51"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="29"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="24"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Peanut 4000</title>
          <description>Oral immunotherapy with peanut discontinuation arm</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Peanut 300</title>
          <description>Oral immunotherapy with low dose peanut continuation arm.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Placebo Comparator: Oat Flour 600 mg</title>
          <description>Placebo received oat flour</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B4">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="60"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="35"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="25"/>
            <count group_id="B4" value="120"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Inter-Quartile Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10" lower_limit="7" upper_limit="49"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="11" lower_limit="7" upper_limit="47"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11" lower_limit="7" upper_limit="53"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="11" lower_limit="7" upper_limit="53"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="39"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="39"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="23"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="81"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="51"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="34"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="109"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="60"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="35"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="25"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="120"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Passing the Week 117 DBPCFC to Peanut</title>
        <description>Number of Participants with No Clinical Reactivity to Peanuts</description>
        <time_frame>Week 117 - Number of participants with no clinical reactivity to peanuts</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Peanut 4000</title>
            <description>Oral immunotherapy with peanut discontinuation arm</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Peanut 300</title>
            <description>Oral immunotherapy with low dose peanut continuation arm.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Placebo Comparator: Oat Flour 600 mg</title>
            <description>Placebo received oat flour</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Passing the Week 117 DBPCFC to Peanut</title>
          <description>Number of Participants with No Clinical Reactivity to Peanuts</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="60"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="35"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="25"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Passing the DBPCFC to Peanut at Week 130</title>
        <description>Secondary endpoint: Passing the DBPCFC to peanut at 130 weeks</description>
        <time_frame>Week 130</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Peanut 4000</title>
            <description>Arm A on peanut OIT until week 104 (maintenance) and once meeting criteria on OIT treatment for minimum 104 weeks, 2) taking daily maintenance dose of 4,000 mg protein for at least 13 weeks, 3) no severe reactions to home dosing from Week 91-Week 104, and 4) no reactions at the Week 104 DBPCFC] will be assigned to avoid peanut (i.e. will consume 600 mg oat flour daily) and will proceed to tolerance and desensitization phase.
Peanut Protein 4,000mg: Arm A will be defined as &quot;clinically tolerant&quot; if there is no clinical reactivity at the Week 104 and Week 117 DBPCFC. Clinical reactivity is defined as any reaction ≥ Grade 1 based on the Bock's Criteria (Appendix 4). Individuals in Arm A who meet the definition of &quot;clinically tolerant&quot; will continue to avoid peanut protein (i.e. continue on 600 mg per day of oat flour) as long as each subsequent DBPCFC (performed every 13 weeks until end of study) shows no clinical reactivity.
Oat Flour: Arm C will be defined as &quot;natural l</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Peanut 300</title>
            <description>Arm B on peanut OIT until week 104 and once meeting criteria specified in description of Arm A, will be assigned to be maintained on 300 mg peanut protein (i.e. 600 mg peanut flour) daily and will proceed to the tolerance and desensitization testing phase.
Oat Flour: Arm C will be defined as &quot;natural loss of responsiveness&quot; if they show no clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).
Peanut Protein 300 mg: Arm B will be defined as &quot;desensitized&quot; to a minimum of 300 mg per day of peanut protein if they show no clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Placebo Comparator: Oat Flour 600 mg</title>
            <description>Arm C that is maintained on placebo (oat flour) throughout the study; this arm will receive 600 mg oat flour beginning on week 104. This will be true even if a subject in the placebo group meets criteria at week 104
Oat Flour: Arm C will be defined as &quot;natural loss of responsiveness&quot; if they show no clinical reactivity at DBPCFCs (week 117 to end of study).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Passing the DBPCFC to Peanut at Week 130</title>
          <description>Secondary endpoint: Passing the DBPCFC to peanut at 130 weeks</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="60"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="35"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="25"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
      <desc>Safety outcomes determined by Common Terminology Criteria.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Peanut-4000</title>
          <description>Oral immunotherapy with peanut discontinuation arm</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Peanut-300</title>
          <description>Oral immunotherapy with low dose peanut continuation arm</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Placebo Comparator: Oat Flour 600 mg</title>
          <description>Placebo received oat flour</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="60"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="60"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>eosinophilic esophagitis</sub_title>
                <description>One peanut-0 participant developed eosinophilic esophagitis and his symptoms resolved after termination from the study.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="60"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>anaphylaxis with moderate hypotension</sub_title>
                <description>The other SAE occurred following an up-dosing in the peanut-300 arm. The participant engaged in vigorous exercise and experienced anaphylaxis with moderate hypotension which was reversed after one dose of injectable epinephrine.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="60"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>1</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="60"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr Andres Alvarez Pinzon, Director of Regulatory Affairs and Translational Medicine</name_or_title>
      <organization>The Sean N. Parker Center for Allergy Research at Stanford</organization>
      <phone>9544465645</phone>
      <email>andresap@stanford.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

