<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04472377</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HT19-HPV-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04472377</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Agreement of hrHPV Detections Between Vaginal Self-sampling and Physician Sampling</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluate the Agreement of High-risk Human Papillomavirus (hrHPV) Detections Between Vaginal Self-sampling Using &quot;Hygeia Touch Self Sampling Kit for Women&quot; and Physician Sampling</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hygeia Touch Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hygeia Touch Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hygeia Touch Inc. has developed a safe and comfortable vaginal self-sampling device &quot;Hygeia
      Touch Self Sampling Kit for Women&quot; to self-collect the vaginal samples for high-risk Human
      Papillomavirus (hrHPV) detection.

      This clinical trial aimed to evaluate the agreement of hrHPV detections between vaginal
      self-sampling using &quot;Hygeia Touch Self Sampling Kit for Women&quot; and physician sampling, and
      these results will be applied for TFDA registration approval.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 29, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two samples were collected, one by the study investigator using a cervical swab and another one by the patient using the study device and after viewing the instruction video. The latter was blinded to the laboratory personnel.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The identification of self sampled specimens is blinded to the laboratory personnel.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Agreement in the detection of high-risk HPV type in physician collected specimen and patient sampled specimen.</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of the &quot;agreement&quot;. The &quot;agreement&quot; is defined as either (1) presence of any high-risk HPV type in physician collected specimen, and the patient sampled specimen, or (2) absence of high-risk HPV in physician collected specimen and the patient sampled specimen.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Agreement in HPV detection between physician collected sample and self-collected sample</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of the &quot;agreement&quot;. The &quot;agreement&quot; is defined as either (1) presence of any HPV type in physician collected specimen, and the patient sampled specimen, or (2) absence of any HPV in physician collected specimen and the patient sampled specimen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of a valid specimen, according to the presence of the beta-globin gene in the self-collected specimen, and compares to the physician-collected specimen</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of the presence of the beta-globin gene. The ratio could be calculated between self-collected and physician-collected specimens.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any adverse event resulted from collecting the specimen</measure>
    <time_frame>within one month after sample collection</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants with any adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Papillomavirus Infection</condition>
  <condition>Self Sampling</condition>
  <condition>Vaginal Discharge</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>study population</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We enroll a total of 1,200 women, as follows,
120 cases with no history or current cervical intraepithelial lesion or malignancy.
180 cases with a history of abnormal Pap test including ASCUS, CIN1, or atypical glandular cell.
240 cases with a history of atypical squamous cells favor HSIL, dysplasia cannot exclude HSIL, CIN2, CIN3, cervical carcinoma in situ, squamous cell carcinoma, atypical glandular cells favor neoplasm, adenocarcinoma in situ, or cervical adenocarcinoma.
240 cases with current ASCUS, CIN1, or atypical glandular cell.
420 cases with current abnormal Pap test as atypical squamous cells favor HSIL, dysplasia cannot exclude HSIL, CIN2, CIN3, cervical carcinoma in situ, squamous cell carcinoma, atypical glandular cells favor neoplasm, adenocarcinoma in situ, or cervical adenocarcinoma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self sampling kit for collecting discharge from vaginal fornix</intervention_name>
    <description>A device to collect exfoliative cells from vaginal fornix that can self-operated with ease and comfort.</description>
    <arm_group_label>study population</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hygeia Touch Self Sampling Kit for Women</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Woman with a uterine cervix, i.e., with no previous total hysterectomy or radiotherapy
        for cervical tumor. The woman who received subtotal hysterectomy is allowed.

        2. Signed informed consent. 3. Fit any one of the following conditions,

          1. with no history or current cervical intraepithelial lesion or malignancy.

          2. with a history of abnormal Pap test including atypical squamous cells of undetermined
             significance, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia grade 1, or atypical glandular cell.

          3. with a history of atypical squamous cells favor high-grade squamous intraepithelial
             lesion, dysplasia cannot exclude high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion, cervical
             intraepithelial neoplasia grade 2, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia grade 3,
             cervical carcinoma in situ, squamous cell carcinoma, atypical glandular cells favor
             neoplasm, adenocarcinoma in situ, or cervical adenocarcinoma.

          4. with current atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance, cervical
             intraepithelial neoplasia grade 1, or atypical glandular cell.

          5. with current abnormal Pap test as atypical squamous cells favor high-grade squamous
             intraepithelial lesion, dysplasia cannot exclude high-grade squamous intraepithelial
             lesion, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia grade 2, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia
             grade 3, cervical carcinoma in situ, squamous cell carcinoma, atypical glandular cells
             favor neoplasm, adenocarcinoma in situ, or cervical adenocarcinoma.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of total hysterectomy

          2. Pregnant

          3. Current cervicitis that requires therapy

          4. Received treatment for cervical lesion within 90 days

          5. Had undergone radiotherapy or is receiving radiation over the uterus, cervix or vagina

          6. Had sexual activity without a condom in 48 hours

          7. Excessive vaginal discharge, either in the ovulation period or due to inflammation

          8. is undergoing local therapy with an intravaginal tablet or residual drug in the
             vaginal canal

          9. during mense
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Detection of HPV in female genital tract.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hung-Hsueh Chou, MBBS, VS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hung-Hsueh Chou, MBBS, VS</last_name>
    <phone>+886 3 3281200</phone>
    <phone_ext>8614</phone_ext>
    <email>ma2012@cgmh.org.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yu Hsuan Wu, MS</last_name>
    <phone>+886 2 2394 1052</phone>
    <email>arielwu@hygeiatouch.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaohsiung Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung</city>
        <zip>833161</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hao Lin, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>+886 7 7317123</phone>
      <email>haolin@adm.cgmh.org.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taichung Veterans General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <zip>40705</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chien-Hsing Lu, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+886 4 23592525</phone>
      <phone_ext>5801</phone_ext>
      <email>chlu@vghtc.gov.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Linkou Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <zip>33305</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hung-Hsueh Chou, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>+886 3 3281200</phone>
      <phone_ext>8614</phone_ext>
      <email>ma2012@cgmh.org.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cervical screening</keyword>
  <keyword>human papillomavirus</keyword>
  <keyword>self sampling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Papillomavirus Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaginal Discharge</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>For clinical trial participation.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>3 months after accepting for report publication</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>to the public</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

