<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04478734</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUNTIAM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04478734</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of the Combined Use of Thiamine and Biotin in Patients With Huntington's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>HUNTIAM</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicentric Trial on the Use of Combined Therapy of Thiamine and Biotine in Patients With Huntington´s Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ciberned (Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluate the safety and tolerability of combined oral thiamine with biotin therapy in
      patients with Huntington´s disease in mild to moderate stages and it is intended to evaluate
      the biological effect of the treatment in the central nervous system of these patients using
      as a main biomarker the increase in the level of thiamine monophosphate (TMP) in
      cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) of these patients with Huntington Disease (HD) during a follow-up
      period of one year.

      The hypothesis we propose could be the combination therapy of thiamine and biotin,
      administered orally in doses equivalent to those administered in congenital thiamine deficit
      disorders are problems of modifying the natural history of the disease avoiding the
      progression of symptoms and even being able to improve the existing symptomatology
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The assessment of the safety and tolerability of the combined oral thiamine and biotin
      therapy in patients with HD will be performed by:

        -  Periodic clinical examination and anamnesis directed by a neurologist during
           face-to-face and non-contact visits.

        -  The collection of adverse effects during interviews of face-to-face visits to assess
           tolerability.

        -  Analytical monitoring with hematological and biochemical control (hepatic and renal
           function) during the dose escalation period, subsequently being this periodic control
           every 3 months, from signature of informed consent until the end the follow up.

      The evaluation of the efficacy of treatment with combined oral thiamine and biotin therapy in
      increasing thiamine monophosphate (TMP) levels in CSF of patients with HD is to be performed
      by:

        -  The determination of thiamine levels: free, TMP thiamine pyrophosphate (TTP) in
           cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) and blood of patients at the beginning and after the end of
           it.

        -  Comparison of thiamine levels (free, TMP and TTP) between the start and end of the study
           in CSF and serum of patients with HD.

      The evaluation of the efficacy of the treatment with combined oral thiamine and oral biotin
      therapy in neurodegeneration produced in HD will be performed by:

        -  Measurement of neurofilament light chain protein (NfL) levels in CSF and blood.

        -  The score obtained in the motor and Total Functional Capacity (TFC) section of the
           UHDRS.

        -  Measurement of bradykinesia through quantitative motion measurement techniques
           (Quantitative motor assesment, Q-motor). Q-motor assesment relies on three-dimensional
           position sensors and pre-calibrated force translators, for standardized movement
           recording. This measurement will be made to patients in the pre-selection visit,
           randomization and quarterly face-to-face visits.

        -  Score on the quality of life scale (SF-36)).

        -  Variation in the overall clinical impression scale of the patient and the examiner.

        -  Measurement of the change in the volume of the caudate nucleus, white substance and
           cortical thinning, comparing these values with those described in prospective registries
           of patients with HD.

      For the evaluation of secondary and exploratory objectives, a sample size was considered
      considered a high treatment effect (&gt; 60%) given the remarkable therapeutic effect of therapy
      in patients with Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease (BTBGD)and in animal
      experimentation models of the studies carried out by the researchers of the Severo Ochoa
      Molecular Biology Center (CBMSO). Therefore, we would expect to detect a treatment effect
      size of 60-70% in a 12-month follow-up, in a population of 24 patients with mild-moderate HD,
      considering a statistical power of 80% and an alpha error of 0, 05.

      The collection of demographic data and related to the different variables analyzed during the
      study will be done through an electronic data collection notebook. The notification of
      adverse effects, severity and relationship with study medication will be done through an
      electronic data collection notebook.

      The statistical analysis will be carried out using the statistical program IBM SPSS
      Statistics v.24.0. Linear regression will be used when the variables are quantitative (eg,
      scale measurements, thiamine levels in CSF, NfL levels in CSF, among others), logistic or
      multinomial regression when the variables are group (binary or multinomial).

      Magnetic resonance imaging performed during the study will be processed with specific
      neuroimaging programs for volumetry, diffusion and cortical thickness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events as assessed by clinical examination anamnesis and Analytical monitoring with hematological and biochemical control (hepatic and renal function)</measure>
    <time_frame>From signature of informed consent form, at all scheduled visits, to end of follow up week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Patient´s condition and emergence of comorbidity by clinical examination and anamnesis directed by a neurologist, by measuring of vital signs (blood pressure, heart rate,breath rate weight and height)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of the efficacy of treatment with combined oral thiamine and biotin therapy in increasing thiamine monophosphate (TMP) levels in CSF of patients with HD</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0) and visit 8 (week 48)</time_frame>
    <description>Determination and comparison of thiamine levels (free, TMP and TTP) in CSF and blood at the beginning and the end of the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of treatment due to increased levels of NfL in neurodegeneration produced in HD</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24, week 48 and week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of neurofilament levels in CSF and blood, and the assessment of the increase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24 and week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the score of the quality of life scale (SF-36)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of bradykinesia</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24 and week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate changes in the score of Huntington's disease rating scale &quot;(UHDRS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of bradykinesia through quantitative movement measurement techniques</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24 and week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate changes in the score of Quantitative-motor assessments (Q-motor)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative movement measurement techniques and evaluate change in bradykinesia</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24 and week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the score of Global Impression - Severity scale-S (CGI-C)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of CSF neurofilament levels in patients with HD</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24, week 48 and week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of NfL levels in CSF and blood</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of neuroimaging progression markers in patients with HD</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (week 0), week 24, week 48 and week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the change in the volume of the caudate nucleus, white substance and cortical thinning, comparing these values with those described in prospective registries of patients with HD</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Huntington Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate doses</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>moderate doses of combination therapy applying the minimum average dosage of thiamine and biotin used in patients with BTBGD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High doses</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>high doses of the combination therapy applying the average standard dosage of thiamine and biotin used in patients with BTBGD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moderate doses of Thiamine y Biotin</intervention_name>
    <description>Thiamine 600 mg every day + Biotin 150mg every day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate doses</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>moderate doses of combination therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High doses of Thiamine y Biotin</intervention_name>
    <description>Thiamine 1200 mg every day + Biotin 300mg every day</description>
    <arm_group_label>High doses</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>high doses of the combination therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of legal age with manifest Huntington's disease with motor symptoms (chorea,
             dystonia or bradykinesia) and/or neuropsychiatric; and genetic confirmation of a
             number of repetitions of the CAG triplet in the HTT gene (coding for HTT) greater than
             or equal to 39

          -  Women of childbearing age should obtain a negative result in the serum or urine
             pregnancy test at the screening visit. They must also accept the use of appropriate
             contraceptive methods during the course of the clinical trial and men who have a
             partner of childbearing age, accept the use of contraceptive methods

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dependent patients for basic activities of daily life (ABVD) or with a degree of
             severe cognitive impairment that prevents participation/follow-up in the study (UHDRS
             TFC &lt;7).

          -  Patients with active psychosis at the time of clinical evaluation.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding patients.

          -  Advanced-grade renal failure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pablo Mir Rivera, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Biomedicine of Seville (IBiS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clara M. Rosso Fernández</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virgen del Rocío University Hospital Research and Clinical Trials Unit</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pablo Mir Rivera, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 955923039</phone>
    <email>pmir@us.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Clara M. Rosso Fernández, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 955012144</phone>
    <email>claram.rosso.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virgen del Rocío Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <state>Seville</state>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clara M Rosso Fernández, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34 955012144</phone>
      <email>claram.rosso.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pablo Mir Rivera, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34955923039</phone>
      <email>pmir@us.es</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pablo Mir Rivera, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>thiamine and biotine</keyword>
  <keyword>combination therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Huntington Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thiamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Biotin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Once the study is completed and the data processed, the results will be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>After the primary completion date and submit results information</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>collaborating researchers</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

