<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04479761</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20-0312</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04479761</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sensory Integration of Auditory and Visual Cues in Diverse Contexts</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sensory Integration of Auditory and Visual Cues in Diverse Contexts Given Age, Vestibular Hypofunction and Hearing Loss</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The New York Eye &amp; Ear Infirmary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      More than 1/3 of adults in the United States seek medical attention for vestibular disorders
      and hearing loss; disorders that can triple one's fall risk and have a profound effect on
      one's participation in activities of daily living. Hearing loss has been shown to reduce
      balance performance and could be one modifiable risk factor for falls. Patients with
      vestibular hypofunction tend to avoid busy, hectic, visually complex, and loud environments
      because these environments provoke dizziness and imbalance. While the visual impact on
      balance is well known, less is known about the importance of sounds for balance. In search
      for a possible mechanism to explain a relationship between what we hear and balance control,
      some studies suggested that sounds may serve as an auditory anchor, providing spatial cues
      for balance, similar to vision. However, the majority of these studies tested healthy adults'
      response to sounds with blocked visuals. It is also possible that a relationship between
      hearing loss and balance problems is navigated via an undetected vestibular deficit. By
      understanding the role of auditory input in balance control, we can be better equipped to
      help this large portion of the population who seek medical attention for vestibular disorders
      and hearing loss. Therefore, there is a critical need for a systematic investigation of
      balance performance in response to simultaneous visual and auditory perturbations, similar to
      real-life situations.

      To answer this need, our team used recent advances in virtual reality technology and
      developed a Head Mounted Display (HMD) protocol of immersive environments, combining specific
      manipulations of visuals and sounds, including generated sounds (i.e., white noise) and
      real-world recorded sounds (e.g., a train approaching a station). This research will answer
      the following questions: (1) Are sounds used for balance and if yes, via what mechanism? (2)
      Do individuals with single-sided hearing loss have a balance problem even without any
      vestibular issues? (3) Are those with vestibular loss destabilized by sounds? To address
      these questions, the following specific aims will be investigated in individuals with
      unilateral peripheral vestibular hypofunction (n=45), individuals with single-sided deafness
      (n=45), and age-matched controls (n=45): Aim 1: Establish the role of generated and natural
      sounds in postural control in different visual environments; Aim 2: Determine the extent to
      which a static white noise can improve balance within a dynamic visual environment. We expect
      to clarify the role of sounds in the control of balance. This contribution will be
      significant because the mechanism underlying possible link between hearing loss and falls
      needs to be better understood. Our work will inform the development of improved balance
      assessments, specifically whether balance tests need to include postural responses to sounds.
      Hearing status may need to be considered as a potential indicator of increased fall risk. Our
      work will also inform the development of new rehabilitation combining sounds and visuals in
      different contexts. HMDs and headphones affordability and portability will allow future
      translation to a clinical setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>We will have 3 groups: people with unilateral vestibular loss, people with single-sided hearing loss and controls. All groups will go through the same procedure.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sway Directional Path (DP) anterior-posterior [AP] and medio-lateral [ML] in mm</measure>
    <time_frame>Will be measured during all 60 seconds scenes</time_frame>
    <description>Total path length of the position curve for a selected direction. DP is a measure of postural steadiness and is used as an indication of how much static balance was perturbed with a given sensory manipulation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sway Area (mm2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Will be measured during all 60 seconds scenes</time_frame>
    <description>confidence ellipse surface containing 95% of all center-of-pressure positions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">135</enrollment>
  <condition>Vestibular Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Reality</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be wearing a virtual reality headset and observing 2 types of scenes: abstract (a display of stars) or contextual (a subway station).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Visual and Auditory Cues</intervention_name>
    <description>Within each scene there will be 2 levels of visual input (static or dynamic) combined with 3 levels of sounds (static, none or dynamic). Postural responses to each combination will be evaluated in order to assess the role of generated and natural sounds in postural control and whether static sounds can improve balance within dynamic virtual environments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual Reality</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Group 1: Unilateral peripheral vestibular hypofunction and normal hearing, e.g., vestibular
        neuritis.

        a complaint of head motion provoked instability or dizziness affecting their functional
        mobility and quality of life at least 1 positive finding indicating unilateral vestibular
        hypofunction on the following clinical tests: head thrust, subjective visual vertical and
        horizontal, post head shaking nystagmus, spontaneous and gaze holding nystagmus a score of
        at least 16 (mild handicap) on the Dizziness Handicap Inventory (DHI).

        meeting at least 1 of the following diagnostic criteria: 25% or above unilateral weakness
        on caloric testing; Low gain on Video Head Impulse Test (vHIT) &lt;.8; Ocular Vestibular
        evoked myogenic potential (oVemp) amplitude asymmetry greater than 34%; Cervical (cVemp)
        amplitude asymmetry greater than 40%. Normal hearing, defined as an unaided PTA &lt; 26dB HL
        (0.5-4 kHz) bilaterally.

        Group 2: Acquired severe / profound unilateral hearing loss (i.e., single-sided deafness
        [SSD]), no evidence of retrocochlear pathology on MRI and no active complaint of dizziness
        (DHI score &lt; 10) or imbalance. SSD will be defined as having an unaided pure-tone average
        (PTA) of hearing thresholds at 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 kHz in the affected ear &gt; 70 dB HL and
        normal hearing in the contralateral ear. Normal hearing will be defined as an unaided PTA &lt;
        26dB HL (0.5-4 kHz). This is considered healthy hearing according to the World Health
        Organization.

        Group 3: Healthy controls who are matched for age and sex with group 1.

        For those above 65 years of age, symmetric age-related hearing loss (ARHL) in the mild
        hearing loss range, specifically an unaided PTA &lt; 40 dB (0.5-4KHz) will be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        a medical diagnosis of peripheral neuropathy; lack of protective sensation based on the
        Semmes-Weinstein 5.07 Monofilament Test; conductive hearing loss or air bone gap; visual
        impairment above 20/63 (NYS Department of Motor Vehicle cutoff for driving) on the Early
        Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) Acuity Test that cannot be corrected with
        lenses; pregnancy; any neurological condition interfering with balance or walking (e.g.
        multiple sclerosis, Parkinson's disease, stroke); acute musculoskeletal pain at time of
        testing; currently seeking medical care for another orthopaedic condition; inability to
        read an informed consent in English, Spanish or Chinese. Control participants will be
        excluded for any positive finding on the vestibular diagnostic testing or history of
        vestibular symptoms (dizziness, vertigo) or any hearing loss that does not fit ARHL as per
        the criteria specified above.

        Patients with vestibular hypofunction will be excluded if they are diagnosed with an
        unstable peripheral lesion, e.g., Meniere's Disease, Perilymphatic Fistula, Superior Canal
        Dehiscence, or Acoustic Neuroma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Eye and Ear Infirmary of Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University Physical Therapy Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anat V Lubetzky, PT, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>212-998-9195</phone>
      <email>anat@nyu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deafness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vestibular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

