<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04472832</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AG348-C-014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04472832</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of Mitapivat (AG-348) in Healthy Adult Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Randomized, Four-Period, Crossover Food-Effect Study With Mitapivat Sulfate In Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Agios Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Agios Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, randomized, single-dose, double-blinded, 4-period, crossover study to
      evaluate the pharmacokinetics, safety, and tolerability of mitapivat in healthy adult
      participants under fasted and fed (high-fat meal) conditions. Secondary objectives include
      evaluating the effect of mitapivat on electrocardiogram (ECG) parameters, including
      concentration-QT interval corrected for heart rate (C-QTc) analysis under fasted conditions.
      The study will include a 28-day screening period, four 7-day treatment periods. Participants
      will receive a follow-up telephone call within 28 (±1) days after the last dose of study
      drug.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 17, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration Versus Time Curve (AUC) From Time 0 to the Last Quantifiable Concentration (AUC0-T) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC From Time 0 Extrapolated to Infinity (AUC0-Inf) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Reach Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Tmax) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Terminal Elimination Half-Life (T1/2) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Oral Clearance (CL/F) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Terminal Elimination Rate Constant (Λz) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent Volume of Distribution (Vd/F) for Mitapivat Under Fasted and High-Fat Meal Conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative Bioavailability (Frel; AUC0-Inf [fed]/AUC0-Inf [fasted]) for Fed Treatment Following Administration of Mitapivat 100-mg Dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at various timepoints through 120 hours postdose within each 7-day period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and which does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Abnormalities in Clinical Laboratory Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical laboratory tests will include hematology, serum chemistry, and urinalysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Abnormalities in Vital Sign Measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure, pulse rate, respiratory rate, and body temperature.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Abnormalities in 12-lead Electrocardiogram (ECG) Results</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Abnormalities in Physical Examination Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single oral dose of mitapivat-matching placebo under fasted conditions on Day 1 of each of 4 periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single oral dose of mitapivat 100 milligrams (mg) and placebo under fasted conditions on Day 1 of each of 4 periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single oral dose of mitapivat 100 mg and placebo under high-fat meal conditions on Day 1 of each of 4 periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a single oral dose of mitapivat 300 mg under fasted conditions on Day 1 of each of 4 periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for Treatment A</intervention_name>
    <description>6 tablets matched to mitapivat tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mitapivat 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Two 50-mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AG-348</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for Treatment B</intervention_name>
    <description>4 tablets matched to mitapivat tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mitapivat 300 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Six 50-mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment D</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AG-348</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo for Treatment C</intervention_name>
    <description>4 tablets matched to mitapivat tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is male or female 18 to 55 years of age, inclusive;

          -  If female, is not currently pregnant or breastfeeding OR is of non-childbearing
             potential, defined as either:

               -  Being clinically infertile as the result of surgical sterilization, confirmed
                  postmenopausal status, or another documented medical condition (eg, was born
                  without a uterus) OR

               -  Agreeing to either abstain from sexual intercourse with a male partner OR agrees
                  to use a highly effective form of contraception, beginning at the time of
                  screening and continuing throughout the study and for 28 days after dosing. The
                  following are considered highly effective forms of contraception: hormonal oral
                  contraceptives, injectables, and patches; intrauterine devices; double-barrier
                  methods (synthetic condom, diaphragm, or cervical cap used with spermicidal foam,
                  cream, or gel); and male partner sterilization;

          -  If male, agrees to abstain from sexual intercourse with a female partner OR agrees to
             use a highly effective form of contraception, beginning at the time of screening and
             continuing throughout the study and for 90 days after dosing, AND to refrain from
             donating sperm for the duration of the study and for 90 days after dosing;

          -  Participant has a body mass index 18 to 32 kilograms per square meter (kg/m^2),
             inclusive, at screening;

          -  Participant is considered by the investigator to be in good general health as
             determined by medical history, clinical laboratory test results, vital sign
             measurements, 12-lead ECG results, and physical examination findings at screening;

          -  Participant has no clinically significant history or presence of ECG findings as
             judged by the investigator at screening and check-in, including each criterion as
             follows:

               -  Normal sinus rhythm (heart rate [HR] between 45 beats per minute [bpm] and 100
                  bpm inclusive);

               -  QT interval corrected for HR using Fridericia's formula (QTcF) ≤450 milliseconds
                  (msec);

               -  QRS interval ≤110 msec; and confirmed by manual over read if &gt;110 msec;

               -  PR interval between 120 and 220 msec;

          -  Participant agrees to comply with all protocol requirements;

          -  Participant is able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has any medical or surgical condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, could affect study drug absorption, distribution, metabolism, or
             excretion;

          -  Participant has undergone any major surgical procedure within the 3 months prior to
             screening;

          -  Participant has a history of any primary malignancy (including any melanoma or
             suspicious undiagnosed skin lesions), with the exception of in situ basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinomas of the skin, cervical carcinoma in situ, or other
             malignancies that have been curatively treated and for which the participant has
             displayed no evidence of disease within the 5 years prior to screening;

          -  Participant has glucose-6-phosphate-dehydrogenase deficiency;

          -  Participant has a known history or presence of liver disease.

          -  Participant has a positive test result for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg),
             hepatitis C virus antibody (HCVAb), or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) types 1 or 2
             antibodies at screening;

          -  Participant has liver function tests including alanine aminotransferase (ALT),
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase, and total bilirubin that are
             greater than the upper limit of normal at screening or check-in (results may be
             repeated once);

          -  Participant has platelet count or hemoglobin and hematocrit values that are below the
             lower limit of normal at screening or check-in (results may be repeated once);

          -  Participant has a positive test result for drugs of abuse, alcohol, or cotinine
             (indicating active current smoking) at screening or before the first dose of study
             drug or throughout the study.

          -  Participant has used any prescription (excluding hormonal birth control) medications
             within 30 days (or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer) before the first dose of study
             drug or throughout the study;

          -  Participant has used any over-the-counter medications, including herbal or nutritional
             supplements, within 28 days (or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer) before the first
             dose of study drug or throughout the study;

          -  Participant has received study drug in another investigational study within 30 days
             (or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer) of dosing.

          -  Participant has donated blood or blood products &gt;450 milliliters (mL) within 30 days
             before the first dose of study drug.

          -  Participant has history or presence of:

               -  Risk factors for torsades de pointes (eg, heart failure, cardiomyopathy, or
                  family history of long QT syndrome);

               -  Sick sinus syndrome, second- or third-degree atrioventricular block, myocardial
                  infarction, pulmonary congestion, cardiac arrhythmia, prolonged QT interval, or
                  conduction abnormalities;

               -  Repeated or frequent syncope or vasovagal episodes;

               -  Hypertension, angina, bradycardia (if assessed as clinically significant by the
                  investigator), or severe peripheral arterial circulatory disorders;

               -  Clinically significant laboratory assessment findings, including hypokalemia,
                  hypercalcemia, or hypomagnesemia;

          -  Participant has history or presence of:

               -  Any evidence of atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, complete right or left
                  bundle branch block, or Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome on the screening or
                  baseline ECG;

               -  Any morphology that renders measurement of QT interval imprecise (eg,
                  neuromuscular artifact that cannot be readily eliminated, indistinct QRS onset,
                  low-amplitude T-wave, merged T and U-waves, prominent U-waves, arrhythmia) on the
                  screening or baseline ECG.

          -  Participant is not willing to refrain from marijuana or cannabinol-containing products
             for 7 days before the first dose of study drug and throughout the study;

          -  Participant has consumed caffeine- or xanthine containing products within 24 hours
             prior to first dose of study drug or throughout the study;

          -  Participant has consumed grapefruit or grapefruit juice, Seville orange or Seville
             orange containing products (eg, marmalade) within 28 days before the first dose of
             study drug or throughout the study;

          -  Participant has consumed fruit juices 72 hours prior to first dosing or during the
             study (with exception to the juices in relation to the fruits specified above);

          -  Participant has consumed vegetables from the mustard green family (eg, kale, broccoli,
             watercress, collard greens, kohlrabi, Brussel sprouts, and mustard), or charbroiled
             meats for 7 days prior to first dose of study drug or throughout the study;

          -  Participant is a smoker or has used nicotine or nicotine-containing products (eg,
             snuff, nicotine patch, nicotine chewing gum, mock cigarettes, vaporizers, or inhalers)
             within 6 months before the first dose of study drug;

          -  Participant has a history of alcohol abuse or drug addiction within the last year or
             excessive alcohol consumption (regular alcohol intake &gt;21 units per week for male
             participants and &gt;14 units of alcohol per week for female participants) (1 unit is
             equal to approximately ½ pint [200 mL] of beer, 1 small glass [100 mL] of wine, or 1
             measure [25 mL] of spirits) or consumed alcohol 72 hours before the first dose of
             study drug or throughout the follow-up telephone call;

          -  Participant is involved in strenuous activity or contact sports within 24 hours before
             the first dose of study drug or throughout the study;

          -  Participant has a history of relevant drug and/or food allergies (ie, allergy to
             mitapivat or excipients [microcrystalline cellulose, croscarmellose sodium, sodium
             stearyl fumarate, magnesium stearate, and mannitol]);

          -  Participant has a history of allergy to sulfonamides (eg, co-trimoxazole antibiotic,
             silver sulfadiazine topical antibiotic for burn wounds) that has been characterized by
             acute hemolytic anemia, drug-induced liver injury, anaphylaxis, rash of erythema
             multiforme type, or Stevens-Johnson syndrome;

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, the participant is not suitable for entry into the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Affairs</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Agios Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Medical Affairs</last_name>
    <phone>833-228-8474</phone>
    <email>medinfo@agios.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PPD Development, LP</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78744</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

