<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04478708</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20180048</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04478708</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Ascending Dose Study of AMG 133 in Subjects With Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Single Ascending Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of AMG 133 in Subjects With Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to assess the safety and tolerability of AMG 133 as single doses in
      participants with obesity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 7, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 8, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 8, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Treatment-emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Clinically Significant Laboratory Values</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Clinically Significant Changes in Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Clinically Significant Changes in Electrocardiogram (ECG) Measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Maximum Plasma Concentration (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 120 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 133</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Up to 6 single ascending dose cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Up to 6 single ascending dose cohorts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 133</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive a single dose of AMG 133.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 133</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive a single dose of placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has provided informed consent before initiation of any study-specific
             activities/procedures.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years to ≤ 65 years, at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Except for obesity, otherwise healthy as determined by the investigator or medically
             qualified designee based on a medical evaluation including medical history, physical
             examination, laboratory tests, and ECGs on day -2 and screening.

          -  Body mass index between ≥ 30.0 kg/m2 and ≤ 40.0 kg/m2.

          -  Have a stable body weight (&lt; 5 kg self-reported change during the previous 8 weeks)
             before screening.

          -  Willing to maintain current general diet and physical activity regimen, except for the
             physical activity in the 72 hours before each blood sample collection for the clinical
             laboratory analysis, which should not be strenuous.

          -  Females must be of nonreproductive potential

             • Postmenopausal as defined as:

          -  Age of ≥ 55 years with no menses for at least 12 months; OR

          -  Age &lt; 55 years with no menses for at least 12 months AND with a follicle-stimulating
             hormone level &gt; 40 IU/L or according to the definition of &quot;postmenopausal range&quot; for
             the laboratory involved; OR

               -  History of hysterectomy; OR

               -  History of bilateral oophorectomy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or clinical evidence of diabetes mellitus, including hemoglobin A1c &gt; 6.5%
             and/or a fasting glucose ≥ 125 mg/dl (6.9 mmol/L) at screening.

          -  Triglycerides ≥ 5.65 mmol/L (ie, 500 mg/dL) at screening.

          -  Screening calcitonin ≥ 50 ng/L.

          -  Hepatic liver enzymes aspartate aminotransferase, alanine aminotransferase, alkaline
             phosphatase, or total bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) at
             screening.

          -  History or clinical evidence of bleeding diathesis or any coagulation disorder,
             including prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time, international
             normalized ratio, or platelet count outside of the laboratory's normal reference range
             at screening.

          -  History of gastrointestinal abnormality that could affect gastrointestinal motility
             (including small bowel or colonic resection, inflammatory bowel disease, irritable
             bowel disease, and colon or gastrointestinal tract cancer).

          -  Participants with a family or personal history of medullary thyroid carcinoma or
             multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2 or a personal history of nonfamilial medullary
             thyroid carcinoma.

          -  Participants with a history of confirmed chronic pancreatitis or idiopathic acute
             pancreatitis.

          -  Participants with a history of gall bladder disease (ie, cholelithiasis or
             cholecystitis) not treated with cholecystectomy.

          -  Untreated or uncontrolled hypothyroidism/hyperthyroidism defined as thyroid
             stimulating hormone &gt; 6 mIU/L or &lt;0.4 mIU/L.

          -  A corrected QT interval (QTc) at screening of &gt; 450 msec in males or &gt; 470 msec in
             females or history of long QT syndrome.

          -  Participants with a history of renal impairment or renal disease and/or estimated
             glomerular filtration rate ≤ 60 mL/min/1.73 m2.

          -  Obesity induced by other endocrinologic disorders (eg, Cushing's Syndrome).

          -  Previous surgical treatment for obesity (excluding liposuction if performed &gt;1 year
             before study entry) and/or participants with recent (within 6 months) or planned
             endoscopic treatment for obesity.

          -  History of major depressive disorder.

          -  History of other severe psychiatric disorders, eg schizophrenia, bipolar disorder.

          -  Any lifetime history of a suicidal attempt or of any suicidal behavior.

          -  Surgery scheduled for the study duration period, except for minor surgical procedures,
             at the discretion of the investigator.

          -  Positive results for human immunodeficiency virus antibodies, hepatitis B surface
             antigen, hepatitis B core antibody, or hepatitis C virus RNA. For hepatitis C,
             hepatitis C antibody testing is done at screening, followed by hepatitis C virus RNA
             by polymerase chain reaction if hepatitis C antibody is positive.

          -  Systolic blood pressure ≥ 150 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure ≥ 90 mm Hg at
             screening, or on day -2. For each visit, if the initial blood pressure is elevated,
             the reading may be repeated once at least 15 minutes later and the lower of the 2
             readings may be used.

          -  History of malignancy of any type, other than in situ cervical cancer or surgically
             excised nonmelanomatous skin cancers occurring more than 5 years before randomization.

          -  Use of the following agents are excluded unless there is a prior consultation between
             the investigator and Amgen medical monitor:

               -  Prescription and nonprescription drugs within 14 days or 5 half-lives, whichever
                  is longer, before the first dose of investigational product, with exception of
                  hormone replacement therapy (eg, estrogen, thyroid).

               -  All herbal medicines, vitamins, and supplements within 30 days before receiving
                  the first dose of investigational product.

               -  Exceptions must be reviewed and approved by the investigator and Amgen medical
                  monitor. Written documentation of this review and Amgen acknowledgment is
                  required for participant participation.

          -  Current or history of treatment with medications that may cause significant weight
             gain or loss, within 3 months before screening, including systemic corticosteroids
             (except for a short course of treatment, ie, 7 to 10 days), tricyclic antidepressants,
             atypical antipsychotic and mood stabilizers (eg, imipramine, amitriptyline,
             mirtazapine, paroxetine, phenelzine, chlorpromazine, thioridazine, clozapine,
             olanzapine, valproic acid and its derivatives, and lithium).

          -  Current participation (or within the last 3 months) in an organized weight reduction
             program or currently using or used within 3 months before screening: pramlintide,
             sibutramine, orlistat, zonisamide, topiramate, phentermine, naltrexone, bupropion,
             lorcaserin, metformin, or any GLP-1R agonists (either by prescription or as part of a
             clinical study).

          -  Currently receiving treatment in another investigational device or drug study, or less
             than 5 half-lives since ending treatment on another investigational device or drug
             study(ies). Other investigational procedures while participating in this study are
             excluded.

          -  Female participants with a positive pregnancy test assessed at screening and/or day -2
             by a serum pregnancy test and/or urine pregnancy test) or female participants who are
             breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant or breastfeed during treatment and for an
             additional 5 months after the last dose of AMG 133.

          -  Male participants with a female partner of childbearing potential who are unwilling to
             practice sexual abstinence (refrain from heterosexual intercourse) or use an
             acceptable method of contraception during treatment and for an additional 5 months
             after the last dose of AMG 133.

          -  Male participants unwilling to abstain from donating sperm during treatment and for an
             additional 5 months after the last dose of AMG 133.

          -  Participant has known sensitivity to AMG 133 or components thereof or a history of
             drug or other allergy that is in the opinion of the investigator or medical monitor
             (if appropriate), contraindicates their participation.

          -  Participant has a known sensitivity to GLP-1R agonists.

          -  Participant has known sensitivity to mammalian derived products.

          -  Participant has an allergy or known sensitivity to acetaminophen.

          -  Participant is unwilling or unable to limit alcohol consumption throughout the course
             of the study. Alcohol is prohibited 48 hours before day -2 and is limited to no more
             than to 2 drinks per day for males and 1 drink per day for females for the duration of
             the study (1 drink being equivalent to 12 ounces of regular beer, 8 to 9 ounces of
             malt liquor, 5 ounces of wine, or 1.5 ounces of 80 proof distilled spirits).

          -  Participant uses nicotine or tobacco containing products (including but not limited
             to: snuff, chewing tobacco, cigars, cigarettes, e-cigarettes, pipes, or nicotine
             patches) within 6 months before screening. Participant is unwilling or unable to
             abstain from nicotine or tobacco, cigars, cigarettes, pipes, or nicotine patches
             throughout the course of the study.

          -  Participant is tested positive for alcohol and/or drugs of abuse at screening.

          -  History of substance abuse (ie, alcohol, licit or illicit drugs) within 12 months
             before screening.

          -  Participant is unwilling to refrain from strenuous exercise (eg, heavy lifting, weight
             training, and aerobics) for 72 hours before each blood collection for clinical
             laboratory tests.

          -  Participant has donated or lost ≥ 500 mL of blood or plasma within 60 days of day -2.

          -  Participant likely to not be available to complete all protocol-required study visits
             or procedures, and/or to comply with all required study procedures to the best of the
             participant and investigator's knowledge.

          -  History or evidence of any other clinically significant disorder, condition or disease
             (with the exception of those outlined above) that, in the opinion of the investigator
             or Amgen physician, if consulted, would pose a risk to participant safety or interfere
             with the study evaluation, procedures or completion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amgen Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>866-572-6436</phone>
    <email>medinfo@amgen.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual patient data for variables necessary to address the specific research question in an approved data sharing request.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data sharing requests relating to this study will be considered beginning 18 months after the study has ended and either 1) the product and indication (or other new use) have been granted marketing authorization in both the US and Europe or 2) clinical development for the product and/or indication discontinues and the data will not be submitted to regulatory authorities. There is no end date for eligibility to submit a data sharing request for this study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Qualified researchers may submit a request containing the research objectives, the Amgen product(s) and Amgen study/studies in scope, endpoints/outcomes of interest statistical analysis plan, data requirements, publication plan, and qualifications of the researcher(s). In general, Amgen does not grant external requests for individual patient data for the purpose of re-evaluating safety and efficacy issues already addressed in the product labelling. Requests are reviewed by a committee of internal advisors, and if not approved, may be further arbitrated by a Data Sharing Independent Review Panel. Upon approval, information necessary to address the research question will be provided under the terms of a data sharing agreement. This may include anonymized individual patient data and/or available supporting documents, containing fragments of analysis code where provided in analysis specifications. Further details are available at the URL below.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://www.amgen.com/datasharing</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

