<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04478240</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AA027422</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04478240</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Automating Peer Learning to Reduce Alcohol Use and Related Deviant Behavior in Secondary School</brief_title>
  <acronym>PeerLearning</acronym>
  <official_title>Automating Peer Learning to Reduce Alcohol Use and Related Deviant Behavior in Secondary School</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Research Behavioral Intervention Strategies, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Research Behavioral Intervention Strategies, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Deviant peer affiliation is one of the most important predictors of alcohol use in
      adolescence. These affiliations arise when socially marginalized youth self-aggregate and
      reinforce alcohol use and other deviant activity (i.e., &quot;deviant peer clustering&quot;). Existing
      efficacious school-based prevention programs generally have small effects and can be
      difficult to disseminate with fidelity and challenging to sustain due to complex designs and
      significant time-and-money expenditures required for materials and training. Existing
      school-based prevention programs have not provided compelling value to schools, which has
      limited their dissemination. The investigators found significantly lower rates of deviant
      peer affiliation and alcohol/tobacco use and moderate-to-strong suppressive effects on
      bullying, victimization, stress, and emotional problems, and strong positive effects on
      student engagement and achievement in peer-learning intervention schools compared to control
      schools. However, teachers in intervention schools faced challenges implementing peer
      learning, including: (1) design fidelity: ensuring that peer learning provided the most
      positive student experience by including all the essential design elements; and, (2)
      instructional support: managing the flow and timing of the activities to complete the lesson
      on time while dealing with unexpected disruptions. Investigators developed an initial version
      of a mobile software application (PeerLearning.net) that provided easy-to-use organizational
      templates with workflow support that teachers used to automate the design and delivery of
      peer learning lessons. In this cluster randomized trial of the app, the investigators will
      use a sample of middle and high schools and conduct pre/post student assessments of peer
      relations, alcohol/drug use, antisocial/prosocial behavior, and social-emotional skills.
      Investigators will also collect data on the frequency of lesson delivery with the app by
      teacher and school to assess dosage, which will be incorporated into our analyses. The
      investigators hypothesize that use of PeerLearning.net will have significant suppressive
      effects on alcohol use and related outcomes (i.e., tobacco/marijuana use, antisocial
      behavior, bullying, emotional problems) and promote increased levels of social-emotional
      skills and prosocial behavior. The investigators hypothesize that these results will be
      moderated by dosage (i.e., use of the app), such that greater usage yields larger effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Schools (N = 24) will be randomly assigned to intervention or waitlist control conditions,
      and data will be collected immediately in the fall (i.e., baseline measure) and in the
      spring, approximately 6 months later (i.e., post-treatment assessment). Overall, the
      investigators will have two assessment points. Data will be collected from teachers and
      students via on-line surveys (i.e., Qualtrics) and through observations; see below on the
      Measures. Intervention schools will receive training and access to the PeerLearning.net app
      immediately, whereas control schools will receive access in the spring after the second wave
      of data collection is completed.

      The investigators hypothesize that usage of PeerLearning.net will promote increasing levels
      of prosocial behavior and have a significant suppressive effects on alcohol use and related
      outcomes (i.e., tobacco/marijuana use, antisocial behavior, bullying, emotional problems).
      The investigators hypothesize that this link will be &quot;moderated&quot; by dosage (i.e., usage of
      the app). Finally, the investigators will examine differences in program effects by sex
      (gender) and ethnicity, which the investigators expect to be small or nonexistent.

      Participants will include both teachers and students at 24 middle and high schools, cluster
      randomized to intervention vs. waitlist control. Teachers will use PeerLearning.net to design
      and deliver small-group peer learning lessons during the school year. The investigators will
      not exclude any participant based upon race/ethnicity, gender, or disability. Participating
      schools, teachers, and students will be rewarded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a cluster randomized trial, where assignment to condition occurs at the school level. Randomization of schools to condition (intervention vs. control) occurs at the beginning of the study and there is no cross-over.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol and other drug (AOD) use</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and 6 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Youth will complete the SAMHSA Participant Outcome Measures for Discretionary Programs. This survey tool was used as part of SAMHSA's national cross-site evaluation and is comprised of questions that include alcohol, tobacco, and other drug (ATOD) use and knowledge; ATOD beliefs and perceived risk of harm from ATOD use; and future intentions to use drugs. The investigators will also assess binge alcohol use (i.e., occasions at which 5/more drinks were consumed). The minimum score is zero.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antisocial/prosocial behavior and mental health</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and 6 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ),has subscales for Conduct Problems (antisocial behavior), Prosocial Behavior, and Emotional Problems. Subscales for conduct problems (e.g., &quot;I get very angry and often lose my temper&quot;), emotional problems (e.g., &quot;I worry a lot&quot;), and prosocial behavior (e.g., &quot;I usually share with others&quot;) items scores 1 (none) to 3 (a lot), and the investigators average these, so the minimum is 1 and the maximum is 3.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bullying and victimization</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and 6 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Illinois Aggression Scales (Espelage &amp; Holt, 2001) includes three subscales. The bullying and victimization subscales will be used. The 9-item Illinois Bully Scale measures frequency of teasing, name-calling, and social exclusion within the last 30 days. The 4-item Illinois Peer Victimization Scale assesses verbal and physical peer victimization within the past 30 days. Each item scores between 0 (none) and 4 (a lot), and the investigators average these so the minimum score is zero and the maximum is 4.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7440</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (access to PeerLearning.net)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Teachers and students in intervention schools will be given access to PeerLearning.net software for the purposes of instruction for the 2021-2022 school year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Passive Control (no intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Teachers and students in control schools will conduct instruction as usual without PeerLearning.net.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PeerLearning.net</intervention_name>
    <description>PeerLearning.net is a software package that supports teachers in designing and delivering peer learning lessons, either in-person or remotely while students are learning at home.
Peer learning is an instructional technique that puts students in groups under conditions of positive interdependence, where they are incentivized to work together and promote the success of one another. Peer Learning lessons also ensure individual accountability and explicitly observe for and reward specific group social skills (e.g., encouraging participation, checking for understanding). Peer Learning also includes group processing after the lesson is completed so that the students in the groups have an opportunity to discuss what they did well and what could use improvement; they also have the opportunity to provide positive reinforcement to one another for contributing to the success of the group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (access to PeerLearning.net)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All teachers and students in participating schools will be eligible to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The investigators will not exclude any participant based upon race/ethnicity, gender,
             or disability.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Espelage DL, Holt MK. Bullying and Victimization During Early Adolescence, Journal of Emotional Abuse. 2001. 2:2-3, 123-142, DOI: 10.1300/J135v02n02_08</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cooperative learning</keyword>
  <keyword>Deviant peer affiliation</keyword>
  <keyword>School-based prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol and other drug use</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescence Middle/high school</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

