<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04479943</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-0010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>A549000</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NUR/FACULTY AFFAIRS/ADMIN</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Protocol Version 1/23/2020</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HS026733-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04479943</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Patient Walking During Hospitalization</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preventing Hospital-Acquired Disability: An Intervention to Improve Older Adult Patient Ambulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin Institute for Clinical and Translational Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aurora Health Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UW Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The MOVIN (Mobilizing Older adult patients Via a systems-based Intervention) randomized
      controlled trial is designed to evaluate the impact of the MOVIN intervention on improving
      the functional ability of older adult hospital patients and reducing their healthcare
      utilization post-hospitalization. MOVIN is a program to increase patient ambulation while
      hospitalized. The study's hypothesis is that MOVIN will improve functional outcomes for
      hospitalized older adult patients by producing a change in nursing practice and culture of
      ambulation on inpatient units. MOVIN is a unit-based intervention. Therefore all patients on
      this unit are exposed to the intervention once it is implemented regardless of whether or not
      they participate in the trial. The study will enroll 320 total hospitalized participants 65
      years and older for the duration of their stay.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Up to 65% of hospitalized older adults will lose the ability to ambulate independently during
      their hospital stay. Loss of independent ambulation has been identified as a
      hospital-acquired disability and is a critical patient safety concern, resulting in permanent
      loss of function for 50% of older adults one-year post discharge. Functional loss is
      associated with multiple negative outcomes including a 33% increase in new nursing home
      placement, increase in length of hospital stay, need for home health services, falls,
      caregiver burden, decreased quality of life, and increased mortality. Given the rapid
      increase in the elderly population, loss of independent ambulation primarily due to the
      process of care in hospital settings may significantly increase future healthcare costs and
      further exacerbate concerns related to patient care quality.

      Lack of walking during hospitalization has been directly linked to loss of independent
      ambulation in older adults. Nurses are responsible for promoting and maintaining patient
      independent mobility. However, the investigators research has identified multiple personal
      and organizational barriers that prevent nurses from walking patients. The investigators have
      developed and pilot tested a novel systems based multi-component intervention to improve
      ambulation of older adult patients, Mobilizing Older adult patients Via a systems-based
      INtervention (MOVIN). MOVIN is comprised of five components: 1) psychomotor skills training;
      2) communication tools; 3) ambulation pathways; 4) ambulation resources; and 5) unit
      ambulation culture. The Investigators pilot study of MOVIN demonstrated a statistically
      significant increase in frequency and weekly distance of patient ambulation as well as
      changes in nursing practice and unit culture. Notably, these changes have been sustained for
      greater than two years after completion of the study.

      The investigators' goal is to eliminate loss of independent ambulation in hospitalized older
      adults. In pursuit of this goal, the specific aims are to:

        1. Test the effectiveness of MOVIN to improve functional ability of older adult patients at
           discharge, and 1, 3 and 6 months post discharge;

        2. Test the effectiveness of MOVIN to reduce healthcare utilization of older adults at
           discharge, and 1, 3 and 6 months post discharge;

        3. Measure change in nurse behaviors and unit culture and identify ongoing systems barriers
           that impact translation of MOVIN across inpatient units and different hospitals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study uses an incomplete stepped wedge cluster randomized controlled trial. In the incomplete stepped wedge design, inpatient units are randomly sequenced into the intervention. A baseline (control period) and 2 follow up data collection periods (intervention and post intervention period) occur for each unit. Incomplete stepped wedge cluster randomized trials are novel study designs that are particularly beneficial for evaluating service delivery interventions using a pragmatic design, when evaluations need to be completed at a system or population level, or it is impractical or cost prohibitive to roll out an intervention across multiple units simultaneously.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gait speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of hospital admission, Within 8 hours of hospital discharge, 3 months post-discharge; Up to 4 months total</time_frame>
    <description>Gait Speed is a physical performance measure identified as a sensitive clinical indicator of health, mortality, healthcare utilization, and independence in ambulation, and is feasible to test in hospitalized older adults. A 4 meter walk test will be conducted on admission to the study, discharge from the hospital and at 3 months post discharge in the subjects home or the hospital or clinic. A trained member of the research team will conduct the gait speed test. Interrater reliability for the 4 meter walk test will be conducted between all members of the research team prior to collecting gait speed data on study participants. Change scores will be calculated as the difference among gait speeds measured at each time points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-report on Activities of Daily Living (ADL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of hospital admission, Within 8 hours of hospital discharge, 1 month post-discharge, 3 months post-discharge; 6 months post-discharge; Up to 7 months total</time_frame>
    <description>A trained member of the research team will collect patients self-report of ADLs on admission to the study, discharge from the hospital, by phone at 1 month post intervention, and in person at the 3 month post intervention visit using the Katz ADL Index. The Katz ADL Index is a self-report scale that measures five ADL on three levels (independent, requiring assistance of another and unable to do). A score of 0-6 is possible, with higher scores indicating higher independence with ADLs and lower scores indicating higher dependence on others to perform ADLs. The scale demonstrates excellent reliability and predictive validity, and is sensitive to change in hospital settings. Change scores will be calculated as the difference among ADL independence measured at each time point.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Life Space Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of hospital admission, Within 8 hours of hospital discharge, 1 month post-discharge, 3 months post-discharge; 6 months post-discharge; Up to 7 months total</time_frame>
    <description>The UAB Life Space Assessment (LSA) is a self-report scale of ambulation that measures spaces patients' move in, the frequency of moving into those spaces, and dependency in moving into those spaces. This scale has demonstrated reliability and predictive validity and sensitivity to change after hospital stay. Level scores are calculated by multiplying the life-space level (higher numbers indicate farther distances moved, e.g., 1-inside the home to 5-places outside of the person's town), degree of independence (higher scores indicate greater independence), and frequency of movement (higher scores equal greater frequency). Total scores range from 0 (totally bed-bound) to 120 (moved out of town every day without assistance). A trained member of the research team will collect patients self-report on Life Space. Change scores will be calculated as the difference among LSA ambulation measured at each time point.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post-discharge; 3 months post-discharge; 6 months post-discharge; Up to 7 months total</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital readmissions will be collected via patient medical record review by a nurse researcher from the study team.The nurse researcher from the study team will also collect patient self reports of hospital readmissions to account for any out of network visits that might be missed in medical record reviews.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency Room Visits</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post-discharge; 3 months post-discharge; 6 months post-discharge; Up to 7 months total</time_frame>
    <description>Emergency room visits Discharge destination (home, skilled nursing facility) will be collected via patient medical record review by a nurse researcher from the study team. The nurse researcher from the study team will also collect patient self reports of emergency room visits to account for any out of network visits that might be missed in medical record reviews.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Hospital Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 3 months post-discharge; Up to 4 months total</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay will be collected via patient medical record review by a nurse researcher from the study team.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Discharge destination</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 3 months post-discharge; Up to 4 months total</time_frame>
    <description>Discharge destination (home, skilled nursing facility) will be collected via patient medical record review by a nurse researcher from the study team.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">320</enrollment>
  <condition>Early Mobility</condition>
  <condition>Older Adults</condition>
  <condition>Hospital Acquired Condition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-intervention/control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>160 older adult patients (age 65 or older) will be recruited on four units across two hospitals (two units per hospital) over 6 months prior to implementation of the unit-based MOVIN intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>160 older adult patients (age 65 or older) will be recruited on four units across two hospitals (two units per hospital) over 6 months after MOVIN has been implemented on the unit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MOVIN</intervention_name>
    <description>MOVIN is a multi-component unit-based intervention comprised of five components that are implemented simultaneously in a hospital unit. The five components are: 1) psychomotor skills training, 2) unit ambulation culture, 3) communication, 4) resources, 5) ambulation environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 65 years or older

          -  able to walk with or without assistance

          -  living in the community (not long term care) prior to admission

          -  have an ambulation order

          -  admitted to hospital's general adult medical unit

          -  able to speak and understand English.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  activated Power of Attorney

          -  dementia diagnosis

          -  lower extremity amputation

          -  terminal diagnosis (Comfort Care)

          -  on hospice

          -  bed rest order or activity restriction

          -  wheelchair bound
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linsey M Steege, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Linsey M Steege, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>608-263-5191</phone>
    <email>lsteege@wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Barb King, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>608-263-5319</phone>
    <email>bjking2@wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UW Health-University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kip Schick, DPT</last_name>
      <phone>608-220-7550</phone>
      <email>MSchick@uwhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sue Rees, DNP</last_name>
      <email>Srees@uwhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aurora St. Luke's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>nursing care</keyword>
  <keyword>hospitalization</keyword>
  <keyword>aged</keyword>
  <keyword>walking</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iatrogenic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

