<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04033874</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Eskisehir Osmangazi University</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04033874</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Efficacy of Non-pharmacological Interventions on Pain Levels, Crying Times and Voice Decibels in Newborns</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Efficacy of Non-pharmacological Interventions on Pain Levels, Crying Times and Voice Decibels in Newborns: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eskisehir Osmangazi University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eskisehir Osmangazi University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aimed to investigate and compare the effects of different non-pharmacological
      interventions (kangaroo care, holding on mother's lap, white noise listening, ambient sound
      listening) on newborns' crying times, voice decibels and pain levels during heel-stick
      procedure
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, randomized controlled trial including pre and post tests of four
      groups. The population of the study consisted of newborns who were followed in the Neonatal
      Service of Eskişehir City Hospital. The number of newborns to be sampled was determined by
      power analysis. With a 95% confidence interval, 0.25 effect size and 0.85 strength, 34
      newborns are planned to be included in each group. Newborns who meet the inclusion criteria
      will be randomly assigned to the groups.

      In the randomization process; in the four-group design, the rooms were randomly assigned to
      the study groups by drawing lots in order to eliminate the probability of influence of
      newborns from each other. Internal blinding was used as a blinding method in order to ensure
      complete randomization and to prevent Rosental effect. The randomization was performed by the
      responsible nurse of the unit who was unaware of the pre-test and post-tests of the
      application.

        1. Four different groups were formed in order to prevent the causes of concern in the
           randomization of patients who were leveled according to their clinical status in the
           neonatal intensive care unit.

        2. In the absence of neonatal intensive care environment noise, four groups were considered
           due to the limitation in explaining the benefit, contribution and effect of white noise,
           kangru care and being in the lap of the mother in reducing pain.

        3. The newborns treated with kangaroo care and the mother's lap will be the control groups
           of each other and the newborns treated with white noise and ambient sound will be the
           control groups of each other.

      Research hypotheses:

      H1. Newborns receiving kangaroo care during the heel-stick procedure have lower pain levels
      than newborns who are holding on their mother's lap.

      H2. Newborns receiving kangaroo care during the heel-stick procedure have less crying time
      than newborns who are holding on their mother's lap.

      H3. The highest level of sound decibels in the crying process of newborns who receiving
      kangaroo care during the heel-stick procedure are less than newborns who are holding on their
      mother's lap.

      H4. Newborns listened to white noise during the heel-stick procedure have lower pain levels
      than newborns who listened to ambient sound.

      H5. Newborns listened to white noise during the heel-stick procedure have less crying time
      than newborns who listened to ambient sound.

      H6. The highest level of sound decibels in the crying process of newborns who listened to
      white noise during the heel-stick procedure are less than newborns listened to ambient sound.

      In the study, NIPS (Neonatal Infant Pain Scale) will be used to evaluate the pain severity of
      newborns in addition to the data form prepared by the researchers.

      During the application, pulse oximetry device will be placed on each newborn right wrist,
      then heart rate and SpO2 values will be recorded before, during and after the procedure. The
      device will remain attached to the baby's wrist during the procedure. Then, the pain level
      will be assessed with NIPS and heel-stick procedure will be initiated. To determine the
      crying time, the stopwatch shall be turned on and the sound decibel meter shall be turned on
      to determine the sound decibel. The general pain level of the newborns will be evaluated by
      one minute before the procedure and their response to the pain for three minutes during and
      after the procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The prospective, randomized controlled trial including pre and post tests of four groups</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Crying times</measure>
    <time_frame>Five months</time_frame>
    <description>Newborns' crying times during heel-stick procedure will be assessed with the stopwatch</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Voice decibels</measure>
    <time_frame>Five months</time_frame>
    <description>Newborns' voice decibels during heel-stick procedure will be assessed with the sound decibel meter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Five months</time_frame>
    <description>Newborns' pain levels during heel-stick procedure will be assessed with NIPS (Neonatal Infant Pain Scale)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">136</enrollment>
  <condition>Newborn</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kangaroo care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Heel stick procedure will be performed during kangaroo care.
During the application, pulse oximetry device will be placed on each newborn right wrist, then heart rate and SpO2 values will be recorded before, during and after the procedure. The device will remain attached to the baby's wrist during the procedure. Then, the pain level will be assessed with NIPS (Neonatal Infant Pain Scale) and heel-stick procedure will be initiated. To determine the crying time, the stopwatch shall be turned on and the sound decibel meter shall be turned on to determine the sound decibel. The general pain level of the newborns will be evaluated by one minute before the procedure and their response to the pain for three minutes during and after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mother's lap</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Heel stick procedure will be performed during newborns who are holding on their mother's lap.
During the application, pulse oximetry device will be placed on each newborn right wrist, then heart rate and SpO2 values will be recorded before, during and after the procedure. The device will remain attached to the baby's wrist during the procedure. Then, the pain level will be assessed with NIPS (Neonatal Infant Pain Scale) and heel-stick procedure will be initiated. To determine the crying time, the stopwatch shall be turned on and the sound decibel meter shall be turned on to determine the sound decibel. The general pain level of the newborns will be evaluated by one minute before the procedure and their response to the pain for three minutes during and after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>White noise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Heel stick procedure will be performed during newborns listened to white noise.
For the white noise; the track named &quot;do not cry your baby, pt. 2&quot; will be played in Orhan Osman's Colic album. The white noise level will be adjusted to an average of 55 decibels. During the application, pulse oximetry device will be placed on each newborn right wrist, then heart rate and SpO2 values will be recorded before, during and after the procedure. The device will remain attached to the baby's wrist during the procedure. Then, the pain level will be assessed with NIPS (Neonatal Infant Pain Scale) and heel-stick procedure will be initiated. To determine the crying time, the stopwatch shall be turned on and the sound decibel meter shall be turned on to determine the sound decibel. The general pain level of the newborns will be evaluated by one minute before the procedure and their response to the pain for three minutes during and after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ambient sound</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Heel stick procedure will be performed during newborns listened to ambient sound.
During the application, pulse oximetry device will be placed on each newborn right wrist, then heart rate and SpO2 values will be recorded before, during and after the procedure. The device will remain attached to the baby's wrist during the procedure. Then, the pain level will be assessed with NIPS (Neonatal Infant Pain Scale) and heel-stick procedure will be initiated. To determine the crying time, the stopwatch shall be turned on and the sound decibel meter shall be turned on to determine the sound decibel. The general pain level of the newborns will be evaluated by one minute before the procedure and their response to the pain for three minutes during and after the procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>kangaroo care</intervention_name>
    <description>kangaroo care</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kangaroo care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>holding on the mother's lap</intervention_name>
    <description>holding on the mother's lap</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mother's lap</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>white noise listening</intervention_name>
    <description>white noise listening</description>
    <arm_group_label>White noise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ambient sound listening</intervention_name>
    <description>ambient sound listening</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ambient sound</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestation age is between 34-42 weeks

          -  Birth weight is between 2500-4000 gr

          -  Apgar score of 1 minute and 5 minutes 8 and above

          -  Passing the newborn hearing screening test

          -  To being followed in the neonatal intensive care unit

          -  To being fed at least half an hour before the procedure

          -  To being agreed to participate in the study by parents

          -  To being never received mechanical ventilation / CPAP support after birth

          -  Having none of congenital anomaly

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to take blood the first attempt, as the pain level may change

          -  Failure of the newborn to pass the hearing screening test

          -  Newborns hospitalized from polyclinic and emergency department because heel blood was
             taken before

          -  Refusing to participate in the study by parents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Özlem Örsal, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eskişehir Osmangazi University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pınar Duru, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+90(222)2393750</phone>
    <phone_ext>1109</phone_ext>
    <email>pinarduruu@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eskişehir Osmangazi University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eskişehir</city>
        <zip>26480</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pınar Duru, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>90(222)2393750</phone>
      <phone_ext>1109</phone_ext>
      <email>pinarduruu@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Özlem Örsal, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pınar Duru, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zehra Akkoca, MsN (c)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gao H, Xu G, Gao H, Dong R, Fu H, Wang D, Zhang H, Zhang H. Effect of repeated Kangaroo Mother Care on repeated procedural pain in preterm infants: A randomized controlled trial. Int J Nurs Stud. 2015 Jul;52(7):1157-65. doi: 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2015.04.006. Epub 2015 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25912524</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Johnston C, Campbell-Yeo M, Disher T, Benoit B, Fernandes A, Streiner D, Inglis D, Zee R. Skin-to-skin care for procedural pain in neonates. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 Feb 16;2:CD008435. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008435.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28205208</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhu J, Hong-Gu H, Zhou X, Wei H, Gao Y, Ye B, Liu Z, Chan SW. Pain relief effect of breast feeding and music therapy during heel lance for healthy-term neonates in China: a randomized controlled trial. Midwifery. 2015 Mar;31(3):365-72. doi: 10.1016/j.midw.2014.11.001. Epub 2014 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25467598</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Eskisehir Osmangazi University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pınar Duru</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heel stick</keyword>
  <keyword>Newborn</keyword>
  <keyword>NIPS</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain levels</keyword>
  <keyword>Crying times</keyword>
  <keyword>Voice decibels</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>It is planned to share the data of this study in December 2019</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

