<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04034303</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NEOCEL2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04034303</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk Factors for the Development of Celiac Disease in Genetically Predisposed Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEOCEL</acronym>
  <official_title>Natural History, Risk Factors and Predictive Biomarkers for Celiac Disease: a Prospective Multicenter Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federico II University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federico II University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to identify risk factors for the development of Celiac Diseases in families
      with a recognized genetic risk for the presence of a confirmed proband case. Candidate mother
      will be recruited before a planned pregnancy or within the first 12 weeks of pregnancy.
      Familial and environmental risk factors will be evaluated within the couple of parents.
      Pregnancy will be followed up and appropriate biological samples collected. Delivery will be
      supervised in order to collect biological samples. Newborns will be controlled from birth up
      to the 6th year of age. Data about clinical events related to health, life attitudes,
      nutrition will be collected together with biological samples either in the pregnant mother as
      well as in the infant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  CD epidemics: Celiac Disease incidence is increasing at unexpected rates in the last two
           decades in all gluten-consuming populations.

        -  Remarkable stratified genetic risk: there is a strong genetic component as the main risk
           to develop disease, as supported by &gt; 85% concordance in monozygotic twins, but genetics
           cannot change over decades and does not explain the epidemic which has been observed.
           The presence of double HLA DQ2 in female subjects does increases the risk of disease
           above that of a mendelian recessive inheritance. Hence the estimation of environmental
           factors associated to the genetic risk is quite complex and does need a very strict
           prospective longitudinal study design, since each factor is likely to produce, if ever,
           a quite small odds ratio .

        -  Gene expression in the first year of life: we have observed, in our previous cohort
           studies, that the expression of at least a small set of CD associated candidate genes is
           substantially different between the children who eventually develop Cd and those who do
           not, already a 6 months of age, much before any measurable recognition of the gluten
           antigen, development of antibodies or any clinical sign (ref 3 Galatola).

        -  Epigenetic changes in small intestinal tissue: in addition of the previously reported
           gene expression differences, gene methylation and related expression of CD associated
           candidate genes have been observed in the epithelium and the lamina propria of Cd
           patients . In addition, microRNA appear to be differently expressed in patients versus
           controls.

        -  Early events in the first-second year of life before diagnosis: our groups and others
           observed that the occurrenceof acute respiratoryinfections in the first and second year
           of life, at least 12 months before the onset of disease, was associated to increased
           odds (&gt; x2) of developing CD. It is most likely that viral infections (as the large
           majority of URTI in children) play a role in the development of food antigen intolerance
           leading to CD . A role of non-pathogenic viral infections has been also suggestedin the
           developmentof intolerance to gluten.

        -  No influence of breast-feeding or gluten introduction: breast feeding does not prevent
           the incidence of CD in at risk infants: its most likely effect is to delay the onset of
           clinical symptoms. Similarly, the time and quantity of gluten introduction is not
           associated to the actual incidence, but is only associated to delayed time effects.

        -  Possible implication of microbiome: despite the complexity of estimating differences in
           the composition of microbiome in the infants, it has been suggested that infants who
           later develop CD might show a fila composition slightly different from their matched
           controls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Celiac Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>6 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of new cases of infants affected by Celiac Disease in relation to genetic (HLA and non-HLA Associated Genes), Epigenetic (DNA Methylation, Gene Expression, Istone Acetylation of candidate gene) and environmental factors (Maternal factors, Nutrition, Infections)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analysis of microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 years</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the microbiome composition of the group of infants who eventually develop Celiac Disease versus those who do not develop the disease.
Comparison of Fecal Microbiome of infants at 4, 12 and 24 months subgrouped by outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Prevention of Clinical Symptoms in Celiac Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>analysis of genetic and epigenetic risk factors</intervention_name>
    <description>analysis of gene, methylation and expression, microbiome</description>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples for serum, cells, nucleic acids Urine for metabolomic Analysis Breast Milk for
      metabolomic analysis Feces for microbiome
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pregnant women from a family with a confirmed CD proband Live newborns from the above
        mothers
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Pregnant women from a family with a confirmed CD proband

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Women affected by severe chronic disease and cancer Women not able to attend the schedule
        of visits

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Naples Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Naples</city>
        <state>Campania</state>
        <zip>80131</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federico II University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Renata Auricchio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Celiac Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

