<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04038658</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Lai/27/6/13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04038658</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Digital Worksite Exercise Intervention in China: Outcome and Process Evaluation</brief_title>
  <acronym>Move-It</acronym>
  <official_title>Move-It: A Cluster-randomised Digital Worksite Exercise Intervention in China: Outcome and Process Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nottingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nottingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to evaluate the outcomes and processes of a video and web-based
      worksite exercise intervention for sedentary office workers in China.

      The intervention is informed by behaviour change theory, and is a digital workplace
      intervention (called Move-It) involving a 10-minute Qigong exercise session (video
      demonstration via website) which is delivered twice a day at set break times during the
      working day for 12 consecutive weeks.

      The setting is a large organisation with 2 sites (in Beijing and Guangzhou). The objectives
      are to examine the effect of a video-based intervention on employees' physical activity, time
      spent sitting and work performance. This is tested in a 2-group, randomised wait-list control
      trial. This means that employees at one site receive the intervention first (site 1 -
      intervention group), and when they have completed (12 weeks later), the other site then
      receives the same intervention (site 2 - wait-list control). At the end of the intervention,
      there is a process evaluation with the intervention group which includes focus groups with
      employees and managers to gather information about the way in which the intervention was
      implemented. The process evaluation is based on a framework called 'Reach Effectiveness
      Adoption Implementation Maintenance' (RE-AIM). Data were collected at baseline (before the
      intervention began) and after 12 weeks in both groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim The aim of the study is to deliver a digital video-based worksite exercise intervention
      in China and conduct outcome and process evaluation. The objectives are: [1] to examine the
      effect of a video-based intervention on physical activity (PA) and weekday sitting hours
      (individual level); [2] to examine the effect of a video-based intervention on individual
      work performance (individual level); [3] to conduct a process evaluation of the intervention
      implementation (individual and cluster level).

      Design This is a 2-arm cluster-randomised wait-list control trial, with outcomes assessed in
      two groups: intervention and wait-list control (objectives 1 and 2).

      Clusters (sites) will be randomly allocated to groups at 1:1 ratio using computer-generated
      random number sequence.

      Setting 2 sites of a major organisation in China (one in Beijing, one in Guangzhou), with a
      total of 490 employees.

      Data Collection Data will be collected through online questionnaires emailed to all employee
      participants (Time 1 = T1). Employees in both groups will complete a second online
      questionnaire (Time 2 = T2). For the intervention group T2 will be immediately
      post-intervention, for the wait-list control group this will be just prior to receiving the
      intervention.

      Sample size At an individual level, the estimated sample size is a minimum 72 for
      intervention group and 72 for control group, alpha 0.05, beta 0.2 and power 0.8.

      Intervention This digital intervention consists of a series of six video clips demonstrating
      Qigong exercises designed to be undertaken at set exercise break times during the working
      day. The intervention includes a specially designed logo and selected images to be used on
      promotional posters and a dedicated 'Move-It' webpage. The six promotional videos are
      designed to be posted in sequence, one every two weeks, on the Move-It website. A Move-It
      icon on each employee's desktop computer screen will be scheduled to pop up twice a day as a
      prompt to interrupt sitting. The intervention is designed to be completed within 12 weeks.

      Measures Self-report measures of PA, work performance and weekday sitting hours are taken at
      T1 (baseline) and T2 (12 week follow-up).

      Data analysis Intervention outcome data will be analysed using the Statistical Package for
      the Social Sciences (IBM SPSS) Version 24.

      Outcomes will be compared between the pre- and post-intervention time points. Intracluster
      correlations and estimated effects sizes will be presented for each outcome. Data from both
      clusters will be included in all analyses, and analysis is by intention-to-treat.

      Process evaluation Will take place at the end of the intervention (intervention site only).
      This will include up to 6 focus groups (up to n=35) with employees (both participants and
      non-participants), organisational committee members and senior management.

      These will be aligned with the RE-AIM framework to explore intervention reach, effectiveness,
      adoption, implementation and maintenance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 7, 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cluster randomised control trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Statistical analysis undertaken by researcher blinded to group allocation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) Taiwanese short form</measure>
    <time_frame>Covers a person's record of physical activity for a period of seven days</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of self-reported physical activity. Includes culturally sensitive Chinese translations for the terms &quot;moderate&quot;, &quot;vigorous&quot; and &quot;physical activity&quot; as well as to identify representative types of physical activity for Taiwanese. Content validity 0.994.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health and Work Performance Questionnaire (HPQ).</measure>
    <time_frame>Overall performance rating for the days worked over the past 4 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported work performance. Single item was used from this scale. Item was measured on a 10-point scale ranging from 0=worst performance to 10=top performance.
Item is: 'how would you rate your overall performance on the days you worked during the past 4 weeks?'.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weekday sitting hours</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (average)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported average sitting hours per day: participants report number of hours (to the nearest whole hour) spent sitting on a typical workday.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">216</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (MoveIt)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10-minute Qigong exercise session (video demonstration via website) delivered twice a day at set break times during the working day for 12 consecutive weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-list control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention for 12 weeks. Then received the MoveIt Intervention for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Move-It</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (MoveIt)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Employee of participating organisation

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Not an employee of participating organisation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nottingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nottingham</city>
        <zip>NG7 2HA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>worksite</keyword>
  <keyword>digital</keyword>
  <keyword>health promotion</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Will adhere to data sharing regulations of target journal</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Study registered online at clinical trials.gov (permanent). This includes statistical analysis plan. Data accessible on request - available for 7 years.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data accessible on request - available for 7 years.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

