<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04036162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC18.294</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-A01065-52</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04036162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Spatial and Dynamic Characterization of Brain Activity for Language and Posture (Verticality) During Normal Aging. Magnetoencephalography (MEG) Study (MEG-AGING)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MEG-AGING</acronym>
  <official_title>Spatial and Dynamic Characterization of Brain Activity for Language and Posture (Verticality) During Normal Aging. Magnetoencephalography (MEG) Study (MEG-AGING)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinatec, COMMISSARIAT À L'ÉNERGIE ATOMIQUE ET AUX ÉNERGIES ALTERNATIVES (CEA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laboratoire de Psychologie et NeuroCognition (LPNC), Université Grenoble Alpes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Depending on the point of view, different definitions of aging have been proposed. Thus, at
      the biological level, aging corresponds to a natural physiological process that leads to the
      progressive degeneration of cells and the slowing down of the vital functions of a living
      organism. More generally, aging is a multifactorial and multidimensional process that occurs
      at the cognitive, social, biological or psychological level.

      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the balance between activation
      (Task-Positive Network : TPN-Language, L, TPN-Verticality, V) and rest (Task-Negative Network
      : TNN) activity during normal aging, in two domains (language and posturo-spatial perception
      of verticality).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      From a cognitive point of view, although healthy older people become slower to analyze
      information, they remain just as accurate as young adults in performing different cognitive
      tasks. This necessarily implies compensation processes, with new cognitive strategies and a
      restructuring of the brain networks underlying these processes. These compensatory phenomena
      are known under the general name of neurocognitive reserve.

      Specific functions such as language, visuospatial skills, motor control, posture, or memory,
      are affected in a very variable way among the elderly. This variability involves multiple
      cognitive profiles rather than just one form of aging. Indeed, healthy aging can be defined
      cognitively in two ways, as a homogeneous or rather heterogeneous process. According to the
      homogeneous hypothesis of aging, the behavioral, cognitive and brain-like manifestations are
      similar among the elderly, without differentiation between functions. In other words,
      according to this hypothesis, aging would affect all the elderly and cognitive processes in
      the same way. Conversely, according to the heterogeneous hypothesis, significant differences
      should be revealed between individuals and in the same individual according to different
      cognitive processes. This heterogeneity is explained by multiple factors (genetic,
      environmental, societal, educational, or lifestyle). If neuropsychological tests or
      behavioral experiments (and performance of the task) allow to identify rather easily the
      differences encountered among the elderly in terms of cognitive heterogeneity, this
      differential activity at the cerebral level is more difficult to highlight. Functional
      neuroimaging methods and techniques can provide a pathway for this purpose, to provide both
      spatial information (involved brain regions) and temporal information (dynamics of brain
      activation) when performing cognitive tasks or when the rest period.

      In this context, the magnetoencephalography (MEG) method is a preferred technique that can
      provide all these types of information on brain activity. Two types of networks can therefore
      be recorded : task-positive network (TPN) activated when the participant is involved in a
      task (in this project, language and posture / verticality), and task-negative network (TNN)
      specific to the state of rest , represented by regions that are called &quot;deactivated&quot;. These
      two networks will therefore be characterized in the study by the following parameters: (a)
      network: set of regions involved; (b) temporal dynamics of their activity, and (c) functional
      connectivity between the regions of TPN and TNN.

      To answer the question of homogeneity vs. heterogeneity of cognitive cerebral aging, TPNs vs.
      TNN will be compared in a group of healthy young adults compared to a group of healthy
      elderly subjects. The comparison will be made for the three categories of parameters
      mentioned above (a-c).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Right-handed healthy volunteers</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Balance between activation (TPN-Language, L, TPN-Verticality, V) and rest (TNN) activity during normal aging, in two domains (language and posturo-spatial perception of verticality) recorded by magnetoencephalography (MEG)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Evoked and continuous magnetic fields recorded during both cognitive tasks and during the rest period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between neuropsychological scores and brain activation or functional connectivity parameters recorded by magnetoencephalography (MEG) depending on both domains studied</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Neuropsychological scores on tests for all participants :
frontal cognitive functioning
anxiety and/or depressive symptoms
executive functions
verbal intelligence
language
Advanced analyses of cerebral activity as measured by MEG
frequency time analyses via spectral decomposition (induced brain rhythms)
functional and effective connectivity analysis through coherence, phase locking value, and Dynamic Causal Modelling measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Young group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Young Right-handed healthy volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aged group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aged Right-handed healthy volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive tasks</intervention_name>
    <description>MagnetoEncephaloGraphy (MEG) records</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aged group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Young group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy volunteers from 25 to 85 years old : young group (25-49 years) / aged group
             (50 to 85 years)

          -  Right-handed

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  French mother tongue

          -  Speaking fluent French

          -  Normal or corrected view

          -  Medical examination conducted prior to participation in the trial

          -  Registered in the French social security scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindication to Magnetoencephalography (MEG) and/or Magnetic resonance imaging
             (MRI) : implanted material, claustrophobia,…

          -  Generally severe condition: cardiac, respiratory, hematological, kidney, liver, cancer

          -  Regular use of anxiolytics, sedatives, antidepressants, neuroleptics

          -  Psychiatric pathology characterized

          -  Alcohol ingestion before the exam

          -  All categories of protected persons (Pregnant or lactating women, persons subject to a
             legal protection measure, persons deprived of their liberty by judicial or
             administrative decision)

          -  Alcohol ingestion before the exam

          -  Participation in other ongoing clinical trial with exclusion period or in the previous
             week

          -  Score MINI MENTAL STATE EXAMINATION (MMSE) &lt; 24
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monica BACIU, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHUGA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emilie COUSIN, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>33 (0)4 76 82 58 76</phone>
    <email>cousin.emilie@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Caroline SANDRE-BALLESTER, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>33 (0)4 38 78 28 51</phone>
    <email>CSandreballester@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUGA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emilie COUSIN, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33 (0)4 76 82 58 76</phone>
      <email>cousin.emilie@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Caroline SANDRE-BALLESTER, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33 (0)4 38 78 28 51</phone>
      <email>CSandreballester@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Monica BACIU, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoyau E, Roux-Sibilon A, Boudiaf N, Pichat C, Cousin E, Krainik A, Jaillard A, Peyrin C, Baciu M. Aging modulates fronto-temporal cortical interactions during lexical production. A dynamic causal modeling study. Brain Lang. 2018 Sep;184:11-19. doi: 10.1016/j.bandl.2018.06.003. Epub 2018 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29913316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baciu M, Boudiaf N, Cousin E, Perrone-Bertolotti M, Pichat C, Fournet N, Chainay H, Lamalle L, Krainik A. Functional MRI evidence for the decline of word retrieval and generation during normal aging. Age (Dordr). 2016 Feb;38(1):3. doi: 10.1007/s11357-015-9857-y. Epub 2015 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26711670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boudiaf N, Laboissière R, Cousin É, Fournet N, Krainik A, Baciu M. Behavioral evidence for a differential modulation of semantic processing and lexical production by aging: a full linear mixed-effects modeling approach. Neuropsychol Dev Cogn B Aging Neuropsychol Cogn. 2018 Jan;25(1):1-22. doi: 10.1080/13825585.2016.1257100. Epub 2016 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27883290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aging</keyword>
  <keyword>Task-Positive Network (TPN)</keyword>
  <keyword>Task-Negative Network (TNN)</keyword>
  <keyword>MagnetoEncephaloGraphy (MEG)</keyword>
  <keyword>Verticality</keyword>
  <keyword>Language</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemispheric asymmetry</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

