<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04035473</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KX-ORAX-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04035473</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Determine the Bioequivalence of Oraxol in Cancer Patients Treated With Intravenous Paclitaxel</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Crossover Study to Determine the Bioequivalence of Three Consecutive Daily Doses of Oraxol in Cancer Patients Treated With Intravenous Paclitaxel</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Athenex, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PharmaEssentia</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Athenex, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, open-label, 2-stage study with a 2-treatment period crossover design.
      Eligible participants are adults with cancer for whom weekly therapy with IV paclitaxel at a
      dose of 80 mg/m2 over 1 hour is indicated.

      Stage 1 will consist of an initial cohort (Cohort 1) up to 6 evaluable participants who will
      receive a dosing regimen of Oraxol consisting of a 15-mg oral HM30181AK-US tablet plus an
      oral paclitaxel dose of 205 mg/m2, both administered once daily for 3 consecutive days. The
      stages and cohorts are further described in the &quot;Study Design - Stages and Cohorts&quot; table
      below. An interim analysis of pharmacokinetic (PK) data from Cohort 1 will be conducted to
      determine if the administered regimen would appear likely to achieve BE (AUC0-∞), if tested
      in a greater number of participants in Stage 2. If it appears unlikely that the selected
      regimen will meet the criteria for BE based on AUC0-∞ data, a second cohort (Cohort 2) of up
      to 6 evaluable participants may be enrolled in Stage 1, and the dose of paclitaxel in Oraxol
      may be adjusted by a maximum of +/- 25%. If Cohort 2 is enrolled, a second interim analysis
      will be conducted.

      After the interim analysis/analyses (depending on the outcomes), a decision will be made by
      consensus of the DSMB, Kinex, Zenith Technology, and the Principal Investigator as to what
      dose should be administered in Stage 2. The DSMB will consist of a clinical oncologist, an
      ethicist, an independent statistician, and additional members, as deemed necessary. A DSMB
      charter will describe the planned evaluations and decision points used to determine the dose
      for Stage 2. An additional 18 to 42 evaluable participants will be enrolled into Stage 2
      based on the Stage 1 results (AUC0-∞). Thus a total of up to 54 evaluable participants could
      potentially be enrolled in this study (6 each from Stage 1, Cohorts 1 and 2, and up to 42
      participants in Stage 2).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stage 1 will consist of an initial cohort (Cohort 1) up to 6 evaluable participants who will
      receive a dosing regimen of Oraxol consisting of a 15-mg oral HM30181AK-US tablet plus an
      oral paclitaxel dose of 205 mg/m2, both administered once daily for 3 consecutive days. The
      stages and cohorts are further described in the &quot;Study Design - Stages and Cohorts&quot; table
      below. An interim analysis of pharmacokinetic (PK) data from Cohort 1 will be conducted to
      determine if the administered regimen would appear likely to achieve BE (AUC0-∞), if tested
      in a greater number of participants in Stage 2. If it appears unlikely that the selected
      regimen will meet the criteria for BE based on AUC0-∞ data, a second cohort (Cohort 2) of up
      to 6 evaluable participants may be enrolled in Stage 1, and the dose of paclitaxel in Oraxol
      may be adjusted by a maximum of +/- 25%. If Cohort 2 is enrolled, a second interim analysis
      will be conducted.

      After the interim analysis/analyses (depending on the outcomes), a decision will be made by
      consensus of the DSMB, Kinex, Zenith Technology, and the Principal Investigator as to what
      dose should be administered in Stage 2. The DSMB will consist of a clinical oncologist, an
      ethicist, an independent statistician, and additional members, as deemed necessary. A DSMB
      charter will describe the planned evaluations and decision points used to determine the dose
      for Stage 2. An additional 18 to 42 evaluable participants will be enrolled into Stage 2
      based on the Stage 1 results (AUC0-∞). Thus a total of up to 54 evaluable participants could
      potentially be enrolled in this study (6 each from Stage 1, Cohorts 1 and 2, and up to 42
      participants in Stage 2).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 27, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 27, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve zero time extrapolated to infinite time (AUC0-∞)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pharmacokinetic Sampling for IV Paclitaxel - Days 1 to 5, Pharmacokinetic Sampling for Oradoxel - Days 1 to 9</time_frame>
    <description>The equivalence of the extent of absorption will be determined by comparing the log-transformed AUC0-∞ of the oral paclitaxel to the log-transformed AUC0-∞ of IV paclitaxel. If the 90% CIs for AUC0-∞ fall within 80% to 125%, it will be concluded that the oral paclitaxel (in Oraxol) is bioequivalent to IV paclitaxel.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pharmacokinetic Sampling for IV Paclitaxel - Days 1 to 5, Pharmacokinetic Sampling for Oradoxel - Days 1 to 9</time_frame>
    <description>The primary PK parameters will be compared between IV paclitaxel (reference) and oral paclitaxel (test) formulations. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be performed (α=0.05) on the un-transformed and log10-transformed PK parameters Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ for paclitaxel. The ANOVA model will include sequence, subjects nested within the sequence, period, and formulation as factors. The significance of the sequence effect will be tested using the subjects nested within the sequence as the error term.
Two-sided 90% CIs for the log-transformed ratio of test/reference of the least squares means obtained from the ANOVA for Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time at which the highest drug concentration occurs (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pharmacokinetic Sampling for IV Paclitaxel - Days 1 to 5, Pharmacokinetic Sampling for Oradoxel - Days 1 to 9</time_frame>
    <description>The primary PK parameters will be compared between IV paclitaxel (reference) and oral paclitaxel (test) formulations. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be performed (α=0.05) on the un-transformed and log10-transformed PK parameters Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ for paclitaxel. The ANOVA model will include sequence, subjects nested within the sequence, period, and formulation as factors. The significance of the sequence effect will be tested using the subjects nested within the sequence as the error term.
Two-sided 90% CIs for the log-transformed ratio of test/reference of the least squares means obtained from the ANOVA for Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination phase half-life (t½)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pharmacokinetic Sampling for IV Paclitaxel - Days 1 to 5, Pharmacokinetic Sampling for Oradoxel - Days 1 to 9</time_frame>
    <description>The primary PK parameters will be compared between IV paclitaxel (reference) and oral paclitaxel (test) formulations. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be performed (α=0.05) on the un-transformed and log10-transformed PK parameters Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ for paclitaxel. The ANOVA model will include sequence, subjects nested within the sequence, period, and formulation as factors. The significance of the sequence effect will be tested using the subjects nested within the sequence as the error term.
Two-sided 90% CIs for the log-transformed ratio of test/reference of the least squares means obtained from the ANOVA for Cmax, AUC0-t and AUC0-∞ will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening until final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy)</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical event that occurs in a participant administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EASTERN COOPERATIVE ONCOLOGY GROUP STATUS</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -28 to -2) , Baseline for Treatment Period 2(Day -1) , and at the Final Visit.(within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy)</time_frame>
    <description>The participant's performance status should be assessed according to ECOG criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence A (Oraxol, IV paclitaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment sequences will be:
A Oraxol (paclitaxel + HM30181) on Days 1, 2, and 3 of Treatment Period 1 followed by IV paclitaxel on Day 1 of Treatment Period 2 B IV paclitaxel on Day 1 of Treatment Period 1 followed by Oraxol on Days 1, 2, and 3 of Treatment Period 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence B (IV paclitaxel, Oraxol)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment sequences will be:
A IV paclitaxel on Day 1 of Treatment Period 1 followed by Oraxol on Days 1, 2, and 3 of Treatment Period 2 B Oraxol (paclitaxel + HM30181) on Days 1, 2, and 3 of Treatment Period 1 followed by IV paclitaxel on Day 1 of Treatment Period 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HM30181 methanesulfonate monohydrate plus oral paclitaxel capsules</intervention_name>
    <description>HM30181 methanesulfonate monohydrate plus oral paclitaxel capsules
Oral paclitaxel capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence A (Oraxol, IV paclitaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence B (IV paclitaxel, Oraxol)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ORAXOL</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed written informed consent

          2. Males and females ≥18 years of age on day of consent

          3. Cancer patients for whom treatment with IV paclitaxel at 80 mg/m2has been recommended
             by their oncologist, either as monotherapy or in combination with other agents

          4. Adequate hematologic status at Screening/Baseline:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5 x 109/L

               -  Platelet count ≥100 x 109/L

               -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥90 g/L

          5. Adequate liver function at Screening/Baseline as demonstrated by:

               -  Total bilirubin of ≤20 μmol/L or ≤30 μmol/L for participants with liver
                  metastasis

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤3 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or ≤5 x ULN if
                  liver metastasis is present

               -  Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) ≤3 x ULN or ≤5 x ULN if liver or bone metastasis are
                  present

               -  ALP &gt;5 x ULN if liver or bone metastasis are present and the major fraction of
                  ALP is from bone metastasis, at the discretion of the Investigator

               -  Gamma glutamyl transferase (GGT) &lt;10 x ULN

          6. Adequate renal function at Screening/Baseline as demonstrated by serum creatinine ≤177
             μmol/L or creatinine clearance &gt;50 mL/min as calculated by the Cockcroft and Gault
             formula

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 16

          8. Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          9. Willing to fast for 8 hours before and 4 hours after Oraxol administration

         10. Willing to abstain from alcohol consumption for 3 days before the first dose of study
             drug through the completion of protocol-specified PK sampling in Treatment Period 2

         11. Willing to refrain from caffeine consumption for 12 hours before each treatment period
             through the completion of protocol-specified PK sampling for that dose

         12. Women must be postmenopausal (&gt;12 months without menses) or surgically sterile (ie, by
             hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy) or, if sexually active, must be using
             effective contraception (ie, oral contraceptives, intrauterine device, double barrier
             method of condom and spermicide) and agree to continue use of contraception for the
             duration of their participation in the study. Women of childbearing potential must
             agree to use contraception for 30 days after their last dose of study drug.

         13. Sexually active male participants must use a barrier method of contraception during
             the study and agree to continue the use of male contraception for at least 30 days
             after the last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Currently taking a prohibited concomitant medication:

               -  Strong inhibitors (eg, ketoconazole) or strong inducers (eg, rifampin or St.
                  John's Wort) of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4 (within 2 weeks prior to the start of
                  dosing in the study)

               -  Strong inhibitors (eg, gemfibrozil) or strong inducers (eg, rifampin) of CYP2C8
                  (within 2 weeks prior to the start of dosing in the study)

               -  Known P-glycoprotein (P-gp) inhibitors or inducers. Participants who are taking
                  such medications but who are otherwise eligible may be enrolled if they
                  discontinue the medication ≥1 week before dosing and remain off that medication
                  through the end of PK sampling after the administration of the second study
                  treatment.

               -  An oral medication with a narrow therapeutic index known to be a P-gp substrate
                  (eg, digoxin, dabigatran) within 24 hours prior to start of dosing in the study

          2. Use of warfarin. Participants receiving warfarin who are otherwise eligible and who
             may be appropriately managed with low molecular weight heparin, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, may be enrolled in the study provided they are switched to low molecular
             weight heparin at least 7 days prior to receiving study treatment.

          3. Unresolved toxicity from prior chemotherapy (participants must have recovered all
             significant toxicity to ≤ Grade 1 CTCAE toxicity1 from previous anticancer treatments
             or previous investigational agents). This does not extend to symptoms or findings that
             are attributable to the underlying disease

          4. Received investigational agents within 14 days or 5 half-lives prior to the first
             study dosing day, whichever is longer

          5. Women of childbearing potential who are pregnant or breastfeeding

          6. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, clinically significant myocardial
             infarction within the last 6 months, unstable angina pectoris, clinically significant
             cardiac arrhythmia, bleeding disorder, chronic pulmonary disease requiring oxygen, or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements

          7. Major surgery to the upper GI tract, or have a history of GI disease or other medical
             condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator may interfere with oral drug
             absorption

          8. A known history of allergy to paclitaxel. Participants whose allergy was due to the IV
             solvent (such as Cremophor®) and not paclitaxel will be eligible for this study.

          9. Any other condition which the Investigator believes would make a subject's
             participation in the study not acceptable
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Cutler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Athenex, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monash Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Auckland City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dunedin Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dunedin</city>
        <zip>9016</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wellington Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wellington</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lotung Poh-Ai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ilan</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shuang Ho hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Taipei City</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tri-Service General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 14, 2020</submitted>
    <submission_canceled>May 18, 2020</submission_canceled>
    <submitted>June 17, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>July 2, 2020</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

