<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04034680</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SI0303150608</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04034680</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Interdisciplinary Model for Evaluation and Treatment of Neuropsychiatric Symptoms in Home Care Services</brief_title>
  <official_title>The TIME -Targeted Interdisciplinary Model for Evaluation and Treatment of Neuropsychiatric Symptoms - for Continuity of Care in Home Care Services</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sykehuset Innlandet HF</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sykehuset Innlandet HF</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Continuity of care in home care services is necessary to facilitate the assessment and
      treatment of persons with dementia and cognitive failure. TIME (Targeted Interdisciplinary
      Model for Evaluation and Treatment of Neuropsychiatric Symptoms) is a multi-component
      intervention with a biopsychosocial approach, based on the theoretical framework of cognitive
      behavioral therapy and person-centred care. The trial is designed to assess the effects of
      TIME on Neuropsychiatric symptoms for persons (NPS) with dementia in home care services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Targeted Interdisciplinary Model for Evaluation and Treatment of Neuropsychiatric
      Symptoms (TIME) is a multi-component intervention with a biopsychosocial approach, based on
      the theoretical framework of cognitive behavioral therapy and person-centred care. TIME
      consists of a manual based multicomponent program which includes a rigorous assessment,
      treatment, and the evaluation of neuropsychiatrc symptoms (NPS).

      The cluster RCT will contain two parallel groups, where randomisation is performed based on
      clusters. One municipality is one cluster, randomized to receive either the intervention with
      TIME or a brief two hours education-only intervention about dementia and NPS for the control
      group. Totally 10 municipalities will be included. Data will be collected at baseline before
      randomisation and at the end of the implementing phase. Measurements at patient level are
      taken at baseline prior to randomization and after 6 months. The primary outcome measure is
      difference in change between the intervention group and the control group from baseline to
      follow up at 6 months in the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD).

      Data collection will be performed by project nurses recruited outside the home care services.
      They will interview the staff or family members who knows the patient best. The assessors
      will be blinded to the randomization of the home care services. Interviews will be done by
      telephone or face-to-face, depending on what is best for the person interviewed.

      After the intervention focus group interviews with staff and family members will be
      conducted.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cluster randomized trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will be masked for the study arm they are randomised to. Staff in the home care service are aware of the study arm their patients are in, while assessors that will interview home care staff by telephone are masked for study randomisation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Affective symptoms measured by the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline of affective symptoms as defined in the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD), a scale ranging from 0-38 where a higher score indicates more severe depressive symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory - nursing home version (NPI-NH): Sub syndrome anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the sub syndrome affective symptoms of the single items anxiety and depression as measured with the NPI-NH. Each single item is scored from 0-12, where a higher score indicates a more severe symptom.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NPI-NH: all separate items</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline of the NPI-NH, scores on all the 12 items. Each single item is scored from 0-12, where a higher score indicates a more severe symptom.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NPI-NH: caregiver distress score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in caregiver distress by the NPI-NH caregiver distress score. The caregiver distress on each NPI-NH item is scored from 0-5, where a higher score indicates more severe distress</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life measured by the scale QUALID</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in quality of life by whitch will be assessed by the scale QUALID: Quality of life in late-stage dementia scale, a scale consisting of 11 single items scored from 1-5 (total score 11-55) where a lower score indicates a better QoL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Relatives Stress scale Score (RSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in relatives stress assessed by the scale RSS: Relatives Stress scale Score, a scale ranging from 0-60 where a higher score indicates more severe distress</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Transferring to nursing home</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the number of patients transferring to nursing home during follow up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal data set (MDS): patient rejection of care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in the patients rejection of care assessed by MDS: Minimal dataset (MDS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home care services - Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Totally 5 municipalities (25 persons with dementia) will be included in the intervention group, and will receive training in the TIME model. This includes two hours of lectures about dementia and neuropsychiatric symptoms (NPS) and three hours of training and roleplay in using the TIME model. The staff of the home care service will receive the TIME manual and access to the TIME website with access to additional educational and information files. From each municipality, three staff members, called TIME administrators, will receive additional three hours of lectures and roleplay in TIME, and will thereafter have the responsibility for performing the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home care services - Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Totally 5 municipalities (25 persons with dementia) will be included in the Control group. The municipalities in the control group will receive the same two hours lectures about dementia and NPS as the intervention group. After the cluster RCT pilot study is ended, municipalities in the control group will receive the same three-hour lessons in the TIME as the intervention group of municipalities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TIME</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention of the TIME model includes two hours of lectures about dementia and NPS and three hours of training and roleplay in using TIME. The staff of the home care service will receive the TIME manual and access to the TIME website with access to additional educational materials. From each municipality, three staff members called TIME administrators, will receive additional three hours of lectures and roleplay in TIME, and will thereafter have the responsibility for performing the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home care services - Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education-only intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Staff in the home care service in municipalities in the control group will receive thesame two hours lectures about dementia and NPS as the intervention grorp. After the cluster RCT pilot study is ended, municipalities in the control group will receive the same three-hour lessons in the TIME as the intervention group of municipalities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home care services - Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Dementia, defined as a score of 1 or more on the Clinical Dementia Rating Scale (CDR)

          -  A minimum of 15 minutes of home care services per day for the last 4 weeks

          -  NPS, defined as a score on the NPI-NH affective subsyndrom (NPI depression + NPI
             anxiety) of 12 or more

          -  Informed consent from the participant or family or next-of-kin

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Terminal disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sverre Bergh, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Research centre for Age-related Functional decline and Disease (AFS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sverre Bergh, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+47 45679393</phone>
    <email>sverre.bergh@sykehuset-innlandet.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kari-Anne Hoel</last_name>
    <phone>+47 97128559</phone>
    <email>kari-anne.hoel@sykehuset-innlandet.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Research centre for Age-related Functional decline and Disease (AFS) at Innlandet Hospital Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottestad</city>
        <zip>2312</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sverre Bergh, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+4745679393</phone>
      <email>sverre.bergh@sykehuset-innlandet.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kari-Anne Hoel</last_name>
      <phone>+47 97128559</phone>
      <email>kari-anne.hoel@sykehuset-innlandet.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Behavioral symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Nevropsychiatric symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychological symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>The TIME model</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

