<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04037319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STH20223</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04037319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Atrial Fibrillation After Surgery for Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>AFAR</acronym>
  <official_title>Atrial Fibrillation After Resection (AFAR): A PROGRESS III Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will report the incidence of atrial fibrillation after elective colorectal cancer
      resection in the over 65 age group. This will be used to validate a risk model for the
      development of post-operative atrial fibrillation.

      Eligible patients will undergo electrocardiogram based screening for atrial fibrillation, as
      well as brain natriuretic peptide tests prior to surgery. They will undergo 24 hour holter
      monitor prior to surgery, and at 30 and 90 days following surgery.

      The primary outcome will be occurrence of atrial fibrillation within 90 days of surgery.
      Secondary outcomes include quality of life change, use of hospital services for atrial
      fibrillation, and complications of atrial fibrillation. This will be used to validate the
      pre-existing model for prediction of atrial fibrillation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background Atrial fibrillation is an irregularly irregular heartbeat and occurs in around
      1.5% of the population. It is associated with negative clinical outcomes such as cardiac
      failure and mortality. It is strongly implicated in the evolution of stroke, which carries
      significant burden and cost to patients and the National Health Service (NHS). Atrial
      fibrillation can be triggered by major physiological stresses such as surgery. The literature
      suggests that symptomatic atrial fibrillation occurs in 10% of patients within 90 days of
      surgery. This means that a proportion of patients may have undetected atrial fibrillation,
      and require treatment to reduce their risk of complications. As the investigators move
      towards stratified and personalised medicine, it is important to identify the characteristics
      of the patients at risk of developing atrial fibrillation after surgery in order to mitigate
      the effects of the condition. This research group has proposed a basic model to stratify
      patients into high risk groups for post-operative atrial fibrillation, although this requires
      testing and refinement in a prospective study.

      Aims To estimate the rate of atrial fibrillation following colorectal cancer surgery and to
      characterise patients at highest risk of atrial fibrillation following surgery for colorectal
      cancer.

      Method A prospective study of patients over the age of 65 undergoing colorectal cancer
      resection will be conducted across 15 colorectal units in the United Kingdom. It will recruit
      720 patients over an 18 month period. The study has been designed with regard to public and
      patient involvement. Patients over the age of 65 undergoing surgery for colorectal cancer
      with curative intent and no prior diagnosis of atrial fibrillation will be eligible for
      inclusion. Participants will be screened prior to entry with an electrocardiogram (ECG).
      Following consent, routine demographic data, EQ-5D-5L (five dimension), and blood sample for
      Brain Natriuretic Peptide (BNP) will be collected. A 24-hour cardiac rhythm recording will be
      undertaken prior to surgery to confirm the absences of atrial fibrillation. ECG will be
      repeated on the day of discharge and 24 hour rhythm recordings repeated at 30 and 90 days
      post surgery. EQ-5D-5L x will be recorded at 90 days along with any use of health services
      for cardiac symptoms. Participants diagnosed with atrial fibrillation during the study will
      be directed to local inpatient or primary care services as appropriate. Demographic
      characteristics, ECG parameters and BNP will be combined with a previously derived model and
      tested for ability to predict atrial fibrillation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of atrial fibrillation within 90 days of colorectal cancer surgery, defined as ≥30 seconds of atrial fibrillation identified on a 24-hour cardiac monitor OR absence of p waves and irregularly irregular rhythm on an electrocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 90 days of colorectal cancer surgery</time_frame>
    <description>24-hour recordings will be undertaken at 30 &amp; 90 days post surgery, and electrocardiogram on the day of discharge from hospital.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life change (EQ-5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 90 days of colorectal cancer surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life change as measured using EQ-5D-5L from baseline to 90 days post-surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of complications of atrial fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 90 days of colorectal cancer surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Includes stroke and embolic events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of health services for atrial fibrillation or sequelae of atrial fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 90 days of colorectal cancer surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Use of health services including for treatment of atrial fibrillation or consequences such as cardiac failure, thromboembolism, or stroke.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">720</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation New Onset</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Main cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Will undergo surgery for colorectal cancer with curative intent as planned by local cancer multidisciplinary team.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>24 Hour Holter Monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>24 hour holter monitor to be performed pre-operatively, and at day 30 and 90 post-operatively.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Main cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with Colorectal Cancer undergoing elective resection with curative intent.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged ≥65 years old

          -  Undergoing elective surgery for colorectal cancer with curative intent

          -  No prior diagnosis of atrial fibrillation.

          -  Willing to consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged less than 65 years old

          -  Pre-existing atrial fibrillation (persistent or paroxysmal)

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Life expectancy &lt;12 months

          -  Prisoners

          -  Known pregnancy

          -  Lack mental capacity

          -  Patients with limited English language as there is no funding to cover costs of
             translation of materials
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Lee, MBChB PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Debby Hawkins, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+(0)114 243 43 43</phone>
    <email>debby.hawkins@sth.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <state>South Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>S5 7AU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Debby Hawkins, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+44 0114 2434343</phone>
      <email>debby.hawkins@sth.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew J Lee, MBChB PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven R Brown, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heywood EG, Drake TM, Bradburn M, Lee J, Wilson MJ, Lee MJ. Atrial Fibrillation After Gastrointestinal Surgery: Incidence and Associated Risk Factors. J Surg Res. 2019 Jun;238:23-28. doi: 10.1016/j.jss.2019.01.017. Epub 2019 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>30735962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chebbout R, Heywood EG, Drake TM, Wild JRL, Lee J, Wilson M, Lee MJ. A systematic review of the incidence of and risk factors for postoperative atrial fibrillation following general surgery. Anaesthesia. 2018 Apr;73(4):490-498. doi: 10.1111/anae.14118. Epub 2017 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>29105078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

