<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04036474</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIUM/504/14/11/2/IREC650</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04036474</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development, Implementation, and Evaluation of School-based Smoking Prevention Education Program Among Non-smoking Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development, Implementation, and Evaluation of School-based Smoking Prevention Education Program Among Non-smoking Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Preventing smoking among adolescents is critical to end the epidemic of smoking in Malaysia.
      Despite the implementation of several smoking prevention programs, the prevalence of
      adolescent smoking and experimenting with tobacco in Malaysia is still increasing. Therefore,
      the purpose of this quasi-experimental study was to evaluate the effectiveness of Smoking
      Prevention Education Programs (SPEP) in preventing the smoking initiation among non-smoker
      adolescents based on their smoking status on follow-up and smoking intention, which includes;
      attitude, subjective norms, and perceived behavioural control as described by the Theory of
      Planned Behaviour. A total of 140 Primary five students (non- smokers) were involved in this
      study. Four schools in Kuantan district were randomly assigned to intervention and control
      groups. The intervention schools received a lecture on the hazards of smoking and SPEP
      intervention whereas the control schools received just a lecture on the hazards of smoking.
      The questionnaires and exhale carbon monoxide levels were first assessed at baseline and then
      again after three months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 28, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of students who smoke</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of students who started smoking by the end of 3 months as assessed by a self-reported questionnaire and through measurement of exhaled CO levels using a handheld CO analyzer (piCO Smokerlyzer, Bedfont Scientific Ltd, England).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score of students' intention to smoke</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-administering questionnaires were used to collect the baseline (before intervention) and follow-up (at 3 months post-intervention) data in this study. The questionnaires with translated versions (in English and Malay) were adapted and modified from the previous study by Melson (2014) based on the Theory of Planned Behaviour.
Out of 24-items in the questionnaire, there are 3 items measuring behaviour intention on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = 'strongly disagree', 5 = 'strongly agree'), a higher value represents less intention to initiate smoking. Sample question for measuring behaviour intention include &quot;I intend to be a non-smoker&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score of students' attitudes towards smoking</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Out of 24-items, there are 9 items measuring attitude on a 5-point Likert scale, a higher value represents an attitude of being in favor of smoking initiation. A sample question for measuring attitude include &quot;I want to be a non-smoker&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score of students' perception of subjective norms</measure>
    <time_frame>3months</time_frame>
    <description>There are 6 items measuring subjective norms on the 5-point Likert scale, a higher value represents an individual experiencing social pressure not to initiate smoking. Sample question for measuring subjective norms include &quot;Most people who are important to me think that I should be a non-smoker&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score of students' perceived behavioural control</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>There are 6 items measuring perceived behaviour control on a 5-point Likert scale, a higher value represents an individual feeling in control from initiating smoking. Sample question for measuring perceived behavior control include &quot;For me to be a non-smoker would be easy&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">145</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Behaviors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smoking Prevention Education Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to the lecture on the hazards of smoking, students received the SPEP intervention. The SPEP consisted of three lessons and each lesson took one to two hours to be implemented. The SPEP intervention was delivered to participants in their usual classroom setting, during school hours combined with relevant school subjects such as physical education class. The duration of SPEP intervention took approximately one month.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediately after the collection of baseline data, students received a one-time lecture on the hazards of smoking by the research assistant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smoking Prevention Education Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The SPEP consisted of three lessons and each lesson took one to two hours to be implemented. SPEP was conducted through direct and indirect method. Direct method was conducted through lectures, question and answer, role play and educational videos. The tools used were video projectors and Power Point presentations. On the other hand, the indirect method was done through distributing of badge buttons and fridge magnets &quot;Be Free from Smoking&quot;. This method brought a simple message to increase awareness among adolescents to prevent smoking uptake. All instruments and protocols in this intervention were pilot tested to confirm feasibility and cultural appropriateness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smoking Prevention Education Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary school students (standard 5)

          -  11years' old

          -  Non- smoker (CO level less than 4ppm) to maintain baseline never- smoker

          -  Both genders

          -  Consented by parent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ex-smoker (self- reporting) and smoker (CO level more than 4ppm)

          -  Students unable to understand and read the national language (Bahasa Malaysia)

          -  Children with special needs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University, Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Esperanza Debby Ng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Assistant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

