<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04036318</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16.02.PPT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04036318</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Presumptive Periodic Treatment (PPT) of Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PPT</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Presumptive Periodic Treatment (PPT) of Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs) Among High-risk Populations Including Men Who Have Sex With Men, Female Sex Workers (FSW) and Mining Populations in Tanzania.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute for Medical Research, Tanzania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute for Medical Research, Tanzania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sexually transmitted infections (STI) are important causes of reproductive health morbidity
      and mortality, and have long been implicated as major co-factors in the sexual transmission
      of HIV. Both ulcerative and non-ulcerative STI have been found to be strongly associated with
      HIV in cross-sectional and prospective studies and hence STI prevention and care are
      important aspects of HIV prevention.

      Periodic Presumptive Treatment of STIS (PPT) where risk populations are presumptively treated
      with a single dose of Azithromycin+Cefixime in regular intervals of 3 months has been shown
      to be effective in reducing STI prevalence at population level and has recently been
      integrated into the National STI guidelines of Tanzania. The USAID funded Sauti program will
      be one of the first to implement these new guidelines and roll out PPT in high risk
      populations in selected regions in Tanzania. This study will evaluate the impact of PPT as
      delivered by the Sauti program on prevalence of STIs in men who have sex with men and female
      sex workers in Dar es Salaam and Shinyanga respectively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This intervention linked study evaluates the impact of PPT on population level in FSW and MSM
      in Tanzania (Shinyanga and Dar es Salaam respectively). It is expected that PPT will reduce
      laboratory diagnosed STIs by 50% in the population after a roll out of 6 months.

      This evaluation uses a cross-sectional venue-based sampling design. Three rounds of cross
      sectional data collection will be undertaken for MSM in Dar es Salaam and FSW in Shinyanga at
      three months intervals (baseline, 3 months and 6 months). The change in prevalence will be
      measured between baseline and 6 months assessments. The interim assessment will be used to
      refine the sample size. Study participants will be recruited in venues frequented by FSW
      (Shinyanga) and MSM (Dar es Salaam) in wards where Sauti operates. Respondents will be
      continuously sampled from all venues until sample size is reached. In each round of data
      collection, study participants will undergo physical examination, biological specimen
      collection, laboratory and HIV tests and a questionnaire.

      STI prevalence in MSM and FSWs will be measured during each survey and laboratory-confirmed
      STI prevalence (gonorrhoea, chlamydia, syphilis) will be assessed.

      Additionally, effect on STI prevalence in the bridge population will be measured by
      retrospective analysis of routine data for the prevalence of syndromic STIs among the mining
      population in Shinyanga, as collected in the context of the Sauti program mobile biomedical
      services (CBHTC+), which will visit the major mines in Shinyanga prior PPT implementation and
      after each survey. By the term major mines, we mean mines with large population of male mine
      workers (between 1000-2000 male mine workers) at higher risk of HIV rather than mines with
      modern mining infrastructure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 12, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 12, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of prevalence of laboratory confirmed bacterial STIs</measure>
    <time_frame>After six months of periodic presumptive treatment of STIs</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in prevalence of laboratory confirmed STIs (a combined measure of gonorrhea, chlamydia and Treponema pallidum) in men who have sex with men (MSMs) in Dar es Salaam and female sex workers (FSWs) in Shinyanga after six months of presumptive treatment of STIs (PPT).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of prevalence of syndromic STIs</measure>
    <time_frame>After six months of periodic presumptive treatment of STIs among FSW in Shinyanga</time_frame>
    <description>Syndromic STI prevalence (Genital ulcers disease (GUD), Anorectal Syndrome (ARS), Urethral Discharge Syndrome (UDS), Painful scrotal swelling (PSS)) among male clients of FSW in Shinyanga mines (bridge population) after six months of availability of PPT to FSWs. initiation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Associations between demographic, socio-economic, behavioral and biological risk factors, STI prevalence and PPT impact.</measure>
    <time_frame>After six months of periodic presumptive treatment of STIs among FSW in Shinyanga</time_frame>
    <description>The association will determined by using the logistic regression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in sexual risk taking behaviors while receiving PPT</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in sexual risk behaviors will be determined by comparing the baseline prevalence and prevalence after six months of PPT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of cervical cancer lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of cervical cancer lesions, will be assessed through Visual Inspection with Acetic Acid (VIA), among the FSW in the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Human Papilloma Virus (HPV), HIV, Hepatitis B and C</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of Human Papilloma Virus (HPV), HIV, Hepatitis B and C will be assessed from the bio-specimens of serum and genital swabs collected during the surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4350</enrollment>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Diseases, Bacterial</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Anorectal swabs, Endocervical swabs and dry swabs from ulcerative lesions will be collected
      for the assessment of the bacterial sexually transmitted infections. In addition, swabs will
      be taken from urethral discharges in men. 5 milliliters of blood will be collected from each
      study participant assessment of viral infections such as HIV and viral hepatitis (HBV and
      HCV)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This study aims to reach men who have sex with men (MSM) in Dar es Salaam region and female
        sex workers (FSWs) in Shinyanga region both of which are representative of the population
        in Tanzania.

        The study also is expected to have an effect on the bridging population in Shinyanga
        region. Bridge population in Shinyanga, are male mine workers who are considered to benefit
        from PPT provided to Female sex workers by Sauti program.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Willing to give oral informed consent

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Is referred from the pre-selected recruitment venues and present and recruitment card.

          -  Sexually active in the last 6 months

          -  At least half of self-reported monthly income is generated through sex work (FSWs
             only)

          -  Men who engage in sexual relations with other men regardless of the motivation (MSMs
             only)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not willing to give informed consent

          -  Not sexually active in the last 6 months

          -  State of intoxication from recreational drugs or alcohol use or other reasons which
             would prevent voluntary and informed consent to the study as judged by investigator

          -  Pregnant women - (determined through pregnancy screening questions used by Sauti)

          -  Does not have a study referral card
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amani Shao, MD; MPH; PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute for Medical Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amani F Shao, MD; MPH; PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+255 22 2771346</phone>
    <email>shaotz@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Evodius Kuringe, MD;MSPH</last_name>
    <phone>+255-28-2500399</phone>
    <email>evokur@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shinyanga Region</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shinyanga</city>
        <state>Kahama</state>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Albert Komba, MD; MPH</last_name>
      <phone>+255 22 2771346</phone>
      <email>albert.komba@jhpiego.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gaspar Mbita, BSc; MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+255 767 898 956</phone>
      <email>Gaspar.Mbita@jhpiego.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dar es Salaam region</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dar es Salaam</city>
        <state>Temeke</state>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Albert Komba, MD; MPH</last_name>
      <phone>+255 22 2771346</phone>
      <email>albert.komba@jhpiego.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gaspar Mbita, BSc; MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+255 767 898 956</phone>
      <email>Gaspar.Mbita@jhpiego.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institute for Medical Research, Tanzania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Amani Shao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sexually Transmitted Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Periodic Presumptive Treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases, Bacterial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>As part of the open data policy, all data emanating from this study will be shared with other researchers</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The IPD will be shared during the study closure</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Will be determined by the funder and sponsor</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

