<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04036396</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-000165</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>OS17-LA-003</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04036396</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention Support for People Leaving Jail</brief_title>
  <acronym>MEPS</acronym>
  <official_title>Prevention Support for People Leaving Jail Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Los Angeles Centers For Alcohol and Drug Abuse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Charles Drew University of Medicine and Science</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>California HIV/AIDS Research Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will provide HIV prevention and related support services to men who have sex with
      men and transgender women who have substance use disorders and are either leaving jail or
      recently released from jail, living in a residential facility providing substance use
      services or supportive housing . The researchers will compare the utilization of HIV
      prevention and other support services between individuals who receive routine case management
      provided following enrollment to those who have access to GeoPassport, a global position
      service (GPS)-based mobile app, incentives, and peer mentor support.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will enroll 300 people in jail or immediately post-release from custody for
      those who transfer to a residential facility or supportive housing facility. During the
      trial, half of participants will be randomized into a control group that will receive usual
      care consistent with the facility in which they live, along with referrals customized to
      their needs and preferences to share with a case manager. They will be compared to the other
      half of participants randomized to the intervention group that, in addition to receiving
      customized referral sources, will also receive the GeoPassport App, incentives, and the
      support of a trained Peer Mentor for six months. The GeoPassport App will provide
      participants with tools for tracking goals and progress toward meeting them, assistance in
      locating services, appointment and medication reminders, opportunities to provide feedback on
      service providers, and built-in tracking and distribution of rewards (incentives) for service
      utilization. GeoPassport will assist Peer Mentors in monitoring participants' service
      utilization. The Peer Mentors will provide encouragement, role modeling, accompaniment to
      appointments, and assistance with goal setting, problem-solving, and reducing logistical and
      psychosocial barriers to service engagement. The intervention can be delivered in person or
      remotely in order to comply with necessary social distancing during the COVID-19 pandemic.
      Participants in both groups will be followed to assess whether those offered the intervention
      are more likely to meet the specific prevention targets described in the Specific Aims. The
      intervention lasts 6 months following departure from jail or residential recovery facility.
      Participants are interviewed at 3, 6, and 9 months from the same point as the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The Mobile Enhanced Prevention Support (MEPS) intervention is designed to support, motivate, and facilitate engagement in preventive health care activities in the period of community reentry following jail. Three components: support from a selected Peer Mentor (PM), incentives, and a developed mobile application. Client-driven approach, in which participants are encouraged to address priorities and immediate needs for that they identify a client-centered needs assessment, prioritization, and wellness planning process, especially social determinants of health that may discourage or undermine preventive health measures.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants establishing a primary care provider who can prescribe PrEP (pre-exposure prophylaxis)</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the participant identifying and completing an appointment with a primary care provider who is willing and able to prescribe HIV pre-exposure prophylaxis. Provide documentation of the appointment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants obtaining screening for PrEP</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the participant completing the screening process for PrEP with an eligible provider or PrEP navigator. Provide documentation of the appointment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who initiate PrEP regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the participant obtaining a prescription for PrEP, providing documentation, reporting taking the medication</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who demonstrate minimal adherence to PrEP</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the participant self-reporting taking prescribed PrEP at least 4 days per week over the prior 30 days</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who remain on PrEP for at least 3 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The participant will provide documentation of filled PrEP prescriptions for 3 or more months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who undergo a HIV test every 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the participant self-reporting having obtained HIV testing every 3 months over the 12 month follow-up period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who undergo a test for gonorrhea, syphilis, and chlamydia every 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the participant self-reporting having obtained testing for these 3 bacterial sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) every 6 months over the 12 month follow-up period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who undergo a test for hepatitis C</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the participant self-reporting having obtained at least one test for Hepatitis C</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants obtaining treatment for substance use disorders (SUDs) in the community</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the participant self-report of completing initial recommended SUD appointments within 3 months of jail release, consistent with each participant's recommended American Society of Addiction Medicine (ASAM) level of care</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who remain engaged in treatment for substance use disorders (SUDs) in the community,</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the participant self-reporting remaining engaged in treatment (i.e., continuing to attend meetings, counseling or other treatment activities) as defined by the recommended ASAM level of care in the 3 months prior to each follow-up interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants in each arm receiving care and treatment for newly diagnosed HIV or STD infections.</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report of whether or not participants received follow-up care and treatment for HIV, STD, and hepatitis C infections diagnosed during study follow-up (n=300)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants in each arm experiencing recidivism</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the comparative effectiveness of each intervention arm on reducing recidivism (n=300), quantified as the number of respondents who are reincarcerated and the total number of reincarcerations per arm over the study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Temporal service utilization patterns of intervention arm participants</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the temporal distribution of PrEP uptake and supportive social service utilization patterns of the participants in the MEPS intervention arm using data collected via the GeoPassport mobile app (n=150).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geographic service utilization patterns of intervention arm participants</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Report the geographic distribution of PrEP uptake and supportive social service utilization patterns of the participants in the MEPS intervention arm using data collected via the GeoPassport mobile app (n=150).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Diseases, Bacterial</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Substance Use Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Case Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A client-centered assessment of priorities and needs, substance abuse-focused transitional case management, and customized prevention and testing referrals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Enhanced Prevention Support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of Care in addition to the Mobile Enhanced Prevention Support Program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mobile Enhanced Prevention Support</intervention_name>
    <description>Access to the newly developed GeoPassport App, incentives for accessing identified services, and a trained Peer Mentor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Enhanced Prevention Support</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MEPS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care plus Customized Referrals</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the control arm will continue to receive services they would normally receive consistent with the setting in which they were recruited. This includes substance use treatment in jail, substance use treatment at a residential recovery facility, and/or supportive housing services. The study will provide referrals customized to their needs and preferences.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Enhanced Prevention Support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Case Management</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. housed in K6G unit or in a residential facility with substance use services (i.e.,
             residential treatment or recovery bridge housing) or supportive housing within six
             months of release

          2. ages 18-49 years

          3. screens positive for substance use disorder (SUD)

          4. Reports sexual intercourse with a male or a male-to-female transgender woman in the
             six months prior to jail entry

          5. if recruited in jail, is likely to be remain either in custody for at least four more
             days, but less than 3 more months based on scheduled court dates, current sentence,
             treatment plan, etc.

          6. has not received an HIV diagnosis (based on self-report)

          7. plans to reside in Los Angeles County for the 12 months following enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. does not have a smartphone and is not willing to obtain one post-release,

          2. is not able to speak and understand English, and

          3. does not have sufficient reading skills to operate a mobile app
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Self-identifies as a man Self-identifies as a woman or a transgender woman (Note all participants will be recruited from a correctional facility for men and will have been labeled male at birth.)</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nina T Harawa, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gabriel Edwards, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>310-267-0609</phone>
    <email>GEdwards@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charles L Hilliard, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>323-563-5865</phone>
    <email>charleshilliard@cdrewu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County Men's Central Jail</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauren Wolchok, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles Center for Alcohol and Drug Abuse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Fe Springs</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90670</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles McWells</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nina T. Harawa, MPH, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor-in-Residence</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV prevention and testing</keyword>
  <keyword>sexually transmitted disease (STD) prevention and testing</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Incarceration</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases, Bacterial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

