<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04037917</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SP-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04037917</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>First-In-Man Study for an Ophthalmic Synthetic Tissue Substitute</brief_title>
  <official_title>The CorNeat EverPatch - a First-In-Man Clinical Study for Demonstrating the Safety of a Synthetic Tissue Substitute for Concealment of Artificial Implants and Glaucoma Tube Shunts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CorNeat Vision Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CorNeat Vision Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Name: The CorNeat EverPatch - a First-In-Man Clinical Study for demonstrating the
      Safety of a Synthetic Tissue Substitute for concealment of artificial implants and glaucoma
      tube shunts

      Objective: The objective of this clinical trial is to demonstrate the Safety of the Corneat
      Everpatch for concealment of artificial implants and glaucoma tube shunts

      The study will consist 10 subjects requiring concealment of a glaucoma shunt or other
      ophthalmic implant. Eligible subjects who signs an ICF will be enrolled to the study.
      Subjects will be implanted with the Corneart EverPatch as part of a glaucoma shunt surgery or
      during a corrective surgery to repair a breached conjunctiva over an implanted device.
      Subjects will be monitored for a period of 12 months post-op during which follow up visits
      will occur at 1 week, 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 &amp; 12 months following surgery including clinical
      examination of the operated eye using slit-lamp biomicroscopy and imaging using OCT or UBM
      (will be performed only at the 6 &amp; 12 months follow up visits).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Name: The CorNeat EverPatch - a First-In-Man Clinical Study for demonstrating the
      Safety of a Synthetic Tissue Substitute for concealment of artificial implants and glaucoma
      tube shunts

      Objective: The objective of this clinical trial is to demonstrate the Safety of the Corneat
      Everpatch for concealment of artificial implants and glaucoma tube shunts

      Study endpoints:

      Primary Safety Endpoint:

      The frequency of all Unanticipated Adverse Device-related Events (UADE) or treatment-related
      adverse events, during and following implantation and follow-up for up to 12 months will be
      10% or less.

      Effectiveness Endpoints:

      Primary: Conjunctival integrity at the implantation site will be 90% or more. Secondary:
      Stability in patch dimensions, less than 10% change (length, projected width and thickness)
      measured by OCT after 1-week and follow-up for up to 12 months post-implantation in 90% of
      the implanted patients.

      Intended uses: The CorNeat EverPatch intended use is concealment of artificial ophthalmic
      implants and glaucoma tube shunts.

      The clinical investigation of the CorNeat EverPatch device is essential to validate its
      safety and efficacy in its target implantation site and to substantiate regulatory clearance.
      Clinical investigation of a medical device must be in compliance with Good Clinical Practice
      as set forth in ISO 14155, which addresses good clinical practices for the design, conduct,
      recording and reporting of clinical investigations carried out in human subjects for the
      purpose of assessing the safety and performance of medical devices for regulatory purposes,
      as well as applicable local laws and regulations.

      Study Population: 10 subjects requiring concealment of artificial ophthalmic implants and
      glaucoma tube shunts. Unilateral and bi-lateral. The device can be implanted in patients'
      right or left eye (selection according to Principle Investigator's discretion).

      Study Duration: Subjects will be followed-up for 12 months from device implantation date.

      Visit Schedule:

      • Screening: Day 0-7, Subjects will sign an Informed Consent Form (ICF) on screening visit
      and baseline assessments for clinical condition, concomitant medication and medical history
      data will be performed.

      • Implantation: Implantation day will be recorded as day 0; enrollment day.

      • Follow up visits at 1 week, 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 &amp; 12-month post-op (total of 7 follow up visits).

      At each follow up visit, subjects will be evaluated for: (i) conjunctival integrity; (ii)
      device dimensions, (iii) clinical evaluation; (iv) device retention and (v) any clinically
      necessary interim safety exam per PI decision. Additionally, at 6 &amp; 12 months post-op,
      subjects will undergo an imaging evaluation of the device's dimensions (either by UBM or
      OCT).

      Safety Assessment: A record of UADE as well as incidence and nature of Serious Adverse Events
      (SAE) will be recorded. Incidence and nature of Adverse Events (AE) will be collected
      throughout the study starting from implantation. The following types of events are outside of
      this category:

      (i) Adverse events related to the disease such as glaucoma and not caused by implant
      concealment (ii) Adverse events related to the primary implant such as tube shunt blockage
      not related to implant concealment
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The frequency of all Unanticipated Adverse Device-related Events (UADE) or treatment-related adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conjunctival integrity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Conjunctival integrity at the implantation should be 90% or more as measured by Slit lamp examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stability in patch dimensions</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Stability in patch dimensions should show less than 10% change (length, projected width and thickness) measured by OCT after 1-week and follow-up for up to 12 months post-implantation in 90% of the implanted patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma Eye</condition>
  <condition>Tissue Breakdown</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Synthetic Tissue Substitute</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Corneat EverPatch - Synthetic Tissue Substitute for Covering Ophthalmic Implants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CorNeat EverPatch</intervention_name>
    <description>Covering Ophthalmic Implants</description>
    <arm_group_label>Synthetic Tissue Substitute</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female

          2. Aged ≥ 18 and ≤ 80 years on screening day

          3. Concealment of an artificial ophthalmic implant or a glaucoma tube shunt is indicated.

          4. Candidates must have the ability and willingness to attend all scheduled visits and
             comply with all study procedures

          5. Adequate tear film and lid function

          6. Visual acuity of light perception or better

          7. Female patients of childbearing age must agree to use a method of contraception and
             have negative pregnancy test at screening. An effective method of contraception must
             be used throughout the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current retinal detachment

          2. Active ocular or orbital infection

          3. History or evidence of severe inflammatory eye diseases (i.e. uveitis, retinitis,
             scleritis) in one or both eyes within 6 months prior to planned implantation

          4. History of ocular or periocular malignancy

          5. History of extensive keloid formation

          6. Any known intolerance or hypersensitivity to topical anesthetics, mydriatics, or
             component of the device

          7. Signs of current infection, including fever and current treatment with antibiotics

          8. Severe generalized disease that results in a life expectancy shorter than a year

          9. Any clinical evidence that the investigator feels would place the subject at increased
             risk with the placement of the device

         10. Currently pregnant or breastfeeding

         11. Participation in any study involving an investigational drug or device within the past
             30 days or 5 half-lives of the drug (whichever longer) or ongoing participation in a
             study with an investigational drug or device

         12. Intraoperative complication that would preclude implantation of the study device.

         13. Any traumatic perforation

         14. Tissue gaps/weaknesses, resulting either from traumatic, disease-related or iatrogenic
             damage

         15. Loss of scleral integrity where use of tissue or substitutes is indicated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gerry Tal</last_name>
    <phone>+972523562826</phone>
    <email>gerry@corneat.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ido Klein</last_name>
    <phone>+972549350507</phone>
    <email>ido@corneat.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prism Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakville</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L6H OJ8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ayda Shahidi, OD PhD FAAO</last_name>
      <phone>(905) 456-3937</phone>
      <phone_ext>267</phone_ext>
      <email>ayda.shahidi@prismeye.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Iqbal Ike K Ahmed, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Devesh Varma, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Diamond Tam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matt Schlenker, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network - Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olivera Sutakovic, MD CCRC</last_name>
      <email>Olivera.Sutakovic@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lina Chen, MD</last_name>
      <email>Lina.Chen@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Rootman, MD, FRCS(C)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Clara Chan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

