<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04034888</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMaryland</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04034888</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Home Exercise Program for Homebound Older Adults</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEX</acronym>
  <official_title>Home Exercise Program for Homebound Older Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland, Baltimore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland, Baltimore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Exercise can be beneficial for older adults by promoting health, delaying or reversing
      functional decline, reducing chronic disease risk, decreasing falls, increasing strength and
      stamina, improving ability to perform activities of daily living (ADL), and improving overall
      quality of life (QOL). Developing and implementing exercise programs for homebound older
      adults for whom traveling to routine clinic-based appointments may not be feasible or safe
      becomes critical. Homebound, older adults are at increased risk for recurrent
      hospitalization, use of emergency care, nursing home placement, and death. Indeed, one study
      shows patients had significantly higher risk of being admitted into a hospital or nursing
      home, higher mortality, and higher health care expenditures compared to those in a comparison
      group. The purpose of this pilot is to develop and implement a pragmatic and feasible
      intervention to improve physical functioning in older homebound adults with chronic mobility
      disability. Unfortunately, little is known about the feasibility and utility of pragmatic
      home-based exercise rehabilitation in older adults with severe mobility limitations.

      The investigators propose to develop and implement an intervention targeting functional
      limitations in this population with mobility disability. Our overall goals are to maintain
      and restore physical functioning and QOL for older, homebound adults. This research carries
      direct benefits for these patients as even modest improvements in disabled older adults may
      translate into significantly better QOL, reduce disability, minimize or reverse gradual
      declines related to serious chronic disease, resort functional independence, and increase
      community living capacity. Thus, the specified objectives of finalizing and implementing a
      sustainable home-based exercise program have practical implications for disabled older
      adults. Were homebound patients even slightly higher in terms of functional capacity, it
      could provide a partial degree of functional independence, impacting QOL for both patients
      and caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop and implement a pragmatic and feasible intervention
      to improve physical functioning in older homebound adults with chronic mobility disability.
      Unfortunately, little is known about the feasibility and utility of pragmatic home-based
      exercise rehabilitation in older adults with severe mobility limitations.

      The Specific Aims and Hypotheses of this proposal are:

      Specific Aim #1: Using human-centered design methodologies, work with providers and patients
      to develop a feasible multi-component home exercise program targeting mobility, strength, and
      performance of task-oriented ADLs. Feasibility will be determined by assessing adherence and
      retention to the developed exercise program.

      Hypothesis 1: The investigators hypothesize that a task-based exercise intervention can be
      feasibly delivered in the homes of homebound, older adults.

      Specific Aim #2: Perform a feasibility study to better assess feasibility and determine the
      effect(s) of the home-based intervention created in Aim 1 on functional outcomes (primary
      outcome SPPB), mobility, and QOL changes in homebound older adults with mobility disability.

      Hypothesis 2: The investigators hypothesize that the developed 12-week multi-component
      exercise intervention will improve performance of basic ADLs, functional mobility, and QOL;
      as well as outcomes related to patient satisfaction, emergency department visits, and
      hospitalization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    COVID-19
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short Physical Performance Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>captures domains of strength, endurance, and balance and is highly predictive of disability. The SPPB score is based on timed measures of standing balance, walking speed, and ability to rise from a chair.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 30-second sit-to-stand test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>determines lower extremity strength and endurance in older adults. The number of sit-to-stands is recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 30-second arm curl test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>determines upper extremity strength and endurance in older adults. The number of arm curls is recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Grip Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is a surrogate marker for sarcopenia and will be measured with a hand dynamometer. The arm to be tested held by the participant's side and elbow at a 90° angle. The participant squeezes the hand as hard as possible for few seconds. The best out of two trials separated by 60 seconds will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Lower Extremity Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>will be measured with a wireless digital handheld manual muscle dynamometer during leg extension. To evaluate the knee extensor muscles, the dynamometer will be placed on the anterior part of the lower leg. Participants will perform 3 isometric maximal voluntary contractions of 5 seconds with a 60-second recovery period between contractions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Activity Measure for Post-Acute Care (AM-PAC) Basic Mobility and Daily Activity Out-patient Low Functioning Short Form to assess basic mobility, daily activity, and applied cognitive.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barthel Index of Activities of Daily Living</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses functional dependence and independence.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Life Space Activity (LAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A multidimensional construct that reflects the geographical area that a person moves over a period of time.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Late-Life Function and Disability Instrument (LLFDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will be used to assess the subject's self-reported measures of function and disability.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with an analog visual scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home Exercise Program (HEX)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Customized home exercise program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HEX</intervention_name>
    <description>HEX is a customized exercise program with components including: 1) controlled flexibility movements; 2) progressive ADL training focusing on bed mobility, bed to chair transfers, and indoor walking; 3) task-specific seated resistance training to improve ability to get out of bed and; 4) and balance exercises. Participants will be expected to perform their HEX program at least 2 times/week in their home and all individualized exercise sessions will be supervised by an Exercise Physiologist. Each exercise has four levels of difficulty, which will be progressed as tolerated throughout the 12-weeks. Seated resistance exercises were designed to target all the major muscle groups and will include the following: arm curls, shoulder raises (lateral/front), overhead arm raise, wrist curls, leg extensions, hip flexion, hip ab/adduction, sit-to-stands, torso rotation, and marching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home Exercise Program (HEX)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veteran enrolled in the Veterans Administration Medical Health Care System's Home-
             Based Primary Care Program

          -  Aged 65 years or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Paraplegia

          -  Life expectancy of less than 12 months

          -  Currently engaged in a physical therapy program

          -  Any medical condition(s) or contraindications precluding patient participation in the
             study as per medical judgement of study team
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alyssa Stookey, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland School of Medicine and Baltimore VA Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland, Baltimore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alyssa Stookey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Health Scientist (GRECC), Research Associate (SOM)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No individual participant data will be shared with other researchers outside of our study team.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

