<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04034017</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ECM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04034017</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Among College Students</brief_title>
  <official_title>Personal, Academic and Stress Correlates of Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Among College Students in Southwestern Saudi Arabia: A Cross-sectional Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>King Khalid University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King Khalid University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) is a worldwide prevalent gastrointestinal
      disorder which has negative impacts on quality of life, health and economy. The aims of this
      study were to assess the prevalence of GERD among college students in southwestern Saudi
      Arabia and to evaluate its personal, academic and stress correlates Materials and Methods:
      Through a cross-sectional study design, a self-reported questionnaire was distributed between
      a representative sample of students in health and non-health care colleges in southwestern
      Saudi Arabia. The questionnaire included data for personal characteristics, academic study,
      and Arabic versions of GERD questionnaire (GerdQ) and Cohen's Perceived Stress Scale.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design and setting A cross-sectional study was carried out in both male and female
      campuses of King Khalid University (KKU) during the academic year 2018-2019. The University
      is located in Aseer region in the southwestern part of Saudi Arabia. The area of Aseer region
      is about 80.000 square kilometers occupied with more than 1.6 million people. The university
      comprise 5 health colleges and 24 non-health colleges with a total number of 60.312 male and
      female students in the academic year 2014-2015.

      Target population Students in Health and non-health care colleges in KKU were the target
      population.

      Sample size and sampling method Sample size was estimated by using Epi info program version
      7.2 with the anticipated prevalence of GERD symptoms among college students 23.8% [6], 95%
      confidence level and acceptable margin of error of 2.5%. The calculated cluster size was 1113
      students. To account for the possibility of non-response, 1200 students were targeted from
      each of health and non-health care colleges.

      All health care colleges were included in the study. They were colleges of medicine,
      pharmacy, dentistry, nursing and applied medical science. Five non- health care colleges were
      selected by random method. They were colleges of education, science, humanities,
      administrative and financial sciences, and languages and translation. Participants were
      selected through stratified cluster sampling technique. Within each college, students were
      stratified by academic level. Within each level a cluster (section or study group) was
      selected. When possible, all registered students within each cluster were included.

      Study tool and data collection A self-reported questionnaire was distributed personally by
      medical students-during their training in community medicine course- between the
      participants. The questionnaire includes the following sections: a) personal data such as,
      age sex, marital status, smoking status and family income; b) academic data which include,
      name of college, academic level and Grade point average (GPA); c) Arabic version of GERD
      questionnaire (GerdQ)[10]; d) Arabic version of Cohen's Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) [8].

      All incomplete questionnaires were excluded. Arabic version of GERD questionnaire (GerdQ)
      GerdQ is a valid questionnaire used to explore the probaility of GERD. It is consisted of 6
      questions as follow: four positive questions to assess GERD symptoms (heartburn,
      regurgitation, sleep disturbance related to heartburn and regurgitation and use of
      medications) and two negative questions (epigastric pain and nausea). Each item rated from 0
      to 3 depending on the rate of symptoms over the previous week. GERD was detected with a total
      score value of 8 or more [10]. Score value of 8 or more plus total score value of 3 or more
      for the impact questions (sleep disturbance and use of medications) indicted GERD with impact
      on daily life. The Arabic version of GerdQ was developed and validated for use among Arabic
      speakers [11].

      Data analysis The gained data were entered, revised, and analyzed using SPSS, version 22
      software package. Grading of PSS into low, moderate and high was according to Cohen's et al
      [12]. Crude odds ratio (cOR) and adjusted odds ratio (aOR) were calculated using univariate
      and multivariable logistic regression analysis respectively. Their 95% confidence intervals
      (95% CIs) were used to identify significant factors associated with GERD among students.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 18, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence rate of gastroesophogeal reflux disease (GERD) among college students</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Arabic version of GERD questionnaire (GerdQ) was used to screen for GERD among college students. GERD was considered with a total score value of GerdQ of 8 or more</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>assess the association of GERD with students' personal data</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>examining the associations of GERD with the personal data such as, age (in years) sex (male Vs. female), marital status (married Vs. single), smoking status (smoker, ex-smoker and non-smoker) and family income (sufficient Vs. insufficient)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>assess the association of GERD with students' academic data</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>the academic data include: college(health care Vs. non-health care colleges) academic year (first year through six year) student's Grade point average (GPA) in the previous academic year</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>examine the association of GERD with the level of perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>perceived stress was assessed by using the Arabic version of Cohen's Perceived Stress Scale (PSS). Grading of PSS into low, moderate and high was done as the following: scores ranging from 0-13 was considered low stress; scores ranging from 14-26 was considered moderate stress; scores ranging from 27-40 was considered high perceived stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2878</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Reflux</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>no intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>descriptive study, no intervention</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A representative sample of Students in Health and non-health care colleges in King Khalid U
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  College students

          -  Must be cooperative

          -  Agree to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  non cooperative students

          -  disagree to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King Khalid University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Abha</city>
        <state>Aseer</state>
        <zip>61421</zip>
        <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>King Khalid University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nabil Awadalla</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>College students</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastroesophageal reflux disease</keyword>
  <keyword>GERD</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevalence</keyword>
  <keyword>Perceived stress</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis, Peptic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

