<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04031560</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI17/00941</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04031560</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of an Integrative Psychological Program in Bipolar Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of an Integrative Program Combining Mindfulness-based Cognitive Therapy, Psychoeducation and Functional Remediation in Bipolar Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Consorcio Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red, M.P.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Consorcio Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red, M.P.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bipolar disorder is related to a high level of personal, familial, social and economic
      burden. There is a need for feasible adjunctive psychological interventions to use in
      clinical practice as a complement of pharmacotherapy to enhance aspects that medication
      cannot reach. This project aims at develop and evaluate the impact of an adjunctive brief
      integrative program for bipolar patients (euthymic or with subthreshold symptoms). The
      patients (N=124) will be randomly assigned to two different groups. The experimental group
      (62 patients) will take part on a group integrative program consisting of 12-sessions of 90
      minutes (based on psychoeducation, mindfulness and functional remediation) whilst the control
      group (62 patients) will not receive any sort of add-on psychotherapy. All patients will
      mantain standard psychiatric treatment. Together with the baseline assessment, the whole
      sample will be assessed after the intervention and at 12 months from the baseline evaluation,
      regarding sociodemographic, clinical and neuropsychological variables. If the intervention is
      effective it will improve psychosocial functioning (main variable), wellbeing and quality of
      life, as well as improve clinical outcomes and neurocognitive functioning of those affected
      by the illness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design: Single-blind randomized control trial.

      Participants: Study participants will be enrolled from the Bipolar Disorders Program of the
      Hospital Clinic of Barcelona (Spain) and the Bipolar Disorders Unit.

      Procedure: At baseline, the sample will be evaluated with respect to sociodemographic,
      clinical and neuropsychological variables. Subsequently, patients will be randomly assigned
      (1:1) to two different groups. The experimental group (62 patients) will take part on the
      integrative group program consisting of 12-sessions, 90 minutes each, once a week (4 focused
      on psychoeducation, 1 directed to the family relatives, 3 on mindfulness and 4 on functional
      remediation) whilst the control group (62 patients) will not receive any type of add-on
      psychotherapy. All the patients will maintain a standard psychiatric treatment during the
      study. Together with the baseline assessment, the whole sample will be assessed after the
      intervention and at the 12 months of follow-up. Psychiatric medication will be recorded
      during the follow-up and the reasons for eventual modifications. All the subjects will be
      evaluated by researchers blinded to the treatment condition. Semi-structured interviews will
      be conducted and complemented with clinical records and with assessment instruments to
      collect variables related to the course of the illness. This study will be conducted in
      accordance with the ethical principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and Good Clinical
      Practice and approved by the Hospital Clinic Ethics and Research. All participants will be
      asked to provide written informed consent prior to their inclusion in the study.

      Variables assessed:

        1. Demographic variables: gender, age, marital status, educational status and work
           situation.

        2. Clinical variables: age at the onset of BD, age at first hospitalization, total number
           and type of previous episodes, hospitalizations, history of psychotic symptoms, polarity
           of the first episode, seasonal pattern, presence of rapid cycling, bipolar subtype (I or
           II), comorbidities, familial psychiatric history, familial history of affective
           disorder, familial history of complete suicide, previous suicide attempts, number of
           attempts, method and medical severity of attempts, history of drug use.

        3. Clinical scales: Temperament Evaluation of the Memphis, Pisa, Paris, and San Diego
           Autoquestionnaire (TEMPS-A, Akiskal et al, 2005), Barratts Impulsiveness Scale (BIS-11,
           Barratt et al, 1983), Biological Rhythms Interview of Assessment in Neuropsychiatry
           (BRIAN, Rosa et al., 2007), and Cognitive Complaints in Bipolar Disorder Rating
           Assessment (COBRA, Rosa et al., 2013).

        4. Psychosocial functioning: Functional assessment short test (FAST, Rosa et al., 2007).

        5. Wellbeing and quality of life: WHO (Five) Well Being Index (WHO, 1998), Quality of Life
           in Bipolar Disorder scale (QoL.BD, Michalak y Murray, 2010).

        6. Scales of mindfulness: Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ, Baer et al., 2006),
           Mindful Attention Awareness Scale (MAAS, Brown y Ryan, 2003).

        7. Neuropsychological assessment: WAIS-IV (Wechsler, 2012), with the following subtests:
           vocabulary, arithmetic, digit span, letter-number sequencing, symbol search, coding;
           Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST, Heaton et al, 1981); Stroop Color-Word Interference
           Test (Golden y col., 1995); F-A-S Verbal Phonemic Fluency Test (Benton &amp; Hamser, 1978);
           Trail Making Test (TMT, Reitan y Wolfson, 1985); Continuous Performance Test (CPT-III,
           Conners 2014); California Verbal Learning Test (CVLT-II, Delis et al, 2000);
           Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure Test (Osterreith, 1944; Rey, 1941); the Mayer-
           Salovey-Caruso Emotional Intelligence Test (MSCEIT, Mayer et al., 2003) and the Iowa
           Gambling Test (IGT, Bechara et al, 1994).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychosocial functioning measured by functioning assessment short test</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days</time_frame>
    <description>The scale is interviewer-administered, designed for the assessment of psychosocial functioning. The 24 items of the scale are divided among 6 specific areas of functioning: autonomy, occupational functioning, cognitive functioning, financial issues, interpersonal relationships and leisure time. Each individual item is scored from 0 to 3. The global score (0-72) is obtained when the scores of each item are added up. The higher the score, the more serious the difficulties.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">124</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Integrative treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group (62 patients) will not receive any type of add-on psychotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Integrative treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>The experimental group (62 patients) will take part on the integrative group program consisting of 12-sessions, 90 minutes each, once a week (4 focused on psychoeducation, 1 directed to the family relatives, 3 on mindfulness and 4 on functional remediation)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of BD type I or II according to DSM-5 criteria

          -  euthymic or with subthreshold symptoms (HDRS &lt;14; YMRS &lt;8)

          -  absence of an acute mood episode in the 3 months prior to the beginning of the
             intervention

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  estimated Intelligence Quotient (IQ) lower than 85,

          -  significant physical or neurologic illness that can affect neuropsychological
             performance

          -  DSM-5 criteria of substance abuse or dependence

          -  inability to understand the purposes of the study

          -  absence of psychosocial interventions in the past 2 years (psychoeducation group,
             functional remediation, mindfulness)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose Sanchez-Moreno</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Consorcio Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red, M.P.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria Reinares, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34932275400</phone>
    <phone_ext>4189</phone_ext>
    <email>reinares@clinic.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>psychoeducation</keyword>
  <keyword>functional remediation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

