<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04037644</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EXHALE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04037644</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Volume Expansion With Albumin vs. Crystalloid and Expiratory Lung Impedance</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXHALE</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Volume EXpansion witH ALbumin vs. Crystalloid on EIT-derived Expiratory Lung Impedance in Critically Ill, Hemodynamically Unstable Patients. A Single-blind, Randomized and Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Milan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Milan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute circulatory failure reduces oxygen delivery below cellular requirements, potentially
      leading to organ failure. Intravenous fluids are generally administered with the aim of
      increasing cardiac output and restore organ perfusion. Nevertheless, only 50% of patients
      increase their cardiac output, while in the remainder not only does fluid loading provide no
      benefit but it also leads to volume overload (peripheral and pulmonary edema).

      There are two types of resuscitation fluids, colloids and crystalloids. Given their oncotic
      pressure, colloids should remain in the intravascular space, while crystalloids distribute
      into the whole extracellular compartment, potentially increasing the risk of tissue edema.
      Surprisingly, only few studies directly compared albumin and crystalloids in terms of their
      overload-related side effects.

      Electrical impedance tomography (EIT) is a noninvasive, radiation-free, lung imaging
      modality, which shows lung impedance as determined by small electrical currents. An increase
      in intrapulmonary gas volume increases impedance, while an increase in blood or fluid volume,
      lowers it. EIT has a high temporal resolution, allowing to assess ventilation and perfusion
      in real-time. Preliminary data suggest its value to assess the variations of intrathoracic
      fluid in patients with pulmonary edema.

      The aim of the present single-blind, randomized, controlled study is to compare the effect of
      a fluid challenge with albumin vs. crystalloids on EIT-derived lung impedance in a group of
      56 critically ill patients with acute circulatory failure. Our hypothesis is that fluid
      challenge with albumin leads to a lesser decrease in lung impedance, that is a lesser
      extravasation of fluids into the lungs.

      Hemodynamic and respiratory variables, blood samples, cardiac ultrasound and EIT measurements
      will be recorded before the fluid challenge, and repeated at the end of fluid infusion, 20
      and 60 minutes after. Factorial Analysis of variance for repeated measures will be used to
      assess the effects of fluid loading
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 24, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in lung impedance</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in EIT-derived end-expiratory lung impedance after the fluid challenge in the group of patients who will receive albumin as compared to patients who will receive crystalloids</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the change expiratory lung impedance, as assessed by EIT, in fluid responders and non-responders</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the change in end-expiratory lung impedance, as assessed by EIT, after the fluid challenge with albumin or Ringer Lactate, in patient who will respond to the fluid challenge with an increase in their stroke volume, as compared to those who will not (non-responders)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of fluid loading with albumin or Ringer Lactate on the change in arterial blood oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Assesment of the reduction in oxygenation, as assessed by blood gas analysis, after the fluid challenge in the group of patients who will receive albumin as compared to patients who will receive crystalloids, and its relationship with the change in expiratory lung impedance, as assessed by EIT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Circulatory Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Albumin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>fluid loading with 200 mL of 4% albumin over a 10' interval</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ringer Lactate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>fluid loading with 5 mL/kg actual body weight of Ringer Lactate over a 10' interval</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluid loading with Albumin</intervention_name>
    <description>Fluid loading with 200 ml of 4% Albumin to reverse acute circulatory failure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Albumin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluid loading with Ringer Lactate</intervention_name>
    <description>Fluid loading with 5 ml per kg of actual body weight to reverse acute circulatory failure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ringer Lactate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &gt;18 years with acute circulatory failure of any cause, receiving mechanical
             ventilation using volume-assisted control mode, without any spontaneous breathing
             activity, scheduled for a fluid bolus by their treating physician will be enrolled.
             Patients will only be included in the study once.

        Acute circulatory failure will be defined as the presence of a systolic blood pressure
        (SBP) ≤90 mmHg or mean arterial pressure (MAP) ≤70 mmHg or requiring vasopressors to
        maintain SBP &gt;90 mmHg or MAP &gt;70 mmHg, along with one or more of the following: 1) urinary
        flow ≤0.5 mL/kg/h for ≥2 hours, 2) heart rate ≥100 beats per minute, 3) presence of skin
        mottling, 4) blood lactate concentration ≥2 mmol/L, 5) oxygen saturation in the central
        venous blood &lt;65%.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients having right ventricular dysfunction, anuria, pregnancy, presence of
             pneumothorax or lung emphysema, previous history of severe chronic obstructive
             pulmonary disease (GOLD III-IV) or contraindications to the use of EIT (e.g., presence
             of pacemaker or automatic implantable cardioverter-defibrillator) and impossibility to
             place the EIT belt in the right position (e.g., presence of surgical wounds dressing)
             will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Davide Chiumello, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ospedale San Paolo - Polo Universitario, ASST Santi Paolo e Carlo, Milan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Davide Chiumello, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+390281844020</phone>
    <email>chiumello@libero.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale San Paolo - Polo Universitario, ASST Santi Paolo e Carlo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20142</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Davide Chiumello, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+390281844020</phone>
      <email>chiumello@libero.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michele Umbrello, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Milan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Davide Chiumello</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Intensive Care</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

