<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04035421</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UTK IRB-19-05178-XP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04035421</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diet, Physical Activity, and Sleep Habits</brief_title>
  <acronym>DPAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Diet, Physical Activity, and Sleep Habits</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to observe if consistency in a young adult's schedule is related to health
      factors and outcomes, such as diet quality, amount of physical activity and sleep, and
      weight.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During young adulthood, patterns regarding physical activity,1,2 dietary intake,3 and weight
      status4 are established that track into later life and can impact health. Social and physical
      cues also impact patterns—particularly those cues that may influence biological and
      behavioral rhythms which can influence the Circadian Timing System (CTS).5 Chronotype, the
      timing of sleep patterns, is closely tied to the CTS as it reflects sleep in relation to the
      light and dark cycle, with morning-type (MT) having a pattern that should assist with better
      entrainment (sleep better entrained to the physical cues of light/dark).6 Research has found
      that chronotype is related to several areas important to health, including diet,6-11 physical
      activity,12-14 weight regulation.15-18. As a whole, research in this area suggests that MT
      individuals are more likely to consume a healthier eating pattern, be more physically active,
      and more successfully manage their weight. However, the research in this area for young
      adults is limited.

      While there has been research regarding chronotype and diet, activity, and weight management,
      there is a paucity of research on the relationship between social cues and social rhythms,
      which also influence the CTS, and health related outcomes. Social rhythms, as measured by the
      Social Rhythm Metric (SRM), are related to chronotype, such that MT is related to a higher
      SRM.19-21 Due to the relationship between SRM and chronotype, and chronotype and diet,
      physical activity, and weight management, it would be anticipated that SRM is also related to
      these health outcomes. Specifically, it would be anticipated that more consistent social
      rhythms (higher SRM) would be related to a healthier eating pattern, greater physical
      activity, and weight management. However, this relationship has never been investigated.

      Therefore, to better understand how social rhythms, which are triggered by social cues, are
      related to health, this investigation will be assessing both chronotype and SRM and
      collecting measures on diet quality, via food records, physical activity and sleep, via
      accelerometers, and anthropometrics, via BMI. The population of interest for this study is
      specifically young adults because young adulthood is a time period when health patterns are
      established for the rest of life. This study aims to observe if consistency in a young
      adult's schedule is related to health factors and outcomes, such as diet quality, amount of
      physical activity and sleep, and weight.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet Quality 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Healthy Eating Index Score calculated using a three-day food record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet Quality 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Total energy intake will be assessed using a three-day food record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Minutes of moderate to vigorous physical activity will be assessed using SenseWear Armbands</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Energy expenditure from moderate to vigorous physical activity will be assessed using SenseWear Armbands</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Length of sleep will be assessed using SenseWear Armbands</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep efficiency will be assessed using SenseWear Armbands</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline appointment</time_frame>
    <description>BMI will be calculated using height and weight measurements</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline appointment</time_frame>
    <description>Body fat percentage will be assessed using the Body Composition Analyzer TBF-300 (TANITA Corporation, Tokyo, Japan)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronotype</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline appointment</time_frame>
    <description>Chronotype will be assessed using the Composite Score for Morningness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Diet Habit</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Young adult between the ages of 18 and 35 years, taking classes and/or working, able to
        engage in physical activity, and having no dietary restrictions.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between the ages of 18-35 years

          -  Able to pass the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire for Everyone (PAR-Q+)
             indicating that they have no health conditions that limit their ability to engage in
             physical activity

          -  Access to an email address and internet each day during their participation

          -  An town when all measures are collected

          -  Taking classes and/or working a job when all measures are collected

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant

          -  Allergy to stainless steel, making the participant unable to wear Body Media Armband

          -  Dietary restrictions of any kind

          -  Shift work, here defined as having to work a shift for any period of time between the
             hours of 12 am and 6 am
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hollie Raynor, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tennessee Knoxville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Healthy Eating and Activity Lab, University of Tennessee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37996</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caspersen CJ, Pereira MA, Curran KM. Changes in physical activity patterns in the United States, by sex and cross-sectional age. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2000 Sep;32(9):1601-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10994912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson MC, Story M, Larson NI, Neumark-Sztainer D, Lytle LA. Emerging adulthood and college-aged youth: an overlooked age for weight-related behavior change. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2008 Oct;16(10):2205-11. doi: 10.1038/oby.2008.365.</citation>
    <PMID>18719665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunn JE, Liu K, Greenland P, Hilner JE, Jacobs DR Jr. Seven-year tracking of dietary factors in young adults: the CARDIA study. Am J Prev Med. 2000 Jan;18(1):38-45.</citation>
    <PMID>10808981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serdula MK, Ivery D, Coates RJ, Freedman DS, Williamson DF, Byers T. Do obese children become obese adults? A review of the literature. Prev Med. 1993 Mar;22(2):167-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8483856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monk TH, Flaherty JF, Frank E, Hoskinson K, Kupfer DJ. The Social Rhythm Metric. An instrument to quantify the daily rhythms of life. J Nerv Ment Dis. 1990 Feb;178(2):120-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2299336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright KP Jr, McHill AW, Birks BR, Griffin BR, Rusterholz T, Chinoy ED. Entrainment of the human circadian clock to the natural light-dark cycle. Curr Biol. 2013 Aug 19;23(16):1554-8. doi: 10.1016/j.cub.2013.06.039. Epub 2013 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23910656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fleig D, Randler C. Association between chronotype and diet in adolescents based on food logs. Eat Behav. 2009 Apr;10(2):115-8. doi: 10.1016/j.eatbeh.2009.03.002. Epub 2009 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>19447353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gontijo CA, Cabral BBM, Balieiro LCT, Teixeira GP, Fahmy WM, Maia YCP, Crispim CA. Time-related eating patterns and chronotype are associated with diet quality in pregnant women. Chronobiol Int. 2019 Jan;36(1):75-84. doi: 10.1080/07420528.2018.1518328. Epub 2018 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>30212228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kogevinas M, Espinosa A, Castelló A, Gómez-Acebo I, Guevara M, Martin V, Amiano P, Alguacil J, Peiro R, Moreno V, Costas L, Fernández-Tardón G, Jimenez JJ, Marcos-Gragera R, Perez-Gomez B, Llorca J, Moreno-Iribas C, Fernández-Villa T, Oribe M, Aragones N, Papantoniou K, Pollán M, Castano-Vinyals G, Romaguera D. Effect of mistimed eating patterns on breast and prostate cancer risk (MCC-Spain Study). Int J Cancer. 2018 Nov 15;143(10):2380-2389. doi: 10.1002/ijc.31649. Epub 2018 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30016830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maukonen M, Kanerva N, Partonen T, Männistö S. Chronotype and energy intake timing in relation to changes in anthropometrics: a 7-year follow-up study in adults. Chronobiol Int. 2019 Jan;36(1):27-41. doi: 10.1080/07420528.2018.1515772. Epub 2018 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>30212231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roßbach S, Diederichs T, Nöthlings U, Buyken AE, Alexy U. Relevance of chronotype for eating patterns in adolescents. Chronobiol Int. 2018 Mar;35(3):336-347. doi: 10.1080/07420528.2017.1406493. Epub 2017 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29231764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harrex HAL, Skeaff SA, Black KE, Davison BK, Haszard JJ, Meredith-Jones K, Quigg R, Saeedi P, Stoner L, Wong JE, Skidmore PML. Sleep timing is associated with diet and physical activity levels in 9-11-year-old children from Dunedin, New Zealand: the PEDALS study. J Sleep Res. 2018 Aug;27(4):e12634. doi: 10.1111/jsr.12634. Epub 2017 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>29160021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olds TS, Maher CA, Matricciani L. Sleep duration or bedtime? Exploring the relationship between sleep habits and weight status and activity patterns. Sleep. 2011 Oct 1;34(10):1299-307. doi: 10.5665/SLEEP.1266.</citation>
    <PMID>21966061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shechter A, St-Onge MP. Delayed sleep timing is associated with low levels of free-living physical activity in normal sleeping adults. Sleep Med. 2014 Dec;15(12):1586-9. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2014.07.010. Epub 2014 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25311835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arora T, Taheri S. Associations among late chronotype, body mass index and dietary behaviors in young adolescents. Int J Obes (Lond). 2015 Jan;39(1):39-44. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2014.157. Epub 2014 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25135376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Culnan E, Kloss JD, Grandner M. A prospective study of weight gain associated with chronotype among college freshmen. Chronobiol Int. 2013 Jun;30(5):682-90. doi: 10.3109/07420528.2013.782311. Epub 2013 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23688114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross KM, Graham Thomas J, Wing RR. Successful weight loss maintenance associated with morning chronotype and better sleep quality. J Behav Med. 2016 Jun;39(3):465-71. doi: 10.1007/s10865-015-9704-8. Epub 2015 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26660638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruiz-Lozano T, Vidal J, de Hollanda A, Scheer FAJL, Garaulet M, Izquierdo-Pulido M. Timing of food intake is associated with weight loss evolution in severe obese patients after bariatric surgery. Clin Nutr. 2016 Dec;35(6):1308-1314. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2016.02.007. Epub 2016 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26948400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin JS, Hébert M, Ledoux E, Gaudreault M, Laberge L. Relationship of chronotype to sleep, light exposure, and work-related fatigue in student workers. Chronobiol Int. 2012 Apr;29(3):295-304. doi: 10.3109/07420528.2011.653656.</citation>
    <PMID>22390242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mongrain V, Carrier J, Dumont M. Chronotype and sex effects on sleep architecture and quantitative sleep EEG in healthy young adults. Sleep. 2005 Jul;28(7):819-27.</citation>
    <PMID>16124660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monk TH, Buysse DJ, Potts JM, DeGrazia JM, Kupfer DJ. Morningness-eveningness and lifestyle regularity. Chronobiol Int. 2004 May;21(3):435-43.</citation>
    <PMID>15332448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hollie Raynor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Social Rhythm Metric</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronotype</keyword>
  <keyword>Young adult</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>July 23, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/21/NCT04035421/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

