<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04030572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-04020242</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04030572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of Administering Clonidine as a Pharmacological Challenge in Imaging Studies</brief_title>
  <acronym>a2a Agonist</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability, and Feasibility of Administering Clonidine as a Pharmacological Challenge in Future Imaging Studies of Cerebrospinal Fluid Kinetics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a Phase 1, open label study of the pharmacokinetics (PK) and pharmacodynamics
      (PD) of clonidine, an alpha-2 adrenergic (a2a) agonist, in healthy volunteers. The primary
      aim is to show that the drug regimen is safe and reasonably well tolerated. The secondary aim
      is to demonstrate that safety can be monitored with home health devices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects who screen in will participate in a drug-free lead-in period of one week duration.
      Then, the drug test article, clonidine HCl, 0.1 mg tabs, will be administered once daily by
      mouth at bedtime for one week. Steady-state PK will be measured on Day 8 post-drug with a
      single blood draw of 10 mL. This will be followed by a one week wash out period. During each
      of these three different one-week periods, sleep quality will be monitored nightly with a
      blue tooth and wireless enabled, wearable sleep tracker. Vital signs (VSs) will be monitored
      daily at home with a blue tooth and wireless enabled blood pressure machine. VSs and
      electrocardiograms (ECGs) will be measured before drug on Day (-7) and Day 1. Repeat
      measurements will be made during clinic visits on Day 2, Day 8, and Day 16.

      The findings should show that there is, or is not, a PD effect produced by this rather low
      dose of drug administered for a relatively short period of time. Showing a PD effect at a
      safe and reasonably well tolerated dose would qualify this drug dosing regimen as a
      pharmacological challenge in future studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects experiencing adverse events related to drug-induced changes in hemodynamic function.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2 or Day 8 compared to Day (-7) through Day 1 during drug-free lead-in</time_frame>
    <description>clinically significant drop in blood pressure or pulse</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Sleep Duration</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2 and Day 8 on drug and Day 16 washout compared to Day (-7) through Day 1 during drug-free lead-in</time_frame>
    <description>Time interval between falling asleep and waking up as estimated by a wearable sleep tracking device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Deep Sleep Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 2 and Day 8 on drug and Day 16 washout compared to Day (-7) through Day 1 during drug-free lead-in</time_frame>
    <description>amount of time estimated to be in deep sleep versus light sleep by a wearable sleep tracking device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuro-Degenerative Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clonidine Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One week period of clonidine, 0.1 mg tabs, one by mouth daily at bedtime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clonidine Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>0.1 mg tabs, one by mouth daily at bedtime for one week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clonidine Pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>On-Drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  able to give informed consent.

          -  age 18-89

          -  Subjectively healthy and, in the opinion of the investigators, likely to be compliant
             with the drug regimen and the schedule of follow up visits.

          -  Normal hemodynamic function. Systolic blood pressure and pulse must be higher than 120
             mmHg and 60 beats per minute while sitting. At the discretion of the investigators,
             athletic people who are in exceptionally robust condition may be enrolled if their
             systolic blood pressure and pulse are higher than 100 mmHg and 50 beats per minute
             while sitting.

          -  Unremarkable electrocardiograms with PR intervals of less than 200 mSec and QT
             intervals corrected with Fridericia's method (QTcF) of less than 440 mSec.

          -  No concurrent medications with the exception of p.r.n. NSAIDS, which must be
             discontinued one week prior to the lead-in period, and avoided for the next three
             weeks while on study (the one week lead-in period, one week on drug period, and one
             week washout period).

          -  Willing and able to refrain from abusing any recreational drugs, including marijuana
             because of its sleep effects, and drink less than one unit of alcoholic beverages per
             day starting one week prior to the lead-in period, and avoided for the next three
             weeks while on study (the one week lead-in period, one week on drug period, and one
             week washout period).

          -  Willing to refrain from donating blood while during the month of study.

          -  Willing to refrain from participating in any other research study that requires taking
             medication during the month of study.

          -  Willing to refrain from being vaccinated during the month of study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of allergy to clonidine.

          -  History of multiple hypersensitivity reactions, as indicated by allergies to multiple
             medications, foods, and seasonal pollen.

          -  History or physical examination suggestive of a condition, disorder, or disease that
             could represent a contra-indication to taking an antihypertensive. The relative
             contraindications to clonidine listed in the package insert under the section on
             precautions will be exclusionary in this study. They include subjects with coronary
             artery insufficiency syndromes, histories of myocardial infarction, cardiac conduction
             abnormalities, cerebrovascular disease, and chronic renal failure.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast feeding will not be eligible to participate in the
             study, as clonidine is classified as a Class C risk to a fetus. (In fact, there is a
             safety signal in pregnant animal models that justifies exclusion, even if the signal
             is weak.)

          -  History or physical examination suggestive of a condition, disorder, or disease that
             could affect the adsorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of the study drug.

          -  Positive urine toxicology screen for recreational drugs, other than cannabis.

          -  History of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) as a child or a residual
             disorder as an adult, because safety, tolerability, and patient acceptability have
             already been shown in these populations.

          -  Subjects may not be a member of a vulnerable population.

          -  May not have taken any controlled medications, including other study drugs, in the
             last 30 days or for 10 half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  May not have donated blood in the 30 days prior to the start of the lead-in period.

          -  May not have participated in research administering drugs in the last 30 days.

          -  May not have been vaccinated in the 30 days prior to the start of the lead-in period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>P. David Mozley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>P. David Mozley, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212 746 5805</phone>
    <email>dvm9029@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</last_name>
    <phone>646 962 8200</phone>
    <email>jcto@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>P. David Mozley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-5805</phone>
      <email>dvm9029@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neurodegenerative Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clonidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All de-identified on-study data will be shared.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be made available within six months of last study visit or acceptance for publication, whichever comes first.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Any reasonable request sent to dvm9029@med.cornell.edu</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

