<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04038931</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ORG-ISR-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04038931</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collection of Human Liver Biopsy and Whole Blood Samples From T1DM, TP or PP Patients for Potential Use for Insulin Producing Cells in Future Clinical Studies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Human Liver Biopsy and Whole Blood Samples From Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus (T1DM), Total or Partial Pancreatectomy Patients for Potential Use as an Autologous Source for Insulin Producing Cells in Future Clinical Studies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Orgenesis Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Orgenesis Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, liver samples will be collected, processed and stored in a specialized,
      clinical grade, cell bank for potential future clinical use. A set of ex-vivo immunogenicity
      and transdiffrentiation tests will be carried to confirm the ability of this cryopreserved
      cell batch to be used as clinical grade raw material. Biopsies will be collected during TP or
      PP with the assumption that some of the patients (especially PP patients will not go through
      Islets autotransplantation) will develop brittle diabetes, thus Orgenesis therapy can provide
      them in the long run, a treatment. In terms of T1DM the purpose is to have available clinical
      grade raw material for cell replacement therapy.

      The collected liver samples will be proliferated (up to passage 4) for future use. A portion
      of the stored cells will be utilized in a small-scale process to test possible immunogenicity
      performed on the collected blood sample. The assay will provide data whether immunomodulation
      treatment will be required in the future clinical trials. Also the transdffrentiated cells
      (AIPs) will be tested according to release criteria relevant for clinical IPC production.
      Liver biopsy donors will be contacted upon approval of the consecutive study and will have
      study recruitment priority. The donors can refuse to participate in the future study or may
      not need the therapy, however, their biopsies will be stored for a potential use if required,
      after the therapy is approved.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirmation of patients' suitability eligibility to participate in future clinical study</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post biopsy collection</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by a successful AIPs production from their liver biopsy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating autoimmune response to AIPs</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post biopsy collection</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by Mixed Lymphocyte Reaction (MLR) assay based on the patient's PBMCs isolated from whole blood samples and following in-vivo subcutaneous implantation into the patients' arm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatectomy; Hyperglycemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liver biopsy collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Liver biopsy collection to Confirm suitability of T1DM, total or partial pancreatectomy patient's liver cells to be used as future personalized cell replacement therapy.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        study population comprises of patients undergoing total or partial pancreatectomy or from
        T1DM patients undergoing an elective abdominal surgery (in which there is an easy access to
        the liver).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients between the ages of 18 and 70 years old, inclusive.

          -  For T1DM - Patients with history of established T1DM undergoing an elective abdominal
             surgery with an easy access to the liver

          -  Patients undergoing total or partial Pancreatectomy

          -  Female patients who agree not to breastfeed during the study up to at least seven days
             after the study is completed.

          -  For T1DM - Receiving multiple daily insulin injections or insulin pump therapy.

          -  For T1DM - HbA1c ≤10%.

          -  Willing to sign the study informed consent document.

          -  In good general health with no infections, or concomitant medical conditions that
             would influence the outcome of the trial, at the discretion of the Investigator and
             the Sponsor.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Received any investigational product within 30 days of admission into this study or
             plan to participate in any other clinical study during the conduct of this study.

          -  Received methotrexate or other rheumatoid disease modifying agents within the last 6
             months.

          -  Administration of a live vaccine 30 days prior to screening.

          -  No evidence of liver Cirrhosis or Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH, grade 3 and
             above) within the last month.

          -  Patients diagnosed with liver viral infections such as HBV, HCV, HIV

          -  Patients diagnosed with CMV (defined by IgM positive).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperglycemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

