<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04039568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EO1-162072</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EO1-162072</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04039568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Meditation Versus Education for Improving Depression in Chronic Pain, a Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Meditation Versus Education for Improving Depression in Chronic Pain, a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mount Sinai Hospital, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lunenfeld Tanenbaum Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rivlin Medical Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Art of Living Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Mental Health Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mount Sinai Hospital, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study two possible treatment options available for depression and chronic pain will
      be explored. Both of these treatments will be offered in groups which could translate to
      cost-savings for the health care system. The two treatment options are:

        1. The Health Enhancement Program (HEP). Designed to give participants information and
           guidance on how to lead a healthy lifestyle, which could be beneficial in treating
           depression.

        2. Sahaj Samadhi Meditation (SSM). A unique and easy-to-learn meditation technique that
           reduces stress and provides deep relaxation which could be beneficial in treating
           depression.

      This study will use a hybrid type 1 evaluation design that primarily focuses on a
      single-site, single-blinded (investigator, and clinician), 12-week randomized controlled
      trial (RCT) comparing SSM (n=80) versus HEP (n=80) in 160 older adults with depression and
      chronic pain on opioid medication. Participants will be blinded to the treatment hypothesis
      while investigators, raters and treating clinicians will be additionally blinded to the
      intervention. Evaluations of depression (PHQ-9), pain symptoms (BPI), quality of life
      (SF-36), and opioid use will be collected at baseline, intervention completion (12 week), and
      at 24 week follow-up. An implementation evaluation will draw from four key study populations:
      (1) the patients discussed above whom participate in the SSM arm of the RCT; (2) the expert
      meditation instructors facilitating the intervention; (3) the RMG administrative staff
      involved in supporting the logistics of the intervention arm of the RCT; and (4) the clinical
      staff at RMG.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES To determine whether depressive symptoms, pain severity, function, quality of
      life, as well as opioid use can be affected by a lifestyle intervention program in depression
      and chronic pain. To evaluate the implementation of the program at Rivlin Medical Group (RMG)
      chronic pain clinic, and to understand how the SSM intervention can be translated to other
      settings.

      RCT RECRUITMENT AND CONSENT Older adults with chronic pain and depression will be recruited
      from the Rivlin Medical Group. Patients will be pre-screened by clinic staff and be given a
      letter of information/consent form. All potential participants will be given a minimum of 24
      hours to consider participation. After this time, written informed consent will be obtained
      from those interested in participating and they will be screened for eligibility by a
      research coordinator.

      STUDY INTERVENTIONS This study is a 12-week, randomized controlled trial seeking to recruit
      160 participants with depression and chronic pain from RMG. The SSM intervention will be
      offered by trained and certified teachers from the Art of Living Foundation. The HEP
      intervention will be offered by a trained Nurse Practitioner, Social Worker, Psychologist,
      Occupational Therapist or other qualified professional. Raters, clinicians, and care
      providers will be blind to participant study condition.

      DATA COLLECTION Participants will be screened for eligibility using the Patient Health
      Questionnaire (PHQ-9) and Mini Internation Neuropsychiatric Interview Screen and Standard
      7.0.2 (MINI). The primary outcome (depression) will be evaluated using the PHQ-9. The
      secondary outcome (pain severity and pain-related function) will be evaluated using the Brief
      Pain Inventory (BPI. Exploratory outcomes (health related quality of life, and opioid use)
      will be evaluated using the Short-form 36 (SF-36), and a medication log, respectively.
      Measures of primary and secondary outcomes will be administered at all 3 assessment sessions
      and are described below.

      At the baseline assessment the following information will be collected:

      i. Demographics survey that will collect information on age, partial Date of Birth (DOB),
      gender, ethnic background, employment status, housing type, highest level of education
      achieved, smoking, caffeine intake, drug and alcohol use, duration of pain and pain
      diagnosis. Participants will also be asked about their psychiatric history including age of
      first contact with services for mental illness (and which illness), history of hospital
      admissions and the number of episodes of depression; ii. PHQ-9; iii. BPI scale; iv. SF-36; v.
      Medication names, dosages, dosages per day, total daily dosage, and reason for use will be
      recorded, including vitamins and over-the-counter (OTC) medications; vi. Psychology Intake
      Form.

      During the 12 week and 6 month assessment the following questionnaires and measurements will
      be completed:

      i. PHQ-9; ii. BPI scale; iii. SF-36; iv. Medication names and doses will be collected and the
      recordings for opioids will be converted to total daily morphine equivalents using
      standardized conversion tables.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health and Depression Symptomology</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 0), Follow-up 1 (Study completion; Week 12-13), Follow-up 2 (Week 24)</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) is a well-validated and widely used self-report scale used in depression and chronic pain clinical care and research. Reduction in a continuous outcome score is a more sensitive test viz a viz percent reduction in scores which has been reported in some depression studies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain Severity and pain-related function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 0), Follow-up 1 (Study completion; Week 12-13), Follow-up 2 (Week 24)</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) is a validated self-report scale used in pain trials and clinical pain practice and is a core outcome measure per the Initiative on Methods, Measurement, and Pain Assessment in Clinical Trials (IMMPACT) recommendations. Two independent measures are included: pain severity and pain interference with function - both are clinically relevant outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Medication Information</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 0), Follow-up 1 (Study completion; Week 12-13), Follow-up 2 (Week 24)</time_frame>
    <description>Opioid dose will be collected via patient log is the most common measure of opioid use in clinical research trials as per our current review of multidisciplinary care for opioid tapering. Given that patients are on a variety of distinct opioids and that single patients may be on &gt;1 formulation, there is a need for common reporting as provided by morphine equivalent doses.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health-Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Week 0), Follow-up 1 (Study completion; Week 12-13), Follow-up 2 (Week 24)</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 is validated as a QoL measurement in the chronic pain population and is recommended by IMMPACT. Included here as an exploratory outcome with expected positive findings from pilot data collected by co-I Vasudev (unpublished) and other meditation interventions, which demonstrate moderate to large effect sizes. This measure is well-aligned to the intervention which is designed as a means of improving overall QoL more than as a disease treatment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten to fifteen participants in the HEP arm will participate in the program for 4 consecutive days (2hrs/day) in the 1st week, followed by 75 min/week reinforcement sessions for 11 weeks.
The Health-Enhancement Program (HEP) was designed and used as a manualized active control in meditation-based intervention trials. HEP controls for several non-specific factors found in a meditation groups, including: group support and morale, behavioural activation, reduction of stigma, facilitator attention, treatment duration, and time spent on at-home practice. HEP is tailored to be structurally equivalent to SSM with similar-sized groups, meeting schedule, total contact hours, amount of home practice and encouragement to keep practice logs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ten to fifteen participants in the SSM arm will be trained for 4 consecutive days (2hrs/day) in the 1st week, followed by 75 min/week reinforcement sessions for 11 weeks.
This standardized, manualized therapy will be delivered by certified meditation instructors. On day 1, participants will learn the nature of meditation, and then undergo personal guided meditation. Training on days 2-4 includes understanding the nature of the mind and the thoughts arising from it, guided meditations by the instructor, and a discussion of meditation processes. Weekly 75 min reinforcement sessions will include 20 minutes of guided meditation practice, and then focus on participants' experiences with meditation during the week, additional observations, and a review of relevant knowledge to support their home practice. Participants will also be encouraged to practice twice daily at home for 20 minutes per session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Enhancement Program (HEP)</intervention_name>
    <description>This is the active control group of the study, where participants will be educated on health promotion, healthy diet, music, and exercise, but do not learn breathing techniques, or meditation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sahaj Samadhi Meditation (SSM)</intervention_name>
    <description>This is the experimental arm of the study, where participants will be trained in a form of meditation that may improve depressive symptoms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. &gt;45 years of age;

          2. Comorbid depression (PHQ-9 score ≥10);

          3. Chronic pain (pain ≥3 months duration in any body region, by self-report);

          4. On long term opioid therapy (LTOT) (any opioid, at any dose for ≥3 months, by
             self-report);

          5. Be willing and able to attend all 4 training sessions of SSM/HEP and 75% of follow-up
             sessions;

          6. Understanding of English language (spoken and written);

          7. Able to sit for 20-25 minutes without significant discomfort.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Other major psychiatric conditions including substance use disorder, psychosis and
             cognitive impairment as excluded by the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview
             (MINI) Screening and Standard tool; severe depression (PHQ-9 ≥20) and risk of imminent
             suicide as per MINI and/or PHQ-9;

          2. Non-correctable, clinically significant sensory impairment;

          3. Acutely unstable medical illnesses, including delirium or acute cerebrovascular or
             cardiovascular events within the last 6 months;

          4. A terminal medical diagnosis with prognosis of less than 12 months;

          5. Currently practicing any form of mind-body intervention;

          6. Inability to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ross Upshur, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sinai Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abhimanyu Sud, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sinai Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle Nelson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sinai Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Darren K Cheng, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>4164618252</phone>
    <phone_ext>2884</phone_ext>
    <email>darren.cheng@sinaihealthsystem.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alana Armas, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>4164618252</phone>
    <phone_ext>2896</phone_ext>
    <email>alana.armas@sinaihealthsystem.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rivlin Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L5B 2V2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Central Contact Person</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://bit.ly/2ws9ome</url>
    <description>Manual for Health Enhancement Program</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Curran GM, Bauer M, Mittman B, Pyne JM, Stetler C. Effectiveness-implementation hybrid designs: combining elements of clinical effectiveness and implementation research to enhance public health impact. Med Care. 2012 Mar;50(3):217-26. doi: 10.1097/MLR.0b013e3182408812.</citation>
    <PMID>22310560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacCoon DG, Imel ZE, Rosenkranz MA, Sheftel JG, Weng HY, Sullivan JC, Bonus KA, Stoney CM, Salomons TV, Davidson RJ, Lutz A. The validation of an active control intervention for Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction (MBSR). Behav Res Ther. 2012 Jan;50(1):3-12. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2011.10.011. Epub 2011 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22137364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacCoon DG, MacLean KA, Davidson RJ, Saron CD, Lutz A. No sustained attention differences in a longitudinal randomized trial comparing mindfulness based stress reduction versus active control. PLoS One. 2014 Jun 23;9(6):e97551. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0097551. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24955584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rayner L, Hotopf M, Petkova H, Matcham F, Simpson A, McCracken LM. Depression in patients with chronic pain attending a specialised pain treatment centre: prevalence and impact on health care costs. Pain. 2016 Jul;157(7):1472-9. doi: 10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000542.</citation>
    <PMID>26963849</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McMillan D, Gilbody S, Richards D. Defining successful treatment outcome in depression using the PHQ-9: a comparison of methods. J Affect Disord. 2010 Dec;127(1-3):122-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2010.04.030. Epub 2010 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>20569992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meader N, Mitchell AJ, Chew-Graham C, Goldberg D, Rizzo M, Bird V, Kessler D, Packham J, Haddad M, Pilling S. Case identification of depression in patients with chronic physical health problems: a diagnostic accuracy meta-analysis of 113 studies. Br J Gen Pract. 2011 Dec;61(593):e808-20. doi: 10.3399/bjgp11X613151. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22137418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dworkin RH, Turk DC, Farrar JT, Haythornthwaite JA, Jensen MP, Katz NP, Kerns RD, Stucki G, Allen RR, Bellamy N, Carr DB, Chandler J, Cowan P, Dionne R, Galer BS, Hertz S, Jadad AR, Kramer LD, Manning DC, Martin S, McCormick CG, McDermott MP, McGrath P, Quessy S, Rappaport BA, Robbins W, Robinson JP, Rothman M, Royal MA, Simon L, Stauffer JW, Stein W, Tollett J, Wernicke J, Witter J; IMMPACT. Core outcome measures for chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendations. Pain. 2005 Jan;113(1-2):9-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15621359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunningham JL, Evans MM, King SM, Gehin JM, Loukianova LL. Opioid Tapering in Fibromyalgia Patients: Experience from an Interdisciplinary Pain Rehabilitation Program. Pain Med. 2016 Sep;17(9):1676-85. doi: 10.1093/pm/pnv079. Epub 2016 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26755658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elliott TE, Renier CM, Palcher JA. Chronic pain, depression, and quality of life: correlations and predictive value of the SF-36. Pain Med. 2003 Dec;4(4):331-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14750909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hilton L, Hempel S, Ewing BA, Apaydin E, Xenakis L, Newberry S, Colaiaco B, Maher AR, Shanman RM, Sorbero ME, Maglione MA. Mindfulness Meditation for Chronic Pain: Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. Ann Behav Med. 2017 Apr;51(2):199-213. doi: 10.1007/s12160-016-9844-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27658913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mount Sinai Hospital, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ross Upshur</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Opioid Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Sahaj Samadhi Meditation</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Enhancement Program</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

