<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04032522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LMU-IMPH-LIFE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04032522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neonatal HIV Early Infant Diagnosis (EID) Versus Standard of Care EID- Long Term Impact on inFant hEalth (LIFE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIFE</acronym>
  <official_title>Neonatal HIV Early Infant Diagnosis (EID) Versus Standard of Care EID - Long Term Impact on inFant hEalth: a Feasibility Study of point-of Care Testing at Birth Versus at 6 Weeks of Age, on the Uptake of ART and Infant Prophylaxis, and on Rates of Infant Survival, Morbidity and Retention in Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Michael Hoelscher</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Nacional de Saude (INS), Ministério da Saúde, Maputo, Mozambique</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NIMR- Mbeya Medical Research Centre (MMRC), Mbeya, Tanzania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Lisbon Instituto Universitário Egas Moniz (IUEM) Lisbon, Portugal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinton Health Access Initiative, Maputo, Mozambique</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ludwig-Maximilians - University of Munich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study we will evaluate the benefit of HIV testing in neonates born from HIV-infected
      mothers in Tanzania and Mozambique. The study will use and evaluate novel point-of-care
      diagnostic systems, that can provide neonatal HIV test results within 2 hours. We will
      evaluate if HIV testing at birth followed by immediate neonatal HIV treatment initiation will
      lead to lesser infant's sickness, HIV progression or even death as compared to the current
      standard procedure which is infant HIV testing at week 6 after delivery. This will be
      associated with a cost-effectiveness analysis in order to guide national HIV programs for
      their guidelines. The study will further evaluate if point-of care viral load testing in
      mothers at birth will identify high-risk scenarios for HIV transmission from the mother to
      her child. This should lead to enhanced prophylactic treatments in HIV-exposed infants and we
      hypothesize that PoC VL monitoring at birth leads to lower transmission rates. The study will
      be performed at 28 maternity health facilities in Tanzania and Mozambique, half of them will
      be randomized to provide birth HIV PoC infant and maternal viral load testing, the other half
      will provide the current standard of care (infant HIV testing at week 6, no PoC VL monitoring
      at birth for the mother). The study is conducted in public health settings, and some study
      objectives also focus on how successful modern HIV treatments can be provided to infants, if
      HIV testing and treatment procedures are feasible for nurses and midwives, and if these
      procedures can be carried out in a timely manner. This study also includes a basic research
      component that will investigate how HIV spreads in the body of HIV-infected infants, and if
      early infant HIV diagnosis and treatment can reduce the spread in cells of HIV-infected
      individuals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical impact of a PoC-EID</measure>
    <time_frame>Proportion of combined clinical endpoints in HIV-infected infants at months 18 between arms</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective is to establish the clinical impact of a PoC-EID for infants and neonates at birth and week 4-8 weeks, linked with nurse-supported immediate ART initiation in HIV-infected neonates, versus standard-of-care (SoC) on the primary and secondary endpoints. Combined clinical outcomes will include mortality, morbidity (WHO Stage 2 or above disease, severe infant medical conditions), hospitalization, toxicity (Grade 3 or above laboratory abnormality), poor antiretroviral treatment response (confirmed virological failure, treatment termination or prolonged interruption), or loss to follow up of HIVinfected infants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV, Neonatal HIV Early-Infant-Diagnosis (EID), Point-of-Care Testing (PoC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm (A)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Half of the health facilities will implement the intervention package. All mothers will be tested using PoC-VL at delivery and all HIV-exposed infants will be offered PoC-EID at birth and week 4-8. Newborns found to be HIV-positive will be offered immediate ART. Neonatal ART initiation will be supported at birth by trained nurses/midwives, and approved and supervised by local doctors from the affiliated HIV CTC. Following ART initiation infants will be referred for consolidated ART management to their paediatric HIV clinic following local procedures. Newborns testing HIV-negative will be offered postnatal prophylaxis (PNP) or enhanced postnatal prophylaxis (ePNP), depending on clinical risk factors, the maternal VL and country guidelines. Mothers with HIV-RNA &gt;1000 copies/mL will receive immediate referral information for ART initiation if not on ART or enhanced ART counselling, with follow up virologic testing and switch of ART regimen as applicable at their local HIV clinic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm (B)</arm_group_label>
    <description>The other half of the health facilities will implement the standard of care (SoC). Enrolled mothers will not receive immediate PoC VL at delivery, but infants deemed to be at high risk using clinical criteria (e.g. no or late initiation of maternal ART) will be offered ePNP. EID testing will follow the national algorithm with testing at 4-8 weeks, followed by referral for immediate ART initiation for all HIV-infected infants. As PoC EID testing is expected to be nationally implemented on a programme level we will facilitate the availability of PoC testing at these sites.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>point-of care (PoC) neonatal HIV early infant diagnosis (EID)</intervention_name>
    <description>clinical impact of a PoC-EID for infants and neonates at birth and week 4-8 weeks, linked with nurse-supported immediate ART initiation in HIV-infected neonates, versus standard-of-care (SoC)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm (A)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        HIV infected pregnant women and their exposed infants will be recruited at maternity
        clinics in Mozambique and Tanzania. Assuming a 4% MTCT rate by week 6 and a difference of
        combined HIV-infected infant endpoints of 14% (Arm A) versus 30% (Arm B) the study target
        is to enrol at least 224 HIV infected infants (112 per arm) from both countries into the
        follow-up phase resulting in an overall recruitment number of 6000 mother-child pairs (3000
        per arm), including an assumed 5% loss to follow-up. Furthermore, we will enrol 400
        HIV-exposed infants from both countries after week 12 into a long-term follow-up phase to
        investigate MTCT rates and associated MTCT risks until the end of the study period after
        cessation of breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Voluntary and informed consent of the mother for her own study participation

          2. Voluntary and informed consent of the legal guardian of the child for participation of
             the child in the study.

          3. Mothers/legal guardians ≥18 years of age.

          4. Documented maternal HIV infection.

          5. Willingness to consent to HIV testing for the child and herself.

          6. Willingness to consent to active tracing including home tracing.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Deficiency in the mother, rendering it difficult, if not impossible, for her or her
             infant to take part in the study or understand the information provided to her. This
             includes alcoholism, drug dependency as well as psychiatric illnesses, suicidal
             tendencies or any other inability.

          2. Having delivered more than 72h (3 days) ago

          3. Prisoners

          4. Women presenting with an emergency requiring immediate medical assistance if not
             resolved at study inclusion

          5. Stillbirths

          6. Infant requiring emergency care (e.g. immediate or rapid occurring life threatening
             conditions, resuscitation, prolonged obstetric related intensive care, severe
             jaundice) or born with severe malformation.

          7. If within the discretion of the investigator based on recommendation of the
             gynaecologist or paediatrician in charge study participation would possibly add not
             acceptable risk or burden to the mother or infant (e.g. significant congenital
             malformation, health deficiencies, very low birth weight less than 1500g)

          8. Unlikely to comply with protocol as judged by the principal investigator or his
             designate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arne Kroidl, Dr. med</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and Tropical Medicine, University Hospital, LMU Munich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ilesh Jani, Dr., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto Nacional de Saude (INS), Ministério da Saúde, Maputo, Mozambique</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Issa Sabi, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NIMR- Mbeya Medical Research Centre (MMRC), Mbeya, Tanzania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Otto Geisenberger, Dr. rer. nat.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 89 4400 598</phone>
    <phone_ext>-26</phone_ext>
    <email>geisenberger@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Arne Kroidl, Dr. med.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 89 4400 598</phone>
    <phone_ext>-16</phone_ext>
    <email>akroidl@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Investigacao Operacional da Beira (CIOB)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beira</city>
        <state>Sofala</state>
        <country>Mozambique</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bindiya Meggi, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mozambique</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ludwig-Maximilians - University of Munich</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Hoelscher</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Division of Infectious Diseases and Tropical Medicine, University Hospital, LMU Munich</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

