<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01115608</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHAN-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01115608</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmaceutical Follow-up of Coronary Heart Disease (CHD) Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development of a Standardized Clinical Pharmacist Service for Patients Discharged From Hospital. Measurement of Drug Prescribing Quality in Secondary Prevention of Coronary Heart Disease Utilizing a Medication Assessment Tool (MAT-CHDsp)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Pharmacy of North Norway Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Tromso</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Pharmacy of North Norway Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives To explore the impact of a clinical pharmacist-led 12 month lasting follow-up
      program for patients with established coronary heart disease (CHD) discharged from the North
      Norway University Hospital. Methods A total of 102 patients aged 18-82 years were enrolled in
      a non-blinded, randomized controlled trial. The intervention comprised medication
      reconciliation, medication review and patient education during three meetings; at discharge,
      after three months and after twelve months. The control group received standard care from
      their general practitioner. Primary outcomes were adherence to clinical guideline
      recommendations concerning prescription, therapy goal achievement and lifestyle education
      defined in the medication assessment tool for secondary prevention of CHD (MAT-CHDSP).
      Secondary outcomes included changes in the biomedical risk factors cholesterol, blood
      pressure and blood glucose. Key findings Ninety-four patients completed the trial, 48
      intervention group patients and 46 controls.

      Appropriate prescribing was high, but therapy goal achievement was low in both study groups
      throughout the study. Overall adherence to MAT-CHDSP criteria increased in both groups and
      was significantly higher in the intervention group at study end compared to the control
      group, 78.1% vs. 61.4%, P &lt; 0.001. The difference was mainly due to an increased
      documentation of lifestyle advices in intervention group patients.

      No significant improvements in biomedical risk factors were observed in favor of the
      intervention group, possible due to an underpowered study. Conclusion The clinical
      pharmacist-led follow-up program significantly increased documented lifestyle advices defined
      in the MAT-CHDSP for the intervention group, but did not lead to significant improvements in
      biomedical risk factor measures in favor of the intervention group. Even if prescribing was
      high, therapy goal achievement was low in both study groups. Changes to the follow-up program
      are warranted, in addition to a larger, adequately powered study, before implementation in
      standard patient care can be recommended.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Find published article in Pharm Pract (Granada). 2015 Apr-Jun; 13(2): 575.
      https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4482847/pdf/pharmpract-13-575.pdf
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to MAT-CHDsp (medication assessment tool based on guideline recommendations)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline (both arms)</time_frame>
    <description>MAT-CHDsp includes 20 review criteria assessing both appropriateness of drug prescribing, appropriateness of dose adjustments/change of drugs and appropriateness of information concerning life-style modifications. Achievment of therapeutic goals concerning lipids, blood pressure and blood glucose is also measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to MAT-CHDsp (medication assessment tool based on guideline recommendations)</measure>
    <time_frame>After one year (both arms)</time_frame>
    <description>MAT-CHDsp includes 20 review criteria assessing both appropriateness of drug prescribing, appropriateness of dose adjustments/change of drugs and appropriateness of information concerning life-style modifications. Achievment of therapeutic goals concerning lipids, blood pressure and blood glucose is also measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug related problems</measure>
    <time_frame>At inclusion, after three months and after one year.</time_frame>
    <description>Medication reviews often reveals safety issues concerning the drug regime, except from the primary outcome measures. THese are noted and will be assessed and tried solved during follow-up in close cooperation with the GP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalisation</measure>
    <time_frame>After one year</time_frame>
    <description>Data will be collected, both for the study group and for the control group, concerning hospitalisation during the year included in the study. The groups will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pharmacist follow-up</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients will receive pharmaceutical follow-up during one year after discharge from the hospital. Three meetings are arranged, one at discharge, one after three months and the last after one year. Patients will be called up for arrangement of &quot;consultation&quot;. Written information concerning drugs used will be supplied.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group receives no follow-up from the pharmacist, but will after one year, when they are out of the study, receive one follow-up visit and drug review.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacist follow-up</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug review, drug conversation and written drug information. Follow-up concerning therapeutic goals and cooperation with the patient and the patient's GP to achieve these.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pharmacist follow-up</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  established coronary heart disease

          -  age 18 - 80 years

          -  patients living in the three nearby communities Tromsoe, Balsfjord and Karlsoey, this
             because they need to see the pharmacist personally.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients living in nursing homes

          -  patients included in NORstent, another trial including patients at the same department

          -  patients already receiving pharmaceutical follow-up elsewhere

          -  cancer patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Trude Giverhaug, Dr.Scient.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Pharmacy of North Norway Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Pharmacy of North Norway Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tromsø</city>
        <zip>9020</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://helseforskning.etikkom.no/?_ikbLanguageCode=us</url>
    <description>Regional Committees for Medical and Health Research Ethics (REK)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nsd.uib.no/nsd/english/index.html</url>
    <description>Norwegian Social Science Data Services (NSD)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4482847/pdf/pharmpract-13-575.pdf</url>
    <description>Published Article</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Pharmacy of North Norway Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Beate Hennie Garcia, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Preventive Health Services</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No IPD will be shared</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

