<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01925404</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011-0692-AM02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL114283</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01925404</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting Physical Activity In High Poverty Neighborhoods</brief_title>
  <official_title>Promoting Physical Activity In High Poverty Neighborhoods</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RAND</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>City of Los Angeles Department of Recreation and Parks</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AltaMed Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RAND</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Encouraging greater levels of physical activity is critical to improving health among
      Americans, who are largely sedentary. Neighborhood parks are resources for physical activity
      that are available to most Americans within a couple miles of their homes, yet many residents
      are unaware of the programs and facilities available. Previous research indicates that park
      use is related to park programming and outreach. Because funding for parks is limited,
      low-cost interventions are needed to attract more people to parks to engage in
      moderate-to-vigorous physical activity. While many community-based organizations would like
      to invest in efforts that increase physical activity, few low-cost park programs are
      documented to be both scalable and cost-effective. Effective programs that can be replicated
      to make population-level impacts are needed. The goal of this study is to develop and test 2
      low-cost community-level approaches, free exercise classes vs. a frequent user program, to
      promoting physical activity, singly and in combination, in 48 park settings in Los Angeles
      low-income neighborhoods.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While routine physical activity is critical to optimal health, our preliminary studies have
      indicated that residents of low-income communities in Los Angeles are less likely to exercise
      than those in high-income communities, and they are less likely to use their neighborhood
      parks, even when the parks are within walking distance. Parks in low-income neighborhoods
      tend to be smaller and serve a greater population density, but even after accounting for the
      size and the population served, they are still used less than parks in wealthier
      neighborhoods. In our preliminary studies we found that parks in low-income neighborhoods
      also had fewer part-time staff and offered fewer programs and organized activities than parks
      in higher-income areas, and these factors partly accounted for their lower use. As well,
      parks in low-income neighborhoods are often perceived as less safe, a characteristic
      associated with lower use 4. Simultaneously, the lack of use and dearth of programming may
      contribute to a perception of lack of safety, creating a vicious cycle. Nonetheless, we have
      documented that when parks in low-income neighborhoods offer events and activities, they can
      be just as busy as parks in higher-income areas. We hypothesize that limited park use in
      low-income areas can be attributed to the lack of organized and reliable infrastructure of
      activities that meet the needs of local residents and that offering more activities and
      programs in parks will increase park use and park-based physical activity.

      According to the Task Force on Community Level Preventive Services, community-level campaigns
      are both effective and scalable.6 For the past eight years, we have conducted research in
      public neighborhood parks and found that these venues offer great potential for increasing
      physical activity for populations. Based upon this work, as well as our previous work on the
      cost-effectiveness of physical activity interventions, we propose to test community-level
      campaigns targeting low-income populations that will be relatively low-cost and easy to
      replicate.

      The proposed study has three specific aims:

        1. Using a full factorial design, compare whether park use and population physical activity
           in low-income neighborhoods increase with the availability of a) more organized physical
           activity classes, including zumba, line dancing, and aerobics indoors and outdoors,
           and/or b) a loyalty program approach that rewards frequent park users.

        2. Determine whether either of these two approaches changes the perception of park safety
           and neighborhood safety.

        3. Identify the cost effectiveness of both approaches in terms of dollars spent to generate
           increased physical activity in parks as measured through systematic observation.

      Most Los Angeles parks have full-time staff, but their role has become increasingly
      administrative. Park staff may not have the time or the skills to lead physical activity
      programs and activities nor conduct effective outreach to the community to promote these
      activities. Although there is a small literature on &quot;best practices&quot; for parks, there is no
      underlying foundation of rigorous scientific research, and there has been no identification
      of which park practices, designs, or activities lead to the most physical activity in a
      community. Standard practice is currently based primarily on anecdotes, demands of special
      interest groups, and the experience of professionals. The science of objectively measuring
      physical activity in parks is new, developed only in the past decade. Because neighborhood
      parks are settings designed for moderate to vigorous physical activity (MVPA) and are
      accessible to 70% of the US population, identifying which programs help populations achieve
      physical activity goals at a reasonable cost would be highly useful, particularly for groups
      disproportionately affected with chronic diseases that could be reduced with physical
      activity. Parks are community resources typically funded by dedicated revenue streams and
      fee-based programs, yet park systems frequently lack the tools and resources to either market
      programs or measure their reach or effectiveness. Our study will document all the steps
      required for implementing and maintaining two physical activity promotion interventions--one
      a standard approach offering traditional organized physical activity programs, the other an
      innovative application of popular customer loyalty programs. We will determine their impact
      on physical activity and their cost-effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage Change in Park-based Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>difference between baseline and follow-up (1 year)</time_frame>
    <description>Physical activity was measured in MET-hours (Metabolic equivalents)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Park Use (% Change)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline versus 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>We will count the number of parks users and compare differences between the number counted at baseline to the number counted at follow-up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Frequent User Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Park users will be able to earn rewards or prizes by coming more frequently to the park</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Free Physical Activity Classes/programs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We will offer at least 100 free physical activity classes at the park</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We will offer free classes and the frequent user program at the park</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Business as usual, no special physical activity programs offered</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Free physical activity classes</intervention_name>
    <description>100 hours of free activity classes will be provided</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Free Physical Activity Classes/programs</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Frequent User</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Frequent User Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Parks are in low-income neighborhoods; individuals visit parks and/or
        live within 1 mile radius of the park; -

        Exclusion Criteria: Parks are not in low income neighborhoods; individuals do not visit the
        park and do not live within a 1 mile radius

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah A Cohen, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>RAND</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>RAND</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Monica</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>December 15, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2018</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>parks</keyword>
  <keyword>programming</keyword>
  <keyword>public health</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>May be available upon request as appropriate. We have response data from park users and residents living within one mile of enrolled parks. Interested researchers should contact the PI</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 10, 2013</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/04/NCT01925404/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 26, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/04/NCT01925404/SAP_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Parks are the unit of analysis; Parks were randomly assigned to the study arms</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Frequent User Arm</title>
          <description>Park users will be able to earn rewards or prizes by coming more frequently to the park
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Free Physical Activity Classes/Programs</title>
          <description>We will offer at least 100 free physical activity classes at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Combined Arm</title>
          <description>We will offer free classes and the frequent user program at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P4">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>Business as usual, no special physical activity programs offered</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="NA">The primary outcome of this study is at the level of a park.
The park is the unit of analysis. We did not recruit participants, but had measure of park use by counting observed users</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="NA">The park is the unit of analysis. We did not recruit participants, but had measure of park use by counting observed users</participants>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="NA">The park is the unit of analysis. We did not recruit participants, but had measure of park use by counting observed users</participants>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="NA">The park is the unit of analysis. We did not recruit participants, but had measure of park use by counting observed users</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="NA">We did not recruit participants or follow the same park users over time. The follow up numbers of users are greater than at baseline, and this generates an error message.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="NA">We did not recruit participants or follow the same park users over time. The follow up numbers of users are greater than at baseline, and this generates an error message.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="NA">We did not recruit participants or follow the same park users over time. The follow up numbers of users are greater than at baseline, and this generates an error message.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="NA">We did not recruit participants or follow the same park users over time. The follow up numbers of users are greater than at baseline, and this generates an error message.</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="NA"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="NA"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="NA"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="NA"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>Participants were not assigned to study arms</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Frequent User Arm</title>
          <description>Park users will be able to earn rewards or prizes by coming more frequently to the park
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Free Physical Activity Classes/Programs</title>
          <description>We will offer at least 100 free physical activity classes at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Combined Arm</title>
          <description>We will offer free classes and the frequent user program at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B4">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>Business as usual, no special physical activity programs offered</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B5">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="NA"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="NA"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="NA"/>
            <count group_id="B4" value="NA"/>
            <count group_id="B5" value="NA"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
        <analyzed>
          <units>parks</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B4" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B5" value="48"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <description>Age data are not relevant to parks</description>
          <units>parks</units>
          <param>Count of Units</param>
          <units_analyzed>parks</units_analyzed>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="NA">Total not calculated because data are not available (NA) in one or more arms.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="NA">Total not calculated because data are not available (NA) in one or more arms.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="NA">Age is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="NA">Total not calculated because data are not available (NA) in one or more arms.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <description>Gender data are not relevant to parks</description>
          <units>parks</units>
          <param>Count of Units</param>
          <units_analyzed>parks</units_analyzed>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="NA">Total not calculated because data are not available (NA) in one or more arms.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="NA">Gender is not relevant to parks</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="NA">Total not calculated because data are not available (NA) in one or more arms.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>park size,</title>
          <units>acres</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <units_analyzed>parks</units_analyzed>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6.1" lower_limit="2.6" upper_limit="10.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9.0" lower_limit="1.9" upper_limit="19.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="8.0" lower_limit="1.9" upper_limit="25.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="10.3" lower_limit="1.5" upper_limit="25.0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="8.4" lower_limit="1.5" upper_limit="25.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>population density</title>
          <units>people</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <units_analyzed>parks</units_analyzed>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="659102"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="583346"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="603596"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="664846"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B5" value="2510890"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Percentage Change in Park-based Physical Activity</title>
        <description>Physical activity was measured in MET-hours (Metabolic equivalents)</description>
        <time_frame>difference between baseline and follow-up (1 year)</time_frame>
        <population>The unit of analysis was at the level of the park.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Frequent User Arm</title>
            <description>Park users will be able to earn rewards or prizes by coming more frequently to the park
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Free Physical Activity Classes/Programs</title>
            <description>We will offer at least 100 free physical activity classes at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Combined Arm</title>
            <description>We will offer free classes and the frequent user program at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O4">
            <title>Control</title>
            <description>Business as usual, no special physical activity programs offered</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage Change in Park-based Physical Activity</title>
          <description>Physical activity was measured in MET-hours (Metabolic equivalents)</description>
          <population>The unit of analysis was at the level of the park.</population>
          <units>Percent change in MET-hours</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <units_analyzed>Parks</units_analyzed>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="NA"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="NA"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="NA"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="NA"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Parks</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="12"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="11.2" lower_limit="-6.2" upper_limit="28.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6.1" lower_limit="-7.2" upper_limit="19.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="5.6" lower_limit="-9.9" upper_limit="21.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="8.4" lower_limit="-4.9" upper_limit="21.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
              <group_id>O3</group_id>
              <group_id>O4</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Comparison of change from baseline;</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <non_inferiority_desc>We fitted difference-in-differences (DID) models between the two measurement waves and four study arms. The effect of the intervention was modeled as the wave by study arm interaction. All models used random effects to account for intra-class correlation within each park as well as fixed effects to account for observation times (time of day, weekend versus weekdays).</non_inferiority_desc>
            <p_value>.0063</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Significance threshold. p=0.05</p_value_desc>
            <method>negative binomial distribution</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Park Use (% Change)</title>
        <description>We will count the number of parks users and compare differences between the number counted at baseline to the number counted at follow-up</description>
        <time_frame>baseline versus 1 year</time_frame>
        <population>Participants were not assigned to study arms</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Frequent User Arm</title>
            <description>Park users will be able to earn rewards or prizes by coming more frequently to the park
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Free Physical Activity Classes/Programs</title>
            <description>We will offer at least 100 free physical activity classes at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Combined Arm</title>
            <description>We will offer free classes and the frequent user program at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O4">
            <title>Control</title>
            <description>Business as usual, no special physical activity programs offered</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Park Use (% Change)</title>
          <description>We will count the number of parks users and compare differences between the number counted at baseline to the number counted at follow-up</description>
          <population>Participants were not assigned to study arms</population>
          <units>percentage change in park users</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <units_analyzed>parks</units_analyzed>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="NA"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="NA"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="NA"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="NA"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
            <analyzed>
              <units>parks</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O4" value="12"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="10" lower_limit="-9.4" upper_limit="29.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.0" lower_limit="-10.3" upper_limit="18.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="6.6" lower_limit="-11.6" upper_limit="24.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O4" value="9.7" lower_limit="-2.7" upper_limit="22.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
      <desc>Adverse events occurred if there was any injury associated with our intervention.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Frequent User Arm</title>
          <description>Park users will be able to earn rewards or prizes by coming more frequently to the park
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Free Physical Activity Classes/Programs</title>
          <description>We will offer at least 100 free physical activity classes at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Combined Arm</title>
          <description>We will offer free classes and the frequent user program at the park
Free physical activity classes: 100 hours of free activity classes will be provided
Frequent User: Participants can become eligible for prizes by visiting the park more frequently</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E4">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>Business as usual, no special physical activity programs offered</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E4" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Park observations were snapshot direct observations of aggregated activities. Resident surveys were based on self-reports, subject to reporting biases. The resident sample was a repeated-cross sectional sample rather than a longitudinal cohort.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Deborah Cohen</name_or_title>
      <organization>RAND</organization>
      <phone>310 3930411</phone>
      <email>dcohen@rand.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

