<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01659749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00002447a</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01659749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Educational, Social Support, and Nutritional Interventions and Their Cumulative Effect on Pregnancy Outcomes and Quality of Life in Teen and Adult Women With Phenylketonuria</brief_title>
  <official_title>Educational, Social Support, and Nutritional Interventions and Their Cumulative Effect on Pregnancy Outcomes and Quality of Life in Teen and Adult Women With Phenylketonuria (PKU) or Maple Syrup Urine Disease (MSUD).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this project is to study the effectiveness of teaching teens and young women
      with Phenylketonuria (PKU) or Maple Syrup Urine Disease (MSUD) about their disease and
      nutrition related issues in a camp environment. It will also look at pregnancy outcome
      results in women with PKU who attended Metabolic Camp and compare their results to other
      women with PKU who have not attended the Metabolic Camp.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic Camp is an educational and social support program with research opportunities that
      was developed in 1995 by Rani H. Singh, PhD, RD for females age 11 through adult with
      phenylketonuria (PKU) and maple syrup urine disease (MSUD), two inherited metabolic disorders
      (IMD). Camp provides a supportive environment for adolescent girls and women to learn about
      the importance of nutrition and diet self-management, with the intention of arresting the
      disease process and minimizing the instances of miscarriages and severe birth defects, which
      are high in this population. After 20+ years, Metabolic Camp is established as a unique,
      national program allowing up to 35 campers to live and learn during a week of nutritional
      support and productive activities, while simultaneously providing researchers an opportunity
      to gather important data.

      The aims of Metabolic Camp are 1) to implement education curriculum and support activities as
      an intervention program for females with PKU and MSUD, 2) to evaluate knowledge of disease
      and dietary management, dietary treatment compliance, quality of life, and reproductive
      choice issues and assess change in outcomes post-Camp, 3) to gather data through the
      implementation of a research protocol during baseline and post-Camp each year, and 4) to
      provide clinical and research training in IMD for professionals, from dietitians to medical
      students. Campers must complete an informed consent process, should they decide to
      participate in research activities. All campers submit a three-day food record and blood
      samples to measure plasma amino acids on the first and last day of camp, both of which are
      not classified as research activities, but rather standard of care for their disorder.
      Additional studies such as indirect calorimetry, bone health markers, anthropometric markers,
      nutritional status, mental and emotional wellbeing, neurocognitive functioning, access to
      disease specific care, metabolomic profiling, gut microbiota, and blood and urine analysis,
      have been and may continue to be assessed in those who participate in research pre and
      post-Camp. These are novel investigations for the study of IMD and essential to understand
      the physiological effects of Camp.

      In over 20 years of Metabolic Camp, the following data have been collected: health history
      and demographics, anthropometrics, dietary intake, compliance with medically prescribed diet,
      quality of life, physical activity, plasma amino acids, select blood and urine biomarkers,
      and bone density. Data are stored in REDCap, allowing evaluation of short- and long-term
      outcomes on the life course of females with PKU and MSUD. Each year, phenylalanine
      (Phe)/leucine (Leu) blood concentrations of campers decrease over the one week camp period,
      demonstrating better metabolic control and compliance with diet. Campers' knowledge of
      disease etiology, management, and effects, including Maternal PKU Syndrome (MPKU) are
      improved. Social support networks are strengthened by meeting peers with the same or similar
      disorder. The study protocol includes a comprehensive assessment of blood and urine
      biomarkers to examine PKU from a much broader approach compared to the traditional
      measurement of a single biomarker to assess patient status. Beneficial to campers and
      clinicians alike, Metabolic Camp is an invaluable experience to gain insight, knowledge, and
      stimulate new ideas related to research and optimal patient care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2037</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2035</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma Amino Acid concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration of Phenylalanine in plasma (measured in mg/dL) will be measured the first day of metabolic camp and at the last day of the camp.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Dietary intake of Phenylalanine</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 1</time_frame>
    <description>Dietary intake of Phenylalanine (measured in mg/Kg) will be measured the first day of metabolic camp and at the last day of the camp, using a three-day diet food record that has been completed at baseline and post-camp.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Phenylketonuria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metabolic Camp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Metabolic Camp is an educational and social support program for females age 11 through adult with phenylketonuria (PKU) and maple syrup urine disease (MSUD), two inherited metabolic disorders (IMD). Camp provides a supportive environment for adolescent girls and women to learn about the importance of nutrition and diet self-management, with the intention of arresting the disease process and minimizing the instances of miscarriages and severe birth defects, which are high in this population. After 20+ years, Metabolic Camp is established as a unique, national program allowing up to 35 campers to live and learn during a week of nutritional support and productive activities, while simultaneously providing researchers an opportunity to gather important data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metabolic camp</intervention_name>
    <description>To use an recreational camp setting to instruct PKU females of reproductive age how to make responsible dietary and reproductive decisions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metabolic Camp</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with PKU or other aminoacidopathy, female, age 11 or older, able to provide
             informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those not fitting the inclusion criteria

        Inclusion Criteria for healthy controls

        Individuals eligible to participate in this study must meet all of the following criteria:

          -  Adult camp counselors or staff determined to be in good health.

          -  Not diagnosed with PKU, MSUD or other hereditary metabolic disorder

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent

          -  Willing and able to comply with relevant camp guidelines and study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rani H Singh, PhD RD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rani H Singh, PhD RD</last_name>
    <phone>4047278519</phone>
    <email>rsingh@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristen Narlow, MS RD</last_name>
    <phone>4047788610</phone>
    <email>kristen.narlow@emory.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Department of Human Genetics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rani H Singh, PhD RD</last_name>
      <phone>404-727-8519</phone>
      <email>rsingh@emory.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rani Singh PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Maternal PKU</keyword>
  <keyword>Phenylketonuria (PKU)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phenylketonurias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: assent form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 12, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/49/NCT01659749/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form: assent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 12, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/49/NCT01659749/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

