<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02726997</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0900</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-00557</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-0900</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02726997</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Matched Paired Pharmacodynamics and Feasibility Study of Durvalumab in Combination With Chemotherapy in Frontline Ovarian Cancer (N-Dur)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Matched Paired Pharmacodynamics and Feasibility Study of Durvalumab in Combination With Chemotherapy in Frontline Ovarian Cancer (N-Dur)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies how well durvalumab works when given in combination with
      carboplatin and paclitaxel in treating patients with stage III-IV ovarian, primary
      peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer. Immunotherapy with monoclonal antibodies, such as
      durvalumab, may help the body's immune system attack the cancer, and may interfere with the
      ability of tumor cells to grow and spread. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as carboplatin
      and paclitaxel, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing
      the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Giving
      durvalumab in combination with carboplatin and paclitaxel may be a better treatment for
      ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To explore basal levels and effects of durvalumab in combination with chemotherapy on
      molecular markers in immune-related pathways, including but not limited to, deoxyribonucleic
      acid (DNA) copy number, mutation, and level of ribonucleic acid (RNA) and protein expression,
      before and after durvalumab and chemotherapy treatment in women with primary advanced high
      grade serous ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary peritoneal cancer.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate progression-free survival of paclitaxel and carboplatin and durvalumab in
      patients with advanced stage, metastatic ovarian cancer undergoing neoadjuvant chemotherapy.

      II. To describe the feasibility of combination therapy and maintenance durvalumab in this
      population.

      III. To evaluate the safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics (PK) of combination and
      maintenance durvalumab.

      IV. To report overall survival.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate circulating lymphoid populations (subsets). II. To determine tissue programmed
      death-ligand 1 (PD-L1) expression and T-cell infiltration.

      III. To measure circulating immune-related cytokines/chemokines. IV. To capture patient
      reported outcomes (symptoms, quality of life, and patient utilities).

      OUTLINE:

      NEOADJUVANT CHEMOTHERAPY: Before debulking surgery, patients receive durvalumab and
      carboplatin intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on day 1, and paclitaxel IV over 3 hours on days
      1, 8, and 15. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then undergo debulking surgery.

      SURGERY: After 3 courses of chemotherapy, patients undergo debulking laparoscopic surgery.

      ADJUVANT THERAPY: Beginning after debulking surgery, patients receive carboplatin IV over 1
      hour on day 1, paclitaxel IV over 3 hours on days 1, 8, and 15, and durvalumab IV over 1 hour
      on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      MAINTENANCE THERAPY: Patients receive durvalumab IV over 1 hour on day 1 and 15. Treatment
      repeats every 28 days for up to 7 courses in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 9,
      10, and 12 months, and then every 6 months thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 6, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic Changes Induced by Treatment with Durvalumab in Combination with Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Women with Advanced Stage, Metastatic Ovarian Cancer Using Paired T-Test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Paired t-test with a 2-sided significance level of 0.05 used to test whether the change in biomarker expression from pre-treatment to post-treatment with Durvalumab is different from 0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic Changes Induced by Treatment with Durvalumab in Combination with Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Women with Advanced Stage, Metastatic Ovarian Cancer Using an Exact Binomial Test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Exact binomial test with a 1-sided significance level of 0.05 used to test whether the probability of a biomarker increasing (or decreasing) is &gt; 0.50.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic Changes Induced by Treatment with Durvalumab in Combination with Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Women with Advanced Stage, Metastatic Ovarian Cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Fisher's exact test with a 1-sided significance level of 0.05 used to compare the proportion of participants treated with Durvalumab who have increasing (or decreasing) expression rates with the corresponding proportion from a historical control group of 30 untreated patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic Changes Induced by Treatment with Durvalumab in Combination with Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Women with Advanced Stage, Metastatic Ovarian Cancer Using a 2-Sample T-Test</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>A 2-sample t-test with a 2-sided significance level of 0.05 used to compare change in biomarker expression between patients treated with Durvalumab and a control group of 30 untreated patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival with Treatment with Durvalumab in Combination with Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Women with Advanced Stage, Metastatic Ovarian Cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Progression defined by any of the following: 25% increase in sum of the products of perpendicular diameters of enhancing lesions compared with the smallest tumor measurement obtained either at baseline (if no decrease) or best response, on stable or increasing doses of corticosteroids; significant increase in T2/FLAIR nonenhancing lesion on stable or increasing doses of corticosteroids compared with baseline scan or best response after initiation of therapy not caused by comorbid events (eg, radiation therapy, demyelination, ischemic injury, infection, seizures, postoperative changes, or other treatment effects); any new lesion; clear clinical deterioration not attributable to other causes apart from the tumor (eg, seizures, medication adverse events, complications of therapy, cerebrovascular events, infection) or changes in corticosteroid dose; failure to return for evaluation as a result of death or deteriorating condition; or clear progression of nonmeasurable disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Treatment with Durvalumab in Combination with Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Women with Advanced Stage, Metastatic Ovarian Cancer Determined by Methods of Thall et all</measure>
    <time_frame>126 days</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility defined as the ability to complete all planned cycles of adjuvant therapy, using the methods of Thall et al. (1994).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage III Fallopian Tube Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Ovarian Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Primary Peritoneal Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Fallopian Tube Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Ovarian Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Primary Peritoneal Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Fallopian Tube Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Ovarian Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Primary Peritoneal Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Fallopian Tube Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Ovarian Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Primary Peritoneal Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Fallopian Tube Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Ovarian Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Primary Peritoneal Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NEOADJUVANT CHEMOTHERAPY: Before debulking surgery, patients receive durvalumab and carboplatin IV over 1 hour on day 1, and paclitaxel IV over 3 hours on days 1, 8, and 15. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then undergo debulking surgery.
SURGERY: After 3 courses of chemotherapy, patients undergo debulking laparoscopic surgery.
ADJUVANT THERAPY: Beginning after debulking surgery, patients receive carboplatin IV over 1 hour on day 1, paclitaxel IV over 3 hours on days 1, 8, and 15, and durvalumab IV over 1 hour on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
MAINTENANCE THERAPY: Patients receive durvalumab IV over 1 hour on day 1 and 15. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 7 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blastocarb</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatin Hexal</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosol</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbotec</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>Displata</other_name>
    <other_name>Ercar</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Nealorin</other_name>
    <other_name>Novoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinwas</other_name>
    <other_name>Ribocarbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Imfinzi</other_name>
    <other_name>Immunoglobulin G1, Anti-(Human Protein B7-H1) (Human Monoclonal MEDI4736 Heavy Chain), Disulfide with Human Monoclonal MEDI4736 Kappa-chain, Dimer</other_name>
    <other_name>MEDI-4736</other_name>
    <other_name>MEDI4736</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anzatax</other_name>
    <other_name>Asotax</other_name>
    <other_name>Bristaxol</other_name>
    <other_name>Praxel</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol Konzentrat</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (durvalumab, carboplatin, paclitaxel, questionnaire)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent and any locally-required authorization (e.g., Health
             Information Portability and Accountability Act [HIPAA] in the United States of America
             [USA], European Union [EU] Data Privacy Directive in the EU) obtained from the subject
             prior to performing any protocol-related procedures, including screening evaluations

          -  Histology showing high-grade epithelial non-mucinous ovarian, primary peritoneal, or
             fallopian tube cancer

          -  No prior treatment for primary advanced (stage III or IV) epithelial ovarian, primary
             peritoneal, or fallopian tube carcinoma such as irradiation, chemotherapy, hormonal
             therapy, immunotherapy, investigational therapy, surgery, and/or other concurrent
             agents or therapies

          -  A disposition to neoadjuvant chemotherapy with planned interval tumor reductive
             surgery after 3 complete cycles of treatment

          -  Planned chemotherapy with combination carboplatin and paclitaxel given intravenously

          -  Have measurable disease based on Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)
             version 1.1

               -  Measurable disease is defined at least one lesion that can be accurately measured
                  in at least one dimension (longest dimension to be recorded); each target lesion
                  must be &gt; 20 mm when measured by conventional techniques, including palpation,
                  plain x-ray, computed tomography (CT), and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or &gt;
                  10 mm when measured by spiral CT

               -  Patients with non-measurable but evaluable solid tumors may be deemed eligible
                  contingent upon principal investigator (PI) review; a non-measurable but
                  evaluable solid tumor is defined as either unidimensionally measurable lesions,
                  masses with margins not clearly defined, or lesions with maximal perpendicular
                  diameters &lt; 10 mm that can still be evaluated for the primary endpoint

          -  Peripheral neuropathy grade 0 or 1 by National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.03

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L (&gt; 1500 per mm^3)

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L (&gt; 100,000 per mm^3)

          -  Serum bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Aspartate Transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x institutional
             upper limit of normal (ULN) unless liver metastases are present, in which case it must
             be =&lt; 5 x ULN

          -  Serum creatinine clearance (CL) &gt; 40 mL/min by the Cockcroft-Gault formula or by
             24-hour urine collection for determination of creatinine

          -  Subjects must either be of non-reproductive potential (i.e., post-menopausal by
             history: &gt;= 60 years old and no menses for &gt;= 1 year without an alternative medical
             cause; OR history of hysterectomy, OR history of bilateral tubal ligation, OR history
             of bilateral oophorectomy) or must have a negative serum pregnancy test upon study
             entry

          -  Subject is willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study
             including undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and examinations including follow
             up

          -  Pre-treatment tumor tissue available for research purposes; this tissue can be
             collected from preoperative laparoscopy, other diagnostic biopsy, or a
             research-specific biopsy; this pre-treatment tumor must be amenable to repeat tissue
             sampling after induction therapy

          -  Signed informed consent on protocol LAB02-188

          -  For participation in the patient-reported outcomes and qualitative interviews,
             subjects must be fluent in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study (applies to both AstraZeneca
             staff and/or staff at the study site)

          -  Previous enrollment in the present study

          -  Prior treatment for ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary peritoneal cancer

          -  Histology showing mucinous or low grade epithelial carcinoma

          -  Participation in another clinical study with an investigational product during the
             last 4 weeks

          -  Any previous treatment with a programmed cell death protein 1 (PD1) or programmed cell
             death ligand 1 (PD-L1) inhibitor, including durvalumab

          -  History of another primary malignancy except for: malignancy treated with curative
             intent and with no known active disease &gt;= 5 years before the first dose of study drug
             and of low potential risk for recurrence; adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer
             or lentigo maligna without evidence of disease; or adequately treated carcinoma in
             situ without evidence of disease e.g., cervical cancer in situ

          -  Mean QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc) &gt;= 470 ms calculated from 3
             electrocardiograms (ECGs) using Bazett's correction

          -  Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 28 days before the first
             dose of durvalumab, with the exceptions of intranasal and inhaled corticosteroids or
             systemic corticosteroids at physiological doses, which are not to exceed 10 mg/day of
             prednisone, or an equivalent corticosteroid

          -  Any unresolved toxicity (&gt; CTCAE grade 2) from previous anti-cancer therapy; any prior
             grade &gt;= 3 immune-related adverse event (irAE) while receiving any previous
             immunotherapy agent, or any unresolved irAE &gt; grade 1

          -  Active or prior documented autoimmune disease within the past 2 years; NOTE: Subjects
             with vitiligo, Grave's disease, or psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment (within
             the past 2 years) are not excluded

          -  Active or prior documented inflammatory bowel disease (e.g., Crohn's disease,
             ulcerative colitis)

          -  History of primary immunodeficiency

          -  History of allogeneic organ transplant

          -  History of hypersensitivity to durvalumab or any excipient

          -  History of hypersensitivity to paclitaxel or carboplatin or their excipients

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, active peptic ulcer disease or gastritis, active
             bleeding diatheses including any subject known to have evidence of acute or chronic
             hepatitis B, hepatitis C or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements or
             compromise the ability of the subject to give written informed consent

          -  Known history of previous clinical diagnosis of tuberculosis

          -  History of leptomeningeal carcinomatosis

          -  Receipt of live attenuated vaccination within 30 days prior to study entry or within
             30 days of receiving durvalumab

          -  Female subjects who are pregnant/breast-feeding or who are of reproductive potential
             and not employing acceptable methods of birth control; acceptable methods of
             contraception include true abstinence in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle
             choice of the patient, tubal ligation, vasectomized partner, barrier methods (e.g.,
             cap plus spermicide, sponge plus spermicide, diaphragm plus spermicide, or male condom
             plus a spermicide), intrauterine device methods (e.g., Copper T or
             Levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system), or hormonal methods (e.g., any
             registered and marketed contraceptive agent that contains an estrogen and/or a
             progestational agent) and that is administered via the oral, subcutaneous,
             transdermal, intrauterine, or intramuscular route as an implant, hormone shot or
             injection, combined pill, minipill or patch; all methods of contraception should be
             used in combination with the use of a condom by their male sexual partner for
             intercourse

          -  Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with
             evaluation of study treatment or interpretation of patient safety or study results

          -  Symptomatic or uncontrolled brain metastases requiring concurrent treatment, inclusive
             of but not limited to surgery, radiation and/or corticosteroids

          -  Subjects with uncontrolled seizures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shannon N Westin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ovarian Epithelial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fallopian Tube Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peritoneal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Durvalumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulin G</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

