<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03263572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0792</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-01078</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-0792</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03263572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blinatumomab, Methotrexate, Cytarabine, and Ponatinib in Treating Patients With Philadelphia Chromosome-Positive, or BCR-ABL Positive, or Relapsed/Refractory, Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of the Combination of Blinatumomab and Ponatinib in Patients With Philadelphia Chromosome (Ph)-Positive and/or BCR-ABL Positive Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well blinatumomab, methotrexate, cytarabine, and ponatinib
      work in treating patients with Philadelphia chromosome (Ph)-positive, or BCR-ABL positive, or
      acute lymphoblastic leukemia that has come back or does not respond to treatment.
      Immunotherapy with monoclonal antibodies, such as blinatumomab, may induce changes in body's
      immune system and may interfere with the ability of tumor cells to grow and spread. Drugs
      used in chemotherapy, such as methotrexate and cytarabine, work in different ways to stop the
      growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by
      stopping them from spreading. Ponatinib may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some
      of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving blinatumomab, methotrexate, cytarabine, and
      ponatinib may work better in treating patients with acute lymphoblastic leukemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the complete molecular response rate in cohort 1 (newly diagnosed Philadelphia
      chromosome [Ph-positive] and/or BCR-ABL-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia [ALL]) and the
      overall response (complete remission [CR]+CR with incomplete blood count recovery [CRi]) rate
      in cohort 2 (relapsed/refractory disease).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate other clinical efficacy endpoints (complete cytogenetic response, complete
      molecular response [CMR], event-free survival [EFS] and overall survival [OS]) and safety of
      the regimen.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To characterize the role of ABL1 kinase domain mutations on treatment failure and relapse
      in patients with Ph+ ALL treated with blinatumomab plus ponatinib.

      II. To determine the impact of recurrent genomic alterations and ribonucleic acid (RNA)
      expression at diagnosis on relapse-free survival (RFS) in patients with Ph+ ALL treated with
      blinatumomab plus ponatinib.

      III. To investigate the impact of next-generation sequencing-based minimal residual disease
      assessment on relapse-free survival in patients with Ph+ ALL.

      IV. To determine the effect on immune cell subsets in patients with Ph+ ALL treated with
      blinatumomab plus ponatinib.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive blinatumomab intravenously (IV) nonstop on days 1-28 of cycles 1-5, and
      methotrexate and cytarabine intrathecally (by spinal tap) on days 1, 15, and 29 of cycles
      1-4. Patients also receive ponatinib orally (PO) daily. Cycles repeat every 6 weeks in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days and every 6 months
      thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 29, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete molecular response (CMR) rate in newly diagnosed Ph-positive and/or BCR-ABL-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 18 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR) in relapsed/refractory ALL</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is defined as the percentage of patients achieving complete remission (CR) or CR with incomplete blood count recovery (CRi).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From documented complete response until relapse or death, assessed up to 6 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day of treatment until any failure (resistant disease, relapse, or death), assessed up to 6 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>First day of treatment to time of death from any cause, assessed up to 6 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Accelerated Phase Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia, BCR-ABL1 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>BCR-ABL1 Fusion Protein Expression</condition>
  <condition>Blast Phase Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia, BCR-ABL1 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Philadelphia Chromosome Positive</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>t(9;22)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (blinatumomab, chemotherapy, ponatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive blinatumomab IV nonstop on days 1-28 of cycles 1-5, and methotrexate and cytarabine intrathecally (by spinal tap) on days 1, 15, and 29 of cycles 1-4. Patients also receive ponatinib PO daily. Cycles repeat every 6 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blinatumomab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (blinatumomab, chemotherapy, ponatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anti-CD19 x Anti-CD3 Bispecific Monoclonal Antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Anti-CD19/Anti-CD3 Recombinant Bispecific Monoclonal Antibody MT103</other_name>
    <other_name>Blincyto</other_name>
    <other_name>MEDI-538</other_name>
    <other_name>MT-103</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intrathecally via spinal tap</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (blinatumomab, chemotherapy, ponatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>.beta.-Cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>1-.beta.-D-Arabinofuranosyl-4-amino-2(1H)pyrimidinone</other_name>
    <other_name>1-.beta.-D-Arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>1-Beta-D-arabinofuranosyl-4-amino-2(1H)pyrimidinone</other_name>
    <other_name>1-Beta-D-arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>1.beta.-D-Arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>2(1H)-Pyrimidinone, 4-Amino-1-beta-D-arabinofuranosyl-</other_name>
    <other_name>2(1H)-Pyrimidinone, 4-amino-1.beta.-D-arabinofuranosyl-</other_name>
    <other_name>Alexan</other_name>
    <other_name>Ara-C</other_name>
    <other_name>ARA-cell</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabine</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabinosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytin</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytine</other_name>
    <other_name>Beta-cytosine Arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>CHX-3311</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytarabinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytarbel</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine Arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine-.beta.-arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine-beta-arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>Erpalfa</other_name>
    <other_name>Starasid</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarabine PFS</other_name>
    <other_name>U 19920</other_name>
    <other_name>U-19920</other_name>
    <other_name>Udicil</other_name>
    <other_name>WR-28453</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intrathecally via spinal tap</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (blinatumomab, chemotherapy, ponatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abitrexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Alpha-Methopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Amethopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Brimexate</other_name>
    <other_name>CL 14377</other_name>
    <other_name>CL-14377</other_name>
    <other_name>Emtexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Emthexat</other_name>
    <other_name>Emthexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Farmitrexat</other_name>
    <other_name>Fauldexato</other_name>
    <other_name>Folex</other_name>
    <other_name>Folex PFS</other_name>
    <other_name>Lantarel</other_name>
    <other_name>Ledertrexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Lumexon</other_name>
    <other_name>Maxtrex</other_name>
    <other_name>Medsatrexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Metex</other_name>
    <other_name>Methoblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Methotrexate LPF</other_name>
    <other_name>Methotrexate Methylaminopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Methotrexatum</other_name>
    <other_name>Metotrexato</other_name>
    <other_name>Metrotex</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate-AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>MTX</other_name>
    <other_name>Novatrex</other_name>
    <other_name>Rheumatrex</other_name>
    <other_name>Texate</other_name>
    <other_name>Tremetex</other_name>
    <other_name>Trexeron</other_name>
    <other_name>Trixilem</other_name>
    <other_name>WR-19039</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ponatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (blinatumomab, chemotherapy, ponatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AP-24534</other_name>
    <other_name>AP24534</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of one of the following:

               -  Patients &gt;= 60 years of age with previously untreated Ph-positive ALL (either
                  t(9;22) and/or BCR-ABL positive) (includes patients initiated on first course of
                  therapy before cytogenetics known) or with lymphoid accelerated or blast phase
                  chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML). These patients could have received one or two
                  courses of chemotherapy with or without other tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs)
                  and still eligible. Patients &lt; 60 years of age may be enrolled if they are
                  considered unfit for intensive chemotherapy: i) if they achieved CR, they are
                  assessable only for event-free and overall survival; OR ii) If they failed to
                  achieve CR, they are assessable for CR, event-free, and overall survival;

               -  Patients &gt;= 18 years of age with relapsed / refractory Ph-positive ALL or with
                  previously treated lymphoid accelerated or blast phase CML.

          -  Performance status =&lt; 2 (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group [ECOG] scale).

          -  Total serum bilirubin =&lt; 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN), unless due to Gilbert's
             syndrome (unless the increased values are judged to be leukemia disease related).

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 3 x ULN (unless the increased values are judged to
             be leukemia disease related).

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 3 x ULN (unless the increased values are judged to
             be leukemia disease related).

          -  Serum lipase and amylase =&lt; 1.5 x ULN.

          -  For females of childbearing potential, a negative urine pregnancy test must be
             documented.

          -  Female patients who: are postmenopausal for at least 1 year before the screening
             visit, OR are surgically sterile, OR If they are of childbearing potential, agree to
             practice 2 effective methods of contraception, at the same time, from the time of
             signing the informed consent through 4 months after the last dose of study drug, OR
             agree to completely abstain from heterosexual intercourse.

          -  Male patients, even if surgically sterilized (i.e., status post-vasectomy), who: agree
             to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study treatment period
             and through 4 months after the last dose of study drug, OR agree to completely abstain
             from heterosexual intercourse.

          -  Adequate cardiac function as assessed clinically by history and physical examination.

          -  Signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active serious infection not controlled by oral or intravenous antibiotics.

          -  History of acute pancreatitis within 1 year of study or history of chronic
             pancreatitis.

          -  History of alcohol abuse.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertriglyceridemia (triglycerides &gt; 450 mg/dL).

          -  Active secondary malignancy other than skin cancer (e.g., basal cell carcinoma or
             squamous cell carcinoma) that in the investigator's opinion will shorten survival to
             less than 1 year.

          -  Active grade III-V cardiac failure as defined by the New York Heart Association
             criteria.

          -  Uncontrolled, or active cardiovascular disease, specifically including, but not
             restricted to: myocardial infarction (MI), stroke, or revascularization within 3
             months; unstable angina or transient ischemic attack; congestive heart failure prior
             to enrollment, or left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) less than lower limit of
             normal per local institutional standards prior to enrollment; diagnosed or suspected
             congenital long QT syndrome; clinically significant atrial or ventricular arrhythmias
             (such as atrial fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, or
             Torsades de pointes) as determined by the treating physician; prolonged corrected QT
             (QTc) interval on pre-entry electrocardiogram (&gt; 470 msec) unless corrected after
             electrolyte replacement or approved by cardiologist. Significant venous or arterial
             thromboembolism including deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism. Patients with
             a history of treated prior superficial or catheter associated will not be considered
             as significant embolism and after discussion with principal investigator (PI) will not
             be excluded from eligibility; uncontrolled hypertension (diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90
             mmHg; systolic &gt; 140 mmHg). Patients with hypertension should be under treatment on
             study entry to effect blood pressure control.

          -  Taking any medications or herbal supplements that are known to be strong inhibitors of
             CYP3A4 within at least 14 days or 5 half-lives before the first dose of ponatinib in
             patients with newly diagnosed only.

          -  History or presence of clinically relevant central nervous system (CNS) pathology such
             as epilepsy, childhood or adult seizure, paresis, aphasia, stroke, severe brain
             injuries, dementia, Parkinson's disease, cerebellar disease, organic brain syndrome,
             or psychosis. Patients with active CNS leukemia will be excluded.

          -  Current autoimmune disease or history of autoimmune disease with potential CNS
             involvement.

          -  Treatment with any investigational antileukemic agents or chemotherapy agents in the
             last 7 days before study entry, unless full recovery from side effects has occurred or
             patient has rapidly progressive disease judged to be life-threatening by the
             investigator.

          -  Pregnant and lactating women will not be eligible; women of childbearing potential
             should have a negative urine pregnancy test prior to entering on the study and be
             willing to practice methods of contraception. Women do not have childbearing potential
             if they have had a hysterectomy or are postmenopausal without menses for 12 months. In
             addition, men enrolled on this study should understand the risks to any sexual partner
             of childbearing potential and should practice an effective method of birth control.

          -  History of significant bleeding disorder unrelated to cancer, including: diagnosed
             congenital bleeding disorders (e.g., von Willebrand's disease); diagnosed acquired
             bleeding disorder within one year (e.g., acquired anti-factor VIII antibodies).

          -  Patients with documented significant pleural or pericardial effusions unless they are
             thought to be secondary to their leukemia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elias Jabbour</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elias Jabbour, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-4764</phone>
    <email>ejabbour@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elias Jabbour</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-4764</phone>
      <email>ejabbour@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elias Jabbour</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Accelerated Phase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blast Crisis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Philadelphia Chromosome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antineoplastic Agents, Immunological</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blinatumomab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ponatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muromonab-CD3</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Bispecific</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

