<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01550731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 11-110</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01550731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preparing Older Veterans With Serious and Chronic Illness for Decision Making</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREPARE</acronym>
  <official_title>Preparing Older Veterans With Serious and Chronic Illness for Decision Making</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Millions of diverse Veterans live with severe and chronic illness for which they will face
      complex, ongoing decisions. Although the VHA has been at the forefront of patient-centered
      chronic care, interventions to prepare Veterans for complex decision-making over the course
      of chronic illness are lacking. This proposal addresses this gap by testing the efficacy of a
      novel preparation guide designed to prepare Veterans to communicate with their surrogates and
      to work with clinicians to make complex, ongoing decisions. The multi-media guide teaches
      communication and preparation skill behaviors (e.g., how to choose a surrogate and ask
      clinicians questions) in a culturally appropriate, easy-to-use format (targeted to a 5th
      grade reading level). This study aims to provide an impetus for changing the paradigm of
      advance care planning policies within the VA by moving beyond documentation of end-of-life
      wishes to the activation of Veterans to participate in ongoing communication of their values
      and goals - a process that is essential to fully realize patient-centered care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      4.5 million Veterans are over age 65 and an increasing number are living with chronic and
      serious illness. Most older Veterans and their surrogate decision makers will eventually face
      complex, ongoing decisions over the course of chronic illness. These decisions are difficult,
      especially for the 50% of older Veterans with limited health literacy. The old paradigm of
      advance care planning has focused on making decisions about life- prolonging procedures
      (e.g., resuscitation) by completing advance directives. Yet, this old paradigm is
      problematic. The forms are difficult to understand and often culturally insensitive. They
      also fail to prepare patients with concrete skills, such as how to identify one's values and
      communicate with surrogates and clinicians. The investigators have published a new paradigm
      of advance care planning that focuses instead on preparing patients to communicate with their
      surrogates and to actively participate with clinicians in making the best possible
      in-the-moment decisions. The new paradigm seeks to ensure that complex, ongoing decisions are
      based on a comprehensive set of considerations including the current clinical context,
      evolving goals, and patients' and surrogates' needs. To do this effectively, Veterans need to
      prepare. However, an easy-to-use, culturally-appropriate preparation guide does not exist.
      The investigators have created an easy-to-understand (5th grade reading level) preparation
      guide based on the investigators' new paradigm called PREParation, Activation, Reflection,
      and Engagement in advance care planning or PREPARE. PREPARE is designed to teach Veterans
      preparation skills including how to choose a surrogate and discuss surrogate decision making,
      clarify personal values for specific health states, and ask clinicians questions to make
      informed choices. The aims of this study are: (1) to conduct a randomized control trial to
      determine the efficacy of PREPARE to engage older Veterans with chronic illness in
      preparation skill behaviors (i.e., did they choose a surrogate, clarify their values, ask
      clinicians questions); (2) to determine the efficacy of PREPARE to activate Veterans and
      clinicians within clinical encounters (i.e., did Veterans ask clinicians questions or discuss
      preparation topics and did clinicians respond) and to improve satisfaction with decision
      making; and (3) to obtain input from Veterans, surrogates, and clinicians about
      implementation of PREPARE within the VA. To achieve Aim 1, 205 Veterans will be randomly
      assigned to the intervention (PREPARE materials plus an advance directive) and 205 will be
      assigned to the control group (advance directive only). Veterans in the PREPARE arm will view
      the easy-to-understand, multi-media PREPARE website during the study interview and then take
      home PREPARE materials in photo booklet and pamphlet format to ensure universal access to the
      information. The primary outcome is Veteran-reported engagement in preparation skill
      behaviors at 3 and 6 months, which will be measured with standard cognitive behavioral
      measures. For Aim 2, activation within the clinical encounters will be measured with
      validated quantitative analysis techniques of audio-recordings. Satisfaction with decision
      making will be measured with validated, self-reported measures. For Aim 3, the investigators
      will ask Veterans randomized to the PREPARE arm and their surrogates and clinicians how best
      to implement PREPARE within the clinical setting. The investigators will use standard
      parametric or non-parametric statistical tests to assess group differences, will control for
      demographic or other variables that differ between randomization groups, and adjust for
      potential clustering by clinician. For Aims 1 and 2 the investigators will assess differences
      in engagement and satisfaction by race/ethnicity, literacy, and gender. The research team has
      extensive experience testing literacy-appropriate, multi-media health education materials in
      randomized trials. The study team is poised to test the efficacy of PREPARE, and findings
      from this study will pave the way for multi-site effectiveness testing and widespread VA
      dissemination of PREPARE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>New Advance Care Planning Documentation in the Medical Record at 9 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months after study enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is documentation of advance care planning wishes in the medical record. ACP documentation for the purposes of this study includes the easy-to-read advance directive or other valid advance directives or living wills, a durable power of attorney for healthcare document (DPOAHC), a physicians orders for life sustaining treatment (POLST) form, or other documentation of patients wishes for medical care (ie, documentation of oral directives by a physician, or code status, such as full code or do not resuscitate or do not intubate orders or notes by a physician).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported Engagement in Advance Care Planning (ACP) Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcome was chosen to measure the full process of Advance Care Planning (ACP) using validated questionnaires, such as the patient-reported ACP Engagement Survey. This questionnaire includes Behavior Change Process measures. Behavior Change Process measures include knowledge, contemplation, self-efficacy, and readiness for several ACP actions. The Process measures are assessed on an average 5-point Likert scale with a low of 1 and a high of 5, with high scores indicating more ACP engagement. The investigators used mixed effects models to create an overall adjusted score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">414</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PREPARE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention group will review the PREPARE advance care planning website and PREPARE materials plus receive an advance directive. The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PREPARE website</intervention_name>
    <description>Advance care planning website and materials plus an advance directive.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PREPARE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Advance directive</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans

          -  60 years of age

          -  who have been seen in the General Medicine, Geriatrics, and Women's Clinics twice in
             the past year

          -  and have 2 or more serious or chronic medical conditions as determined by ICD-9 codes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Veterans will be excluded if they are:

               -  deaf

               -  blind

               -  demented
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Sudore, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>San Francisco VA Medical Center, San Francisco, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Francisco VA Medical Center, San Francisco, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McMahan RD, Knight SJ, Fried TR, Sudore RL. Advance care planning beyond advance directives: perspectives from patients and surrogates. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2013 Sep;46(3):355-65. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2012.09.006. Epub 2012 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23200188</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Allison TA, Sudore RL. Disregard of patients' preferences is a medical error: comment on &quot;Failure to engage hospitalized elderly patients and their families in advance care planning&quot;. JAMA Intern Med. 2013 May 13;173(9):787. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.203.</citation>
    <PMID>23545699</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sudore RL, Knight SJ, McMahan RD, Feuz M, Farrell D, Miao Y, Barnes DE. A novel website to prepare diverse older adults for decision making and advance care planning: a pilot study. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2014 Apr;47(4):674-86. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2013.05.023. Epub 2013 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23972574</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sudore RL, Stewart AL, Knight SJ, McMahan RD, Feuz M, Miao Y, Barnes DE. Development and validation of a questionnaire to detect behavior change in multiple advance care planning behaviors. PLoS One. 2013 Sep 5;8(9):e72465. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0072465. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24039772</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Su CT, McMahan RD, Williams BA, Sharma RK, Sudore RL. Family matters: effects of birth order, culture, and family dynamics on surrogate decision-making. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2014 Jan;62(1):175-82. doi: 10.1111/jgs.12610. Epub 2014 Jan 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24383459</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sudore R, Le GM, McMahan R, Feuz M, Katen M, Barnes DE. The advance care planning PREPARE study among older Veterans with serious and chronic illness: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial. Trials. 2015 Dec 12;16:570. doi: 10.1186/s13063-015-1055-9. Erratum in: Trials. 2016;17:42. McMahon, Ryan [Corrected to McMahan, Ryan].</citation>
    <PMID>26654250</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sudore RL, Boscardin J, Feuz MA, McMahan RD, Katen MT, Barnes DE. Effect of the PREPARE Website vs an Easy-to-Read Advance Directive on Advance Care Planning Documentation and Engagement Among Veterans: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2017 Aug 1;177(8):1102-1109. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2017.1607.</citation>
    <PMID>28520838</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 12, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>October 17, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>advance care planning</keyword>
  <keyword>health communication</keyword>
  <keyword>aging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Veterans were enrolled from a women's, geriatrics, and several general medicine clinics at the San Francisco VA from April 2013 through July 2016. Veterans had to be 60 years or older, have had at least 2 chronic medical conditions, and had 2 or more visits with a primary care clinician, plus 2 VA clinic, ER, or hospital visits in the past year.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>PREPARE</title>
          <description>The intervention group will review the PREPARE advance care planning website and PREPARE materials plus receive an advance directive. The control group will only receive an advance directive.
PREPARE website: Advance care planning website and materials plus an advance directive.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>CONTROL</title>
          <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.
Advance directive: The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="205"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="209"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="205"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="209"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>PREPARE</title>
          <description>The intervention group will review the PREPARE advance care planning website and PREPARE materials plus receive an advance directive. The control group will only receive an advance directive.
PREPARE website: Advance care planning website and materials plus an advance directive.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>CONTROL</title>
          <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.
Advance directive: The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="205"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="209"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="414"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="46"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="50"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="96"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="159"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="159"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="318"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="70.7" spread="7.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="71.5" spread="7.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="71.1" spread="7.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="38"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="186"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="190"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="376"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="33"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="189"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="192"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="381"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="25"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="46"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="42"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="88"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="129"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="139"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="268"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="26"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="205"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="209"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="414"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>New Advance Care Planning Documentation in the Medical Record at 9 Months</title>
        <description>The primary outcome is documentation of advance care planning wishes in the medical record. ACP documentation for the purposes of this study includes the easy-to-read advance directive or other valid advance directives or living wills, a durable power of attorney for healthcare document (DPOAHC), a physicians orders for life sustaining treatment (POLST) form, or other documentation of patients wishes for medical care (ie, documentation of oral directives by a physician, or code status, such as full code or do not resuscitate or do not intubate orders or notes by a physician).</description>
        <time_frame>9 months after study enrollment</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>PREPARE</title>
            <description>The intervention group will review the PREPARE advance care planning website and PREPARE materials plus receive an advance directive. The control group will only receive an advance directive.
PREPARE website: Advance care planning website and materials plus an advance directive.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>CONTROL</title>
            <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.
Advance directive: The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>New Advance Care Planning Documentation in the Medical Record at 9 Months</title>
          <description>The primary outcome is documentation of advance care planning wishes in the medical record. ACP documentation for the purposes of this study includes the easy-to-read advance directive or other valid advance directives or living wills, a durable power of attorney for healthcare document (DPOAHC), a physicians orders for life sustaining treatment (POLST) form, or other documentation of patients wishes for medical care (ie, documentation of oral directives by a physician, or code status, such as full code or do not resuscitate or do not intubate orders or notes by a physician).</description>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="205"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="209"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="35"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="25"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Self-reported Engagement in Advance Care Planning (ACP) Behaviors</title>
        <description>Secondary outcome was chosen to measure the full process of Advance Care Planning (ACP) using validated questionnaires, such as the patient-reported ACP Engagement Survey. This questionnaire includes Behavior Change Process measures. Behavior Change Process measures include knowledge, contemplation, self-efficacy, and readiness for several ACP actions. The Process measures are assessed on an average 5-point Likert scale with a low of 1 and a high of 5, with high scores indicating more ACP engagement. The investigators used mixed effects models to create an overall adjusted score.</description>
        <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>PREPARE</title>
            <description>The intervention group will review the PREPARE advance care planning website and PREPARE materials plus receive an advance directive. The control group will only receive an advance directive.
PREPARE website: Advance care planning website and materials plus an advance directive.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>CONTROL</title>
            <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.
Advance directive: The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Self-reported Engagement in Advance Care Planning (ACP) Behaviors</title>
          <description>Secondary outcome was chosen to measure the full process of Advance Care Planning (ACP) using validated questionnaires, such as the patient-reported ACP Engagement Survey. This questionnaire includes Behavior Change Process measures. Behavior Change Process measures include knowledge, contemplation, self-efficacy, and readiness for several ACP actions. The Process measures are assessed on an average 5-point Likert scale with a low of 1 and a high of 5, with high scores indicating more ACP engagement. The investigators used mixed effects models to create an overall adjusted score.</description>
          <units>score on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="205"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="209"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.78" spread="3.67"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3.64" spread="3.53"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse event data were collected for the length of the study for each participant (6 months).</time_frame>
      <desc>For this behavioral trial, adverse events were defined as any unexpected negative psychological effects caused by the patient education materials.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>PREPARE</title>
          <description>The intervention group will review the PREPARE advance care planning website and PREPARE materials plus receive an advance directive. The control group will only receive an advance directive.
PREPARE website: Advance care planning website and materials plus an advance directive.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>CONTROL</title>
          <description>The control group will only receive an advance directive.
Advance directive: The control group will only receive an advance directive.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="205"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="209"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="205"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="209"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="205"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="209"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Older veterans were recruited from clinics at the SFVA, potentially limiting generalizability. Materials were viewed in study offices with computer access, potentially limiting generalizability. Study interviews and reminder calls may be activating.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Rebecca Sudore</name_or_title>
      <organization>Veterans Administration</organization>
      <phone>(415) 221-4810 ext 23475</phone>
      <email>Rebecca.Sudore@va.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

