<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04057534</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Chess_SUD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04057534</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurobiological Mechanisms of Chess as an Add-On Treatment Against SUD</brief_title>
  <acronym>Chess_SUD</acronym>
  <official_title>Investigating Neurobiological Mechanisms of Chess as an Add-On Treatment Against Substance Use Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Central Institute of Mental Health, Mannheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Central Institute of Mental Health, Mannheim</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Neurobiological and neuropsychological approaches to investigate the potential mechanism of
      action of chess as an add-on therapy (chess based - cognitive remediation treatment, CB-CRT)
      to reduce cognitive deficits in individuals with alcohol use disorder (AUD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to investigate the potential mechanism of action of chess as a &quot;chess based -
      cognitive remediation treatment, CB-CRT&quot; to reduce cognitive deficits in individuals with
      substance use disorder (SUD) seeking treatment using neurobiological and neuropsychological
      approaches. Furthermore, it will be assessed whether this chess intervention has a
      generalized positive effect on short-term abstinence. Interestingly, the functional domains
      and associated underlying neuronal networks observed to be affected in individuals with SUD
      overlap significantly with those that could be strengthened by chess-based cognitive training
      or formal chess. Specifically, strengthening of cortical control regions (dorsolateral
      prefrontal cortex, DLPFC) and brain areas relevant for decision-making (orbitofrontal cortex,
      OFC) could prevent future relapse. Therefore, chess as an add-on therapy to complement other
      standard treatments of SUD could lead to improved therapeutic outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in neural cue-reactivity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 time points: before and after 6 weeks chess-based cognitive training</time_frame>
    <description>fMRI cue-reactivity task (Vollstädt-Klein et al. 2010)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in sequential reinforcement-based neural mechanisms</measure>
    <time_frame>2 time points: before and after 6 weeks chess-based cognitive training</time_frame>
    <description>fMRI sequential reinforcement-based task (Huys et al. 2012)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in neural correlates of inhibition</measure>
    <time_frame>2 time points: before and after 6 weeks chess-based cognitive training</time_frame>
    <description>fMRI stop-signal task (Whelan et al. 2012)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>substance use (alcohol consumption and tabacco use)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months follow-up after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>self-report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in neural working memory processes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 time points: before and after 6 weeks chess-based cognitive training</time_frame>
    <description>fMRI spatial working memory task (Vollstädt-Klein et al. 2010)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in working memory capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>working memory capacity measured by letter-number sequencing task of the [Wechsler Memory Scale (Kent 2013)]; raw values will be transformed to IQ-like scales (mean 100, SD 15); the higher the value, the higher the working memory capacity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in planning ability</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>One Touch Stockings of Cambridge task from the Cambridge Automated Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (Robbins et al. 1994)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive flexibility</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Internal-External Set Shifting task from the Cambridge Automated Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (Robbins et al. 1994)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in impulsivity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>impulsivity measured with BIS scale [Barratt impulsiveness scale (Patton et al. 1995)];range 15-60; total score will be used; high values represent high impulsivity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in decision-making</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>[Iowa Gambling Task (Bechara et al. 1994)]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mental flexibility</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>[Reversal learning task (Vanes et al. 2014)]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in attentional capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 time points: before and after 6 weeks SCP plus after 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>[d2 Test of Attention (Brickenkamp 2002)].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in functional connectivity within the salience network (SN) and executive control network (ECN)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 time points: before and after 6 weeks therapy and chess-based cognitive training</time_frame>
    <description>[measured with fMRI]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance Use Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CB-CRT AUD group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>experimental group AUD: patients receive standard clinical therapy and an add-on chess based - cognitive remediation treatment (CB-CRT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group AUD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>control group: patients with AUD receive standard clinical therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CB-CRT TUD group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>experimental group TUD: patients receive standard smoking cessation therapy and an add-on CB-CRT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group TUD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>control group: patients with TUD receive standard smoking cessation therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard therapy for AUD plus Chess-based cognitive treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral: standard AUD Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) in Clinical setting.
Patients who voluntarily submit to enter a qualified detoxification treatment program will be examined, either in-patient, out-patient, or in a day-clinic setting at the Department of Addictive Behaviour and Addiction Medicine. They receive a six-week standard therapy. Additional, the experimental group receives chess based cognitive remediation treatment (CB-CRT) for 1,5 hours three times a week. The tasks of the treatment were created by our cooperation partner, the psychologist Juan Antonio Montero. He is currently successfully applying this battery as an add-on therapy before. The training battery is designed to strengthen cognitive functioning in specific domains such as short-term memory, focal attention, selective attention, pattern recognition, visuospatial abilities and also inhibition.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CB-CRT AUD group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard therapy for AUD</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral: standard AUD Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) in Clinical setting. Patients who voluntarily submit to enter a qualified detoxification treatment program will be examined, either in-patient, out-patient, or in a day-clinic setting at the Department of Addictive Behaviour and Addiction Medicine. They receive a six-week standard therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group AUD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard smoking cessation therapy for TUD plus Chess-based cognitive treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral: standard smoking cessation therapy for TUD in group therapy setting.
Patients who voluntarily submit to enter a qualified smokind cessation program will be examined,out-patient setting at the Department of Addictive Behaviour and Addiction Medicine. They receive a six-week standard therapy (one 1,5 hours group therapy per week). Additional, the experimental group receives chess based cognitive remediation treatment (CB-CRT) for 1,5 hours three times a week. The tasks of the treatment were created by our cooperation partner, the psychologist Juan Antonio Montero. He is currently successfully applying this battery as an add-on therapy before. The training battery is designed to strengthen cognitive functioning in specific domains such as short-term memory, focal attention, selective attention, pattern recognition, visuospatial abilities and also inhibition.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CB-CRT TUD group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard therapy for TUD</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral: standard smoking cessation therapy for TUD in group therapy setting.
Patients who voluntarily submit to enter a qualified smokind cessation program will be examined,out-patient setting at the Department of Addictive Behaviour and Addiction Medicine. They receive a six-week standard therapy (one 1,5 hours group therapy per week). Additional, the experimental group receives chess based cognitive remediation treatment (CB-CRT) for 1,5 hours three times a week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group TUD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  severe alcohol (AUD) or tabacco use disorder (SUD) according to DSM-5

          -  abstinence from alcohol for at least 72 hours

          -  sufficient ability to communicate with investigators and answer questions in both
             written and verbal format

          -  ability to provide fully informed consent and to use self-rating scales

          -  main diagnosis AUD: inpatient or outpatient treatment in our clinic

          -  main diagnosis TUD: participation in 6 weeks smoking cessation treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  severe internal, neurological, and/or psychiatric comorbidities; other Axis I mental
             disorders other than TUD according to ICD-10 and DSM 5 (except for other substance use
             disorders - if AUD or TUD is still the main diagnosis -, ADHD, mild or normal
             depression, i.e. F32.0, remitted depression, adjustment disorder, generalized anxiety
             disorder, phobias, panic disorder or other mild or moderate personality disorders) in
             the last 12 months

          -  severe SUD withdrawal effects

          -  alcohol intoxication (&gt;0‰)

          -  history of brain injury

          -  common exclusion criteria for MRI (e.g. metal, claustrophobia, pregnancy)

          -  positive drug screening before MRI scan (THC, opioids, benzodiazepines, barbiturates,
             cocaine, amphetamines)

          -  psychotropic medication within the last 14 days, except sleep medication and
             antidepressants; clomethiazole or benzodiazepines for treating withdrawal is allowed,
             but has to be completed since at least 3 days

          -  suicidality or endangerment of others

          -  positive Covid-19 screening
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sabine Vollstädt-Klein, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Central Institute of Mental Health, Mannheim</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sabine Vollstädt-Klein, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+49-621/1703</phone>
    <phone_ext>3912</phone_ext>
    <email>s.vollstädt-klein@zi-mannheim.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gereon Lex, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+49-621/1703</phone>
    <phone_ext>3927</phone_ext>
    <email>gereon.lex@zi-mannheim.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinik für Abhängiges Verhalten, Zentralinstitut für Seelische Gesundheit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sabine Vollstädt-Klein</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adinoff B. Neurobiologic processes in drug reward and addiction. Harv Rev Psychiatry. 2004 Nov-Dec;12(6):305-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15764467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fauth-Bühler M, de Rover M, Rubia K, Garavan H, Abbott S, Clark L, Vollstädt-Klein S, Mann K, Schumann G, Robbins TW. Brain networks subserving fixed versus performance-adjusted delay stop trials in a stop signal task. Behav Brain Res. 2012 Nov 1;235(1):89-97. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2012.07.023. Epub 2012 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22820235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Amidzic O, Riehle HJ, Fehr T, Wienbruch C, Elbert T. Pattern of focal gamma-bursts in chess players. Nature. 2001 Aug 9;412(6847):603.</citation>
    <PMID>11493907</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Atherton M, Zhuang J, Bart WM, Hu X, He S. A functional MRI study of high-level cognition. I. The game of chess. Brain Res Cogn Brain Res. 2003 Mar;16(1):26-31.</citation>
    <PMID>12589885</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bates ME, Buckman JF, Nguyen TT. A role for cognitive rehabilitation in increasing the effectiveness of treatment for alcohol use disorders. Neuropsychol Rev. 2013 Mar;23(1):27-47. doi: 10.1007/s11065-013-9228-3. Epub 2013 Feb 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23412885</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Blasco-Fontecilla H, Gonzalez-Perez M, Garcia-Lopez R, Poza-Cano B, Perez-Moreno MR, de Leon-Martinez V, Otero-Perez J. Efficacy of chess training for the treatment of ADHD: A prospective, open label study. Rev Psiquiatr Salud Ment. 2016 Jan-Mar;9(1):13-21. doi: 10.1016/j.rpsm.2015.02.003. Epub 2015 Apr 22. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>25911280</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Demily C, Cavézian C, Desmurget M, Berquand-Merle M, Chambon V, Franck N. The game of chess enhances cognitive abilities in schizophrenia. Schizophr Res. 2009 Jan;107(1):112-3. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2008.09.024. Epub 2008 Nov 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18995990</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fattahi F, Geshani A, Jafari Z, Jalaie S, Salman Mahini M. Auditory memory function in expert chess players. Med J Islam Repub Iran. 2015 Oct 6;29:275. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26793666</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gonçalves PD, Ometto M, Bechara A, Malbergier A, Amaral R, Nicastri S, Martins PA, Beraldo L, dos Santos B, Fuentes D, Andrade AG, Busatto GF, Cunha PJ. Motivational interviewing combined with chess accelerates improvement in executive functions in cocaine dependent patients: a one-month prospective study. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2014 Aug 1;141:79-84. doi: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2014.05.006. Epub 2014 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24913200</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Onofrj M, Curatola L, Valentini G, Antonelli M, Thomas A, Fulgente T. Non-dominant dorsal-prefrontal activation during chess problem solution evidenced by single photon emission computerized tomography (SPECT). Neurosci Lett. 1995 Oct 6;198(3):169-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8552313</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vollstädt-Klein S, Wichert S, Rabinstein J, Bühler M, Klein O, Ende G, Hermann D, Mann K. Initial, habitual and compulsive alcohol use is characterized by a shift of cue processing from ventral to dorsal striatum. Addiction. 2010 Oct;105(10):1741-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1360-0443.2010.03022.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20670348</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lally N, Huys QJM, Eshel N, Faulkner P, Dayan P, Roiser JP. The Neural Basis of Aversive Pavlovian Guidance during Planning. J Neurosci. 2017 Oct 18;37(42):10215-10229. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0085-17.2017. Epub 2017 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28924006</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alcohol Dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <keyword>Craving</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Change</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive remediation</keyword>
  <keyword>Chess based cognitive training</keyword>
  <keyword>Working Memory</keyword>
  <keyword>Decision Making</keyword>
  <keyword>Executive Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Chess</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine use disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco use disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

