<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04052087</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ceadac</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04052087</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cross-cultural Adaptation to the Spanish Population and Validation of the BESTest and Mini-BESTest</brief_title>
  <acronym>BESTest</acronym>
  <official_title>Cross-cultural Adaptation to the Spanish Population and Validation of the Test of Systems of Evaluation of Balance (BESTest) and Its Version Reduced in Persons With Acquired Brain Injury in Subacute and Chronic Phase</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro de Referencia Estatal de Atención Al Daño Cerebral</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Alcala</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro de Referencia Estatal de Atención Al Daño Cerebral</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Due to brain damage acquired (BDA), is often difficulty in gait and balance alterations, as
      problems that patients designated as the most disabling. It is essential to an effective
      assessment of the balance.

      Objective: The purpose of the present project adapt and verify the validity of the scale
      MiniBESTest, version of the BESTest, in patients with BDA in subacute and chronic stage,
      since that is postulated as a brief tool and covering the peculiarities of the specific
      alterations of the patient after suffering brain damage.

      Methodology: Between September 2019 and December 2020 will be transcultural adaptation to the
      BDA and validation of psychometric scale Mini-BESTest in three phases. 60 subjects who
      receive treatment in the center of attention State reference to brain damage (CEADAC),
      together with the comunidad de Madrid private neurological rehabilitation centers will be
      recruited.

      Results: validity and reliability parameters shall be calculated by means of descriptive
      statistics for each item of the scales and the set of scale score. You will also analyze the
      internal consistency using Cronbach's alpha, the interclass correlation coefficient will be
      used to determine the reliability, and the items will be scanned with the Pearson
      coefficient: &gt; 0.20, among other parameters.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Marta Fernández Hontoria, physiotherapist at the State Reference Center of Attention to Brain
      Injury (CEADAC), will develop, together with her team formed by Cristina Lirio Romero and
      María Torres Lacomba of the Department of Physiotherapy at the University of Alcalá, a
      cross-cultural adaptation to the Spanish population with Adquired Brain Injury (ABI) and
      psychometric validation of the Mini-BESTest scale. Previously, the author of the scale has
      been asked for consent. The study will take place at the CEADAC. After receiving the approval
      of the Ethics and Clinical Research Committee of the University of Alcalá (Madrid), it is
      proposed to implement the study between September 2019 and May 2020. A minimum of 100 adults,
      aged between 18 and 65, will be recruited subacute or chronic state after suffering brain
      damage. The sample size conforms to COSMIN recommendations.

      After verifying that there are no parallel studies on the subject in progress, the possible
      participants will be informed of the development of the investigation (ANNEX 1), who must
      sign the informed consent (ANNEX 2) before being recruited into the study. In addition, a
      coding sheet (ANNEX 3) of the participants will be filled in so that from now on the data
      related to the proper name does not appear but with a number that ensures the protection of
      their data.

      The participants will be all users of CEADAC and the selection criteria to enter to
      participate in the study will be: adults who had suffered a ABI at least 2 months ago, that
      their disability before suffering it was less than or equal to three on the scale modified by
      Rankin, who have an absence of cognitive impairment according to the Minimental State
      Examination scale, that is, a score in it greater than 24, without previous diseases that
      alter the balance, that were clinically stable and without fever, with the ability to walk
      with help technical or without it, and that they gave their informed consent.

      On the other hand, those people with medical contraindications for physical tests (acute
      musculoskeletal or peripheral nervous system disorders), who did not understand the
      instructions, severe aphasias or with subjects with acute processes of any added pathology
      will be excluded.

      The study was developed in 3 phases:

      Phase 1: Transcultural adaptation process. Phase 2: Pre-Test: collected , as well as the ease
      of interpretation of the results.

      Phase 3: Psychometric validation process.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Test-retest Reliability</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>the overall consistency measures the homogeneity of the scale and the interdependence of the items, indicating the relationship between them.
To determine test-retest test reliability, the intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC) will be used. Derived from the test-retest reliability study, the measurement error will be calculated, using the formula ED (estandar deviation) x √1-ICC.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>To analyze the convergent validity, it will be applied on the first day of the week and before receiving treatment. Along with the scales to be evaluated, other balance scales will be administered.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity to change</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ability of the instrument to detect real changes in the health of the subjects, whether positive or negative.
The differences in the scores between the periods of the beginning of any proposed treatment and at the end of this will be evaluated by the effect size and the standardized response to the change.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Damage</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Spanish population with Brain Damage Acquired.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The participants will be all Ceadac's users.

          -  Adults who had suffered a BDA, at least 2 months before.

          -  The disability before suffering BDA was less than or equal to three on the scale
             modified Rankin.

          -  Lack of cognitive impairment scale Minimental State Examination, with a score is &gt; 24.

          -  No previous diseases that alter the balance.

          -  Clinically stable and without fever-

          -  Ability to walk with technical support or without it.

          -  Signing an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical contraindications to perform physical tests (acute or peripheral nervous
             system musculoskeletal disorders).

          -  Not understand the instructions.

          -  Subjects with severe aphasia.

          -  Subjects with acute processes of any added pathology.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>54 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cristina Lirio Romero, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Castilla-La Mancha</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marta Fernandez Hontoria, PT</last_name>
    <phone>+34 657552465</phone>
    <email>martafh1985@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ceadac</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28034</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marta Fernández Hontoria, PT</last_name>
      <phone>+34 657552465</phone>
      <email>martafh1975@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marta Fernandez Hontoria, PT</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cristina Lirio Romero, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centro de Referencia Estatal de Atención Al Daño Cerebral</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>MARTA FERNANDEZ HONTORIA</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physical Therapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brain Damage Acquired</keyword>
  <keyword>BDA in subacute and chronic stage</keyword>
  <keyword>BESTest</keyword>
  <keyword>Mini-BESTest</keyword>
  <keyword>Balance</keyword>
  <keyword>Postural control</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Cross-cultural adaptation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

