<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04054128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>479/01/19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04054128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bicarbonate vs Heparin Catheter Lock in Chronic Hemodialysis Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>BICATH</acronym>
  <official_title>Bicarbonate vs Heparin Catheter Lock in Chronic Hemodialysis Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital General “Dr. Miguel Silva” de Morelia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NAUSLIFE HEMODIALYSIS CLINICS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital General “Dr. Miguel Silva” de Morelia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy of catheter lock with bicarbonate vs
      heparin in chronic hemodialysis patients. Two groups will be created, sodium bicarbonate lock
      group (experimental group) and heparin lock group (control group). Catheter pressures, flow,
      patency and infection outcomes will be compare between groups at different time points (30,
      60 and 90 days).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective, randomized, clinical, open-label trial at Hospital General &quot;Dr. Miguel Silva&quot;
      de Morelia, Mexico.

      The study period will be between august 16, 2019 to November 16, 2019. The aim of this study
      is to evaluate the efficacy of catheter lock with bicarbonate vs heparin in chronic
      hemodialysis patients. Primary outcome will be catheter function. Secondary outcomes will be
      Infectious complications, thrombotic complications, and frequency of adverse effects between
      groups.

      All patients provided written informed consent before enrollment. The trial protocol was
      approved by Hospital General &quot;Dr. Miguel Silva&quot; Internal Review Board, register number
      17-CI-16053153, and Research &amp; Ethics committee, with register number 16-CEI-004-20161212,
      Study registry # 479/01/9.

      Patients between 18-65 years old, incident or prevalent chronic hemodialysis, with 1 month of
      clinical stability and with temporal catheter as vascular access for hemodialysis are
      eligible. A total of 60 patients will be included in the study. All patients will be randomly
      assigned into one of two groups: SBCL (n=30), intervention group and HCL (n=30), as control
      group.

      Before each hemodialysis treatment, catheters and connections will be inspected for leaks,
      evidence of damage, exit-site infection and tunnel infection. Intraluminal SBCL or HCL
      solution will be removed before connecting the hemodialysis catheter to a dialysis machine
      prior to any treatment.

      During each treatment, patients will be prescribed and monitored for complications and
      standard treatment will be provided to every patient. After each treatment, blood will be
      rinsed from dialysis lines with 0.9% saline solution back to the patient. Upon the conclusion
      of treatment, all catheters will be flushed with 10 mL 0.9% saline solution per blood line
      respectively, after saline flush, catheter lock will be prescribed; SBCL group with 7.5%
      sodium bicarbonate solution, at a dose of 2 milliliters per lumen, and HCL group with sodium
      heparin at a concentration of 1000 units per milliliter, at a dose of 2 milliliters per
      lumen. Catheter exit site dressing changes occurred after each HD treatment.

      Niagra 13.5 French/20 cm non tunneled catheter will be the standard vascular access. All
      central venous catheters will be inserted by an expert operator under strict aseptic
      protocol. Catheter care will be performed by trained dialysis staff. At the end of dialysis,
      all catheters will be flushed and locked with the respectively arm solution.

      Function assessment will be based on both, pressure and flow measurements on arterial line,
      as well as measurements of arterial and venous line pressures and flow during hemodialysis
      sessions. Infectious and thrombotic complications will be assessed as defined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, open label, clinical trial in chronic hemodialysis patients with a catheter as a vascular access, randomized to bicarbonate lock or heparin lock (control) as standard treatment.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial line pressure at fixed blood flow in sodium bicarbonate lock versus heparin lock catheters in chronic hemodialysis patients</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Arterial line pressure[mmHg] at 300 mL/min blood flow will be compared between sodium bicarbonate lock and heparin lock in chronic hemodialysis patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial line pressure at fixed blood flow in sodium bicarbonate lock versus heparin lock catheters in chronic hemodialysis patients</measure>
    <time_frame>60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Arterial line pressure[mmHg] at 300 mL/min blood flow will be compared between sodium bicarbonate lock and heparin lock in chronic hemodialysis patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial line pressure at fixed blood flow in sodium bicarbonate lock versus heparin lock catheters in chronic hemodialysis patients</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Arterial line pressure[mmHg] at 300 mL/min blood flow will be compared between sodium bicarbonate lock and heparin lock in chronic hemodialysis patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence rate of catheter related bloodstream infection</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Catheter related bloodstream infection rate (events per 100 days/catheter) will be compare between sodium bicarbonate lock versus heparin lock in chronic hemodialysis patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence rate of catheter thrombosis</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Catheter thrombosis rate (events per 100 days/catheter) will be compare between sodium bicarbonate lock versus heparin lock in chronic hemodialysis patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the frequency of hemorrhagic event, anaphylaxis, hypernatremia or death between sodium bicarbonate lock vs heparin lock in chronic hemodialysis patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Access Complication</condition>
  <condition>Catheter Complications</condition>
  <condition>Hemodialysis Access Failure</condition>
  <condition>Hemodialysis Catheter Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sodium bicarbonate catheter lock group (SBCL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chronic hemodialysis patients with a catheter as a vascular access, will be lock with sodium bicarbonate 7.5% Injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heparin catheter lock group (HCL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chronic hemodialysis patients with a catheter as a vascular access, will be lock with heparin, 1000 Units/mL injectable solution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sodium Bicarbonate 7.5% Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Sodium bicarbonate solution for catheter lock; 7.5% sodium bicarbonate solution will be used for catheter lock in both catheter lumens, 1.9 mL in each catheter lumen will be infused after hemodialysis treatment during 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sodium bicarbonate catheter lock group (SBCL)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bicarnat® arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Heparin Sodium, 1000 Units/mL Injectable Solution 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Heparin for catheter lock: 1000 u/mL heparin solution will be used for catheter lock in both catheter lumens as standard treatment, 1.9 mL in each catheter lumen will be infused after hemodialysis treatment during 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Heparin catheter lock group (HCL)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Inhepar® arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who accept participation and sign informed consent.

          -  Incident or prevalent chronic hemodialysis patients who receive at least 2 sessions
             per week with 1 month of clinical stability defined as: no hospitalizations, no
             vascular access infections, no changes in blood flow prescription due to vascular
             access dysfunction.

          -  Patients with temporal catheter (Niagra 13.5 French/20 cm length, BARD Access System,
             Salt Lake City, Utah, USA) as vascular access for hemodialysis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Catheter dysfunction at baseline

          -  On anticoagulation therapy

          -  Patients with known coagulopathy or hemophilia

          -  Patients with Child-Pugh B or C liver failure

          -  Patients with thrombocytopenia less than 100,000 u / L

          -  Patients with central vessel stenosis and vena cava syndrome, previously documented.

          -  Patients with vascular access exhaustion.

          -  Patients who have undergone more than 2 vascular approaches for hemodialysis
             catheters.

          -  Patients with heparin-induced thrombocytopenia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Israel Campos, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital General “Dr. Miguel Silva” de Morelia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General &quot;Dr. Miguel Silva&quot; de Morelia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morelia</city>
        <state>Michoacan</state>
        <zip>58020</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jha V, Garcia-Garcia G, Iseki K, Li Z, Naicker S, Plattner B, Saran R, Wang AY, Yang CW. Chronic kidney disease: global dimension and perspectives. Lancet. 2013 Jul 20;382(9888):260-72. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60687-X. Epub 2013 May 31. Review. Erratum in: Lancet. 2013 Jul 20;382(9888):208.</citation>
    <PMID>23727169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ma A, Shroff R, Hothi D, Lopez MM, Veligratli F, Calder F, Rees L. A comparison of arteriovenous fistulas and central venous lines for long-term chronic haemodialysis. Pediatr Nephrol. 2013 Feb;28(2):321-6. doi: 10.1007/s00467-012-2318-2. Epub 2012 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23052655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adib-Hajbaghery M, Molavizadeh N, Alavi NM. Quality of care of vascular access in hemodialysis patients in a hemodialysis center in Iran. J Vasc Nurs. 2012 Mar;30(1):24-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jvn.2011.10.002.</citation>
    <PMID>22321404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agharazii M, Plamondon I, Lebel M, Douville P, Desmeules S. Estimation of heparin leak into the systemic circulation after central venous catheter heparin lock. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2005 Jun;20(6):1238-40. Epub 2005 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>15855206</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moran JE, Ash SR; ASDIN Clinical Practice Committee. Locking solutions for hemodialysis catheters; heparin and citrate--a position paper by ASDIN. Semin Dial. 2008 Sep-Oct;21(5):490-2. doi: 10.1111/j.1525-139X.2008.00466.x. Epub 2008 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18764795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen FK, Li JJ, Song Y, Zhang YY, Chen P, Zhao CZ, Gong HY, Yao DF. Concentrated sodium chloride catheter lock solution--a new effective alternative method for hemodialysis patients with high bleeding risk. Ren Fail. 2014 Feb;36(1):17-22. doi: 10.3109/0886022X.2013.830207. Epub 2013 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23992231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palomo I, Pereira J, Alarcón M, Díaz G, Hidalgo P, Pizarro I, Jara E, Rojas P, Quiroga G, Moore-Carrasco R. Prevalence of heparin-induced antibodies in patients with chronic renal failure undergoing hemodialysis. J Clin Lab Anal. 2005;19(5):189-95.</citation>
    <PMID>16170812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yon CK, Low CL. Sodium citrate 4% versus heparin as a lock solution in hemodialysis patients with central venous catheters. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2013 Jan 15;70(2):131-6. doi: 10.2146/ajhp120300.</citation>
    <PMID>23292266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shanks RM, Sargent JL, Martinez RM, Graber ML, O'Toole GA. Catheter lock solutions influence staphylococcal biofilm formation on abiotic surfaces. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2006 Aug;21(8):2247-55. Epub 2006 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16627606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao Y, Li Z, Zhang L, Yang J, Yang Y, Tang Y, Fu P. Citrate versus heparin lock for hemodialysis catheters: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Am J Kidney Dis. 2014 Mar;63(3):479-90. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2013.08.016. Epub 2013 Oct 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24125729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beigi AA, HadiZadeh MS, Salimi F, Ghaheri H. Heparin compared with normal saline to maintain patency of permanent double lumen hemodialysis catheters: A randomized controlled trial. Adv Biomed Res. 2014 May 28;3:121. doi: 10.4103/2277-9175.133192. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24949292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhong L, Wang HL, Xu B, Yuan Y, Wang X, Zhang YY, Ji L, Pan ZM, Hu ZS. Normal saline versus heparin for patency of central venous catheters in adult patients - a systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Care. 2017 Jan 8;21(1):5. doi: 10.1186/s13054-016-1585-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28063456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong DW, Mishkin FS, Tanaka TT. The effects of bicarbonate on blood coagulation. JAMA. 1980 Jul 4;244(1):61-2.</citation>
    <PMID>7382058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farha MA, French S, Stokes JM, Brown ED. Bicarbonate Alters Bacterial Susceptibility to Antibiotics by Targeting the Proton Motive Force. ACS Infect Dis. 2018 Mar 9;4(3):382-390. doi: 10.1021/acsinfecdis.7b00194. Epub 2018 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>29264917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nostro A, Cellini L, Di Giulio M, D'Arrigo M, Marino A, Blanco AR, Favaloro A, Cutroneo G, Bisignano G. Effect of alkaline pH on staphylococcal biofilm formation. APMIS. 2012 Sep;120(9):733-42. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0463.2012.02900.x. Epub 2012 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22882263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital General “Dr. Miguel Silva” de Morelia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>J ARMANDO VÁZQUEZ ÁVILA, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Nephrology fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sodium bicarbonate lock</keyword>
  <keyword>Heparin lock</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular access complication</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium heparin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

