<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04051541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A18-400</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04051541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Simulation of Adenosine Push Methods for Treatment of SVT Using Agitated Saline Visualized by Ultrasound</brief_title>
  <official_title>Simulation of Adenosine Push Methods for Treatment of SVT Using Agitated Saline Visualized by Ultrasound</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>HealthPartners Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>HealthPartners Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Supraventricular tachycardia (SVT) is an abnormally fast heart rhythm arising from improper
      electrical activity in the upper part of the heart. SVT is commonly treated with adenosine
      using three different IV administration techniques. However, it is not well known which of
      these three techniques is the quickest or most likely to reach the heart in order to stop
      SVT. This study will simulate each of those techniques in an investigator-blinded procedure.
      Intravenous agitated saline, used as a surrogate for a dose of adenosine, will be
      administered to healthy volunteers using all three techniques and monitored using bedside
      ultrasound to observe their efficacy and speed in reaching the right side of the heart.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 28, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a simulation study in which all participants receive a dose of agitated saline through an IV using three different administration methods.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The investigator performing the ultrasound and the person timing the simulation were both blind to the method used for each push. An unblended investigator performed the pushes but did not assess the outcomes.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to ultrasound visualization of agitated saline in the right heart</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;5 seconds</time_frame>
    <description>Time from IV push to ultrasound visualization of agitated saline in the right heart</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Supraventricular Tachycardia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Simulation arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients were entered into the Simulation arm and received 3 pushes of agitated saline via 3 different methods of delivery. All patients received all methods. The order of the methods for each patient was randomized.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Agitated saline push</intervention_name>
    <description>Push of agitated saline to simulate adenosine used for supraventricular tachycardia</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simulation arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Volunteers aged 18 years and older

          -  Able to understand and provide signed consent for the study

          -  Must be healthy; not being actively treated for any condition that requires active
             medical intervention or monitoring to avert serious danger to the participant's health
             or well-being, as evaluated by study investigator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-English speaker

          -  Those with contraindications to peripheral IV placement, such as infection or other
             contraindication noted from evaluation by study investigator

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regions Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murman DH, McDonald AJ, Pelletier AJ, Camargo CA Jr. U.S. emergency department visits for supraventricular tachycardia, 1993-2003. Acad Emerg Med. 2007 Jun;14(6):578-81. Epub 2007 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17449792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brubaker S, Long B, Koyfman A. Alternative Treatment Options for Atrioventricular-Nodal-Reentry Tachycardia: An Emergency Medicine Review. J Emerg Med. 2018 Feb;54(2):198-206. doi: 10.1016/j.jemermed.2017.10.003. Epub 2017 Nov 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29239759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alabed S, Sabouni A, Providencia R, Atallah E, Qintar M, Chico TJ. Adenosine versus intravenous calcium channel antagonists for supraventricular tachycardia. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 Oct 12;10:CD005154. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD005154.pub4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29025197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weberding NT, Saladino RA, Minnigh MB, Oberly PJ, Tudorascu DL, Poloyac SM, Manole MD. Adenosine Administration With a Stopcock Technique Delivers Lower-Than-Intended Drug Doses. Ann Emerg Med. 2018 Feb;71(2):220-224. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2017.09.002. Epub 2017 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>29089171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Losek JD, Endom E, Dietrich A, Stewart G, Zempsky W, Smith K. Adenosine and pediatric supraventricular tachycardia in the emergency department: multicenter study and review. Ann Emerg Med. 1999 Feb;33(2):185-91.</citation>
    <PMID>9922414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kleinman ME, Chameides L, Schexnayder SM, Samson RA, Hazinski MF, Atkins DL, Berg MD, de Caen AR, Fink EL, Freid EB, Hickey RW, Marino BS, Nadkarni VM, Proctor LT, Qureshi FA, Sartorelli K, Topjian A, van der Jagt EW, Zaritsky AL. Part 14: pediatric advanced life support: 2010 American Heart Association Guidelines for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2010 Nov 2;122(18 Suppl 3):S876-908. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.971101. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20956230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Madsen CD, Pointer JE, Lynch TG. A comparison of adenosine and verapamil for the treatment of supraventricular tachycardia in the prehospital setting. Ann Emerg Med. 1995 May;25(5):649-55.</citation>
    <PMID>7741343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neumar RW, Otto CW, Link MS, Kronick SL, Shuster M, Callaway CW, Kudenchuk PJ, Ornato JP, McNally B, Silvers SM, Passman RS, White RD, Hess EP, Tang W, Davis D, Sinz E, Morrison LJ. Part 8: adult advanced cardiovascular life support: 2010 American Heart Association Guidelines for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2010 Nov 2;122(18 Suppl 3):S729-67. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.970988. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2011 Feb 15;123(6):e236. Circulation. 2013 Dec 24;128(25):e480.</citation>
    <PMID>20956224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng GA, Martin W, Rankin AC. Imaging of adenosine bolus transit following intravenous administration: insights into antiarrhythmic efficacy. Heart. 1999 Aug;82(2):163-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10409529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wen M, Stock K, Heemann U, Aussieker M, Küchle C. Agitated saline bubble-enhanced transthoracic echocardiography: a novel method to visualize the position of central venous catheter. Crit Care Med. 2014 Mar;42(3):e231-3. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000000130.</citation>
    <PMID>24317496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duran-Gehring PE, Guirgis FW, McKee KC, Goggans S, Tran H, Kalynych CJ, Wears RL. The bubble study: ultrasound confirmation of central venous catheter placement. Am J Emerg Med. 2015 Mar;33(3):315-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2014.10.010. Epub 2014 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25550065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gekle R, Dubensky L, Haddad S, Bramante R, Cirilli A, Catlin T, Patel G, D'Amore J, Slesinger TL, Raio C, Modayil V, Nelson M. Saline Flush Test: Can Bedside Sonography Replace Conventional Radiography for Confirmation of Above-the-Diaphragm Central Venous Catheter Placement? J Ultrasound Med. 2015 Jul;34(7):1295-9. doi: 10.7863/ultra.34.7.1295.</citation>
    <PMID>26112633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weekes AJ, Johnson DA, Keller SM, Efune B, Carey C, Rozario NL, Norton HJ. Central vascular catheter placement evaluation using saline flush and bedside echocardiography. Acad Emerg Med. 2014 Jan;21(1):65-72. doi: 10.1111/acem.12283.</citation>
    <PMID>24552526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ketkar VA, Kolling WM, Nardviriyakul N, VanDer Kamp K, Wurster DE. Stability of undiluted and diluted adenosine at three temperatures in syringes and bags. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 1998 Mar 1;55(5):466-70.</citation>
    <PMID>9522931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green AP, Giattina KH. Adenosine administration for neonatal SVT. Neonatal Netw. 1993 Aug;12(5):15-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8350844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia, Supraventricular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

