<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04059003</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Shengjing-LJY03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04059003</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CTC Changes and Efficacy of Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy for Triple-negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Circulating Tumor Cell Changes and Efficacy of Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy for Triple-negative Breast Cancer: a Cohort Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shengjing Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shengjing Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chemotherapy before operation for malignant tumors can reduce the size of tumors to a certain
      extent, even eliminate micrometastases. Chemotherapy can also detect the sensitivity of
      chemotherapeutic drugs and create opportunities for breast-conserving or surgical treatment
      for patients. This may lead to high survival opportunities for triple-negative breast cancer
      patients who are not sensitive to targeted therapy or endocrine therapy. However, during
      neoadjuvant therapy, CT or MRI tests are needed to monitor the patient's condition.
      Therefore, if there is any deterioration, to consider changing the treatment regimen or
      immediately carrying out surgery is necessary. However, because of the need for multiple
      imaging examinations during neoadjuvant therapy, which will increase medical costs, to
      explore a cheaper examination method is necessary . Circulating tumor cells in peripheral
      blood are derived from the shedding of breast cancer lesions. Detection of these circulating
      tumor cells may monitor the therapeutic effect on breast cancer, and the cost of detecting
      circulating tumor cells is much lower than that of conventional PET-CT, which can obviously
      reduce the medical costs of patients. However, there is no clinical study on the changes of
      circulating tumor cells and the efficacy of neoadjuvant chemotherapy in the treatment of
      triple-negative breast cancer in and outside China.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Triple-negative breast cancer refers to breast cancer with negative human epidermal growth
      factor receptor 2, estrogen receptor and progesterone receptor. Triple-negative breast cancer
      has poor differentiation, high invasiveness and high recurrence rate, accounting for
      15.0%-23.8% of breast cancer. Due to the phenotypic specificity of triple-negative breast
      cancer, both targeted therapy and endocrine therapy are insensitive, making chemotherapy an
      important part in the treatment of triple-negative breast cancer.

      In 1982, Frei proposed the concept of neoadjuvant chemotherapy, which is to apply
      chemotherapy before surgery for malignant tumors. Chemotherapy can reduce the size of tumors
      to some extent, even eliminate micrometastases, detect the sensitivity of chemotherapy drugs,
      and create opportunities for patients to have breast-conserving or surgical treatment. For
      triple-negative breast cancer, neoadjuvant chemotherapy with synchronous combination of
      anthracyclines and taxanes or intensive sequential combination of anthracyclines and taxanes
      is the first choice. Simultaneously, chemotherapeutic drugs such as platinum, albumin, and
      paclitaxel as well as poly-ADP-ribose polymerase inhibitors can be added according to the
      patient's condition. However, during neoadjuvant therapy, a CT or MRI test is needed to
      monitor the patient's condition, so if there is any deterioration, to consider changing the
      treatment plan or immediately performing surgery is necessary. However, because of the need
      for multiple imaging examinations during neoadjuvant therapy, which increases the medical
      costs, to explore a low cost inspection method is necessary.

      Circulating tumor cells are a new type of tumor molecular marker. Circulating tumor cells in
      peripheral blood originate from breast cancer (primary and metastatic lesions) shedding.
      Detection of these circulating tumor cells may monitor the therapeutic effect on breast
      cancer. The cost of detecting circulating tumor cells is much lower than that of conventional
      PET-CT, which can noticeably reduce medical expenses of patients. However, there is no
      clinical study on the changes of circulating tumor cells and the efficacy of neoadjuvant
      chemotherapy for triple-negative breast cancer in and outside China. This study aims to
      explore the correlation between the changes of circulating tumor cells and the efficacy of
      neoadjuvant chemotherapy for triple-negative breast cancer, and to compare the time intervals
      between the changes of circulating tumor cells and the changes of efficacy in patients with
      different sensitivities of neoadjuvant chemotherapy, so as to provide experimental evidence
      for predicting the efficacy of neoadjuvant chemotherapy by observing the changes of
      circulating tumor cells in clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of neoadjuvant chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>At 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The efficacy will be evaluated by the response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST) score, which is based on CT or X-ray results. (1) Complete response (CR): disappearance of all lesions; (2) partial response (PR): 30% decrease in sum of all target lesions in longest axis measurement; (3) stable disease (SD): the sum of the longest diameter of all lesions decreases but does not reach PR or increases but does not reach PD; (4) progressive disease (PD): 20% increase in the sum of the longest diameter or appearance of new lesions. SD: One or more non-target lesions and/or tumor markers are higher than normal and persistent.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of neoadjuvant chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The efficacy will be evaluated by the response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST) score, which is based on CT or X-ray results. (1) Complete response (CR): disappearance of all lesions; (2) partial response (PR): 30% decrease in sum of all target lesions in longest axis measurement; (3) stable disease (SD): the sum of the longest diameter of all lesions decreases but does not reach PR or increases but does not reach PD; (4) progressive disease (PD): 20% increase in the sum of the longest diameter or appearance of new lesions. SD: One or more non-target lesions and/or tumor markers are higher than normal and persistent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of circulating tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 weeks of neoadjuvant chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>At 3 weeks of neoadjuvant chemotherapy, 2.5 ml of blood will be taken from median elbow vein of upper arm, and the number of circulating tumor cells is ≤ 2 or CD133 ≤ 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Miller-Payne grading score</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 18 weeks after chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The Miller-Payne grading system is as follows: Grade 1: no reduction in overall cellularity; grade 2: up to 30% reduction of cellularity; grade 3: between an estimated 30% and 90% reduction in tumor cellularity; grade 4: a marked disappearance of more than 90% of tumor cells; grade 5: no invasive malignant cells identifiable in sections from the site of the tumor, but ductal carcinoma in situ may be present.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sensitivity group</arm_group_label>
    <description>100 patients will be assigned into sensitivity group according to the actual situation of them.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug resistance group</arm_group_label>
    <description>100 patients will be assigned into drug resistance according to the actual situation of them.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Taxanes or/and anthracycline-based therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Taxanes or/and anthracycline-based therapy will be used in this group. That is, intravenous injection of 90 mg/m2 epirubicin (trade name: Pharmorubicin, Pfizer, Shanghai, China; drug approval number: H20100155) + 135 mg/m2 paclitaxel liposome (trade name: Taxotere, Sanofi (Hangzhou) Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Hangzhou, China; drug approval number: J20090104), every 3 weeks as a course of treatment. The efficacy will be evaluated every 2 courses. After the 6th course, mastectomy will be performed according to the patient's conditions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug resistance group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sensitivity group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Totally 200 patients who meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be consecutively
        enrolled in the trial and grouped according to their sensitivity.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  triple-negative breast cancer confirmed by breast biopsy;

          -  stage III breast cancer (IIIA-C) assessed by CT or MRI;

          -  neoadjuvant chemotherapy;

          -  informed consent of patients and their family members.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  use of second-line chemotherapy regimen;

          -  bilateral breast cancer;

          -  inflammatory breast cancer;

          -  pregnant or breast-feeding;

          -  distant metastasis;

          -  a history of other cancers or chest radiotherapy;

          -  a history of abnormal blood test or other infectious symptoms.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jianyi Li</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shengjing Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jianyi Li</last_name>
    <phone>+8618940257177</phone>
    <email>sjbreast@yeah.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shengjing Hospital of China Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110004</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jianyi Li</last_name>
      <phone>+8618940257177</phone>
      <email>sjbreast@yeah.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shengjing Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jianyi Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Positron Emission Tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Computed Tomography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Taxane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

