<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04050566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PV5940</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04050566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Malaria Birth Cohort</brief_title>
  <acronym>MBC</acronym>
  <official_title>Analysis of Anti-malarial Immunity Development, Parasite Diversity, Endothelial Cell Activation, the Influence of Microbiota, and Behavioural and Socio-economic Risk Factors in Early Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bernhard Nocht Institute for Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kumasi Centre for Collaborative Research (KCCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heidelberg University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>KEMRI-Wellcome Trust Collaborative Research Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agogo Presbyterian Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bernhard Nocht Institute for Tropical Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim od the study is the investigation of immunity development against malaria with regards to
      parasite, human, and socio-economic factors.

      In detail, the objectives are as follows:

        -  Analysis of temporal changes of immune cell phenotypes, their correlation with
           protection and pathology

        -  Analysis of temporal changes of humoral immune responses, their correlation with
           protection and pathology, and analysis of protective antibody responses over time

        -  Analysis of malaria specific autoantibody profiles at time of birth (T=0) compared to
           after completion of first year of life and their association with disease outcome

        -  Analysis of parasite diversity during different malaria episodes in the first year of
           life

        -  Analysis of the influence of malaria infection on human endothelial activation

        -  Analysis of development, composition, diversity, and richness of intestinal microbiota
           from birth to 12 months and its relationship to occurrence and severity of malaria

        -  Analysis of behavioural, socio-economic and environmental factors and pathways
           associated with malaria in children

      The study is planned as a prospective birth cohort. Pregnant women will be recruited in the
      study hospital during antenatal care visits over a period of twelve months to account for
      seasonal fluctuations in disease prevalence. Children will be passively followed for 12
      months at regular vaccination visits in the frame of the EPI schedule (WHO Expanded Program
      of Immunization), which are organised by the health facilities in the district according to a
      fixed schedule. The participant's household will be visited within the first six weeks after
      birth to conduct questionnaires and record residential GPS coordinates. An additional visit
      is scheduled for 12 months after birth for a last follow-up visit. Parents and primary
      caregivers are encouraged to bring their child to the study hospital in case of a fever
      episode for an examination and treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinical manifestations of malaria range from asymptomatic infections, uncomplicated disease
      to severe complications, including cerebral malaria. Although the exact molecular mechanisms
      that lead to these diverse disease outcomes are not yet fully understood, it is generally
      accepted to be a complex interplay of factors involving the host, the parasite, and the
      geographical/environmental/socioeconomic setting. It was shown that the parasite expresses
      certain proteins on its host cell surface to enable cytoadherence and avoid clearance through
      the spleen. Together with a pro-inflammatory immune response, immunopathology, as well as
      low-affinity self-reacting antibodies and short-lived plasma cells, this contributes and
      shapes the course and magnitude of illness.

      The presented project intends to analyse the activation and development of immunity against
      malaria parasites and endothelial cytoadhesion of infected erythrocytes in the context of the
      parasite diversity during different malaria infections in the first year of life. The
      information obtained is essential for the understanding of the host-parasite interaction, the
      evaluation of vaccine effects, and the development of new anti-malarial vaccines. Measures of
      immunity and parasitology will be compared between episodes of asymptomatic parasitaemia,
      uncomplicated malaria, and severe malaria.

      The study addresses a major health problem in many resource-poor countries: the high malaria
      morbidity and mortality in young children. Though recognised as a public health issue, it has
      still not been well understood how clinical immunity against malaria parasites develops,
      which parasite and host factors play a role in infection susceptibility, and why some
      infections proceed to develop severe complications while others resolve after a mild disease.

      The composition of the entirety of bacteria in the gut (i.e. the intestinal microbiota) has
      recently been suggested to influence the development of immunity and thus the risk for
      malarial infection and clinical malaria. Animal models have shown that the intestinal
      microbiota composition determines certain immune responses, which confer protection against
      Plasmodium infections. The microbiota in turn is dependent on many internal and external
      factors, such as the contact to the mother. Thus, the intestinal microbiota seem to be
      crucial for the early development of anti-malarial immunity and the individual risk of the
      exposed individuals and shall be studied the first time in the project proposed here.

      In order to identify interactions between parasite and host, a longitudinal study will be
      performed starting with pregnant women in their last trimester. The study area covers a rural
      area in the Ashanti Region in Ghana, an area with high malaria endemicity. The study design
      allows to analyse the neonatal immune status at birth, after potential in-utero exposure, and
      follow the development of immunity over the first 12 months of life. The hypothesis is that
      time points and frequency of exposure to infection, as well as the type of variant surface
      antigen expressed by a parasite population, have an impact on the cellular and humoral immune
      response to malaria, the development of clinical immunity, as well as the risk for future
      complications. Additionally, we hypothesise that the intestinal microbiota has an impact on
      the development of anti-malarial immunity and therefore on the risk for malaria and severe
      courses of the disease in children and adolescents. The results can serve as a
      proof-of-concept of the hypothesis for other infectious diseases.

      A recent systematic review has revealed a lack of birth cohorts in Africa with appropriate
      study size and follow-up periods, highlighting the need of large-scale cohorts to study the
      development of immunity against infectious diseases. This study plans to address malaria as a
      relevant health problem in children and to overcome the limited capacity for competitive and
      translational research in sub-Saharan Africa.

      The aim of the study is to better understand anti-malarial immunity development, parasite
      diversity, endothelial cell activation, the influence of microbiota, and behavioural and
      socio-economic risk factors and their correlations with protection and pathology.

      Starting point of the study is the antenatal care visit of mothers at APH during the third
      trimester of pregnancy. Between pregnancy week 28 to 36, mothers are visiting the hospital
      biweekly, and weekly from week 36 until delivery. During these visits, gynaecologists and
      nurses will identify and approach participants over the course of twelve months to account
      for seasonal fluctuations in malaria incidence. During recruitment, the mother/primary
      caregivers will be asked to read and sign an informed consent form approved by the local
      ethical committee. After consent has been obtained from the mother/primary caregivers,
      biological samples will be taken between pregnancy week 30 and 32, and a case report form
      will be filled.

      An identification card with a unique code number will be handed out. The first follow-up
      visit will occur at the birth of the child. At this time point, the child receives the BCG
      (bacillus Calmette-Guerin) and the first dose of the oral polio vaccine (OPV-0).
      Mothers/primary caregivers are encouraged to bring the child to the hospital when it shows an
      excessive vaccine reaction against the BCG vaccine. Mothers/primary caregivers will be
      invited to observe the EPI visits offered at their nearest health post for further
      follow-ups. In the first year after birth, the EPI schedule includes the following visits:
      EPI1 at six weeks (pentavalent vaccine (Penta)-1, pneumococcal vaccine (Pneumo)-1, OPV-1, and
      the rotavirus vaccine), EPI2 at ten weeks (Penta-2, OPV-2), EPI3 at 14 weeks (Penta-3,
      OPV-3), EPI4 at six months (Vitamin A), and EPI5 at nine months (Measles 1 and yellow fever).
      In Agogo, 10-15 EPI sites are visited during the observation period.

      In the first six weeks after birth, the household will be visited to complete a household
      questionnaire including housing characteristics and household assets. Additionally, a women's
      questionnaire will be administered, which will collect demographic and socioeconomic
      background characteristics as well as health and related behavioural data.

      Twelve month after birth, mothers/primary caregivers are encouraged to bring their children
      to the study hospital (APH) for a medical check-up.

      Mothers/primary caregivers are strongly encouraged to visit the study hospital every time the
      child experiences a febrile illness or a history of fever in last week during the observation
      period (fever visits). Upon presentation of their identification card, the child will receive
      preferential treatment from the study physician.

      Our sample size calculation is based on the following assumptions: Based on previous study
      results, we assume that 80% of children encounter at least one malaria episode during one
      year of observation. 50% of those children will be brought to hospital for examination. 8% of
      these children will develop severe malaria. Furthermore, we assume that 15% of the study
      cohort will be lost to follow-up due to different reasons (e.g. withdrawal from study, infant
      mortality, relocation of residence). Different blood parameters, immunity parameters and
      parasites characteristics will be compared between established study groups, namely i)
      children that develop severe malaria according to established criteria during the follow-up
      time, ii) children with uncomplicated malaria (asexual parasitaemia), but no severe malaria
      symptoms, and iii), asymptomatic infection) children without fever visit during the
      observation period but with malaria parasitaemia at invited hospital visit (12 month).
      Several outcome parameters measured in the study follow a continuous distribution, thus the
      primary sample size calculation is based on a two-sample t-test (i.e. allowing a comparison
      of parameter differences between two of the three groups at one time). Assuming an alpha of
      5% and a power of 80%, a sample size of 27 per group would be sufficient to detect a moderate
      mean difference (mean = 1; standard deviation [SD]: 1 vs. mean = 2; SD: 1.5). If we recruit
      1,200 newborns into the cohort, 1,050 (85%) would complete follow-up. Of these, 816 (80%)
      will experience a malaria episode and 408 (50%) will attend the treatment hospital. Hence,
      according to the assumptions outlined above, the estimated study groups will be as follows:
      (i) 33 children with severe malaria, (ii) 375 children with uncomplicated malaria, and (iii)
      204 children without symptomatic malaria as described above. In all two/three groups, data
      and samples from all available follow-ups before the event are analysed in the different work
      packages.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>First severe malaria episode</measure>
    <time_frame>First year of life</time_frame>
    <description>Severe Malaria episode as defined by the WHO measured by microscopy and PCR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2400</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pregnant women during the third trimester of pregnancy visiting Agogo Prespyterian Hospital
        (APH) for their antenatel care visit.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Catchment area of the EPI (Expanded Program of Immunization) centres with good
             accessibility to Agogo Prespyterian Hospital (APH)

          -  Willingness and able to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Maternal age &lt;18 years

          -  Positive HIV status of mother

          -  Refusal or withdrawal of informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jürgen May, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bernhard Nocht Institute for Tropical Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel Eibach, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 40 42818-0</phone>
    <phone_ext>504</phone_ext>
    <email>eibach@bnitm.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eva Mertens, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 40 42818-0</phone>
    <phone_ext>243</phone_ext>
    <email>mertens@bnitm.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bernhard Nocht Institute for Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20359</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kumasi</city>
        <country>Ghana</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Amuasi, Dr</last_name>
      <email>amuasi@kccr.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Oumou Maige-Ascofaré, PhD</last_name>
      <email>maiga@bnitm.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Ghana</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andrade BB, Barral-Netto M. Biomarkers for susceptibility to infection and disease severity in human malaria. Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz. 2011 Aug;106 Suppl 1:70-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21881759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller LH, Baruch DI, Marsh K, Doumbo OK. The pathogenic basis of malaria. Nature. 2002 Feb 7;415(6872):673-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11832955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowe JA, Claessens A, Corrigan RA, Arman M. Adhesion of Plasmodium falciparum-infected erythrocytes to human cells: molecular mechanisms and therapeutic implications. Expert Rev Mol Med. 2009 May 26;11:e16. doi: 10.1017/S1462399409001082. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19467172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medana IM, Turner GD. Human cerebral malaria and the blood-brain barrier. Int J Parasitol. 2006 May 1;36(5):555-68. Epub 2006 Mar 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16616145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ippolito MM, Denny JE, Langelier C, Sears CL, Schmidt NW. Malaria and the Microbiome: A Systematic Review. Clin Infect Dis. 2018 Nov 28;67(12):1831-1839. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciy374.</citation>
    <PMID>29701835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferretti P, Pasolli E, Tett A, Asnicar F, Gorfer V, Fedi S, Armanini F, Truong DT, Manara S, Zolfo M, Beghini F, Bertorelli R, De Sanctis V, Bariletti I, Canto R, Clementi R, Cologna M, Crifò T, Cusumano G, Gottardi S, Innamorati C, Masè C, Postai D, Savoi D, Duranti S, Lugli GA, Mancabelli L, Turroni F, Ferrario C, Milani C, Mangifesta M, Anzalone R, Viappiani A, Yassour M, Vlamakis H, Xavier R, Collado CM, Koren O, Tateo S, Soffiati M, Pedrotti A, Ventura M, Huttenhower C, Bork P, Segata N. Mother-to-Infant Microbial Transmission from Different Body Sites Shapes the Developing Infant Gut Microbiome. Cell Host Microbe. 2018 Jul 11;24(1):133-145.e5. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2018.06.005.</citation>
    <PMID>30001516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell A, Rudan I. Systematic review of birth cohort studies in Africa. J Glob Health. 2011 Jun;1(1):46-58.</citation>
    <PMID>23198102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaper AG, Kaplan MH, Mody NJ, McIntyre PA. Malarial antibodies and autoantibodies to heart and other tissues in the immigrant and indigenous peoples of Uganda. Lancet. 1968 Jun 22;1(7556):1342-6.</citation>
    <PMID>4172652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenwood BM, Herrick EM, Holborow EJ. Speckled antinuclear factor in African sera. Clin Exp Immunol. 1970 Jul;7(1):75-83.</citation>
    <PMID>4991609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adu D, Williams DG, Quakyi IA, Voller A, Anim-Addo Y, Bruce-Tagoe AA, Johnson GD, Holborow EJ. Anti-ssDNA and antinuclear antibodies in human malaria. Clin Exp Immunol. 1982 Aug;49(2):310-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6982135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yahya TM, Benedict S, Shalabi A, Bayoumi R. Anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (ANCA) in malaria is directed against cathepsin G. Clin Exp Immunol. 1997 Oct;110(1):41-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9353147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guiyedi V, Bécavin C, Herbert F, Gray J, Cazenave PA, Kombila M, Crisanti A, Fesel C, Pied S. Asymptomatic Plasmodium falciparum infection in children is associated with increased auto-antibody production, high IL-10 plasma levels and antibodies to merozoite surface protein 3. Malar J. 2015 Apr 16;14:162. doi: 10.1186/s12936-015-0658-7.</citation>
    <PMID>25889717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lang B, Newbold CI, Williams G, Peshu N, Marsh K, Newton CR. Antibodies to voltage-gated calcium channels in children with falciparum malaria. J Infect Dis. 2005 Jan 1;191(1):117-21. Epub 2004 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>15593012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guiyedi V, Chanseaud Y, Fesel C, Snounou G, Rousselle JC, Lim P, Koko J, Namane A, Cazenave PA, Kombila M, Pied S. Self-reactivities to the non-erythroid alpha spectrin correlate with cerebral malaria in Gabonese children. PLoS One. 2007 Apr 25;2(4):e389.</citation>
    <PMID>17460756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernandez-Arias C, Rivera-Correa J, Gallego-Delgado J, Rudlaff R, Fernandez C, Roussel C, Götz A, Gonzalez S, Mohanty A, Mohanty S, Wassmer S, Buffet P, Ndour PA, Rodriguez A. Anti-Self Phosphatidylserine Antibodies Recognize Uninfected Erythrocytes Promoting Malarial Anemia. Cell Host Microbe. 2016 Feb 10;19(2):194-203. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2016.01.009.</citation>
    <PMID>26867178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller RH, Hathaway NJ, Kharabora O, Mwandagalirwa K, Tshefu A, Meshnick SR, Taylor SM, Juliano JJ, Stewart VA, Bailey JA. A deep sequencing approach to estimate Plasmodium falciparum complexity of infection (COI) and explore apical membrane antigen 1 diversity. Malar J. 2017 Dec 16;16(1):490. doi: 10.1186/s12936-017-2137-9.</citation>
    <PMID>29246158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clemente JC, Ursell LK, Parfrey LW, Knight R. The impact of the gut microbiota on human health: an integrative view. Cell. 2012 Mar 16;148(6):1258-70. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2012.01.035. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22424233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmer C, Bik EM, DiGiulio DB, Relman DA, Brown PO. Development of the human infant intestinal microbiota. PLoS Biol. 2007 Jul;5(7):e177. Epub 2007 Jun 26.</citation>
    <PMID>17594176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung H, Pamp SJ, Hill JA, Surana NK, Edelman SM, Troy EB, Reading NC, Villablanca EJ, Wang S, Mora JR, Umesaki Y, Mathis D, Benoist C, Relman DA, Kasper DL. Gut immune maturation depends on colonization with a host-specific microbiota. Cell. 2012 Jun 22;149(7):1578-93. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2012.04.037.</citation>
    <PMID>22726443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong SN, Rhee PL. Unraveling the ties between irritable bowel syndrome and intestinal microbiota. World J Gastroenterol. 2014 Mar 14;20(10):2470-81. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v20.i10.2470. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24627584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taniguchi T, Miyauchi E, Nakamura S, Hirai M, Suzue K, Imai T, Nomura T, Handa T, Okada H, Shimokawa C, Onishi R, Olia A, Hirata J, Tomita H, Ohno H, Horii T, Hisaeda H. Plasmodium berghei ANKA causes intestinal malaria associated with dysbiosis. Sci Rep. 2015 Oct 27;5:15699. doi: 10.1038/srep15699. Erratum in: Sci Rep. 2016;6:17248.</citation>
    <PMID>26503461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yooseph S, Kirkness EF, Tran TM, Harkins DM, Jones MB, Torralba MG, O'Connell E, Nutman TB, Doumbo S, Doumbo OK, Traore B, Crompton PD, Nelson KE. Stool microbiota composition is associated with the prospective risk of Plasmodium falciparum infection. BMC Genomics. 2015 Aug 22;16:631. doi: 10.1186/s12864-015-1819-3.</citation>
    <PMID>26296559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yilmaz B, Portugal S, Tran TM, Gozzelino R, Ramos S, Gomes J, Regalado A, Cowan PJ, d'Apice AJ, Chong AS, Doumbo OK, Traore B, Crompton PD, Silveira H, Soares MP. Gut microbiota elicits a protective immune response against malaria transmission. Cell. 2014 Dec 4;159(6):1277-89. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2014.10.053.</citation>
    <PMID>25480293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teklehaimanot A, Mejia P. Malaria and poverty. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2008;1136:32-7. doi: 10.1196/annals.1425.037.</citation>
    <PMID>18579874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Somi MF, Butler JR, Vahid F, Njau J, Kachur SP, Abdulla S. Is there evidence for dual causation between malaria and socioeconomic status? Findings from rural Tanzania. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2007 Dec;77(6):1020-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18165515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Castro MC, Fisher MG. Is malaria illness among young children a cause or a consequence of low socioeconomic status? evidence from the united Republic of Tanzania. Malar J. 2012 May 9;11:161. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-11-161.</citation>
    <PMID>22571516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krefis AC, Schwarz NG, Nkrumah B, Acquah S, Loag W, Sarpong N, Adu-Sarkodie Y, Ranft U, May J. Principal component analysis of socioeconomic factors and their association with malaria in children from the Ashanti Region, Ghana. Malar J. 2010 Jul 13;9:201. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-9-201.</citation>
    <PMID>20626839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tusting LS, Willey B, Lucas H, Thompson J, Kafy HT, Smith R, Lindsay SW. Socioeconomic development as an intervention against malaria: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet. 2013 Sep 14;382(9896):963-72. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60851-X. Epub 2013 Jun 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23790353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fobil JN, Kraemer A, Meyer CG, May J. Neighborhood urban environmental quality conditions are likely to drive malaria and diarrhea mortality in Accra, Ghana. J Environ Public Health. 2011;2011:484010. doi: 10.1155/2011/484010. Epub 2011 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21776438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barat LM, Palmer N, Basu S, Worrall E, Hanson K, Mills A. Do malaria control interventions reach the poor? A view through the equity lens. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2004 Aug;71(2 Suppl):174-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15331835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caulfield LE, Richard SA, Black RE. Undernutrition as an underlying cause of malaria morbidity and mortality in children less than five years old. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2004 Aug;71(2 Suppl):55-63. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15331819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tusting LS, Rek J, Arinaitwe E, Staedke SG, Kamya MR, Cano J, Bottomley C, Johnston D, Dorsey G, Lindsay SW, Lines J. Why is malaria associated with poverty? Findings from a cohort study in rural Uganda. Infect Dis Poverty. 2016 Aug 4;5(1):78. doi: 10.1186/s40249-016-0164-3.</citation>
    <PMID>27488674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fobil J, May J, Kraemer A. Assessing the relationship between socioeconomic conditions and urban environmental quality in Accra, Ghana. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2010 Jan;7(1):125-45. doi: 10.3390/ijerph7010125. Epub 2010 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20195437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chuma JM, Thiede M, Molyneux CS. Rethinking the economic costs of malaria at the household level: evidence from applying a new analytical framework in rural Kenya. Malar J. 2006 Aug 30;5:76.</citation>
    <PMID>16939658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sagara I, Giorgi R, Doumbo OK, Piarroux R, Gaudart J. Modelling recurrent events: comparison of statistical models with continuous and discontinuous risk intervals on recurrent malaria episodes data. Malar J. 2014 Jul 29;13:293. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-13-293.</citation>
    <PMID>25073652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Twisk JW, Smidt N, de Vente W. Applied analysis of recurrent events: a practical overview. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2005 Aug;59(8):706-10.</citation>
    <PMID>16020650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rochon J, du Bois A, Lange T. Mediation analysis of the relationship between institutional research activity and patient survival. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2014 Jan 22;14:9. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-14-9.</citation>
    <PMID>24447677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. Research electronic data capture (REDCap)--a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. J Biomed Inform. 2009 Apr;42(2):377-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010. Epub 2008 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18929686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bernhard Nocht Institute for Tropical Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Jürgen May</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Department Head</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunity development</keyword>
  <keyword>Plasmodium diversity</keyword>
  <keyword>Microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelial cell activation</keyword>
  <keyword>Poverty</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

