<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04051242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY19040344</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04051242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhanced Bioscaffold for Volumetric Muscle Loss</brief_title>
  <acronym>MTEC VML</acronym>
  <official_title>XENMATRIX™ AB Surgical Graft for the Repair of Severe Musculotendinous Tissue Damaged by Soft Tissue Trauma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>J. Peter Rubin, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, single center study conducted at the University of Pittsburgh designed
      to test the applicability and utility of XenMatrix™ AB Surgical Graft in the restoration of
      function in the setting of volumetric muscle loss after soft tissue trauma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previously, a human subject clinical trial (NCT01292876, PRO10010500) to evaluate a
      regenerative medicine approach using ECM for VML treatment was conducted. ECM scaffolds were
      implanted and combined with aggressive and early physical therapy in 13 subjects, then
      followed for 24-28 weeks after implantation. Histomorphological assessments collected from
      core needle biopsies identified formation of new, vascularized, innervated islands of
      skeletal muscle within the implantation site. Subjects demonstrated increased force
      production in physical therapy evaluations and improved functional task performance when
      compared with pre-operative performance. By 6 months after ECM implantation, subjects had a
      37.3% improvement in strength and 27.1% improvement in range-of-motion tasks. Additionally,
      changes in nerve conduction study (NCS) and electromyography (EMG) before and after ECM
      implantation were measured. 63% of study participants experienced improvements in NCS or EMG
      within the scaffold remodeling site, indicating clinical improvement in muscle strength. The
      promising functional and regenerative results from this early study encourages evidence of
      ECM bioscaffolding as a viable treatment to VML.

      This study proposes to use XenMatrix™ AB Surgical Graft which has 510(k) approval [#K162193]
      intended for implantation to reinforce soft tissue where weakness exists and for surgical
      repair of damaged or ruptured soft tissue, including abdominal plastic and reconstructive
      surgery; muscle flap reinforcement; hernia repair including abdominal, inguinal, femoral,
      diaphragmatic, scrotal, umbilical, and incisional hernias. The graft has an antibiotic
      coating, specifically, Rifampin and Minocycline. This coating has been shown in preclinical
      in vitro and in vivo testing to reduce or inhibit microbial colonization on the device. The
      claim of reduction of bacterial colonization of the device has not yet been established with
      human clinical data, nor has a clinical impact associated with this claim been demonstrated
      and will need further investigation. This trial proposes to test the applicability and
      utility of XenMatrix™ AB Surgical Graft in the restoration of function in the setting of
      volumetric muscle loss after trauma. 10 subjects will be enrolled for participation in the
      study. Prior to Graft implantation, subjects will receive a pre-operative course of physical
      therapy for a maximum time period of 16 weeks. A physical therapist will confirm that
      functional plateau is reached prior to implantation of the Graft. Following Graft
      implantation, radiographic, functional, and electrophysotherapy outcomes will be measured at
      various time points up to 24-28 weeks post-operatively. A CT scan or MRI will be collected at
      screening and pre-operative visits to evaluate tissue volume, then again at post-operative
      Visit 1 and Visit 6. Physical therapy training will be performed as a research procedure
      following Graft implantation for a maximum of 30 weeks. Additionally, Physical Therapy
      evaluations will be conducted at screening, pre-op visit 1, post-op, and at post-op Visits 3,
      and 4. A small core needle biopsy 1-5 grams will be collected at three time points to conduct
      histomorphological assessment of the tissue prior to Graft implantation (Operative visit,
      Visit 2 and at Visit 4).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>extremity function (number of types of exercises)</measure>
    <time_frame>9-11 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient extremity function post implantation of XENMATRIX AB™ Surgical Graft; after skeletal muscle injury, as determined and measured by physical therapy assessments and types of exercises able to do.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>extremity strength (number of repetitions of exercises)</measure>
    <time_frame>9-11 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient extremity mechanical strength post implantation of XENMATRIX AB™ Surgical Graft; after skeletal muscle injury as determined by physical therapy assessments and amount of exercise repetitions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>9-11 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient rate of infection with the use of XENMATRIX AB™ Surgical Graft</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>XenMatrix AB Surgical Graft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study proposes to use XenMatrix™ AB Surgical Graft which has 510(k) approval [#K162193] intended for implantation to reinforce soft tissue where weakness exists and for surgical repair of damaged or ruptured soft tissue. This trial proposes to test the applicability and utility of XenMatrix™ AB Surgical Graft in the restoration of function in the setting of volumetric muscle loss after trauma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>XenMatrix™ AB Surgical Graft</intervention_name>
    <description>Graft implantation, radiographic, functional, and electrophysotherapy outcomes will be measured at various time points up to 24-28 weeks post-operatively. A CT scan or MRI will be collected at screening and pre-operative visits to evaluate tissue volume, then again at post-operative Visit 1 and Visit 6. Physical therapy training will be performed as a research procedure following Graft implantation for a maximum of 30 weeks. Additionally, Physical Therapy evaluations will be conducted at screening, pre-op visit 1, post-op, and at post-op Visits 3, and 4. A small core needle biopsy 1-5 grams will be collected at three time points to conduct histomorphological assessment of the tissue prior to Graft implantation (Operative visit, Visit 2 and at Visit 4).</description>
    <arm_group_label>XenMatrix AB Surgical Graft</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 18 to 70 years of age and able to provide informed consent

          -  Civilian, and current or former military personnel are eligible to participate

          -  Have suffered injury resulting in a structural deficit of a minimum of 20% of the
             muscle group mass and a functional deficit of a minimum of 25% when compared to a
             contralateral limb present; or if bilateral injury is present to extremities, the
             potential surgical extremity is to be compared against normal expected values of a
             sample population of similar age and gender and evidence of remaining tendon and
             musculotendinous units that could be surgically repaired with sutures.

          -  Injuries may encompass a single muscle belly or compartment, whether an area is
             expected to be repaired by sutures will be determined from imaging studies and
             physical examination. Muscle groups which originate or attach to the long bones of the
             extremity, and which directly affect strength and function (i.e., Pectoralis Major,
             Coracobrachialis, Subscapularis, Teres Major/Minor, Latissimus Dorsi, Supraspinatus,
             Infraspinatus, Gluteus group, Tensor fasciae latae, Piriformis, and quadratus femoris)
             will also be included in this clinical trial.

          -  Have suffered traumatic injury within the last 18 months to the upper and/or lower
             extremity; Target of 18 months or less but subject's may be enrolled with injury
             outside this range if the principal investigator determines that there is viable
             muscle in the injured compartment determined by clinical exam and imaging studies.

          -  Eligible for study procedures 3 months post injury with stability determined by the
             Principal Investigator and/ or Physician Co-Investigator

          -  Willing and able to comply with follow up examinations, radiographic studies, physical
             therapy, muscle biopsy and laboratory tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to provide informed consent

          -  Poor nutrition (demonstrated by clinically significant abnormal lab results for serum
             albumin and pre-albumin values, per the investigator's discretion)

          -  Chronic disease such as congestive heart failure, liver disease, renal disease, or
             diabetes

          -  Active and unstable disease state or infection anywhere in the body per Physician's
             evaluation and determination (demonstrated by stated or medical record history and
             abnormal lab range for CBC with Differential and Platelet, Liver function and
             chemistry panel values)

          -  Known coagulopathy (demonstrated by stated or medical record history of diagnosis)

          -  Pregnancy (demonstrated by a positive result of a urine pregnancy test)• Diagnosis of
             cancer within last 12 months and /or actively receiving chemotherapy or radiation
             treatment

          -  Subjects with an Axis I diagnosis DSM-IV (e.g., Schizophrenia, Bipolar Disorder).
             Subjects who are found to be stable on medication and receive psychiatric clearance
             could be eligible for study participation per the Physician's discretion

             .• Subjects with complete muscle/tendon gaps greater than 5 cm that are obvious on
             imaging studies and are unlikely to be reasonably repaired with sutures and
             reinforcement, and will be excluded. The investigators recognize that these findings
             may not be clear on imaging studies, and that the clinical judgment of the surgeon
             shall be applied in each case.

          -  Subjects with a known hypersensitivity to porcine serum products

          -  Allergies to the antibiotics, Rifampin, minocycline, tetracycline currently associated
             with the XenMatric AB Surgical Graft
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J. Peter Rubin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eleanor Shirley, MA</last_name>
    <phone>4123837712</phone>
    <email>shirleye@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPMC Aesthetic Plastic Surgery Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eleanor Shirley, MA</last_name>
      <phone>412-383-7712</phone>
      <email>shirleye@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alexandra McCloskey, MS</last_name>
      <phone>412-383-7688</phone>
      <email>mccloskeyar2@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dziki J, Badylak S, Yabroudi M, Sicari B, Ambrosio F, Stearns K, Turner N, Wyse A, Boninger ML, Brown EHP, Rubin JP. An acellular biologic scaffold treatment for volumetric muscle loss: results of a 13-patient cohort study. NPJ Regen Med. 2016 Jul 21;1:16008. doi: 10.1038/npjregenmed.2016.8. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>29302336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Han N, Yabroudi MA, Stearns-Reider K, Helkowski W, Sicari BM, Rubin JP, Badylak SF, Boninger ML, Ambrosio F. Electrodiagnostic Evaluation of Individuals Implanted With Extracellular Matrix for the Treatment of Volumetric Muscle Injury: Case Series. Phys Ther. 2016 Apr;96(4):540-9. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20150133. Epub 2015 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26564252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>J. Peter Rubin, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

