<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04056468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-788-1008</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1236-7377</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04056468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate Pharmacokinetics (PK) and Safety of Oral TAK-788 in Participants With Moderate or Severe Hepatic Impairment (HI) and Normal Hepatic Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Pharmacokinetics and Safety Study of Oral TAK-788 in Subjects With Moderate or Severe Hepatic Impairment and Normal Hepatic Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to characterize the single-dose plasma PK of TAK-788 and its
      active metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914) in participants with moderate and/or severe HI
      compared to matched-healthy participants with normal hepatic function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      29-Apr-2020 Enrollment of new patients into this study has been paused due to the COVID-19
      situation. The duration of this pause is dependent on the leveling and control of the
      COVID-19 pandemic.

      The drug being tested in this study is called TAK-788. The study will assess the PK of single
      dose TAK-788 and its active metabolites (including but not limited to AP32960 and AP32914) in
      participants with moderate and/or severe HI compared to matched-healthy participants with
      normal hepatic function.

      The study will enroll approximately 24 participants. Participants will be assigned to 1 of
      the following 3 treatment groups in a staggered manner based on their degree of hepatic
      impairment which will be determined based on Child-Pugh Score as follow:

        -  Moderate HI (Child-Pugh B): TAK-788 40 mg

        -  Severe HI (Child-Pugh C): TAK-788 40 mg

        -  Normal Hepatic Function: TAK-788 40 mg

      Healthy participants with normal hepatic function will be recruited to match both moderate
      and severe HI by age (mean plus or minus [+-] 10 years), gender (+-2 participants per
      gender), and body mass index (BMI, mean +-10 percent [%]).

      All participants will be asked to take single dose of TAK-788 on Day 1. The dose level for
      severe HI may be modified based on the previous results of approximately 3 moderate HI and
      healthy participants who completed up to Day 10 study procedures.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted in the United States. The overall time to
      participate in this study is approximately 51 days. Participants will be contacted by
      telephone 30 days after the last dose of study drug for a follow-up assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 25, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 25, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax: Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax,u: Maximum Observed Unbound Plasma Concentration for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC∞: Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve From Time 0 to Infinity for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC∞,u: Area Under the Unbound Plasma Concentration-time Curve From Time 0 to Infinity for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUClast: Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve From Time 0 to the Time of the Last Quantifiable Concentration for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUClast,u: Area Under the Unbound Plasma Concentration-time Curve From Time 0 to the Time of the Last Quantifiable Concentration for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax: Time to Reach the Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>t1/2z: Terminal Disposition Phase Half-life for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>λz: Terminal Elimination Rate Constant for TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CL/F: Apparent Clearance After Extravascular Administration for TAK-788</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CLu/F: Apparent Clearance for Unbound Drug After Extravascular Administration for TAK-788</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vz/F: Apparent Volume of Distribution During the Terminal Disposition Phase After Extravascular Administration for TAK-788</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vz,u/F: Apparent Volume of Distribution for Unbound Drug During the Terminal Disposition Phase After Extravascular Administration for TAK-788</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and at multiple time points (up to 216 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Protein Binding of TAK-788 and its Active Metabolites (AP32960 and AP32914)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at multiple time points (up to 24 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Reporting one or More Treatment-emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 30 days after last dose of study drug (Day 31)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatic Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate HI (Child-Pugh B): TAK-788 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-788 40 milligram (mg), capsule, orally, a single dose on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Severe HI (Child-Pugh C): TAK-788 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-788 40 mg, capsule, orally, a single dose on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Hepatic Function: TAK-788 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-788 40 mg, capsule, orally, a single dose on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-788</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-788 capsule.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate HI (Child-Pugh B): TAK-788 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Hepatic Function: TAK-788 40 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Severe HI (Child-Pugh C): TAK-788 40 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion Criteria for Healthy Participants

          1. Continuous non-smoker or moderate smoker (less than or equal to (&lt;=) 10 cigarettes/day
             or the equivalent) before screening. Participant must agree to consume no more than 5
             cigarettes or equivalent/day from the 7 days prior to TAK-788 dosing and throughout
             the period of PK sample collection.

          2. BMI greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 18.0 and &lt;=39.0 kilogram per square meter (kg/m^2),
             at screening. Participants will be matched to hepatic impaired participants by BMI
             (mean +- 10%) at screening. At least 50% of the participants will be required to be of
             BMI &gt;=18.0 and &lt;=35.0 kg/m^2, at screening.

          3. Medically healthy with no clinically significant medical history, physical
             examination, laboratory profiles, vital signs or ECGs, as deemed by the Investigator
             or designee. Has liver function tests including alanine aminotransferase (ALT),
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), and total bilirubin
             within the upper limit of normal at screening and at check-in.

          4. Creatinine clearance (estimated glomerular filtration rate [eGFR]) &gt;=60 milliliter per
             minute per 1.73 square meter (mL/min/1.73 m^2) at screening.

          5. Normal baseline spirometry for forced vital capacity (FVC) and forced expiratory
             volume (FEV1)/FVC within 7 days prior to dosing based on the following normal FVC and
             FEV1/FVC range:

               -  18 to 39 years of age: &gt;=80% of predicted normal.

               -  40 to 59 years of age: &gt;=75% of predicted normal.

               -  60 to &lt;80 years of age: &gt;=70% of predicted normal.

        Inclusion Criteria for HI Participants

          1. Continuous non-smoker or moderate smoker (&lt;=10 cigarettes/day or the equivalent)
             before screening. Partcipant must agree to consume no more than 5 cigarettes or
             equivalent/day from the 7 days prior to TAK-788 dosing and throughout the period of PK
             sample collection.

          2. BMI &gt;=18.0 and &lt;=39.0 kg/m^2, at screening. At least 50% of the participants will be
             required to be of BMI &gt;=18.0 and &lt;=35.0 kg/m^2, at screening.

          3. Aside from HI, be sufficiently healthy for study participation based upon medical
             history, physical examination, vital signs, ECGs, and screening clinical laboratory
             profiles, as deemed by the Investigator or designee.

          4. Creatinine clearance (eGFR) &gt;=60 mL/min/1.73 m^2 at screening.

          5. Chronic HI for at least 3 months before screening, and the HI must be stable, that is,
             no significant changes in hepatic function in the 30 days preceding screening (or
             since the last visit if within 6 months before screening) and treatment with stable
             doses of medication. Has a score on the Child-Pugh Class at screening as follows:

               -  Moderate HI arm, Child-Pugh Class B: &gt;=7 and &lt;=9.

               -  Severe HI arm, Child-Pugh Class C: &gt;=10 and &lt;=15.

          6. Normal baseline spirometry for FVC and FEV1/FVC within 7 days prior to dosing based on
             the following normal FVC and FEV1/FVC range:

               -  18 to 39 years of age: &gt;=80% of predicted normal.

               -  40 to 59 years of age: &gt;=75% of predicted normal.

               -  60 to &lt;80 years of age: &gt;=70% of predicted normal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Seated blood pressure is less than 90/40 millimeters of Mercury (mmHg) or greater than
             150/95 mmHg at screening.

          2. Seated heart rate is lower than 40 beats per minute (bpm) or higher than 99 bpm at
             screening.

          3. Corrected QT interval using Fridericia's formula (QTcF) interval is &gt;=450 millisecond
             (msec) in males or &gt;=470 msec in females or has ECG findings deemed abnormal with
             clinical significance by the Investigator or designee at screening.

          4. Unable to refrain from or anticipates the use of any medication or substance
             (including prescription or over-the-counter, vitamin supplements, natural or herbal
             supplements) for the prohibited time period.

          5. Been on a diet incompatible with the on-study diet, in the opinion of the Investigator
             or designee, within the 30 days prior to dosing and throughout the study.

          6. Donation of blood or had significant blood loss within 56 days prior to dosing.

          7. Plasma donation within 7 days prior to dosing.

          8. HI participants: Positive result at screening for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).
             Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) positive participants are allowed to enroll if
             hepatitis B virus (HBV) deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) is below 1000 copies/milliliter
             (mL) in the plasma. Participants who are positive for hepatitis C virus antibodies
             (HCVAb) can be enrolled but must not have detectable Hepatitis C virus (HCV)
             ribonucleic acid (RNA) in the plasma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Pharmacology of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hialeah</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orlando Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32809</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Takeda makes patient-level, de-identified data sets and associated documents available after applicable marketing approvals and commercial availability have been received, an opportunity for the primary publication of the research has been allowed, and other criteria have been met as set forth in Takeda's Data Sharing Policy (see www.TakedaClinicalTrials.com/Approach for details). To obtain access, researchers must submit a legitimate academic research proposal for adjudication by an independent review panel, who will review the scientific merit of the research and the requestor's qualifications and conflict of interest that can result in potential bias. Once approved, qualified researchers who sign a data sharing agreement are provided access to these data in a secure research environment.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

