<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04050722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>212537</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04050722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Study Investigating the Efficacy of a Stannous Fluoride Dentifrice in Improving Gingival Health After Twice Daily Use for 3 Weeks</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Examiner Blind, Clinical Study Investigating the Efficacy of a Stannous Fluoride Dentifrice in Improving Gingival Health After 3 Weeks Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the impact of a stannous fluoride containing
      toothpaste in reducing gingivitis when used twice daily for a maximum for 3 weeks, when
      compared to a standard sodium fluoride toothpaste (negative control).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a single center, controlled, single blind (examiner blind), randomized,
      two-treatment arm, parallel design, clinical study in participants (aged 18-65 years), with
      good general health (non-smokers) and generalized mild-moderate plaque-induced gingivitis and
      greater than equal to (&gt;=) 20 natural teeth. The study consists of 4 study visits. At Visit
      1, Screening, after signing informed consent, participants will be assessed for eligibility
      based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria and will undergo oral soft tissue (OST) and oral
      hard tissue (OHT) assessments. Participants will return between 1 and 28 days following the
      screening visit for the Visit 2, baseline where they will undergo, a full OST examination
      followed by assessments of gingival inflammation (MGI), gingival bleeding (BI) and
      supra-gingival plaque (TPI). Eligible participants will be stratified based on gender and
      baseline mean whole mouth MGI score (low: less than equal to (&lt;=) 2.00/High greater than (&gt;)
      2.00), to ensure a balance of gingivitis across both treatment groups and then randomized to
      study product. All randomized participants will receive full mouth dental prophylaxis
      (followed by flossing) to remove sub and supra-gingival calculus, stain, plaque and debris
      from the teeth. All participants will enter the treatment period with no visible plaque
      (TPI=0). After all clinical assessments, participants will be instructed to brush for 1 timed
      minute at site with their assigned study product, after which they will be instructed to
      continue using this twice daily (morning and evening) for 2 weeks. After 2 weeks the
      participants will return to site for their Week 2 (Visit 3) assessments. They will then
      continue using their test dentifrice for a further week and will continue to record all
      brushing events in the diary provided, after which they will return for their Week 3 (Visit
      4) assessments. All assessments will be carried out on the facial and lingual/palatal
      surfaces of each incisor, canine, pre-molar and molar, excluding third molars. After the Week
      3 visit, study closeout procedures will take place and the participant may undergo an
      additional prophylaxis if it is deemed necessary by the examiner. Adverse events and
      incidents will be recorded from informed consent and at the end of each study visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 13, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 13, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Single Blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Bleeding Index at Week 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 3</time_frame>
    <description>Gingival bleeding will be assessed as measure of gingival health for facial and lingual/palatal gingiva of all evaluable teeth, six sites per tooth (mesiobuccal, buccal, distobuccal, mesiolingual/palatal, lingual/palatal and distolingual/palatal), using Bleeding Index (BI). For assessment, a round-end probe will be inserted 1 millimeters (mm) into gingival sulcus, moved around the tooth, from the distal interproximal area to the mesial interproximal area, gently stretching the gingival epithelium. Gingival bleeding will be assessed 30 seconds (secs) after probing (one quadrant at a time); BI scores will be recorded before moving to the next quadrant. Total score range is 0 to 2, where 0=absence of bleeding on probing, 1=bleeding observed within 30 seconds of probing and 2=Bleeding observed immediately on probing (higher score indicating rapid bleeding). The whole mouth means BI score for each subject will be derived from the total BI score divided by the number of tooth sites scored.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Bleeding Index at Week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Gingival bleeding will be assessed as a measure of gingival health for facial and lingual/palatal gingiva of all evaluable teeth, six sites per tooth (mesiobuccal, buccal, distobuccal, mesiolingual/palatal, lingual/palatal and distolingual/palatal), using the BI. For assessment, a round-end probe will be inserted 1mm into gingival sulcus, moved around the tooth, from the distal interproximal area to the mesial interproximal area, gently stretching the gingival epithelium. Gingival bleeding will be assessed 30 secs after probing (one quadrant at a time); BI scores will be recorded before moving to the next quadrant. Total score range is 0 to 2, where 0=absence of bleeding on probing, 1=bleeding observed within 30 seconds of probing and 2=Bleeding observed immediately on probing (higher score indicating rapid bleeding). The whole mouth means BI score for each subject will be derived from the total BI score divided by the number of tooth sites scored.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Number of Bleeding Sites (NBS) at Week 2 and Week 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, Week 3</time_frame>
    <description>The BI scoring system used to measure bleeding sites is as follows: 0= absence of bleeding on probing 1= Bleeding upon probing after 30 seconds; 2= Immediate bleeding observed. The number of bleeding sites is derived from the BI Index where a bleeding site is a site scored as a 1 or 2. For assessment, a round-end probe will be inserted 1mm into gingival sulcus, moved around the tooth, from the distal interproximal area to the mesial interproximal area, gently stretching the gingival epithelium. Gingival bleeding will be assessed 30 secs after probing (one quadrant at a time). Mean of the total number of bleeding sites at Week 2 and Week 3 will be recorded in this outcome measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Modified Gingival Index (MGI) at Week 2 and Week 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, Week 3</time_frame>
    <description>The Modified Gingival Index (MGI) was assessed on facial and lingual/palatal gingiva of all evaluable teeth, 4 sites per tooth (facial surface -papilla and margin; lingual/palatal surface -papilla and margin). The MGI score 0 to 4, where 0 = absence of inflammation; 1 = mild inflammation; slight change in color, little change in color; little change in texture of any portion of the marginal or papillary gingival unit; 2 = mild inflammation; criteria as above but involving the entire marginal or papillar gingival units; 3= moderate inflammation; glazing, redness, edema, and/ or hypertrophy of the marginal or papillary gingival unit; 4 = severe inflammation; marked redness, edema and/or hypertrophy of the marginal or papillary gingival unit, spontaneous bleeding, congestion, or ulceration. The procedure was performed by a single examiner at Week 2 and Week 3. The whole mouth mean MGI will be calculated based on the total mouth MGI score divided by the number of tooth sites assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Turesky Plaque Index (TPI) (overall and interproximal) at Week 2 and Week 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2, Week 3</time_frame>
    <description>Supra-gingival plaque will be assessed on the facial and lingual surfaces of the teeth using the Turesky Plaque Index (TPI). Each tooth surface is divided into 3 areas; three scores are recorded facially (mesiofacial, facial, distofacial) and three scores lingually (mesiolingual, lingual and distolingual) generating a total of six scores per tooth. The plaque will be disclosed and scored for each site from 0 to 5, where 0= no plaque, 1= separate flecks of plaque at the cervical margin, 2= thin continuous band of plaque (up to 1 mm) at the cervical margin, 3= band of plaque wider than 1 mm but covering less than (&lt;) 1/3 of the tooth surface, 4= plaque covering greater than equal to (&gt;=) 1/3 but &lt; 2/3 of the tooth surface and 5= plaque covering ≥ 2/3 of the tooth surface (higher score indicated more plague). Overall TPI score and interproximal TPI score were calculated as the mean TPI over all tooth sites and mean TPI over interproximal sites (distal and mesial) respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Gingivitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Test Product</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with no visible plaque will be instructed to apply full ribbon of the test product (containing 0.454 percent [%] of stannous fluoride] on head of toothbrush provided and brush their teeth for 1 timed minute twice a day (morning and evening), for 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Negative Control Dentifrice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with no visible plaque will be instructed to apply full ribbon of the negative control dentifrice (containing sodium fluoride) on head of toothbrush provided and brush their teeth for 1 timed minute twice a day (morning and evening), for 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sensodyne Repair and Protect</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will brush their teeth with Sensodyne Repair and Protect (containing 0.454% stannous fluoride) for 1 timed minute twice a day (morning and evening), for 3 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Test Product</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colgate Cavity Protection</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will brush their teeth with Colgate Cavity Protection repair and protect (containing sodium fluoride) for 1 timed minute twice a day (morning and evening), for 3 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Negative Control Dentifrice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        An individual must meet all the following inclusion criteria to be eligible for enrollment
        into the study:

          -  Participant provision of a signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the participant has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study before any
             assessment is performed.

          -  A participant who is willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan
             and other study procedures.

          -  A participant in good general and mental health with, in the opinion of the
             investigator or medically qualified designee, no clinically significant or relevant
             abnormalities in medical history or upon oral examination, or condition, that would
             impact the participant's safety, wellbeing or the outcome of the study, if they were
             to participate in the study, or affect the individual's ability to understand and
             follow study procedures and requirements.

          -  A participant at screening (Visit 1) with: a)at least 20 natural permanent teeth
             excluding 3rd molars; b)at least 40 evaluable surfaces (an evaluable surface is
             defined as having 2/3rds of the natural tooth surface gradable for the selected
             clinical indices. The following should not be included in the evaluable surface count-
             third molars; fully crowned/extensively restored, grossly carious, orthodontically
             banded/bonded or abutment teeth; surfaces with calculus deposits which, in the opinion
             of the clinical examiner, would interfere with the baseline assessments of the
             selected clinical indices); or c) participants with generalized mild-moderate
             plaque-induced gingivitis, in the opinion of the clinical examiner, as confirmed by
             visual examinations.

          -  A participant at baseline (prior to dental prophylaxis, (Visit 2) with: a)ongoing hard
             tissue eligibility and, in the opinion of the clinical examiner, at least 40 evaluable
             surfaces; b) mean whole mouth Modified Gingival Index (MGI) greater than equal to (&gt;=)
             1.75 to less than equal to (&lt;=) 2.30; c) mean whole mouth supra-gingival Turesky
             Plaque Index (TPI) score ≥ 1.5; d) ≥ 20 bleeding sites.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        An individual who meets any of the following exclusion criteria will not be eligible for
        enrollment into the study:

          -  A participant who is an employee of the investigational site, either directly involved
             in the conduct of the study or a member of their immediate family; or an employee of
             the investigational site otherwise supervised by the investigator; or, a
             GlaxoSmithKline employee directly involved in the conduct of the study or a member of
             their immediate family.

          -  A participant who has participated in other studies (including non-medicinal studies)
             involving investigational product(s) within 30 days prior to study entry and/or during
             study participation.

          -  A participant with, in the opinion of the investigator or medically qualified
             designee, an acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or
             investigational product administration or may interfere with the interpretation of
             study results and, in the judgment of the investigator or medically qualified
             designee, would make the participant inappropriate for entry into this study.

          -  A participant with, in the opinion of the investigator or medically qualified
             designee, any clinically significant/relevant abnormalities in medical history or oral
             examination, or any other condition, that would affect the individual's ability to
             understand and follow study procedures and requirements.

          -  A participant with any medical condition which, in the opinion of the investigator or
             medically qualified designee, is causing xerostomia.

          -  A participant with any medical condition which in the opinion of the investigator or
             medically qualified designee, could directly influence gingival bleeding.

          -  A participant who is pregnant or intending to become pregnant over the duration of the
             study (self-reported).

          -  A participant who is breastfeeding.

          -  A participant with known or suspected intolerance or hypersensitivity to the study
             materials (or closely related compounds) or any of their stated ingredients.

          -  A participant with recent history (within the last year) of alcohol or other substance
             abuse.

          -  A participant who is a current smoker or an ex- smoker who stopped within 6 months of
             Screening.

          -  A participant who currently uses smokeless forms of tobacco (e.g. chewing tobacco,
             gutkha, pan containing tobacco, nicotine-based e-cigarettes).

          -  A participant with a severe oral condition (e.g. acute necrotizing ulcerative
             gingivitis or oral or peri-oral ulceration including herpetic lesions) that would, in
             the opinion of the investigator, compromise study outcomes or the oral health of the
             participant/ examiner if they were to participate in the study.

          -  A participant who has presence of a tongue or lip piercing, or any other oral feature
             that could interfere with the usage of a toothbrush

          -  A participant who, in the opinion of the investigator or medically qualified designee,
             should not participate in the study.

          -  A participant unwilling or unable to comply with the following Lifestyle
             Considerations (Dental Product/Treatment and Oral Hygiene Restrictions): a) From
             Screening (Visit 1) to the participants' last study visit- i) a participant should not
             carry out any interproximal dental cleaning. Use of dental floss, toothpicks,
             waterpicks or inter-dental brushes is prohibited (except for the removal of impacted
             food with non-antimicrobial products only), ii)participants should not chew gum or
             consume any confectionery containing xylitol (e.g. sugar-free mints), iii)participants
             should delay any non-emergency dental treatment until after study completion
             (including dental prophylaxis); b) From Baseline (Visit 2) to the participants last
             study visit- participants should not use any other oral care products (e.g.
             dentifrices, toothbrushes, mouth rinse) than those provided during the study; c)
             Before clinical efficacy assessment visits: Baseline (Visit 2), Week 2 (Visit 3) and
             Week 3 (Visit 4)- i) participant's should refrain from oral hygiene procedures for 12
             hours (+6 hours, -2 hours) before their visit and attend the study site with overnight
             plaque growth.

          -  A participant that has used an anti-bacterial mouthwash (e.g. chlorhexidine) or use of
             any oral care product that in the view of the investigator could interfere with plaque
             formation or measures of gingivitis, within 14 days of the Baseline visit.

          -  Periodontal Exclusions: a) participant with signs of active periodontitis; b)
             participant with gingivitis which, in the opinion of the investigator, is not expected
             to respond to treatment with an over-the-counter dentifrice; c) A participant who is
             receiving or has received treatment for periodontal disease (including surgery) within
             12 months of Screening.

          -  Dental Exclusions: a) participant with active caries that could, in the opinion of the
             investigator, compromise study outcomes or the oral health of the participant if they
             were to participate in the study; b )participant with dentures (partial or full); c)
             participant with an orthodontic appliance (bands, appliances or fixed/ removable
             retainers); d) A participant who has received orthodontic therapy within 12 months of
             screening; e) participant with numerous restorations in a poor state of repair; f)
             participant with any dental condition (e.g. overcrowding) that could, in the opinion
             of the investigator, compromise study outcomes or the oral health of the participant
             if they were to participate in the study; g) participant who has had dental
             prophylaxis within 12 weeks of Screening, h) participant who has had teeth bleaching
             within 12 weeks of Screening; i) A participant with high levels of extrinsic stain or
             calculus deposits that might interfere with plaque assessments. - Medication
             Exclusions: a )at screening (Visit 1)- i)participant who requires antibiotics prior to
             dental prophylaxis or other dental procedures, ii) participant who is currently taking
             antibiotics, iii) participant who is currently taking an anti-inflammatory medication
             which, in the opinion of the Investigator, could affect gingival condition (e.g.
             ibuprofen), iv) participant who is currently taking anti-coagulant medication which,
             in the opinion of the Investigator, could affect gingival condition (e.g. warfarin),
             v) participant who is currently taking a systemic medication or traditional/herbal
             remedy which, in the opinion of the Investigator, could affect gingival condition
             (e.g. immunosuppressants such as cyclosporine, phenytoin, calcium channel blockers,
             aspirin therapy); b) at baseline (Visit 2)- i) participant who has taken antibiotics
             in the 14 days prior to baseline, ii) participant who has taken an anti-inflammatory
             medication in the 14 days prior to baseline which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             could affect gingival condition (e.g. ibuprofen), iii)participant who has taken
             anti-coagulant medication in the 14 days prior to Baseline which, in the opinion of
             the Investigator, could affect gingival condition (e.g. warfarin), iv)participant who
             has taken a systemic medication or traditional/herbal remedy in the 14 days prior to
             Baseline which, in the opinion of the Investigator, could affect gingival condition
             (e.g. immunosuppressants such as cyclosporine, phenytoin, calcium channel blockers,
             aspirin therapy), v) participant who has used an antibacterial dentifrice or mouth
             rinse in the period between Screening and Baseline.

          -  Any participant who has previously been enrolled in this study.

          -  Participants who, in the judgement of the investigator, or medically qualified
             designee should not participate on the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89146</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingivitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Listerine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Fluoride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD for this study will be made available via the Clinical Study Data Request site.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>IPD will be made available within 6 months of publishing the results of the primary endpoints of the study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access is provided after a research proposal is submitted and has received approval from the Independent Review Panel and after a Data Sharing Agreement is in place. Access is provided for an initial period of 12 months but an extension can be granted, when justified, for up to another 12 months.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://clinicalstudydatarequest.com</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

