<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04055493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WSG-AM08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04055493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adj. Marker-adjusted Personalized Therapy Comparing ET+Ribociclib vs Chemotherapy in Intermediate Risk, HR+/HER2- EBC</brief_title>
  <acronym>ADAPTcycle</acronym>
  <official_title>Adjuvant Dynamic Marker - Adjusted Personalized Therapy Comparing Endocrine Therapy Plus Ribociclib Versus Chemotherapy in Intermediate Risk, HR+/HER2- Early Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>West German Study Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genomic Health®, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>West German Study Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study investigates, whether the patient group with intermediate-risk early breast cancer
      benefits from treatment with ribociclib in combination with endocrine therapy compared to
      standard-of-care chemotherapy (followed by adjuvant endocrine therapy).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The WSG ADAPT trial program is one of the first new generation trials addressing the issue of
      individualization of (neo)-adjuvant decision-making in early breast cancer (EBC) in a
      subtype-specific manner. The first WSG ADAPT umbrella trial (NCT01779206) aimed to establish
      early predictive molecular surrogate markers for response after a short 3-week induction
      treatment.

      The goals of the WSG ADAPT trial program - early response assessment and subtype-specific
      therapy tailoring to those patients who are most likely to benefit - have contributed to the
      very positive national and international feedback to the ADAPT concept as a whole.

      The aim of this ADAPTcycle phase-III-trial is to investigate whether the intermediate-risk
      patient group identified during the screening phase derives additional benefit from treatment
      with ribociclib in combination with ET compared to chemotherapy (followed by adjuvant ET).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multicenter, interventional, prospective, two-arm, randomized, open-label, controlled (neo)adjuvant, phase-III trial evaluating the efficacy and safety of ribociclib combined with endocrine therapy (ET) versus standard-of-care chemotherapy in early breast cancer (EBC) patients with molecular HR+/HER2- subtype.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>invasive disease-free survival (iDFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>superiority in invasive disease-free survival (iDFS) of ribociclib + ET vs. standard-of-care chemotherapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>distant disease-free survival (dDFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>distant disease-free survival (dDFS) in the ribociclib + ET-group to demonstrate survival rate &gt;92%</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival (OS) 95 % CI</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>95 %-confidence interval (CI) for OS in both arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>distant disease-free survival (dDFS) 95 % CI</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>95 %-confidence interval (CI) for dDFS in both arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QoL</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>quality of life (QoL) and correlation to treatment-related symptoms measured by EQ-VAS and triggered symptom questionnaire,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>treatment adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>treatment adherence measured by drug intake compared between treatment arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pathological complete response (pCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Pathological response rate (defined as ypT0/is/ypN0), as well as further definitions (ypT0/ypN0; ypT0/is/any ypN, near pCR (ypT1a/any ypN)), in neoadjuvant treated patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>clinical response rate (by palpation, ultrasound, and further methods) compared between treatment arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>rate of breast-conservation therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>at end of study, on average 5 years after start of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>prevalence of breast conservation therapy vs. mastectomy compared between treatment arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1670</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Female</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ribociclib plus ET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ribociclib 600mg / day over 26 cycles + endocrine treatment of physician´s choice</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard-of-care chemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard-of-care chemotherapy according to the clinical guidelines, e.g., of the Breast Committee of the German Gynecological Oncology Group (AGO), and regional prescribing information depending on patient's needs for 16-24 weeks,</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ribociclib 200Mg Oral Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>3 x 200 MG per os</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ribociclib plus ET</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kisqali</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients eligible for inclusion in this study have to meet all of the following criteria:

        A. Prior to REGISTRATION in the study:

        1. Written informed consent prior to any screening procedures. 2. Female. 3. ≥ 18 years of
        age. 4a. EITHER: (Post)menopausal status at the time of initiation of (neo)adjuvant study
        medication

          -  patient underwent bilateral oophorectomy, or

          -  age ≥ 60, or

          -  age &lt; 60 and amenorrhea for 12 or more months (in the absence of chemotherapy,
             tamoxifen, toremifene, or ovarian suppression) and/or FSH and estradiol in the
             postmenopausal range per local normal range.

             4b. OR: Pre-menopausal patients:

          -  confirmed negative serum pregnancy test (β-hCG) before starting study treatment, or

          -  patient has had a hysterectomy. 5. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of primary
             estrogen-receptor positive and/or progesterone-receptor positive (&gt; 1%) early breast
             cancer by local laboratory.

             6. Patient has HER2-negative breast cancer defined as

          -  a negative in-situ hybridization test or an IHC status of 0, 1+, or 2+,

          -  if IHC is 2+, a negative in-situ hybridization (FISH, CISH, or SISH) test is required
             (based on the most recently analyzed tissue sample and all tested by a local
             laboratory).

             7. Local therapy of breast cancer (if adjuvant treatment or planned if neoadjuvant
             treatment) according to current guidelines.

        Note: This may include radiotherapy of breast cancer.

        B. Prior to RANDOMIZATION in the study 8. No evidence of distant metastasis (confirmed
        prior to randomization by, preferentially, CT thorax / abdomen, X-ray chest, ultrasound
        liver, bone scan, or PET-CT).

        9. Patient has available tumor tissue from diagnostic biopsy. 10. Patient is classified as
        intermediate risk according to the ADAPT intermediate-risk definition (i) (as follows), or
        (only in case of missing Oncotype DX or Ki-67 response data), according to the clinical
        intermediate-risk definition (ii) (as follows).

        (i). ADAPT intermediate-risk definition: Patient meets one of the following criteria:

          -  c/pN0, RS ≤ 25 with luminal-B-like (Ki-67 ≥20% or G3) or c/pT2-4 without endocrine
             response (post-endocrine Ki-67 &gt; 10 %)

          -  c/pN1, RS ≤ 25 without endocrine response (post-endocrine Ki-67 &gt; 10 %)

          -  c/pN0, RS &gt; 25 with luminal-B-like (Ki-67 ≥20% or G3) or c/pT2-4 with endocrine
             response (Ki-67 ≤ 10 %)

          -  c/pN1, RS &gt; 25 with endocrine response (Ki-67 ≤ 10 %)

          -  c/pN2-3, RS ≤ 25 with endocrine response (Ki-67 ≤ 10 %). Note: Postmenopausal patients
             with pT1-2/pN0 disease and RS &lt; 25, as well as premenopausal patients with pT1-2/pN0
             disease and RS&lt;16, are recommended to be treated by endocrine therapy alone and not to
             be randomized (at investigator´s discretion).

        (ii). Clinical intermediate-risk definition (ascertained by investigator): Clinical
        intermediate risk may be ascertained by the investigator prior to randomization if at
        maximum two of the following three risk factors are present (according to primary diagnosis
        / 1st sample):

          1. cT2-4

          2. c/pN positive

          3. G3 and / or Ki-67 ≥ 20% Note: Inclusion of a patient according to &quot;clinical
             intermediate risk&quot; is permitted only in case of missing baseline Oncotype DX® or Ki-67
             decrease. In this case, investigators will follow a risk-based, step-wise assessment
             process.

        11. No contraindication for (neo)-adjuvant ET. 12. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group
        (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1. 13. Patient has adequate bone marrow and organ function
        as defined by the following laboratory values:

          -  absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5 × 109/L,

          -  platelets ≥ 100 × 109/L,

          -  hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL,

          -  estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) ≥ 30 mL/min by a Cockcroft-Gault formula,

          -  INR ≤ 1.5,

          -  serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL,

          -  total bilirubin &lt; ULN, except for patients with Gilbert's Syndrome who may only be
             included if the total bilirubin is ≤ 3.0 × ULN or direct bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × ULN,

          -  aspartate transaminase (AST) &lt; 2.5 × ULN,

          -  alanine transaminase (ALT) &lt; 2.5 × ULN. 14. 2-lead-ECG (CANKADO) with:

          -  QTcF interval at screening &lt; 450 msec (using Fridericia's correction),

          -  mean resting heart rate 50-90 bpm (determined from the ECG). 15. Ability to swallow
             ribociclib tablets or to administer other study medication, respectively.

             16. Ability to communicate with the investigator and comply with study procedures.

             17. Willing to remain during therapy at the clinical site, as required by the
             protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients eligible for inclusion in this study must not meet any of the following criteria:

          1. Patient with distant metastases of breast cancer beyond regional lymph nodes.

          2. Patient has received prior (neo)-adjuvant treatment with chemotherapy, ET, or any
             CDK4/6 inhibitor for breast cancer.

          3. Patient has received tamoxifen, raloxifene, or aromatase inhibitors (AIs) for
             reduction in risk (&quot;chemoprevention&quot;) of breast cancer and/or treatment for
             osteoporosis within last 2 years prior to screening.

          4. Patient has received prior neoadjuvant/adjuvant treatment with anthracyclines at
             cumulative doses of 450 mg/m² or more for doxorubicin or 900 mg/m² or more for
             epirubicin.

          5. Patient with a known hypersensitivity to any of the excipients of ribociclib, ET, or
             standard-of-care chemotherapy.

          6. Patient with inflammatory breast cancer at screening.

          7. Patient is concurrently using other anti-cancer therapy.

          8. Patient has had major surgery within 14 days prior to starting study drug or has not
             recovered from major side effects.

          9. Patient is currently receiving warfarin or other coumarin-derived anti-coagulant for
             treatment, prophylaxis, or otherwise.

         10. Patient has not recovered from clinical and laboratory acute toxicities related to
             prior anticancer therapies to NCI CTCAE version 5.0 Grade ≤ 1.

         11. Patient has a concurrent malignancy, or malignancy within 5 years of randomization, or
             known history of invasive breast cancer.

         12. Patient has impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of the study drugs (e.g., uncontrolled ulcerative
             diseases, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or
             small-bowel resection).

         13. Patient has a known history of HIV infection.

         14. Patient has known active hepatitis-B-virus (HBV) or hepatitis-C-virus (HCV) infection.

         15. Patient has any other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical condition that
             would, in the investigator´s judgment, cause unacceptable safety risks, contraindicate
             patient participation in the clinical study, or compromise compliance with the
             protocol (e.g., chronic pancreatitis, chronic active hepatitis, active untreated or
             uncontrolled fungal, bacterial, or viral infections, etc.).

         16. Clinically significant, uncontrolled heart disease and/or cardiac repolarization
             abnormality, including any of the following:

               -  history of myocardial infarction (MI), angina pectoris, symptomatic pericarditis,
                  or coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) within 6 months prior to study entry,

               -  documented cardiomyopathy,

               -  left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50 % as determined by multiple gated
                  acquisition (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram (ECHO),

               -  long QT syndrome, family history of idiopathic sudden death, congenital long QT
                  syndrome, or any of the following:

                    -  risk factors for Torsades de Pointe (TdP) including uncorrected hypokalemia
                       or hypomagnesemia, history of cardiac failure, or history of clinically
                       significant/ symptomatic bradycardia,

                    -  concomitant medications with a known risk to prolong the QT interval and/or
                       known to cause Torsades de Pointe that cannot be discontinued or replaced by
                       safe alternative medication (e.g., within 5 half-lives or 7 days prior to
                       starting study drug),

                    -  inability to determine the QTcF interval,

                    -  clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias (e.g., ventricular tachycardia),
                       complete left-bundle branch block, high-grade AV block (e.g., bifascicular
                       block, Mobitz type II, and 3rd-degree AV block),

                    -  systolic blood pressure (SBP) &gt; 160 or &lt; 90 mmHg.

         17. Patient is currently receiving any of the following substances, which cannot be
             discontinued 7 days prior to Cycle 1 Day 1:

               -  concomitant medications, herbal supplements, fruits (e.g. grapefruit,
                  pomegranates, pomelos, star fruit, Seville oranges) and their juices that are
                  strong inducers or inhibitors of CYP3A4/5,

               -  medications that have a narrow therapeutic window and are predominantly
                  metabolized through CYP3A4/5.

         18. Patient is currently receiving or has received systemic corticosteroids ≤ 2 weeks
             prior to starting study drug, or who have not fully recovered from side effects of
             such treatment.

         19. Participation in a prior investigational study within 30 days prior to enrollment or
             within five half-lives of the investigational product, whichever is longer.

         20. Not able to understand and to comply with study instructions and requirements.

         21. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) woman.

         22. Woman of child-bearing potential defined as woman physiologically capable of becoming
             pregnant, unless she is using highly effective methods of contraception during the
             study treatment and for 21 days after stopping the treatment:

               -  total abstinence (when this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of
                  the patient).

               -  female sterilization (have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy with or without
                  hysterectomy), total hysterectomy, or tubal ligation at least 6 weeks before
                  taking study treatment.

               -  male partner sterilization (at least 6 months prior to study screening). For
                  female patients on the study, the vasectomized male partner should be the sole
                  partner for that patient.

               -  placement of an intrauterine device (IUD).

         23. Use of oral (estrogen and progesterone), transdermal, injected, or implanted hormonal
             methods of contraception as well as hormonal replacement therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pre- and postmenopausal women 18 years or older.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nadia Harbeck, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ludwigs-Maximilians-University Munich, Breast Cancer Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anja Braschoss, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49-176-82119153</phone>
    <email>anja.braschoss@wsg-online.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julian Moellers</last_name>
    <phone>+49-2161-56623</phone>
    <phone_ext>11</phone_ext>
    <email>julian.moellers@wsg-online.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum der Universität München Klinik und Poliklinik für Frauenheilkunde und Geburtshilfe, Brustzentrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>80337</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nadia Harbeck, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49-89-440054170</phone>
      <email>nadia.harbeck@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rachel Würstlein, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49-89-440054170</phone>
      <email>Rachel.wuerstlein@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Aachen, Frauenklinik - Senologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aachen</city>
        <state>NRW</state>
        <zip>52074</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katja Krauss, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49-241-8080700</phone>
      <email>kkrauss@ukaachen.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kliniken Essen-Mitte, Klinik für Senologie/Interdisziplinäres Brustzentrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <state>NRW</state>
        <zip>45136</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sherko Kuemmel, PD Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49-201-17433005</phone>
      <email>s.kuemmel@kliniken-essen-mitte.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dorothea Schindowski</last_name>
      <phone>+49-201-17433005</phone>
      <email>d.schindowski@kliniken-essen-mitte.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Praxis für gynäkologische Onkologie am Ev. Krankenhaus Bethesda</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moenchengladbach</city>
        <state>NRW</state>
        <zip>41061</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monika Graeser, PD Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49-2161-8493577</phone>
      <email>monika.graeser@brustzentrum-rhein-ruhr.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Raquel von Schumann, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>+49-2161-8493577</phone>
      <email>raquel.vonSchumann@brustzentrum-rhein-ruhr.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>early breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>ADAPT</keyword>
  <keyword>endocrine therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>ribociclib</keyword>
  <keyword>intermediate risk</keyword>
  <keyword>HER2 negative</keyword>
  <keyword>HR positive</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The sponsor is committed to following high ethical standards for reporting study results, including the timely communication and publication of clinical trial results, whatever their outcome. The sponsor assures that the key design elements of this protocol will be posted on a publicly accessible database, e.g., www.clinicaltrials.gov, before study start.
As part of its commitment to full transparency in publications, the sponsor supports the full disclosure of all funding sources for the study and publications, as well as any actual and potential conflicts of interest of financial and non-financial nature by all authors, including medical writing / editorial support, if applicable.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Within 1 year after end of study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>for regulatory use only</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

