<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04059016</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTN0090 STU-2019-0743</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UG1DA020024</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04059016</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Innovatively Increasing PCP Prescribing of Buprenorphine: Measurement Based Care and Integrated Electronic Solution</brief_title>
  <acronym>MBC4OUD</acronym>
  <official_title>NIDA CTN Protocol 0090 Innovatively Increasing PCP Prescribing of Buprenorphine: Measurement Based Care and Integrated Electronic Solution (MBC4OUD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this observational feasibility project is to assess the feasibility and
      acceptability of universal screening and measurement based care for opioid use disorder (OUD)
      utilizing a computer software program in a network of primary care clinics currently
      utilizing this software for screening and measurement based care (MBC) for the treatment of
      depression. The primary objective of this project is to evaluate the feasibility of screening
      and MBC for OUD in our partner primary care clinics. The secondary objective of this project
      is to evaluate the acceptability of universal screening and measurement based care of OUD,
      including the barriers and facilitators of screening for OUD and providing buprenorphine
      treatment in primary care, changes in provider knowledge and beliefs regarding diagnosis and
      treatment of OUD, and treatment program outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational feasibility project evaluating the impact of universal screening and
      enhanced access to care for patients with opioid use disorder via development and
      implementation of web-based software program that provides clinical decision support to
      primary care providers for the diagnosis and treatment of opioid use disorder (OUD) with
      buprenorphine. The key facets of measurement based care (MBC) for OUD will be supported by
      the software: (1) screening instrument used for all patients, (2) diagnostic instrument for
      patients who screen positive, and (3) buprenorphine treatment algorithm for those with
      diagnosed OUD. The MBC for OUD software will be offered to clinics in the University of Texas
      Southwestern Medical Center (UTSW) North Texas Community Based Primary Care Network. Clinics
      in the Network currently utilize VitalSign6, a software program that implements universal
      screening for depressive symptoms and provides electronic clinical decision support for
      measurement based care (MBC) for major depression. The VitalSign6 team provides training on
      how to clinically diagnose and manage major depression, training on the software, and expert
      clinical support during implementation.

      Clinics in the Network will be offered the opportunity to utilize the newly developed VS6 OUD
      diagnosis and treatment module. Network clinics that take part in this project will be
      provided training in the diagnosis and management of OUD and federally-mandated training in
      the use of buprenorphine for OUD. The primary outcome will be the number of primary care
      providers trained to prescribe buprenorphine for OUD (i.e., complete waiver training). The
      providers and staff at clinics who choose to utilize the newly developed VS6 OUD module
      (i.e., MBC4OUD) will be invited to participate in a research project assessing acceptability
      of the diagnosis and treatment of OUD in primary care.. Focus groups will be utilized to
      assess stakeholder barriers to implementation of buprenorphine treatment for OUD and
      strategies for overcoming these barriers. Providers at clinics taking part in the project
      will be surveyed regarding their beliefs and comfort level with OUD diagnosis and treatment
      at 3 time-points: pre-training, post-training (i.e., prior to software dissemination to the
      clinic when the observation period begins), and at the end of the observation period. All
      data from providers will be collected anonymously. De-identified patient level data will be
      analyzed for the purpose of program evaluation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>% of primary care providers completing buprenorphine waiver training</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of primary care providers who complete buprenorphine waiver training divided by the divided by the number of providers who indicate a desire/willingness to be trained will be computed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinic Interest Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of Network clinics who accept the OUD module divided by the number of clinics that were approached.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Provider Buprenorphine Waiver Training Completion Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of providers in Network clinics who complete buprenorphine waiver training divided by the number of providers who indicated desire/willingness to complete the buprenorphine waiver training.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OUD Module Training Completion Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of providers who complete the VS6 OUD module training divided by the number of providers who indicated desire/willingness to complete the VS6 OUD module training.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Buprenorphine Treatment Acceptability Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Buprenorphine Treatment Acceptability Scale has been created by the investigators for this study. It is a 29-item self report measure. Items 1-27 are assessed on 1-5 Likert scale, with 1=strongly disagree and 5=strongly agree. Items 28 and 29 are scored on a scale of 0-100, with higher scores indicating greater confidence. Items on the scale assess provider motivation for providing treatment for opioid use disorder, provider self-efficacy for the treatment of opioid use disorder, and challenges faced by providers in treating opioid use disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Abuse and Addiction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MBC4OUD</intervention_name>
    <description>This computer software program consists of patient-completed self reports for screening and diagnosis of opioid use disorder among primary care patients and provides web-based clinical decision support to primary care providers for provision of pharmacotherapy for opioid use disorder.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Providers and clinical staff from clinics in the University of Texas Southwestern Medical
        Center (UTSW) North Texas Community Based Primary Care Network that currently utilize
        VitalSign6, a software program that implements universal screening for depressive symptoms
        and provides electronic clinical decision support for measurement based care (MBC) for
        major depression.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Providers and clinical staff from UTSW clinics currently utilizing the VitalSign6
             software program

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Madhukar H Trivedi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Madhukar H. Trivedi, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>opioid use disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>buprenorphine waiver training</keyword>
  <keyword>VitalSign6</keyword>
  <keyword>measurement based care</keyword>
  <keyword>primary care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be transmitted to the NIDA central data repository as requested by NIDA. The data management team will conduct final data quality assurance checks and &quot;lock&quot; the database from further modification. The final analysis dataset will be returned to NIDA, as requested, for storage and archive.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

