<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04058574</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO-ACL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04058574</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Proprioceptive Isokinetic Repositioning, Functional Testing, and a Self-reported Questionnaire Before and After Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRO-ACL</acronym>
  <official_title>Measurement and Relationships of Proprioceptive Isokinetic Repositioning With Muscle Strength, Functional Testing, and Self-reported Questionaires Before and After Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction: A Prospective Study With 12-months Post Operative Follow-up.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Caen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Caen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospectively study aims to evaluate the evolution of knee joint proprioception on
      isokinetic dynamometer before and after Anterior Cruciate Ligament (ACL) reconstruction and
      its relationships with muscle strength, self reported questionnaire and return to sport. This
      study will include 30 athletes with isolated ACL rupture, and treated with ACL reconstruction
      surgery and 15 healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) rupture is a common injury in athletes. It has multiple
      consequences on the knee: instability, pain, loss of muscle strength, proprioceptive
      impairments, modification of the knee kinematics and premature knee osteoarthritis. In
      athletes, the majority of these injuries are treated with ACL reconstruction surgery. The
      main objective of this treatment is the reduction of knee instability to allow return to
      sport, and this at the same level prior to the injury. Thus, the athlete's follow-up after
      the surgery is essential to guide the return to sport and to ensure that the knee
      sensorimotor control allows the return to sport. Currently this assessment is based primarily
      on functional testings and measurement of muscle strength.

      The investigators propose to prospectively study the evolution of instrumentally measured
      knee proprioception using isokinetic dynamometer before and after ACL reconstruction as well
      as a study of the factors associated with its favorable evolution and its impact in the
      return to sport and its level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Intervention Group &quot;ACL&quot;: 30 patient, athletes, with ACL deficiency candidate to a surgical ACL reconstruction Control Group: 15 healthy volunteers, athletes.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline passive proprioceptive evaluation after 7 months</measure>
    <time_frame>ACL group: 6 weeks after surgery and 7 months after surgery; Healthy group: one evaluation at a single point in time through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of knee proprioception by the passive repositioning technique (JPS, in degrees) on isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline active proprioceptive evaluation after 7 months</measure>
    <time_frame>ACL group: 6 weeks after surgery and 7 months after surgery; Healthy group: one evaluation at a single point in time through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of knee proprioception by the active repositioning technique (JPS, in degrees) on isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline TDPM (Threshold to Detection of Passive Motion) evaluation after 7 months</measure>
    <time_frame>ACL group: 6 weeks after surgery and 7 months after surgery; Healthy group: one evaluation at a single point in time through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of knee proprioception by the Threshold to Detection of Passive Motion (TDPM in degrees) on isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>ACL group: Two evaluations on both injured and healthy knees: (1) 3 months after surgery and (2) 7 months after surgery; Healthy group: one evaluation at a single point in time through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of knee extensors and flexors peak strength (in newton.meter, Nm) on isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ACL-RSI questionnaire (Anterior Cruciate Ligament-Return to Sport after Injury)</measure>
    <time_frame>ACL group: Four evaluations on both injured and healthy knees: (1) 2 weeks before surgery, (2) 3 months after surgery, (3) 7 months after surgery and (4) 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The ACL-RSI measures the patient's understanding of his knee. It comprises 12 questions with a score of 1 to 10 for each</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional testing</measure>
    <time_frame>ACL group: Two evaluations on both injured and healthy knees: (1) 3 months after surgery and (2) 7 months after surgery; Healthy group: one evaluation at a single point in time through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Hop test. Single hop: Patients are instructed to stand on one leg and perform 1 jump as far as possible, landing on the same leg.
The total distance is recorded (in cm) .Triple hop: Patients are instructed to stand on one leg and perform 3 hops as far as possible, landing on the same leg.
The total distance for 3 consecutive hops is recorded (in cm). Cross-over hop test : The patient hops forward 3 times while alternately crossing over a marking The patient is instructed to position themselves such that the first of the 3 hops was lateral with respect to the direction of crossover The total distance hopped forward is recorded (in cm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>ACL Tear</condition>
  <condition>ACL - Anterior Cruciate Ligament Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention Group &quot;ACL&quot;: 30 patient, athletes, with ACL deficiency candidate to a surgical ACL reconstruction</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control Group: 15 healthy volunteers, athletes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Proprioception measurement on isokinetic dynamometer</intervention_name>
    <description>Proprioception measurement on isokinetic dynamometer using joint position sense (JPS) and the threshold to detection of passive motion (TTDPM)</description>
    <arm_group_label>ACL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Isolated and primary tear of the ACL

          -  Individual candidate for an ACL reconstruction surgery.

          -  Acute ACL injury (&lt;6 weeks)

          -  Athletes (person who competes in one or more sports that involve physical strength,
             speed or endurance) whatever their level of sport practice

          -  Internet access

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior knee surgery

          -  Complex ligamentous lesion (lateral ligaments, posterior cruciate ligament)

          -  Surgery for meniscal lesions (patients initially included but warranting meniscal
             surgery during arthroscopy will be secondarily excluded from the study.)

          -  Recent muscle damage

          -  History of significant injury on the healthy knee

          -  ACL rupture recurrence

          -  Pregnant woman

          -  Neurological or vestibular antecedent with sequelae

          -  Individuals taking treatment altering alertness (neuroleptics, sedatives)

          -  Informed consent not obtained
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joffrey DRIGNY, MD MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+332 31 06 45 33</phone>
    <email>drigny-j@chu-caen.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Caen University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joffrey DRIGNY, MD MSc</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Caen University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joffrey Drigny, MD MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+33231064533</phone>
      <email>drigny-j@chu-caen.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital, Caen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joffrey DRIGNY</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Resident PM&amp;R and Sport departments MD, MSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anterior Cruciate Ligament Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

