<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04050995</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TCT 021</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>167534</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04050995</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the MuSICCA for Measuring Awareness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Validity, Reliability, and Clinical Utility of the Music Therapy Sensory Instrument for Cognition, Consciousness and Awareness (MuSICCA) in Children and Youth With Prolonged Disorders of Consciousness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Children's Trust, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Temple University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Children's Trust, United Kingdom</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prolonged Disorders Of Consciousness (PDOC) include the Vegetative State (VS) and the
      Minimally Conscious State (MCS) that persist for longer than four weeks. This research seeks
      to evaluate the validity (accuracy), reliability, and clinical utility (usefulness to
      clinicians) of the children's version of the Music Therapy Assessment Tool for Awareness in
      Disorders of Consciousness (MATADOC). The paediatric version is called the Music therapy
      Sensory Instrument for Cognition, Consciousness and Awareness (MuSICCA). The MATADOC is known
      to be accurate in diagnosis and has been shown to be clinically useful when working with
      adults. However, currently, there are no equivalent measures that have been rigorously tested
      for working with children. Therefore, there is a significant need for a valid and reliable
      measure, especially when the consequences of misdiagnosis include insufficient care
      provision, unsuitable treatment programmes, poor identification of intentions to communicate,
      and insufficient evidence for making difficult decisions around withdrawal of hydration and
      nutrition.

      The study will invite participants aged 2-18 years, who the medical team suspect of having a
      PDOC, from various medical facilities in the UK, Ireland and other English-speaking
      countries. Parental/carer consent will be required for inclusion in the study.

      Data collection will occur over 2 years. Each participant will be involved once for a maximum
      of 8 assessment sessions (2 for each measure used). The MuSICCA assessment protocol involves
      presenting musical stimuli in three modalities (visual, auditory, and tactile). The
      participants will be instructed to respond to stimuli and commands. Sessions will be recorded
      using audio-visual equipment and physical responses will be noted on documentation. The
      information gained will inform diagnosis and treatment. The participants' behaviours will
      also be scored on the Coma Recovery Scale - Revised (CRS-R) (the gold standard for diagnosis
      of DOC in adults), the Coma/Near Coma Scale (CNC) and the Nociception Coma Scale Revised
      (NCS-R).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The null hypotheses are as follows:

      The MuSICCA is not a valid tool for use with children and young people with Disorders Of
      Consciousness (DOC).

      The MuSICCA is not a reliable tool for use with children and young people with DOC.

      The MuSICCA is not a clinical useful tool for use with children and young people with DOC.

      The design has been chosen to test the validity and reliability of the MuSICCA. It will
      involve carrying out the two measures and comparing their results against the current gold
      standard (the Coma Recovery Scale-Revised) and the Coma-Near Coma Scale. The design is
      influenced by previous validation studies of these measures conducted with adults.

      There will be no control group because this is not a Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) and,
      therefore, no recruited participant will be deprived of the potential benefits of the
      measures. All participants will receive intervention through the administration of the
      protocols of the assessment measures.

      The study intends to recruit 80 participants. Recruitment will involve the following
      procedure. Medical/clinical teams at each site will identify potential participants according
      to the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The participants' families will be contacted to
      invite them to a meeting to discuss the research. It will be made clear that there will be no
      obligation to attend the meeting and their care or treatment will not be reduced or withdrawn
      if they decide not to be involved in the study. Interested families will be informed about
      the research project at this initial meeting. This information will be delivered verbally in
      person by the assessing clinicians and the families will be given a participant information
      sheet, which will contain all the information about the research so that the family can think
      in their own time about the decision to involve their child. The information given will
      include: 1)what will be carried out during the assessments, 2)how data will be recorded
      (observation recording sheets, video recording), 3)how the data will be stored, 4)what the
      data will be used for, and 5)what will be done with the data when the study has finished. The
      information sheet will also contain information about the families' right to withdraw their
      child from the study at any time without consequence.

      The families will also be given the opportunity to ask questions so that they are satisfied
      that they understand why the research is being conducted, what the research will involve, and
      the extent of their child's involvement in the study if recruited.

      Data collection will take place over a 2-year period at sites in the United Kingdom (UK),
      United States, and other English-speaking countries, e.g. Australia, Canada and New Zealand.

      The data will consist of hand scored forms of the assessment tools and audio-visual
      recordings of the MuSICCA sessions. These recordings will be used to test the reliability of
      the MuSICCA between assessors and between assessment sessions.The selection and allocation of
      video recordings of sessions for inter-rater reliability will be carried out to control for
      differences of experience between assessing clinicians.

      In order to eliminate researcher bias, data will be collated by a research assistant and
      statistical analysis will be undertaken by an independent statistician. In order to eliminate
      bias during data collection, there will be no interim data analysis and data collectors
      (clinicians) will not be able to discuss with each other the findings of their assessments
      until after the assessments have been completed and the results submitted to the research
      assistant.

      Clinical utility of the MuSICCA will be evaluated using a questionnaire for each family and
      each assessing clinician using the tool. After each MuSICCA report is submitted and feedback
      given to the families, assessing clinicians and families will be asked to complete a short
      questionnaire to assess the clinical utility of the MuSICCA.

      Data storage Raw data (score forms and video recordings) will be stored on a secure
      cloud-based system. Access to the data will be managed and authorised by the Chief
      Investigator.

      Data analysis will be carried out by an independent statistician.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Weeks</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Music therapy Sensory Instrument for Cognition, Consciousness and Awareness</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of awareness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Coma Recovery Scale - Revised</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic tool for disorders of consciousness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coma Near Coma Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic tool for disorders of consciousness. Measuring wakefulness and awareness using sensory stimulation and ratings form responses.
It is a scale comprised of 11 items with ratings for responses (0, 2, 4; 0 representing higher level response and 4 representing no response). The total score is calculated by adding the ratings and dividing by the number of items scored. Lower numbers indicate greater awareness/consciousness. The ranges are as follows:
0.00-0.89 indicates NO COMA
0.90-2.00 indicates NEAR COMA
2.01-2.89 indicates MODERATE COMA
2.90-3.49 indicates MARKED COMA
3.50-4.00 indicates EXTREME COMA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nociception Coma Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment tool for measuring responses to potentially painful care and/or stimulation of a potentially painful area. It is a scale comprised of 3 items (motor response, verbal response, and facial expression). Ratings consist of 0, 1, 2, 3, with higher ratings indicating higher level responses.The total score is calculated summing the subscores. The total score range is 0-9. A total score equal to or above 4 suggests the presence of pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Disorder of Consciousness</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children and young people aged 2-18 years with a suspected disorder of consciousness. They
        will be identified by the treating clinical team initially.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 2-18 years of age

          -  Assessed by the interdisciplinary team as having a disorder of consciousness

          -  Be under active investigation for diagnosis of DOC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hearing impairments

          -  Known profound visual impairments

          -  Known musicogenic epilepsy

          -  Seizure disorders that cause frequent and/or prolonged seizures

          -  English not first language
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Consciousness Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

