<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04052269</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19/WE/5104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04052269</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phosphodiesterase Inhibitors in Glaucoma Study (PhiGS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PhiGS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study to Investigate the Effect of Phosphodiesterase Inhibitors on Chorioretinal Blood Flow Using Optical Coherence Tomography Angiography.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is commonly known that high eye pressure is associated with glaucoma. However, there is
      also a theory that poor circulation to the eye is a contributing factor. Therefore, if we can
      increase the flow of blood to the eye, we may be able to stop people losing vision from this
      disease.

      Phosphodiesterase inhibitors (for example sildenafil, tadalafil, Viagra®, Cialis®) are drugs
      used to improve blood flow to certain parts of the body. They are commonly used on an ad-hoc
      basis to treat erectile dysfunction, in addition to problems with blood circulation to the
      lungs, fingers and toes.

      The majority of previous work in this field has been completed using insensitive, poorly
      reproducible techniques such as colour doppler ultrasound. Since then, a new imaging modality
      able to image blood flow in blood vessels without the need for the injection of contrast has
      entered clinical use.

      This initial pilot study is designed as a proof-of-concept study to investigate whether we
      can measure detectable changes in the blood flow to the retina and choroid at the back of the
      eye following ingestion of a phosphodiesterase inhibitor medication by healthy and
      glaucomatous volunteers already taking this medication for erectile dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypotheses

      This study is examining the hypothesis that Phosphodiesterase inhibitors increase
      chorio-retinal blood flow; in other words, we hypothesise that drugs like Viagra that have a
      known effect of generally increasing circulation may also increase the blood flow in the back
      of the eye -retina, with possible beneficial effect.

      Study design

      This is a small pilot study which is not expected to produce a definitive answer to our
      question -however, if successful this study will enable us to progress to a larger study that
      will have much more data to base our conclusions on.

      Our present study will, therefore, examine both healthy and glaucomatous eyes with regards to
      the level of blood flow in the retina - something that can be measured using optical
      coherence tomography (OCT), a safe and non-invasive procedure which has been in use as part
      of the standard of care for some time.

      Estimated Timeline

      Ethics assessment - April 2019 Patient recruitment - June to Sep 2019 Study period - May 2019
      to Jan 2020

      Setting

      Patient encounters will take place at either the eye clinic, level 1, Charing Cross Hospital,
      or the iCORG clinical trials unit, Western Eye Hospital.

      Encounter 1 - As part of the routine clinic visit potentially eligible patients will be
      approached by the members of the regular care team and study discussed with those who are
      interested. Patients who are comfortable to proceed (have discussed the study in detail with
      the doctor and have had their questions answered satisfactorily)will provide consent which
      will be documented in writing; those who wish to have more time will be afforded as much time
      as they need to decide whether or not to participate.

      Once the patient has consented to participate, the following study procedures will be done as
      part of that visit:

      Baseline assessment Medical history Baseline assessment Ophthalmic history Baseline
      assessment Drug history Baseline assessment Allergy history - all of the above will be
      assessed by the study doctor

      Baseline assessment Visual acuity - patient reads letters from a chart 10 feet (3 meters)
      away to ascertain the quality of vision Baseline assessment Visual field test -non-invasive
      test where the study doctor examines how much 'side' vision patient has using a computerized
      machine. Lights are flashed on, and patient has to press a button whenever they see the
      light.

      Baseline assessment Colour vision/contrast sensitivity - patient reads letters /numbers from
      a multi coloured picture.

      Baseline assessment Intraocular pressure (IOP)- Study Doctor places eye drops which numb the
      eyes and measures the pressure in each eye by gently touching the instrument (called a
      tonometer) to the front surface of the eye. This is a standard procedure and the numbing
      eye-drops are safe and have been part of standard care pathway for some time.

      Baseline assessment Slit-lamp examination- study doctor examines eyes using a special lens
      and light Baseline assessment Blood pressure (BP)- standard procedure Baseline assessment OCT
      and OCTA scan - OCT stands for optical coherence tomography which is a type of imaging
      technique that is commonly used to image the eye in the clinic, using light to visualise the
      layers of the back of the eye. There are no risks or discomforts associated with this type of
      imaging.

      Study procedure PDE-5 inhibitor dosing - participants take their drug as per protocol
      (according to what drug they have been taking) Study procedure OCTA 30 minutes - as OCT but
      done in different time intervals 30min, 60min, 120min.

      Study procedure Repeat BP, IOP at 50 minutes - as described above Study procedure OCTA 60
      minutes - as described above Study procedure OCTA 120 minutes- as described above

      Upon completion of the study, patients from both cohorts(glaucoma and andrology) will
      continue their regular care in their usual clinics. The follow-up data routinely generated as
      part of the glaucoma care pathway (only)which is stored within the hospital data system e.g
      the central macular thickness, visual fields, IOP and other parameters will be accessed for 3
      years following completion of participation with a view of correlating initial results with
      possible disease progression and other related outcomes. This segment of the study is purely
      data-based and does not require any active involvement from the patients; participation in
      the data follow-up part of the study is optional and permission to access the relevant data
      will be documented in the informed consent form.

      Analyses

      No interim analyses will take place as they are deemed not needed.

      Sampling

      Sampling /recruiting for this pilot study will be from consecutive eligible patients from
      glaucoma and andrology clinics as well as patients recruited via the Western Eye Hospital
      patient database and replies to poster adverts at Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust.

      The sample size target for this pilot study is 30 including 15 glaucoma subjects and 15
      non-glaucoma subjects.

      No sample size or power calculations are necessary for this pilot study.

      Recruitment sources (aim: 15 non glaucoma participants, 15 glaucoma participants)

      Glaucoma clinics (Imperial Healthcare NHS Trust) Andrology clinics (Imperial Healthcare NHS
      Trust) Western Eye Patient database - potential patients will be contacted by telephone by a
      member of the usual care team and given the opportunity to receive more information about
      research that we are undertaking.

      Poster (attached) advertisements will be strategically placed in andrology and glaucoma
      waiting rooms.

      They will also have the opportunity to be emailed/posted a patient information sheet and
      given the opportunity to ask further questions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Healthy vs affected eyes (glaucoma)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in central macular thickness as assessed by retina imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>30min, 60min, 120min</time_frame>
    <description>OCT and angiographic findings before and after drug administration including</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in retinal vascular density as assessed by retina imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>30min, 60min, 120min</time_frame>
    <description>OCT and angiographic findings before and after drug administration including</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in outer retina flow as assessed by retina imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>30min, 60min, 120min</time_frame>
    <description>OCT and angiographic findings before and after drug administration including</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in choroidal vascular density as assessed by retina imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>30min, 60min, 120min</time_frame>
    <description>OCT and angiographic findings before and after drug administration including</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in central choroidal thickness as assessed by retina imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>30min, 60min, 120min</time_frame>
    <description>OCT and angiographic findings before and after drug administration including</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in choroidal flow as assessed by retina imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>30min, 60min, 120min</time_frame>
    <description>OCT and angiographic findings before and after drug administration including</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>eyes with glaucoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients with glaucoma will have imaging of retina post administration of Sildenafil or Tadalafil.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy (unaffected) eyes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients with healthy eyes who are already taking Sildenafil or Tadalafil have their imaging of retina post administration of Sildenafil or Tadalafil.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sildenafil 100mg</intervention_name>
    <description>study drug (Sildenafil or Tadalafil) administered orally in pill form with glass of water.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy (unaffected) eyes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>eyes with glaucoma</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tadalafil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to give informed consent to participate in the study

          -  Aged between 40 and 80 years of age

          -  Clear optical media

          -  Spherical equivalent +-10D

          -  IOP 21mmHg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  have used sildenafil for 48 hours (4 hour half-life) and tadalafil for 5 days (48 hour
             half-life).

          -  have a known adverse reaction to any phosphodiesterase inhibitors

          -  have an inherited photoreceptor disease (manufacturer contra-indication)

          -  have any other known ocular disease (except glaucoma in this cohort)

          -  have had non-arteritic anterior ischaemic optic neuropathy (manufacturer precaution
             due to lack of long term visualfield studies)

          -  are on current ritonavir, erythromycin, cimetidine treatment (Manufacturer advises if
             concurrent use of ritonavir is unavoidable, the max. dose should not exceed 25 mg
             within 48 hours)

          -  have serious cardiac or liver disease (manufacturer contra-indication)

          -  have had a stroke or myocardial infarction (manufacturer contra-indication) within 6
             months

          -  have anatomical deformation of the penis or conditions predisposing to priapism
             (sickle cell anaemia, leukaemia, multiple myeloma)

          -  have hypotension (manufacturer contra-indication) BP&lt;100/60

          -  have secondary or narrow/closed angle glaucoma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eduardo Dr Normando, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eduardo Dr Normando, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 02033123206</phone>
    <email>eduardomaria.normando@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Serge Miodragovic, BA</last_name>
    <phone>+44 02033123206</phone>
    <email>serge.miodragovic1@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western Eye Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW1 5QH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Normando</last_name>
      <phone>+4402033123206</phone>
      <email>eduardomaria.normando@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Miodragovic</last_name>
      <phone>+4402033123206</phone>
      <email>serge.miodragovic1@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glaucoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sildenafil Citrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tadalafil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

