<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03930238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201901762</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03930238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Increasing Steps Per Day in Rural Veterans</brief_title>
  <official_title>VA MapTrek, an M-Health Intervention to Increase Steps Per Day in Rural Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Iowa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>US Department of Veterans Affairs</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Iowa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      VA MapTrek is a mobile-phone-based web application that allows participants to take a virtual
      walk in interesting locations around the world while tracking their progress against the
      progress of other veterans on an interactive map. Steps are counted using a
      commercially-available triaxial accelerometer (e.g., Fitbit), and users see their progress
      overlaid on Google Maps. The objective of this study is to report activity levels to
      veterans, thereby encouraging them to walk more. Once participants know how to text and use
      Google maps, no additional training is needed. VA MapTrek does not require a special app, so
      there are no logins or passwords to remember. Simply registering one's Fitbit and mobile
      phone at an initial enrollment meeting suffices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All consented participants will be provided with a Fitbit and instructed to wear it all day,
      every day for the next 9 weeks (The first few participants may require an additional week or
      two of wear as we will not begin the first MapTrek race until we have at least 5 participants
      enrolled in the study. They will be told this upon enrollment.). The enrollment process is
      expected to take anywhere from 15 to 45 minutes, depending on group assignment and
      participant familiarity with using Fitbits.

      This, plus an exit survey (given via text message or phone, whichever the participant
      prefers), will be the extent of participation for the control group.

      Members of the intervention group will be instructed on how to use MapTrek, the virtual
      walking race, and will also be given an instruction packet to refer to later. Data collected
      during the first week from the Fitbit will be used to compute baseline activity level. This
      baseline data will be used to place participants into an appropriate initial race group.
      Participants are placed into groups with other individuals who are active at a similar level,
      so that groups will be competitive.

      Each virtual walking race will begin on Monday morning and end on Saturday night. Results of
      each race will be announced on Sundays. Depending on their performance each week, group
      assignment may change. Participants will compete in 8 week-long races over the course of the
      study.

      Participants will receive 2-4 text messages per day including a daily status report and a
      link to view the race. They will also periodically receive challenge messages. If a
      participant completes a challenge, they will be awarded bonus steps to help move them along
      the route quicker.

      To win a race, a participant must be furthest along on the route at 11:59 pm on Saturday.
      There is a leaderboard within MapTrek that helps participants determine their standing within
      each race. Participants are allowed to choose the screen name displayed on the leaderboard so
      that they may remain anonymous if desired.

      At baseline, the following data will be collected about all participants: first and last
      name, last 4 of social security number (for consent documentation and to look up records in
      CPRS), age, sex, race, ethnicity, marital status, height, weight, body mass index, blood
      pressure, zip code, current medications, and comorbidities.

      At the end of the study (9 weeks), the following data will be collected about all
      participants: height, weight, body mass index, blood pressure, current medications, and
      comorbidities.

      At the end of the study (9 weeks), participants will be contacted via text message or phone
      call (based on their preference at baseline) to complete an exit survey. This survey will
      take approximately 10 minutes to complete. All participants will be contacted up to 3 times
      to complete the exit survey. If they cannot be reached, they will be considered lost to
      follow up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Number of Steps per Day</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Fitbit will provide the total number of steps that each Veteran has taken per day.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Challenge Effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of challenges participated in and number of steps taken as a result of challenges will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>VA MapTrek Future Development Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Veterans will report areas of development within VA MapTrek to improve its future efficacy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VA MapTrek</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Veterans in the intervention group receive a Fitbit and access to VA MapTrek, an interactive text-messaging platform. The only equipment needed is a Fitbit (we provide) and a smartphone (required to enroll). Each week, Veterans are assigned to a virtual walking route. Each day, they receive a text message with a link to the current route. The link will take them to a map where they can see their progress and the progress of others. A leaderboard provides information on how many steps each participant has taken. Throughout each race, participants will randomly receive challenge text messages. Completing a challenge awards bonus steps to propel their character along the map.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Veterans randomized to the control group will receive a Fitbit only. This will allow us to determine if changes in physical activity are due to VA MapTrek or simply by giving the Veterans a Fitbit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VA MapTrek</intervention_name>
    <description>The objective is to report activity levels in our virtual environment to Veterans, thereby encouraging them to walk more.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VA MapTrek</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fitbit Only</intervention_name>
    <description>Fitbit Only</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit Only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Comfortable speaking and reading in English

          -  BMI greater than or equal to 25

          -  Have a smart phone with texting and internet capabilities

          -  Willing to download the Fitbit app on their phone

          -  Must be a VA patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Active mental health conditions that prevent them from providing consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Iowa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philip Polgreen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

