<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03932903</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-016325</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03932903</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mobile Health Intervention to Support Oral Chemotherapy Adherence in Adolescents and Young Adults With Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Real Time Mobile Health Approaches to Understand and Promote Oral Chemotherapy Adherence in Adolescents and Young Adults With Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a small-scale micro-randomized clinical trial of a new mobile just-in-time adaptive
      intervention (JITAI) designed to promote oral chemotherapy adherence in adolescents and young
      adults (AYA) with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). The goals of this study are to
      determine intervention feasibility and acceptability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 28-day micro-randomized pilot trial (i.e., a sequential factorial design) of a
      just-in-time adaptive intervention (JITAI) called AYA ADAPTS (ADherence Assessments and
      Personalized Timely Support). AYA ADAPTS is an app that integrate contextually-tailored
      mobile messages designed to promote oral chemotherapy adherence. Participants in the study
      will electronically-monitor 6MP adherence with MEMS TrackCaps and complete short ecological
      momentary assessment (EMA) surveys each afternoon, at the same time prior to the evening 6MP
      dose, for the 28-day period.

      AYA ADAPTS will deliver contextually-tailored text messages triggered based on EMA responses
      (e.g., based on fatigue, mood) and objective data (e.g., time of day, weekend vs. weekday).
      After receiving a contextually-tailored message, AYA will be asked to acknowledge receipt of
      the message by pressing a &quot;thumbs up&quot; or &quot;thumbs down&quot; button, to indicate whether or not
      they liked the message, or a &quot;snooze&quot; button indicating that it was not a good time to
      receive the message.

      Following the 28-day intervention period, MEMS TrackCaps will be returned and downloaded
      during the clinic appointment. AYA will complete a brief acceptability survey electronically
      via REDCAP, rating AYA ADAPTS on a 5-point Likert scale to assess satisfaction, perceived
      appropriateness, perceive positive effects, perceived demands, and potential for future use.
      Exit interviews will also be conducted, audio-recorded, and transcribed to further assess
      acceptability. For feasibility, the following variables will be tracked: (1) screening rates,
      (2) recruitment rates, (3) % acknowledged micro-randomized messages, (4) technical
      difficulties (e.g., micro-randomized messages received when intended), (5) retention rates,
      and (6) completed assessments (EMA, MEMS, post-measures).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a 28-day micro-randomized pilot trial (i.e., a sequential factorial design) of a just-in-time adaptive intervention called AYA ADAPTS (Adherence Assessments and Personalized Timely Support). AYA ADAPTS is an app that will deliver contextually-tailored mobile messages (adapted to AYA's current states, such as mood, pain, and location) designed to promote oral chemotherapy adherence. Each AYA in the study (n=30) will be micro-randomized (with a 60% probability) to receive a contextually-tailored message each day that supports abilities to self-manage and maintain adherence, delivered prior to their scheduled dose, over a 28-day period (i.e., the period between follow-up appointments). The remaining 40% of days, participants will be assigned to receive no messages (i.e., no intervention).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Screening Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of AYA patients referred and screened per month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of AYA patients enrolled in the study per month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of AYA subjects who complete the intervention, out of the total number of AYA subjects enrolled in the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Engagement</measure>
    <time_frame>28-day intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Number of acknowledged micro-randomized text messages; categorized by &quot;thumbs up&quot;, &quot;thumbs down&quot;, and &quot;snooze&quot; responses</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical Difficulties</measure>
    <time_frame>28-day intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Number of technical glitches and errors experienced in implementing the intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of 28-day intervention</time_frame>
    <description>5-point numerical Likert scale; ranging from 0 (not at all) to 4 (completely)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Perceived Appropriateness</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of 28-day intervention</time_frame>
    <description>5-point numerical Likert scale; ranging from 0 (not at all) to 4 (completely)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Perceived Positive Effects</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of 28-day intervention</time_frame>
    <description>5-point numerical Likert scale; ranging from 0 (not at all) to 4 (completely)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Perceived Demands</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of 28-day intervention</time_frame>
    <description>5-point numerical Likert scale; ranging from 0 (not at all) to 4 (completely)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Potential for Intervention Future Use</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of 28-day intervention</time_frame>
    <description>5-point numerical Likert scale; ranging from 0 (not at all) to 4 (completely)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contextually-tailored Mobile Messages for Adherence</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will be micro-randomized to receive contextually-tailored mobile messages designed to promote their oral chemotherapy adherence, with a 60% probability of receiving a contextually-tailored message each day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will also be micro-randomized to not receive messages on some days of the intervention (~40% of the time).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AYA ADAPTS (ADherence Assessments and Personalized Timely Support).</intervention_name>
    <description>AYA ADAPTS is a mobile app intervention that integrates contextually-tailored mobile messages and decision rules about when to deliver the messages, with the ultimate goal of improving oral chemotherapy adherence in adolescents and young adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Each participant will be micro-randomized to receive messages on some days that are adapted to their current characteristics (e.g., mood, pain, location) and designed to promote adherence, and no messages (no intervention) on other days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contextually-tailored Mobile Messages for Adherence</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 15-25

          -  Diagnosed with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)

          -  In the maintenance phase, completed at least one cycle and has at least one month of
             maintenance therapy remaining

          -  Prescribed 6-mercaptopurine (6MP)

          -  Self-reported 6MP adherence &lt;95% in the past month

          -  English language proficiency

          -  For AYA &lt;18, must have informed consent from their caregiver.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cognitive impairments that would limit ability to complete measures, determined by the
             medical team

          -  Absence of inclusion criteria above.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandra M Psihogios, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lamia P Barakat, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandra M Psihogios, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>267-314-0164</phone>
    <email>psihogiosa@email.chop.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhatia S, Landier W, Hageman L, Kim H, Chen Y, Crews KR, Evans WE, Bostrom B, Casillas J, Dickens DS, Maloney KW, Neglia JP, Ravindranath Y, Ritchey AK, Wong FL, Relling MV. 6MP adherence in a multiracial cohort of children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a Children's Oncology Group study. Blood. 2014 Oct 9;124(15):2345-53. doi: 10.1182/blood-2014-01-552166. Epub 2014 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24829202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Modi AC, Pai AL, Hommel KA, Hood KK, Cortina S, Hilliard ME, Guilfoyle SM, Gray WN, Drotar D. Pediatric self-management: a framework for research, practice, and policy. Pediatrics. 2012 Feb;129(2):e473-85. doi: 10.1542/peds.2011-1635. Epub 2012 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22218838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klasnja P, Hekler EB, Shiffman S, Boruvka A, Almirall D, Tewari A, Murphy SA. Microrandomized trials: An experimental design for developing just-in-time adaptive interventions. Health Psychol. 2015 Dec;34S:1220-8. doi: 10.1037/hea0000305.</citation>
    <PMID>26651463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nahum-Shani I, Smith SN, Spring BJ, Collins LM, Witkiewitz K, Tewari A, Murphy SA. Just-in-Time Adaptive Interventions (JITAIs) in Mobile Health: Key Components and Design Principles for Ongoing Health Behavior Support. Ann Behav Med. 2018 May 18;52(6):446-462. doi: 10.1007/s12160-016-9830-8.</citation>
    <PMID>27663578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Psihogios AM, Li Y, Butler E, Hamilton J, Daniel LC, Barakat LP, Bonafide CP, Schwartz LA. Text Message Responsivity in a 2-Way Short Message Service Pilot Intervention With Adolescent and Young Adult Survivors of Cancer. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2019 Apr 18;7(4):e12547. doi: 10.2196/12547.</citation>
    <PMID>30998225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Psihogios AM, Fellmeth H, Schwartz LA, Barakat LP. Family Functioning and Medical Adherence Across Children and Adolescents With Chronic Health Conditions: A Meta-Analysis. J Pediatr Psychol. 2019 Jan 1;44(1):84-97. doi: 10.1093/jpepsy/jsy044.</citation>
    <PMID>29982694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGrady ME, Brown GA, Pai AL. Medication adherence decision-making among adolescents and young adults with cancer. Eur J Oncol Nurs. 2016 Feb;20:207-14. doi: 10.1016/j.ejon.2015.08.007. Epub 2015 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26372619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Butow P, Palmer S, Pai A, Goodenough B, Luckett T, King M. Review of adherence-related issues in adolescents and young adults with cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Nov 10;28(32):4800-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.22.2802. Epub 2010 Mar 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20212260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Young Adult</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Oncology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

