<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03936582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BHAN32214719000</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03936582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting Small Business Support of Youth Physical Activity in Low-income, Minority Neighborhoods</brief_title>
  <official_title>Promoting Small Business Support of Youth Physical Activity in Low-income, Minority Neighborhoods</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Delaware</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Delaware</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An unacceptably high percentage of our nation's low-income, minority youth (&lt; 18 years of
      age) are not regularly physically active. This contributes to extreme health disparities such
      as obesity rates nearly two-fold higher than those seen in white youth and greater risk for
      diabetes and related cardiometabolic disorders. The presence of quality youth physical
      activity opportunities (YPAO) enables and encourages physically active lifestyles.
      Unfortunately, quality YPAOs often are lacking in places where minority youth live, resulting
      in low activity levels and subsequent health issues that represent significant disparities in
      our society. The investigators' previous research found that small businesses (&lt; 500
      employees), which represent over 99% of all employers, are powerful resources for creating
      and improving YPAOs. In accordance with the Socioecological Model and established
      philanthropic principles, the investigators developed an alpha version of an intervention
      (alpha-i) for increasing small businesses' involvement with YPAOs. The investigators are now
      poised to create a beta version (beta-i) and conduct a pilot study of its impact on small
      business support for YPAOs and YPAO utilization by youth in low-income, minority
      neighborhoods. To meet this objective, the investigators will complete the following specific
      aims. Aim 1: Refine alpha-i components by completing focus groups with small business owners,
      YPAO providers, and parents/guardians of youth from low-income, predominantly minority
      neighborhoods. Results of the qualitative analysis will inform final tailoring of the
      intervention to create the beta-i which will be tested in Aim 2. Aim 2: Determine the effect
      of the beta-i on small business support for YPAOs in low-income, minority neighborhoods by
      conducting a plot cluster randomized-control trial with randomization at the neighborhood
      level. Intervention neighborhoods (n=10) will receive the beta-i while control neighborhoods
      (n=10) will be provided a standard practice intervention for a period of one year. The
      primary outcome for aim 2 will be the percentage of small businesses not supporting YPAOs at
      baseline that subsequently provide support for YPAOs at follow-up. The investigators also
      will consider the U.S. dollar equivalent of all types of support (monetary, goods/services
      and time) donated for YPAOs by small businesses. Aim 3: Examine the impact of the increased
      small business support for YPAOs on YPAO utilization by youth. The primary outcome will be
      the percent change in the number of youth participating in YPAOs from baseline and follow-up
      in the treatment and control neighborhoods. The proposed study is significant because it will
      provide evidence that an easily replicated approach can be used to increase small business
      support for YPAOs and that this support results in greater use of the YPAOs by youth. The
      investigators' next step will be to determine if YPAO changes resulting from increased small
      business support positively influence youth physical activity levels as measured by
      accelerometry. The investigators long-term goals are to create a nationally implementable
      practice for increasing support for YPAOs and strengthen the science of addressing health
      disparities in socially disadvantaged populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>percentages of business supporting youth physical activity programs before and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Based on baseline and post-intervention survey data as well as information tracked on the project's websites.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Youth physical activity utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in the number of youth participating in youth activity programs from baseline and follow-up in the treatment and control neighborhoods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All owners/managers of small businesses in 10 treatment neighborhoods will receive a request to support youth physical activity. The owners/managers will be able to direct support to specific programs, get recognized for their support, receive added information on the benefits of supporting such programs, have the oversight of an advisory board and interface with a local program representative</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All owners/managers of small businesses in 10 control neighborhoods will will receive a request to support youth physical activity. None of the other components of the treatment arm (e.g., direct support to specific programs, advisory board) will be provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>information already included in arm/group descriptions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  small business (&lt; 500 employees) in one of the 20 study areas with a physical,
             non-residential location.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  large businesses (500 or more employees) not in one of the 20 study areas, does not
             have a physical location or the physical location is residential.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>richard r suminski, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>3023392570</phone>
    <email>suminski@udel.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shannon Robson, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>: 302-831-6674</phone>
    <email>robson@udel.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Delaware</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Suminski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Project investigators will develop policies/procedures for sharing data with other interested parties not affiliated with the original project. These policies/procedures will be defined in a data-sharing agreement. The investigators will make the data and associated documentation available to users only under the data-sharing agreement that will provide for: a commitment to using the data only for research purposes and not to identify any individual participant/community by name, a commitment to securing the data using appropriate computer technology, determining the quality of the research proposal (significance, innovativeness, approach, and community benefit), a comprehensive dissemination plan (to community and scientific audiences), sharing of administrative costs to prepare data and related documentation, appropriate approvals of research protocols by the IRB and a commitment to destroying or returning the data after analyses are completed.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>after August 2020 for a period of 10 years</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>see above</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

