<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03930576</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-25863</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03930576</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Consequences of Unwanted Pregnancy in Nepal</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pregnancy Context and Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CREHPA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this project is to examine the health consequences of unwanted pregnancy and
      denial of legal pregnancy termination services in Nepal on women and their children. The
      proposed study will be a large, longitudinal, prospective, quantitative study among women
      seeking termination services at 14 diverse facilities in 7 provinces (two facilities in each
      province) of Nepal. Every 6 months following baseline, surveys will cover questions about
      women's physical and mental health, the health and development of their children, as well as
      measures of family wellbeing, such as residency, relationship status and quality, and
      extended family relationships, and financial wellbeing, such as employment status, hours of
      labor, food security, income, and education.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this project is to examine the health consequences of unwanted pregnancy and
      denial of legal pregnancy termination services in Nepal on women and their children. Births
      following unwanted pregnancies can be associated with negative physical, social and economic
      consequences for both the woman and child. Half of all unintended pregnancies are terminated
      before they are carried to term and, when performed in unsafe or illegal conditions, the
      consequences can include infection, infertility, and death. The incidence of mortality and
      morbidity from abortion are notoriously difficult to measure. Widespread stigma associated
      with unwanted pregnancy - even in settings in which termination is legally available -
      contribute to misreporting, concealment, and misattribution of termination-related morbidity
      and mortality. In addition, many women seek illegal methods—both safe and unsafe—which
      further confounds efforts to measure the prevalence of mortality and morbidity from
      terminations. The effects of unwanted pregnancy on children, including children born prior to
      and subsequent to the unwanted pregnancy, are also not well established. A prospective
      longitudinal study of women with unwanted pregnancies is required to validly investigate the
      health consequences for women and their families of termination outside of the legal system
      and delivery of an unwanted pregnancy, as compared to legal termination. Such a study is only
      possible in places like Nepal, where termination is legal but barriers prevent some women
      from receiving the service.

      Aim 1: To investigate the predictors of denial of legal pregnancy termination services and
      identify groups of women who may be at elevated risk of adverse sequelae from unwanted
      pregnancy.

      Aim 2: To assess the health consequences for women of childbirth and illegal termination
      after denial of a legal termination. By comparing the two groups of women denied termination
      of pregnancy to those obtaining legal procedures, the study team will assess the health
      effects of denial while accounting for factors associated with experience of unwanted
      pregnancy.

      Aim 3: To measure the effects of legal and illegal termination compared to birth on the
      health and development of women's existing and subsequent children

      Prospective longitudinal data from women in a less developed country would provide valuable
      evidence for the development of programs and policies globally to improve access to and
      utilization of safe termination services where they are legal, and harm reduction services
      for women who are unable to access services.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion experiencing denial of termination services on day of recruitment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be defined as the proportion of participants who did not receive termination services on the day they were recruited at the clinic site where they are recruited in to the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants who did not receive a termination from an approved facility</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants who did not receive termination services from the recruitment clinic and did not receive a termination at any facility that they were referred to by the recruitment facility</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of termination-seeking participants who received a termination</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will report their pregnancy outcome at 6 months; the proportion of participants who had an abortion by 6 months versus had a miscarriage, gave birth, or were still pregnant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of existing children with stunting at 36 months</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of children existing at the time of termination-seeking who having stunting, or low height-for-age, defined according to the World Health Organization as less than two standard deviations of the World Health Organization Child Growth Standards median.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal deaths during the study period</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of maternal deaths by end of study. The study team will implement a verbal autopsy protocol for any women who die during the study period, with a particular focus on identifying specific pregnancy-related causes of death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of women reporting poor health by 36 months</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of participants who self-report poor or very poor physical health by 36 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subsequent children with stunting</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subsequent children born to participants after the index pregnancy who having stunting, or low height-for-age, defined according to the World Health Organization as less than two standard deviations of the World Health Organization Child Growth Standards median.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion experiencing violence from husband at each year of follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion experiencing any physical violence from husband over time (12 months, 24 months, 36 months), defined pushed you, shake you, throw something at you (yes/no), slapped you (yes/no), twisted your arm or pulled your hair (yes/no), punched you (yes/no), kicked you (yes/no), tried to choke you (yes/no), threatened or attacked you with a weapon (yes/no).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion experiencing violence from any family members or close relatives other than husband at 36 months</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported violence from family members or close relatives other than husband or partner (yes/no) in the past 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion reporting depression at 36 months</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants self-reporting feeling down, depressed or hopeless nearly every day, more than half the days, or several days in the prior two weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1436</enrollment>
  <condition>Unwanted Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early Legal Terminations</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants who receive a legal termination at &lt;10 weeks gestation at a recruiting facility.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Late Legal Terminations</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants who receive a legal termination at 10+ weeks gestation at a recruiting facility.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Turn-aways: Termination outside Legal Setting</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants who receive a termination at another facility or outside the formal healthcare sector.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Turn-aways: Birth</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants who ultimately carry the pregnancy to term</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Receipt of termination services outside of legal setting</intervention_name>
    <description>This study uses variation in gestational age to examine the impact of receipt of legal termination services compared to denial and receipt outside legal settings and birth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Turn-aways: Termination outside Legal Setting</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Carrying unwanted pregnancy to term</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The proposed study will be a large, longitudinal, prospective, quantitative study among
        women seeking termination services at 14 diverse facilities in 7 provinces (two facilities
        in each province) of Nepal. The specific facilities were randomly selected from a list of
        providers who served more than 60 women in FY 2016/17. Providers who serve more than 60
        women per year make up 44% of all providers but provide 92% of termination services. One
        non-governmental organization and one public site was randomly selected within each of 7
        provinces so that their chance of selection was proportionate to the number of women
        served. These sites are a representative sample of women seeking care.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women

          -  seeking pregnancy termination services at one of the study facilities

          -  self-report last menstrual period to be at least 10 weeks ago or not know her
             gestational age

          -  15 years old or older

          -  live in Nepal

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  under 15 years old

          -  not pregnant

          -  do not live in Nepal
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Diana G Foster, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mahesh Puri, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CREHPA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Diana G Foster, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>510-986-8940</phone>
    <email>diana.greenefoster@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah Raifman, MS</last_name>
    <email>sarah.raifman@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CREHPA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kathmandu</city>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mahesh Puri</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 18, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

