<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03937128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00155161</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AWD011726</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03937128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Employment and Reducing Recidivism Among Prison Offenders Via Virtual Interview Training Tool</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Employment and Reducing Recidivism Among Prison Offenders Via Virtual Interviewing Tool</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SIMmersion, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal is to conduct a confirmatory effectiveness RCT (and an implementation evaluation) of
      Virtual Interview Training (VIT) by comparing employment and recidivism outcomes of offenders
      receiving vocational services as usual (SAU) plus VIT (SAU+VIT) with the outcomes of
      offenders receiving only services as usual (SAU-only).

      The plan calls for participants to include offenders who are at moderate to high risk for
      reoffending (with an emphasis on violent-crime reoffending) who are currently enrolled in a
      Vocational Village.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal is to conduct a confirmatory effectiveness RCT (and an implementation evaluation) of
      VIT by comparing employment and recidivism outcomes of offenders receiving vocational
      services as usual (SAU) plus VIT (SAU+VIT) with the outcomes of offenders receiving only
      services as usual (SAU-only). To meet the criteria in the funding announcement, the plan
      calls for participants to include offenders who are at moderate to high risk for reoffending
      (with an emphasis on violent-crime reoffending) who are currently enrolled in a Vocational
      Village. The investigators are well prepared to conduct this study because the team has
      extensive experience with evaluating VIT in several settings (schools and mental-health
      service providers) and has previously collaborated with the Michigan Department of
      Corrections, which administers the Vocational Villages.

      Objective 1. Evaluate whether SAU+VIT, compared with SAU-only, enhances employment outcomes
      and reduces recidivism among this population (i.e., effectiveness). At the individual level,
      the investigators hypothesize (H) that SAU+VIT trainees, compared with SAU-only trainees,
      will have higher employment rates (H1), greater improvement in job-interview skills (H2), and
      reduced recidivism (H3) by six-month follow-up. At the system level, the investigators
      hypothesize that SAU+VIT will be more cost-effective than SAU-only (H4). Subobjective 1.
      Explore whether use of the computerized VIT system frees up SAU staff time for
      non-interview-practice-related vocational training, relative to SAU-only (system
      level).Objective 2. Evaluate the mechanisms of employment outcomes and explore the mechanisms
      of recidivism.

      Based on Corbiere's model, the investigators hypothesize that interview-skill improvement and
      measured role-play interview performance will mediate the effect of interview training on
      employment outcomes (H5). Also, The investigators will explore whether employment outcomes
      mediate the relationship between interviewing skills and recidivism at six-month follow-up
      and twelve month follow ups.

      Objective 3. Conduct a multilevel, mixed-method initial process evaluation of VIT
      implementation to assess the acceptability, scalability, generalizability, and affordability
      of VIT. The investigators will use focus groups, surveys, and interviews (among offenders,
      staff, and leaders) to identify facilitators and barriers to implementing VIT in a
      prison-based vocational service program (the Vocational Village). The investigators will use
      budget-impact analysis to estimate the cost of implementing VIT at the Vocational Village.

      1.1 Virtual Interview Training (VIT). This is an immersive simulation that allows trainees to
      have a virtual conversation with, and influence the behavior of, a simulated character.
      Previous studies suggest that virtual reality simulation training is engaging, and as a
      result, trainees will practice willingly for hours. The VIT simulation far exceeds typical
      interview training by combining video, speech recognition, and nonbranching logic (described
      below) to create an interactive environment in which trainees encounter complex social cues
      and realistic interpersonal exchanges with a virtual hiring manager. VIT was designed as part
      of a collaborative partnership between SIMmersion LLC and the research team to improve
      interview skills using behavioral-learning principles. These principles help develop
      sustainable changes in behavior.

      The team developed the VIT learning objectives, which the investigators re characterized
      using terminology from the literature. The job-related interview content objectives target
      dependability, negotiating skills (e.g., asking for a day off), teamwork, and honesty (e.g.,
      following company policies). The interviewer performance objectives target comfort level
      during the interview, sharing information in a positive way, sounding interested in the
      position, sounding professional, and establishing a rapport with the interviewer. VIT
      includes the following components to help the trainee achieve the learning objectives:
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Employment as measured in Outcome Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month and 12 month follow up after villagers are released; will occur through study completion, average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Employment rate will be measured by participant self-report using a questionnaire. The questionnaire will include information about their job status (unemployed, employed); if they completed any job interviews (yes/no) and how many interviews they completed, if they received a job offer (yes/no), and information about jobs they may have had since their release date (employer name, job type, average hours worked, hourly wage, start date, end date). It will also include questions about their housing status (staying at a friend's, having own apartment, having own house/condo, homeless, or other); and if they thought the virtual interview training helped them prepare for an interview. The employment status will be validated with administrative data collected by MDOC.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mock Interview Scoring</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessments occur pre-intervention and post-intervention and data will be assessed throughout study completion, average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Videos of mock interviews taken pre-intervention and post-intervention will be rated using a developed scale by the UM study team. Performance will be rated using a 1-5 likert scale with 1 being &quot;Poor&quot;, 3 being &quot;Average&quot; and 5 being &quot;Excellent&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recidivism as measured in Outcome Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month and 12 month follow up after villagers are released; will occur through study completion, average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Recidivism status will be collected during the 6 month and 12 month follow up survey. Questions include if they've been re-arrested (yes/no) and if they were convicted of a crime (yes/no). The recidivism self-report data will be validated by administrative data collected from MDOC.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost Effectiveness of VR-JIT as measured by Pre-Delivery Cost Capture Questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Pre-Delivery cost capture surveys ask for MDOC staff to list the number of hours they worked on certain topics, including job interview training, mock interviews, job development/supports, job application skills, educational team meetings, educational team correspondence, project team correspondence, SIMersion team correspondence. This will provide a baseline number of total hours worked on these tasks before VR-JIT use.
The Installation Cost Capture Questionnaire will ask MDOC Staff and Research Staff to list the number of hours they worked on activities related to getting VR-JIT installed and up and running at the prisons.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost Effectiveness of VR-JIT as measured by Installation Cost Capture Questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Installation Cost Capture Questionnaire will ask MDOC Staff and Research Staff to list the number of hours they worked on activities related to getting VR-JIT installed and up and running at the prisons. This includes time spent on phone calls between sites, between IT members, UM staff, Simmersion staff, etc.). This will provide a total number of hours spent on getting VR-JIT up and running in these agencies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost Effectiveness of VR-JIT as measured by Delivery Cost Capture Questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Delivery cost capture surveys ask for MDOC staff to list the number of hours they worked on certain topics (including job interview training, mock interviews, job development/supports, job application skills, educational team meetings, educational team correspondence, project team correspondence, SIMersion team correspondence, VR-JIT teaching, and VR-JIT support while using VR-JIT. This will provide a total number of hours worked on these tasks while delivery of the VR-JIT tool is occurring.
The Installation Cost Capture Questionnaire will ask MDOC Staff and Research Staff to list the number of hours they worked on activities related to getting VR-JIT installed and up and running at the prisons.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological Distress Survey (SCL-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 points throughout the study completion, average of 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>The SCL-10-R is a 10-item self-report checklist of psychological distress based on the Symptom Checklist-90 (SCL-90). This survey will be administered at pre-test, as well as 6 month and 12-month follow up. This survey asks participants, &quot;During the past 30 days, how much have you been stressed by&quot; and then lists items such as &quot;Feeling blue, difficulty making decisions, trouble catching your breath&quot;, etc. They are then able to choose responses varying from &quot;Not at all, A little bit, Moderately, Quite a bit, and Extremely&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DSM-5 Level 1 symptom measure</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 points throughout the study completion, average of 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>The DSM-5 Level 1 symptom measure was created to aid in a comprehensive mental status assessment by measuring mental health symptoms. This survey will be administered at pre-test, as well as 6-month and 12-month follow up. This 20-item self-report survey asks participants, &quot;During the past two weeks, how much (or how often) have you been bothered by the following problems?&quot;. They are then able to choose responses varying from, &quot;None, Slightly Rare, Mild, Moderate, and Severe&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interviewing Anxiety/Comfort</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 points throughout the study completion, average of 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report survey that will be administered at pre-test and post-test. It includes 34 statements where participants can indicate whether they &quot;Strongly Disagree, Disagree, Neutral, Agree, or Strongly Agree&quot; to those statements about job interviewing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interviewing Self-Efficacy/Confidence</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 points throughout the study completion, average of 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report survey that will be administered at pre-test and post-test. It includes 1 statement about how comfortable a participant is going on a job interview, with the options being &quot;Extremely comfortable, Very Comfortable, Moderately Comfortable, Neutral, Slightly Uncomfortable, Very Uncomfortable, and Extremely Comfortable&quot;. The rest of the questions asks how skilled they are at certain tasks, with the options being, &quot;Extremely skilled, Very skilled, Moderately skilled, Neutral, Slightly unskilled, Very unskilled, and Extremely unskilled.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interviewing Motivation/Enjoyment</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 points throughout the study completion, average of 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report survey that will be administered at pre-test and post-test. It includes 30 statements asking participants how true it was for them regarding preparing for a job. The options provided on a 1 to 7 scale, with 1 being &quot;Not at all true&quot;, 4 being &quot;Somewhat true&quot;, and 7 being &quot;Very true&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability/Usability of VR-JIT</measure>
    <time_frame>At one point throughout study completion, average of 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report survey administered only to those in the intervention group. The 15-item surveys asks about participant's general thoughts about the acceptability and usability of the program using rating scales from 1 to 4 and 1 to 7. This will provide a total score of participant's acceptability and usability of VR-JIT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Criminal Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Services as usual + Virtual Reality Job Interview Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to the services as usual comparator, participants will participate in Virtual Reality Job Interview Training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Services as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants will be receiving their Vocational Village services as usual that may include but is not limited to vocational skill training, daily living skill training, and social skill training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual Reality Job Interview Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will engage in training related to preforming well during a job interview as well as repeated job interview practice with a virtual hiring manager. Participants will receive feedback and tips on improving skills throughout the training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Services as usual + Virtual Reality Job Interview Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Services as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>Study participants will be receiving Vocational Village services as usual that may include but is not limited to vocational skill training, daily living skill training, and social skill training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Services as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Services as usual + Virtual Reality Job Interview Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years or older

          2. Identified as at moderate to high risk for reoffending with violent crimes (determined
             at the time of enrollment in the Vocational Village via the COMPAS Risk Assessment
             Classification Instrument [60])

          3. Within three months of their earliest release date

          4. Actively enrolled in a Vocational Village

          5. Have at least a 6th grade reading comprehension

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has uncorrected hearing or visual problem that prevents him or her from using the
             training

          2. Has a medical illness that compromises their cognition (for example, moderate to
             severe traumatic brain injury).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew J Smith, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brittany Ross, Bachelors</last_name>
    <phone>734- 764-2368</phone>
    <email>rossbrit@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Katherine Tucker, MSW</last_name>
    <phone>734-936-8646</phone>
    <email>kmcheck@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brittany Ross</last_name>
      <phone>734-764-2368</phone>
      <email>rossbirt@umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthew Smith</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

