<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03937583</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEETAC</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-003958-25</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03937583</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Screening for Cancer in Patients With Thromboembolic Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>PEETAC</acronym>
  <official_title>Screening for Cancer With PET /TC Scan in Patients With Unprovoked Venous Thromboembolic Disease With High Risk of Developing Cancer. (PEETAC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multicenter, randomized (1:1) and open clinical trial comparing limited screening with
      extended screening with the performance of PET-CT (Positron emission tomography-computed
      tomography) in the search for neoplasms in patients with unprovoked venous thromboembolic
      disease at high risk of developing cancer at follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Venous thromboembolic disease (VTD) is an entity constituted by deep vein thrombosis (DVT)
      and by pulmonary embolism (PE) produced as a result of the migration of a thrombus from the
      venous territory, usually originated in the lower limbs, to the tree pulmonary artery. VTE is
      a complex disease with a multifactorial cause, influenced by the patient's history, clinical
      risk factors, and genetic and environmental interactions.

      There is a clearly established relationship between VTD and the presence of an underlying
      cancer. In addition, ETV can be the first manifestation of cancer in some patients.

      Therefore, the objective of this clinical trial is to perform screening with 18DFG PET-CT in
      patients with unprovoked high-risk VTD to evaluate if it is possible to diagnose a great
      number of not diagnosed neoplasms at an earlier stage and to evaluate which impact would have
      on survival and the quality of life.

      For all this, we propose this clinical trial in which we will compare a limited screening
      strategy (usual management of patients with unprovoked VTE) versus extended screening
      (through 18FDG PET-CT), in patients at high risk of developing cancer in the follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of neoplasms diagnosed using extended screening</measure>
    <time_frame>After 3 years of follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate the impact of an active cancer search strategy using PET-CT in the number of neoplasms diagnosed in the screening process in patients with high-risk unprovoked thromboembolic disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of neoplasms diagnosed in early phase using extended screening</measure>
    <time_frame>After 3 years of follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate the impact of an active cancer search strategy using PET-CT in the number of neoplasms diagnosed in early phase in the screening process in patients with high-risk unprovoked thromboembolic disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival of patients with high-risk unprovoked thromboembolic disease performing limited/extended screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the patient death or finalization of study after three years of follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate the impact of an active cancer search strategy using PET-CT in the overall survival in patients with high-risk unprovoked thromboembolic disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>European Quality of Life-5 (EQ-5D scale validated in Spanish) of patients with high-risk unprovoked thromboembolic disease performing limited/extended screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 90, 180 and 365 days of follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate the impact of an active cancer search strategy using PET-CT in the quality of life evaluated with the scale EQ-5D in patients with high-risk unprovoked thromboembolic disease. The EQ-5D consists of 2 parts - the &quot;Descriptive System&quot; and the &quot;Visual Analogue scale&quot;. The DS comprises 5 dimensions (mobility, self care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression). Each dimension has 5 levels: no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems.
The EQ VAS records the respondent's self-rated health on a 20 cm vertical, visual analogue scale with endpoints labelled 'the best health you can imagine' and 'the worst health you can imagine'. This information can be used as a quantitative measure of health as judged by the individual respondents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">650</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Thromboembolic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Disease</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Deep Venous Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Limited screening</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Complete clinical history, along with routine physical, analytical examination (creatinine, sodium, potassium, red series, white series, liver and calcium profile) and chest x-ray.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extended screening</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Limited screening plus positron emission tomography / computed tomography with 18 FDG (18FDG PET-CT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludeoxyglucose 18F</intervention_name>
    <description>The performance of the 18 FDG PET-CT will require fasting of at least 6 hours, and the glycemia will have to be lower than 126 mg / dL before the injection of 3-5 MBq / kg of 18FDG. Intravenous injection will follow a period of approximately 60 minutes in a quiet room.
Computed tomography (CT) will be performed from the middle of the forehead to the feet with normal and shallow breathing using a low dose adjustment Iodinated contrast will not be administered intravenously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extended screening</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Over 18 years.

          -  Diagnosis of venous thromboembolic disease (proximal deep vein thrombosis of lower
             limbs, pulmonary embolism or both) unprovoked.

          -  High risk classification according to previously published and validated scale

          -  Signature of informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Impossibility to continue an adequate follow-up.

          -  Contrast hypersensitivity used for PET / CT (fludeoxyglucose (18FDG)) or any of the
             excipients according to the characteristics of the product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis Jara Palomares, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospitales Universitarios Virgen del Rocío</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis Jara Palomares, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 955012144</phone>
    <email>luisoneumo@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Clara M Rosso Fernández, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34955012144</phone>
    <email>claram.rosso.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Venous Thromboembolic Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Embolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Extended screening</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiration Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD to be shared with the center participants once the study is officially finished in the foreseen period of three years.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>3 years time</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

