<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03939975</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B2018-151-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03939975</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anti-PD-1therapy Combined With Thermal Ablation for Advanced HCC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study of Anti-PD-1 Inhibitors Therapy in Combination With Incomplete Thermal Ablation in Patients With Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sun Yat-sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sun Yat-sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The inhibition of programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) has shown promising antitumor
      activity in advanced hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). Unfortunately, less than 20% of HCC have
      response. The effect of PD-1 blockade and incomplete thermal ablation in patients with
      advanced HCC is not yet clearly understood. This study aimed to analyze outcomes of advanced
      HCC treated with anti PD-1 inhibitors in combination with incomplete thermal ablation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is ranked as the third leading cause of cancer death both
      worldwide and in the China. In the past decade, survivals of patients with advanced HCC or
      those who have progressed diseases following locoregional treatments can be increased with
      the multi-kinase inhibitor sorafenib, the first evidence identified drug for HCC. Recent
      clinical trials further verified some novel tyrosine kinase inhibitors such as regorafenib
      and cabozantinib, and two programmed cell death protein-1 (PD-1) immune checkpoint inhibitors
      (ICIs), nivolumab and pembrolizumab, as useful therapies in second line setting following
      sorafenib.

      Advances in programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) blockade have shown an ORR of 15-17% and
      median survival time of 12.9-15.0 months among patients with advanced HCC. Of these,
      nivolumab and pembrolizumab have been accelerated approved as second-line treatment of
      advanced HCC. Notably, patients who have tumor responses maintain long-lasting disease
      control for 9.9-17months and still a large proportion of patients (81-83%) do not respond to
      mono PD-1 blockade, which emphasizing the need to explore strategies to increase the efficacy
      of immunotherapy.

      An approach to expanding the benefit of ICIs may involve combinations with locoregional
      therapy like radiofrequency ablation (RFA) and transarterial chemoembolization (TACE), such
      treatments have been shown to boost tumor-specific T-cell response through release of TAAs
      from HCC cells. The intent-to-treat population of this study was a subset of patients
      receiving ongoing ICIs therapy for advanced HCC and is with stable disease or atypical
      responses in different lesions of the same individuals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study subjects were those who with advanced HCC that progressed on first-line sorafenib and treated with anti-PD-1 therapy in combination with incomplete thermal ablation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>6-8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation was done continuously during ICIs treatment and up to 30 days after the last dose by using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE; version 4.03). Complications related to ablation procedure were assessed peri-operation period and reported according to the standardized Society of Interventional Radiology grading system.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response</measure>
    <time_frame>6-8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy included objective response (includes complete and partial response), duration of response, and disease control (Includes complete and partial response, stable disease and atypical progression for at least 3 months).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to tumor progression</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 months</time_frame>
    <description>time from first dose of ICIs drug until the first typical progression of disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 months</time_frame>
    <description>time from first day of ICIs treatment to first typical disease progression, or death, which occurred earlier</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 months</time_frame>
    <description>time from first study treatment to death of any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with stable diseases or atypical progression to ICIs monotherapy would be additionally treated with incomplete thermal ablation along with ICIs therapy; and for those who with no lesions eligible for Incomplete ablation, ICIs would be given solely.
Others with complete or partial responses would keep on going with mono-ICIs therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pembrolizumab or nivolumab or JS001</intervention_name>
    <description>ICIs therapy of nivolumab (3 mg/kg, per 2 weeks) or pembrolizumab (2 mg/kg, per 3 weeks) or JS001 (240mg, per 3 weeks) was performed until the off-treatment criteria were met. For participants with stable disease or atypical progression to ICIs therapy, thermal ablation of radiofrequency ablation or microwave ablation was performed addtionally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>computed tomography guided radiofrequency ablation</other_name>
    <other_name>or computed tomography guided microwave ablation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Eligible patients had pathological diagnosis of HCC by either surgical resection tissue or
        core needle biopsy; and had advanced stage of disease that is refractory to or is with
        unacceptable toxicity of sorafenib. Other eligibility criteria included: Child-Pugh A or B7
        classification; Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group-performance status score 0-2; adequate
        bone marrow (leukocyte count &gt;3.0 ×109/L, hemoglobin &gt;8.0 g/L, and platelet count &gt;60
        ×109/L), liver (alanine aminotransferase and aspartate aminotransferase &lt;200 IU/mL), renal
        (creatinine &lt;1.5 times the upper limit of the normal range) and coagulation (international
        normalized ratio &lt;2.3) function.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria included a history of treatment with immune checkpoint inhibitors,
             allergies to immunetherapeutics, systemic immunosuppressive therapy, and ongoing or
             active infection, or an active autoimmune disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ming Zhao, MD, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510060</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ming Zhao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Nivolumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Pembrolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiofrequency Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Microwave ablation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

