<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03935464</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AI143340</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03935464</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Point-of-care Urine Monitoring of Adherence (PUMA): Testing a Real-Time Urine Assay of Tenofovir in PrEP</brief_title>
  <acronym>PUMA</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Trial to Examine the Feasibility, Acceptability and Impact of an Intervention Using a New Urine-based Tenofovir Adherence Assay</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kenya Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Worldwide expansion of pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) with oral tenofovir disoproxil
      fumarate/emtricitabine (TDF/FTC) will be critical to ending the HIV epidemic. However,
      maintaining daily adherence to PrEP can be difficult and the accuracy of self-reported
      adherence is often limited by social desirability bias. Pharmacologic adherence monitoring
      (measuring drug levels in a biomatrix) has been critical to the interpretation of the PrEP
      trials, but testing usually requires expensive equipment and skilled personnel. We have
      recently developed a point-of-care (POC) immunoassay to measure tenofovir in urine, allowing
      real-time adherence monitoring for the first time. We now want to test the acceptability,
      feasibility and preliminary impact of monitoring adherence in real-time using this novel POC
      assay with adherence feedback provided to the patient with supportive messaging (versus
      standard of care adherence counseling).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a pilot randomized trial to test the acceptability, feasibility, and impact on
      long-term adherence of implementing a POC urine tenofovir test to provide real-time adherence
      feedback among women on PrEP in Kenya. Eligible women (n=100) will be HIV-negative, ≥18 years
      old, and on PrEP. Participants will be randomized 1:1 to the intervention of providing
      real-time feedback via the urine assay versus standard-of-care adherence counseling.
      Acceptability will be assessed by a quantitative survey of participants at the end of the
      study, as well as by qualitative data collected via in-depth interviews (n=20) and focus
      group discussions (n=4 groups of 5-10 women each). Feasibility will be assessed by the
      proportion of women retained in the study, the mean number of missed visits, the proportion
      of planned urine assessments completed and messages delivered, while in-depth interviews with
      providers will explore the ease of administering the urine test. Tenofovir levels in hair
      serve as the long-term metric of adherence.

      Feasibility outcome: The investigators will assess the feasibility of the intervention by
      interviewing health care providers, who will be administering this test at the clinical point
      of care in the future. The investigators will examine provider perceptions of the assay using
      in-depth interviews. These key informant interviews will be performed at the end of this
      study with the healthcare providers (up to 8) who delivered the counseling messages to
      intervention arm participants after performing the POC urine TFV test. The semi-structured
      interview guide will draw from the Unified Theory of Acceptance and Use of Technology (UTAUT)
      model.200 This model incorporates factors that influence technology acceptance (in this case,
      of the POC immunoassay): perceived usefulness (performance expectancy), complexity to use
      (effort expectancy), stigma/social harm (social influence), and benefits (facilitating PrEP
      adherence among patients). These interviews will also elicit barriers and facilitators to
      delivering the TFV assay-informed counseling messages.

      Acceptability outcome: The investigators will conduct a mixed-methods assessment of the
      intervention arm participants' experiences with real-time monitoring and feedback at the end
      of the study. A quantitative survey and a qualitative interview guide for in-depth interviews
      of participants will draw from the Information-Motivation-Behavioral skills (IMB)
      model.205-212 Quantitative data collection will occur via standardized
      interviewer-administered questionnaires. Items to be assessed include the following: 1)
      Feelings about receiving their PrEP adherence results in real time; 2) Likelihood of
      participating in other studies using a similar design; 3) Likelihood of wanting to receive
      results of urine testing outside of a study while they are on PrEP; 4) Concern about the
      privacy and security of the data regarding their urine results; 5) Grading of the potential
      impact of knowing their urine TFV results on subsequent medication adherence; 6) Advantages
      and disadvantages of being told about their adherence in real time; 7) Likelihood of taking
      PrEP just before later study visits because they knew the urine test was being conducted; 8)
      Preferences regarding a yes/no assay versus an assay that provides information on &quot;high&quot;,
      &quot;moderate&quot; or &quot;low&quot; adherence. A 5-point Likert item format will be used to assess graded
      items (such as the likelihood of wanting continued urine testing in the context of PrEP;
      feelings about the urine testing, ranging from negative to positive; concerns about privacy,
      ranging from low to high; the potential impact of real-time feedback on subsequent adherence,
      ranging from low to high). Other items (advantages and disadvantages of being told about
      adherence results) will provide pre-specified options with one &quot;other&quot; option for open-ended
      text fields.

      Adherence outcome: A linear mixed effects linear regression model will estimate the effect of
      the intervention versus standard-of-care on logarithmically transformed levels of tenofovir
      in hair.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pilot Randomized Trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of POC urine TFV testing among women receiving PrEP</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Interviews of health care providers</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of POC urine TFV testing among women receiving PrEP</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative surveys and qualitative interviews of participants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure long-term adherence outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 0 (baseline), 3, 6, 9, and 12-month clinic visits after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Measure TFV and FTC levels in hair samples</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish preference for type of assay</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Via interviews with participants and providers assess if yes/no assay or assay with lines indicating high, moderate, or low adherence is preferred.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Risk Reduction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>POC adherence testing by a urine TFV assay with feedback</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Follow Kenya's PrEP guidelines on standard adherence counselling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PUMA</intervention_name>
    <description>Collect urine on intervention participants and screen for presence of TFV. Feedback will be provided to the participant based on the results on their adherence with provision of standard adherence counseling.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-negative women

          -  women ≥18 years old

          -  women receiving PrEP

          -  estimated creatinine clearance &gt;60 mL/min

          -  returning for a follow-up visit 3 months after PrEP initiation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV positive women

          -  under 18 years old
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women 18 years and above who are HIV-negative on PrEP</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monica Gandhi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monica Gandhi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>415 476 4082</phone>
    <phone_ext>127</phone_ext>
    <email>Monica.Gandhi@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Purba Chatterjee, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>4154766714</phone>
    <email>Purba.Chatterjee@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi M, Bacchetti P, Rodrigues WC, Spinelli M, Koss CA, Drain PK, Baeten JM, Mugo NR, Ngure K, Benet LZ, Okochi H, Wang G, Vincent M. Development and Validation of an Immunoassay for Tenofovir in Urine as a Real-Time Metric of Antiretroviral Adherence. EClinicalMedicine. 2018 Aug-Sep;2-3:22-28. doi: 10.1016/j.eclinm.2018.08.004. Epub 2018 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>30906930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi M, Bacchetti P, Spinelli MA, Okochi H, Baeten JM, Siriprakaisil O, Klinbuayaem V, Rodrigues WC, Wang G, Vincent M, Cressey TR, Drain PK. Brief Report: Validation of a Urine Tenofovir Immunoassay for Adherence Monitoring to PrEP and ART and Establishing the Cutoff for a Point-of-Care Test. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2019 May 1;81(1):72-77. doi: 10.1097/QAI.0000000000001971.</citation>
    <PMID>30664078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spinelli MA, Glidden DV, Rodrigues WC, Wang G, Vincent M, Okochi H, Kuncze K, Mehrotra M, Defechereux P, Buchbinder SP, Grant RM, Gandhi M. Low tenofovir level in urine by a novel immunoassay is associated with seroconversion in a preexposure prophylaxis demonstration project. AIDS. 2019 Apr 1;33(5):867-872. doi: 10.1097/QAD.0000000000002135.</citation>
    <PMID>30649051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PrEP, women, Kenya, adherence, POC monitoring, urine test, immunoassay, tenofovir</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will share de-identified data in publicly accessible databases once study is complete and study findings disseminated.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>48 months from start of study</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Investigators conducting PrEP research.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

