<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03930524</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00006421</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AA026574</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03930524</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adaptive Preventive Intervention for College Alcohol Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Adaptive Preventive Intervention to Optimize the Transition From Universal to Indicated Resources for College Student Alcohol Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research project is designed to promote health among first-year college students by
      implementing an adaptive sequence of preventive intervention strategies to motivate
      heavy-drinking college students to access existing resources in order to reduce high-risk
      alcohol use and negative consequences. If found efficacious, the adaptive preventive
      intervention (API) has the potential to reduce both the acute negative health consequences
      (e.g., injury, alcohol poisoning) and long-term health consequences (e.g., alcohol use
      disorders) of young adult alcohol use, while seeking to leverage technology in order to use
      campus resources in the most efficient way possible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      College student alcohol use and associated negative consequences are public health problems.
      In particular, first-year students transitioning to college are at increased risk. Scarce
      intervention resources must be used as wisely as possible to address these concerns. One way
      to address heavy drinking while conserving resources is to first utilize universal
      interventions, identify students at high risk who do not respond well, and then motivate them
      to engage in indicated intervention. This approach to prevention is 'adaptive' because
      information about the student in the course of the intervention (e.g., response status) is
      used to determine whether more resources should be invested to motivate the student to
      transition to indicated services. The purpose of this project is to implement adaptive
      preventive intervention (API) that employs cost-effective, technology-based brief
      interventions to do the following. First, provide a universal personalized normative feedback
      (PNF) intervention followed by student self-monitoring (SM). Second, motivate students who
      continue to drink heavily (i.e., 2+ reports of 4/5+ drinks for women/men, or 1 report of
      8/10+ drinks for women/men) to transition to additional intervention resources. To optimize
      the efficacy of this intervention, we will investigate the best timing for delivering the
      initial universal PNF+SM intervention (i.e., as an inoculation before moving to college vs.
      once they are experiencing the college context during their first semester). Additionally, we
      will examine how best to motivate heavy-drinking students to pursue indicated intervention
      (i.e., via automated emails vs. online interaction with a personal health coach using
      M-bridge). A sequential multiple assignment randomized trial (SMART) design will be used to
      address these questions. College students will be randomized to receive PNF either before
      college begins (2 weeks before classes start) or during the beginning of the first semester
      (about 3 weeks after they arrive on campus), followed by SM every two weeks during the first
      semester; these SM assessments will be used to identify heavy-drinking students who remain at
      risk. Once heavy drinking is identified, the student will be re-randomized to either an
      automated email or M-bridge health coach to offer indicated intervention resources. The
      specific aims are to examine: (1) the efficacy of the API compared to an assessment-only
      control, (2) whether the API can be optimized by altering the timing of the universal
      intervention and/or the type of message to motivate seeking indicated intervention, and (3)
      moderators of these effects (e.g., pre-college drinking intentions, high-intensity [compared
      to binge] drinking during the start of college). Frequency of heavy drinking, alcohol-related
      consequences, and health services utilization will be assessed prior to the start of classes,
      and at each follow-up point (the end of the semester, the end of the year, and the following
      fall). The API to be refined through this project will offer a novel strategy for mitigating
      both the acute negative health consequences (e.g., injury, alcohol poisoning) and long-term
      health consequences (e.g., alcohol use disorders) of young adult alcohol use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 25, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 25, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Sequential Multiple Assignment Randomized Trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Binge Drinking</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Respondents are asked about the frequency of consuming 4/5+ drinks within a two-hour period in the past 30 days. Questions are based on NIAAA recommended alcohol questions (https://www.niaaa.nih.gov/research/guidelines-and-resources/recommended-alcohol-questions) and Monitoring the Future survey items (http://www.monitoringthefuture.org/).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Young Adult Alcohol Consequences Questionnaire (B-YAACQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Respondents are asked 24 items derived from the 48-item Young Adult Alcohol Consequences Questionnaire. The Brief Young Adult Consequences Questionnaire (B-YAACQ; Read et al., 2006) has items that tap the full range of the alcohol problems continuum from signs of excessive drinking to symptoms consistent with alcohol abuse and alcohol dependence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Utilization of Health Services Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Respondents are asked about their utilization of various health services (e.g. healthcare clinics, therapy, support groups, self-help resources, etc.) in the last 3 months, including when they started, if they are currently utilizing the service/resource, and how helpful it has been.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Number of Drinks</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Respondents are asked about the maximum number of drinks consumed within a 24-hour period in the past 30 days. Question is based on NIAAA recommended alcohol questions (https://www.niaaa.nih.gov/research/guidelines-and-resources/recommended-alcohol-questions).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>7</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">891</enrollment>
  <condition>College Student Drinking</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Assessment Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Universal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prior to beginning their first semester of college, incoming students will receive personalized normative feedback (PNF) comparing their experiences to other college students their age, as well as up to 4 self-monitoring surveys over the course of the semester.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students from the early-college universal arm, who flag on one of the self monitoring surveys are invited to engage in a web-based resource or in-person consultation to improve well-being, with a particular emphasis on alcohol use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students from the early-college universal arm, who flag on one of the self monitoring surveys are invited to correspond with an online health coach who will use motivational interviewing strategies to encourage engagement in a web-based resource or in-person consultation to improve well-being, with a particular emphasis on alcohol use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Universal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After beginning their first semester of college, students will receive personalized normative feedback (PNF) comparing their experiences to other college students their age, as well as up to 4 self-monitoring surveys over the course of the semester.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students from the later-college universal arm, who flag on one of the self monitoring surveys are invited to engage in a web-based resource or in-person consultation to improve well-being, with a particular emphasis on alcohol use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students from the later-college universal arm, who flag on one of the self monitoring surveys are invited to correspond with an online health coach who will use motivational interviewing strategies to encourage engagement in a web-based resource or in-person consultation to improve well-being, with a particular emphasis on alcohol use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Personalized Normative Feedback (PNF)</intervention_name>
    <description>Personalized normative feedback is generated by a process in which: (1) baseline surveys gather respondent information; (2) a computer program links the data with algorithms to select feedback messages; (3) a format for feedback presentation is specified; and (4) the program generates output. Norms will focus on prevalence of drinking, consuming 4/5+ drinks, total number of drinks consumed each week, and maximum drinks consumed. Normative information will be from the national Monitoring the Future (MTF) study college student sample and the University of Minnesota Twin Cities campus. Students will be sent a link to a website where they see their own personal responses in the feedback. Feedback will detail quantity and frequency of drinking (a) reported by the participant him/herself, (b) according to the participant's perception of the descriptive norm for drinking quantity and frequency for the reference group, and (c) reflecting the actual descriptive norm for the reference group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Universal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Universal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>M-Bridge Online Health Coach</intervention_name>
    <description>A health coach will correspond with students via a secure online chat platform, utilizing motivational interviewing strategies to encourage students to consider their values and goals, the possibility of behavior change, and available services. The goal of the dialogue is to motivate the student to access alcohol use interventions (Web-BASICS or an in-person health promotion consultation).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Electronic Bridge to Mental Health Services (eBridge)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Web-BASICS</intervention_name>
    <description>Web-BASICS is delivered online and responds to individual participant input with the same motivational information and feedback as used in the in-person BASICS intervention. In-person BASICS content (Dimeff et. al., 1999) was developed for online use in studies conducted by Drs. Larimer and Lee (e.g., LaBrie et al., 2013; Lee et al., 2014; Neighbors et al., 2012a). Web-BASICS feedback contains text and graphical feedback regarding students' reported drinking quantity, frequency, peak alcohol consumption, and blood alcohol content (BAC), risks for alcohol problems based on participant family history and consumption patterns, protective behaviors the participant already uses and others he/she might consider, and a tips page with a BAC chart, information on reduced-risk drinking, and where to get more information. Participants can print and/or view their individualized content online for up to 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brief Alcohol Screening Intervention for College Students</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Promotion Consultation</intervention_name>
    <description>A health promotion consultation via a campus clinic is a confidential exploration of student drug and alcohol use. Health Promotion Consultants help students assess how their alcohol and other substance use affects their life and learn how to make healthier decisions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-Monitoring (SM)</intervention_name>
    <description>Students will be asked to self-report their alcohol use every 2 weeks in response to two main questions (frequency of 4/5+ drinking in the past 2 weeks, frequency of past 2-week 8/10+ drinking), as well as consequences of their drinking. The therapeutic role of SM is two-fold. First, SM facilitates deliberate attention to and reflection on the person's actions, the conditions under which these actions occur, and their consequences (Bandura, 1998; Kanfer, 1970). Hence, SM of drinking behaviors and consequences has the potential to promote awareness of problematic drinking and need for health services. Second, SM affords the opportunity to obtain ongoing information concerning the target behavior, which can be used to inform timely intervention decisions (Nahum-Shani et al., 2016)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Early-college Universal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college No Coach (automated email)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Later-college Universal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Incoming college students aged 18-21 at the University of Minnesota will be eligible
             and randomly selected for participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Megan Patrick, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Translational Research in Children's Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55415</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://doi.org/10.1080/08870449808407422</url>
    <description>Bandura, A. (1998). Health promotion from the perspective of social cognitive theory.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nahum-Shani I, Smith SN, Spring BJ, Collins LM, Witkiewitz K, Tewari A, Murphy SA. Just-in-Time Adaptive Interventions (JITAIs) in Mobile Health: Key Components and Design Principles for Ongoing Health Behavior Support. Ann Behav Med. 2018 May 18;52(6):446-462. doi: 10.1007/s12160-016-9830-8.</citation>
    <PMID>27663578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Labrie JW, Lewis MA, Atkins DC, Neighbors C, Zheng C, Kenney SR, Napper LE, Walter T, Kilmer JR, Hummer JF, Grossbard J, Ghaidarov TM, Desai S, Lee CM, Larimer ME. RCT of web-based personalized normative feedback for college drinking prevention: are typical student norms good enough? J Consult Clin Psychol. 2013 Dec;81(6):1074-86. doi: 10.1037/a0034087. Epub 2013 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23937346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee CM, Neighbors C, Lewis MA, Kaysen D, Mittmann A, Geisner IM, Atkins DC, Zheng C, Garberson LA, Kilmer JR, Larimer ME. Randomized controlled trial of a Spring Break intervention to reduce high-risk drinking. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2014 Apr;82(2):189-201. doi: 10.1037/a0035743. Epub 2014 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24491072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking in College</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

