<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03930836</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B403201316810c</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03930836</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementation of a New Motor Skill Learning Therapeutic Device in Children With Cerebral Palsy Rehabilitation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Implementation of a New Interactive Interface Applying Motor Skill Learning Principles to Generate Motor, Functional and Neuroplastic Changes During High and Low Dosage Interventions in Children With Cerebral Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université Catholique de Louvain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université Catholique de Louvain</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study of the efficiency of a new interactive interface to apply all the therapeutic
      principles of motor skill learning used in high dosage intensive interventions. Investigation
      of its effects on motor, functional and neuroplastic changes in children after high and low
      dosage intensive interventions using or not the interface.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Assisting Hand Assessments score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The Assisting Hand Assessment has been developped to measure and describe the efficacy of use of the affected hand of children with unilateral cerebral palsy bimanual activity performance. This is a standardized criterion-referenced test. It is conducted as a recorded semi-structured play session using specific objects usually used in a bimanual manner. With twenty-two test items, the child's performance is measured and obtain a sum score measure and a scaled score (percent scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline 6 Minutes Walking Test score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement developped to assess the exercise tolerance and walking abilities by asking the patient to walk as much as possible during 6 minutes in a 30 meters long corridor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Box and Blocks test score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Test measuring hand function through the number of blocks transported in 1 minute from one part an other of a box placed in front of the child. Each hand tested separately</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Jebsen-Taylor Test of Hand Function score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of hand function/dexterity, through 7 activities simulating daily life activities. Each hand is tested separately and time to complete each activity is reported using a stopwatch.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Modified Cooper test at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the stereognosis abilities.16 objects are placed in the hand and the child has to recognise the object only by touch. both hands are tested separately and time to recognise the objects is reported using a stopwatch</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline ABILHAND-Kids questionnaire score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire measuring performance of the child in daily life activities focusing on the upper extremities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline ACTIVLIM-CP questionnaire score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire measuring performance of the child in daily life activities focusing on upper and lower extremities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline ABILOCO-Kids questionnaire at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire measuring performance of the child in daily life activities focusing on the lower extremities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Pediatric Evaluation of Disability Inventory score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire measuring performance of the child in daily life activities focusing on the upper extremities and lower extremities. Only the self-care domain will be assessed here</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline Canadian Occupational Performance Measure scores at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The Canadian Occupational Performance Measure is a measure designed to capture the patient's self-perception of performance in everyday living, over time. It consist of a semi-structured interview were the patient elicits daily life activities performed with difficulties (self-care, nutrition, transfer, household management, school, work, transport, leisure, etc). Five activities are then chosen as the most important to improve and score on a 1 to 10 scale based on the actual patient's performance and satisfaction levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline MHAVIE-child questionnaire score at 1 week post-camp</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-camp (1 week before), post-camp (1 week after), 3 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire measuring social participation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>high/low dosage intervention, intensive or not (motor function rehabilitation)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>interface group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>high/low dosage intensive intervention using the interactive interface (motor function rehabilitation)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hand Arm Bimanual Intensive Therapy Including Lower Extremities</intervention_name>
    <description>Intensive intervention focusing on a constant bimanual coordination with a lower extremities and trunk control stimulation during play and functional activities. 50% of therapeutic time will be performed using the new interactive interface</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>interface group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional physical and occupational therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Conventional therapy (physical and occupational therapy) is mainly based on neurodevelopmental therapeutic principles. 50% of therapeutic time will be performed using the new interactive interface</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of unilateral cerebral palsy

          -  MACS level I, II or III

          -  GMFCS level I, II, III

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unstable seizure

          -  cognitive deficit that prevent understanding of simple games

          -  botulinic toxin injection, surgery, or another unusual intervention in the 6 months
             preceding the study and for the duration of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yannick Bleyenheuft, Pr</last_name>
    <phone>02 764 93 49</phone>
    <email>yannick.bleyenheuft@uclouvain.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Geoffroy Saussez, PhD student</last_name>
    <email>geoffroy.saussez@uclouvain.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Neuroscience, Université catholique de Louvain</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yannick Bleyenheuft, Pr</last_name>
      <email>yannick.bleyenheuft@uclouvain.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Geoffroy Saussez, PhD student</last_name>
      <email>geoffroy.saussez@uclouvain.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université Catholique de Louvain</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yannick Bleyenheuft</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>motor function</keyword>
  <keyword>motor skill learning</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

