<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03935295</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00110399</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03935295</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dysport ® as an Adjunctive Treatment to Bracing in the Management of Adolescent Idiopathic Scoliosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dysport ® (abobotulinumtoxinA) as an Adjunctive Treatment to Bracing in the Management of Adolescent Idiopathic Scoliosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the combined effect of botulinum toxin A (administered as Dysport®
      (Ipsen Pharmaceuticals)) and bracing in children with adolescent idiopathic scoliosis. Two
      thirds of patients will be treated with Dysport® and bracing, while the remaining patients
      will be treated with placebo and bracing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adolescent idiopathic scoliosis (AIS) is lateral curvature of the spine with an unknown cause
      in children 10-16 years old. Without treatment, skeletally immature children with idiopathic
      curves of 20°-40° risk curve progression. Treatment of these patients is focused on either
      observation or bracing. Although bracing has been shown to be more effective than
      observation, success is contingent on patient adherence and has the potential for further
      optimization with adjunct therapies.

      Little research is available concerning adjunct therapies that may be used during bracing of
      AIS patients. One therapy in particular, abobotulinumtoxinA (BTX) injection, has been poorly
      studied. Injection of BTX into the paraspinal musculature of the concave aspect of the major
      curve may result in a more malleable curve and thus optimize brace treatment. If BTX
      injections are found to improve outcomes in this way, a new standard of nonoperative care
      could be established for AIS patients, potentially reducing the number of patients who
      undergo surgery.

      The aim of this study is to assess whether BTX injections (administered as Dysport® (Ipsen
      Pharmaceuticals)) in the paraspinal musculature at the site of the major scoliotic curve
      decrease curve progression in skeletally immature AIS patients who are concurrently treated
      with bracing. Dysport® will be evaluated primarily as an adjunct treatment to bracing.

      Hypotheses

        1. Dysport® injections into the concave-side paraspinal muscles will decrease the rate of
           curve progression, with a lower rate of curve progression in patients treated with both
           Dysport® injections and bracing compared with those treated with only bracing.

        2. Quantitative physical and mental health scores will improve to a greater extent in
           patients treated with Dysport® and bracing compared with patients treated with only
           bracing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in scoliotic curve as assessed by the Major Curve Cobb Angle</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline (time 0), 6 weeks, 4 months, 4 months + 6 weeks, 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in scoliotic curve will be assessed using by the Major Curve Cobb Angle with measurement of standing scoliosis radiographs. Cobb angle refers to a radiographic measurement of side to side spinal curvature, measured in angle degrees.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient Reported Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline (time 0), 6 weeks, 4 months, 4 months + 6 weeks, 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by Scoliosis Research Society (SRS) 22 Survey; The SRS-22 questionnaire is a validated measure used to assesses quality of life in patients with idiopathic scoliosis. It consists of five domains that assess: function, pain, mental health, self-image, and satisfaction with treatment. Higher scores indicate increased satisfaction. Each of the 22 questions are scored on a scale of 1 to 5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Adolescent Idiopathic Scoliosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators plan to administer approximately 1000 U Dysport ® in the concave-sided paraspinal musculature of the major curve, based on an estimated total dose of 1000 U, the maximum allowable dose. The total dose per treatment session will not exceed 15 units/kilogram or 1000 units, whichever is lower. If two curves are equivalent within 3˚, both will be treated, however, the dosing (described above) will be divided equally across both curves.
There will be two cycles of injections. Patients will be treated at time 0 (baseline) and 4 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control patients will receive an injection of placebo specifically prepared as a control for this study. The same volumes as indicated in the &quot;experimental&quot; arm description will be injected.
These will be administered during two cycles of injections. Patients will be treated at time 0 (baseline) and 4 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AbobotulinumtoxinA</intervention_name>
    <description>Paraspinal abobotulinumtoxinA injections (compared to placebo)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dysport, Ipsen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo prepared by Ipsen for use as control</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Custom Thoracolumbosacral Orthosis</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-operative external bracing for scoliosis curves</description>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Clinically determined idiopathic nature of scoliosis

          -  Age 10-16 years

          -  Risser stage 0,1,or 2

          -  major curve of 20°-40°

          -  curve apex caudal to T7 vertebra

          -  ability to adhere to bracing protocol

          -  Botulinum toxin naïve or previously treated greater than 6 months prior to study entry

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of congenital scoliosis, neuromuscular scoliosis, or other &quot;reason&quot; for
             scoliosis - Previous surgery at any segment of the spine

          -  Current need for surgery at any level of the spine

          -  Treatment with any drug known to interfere with neuromuscular function

          -  Any other medical condition, laboratory or diagnostic procedure finding that might
             preclude administration of BTX

          -  Ongoing infection at the injection sites

          -  Diagnosis as either resistant or sensitive to botulinum toxin treatment of any type or
             to any components of the BTX formulation

          -  Cow milk protein allergy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Sponseller, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Hospital Department of Orthopaedic Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Varun Puvanesarajah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Hospital Department of Orthopaedic Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vivian Tran, BS</last_name>
    <phone>4109553136</phone>
    <email>vtran17@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Varun Puvanesarajah, MD</last_name>
    <phone>9193605646</phone>
    <email>vpuvane1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <link>
    <url>http://ipsenus.com/pdfs/Dysport_Full_Prescribing_Information.pdf</url>
    <description>Dysport Prescribing Information</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hresko MT. Clinical practice. Idiopathic scoliosis in adolescents. N Engl J Med. 2013 Feb 28;368(9):834-41. doi: 10.1056/NEJMcp1209063. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23445094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asher MA, Burton DC. Adolescent idiopathic scoliosis: natural history and long term treatment effects. Scoliosis. 2006 Mar 31;1(1):2.</citation>
    <PMID>16759428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstein SL. Idiopathic scoliosis. Natural history. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 1986 Oct;11(8):780-3.</citation>
    <PMID>3810292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstein SL, Dolan LA. The Evidence Base for the Prognosis and Treatment of Adolescent Idiopathic Scoliosis: The 2015 Orthopaedic Research and Education Foundation Clinical Research Award. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2015 Nov 18;97(22):1899-903. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.O.00330. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26582623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstein SL, Dolan LA, Wright JG, Dobbs MB. Effects of bracing in adolescents with idiopathic scoliosis. N Engl J Med. 2013 Oct 17;369(16):1512-21. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1307337. Epub 2013 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24047455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nuzzo RM, Walsh S, Boucherit T, Massood S. Counterparalysis for treatment of paralytic scoliosis with botulinum toxin type A. Am J Orthop (Belle Mead NJ). 1997 Mar;26(3):201-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9240788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong C, Gosvig K, Sonne-Holm S. The role of the paravertebral muscles in adolescent idiopathic scoliosis evaluated by temporary paralysis. Scoliosis Spinal Disord. 2017 Oct 10;12:33. doi: 10.1186/s13013-017-0138-7. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>29046898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kouwenhoven JW, Castelein RM. The pathogenesis of adolescent idiopathic scoliosis: review of the literature. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2008 Dec 15;33(26):2898-908. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181891751. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19092622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong C. Mechanism of right thoracic adolescent idiopathic scoliosis at risk for progression; a unifying pathway of development by normal growth and imbalance. Scoliosis. 2015 Jan 27;10:2. doi: 10.1186/s13013-015-0030-2. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25657814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>RIDDLE HF, ROAF R. Muscle imbalance in the causation of scoliosis. Lancet. 1955 Jun 18;268(6877):1245-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14382561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fidler MW, Jowett RL. Muscle imbalance in the aetiology of scoliosis. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1976 May;58(2):200-1.</citation>
    <PMID>932082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asher M, Min Lai S, Burton D, Manna B. The reliability and concurrent validity of the scoliosis research society-22 patient questionnaire for idiopathic scoliosis. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2003 Jan 1;28(1):63-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12544958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheung KM, Cheng EY, Chan SC, Yeung KW, Luk KD. Outcome assessment of bracing in adolescent idiopathic scoliosis by the use of the SRS-22 questionnaire. Int Orthop. 2007 Aug;31(4):507-11. Epub 2006 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>16896864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwieger T, Campo S, Weinstein SL, Dolan LA, Ashida S, Steuber KR. Body Image and Quality-of-Life in Untreated Versus Brace-Treated Females With Adolescent Idiopathic Scoliosis. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2016 Feb;41(4):311-9. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0000000000001210.</citation>
    <PMID>26555827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong C, Pedersen SA, Kristensen BB, Gosvig K, Sonne-Holm S. The Effect of Botulinum Toxin A Injections in the Spine Muscles for Cerebral Palsy Scoliosis, Examined in a Prospective, Randomized Triple-blinded Study. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2015 Dec;40(23):E1205-11. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0000000000001049.</citation>
    <PMID>26165216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AIS</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescent idiopathic scoliosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Scoliosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>abobotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

