<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03935867</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S15-01199</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03935867</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>New York University Falls Prevention Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>New York University (NYU) Falls Prevention Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Limited health services research and evidence-based programming has been focused on elderly
      fall prevention, despite high fall-related morbidity and mortality. Among NY's elderly
      population, falls account for nearly half of all older adults' injury-related deaths and are
      the 4th leading cause of hospitalizations. As fall risk increases with age, the magnitude of
      this health issue will continue to increase. Scientific evidence shows that prevention
      efforts significantly reduce the frequency and severity of falls. Research also suggests that
      multi-component intervention programs, such as Prevention Of Falls in the Elderly Trial,
      PROFET, are successful because benefits are derived from small improvements across several
      risk categories.

      The investigators propose expanding the reach of fall prevention efforts to at-risk and
      underserved populations of community-dwelling, older adults by delivering a home-based
      program -- C-PROFET, an adaptation of Prevention Of Falls in the Elderly Trial (PROFET), an
      evidence-based, multi-factorial, fall prevention program. Investigators will test two
      hypotheses: (1) Oral health care programs and services can be a portal for identifying
      underserved community dwelling elders at risk for falls who can benefit from a fall
      prevention program; and (2) Provision of fall prevention efforts to an at-risk clinical
      population before these patients experience a serious fall-related injury will reduce
      fall-risk, and potentially decrease fall-related morbidity, mortality, and healthcare costs.

      This initiative is to lay the necessary groundwork for larger implementation efforts that
      will advance efforts to reduce fall risk in vulnerable, community-dwelling older adults. The
      investigators propose to deliver C-PROFET to vulnerable, older adults identified through
      dental clinics and community oral health outreach services. The overall objectives are to
      improve patient-centered health outcomes, demonstrate feasibility of a multicomponent
      intervention to reduce/prevent fall-related morbidity and mortality in an at-risk,
      community-dwelling, clinical population, and disseminate this falls prevention program to
      community partner organizations to broadly translate these findings into clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Implementing innovative, cost-effective community-based delivery modalities that reliably and
      effectively deliver evidence-based, culturally-sensitive programs, proven to prevent injury,
      preserve function, improve quality of life, and reduce morbidity and mortality among an older
      and more diverse population, will significantly impact health costs and help address the
      anticipated surge in demand for health services and long-term care. Such efforts need to
      appeal to diverse populations and have outcomes achievable with a community delivery.

      This application is proposing to expand the reach of an evidence-based program, PROFET,
      developed for older adults who experienced a fall-related injury, to an at risk
      community-dwelling population who have not sustained a fall-related injury requiring medical
      intervention. The investigators hypothesize that oral health care programs and services can
      be a portal for identifying underserved community dwelling elders at risk for falls who can
      benefit from a fall prevention program. As more adults see their dentist than visit a
      physician in a given year, dental clinics, a safety net site for the delivery of oral health
      care to the elderly, are ideally situated to take an active role in injury prevention
      efforts. Dental clinics attached to community health centers and academic institutions have
      established linkages and referral patterns across systems of care and disciplines that can
      facilitate delivery of preventive services prior to an injury-sustaining event, delaying or
      preventing unintentional injuries. To date, fall prevention efforts have predominately
      targeted those who have already experienced an injury-sustaining fall. All older adults may
      profit from fall prevention interventions (regardless of whether they have experienced a
      fall-related serious injury). Expanding delivery to reach an at-risk population living in the
      community, will enable earlier intervention efforts to prevent/reduce falls, serious injury
      and hospital stays including a first serious fall which in and of itself increases risk for
      subsequent serious falls.

      The aims of this initiative are to: (1) adapt and deliver C-PROFET, an evidence-based,
      multifactor fall prevention program, to at-risk, community-dwelling older (65+),
      multi-ethnic, economically constrained, community residents (n=30) identified in
      non-traditional community settings (general dental clinic and community dental outreach
      program delivering oral health care to the elderly in community-based facilities, including
      senior centers); and (2) to assess the reach, uptake, feasibility and acceptability of the
      program. NYU College of Dentistry (NYUCD) dental clinic is a low cost community clinic
      providing quality dental care to the uninsured and those living on a restricted income. The
      clinic maintains over 300,000 patient visits annually and 17% of the patient population are
      65 and older. Examination of the utility of the dental clinic and dental outreach program as
      a portal for fall prevention programs will be guided by the RE-AIM framework consisting of
      five core elements: (1) Reach (&quot;How do investigators reach the targeted population?&quot;); (2)
      Effectiveness (&quot;How do investigators know the program is effective?); (3) Adoption (&quot;How
      effective is this program in different settings?&quot;); (4) Implementation (&quot;How do investigators
      ensure that the program is delivered consistently?&quot;); (5) Maintenance (&quot;How do investigators
      incorporate the program so that it is delivered over the long term?&quot;).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 29, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A change in environmental falls-related risk factors in the home</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A Home Hazards and Safety Assessment will be conducted to identify any fall-related hazards in the home by the C-PROFET. An Occupational Therapist will discuss with the subject the results and recommended changes to the home to minimize the risk of future falls. A brief follow-up telephone survey will be conducted within three months of the home visit to assess the participant's adherence and barriers to fall prevention recommendations and referral follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Falls Related Risk Factors in the Elderly</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C-PROFET group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Community-dwelling, older adults participating in a home-based program -- C-PROFET, our adaptation of Prevention Of Falls in the Elderly Trial (PROFET).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C-PROFET</intervention_name>
    <description>An expansion of the evidence-based, multi-factorial, fall prevention program PROFET (Prevention Of Falls in the Elderly Trial), developed for older adults who experienced a fall-related injury, to an at risk community-dwelling population who have not sustained a fall-related injury requiring medical intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>C-PROFET group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Is 65 years of age or older

          2. Lives in the New York metropolitan area

          3. Lives in a private residence or assisted living apartment

          4. Understands English

          5. Has one or more fall risk factors

          6. Has not had a prior fall-related injury requiring emergency care

          7. Is cognitively competent and has the capacity to give consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has had a prior fall related injury requiring emergency care

          2. Will be unavailable for a home visit within the next 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victoria H. Raveis, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Victoria H. Raveis, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-998-9805</phone>
    <email>victoria.raveis@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Monique Carrero-Tagle, MS</last_name>
    <phone>212-998-9881</phone>
    <email>monique.carrero@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University College of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Victoria H. Raveis, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>212-998-9805</phone>
      <email>victoria.raveis@nyu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Monique Carrero-Tagle, MS</last_name>
      <phone>212-998-9881</phone>
      <email>monique.carrero@nyu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Close J, Ellis M, Hooper R, Glucksman E, Jackson S, Swift C. Prevention of falls in the elderly trial (PROFET): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 1999 Jan 9;353(9147):93-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10023893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Northridge ME, Nevitt MC, Kelsey JL, Link B. Home hazards and falls in the elderly: the role of health and functional status. Am J Public Health. 1995 Apr;85(4):509-15.</citation>
    <PMID>7702114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

