<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03938168</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-4801</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03938168</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Histological and Molecular Mechanisms of Pain in Patient With Chronic Pain From Adhesions</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAIN PAD</acronym>
  <official_title>PAIN PAD Histological and Molecular Mechanisms of Pain in Patient With Chronic Pain From Adhesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maas Hospital Pantein</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      11-20% of patients undergoing abdominal surgery develop chronic abdominal pain. Adhesions are
      a common cause of chronic pain following surgery. Adhesions develop after up to 90% of
      laparotomies and 70% of laparoscopic surgeries. Obviously, not all adhesions cause pain. It
      is still poorly understood why adhesions cause pain in some patients, while other patients
      with adhesions experience no pain.

      In this study we explore possible mechanism through which adhesions might cause pain. For
      this purpose we will assess expression of molecular mediators (such as TRPV-1, SP, and the
      neurokinin receptor), histological characteristics, and fecal microbioma that might be
      associated with pain.Expression of these factor will be compared to sample from 30 patients
      with chronic pain attributed to adhesions, and 30 patients undergoing a reoperation with
      adhsiolysis for reasons unrelated to pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction and rationale:

      11-20% of patients undergoing abdominal surgery develop chronic abdominal pain. Adhesions are
      the most common cause of chronic abdominal complaints after surgery. Chronic pain from
      adhesions has devastating consequences for quality of life, and one in three patients with
      pain from adhesions is opioid dependent.

      Adhesions develop after up to 90% of laparotomies and 70% of laparoscopic surgeries.
      Obviously, not all adhesions cause pain. It is still poorly understood why adhesions cause
      pain in some patients, while other patients with adhesions experience no pain.

      In a recent study we demonstrated that in selected patients adhesion-related pain can
      effectively be treated by operation with adhesiolysis and application of an adhesion barrier.
      However, almost 50% part of patients with adhesion-related pain are not considered a
      candidate for surgical treatment, for various reasons.

      Exploring the mechanisms that contribute to development of pain in patients with adhesions
      could provide novel targets for medical therapies. These could greatly benefit many patients
      suffering from adhesion- related pain. Two factors that might explain why some patients with
      adhesions develop chronic pain are activation of molecular mechanisms involved in chronic
      pain and stimulation of nerve fibers present in adhesions. Specifically type C nerve fibres
      are associated with development of neuropathic pain. Further we will also explore differences
      in microbioma, which has recently been demonstrated to have an important role in a variety of
      abdominal conditions.

      Adhesion formation at the molecular level involves a complex interaction of mediators. One
      such mediator that might link adhesion formation to nociception is the pro-inflammatory
      peptide substance P.(1) Substance P in turn is mediated by Transient Receptor Potential
      Vanilloid (TRPV1), which is known to be upregulated in many conditions associated with
      chronic pain. There is currently much research in developing new analgesics targeting this
      receptor. Previous studies have shown that nerve fibres can be present in adhesive tissue.
      Presence of such fibres, and especially type C fibres might be responsible for a neuropathic
      type of pain. Stimulation of TRPV1 might also activate type C nerve fibre endings.

      Objective:

      Quantify and compare expression of molecular mediators (such as TRPV-1, SP, and the
      neurokinin receptor) and histological characteristics of adhesions from patients with
      postoperative adhesions with and without chronic abdominal pain. Comparison of microbioma in
      fecal samples between patients with adhesions with and without chronic abdominal pain

      Study design:

      This is a prospective observational cohort study.

      Study population:

      30 patients eligible for adhesiolysis because of chronic adhesion-related pain. Patients are
      recruited at the RadboudUMC, MUMC+ and Pantein hospital departments of surgery. These are
      patients with chronic pain after previous abdominal surgery who have been selected for
      operative treatment after evaluated with CineMRI. CineMRI is used to map adhesions. This
      technique has been established to provide insight in localization of adhesions in relation to
      the pain, and risk of bowel injury based on extensiveness of adhesions. The control group
      will comprise of 30 patients undergoing an abdominal reoperation during which adhesiolysis
      has to be performed for reasons other than chronic adhesion-related pain.

      Study procedures:

      Prior to surgery patients are requested to take a stool sample. During surgery histological
      samples of adhesions will be taken during adhesiolysis in both groups. In the control group
      histological samples of adhesions will only be taken if it does not require extension of the
      incision and if it is not accompanied with additional risk of intraoperative complications
      other than necessary for their planned surgery.

      Main study parameters/endpoints:

      Primary outcome mRNA expression levels of TRPV1 by quantitative polymerase chain reaction
      (qPCR) compared between patients with and without chronic pain. Secondary outcomes are TRPV1
      protein levels (measured by Westernblot), SP, and neurokinin expression, and the amount and
      types of nerve fibres found at histological assessment. Further we will explore microbioma in
      feca samples.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness:

      Taking fecal and histological samples for this study does not result in additional operative
      risk. Adhesiolysis is often performed during any type of abdominal reoperation. Histological
      samples in controls are only taken from adhesions that are easily accessible and not from
      dense adhesions in close proximity to bowel or other vulnerable organs. No additional
      adhesiolysis apart from biopsy will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TRPV-1</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>mRNA expression levels of TRPV1 by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TRPV-1 protein</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>TRPV1 protein levels (measured by Westernblot)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SP</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Substance P</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NK-1</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Neurokinin 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nerve fibers</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Histological assessment for the presence of nerve fibers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbioma</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fecal microbioma pre-operative and at 12 months after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Tissue Adhesion</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>30 patients eligible for adhesiolysis because of chronic adhesion-related pain. Patients are recruited at the RadboudUMC, MUMC+ and Pantein hospital departments of surgery. These are patients with chronic pain after previous abdominal surgery who have been selected for operative treatment after evaluated with CineMRI. CineMRI is used to map adhesions. This technique has been established to provide insight in localization of adhesions in relation to the pain, and risk of bowel injury based on extensiveness of adhesions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The control group will comprise of 30 patients undergoing an abdominal reoperation during which adhesiolysis has to be performed for reasons other than chronic adhesion-related pain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biopsy, fecal sample</intervention_name>
    <description>Preoperatively and at 12 months after surgery, patients will obtain a fecal stool sample for microbioma analysis. Adhesions that are cut and released to acquire access to the operative field are stored for molecular and histological analyses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pain patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Samples from adhesions are taken. Fecal samples are taken for microbioma analysis.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Chronic abdominal pain after surgery is a frequent condition.(13) At present the
        RadboudUMC, MUMC+, and Pantein hospital departments of surgery annually evaluate 60-80
        patients each for chronic pain by cineMRI. Between 30-40 of these patients are expected to
        undergo surgical treatment. Yearly between 600-700 patients will undergo an elective
        abdominal reoperation at the participating departments of surgery. Thus there is ample
        surgical volume for this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        In order to be eligible to participate patients with chronic pain, must meet all of the
        following criteria:

          -  Abdominal pain for more than 12 months after last surgery

          -  Insufficient improvement of pain after conservative treatments for at least 6 months

          -  Pre-operative work-up with cineMRI showing expected beneficial outcomes of
             adhesiolysis, in accordance to our current standard practice for adhesion-related
             pain.

        Inclusion criteria for controls:

          -  Patients between 18 and 75 years old scheduled for elective abdominal reoperation

          -  No present chronic abdominal pain

          -  No other diseases or syndromes that cause chronic pain (e.g. rheumatic arthritis)

        Exclusion criteria

        A potential subject with chronic pain will be excluded from participation in this study in
        the following cases:

          -  Contra-indications for general anaesthesia and re-operation

          -  Inability to acquire informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard P ten Broek, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harry van Goor, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard P ten Broek, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard P ten Broek, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31243611111</phone>
    <email>Richard.tenBroek@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Martijn W Stommel, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <email>Martijn.Stommel@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maasziekenhuis Pantein</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boxmeer</city>
        <state>Gelderland</state>
        <zip>5830 AB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Floris Ferenschild</last_name>
      <email>F.Ferenschild@Pantein.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <state>Gelderland</state>
        <zip>6500HB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard P ten Broek, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+31243611111</phone>
      <email>Richard.tenBroek@radboudumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Martijn W Stommel, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+31243611111</phone>
      <email>Martijn.Stommel@radboudumc.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht Universitair Medisch Centrum+</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>6202 AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicole D Bouvy, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>n.bouvy@mumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Beukel BAW, Stommel MWJ, van Leuven S, Strik C, IJsseldijk MA, Joosten F, van Goor H, Ten Broek RPG. A Shared Decision Approach to Chronic Abdominal Pain Based on Cine-MRI: A Prospective Cohort Study. Am J Gastroenterol. 2018 Aug;113(8):1229-1237. doi: 10.1038/s41395-018-0158-9. Epub 2018 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29946174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reed KL, Fruin AB, Bishop-Bartolomei KK, Gower AC, Nicolaou M, Stucchi AF, Leeman SE, Becker JM. Neurokinin-1 receptor and substance P messenger RNA levels increase during intraabdominal adhesion formation. J Surg Res. 2002 Nov;108(1):165-72.</citation>
    <PMID>12443729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ten Broek RP, Issa Y, van Santbrink EJ, Bouvy ND, Kruitwagen RF, Jeekel J, Bakkum EA, Rovers MM, van Goor H. Burden of adhesions in abdominal and pelvic surgery: systematic review and met-analysis. BMJ. 2013 Oct 3;347:f5588. doi: 10.1136/bmj.f5588. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24092941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keszthelyi D, Troost FJ, Jonkers DM, Helyes Z, Hamer HM, Ludidi S, Vanhoutvin S, Venema K, Dekker J, Szolcsányi J, Masclee AA. Alterations in mucosal neuropeptides in patients with irritable bowel syndrome and ulcerative colitis in remission: a role in pain symptom generation? Eur J Pain. 2013 Oct;17(9):1299-306. doi: 10.1002/j.1532-2149.2013.00309.x. Epub 2013 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23529955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scotland RS, Chauhan S, Davis C, De Felipe C, Hunt S, Kabir J, Kotsonis P, Oh U, Ahluwalia A. Vanilloid receptor TRPV1, sensory C-fibers, and vascular autoregulation: a novel mechanism involved in myogenic constriction. Circ Res. 2004 Nov 12;95(10):1027-34. Epub 2004 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>15499026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tissue Adhesions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will be shared upon reasonable request through DANS easy archive</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>12 months after publication of primary results</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

