<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03931824</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRP-HSP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03931824</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy Of Platelet Rich Plasma In The Treatment Of Hemiplegıc Shoulder Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy Of Platelet Rich Plasma In The Treatment Of Hemiplegıc Shoulder Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ege University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ege University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study assessing whether platelet rich plasma injections(PRP) are effective in the
      management hemiplegic shoulder pain, 55 patients with hemiplegic shoulder pain was recruited
      to this randomized controlled study. Patients were randomized into two groups, first getting
      PRP injections, and other group taking sham injections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 7, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 18, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 18, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Solutions were prepared by an investigator, and injectors were coated with an opaque layer in order to conceal the content from both the one performing the injection and the patients. Data was then analyzed by an investigator who was blind to the study groups</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analogous Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Analogous Scales for pain were used as outcome measures. Both resting and activity pain levels were evaluated. Patients were asked to describe their pain, level of disability or treatment satisfaction on a 10 cm long line, with 0 point being &quot;none&quot;, and 10 cm point being &quot;highest possible&quot;. The proximity of the marked point to the 0 end was measured, and the results were recorded</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Shoulder ranges of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Shoulder range of motions were also evaluated as outcome measures. The measurements were done accordingly to the guidelines of American College of Orthopedic Surgeons by a conventional goniometer(20, 21). The researcher who performed the measurements was an experienced in this field, and was blinded to the treatment groups. External and internal rotation, adduction, abduction, flexion and extension of both shoulders were recorded for each group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Independence Measure(FIM)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Independence Measure(FIM) is used to evaluate independence for the activities of daily living. It was developed to measure the results of the rehabilitation on the patient, and Turkish version of the tool shown to be valid and reliable in 2001. Having motor and cognitive subscales, the higher scores in FIM are interpreted as better functional independence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Shoulder Pain</condition>
  <condition>Shoulder Impingement</condition>
  <condition>Hemiplegia, Infantile</condition>
  <condition>Shoulder Subluxation</condition>
  <condition>Spasticity, Muscle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PRP group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A venous blood sample of 8.5 ml were obtained from patients. For the study group, the blood samples were mixed with 1.5 ml ACD-A or sodium citrate to achieve anticoagulation. Resulting material was then centrifugated for 5 minutes with RCF 1200 G speed to clump erythrocytes, and then centrifugated for 10 minutes in same speed to obtain thrombocyte concentrate. 2 ml's of the platelet rich plasma was injected to the shoulder of the subjects. For the sham injection group, same amount of blood was taken and they were given a of waiting time of same duration with the study group, with the resulting preparate being 2 ml's of 0,9% saline instead. PRP solutions were prepared with kits of Easy PRP(Neotec Biotechnology, Istanbul, Turkey).
Injections were done every two weeks, for a total of 3 times.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injections containing saline were done every two weeks, for a total of 3 times. 21 G injection needles with injection technique of posterior approach were used. To provide blindness, all injections were done using injectors coated with non transparent tape. All of the PRP injections were done by the same physician each time, with compliance to preventive measures against complications such as infections. Patients and the physician who applied the injection were blinded to the groups, and the solution was prepared by another researcher who was not blind to the groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PRP</intervention_name>
    <description>A venous blood sample of 8.5 ml were obtained from patients. For the study group, the blood samples were mixed with 1.5 ml ACD-A or sodium citrate to achieve anticoagulation. Resulting material was then centrifugated for 5 minutes with RCF 1200 G speed to clump erythrocytes, and then centrifugated for 10 minutes in same speed to obtain thrombocyte concentrate. 2 ml's of the platelet rich plasma was injected to the shoulder of the subjects. For the sham injection group, same amount of blood was taken and they were given a of waiting time of same duration with the study group, with the resulting preparate being 2 ml's of 0,9% saline instead. PRP solutions were prepared with kits of Easy PRP(Neotec Biotechnology, Istanbul, Turkey).
Injections were done every two weeks, for a total of 3 times. 21 G injection needles with injection technique of posterior approach were used(18, 19). To provide blindness, all injections were done using injectors coated with non transparent tape.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRP group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Platelet rich plasma injections</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>All of the patients were also informed about proper positioning and the standard care for the affected extremity. Their process of neurological rehabilitation was not changed, which was 5 days of the week, one session of 45 minutes a day. They were also given a program of standardized ROM exercises, which included passive and active motions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRP group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rehabilitation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria were being an adult stroke patient with more than two weeks of
             shoulder pain and restriction, and not having a history of stroke before the recent
             incident.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with aphasia, severe cognitive or psychiatric disorders, history of trauma,
             recent injection (&lt;3 months) or surgery on the affected joint, complex regional pain
             syndrome, infections, pregnancy, thrombocytopenia(&lt;150000 per microliter) or
             coagulation disorders or severe spasticity of the affected limb(Modified Ashworth
             Scale &gt;3) were excluded from the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ege university school of medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izmir</city>
        <zip>35100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ege University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hale Karapolat</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor in Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Shoulder Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemiplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Shoulder Subluxation</keyword>
  <keyword>Spasticity</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Impingement Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemiplegia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

