<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03933436</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FWH20190009H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03933436</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EPIC: Effect of Povidone Iodine Periurethral Cleansing on Level of Contamination With Clean Catch</brief_title>
  <official_title>EPIC: Effect of Povidone Iodine Periurethral Cleansing on Level of Contamination With Clean Catch: A Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Travis Callahan</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mike O'Callaghan Military Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this study is to see if the use of an antiseptic preparation (povidone
      iodine) versus cold normal saline, will decrease rates of urine contamination during the
      non-invasive Quick Wee (QW) collection of pediatric urine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Urinary tract infections (UTI) are common acute illnesses among pediatric patients,
      accounting for 5-7% of emergency department visits in the under two-year-old population.
      However, obtaining urine samples from the precontinent patient can be difficult. There is an
      ongoing debate regarding which noninvasive method for urine specimen collection is best for
      this population. The main argument against clean catch is the high rate of contamination
      compared to invasive collection and reliability.

      There are many methods of noninvasive urine collection. These methods are preferred as they
      are fairly well tolerated by patients, less distressing to parents, cost effective, and
      require less technical expertise. In the past; these methods have been dismissed due to their
      high rates of contamination, time to void and also effectiveness. The National Institute of
      Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE, UK) recommends a clean-catch urine (CCU) be the first
      attempt at obtaining a urine specimen from children suspected of having UTI. This means
      placing the urine specimen collection container into the urine mid-stream once the child has
      begun to void to avoid contamination. Conversely, the American Academy of Pediatrics
      recommends clean catch urine for screening and a catheter specimen urine collection or
      suprapubic aspiration for definitive diagnosis. Both of these invasive techniques produce
      quick urine samples with low rates of contamination; however they can be painful and
      distressing to both the patient and parent.

      The Quick-Wee method for noninvasive urine collection has been evaluated in a one randomized
      controlled trial and has been shown to significantly increase the five minute voiding success
      rate for CC urine collection; 31%, n= 174. However a past study demonstrated contamination
      rate of 27%, n=174. No study has directly evaluated the use of antiseptic solution in the
      evaluation of the QW rate of contamination in pediatric patients. The purpose of this study
      is to see whether the use of povidone iodine swabs prior to the QW method will decrease the
      rate of contamination. A decrease of the rate of contamination would strengthen the validity
      of this simple CCU method. Also using the this method for the collection method in both the
      experimental and control groups will further evaluated the five min void success rate.

      The investigators chose to use iodine as the prepping agent because it is currently the
      standard cleaning solution used for adult and pediatric patients. It is readily available,
      inexpensive and has been shown to be less caustic then other prepping agents.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 28, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participant samples indicating urine contamination</measure>
    <time_frame>24 to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no outcome of detection of microbial markers to determine level of contamination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who void urine</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no outcome of voiding urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Urine Contamination</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iodine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Iodine swabs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline flush.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iodine swabs.</intervention_name>
    <description>Children will then have their periurethral region gently cleansed for ten seconds with iodine swabs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iodine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline flush.</intervention_name>
    <description>Children will then have their periurethral region gently cleansed for ten seconds with saline flush.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        **Patients must be able to get care at Nellis Air Force Base (a military installation) in
        order to participate in this study**

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  DoD children aged one month (28 days) to 12 months (365 days) (if the child was born
             less than 36 weeks gestation, age will be corrected)

          -  Precontinent (meaning that the child is unable to void on command)

          -  Treating clinician has determined that the child requires urine sample collection for
             course of treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  If the treating clinician has determined that there is a need for immediate treatment
             and urine sample collection via invasive method, any type of anatomical or neurologic
             condition that will affect the ability to void or sensation of the suprapubic area.

          -  Children with past hypersensitivity reactions to iodine swabs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul F Crawford, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Mike O'Callaghan Military Medical Center, 99MDG, US Air Force</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mike O'Callaghan Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89191</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw KN, Gorelick M, McGowan KL, Yakscoe NM, Schwartz JS. Prevalence of urinary tract infection in febrile young children in the emergency department. Pediatrics. 1998 Aug;102(2):e16.</citation>
    <PMID>9685461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Collaborating Centre for Women's and Children's Health (UK). Urinary Tract Infection in Children: Diagnosis, Treatment and Long-term Management. London: RCOG Press; 2007 Aug.</citation>
    <PMID>21290637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Practice parameter: the diagnosis, treatment, and evaluation of the initial urinary tract infection in febrile infants and young children. American Academy of Pediatrics. Committee on Quality Improvement. Subcommittee on Urinary Tract Infection. Pediatrics. 1999 Apr;103(4 Pt 1):843-52. Erratum in: 2000 Jan;105(1 Pt 1):141. Pediatrics 1999 May;103(5 Pt 1):1052, 1999 Jul;104(1 Pt 1):118.</citation>
    <PMID>10103321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mike O'Callaghan Military Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Travis Callahan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>April 4, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/36/NCT03933436/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 22, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/36/NCT03933436/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

