<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04356066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>zahraa</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04356066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CXCL10 As a Biomarker Of ILD in Patients WithRA</brief_title>
  <official_title>CXCL10 As a Biomarker Of Interstitial Lung Disease in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis is a chronic inﬂammatory disease that affects the joints, causing
      symmetric pain, stiffness, swelling, and limited motion and function of multiple joints, its
      ﬁbro inﬂammatory manifestations may develop in other organs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis is complicated by lung manifestations, such as interstitial lung disease
      which is the most common cause of morbidity and mortality in rheumatoid arthritis patients.
      Rheumatoid arthritis-interstitial lung disease is a progressive fibrotic disease of the lung
      parenchyma that includes a broad spectrum of disorders such as nonspeciﬁc interstitial
      pneumonia, usual interstitial pneumonia , desquamative interstitial pneumonia, cryptogenic
      organizing pneumonia, diﬀuse alveolar damage, acute interstitial pneumonia, and lymphocytic
      interstitial pneumonia . Rheumatoid arthritis-interstitial lung disease in which available
      data indicate that dysregulated inflammatory cascades can elaborate a host of cytokines,
      chemokines, and growth factors that collectively promote epithelial and endothelial cell
      damage, angiogenesis, fibroblast differentiation/proliferation, and lung fibrosis . Given the
      clinical implications of putative signaling cascades involved in these processes, biomarkers
      that can be used to clarify disease pathogenesis and identify factors governing disease
      progression are clearly needed .
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 19, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 19, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 19, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CXCL10 As a Biomarker Of Interstitial Lung Disease in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>serum level</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Interstitial Lung Disease in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adult Rheumatoid Arthritis Patient with Interstitial Lung Dise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>History taking: age, sex, disease duration, history of present illness, drug intake, past and family history.
Physical examination including thorough clinical examination.
Health assessment questionnaire-disability index (HAQ-DI): It is used as a subjective measure of physical function of RA patients (Pincus et al., 1983). There are 20 items in 8 categories: dressing, rising, eating, walking, hygiene, reach, grip, and usual activities (Jessica et al., 2018).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>serum cxcl10 by ELISA</intervention_name>
    <description>serum sample</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adult Rheumatoid Arthritis Patient with Interstitial Lung Dise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult rheumatoid arthritis patients who fulfilled the 2010 American College of
             Rheumatology/European league against rheumatism criteria for the classification of
             Rheumatoid Arthritis.

          2. Adult rheumatoid arthritis patients with interstitial lung disease.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individuals with other autoimmune diseases (systemic lupus erythematosus,
             polyarteritis nodosa, dermatomyositis, scleroderma, spondyloarthritis and inflammatory
             bowel disease).

          2. Individuals with hepatitis, Rhinovirus infection, cerebral malaria.

          3. Individuals with colorectal carcinoma, syndrome of frailty, vetiligo.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Naima Mohamed Mostafa, professor doctor</last_name>
    <phone>01223947372</phone>
    <email>naimamohamed21@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Samar Hassanein Goma, Ass Prof</last_name>
    <phone>01061828586</phone>
    <email>Samarhassanein2010@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>1. Chen J, Doyle TJ, Liu Y, et al. Biomarkers of rheumatoid arthritis-associated interstitial lung disease. Arthritis Rheumatol. 2015;67(1):28-38. doi:10.1002/art.38904 2. Richards TJ, Eggebeen A, Gibson K, et al. Characterization and peripheral blood biomarker assessment of anti-Jo-1 antibody-positive interstitial lung disease. Arthritis Rheum. 2009;60(7):2183-2192. doi:10.1002/art.24631 3. Amigues I, Ramadurai D, Swigris JJ. Current Perspectives On Emerging Biomarkers For Rheumatoid Arthritis-Associated Interstitial Lung Disease. Open Access Rheumatol. 2019;11:229-235. Published 2019 Oct 15. doi:10.2147/OARRR.S166070 4. Vij R, Strek ME. Diagnosis and treatment of connective tissue disease-associated interstitial lung disease. Chest. 2013;143(3):814-824. doi:10.1378/chest.12-0741 5. Castelino FV, Varga J. Interstitial lung disease in connective tissue diseases: evolving concepts of pathogenesis and management. Arthritis Res Ther. 2010;12(4):213. doi:10.1186/ar3097 6. Laragione T, Brenner M, Sherry B, Gulko PS. CXCL10 and its receptor CXCR3 regulate synovial fibroblast invasion in rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Rheum. 2011;63(11):3274-3283. doi:10.1002/art.30573 7. Gao B, Lin J, Jiang Z, et al. Upregulation of chemokine CXCL10 enhances chronic pulmonary inflammation in tree shrew collagen-induced arthritis. Sci Rep. 2018;8(1):9993. Published 2018 Jul 3. doi:10.1038/s41598-018-28404-y</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elzahraa Awny Fathy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Interstitial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

