<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04351048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>70198063-050.06.0416-12.1/12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04351048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stepwise and One Step Techniques In Deep Dentin Lesion</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Evaluation of Stepwise and One Step Excavation Techniques In The Management of Deep Dentin Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>TIJEN PAMIR</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ege University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This double blind, randomized, controlled clinical trial aimed to observe the success of
      stepwise (SW) and one step (OneS) excavation techniques in the management of deep dentin
      caries. Additionally, evaluation of glass ionomer cement (GIC) as temporary restorative was
      also performed. For this purpose, forty participants were selected among the routine patients
      coming to university clinic. A permanent tooth having caries lesions penetrating to 75
      percentage or more of dentin of patient were included. Randomization to SW and OneS groups
      were organized by coin method. The periphery of the cavities including enamel-dentin junction
      was cleaned until reach to hard dentin. Afterwards, selective removal to soft dentin on the
      pulpal side of the cavities was applied manually excavation and covered with pure calcium
      hydroxide and zinc oxide eugenol cement. GIC was used for temporary filling. This process was
      implemented both the first stage excavation of SW and OneS groups. Clinical and radiographic
      evaluations were performed at 6 months according to clinical signs and symptoms and
      radiographic sings using Periapical Index (PAI). Besides, temporary restorations were
      evaluated according to the of Ryge/Modified USPHS criteria. Following this evaluation, on the
      SW group, the cavities was re-entered and selective removal was applied up to firm dentin and
      pulp-capping were applied as mentioned above. In OneS group, temporary restoration was
      reduced as a base. All of the cavities were permanently restored with resin composite. Whole
      procedure was completed at one centre by a specialist, and control sessions was performed two
      experienced experts. Participants and experts were blinded in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 12, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulpal Success Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>a 6-month periods</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of vitality in treated tooth with positive response to electrical and thermal stimuli, no history of spontaneous pain and no response to percussion and pain (sensitivity) sign in palpation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Status of Periapical Tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>a 6-month periods</time_frame>
    <description>According to Orstavik' Periapical Index (PAI), scoring with PAI 1 or PAI 2 refer to healthy tooth</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Caries, Dental Pulp Exposure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stepwise excavation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OneS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>one step excavation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stepwise Excavation</intervention_name>
    <description>stepwise excavation includes selective caries removal to soft dentine on pulpal wall in the first stage of the excavation and
after six months, the second stage of intervention includes re-entring the cavities and wall selective removal to firm dentine on pulpal wall.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SW</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>One Step Excavation</intervention_name>
    <description>*one step excavations is completed in the first stage via performing selective removal to soft dentine on pulpal wall of the cavities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OneS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Molar teeth with primary caries lesion prolonged of 75 percentage or more of dentin
             radiographically1 Existence of vitality with positive response to

               -  electrical pulp test and

               -  cold test

          -  No history of spontaneous pain on the teeth

          -  No sign of pain on percussion and palpation (sensitivity)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals with the systemic disease who require hospitalization (oncological
             treatment, transplantation patients)

          -  Patients with uncontrolled hyperglycaemia or using insulin

          -  Patients with pregnancy/suspected

          -  Observation of radiolucency in the apex of the relevant tooth (PAI&gt; 2)

          -  Secondary decayed teeth
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tijen Pamir, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ege University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Innes NP, Frencken JE, Bjørndal L, Maltz M, Manton DJ, Ricketts D, Van Landuyt K, Banerjee A, Campus G, Doméjean S, Fontana M, Leal S, Lo E, Machiulskiene V, Schulte A, Splieth C, Zandona A, Schwendicke F. Managing Carious Lesions: Consensus Recommendations on Terminology. Adv Dent Res. 2016 May;28(2):49-57. doi: 10.1177/0022034516639276.</citation>
    <PMID>27099357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bjørndal L, Reit C, Bruun G, Markvart M, Kjaeldgaard M, Näsman P, Thordrup M, Dige I, Nyvad B, Fransson H, Lager A, Ericson D, Petersson K, Olsson J, Santimano EM, Wennström A, Winkel P, Gluud C. Treatment of deep caries lesions in adults: randomized clinical trials comparing stepwise vs. direct complete excavation, and direct pulp capping vs. partial pulpotomy. Eur J Oral Sci. 2010 Jun;118(3):290-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0722.2010.00731.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20572864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maltz M, Jardim JJ, Mestrinho HD, Yamaguti PM, Podestá K, Moura MS, de Paula LM. Partial removal of carious dentine: a multicenter randomized controlled trial and 18-month follow-up results. Caries Res. 2013;47(2):103-9. doi: 10.1159/000344013. Epub 2012 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23207420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayashi M, Fujitani M, Yamaki C, Momoi Y. Ways of enhancing pulp preservation by stepwise excavation--a systematic review. J Dent. 2011 Feb;39(2):95-107. doi: 10.1016/j.jdent.2010.10.012. Epub 2010 Dec 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20971154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ege University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>TIJEN PAMIR</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Selective Caries Removal</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep Dentin Lesion</keyword>
  <keyword>Permanent Teeth</keyword>
  <keyword>Stepwise and One Step Excavation Technique</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dental Pulp Exposure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

