<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04358601</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Allpoly Triathlon PS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04358601</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>All-poly Versus Metal-backed</brief_title>
  <official_title>Migration and Survival of All-polyethylene Tibial Components Compared to the Metal-backed Modular Components of the Triathlon PS Total Knee System. A RSA Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Region Skane</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Region Skane</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is the assessment of prosthetic migration results after two years of
      the Triathlon PS Knee System with all-polyethylene tibial components compared to the
      Triathlon PS Knee System with metal-backed modular components by means of Roentgen
      Stereophotogrammetry.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The secondary objective will be the prediction of the long-term survival based on the
      two-year migration patterns combined with clinical factors and radiographic aspects. In order
      to identify other clinical parameters besides the fixation of the prosthesis components,
      clinical scores and radiographic aspects will be correlated with the RSA outcome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 17, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Migration, measured by means of RSA</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Migration (MTPM in mm) of the prosthesis with respect to the host bone measured by means of roentgen stereophotogrammetric analysis (RSA)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Migration, measured by means of RSA</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Migration (MTPM in mm) of the prosthesis with respect to the host bone measured by means of roentgen stereophotogrammetric analysis (RSA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of clinical performance and patient outcome with the Knee Society Score (KSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-operative, 3 months, 1, 2, 5, 7 and 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Knee Society Clinical Rating System is comprised of two distinct sub-scores: one for pain, range of motion (ROM) and joint stability, and one for functional parameters. Sub-scores range from a potential minimum score of 0 to a maximum score of 100 points. Although the specific scores are not distinguished as &quot;excellent,&quot; &quot;good,&quot; &quot;fair,&quot; or &quot;poor,&quot; a higher value represents a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of clinical performance and patient outcome with the Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) patient questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-operative, 3 months, 1, 2, 5, 7 and 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>KOOS consists of 5 subscales: Pain, other symptoms, function in daily living , function in sport and recreation and knee related quality of life (QOL). The previous week is the time period considered when answering the questions. Standardized answer options are given (5 Likert boxes) and each question is assigned a score from 0 to 4. A normalized score (100 indicating no symptoms and 0 indicating extreme symptoms).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of clinical performance and patient outcome with EuroQuol-5 dimension (EQ-5D) patient questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-operative, 3 months, 1, 2, 5, 7 and 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D health questionnaire provides a simple descriptive profile and a single index value for health status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of clinical performance and patient outcome with the Forgotten Joint Score (FJS) patient questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-operative, 3 months, 1, 2, 5, 7 and 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The FJS consists of 12 questions and focuses on the patients' awareness of their joint replacement during a range of day to day and recreational activities. The score has a range of 0-100.questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of patient outcome with radiographic analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-operative, 3 months, 1, 2, 5, 7 and 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Plain radiographs will be obtained for assessment of fixation of the device.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All-polyethylene tibial components</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Triathlon PS Knee System with all-polyethylene tibial components</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metal-backed modular components</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Triathlon PS Knee System with metal-backed modular components</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triathlon PS Knee System with all-polyethylene tibial components</intervention_name>
    <description>Primary Total Knee Replacement</description>
    <arm_group_label>All-polyethylene tibial components</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stryker Orthopaedics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triathlon PS Knee System with metal-backed modular components</intervention_name>
    <description>Primary Total Knee Replacement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metal-backed modular components</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stryker Orthopaedics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. The subject is morbidly obese, defined as Body Mass Index (BMI) of &gt; 40. 2. Patient has
        a flexion contracture of 15° and more. 3. Patient has a varus/valgus contracture of 15° and
        more. 4. Patients with a pre-operative knee score of &gt;70. 5. The subject has a history of
        total or unicompartmental reconstruction of the affected joint. 6. The subject will be
        operated bilaterally. 7. Patients who had a Total Hip Arthroplasty (THA) on contralateral
        and/or ipsilateral side within the last year that is considered to have an unsatisfactory
        outcome (Patients with contralateral and/or ipsilateral THA &gt; 1 year ago with good outcome
        can be included in the study). 8. Patients who had a Total Knee Arthroplasty (TKA) on
        contralateral side within the last 6 months that is considered to have an unsatisfactory
        outcome. (Patients with contralateral TKA &gt; 6 months ago with good outcome can be included
        in the study). 9. The subject has an active or suspected latent infection in or about the
        knee joint. 10. Osteomyelitis 11. Sepsis 12. Patient who is expected to need lower limb
        joint replacement for another joint within one year. 13. The subject has a neuromuscular or
        neurosensory deficiency, which would limit the ability to assess the performance of the
        device. 14. The subject has a systemic or metabolic disorder leading to progressive bone
        deterioration. 15. The subject is immunologically suppressed or receiving steroids in
        excess of normal physiological requirements. 16. The subject's bone stock in compromised by
        disease or infection which cannot provide adequate support and/or fixation to the
        prosthesis. 17. The subject has had a knee fusion to the affected joint. 18. Female
        patients planning a pregnancy during the course of the study. 19. The patient is unable or
        unwilling to sign the Informed Consent specific to this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

