<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04356430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IUNU-PC-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04356430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neoadjuvant Therapy of Abiraterone Plus ADT for High Risk Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Medical Ethics Committee of Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital Affiliated to Medical School of Nanjing University</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Affiliated Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital of Nanjing University Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Affiliated Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital of Nanjing University Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      High risk prostate cancer (PCa) had worse outcomes on radical treatment results, short-time
      oncological results, even cancer-specific survival, than those low or mediate risk PCa.
      Neoadjuvant treatment before radical prostatectomy had been proven to get some benefits on
      peri-operation results, especially on reduction of tumor volume and minimization of
      biochemical recurrence. This study will evaluate the efficacy and safety of androgen
      deprivation therapy (ADT) with abiraterone in neoadjuvant therapy for surgically resectable
      high-risk or very high-risk PCa.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic Complete Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with no morphologically recognizable cancer cell in tumor specimens after radical prostatectomy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Subjects With Minimal Residual Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects that have residual tumors with maximum diameter of 5 mm or less after radical prostatectomy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Stage Degradation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical or pathological stage degradation after neoadjuvant therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Positive Surgical Margins</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with positive surgical margins after radical prostatectomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Complete Serum Remission</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects whose PSA is less than or equal to 0.2 ng/ml after 6 months of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects without PSA progression</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects whose PSA has never gone below 1 ng/ml or who receive any radiotherapy or systemic treatment after radical prostatectomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Imaging Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects whose primary tumor is in complete remission on imaging or residual tumor's maximum diameter is less than 0.5cm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADT with Abiraterone and prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects in this arm will receive luteinizing hormone releasing hormone analogue (LHRHa) plus abiraterone acetate and prednisone, as per standard of care. Goserelin 10.8 mg will be used once per 12 weeks. Abiraterone acetate will be administered orally as 1000 mg once daily along with 5 mg of oral prednisone once per day. Subjects will continue to take abiraterone acetate and prednisone for 24 weeks before robotic assisted radical prostatectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADT alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects in this arm will receive LHRHa alone for 24 weeks before receiving robotic assisted radical prostatectomy. Goserelin 10.8 mg will be administered once per 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abiraterone Acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 mg orally daily for 24 weeks before robotic assisted radical prostatectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT with Abiraterone and prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg oral low dose prednisone, once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT with Abiraterone and prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Goserelin 10.8 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>10.8 mg goserelin hypodermic once per 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADT alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ADT with Abiraterone and prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be ≥ 18 and ≤75 years of age.

          -  All patients must have a histologically or cytologically diagnosis of prostate cancer
             and must be eligible for radical prostatectomy.

          -  All patients must undergo thorough tumor staging and meet one of the following
             criteria: 1. multi-parameter MRI or PSMA PET / CT shows clinical staging of primary
             tumor ≥ T3, 2. Gleason score of primary tumor ≥ 8, 3. prostate specific antigen (PSA)
             ≥20 ng/ml.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) physical condition score ≤ 1

          -  Patients must have adequate hematologic function, within 28 days prior to registration
             as evidenced by: white blood cell (WBC) ≥ 4.0 × 109 / L, platelets≥ 100 × 109 / L,
             hemoglobin ≥ 9 g / dL, and international normalized ratio (INR) &lt; 1.5.

          -  Patients must have adequate hepatic function, within 28 days prior to registration, as
             evidenced by: total bilirubin (TBIL)≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN),and SGOT (AST)
             and SGPT (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN.

          -  Patients must have adequate renal function, within 28 days prior to registration, as
             evidenced by serum creatinine ≤2×ULN

          -  Patients must participate voluntarily and sign an informed consent form (ICF),
             indicating that they understand the purpose and required procedures of the study, and
             are willing to participate in. Patients must be willing to obey the prohibitions and
             restrictions specified in the research protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with prostate having neuroendocrine, small cell, or sarcoma-like features are
             not eligible.

          -  Patients with low-risk and medium-risk, localized prostate cancer (the following
             conditions are met at the same time) are not eligible: multi-parameter MRI or PSMA PET
             / CT shows clinical staging of primary tumor &lt; T3, Gleason score of primary tumor &lt; 8,
             and prostate specific antigen (PSA) &lt;20 ng/ml.

          -  Patients with clinical or radiological evidence of regional or extra-regional lymph
             node metastases or bone metastases or visceral metastases are not eligible.

          -  Patients with clinical or radiological evidence of regional or extra-regional lymph
             node metastases or bone metastases or visceral metastases are not eligible.

          -  Patients who have previously received androgen deprivation therapy (medical or
             surgical) or focal treatment of prostate cancer or prostate cancer radiotherapy or
             prostate cancer chemotherapy are not eligible.

          -  Patients with severe or uncontrolled concurrent infections are not eligible.

          -  Patients must not have New York Heart Association Class III or IV congestive heart
             failure at the time of screening. Patients must not have any thromboembolic event,
             unstable angina pectoris, myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to registration.

          -  Patients must not have uncontrolled severe hypertension, persistent uncontrolled
             diabetes, oxygen-dependent lung disease, chronic liver disease, or HIV infection.

          -  Patients must not have had other malignancies other than prostate cancer in the past 5
             years, but cured basal cell or squamous cell skin cancers can be enrolled.

        Patients with mental illness, mental disability or inability to give informed consent are
        not eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hongqian Guo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital, affiliated to medical school of Nanjing University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Junlong Zhuang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+86 15950451917</phone>
    <email>zhuangjl-2008@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Urology, Drum Tower Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Institute of Urology, Nanjing University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Junlong Zhuang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>8615950451917</phone>
      <email>zhuangjl-2008@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Affiliated Nanjing Drum Tower Hospital of Nanjing University Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hongqian Guo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Department of Urology, Drum Tower Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Goserelin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abiraterone Acetate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

