<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04351165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMP4297-107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04351165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BA Study of IMP4297 (20mg vs 10mg) in Healthy Male Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Randomized, Single-Dose, 2-Way Crossover Study to Compare the Bioavailability of Two IMP4297 Formulations (20 mg Capsules and 10 mg Capsules) After Single Oral Administration of 100 mg IMP4297 Under Fasted Condition in Healthy Male Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Impact Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Impact Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An open-label, randomized, single-dose, 2-way crossover study to compare the bioavailability
      of two IMP4297 formulations (20 mg capsules and 10 mg capsules) after single oral
      administration of 100 mg IMP4297 under fasted condition in healthy male subjects
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be an open-label, randomized, single-dose, 2-way crossover study to compare the
      bioavailability of two IMP4297 formulations (10 mg capsules and 20 mg capsules) after single
      oral administration of 100 mg IMP4297 under fasted condition in healthy male subjects. It
      will be conducted at one site, and approximately a total of 18 subjects will be enrolled.

      Subjects will be randomized to one of the 2 treatment sequences according to a
      computer-generated randomization schedule. Each treatment sequence will consist of 2 periods,
      separated by a washout period of at least 7 days between each period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>peak concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-last</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>area under the curve from time zero to the time with the last quantifiable concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-inf</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>area under the curve from time zero to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>time to reach Cmax</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>t½</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>elimination half-life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>apparent clearance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vz/F</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>apparent volume of distribution</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Period 1:
100 mg oral dose of IMP4297 (5 capsules, 20 mg/capsule);
Period 2:
100 mg oral dose of IMP4297 (10 capsules, 10 mg/capsule);
Each treatment sequence will consist of 2 periods, separated by a washout period of at least 7 days between each Dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Period 1:
100 mg oral dose of IMP4297 (10 capsules, 10 mg/capsule);
Period 2:
100 mg oral dose of IMP4297 (5 capsules, 20 mg/capsule);
Each treatment sequence will consist of 2 periods, separated by a washout period of at least 7 days between each Dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IMP4297</intervention_name>
    <description>IMP4297 10mg/capsule; IMP4297 20mg/capsule;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy male subjects, 18 to 55 years of age (both inclusive) on the day of signing
             informed consent form (ICF).

          2. Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18 to 30 kg/m2 (both inclusive); and a total body weight 50
             kg.

          3. Healthy is defined as no clinically relevant abnormalities identified by a detailed
             medical history, physical examination, including blood pressure (BP), pulse rate (PR)
             measurement, temperature, 12-lead ECG, or clinical laboratory tests, etc., judged by
             the investigator. For example, the reference normal ranges (inclusive) are as follows:
             after at least 5-minute rest in a supine position, BP: 90-139/60-89 mmHg, and PR:
             50-100 bpm. Repeat assessment can be conducted at the discretion of the investigator
             or delegate.

          4. Subjects able to father children must use a highly effective non-drug contraception
             double barrier method for the duration of the study and for at least 90 days after the
             last dose of study medication and should not have any plan for sperm donation
             throughout this period. Note: Sexual abstinence is allowed if this is the preferred
             and usual lifestyle of the subject. Male subjects are also eligible to participate if
             they have a bilateral vasectomy or have a female partner of non-childbearing
             potential.

          5. Subjects must voluntarily participate in this study. Be willing and be able to provide
             written informed consent for this clinical trial. Evidence of a personally signed and
             dated informed consent document indicating that the subject has been informed of all
             pertinent aspects of the study.

          6. Subjects who are willing and able to comply with all scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             laboratory tests, and other study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence or history of clinically significant diseases, including but not limited to
             neurologic, cardiovascular, hematological, immunological, renal, hepatic,
             gastrointestinal, pulmonary, endocrine, metabolic, psychiatric, or allergic disease
             (including drug and food allergies).

          2. Any condition possibly affecting drug absorption (e.g., gastrectomy, difficulty in
             swallowing).

          3. General anesthesia within 3 months before administration, or have a planned surgery
             during the study period.

          4. History of drug abuse within the past 5 years, or a positive urine drug test at
             screening or the admission. Repeat assessment can be conducted at the discretion of
             the investigator or delegate.

          5. History of excessive alcohol intake exceeding 10 drinks/week (1 standard drink = 150
             mL of wine, 360 mL of beer, or 45 mL of hard liquor) within 3 months prior to
             screening, or a positive alcohol breath test at screening or the admission. Repeat
             assessment can be conducted at the discretion of the investigator or delegate.

          6. Use of tobacco or nicotine containing products in excess of the equivalent of 5
             cigarettes per day within 3 months prior to screening, a positive urine nicotine test
             at screening or the admission, or difficulty abstaining from smoking for the duration
             of study confinement. Repeat assessment can be conducted at the discretion of the
             investigator or delegate.

          7. Treatment with an investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to the first dose of study drug; participation in a clinical trial of
             device(s) within 30 days prior to the first dose of study drug; participation in ≥4
             clinical trials within one year prior to the first dose of study drug.

          8. Blood donation (excluding plasma donations) or significant loss of blood (≥400 mL)
             within 1 month prior to screening, received blood transfusion or use of blood
             products.

          9. Use of any medicinal product that changes the activity of hepatic enzymes within 28
             days prior to the first dose of study drug, such as potent CYP3A4 inhibitors or
             inducers, or subjects who need to continue receiving these medications during the
             study period (refer to Appendix 18.2 for the list of common CYP3A4 inhibitors or
             inducers).

         10. Use of prescription or nonprescription drugs, dietary supplements, or herbal
             medicines, within 14 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first
             dose of study drug. As an exception, paracetamol may be used at doses of ≤1 g/day.
             Limited use of nonprescription medications that are not believed to affect the overall
             results of the study may be permitted on a case by case basis following approval by
             the principal investigator and the sponsor.

         11. Subjects with history of hepatitis, or positive result at screening for hepatitis B
             surface antigen (HepBsAg), hepatitis B core antibody (HepBcAb), hepatitis C antibody
             (HCVAb), or human immunodeficiency virus antibody (HIVAb).

         12. Screening supine 12-lead ECG demonstrating a QTcF (using Fridericia's formula, QTcF =
             QT/RR1/3) interval &gt;450 msec, or a QRS interval &gt;120 msec. If QTcF &gt;450 msec or QRS
             &gt;120 msec, the ECG should be repeated 2 more times and the average of the 3 QTcF or
             QRS values should be used to determine the subject's eligibility.

         13. Unable to abstain from strenuous exercise within 48 hours prior to dosing and during
             the study period.

         14. Use of products containing alcohol, tobacco, nicotine, caffeine within 48 hours prior
             to dosing; or unable to abstain from using these products for the duration of study
             confinement.

         15. History of sensitivity to any ingredients of IMP4297 products evaluated in this study.

         16. History of hemophobia, inability to tolerate venipuncture, and being afraid of
             needles.

         17. Subjects who have received live vaccine within 28 days prior to screening.

         18. Any other medical or psychiatric condition that may interfere with the interpretation
             of study results and, in the judgment of the investigator, would make the subject
             inappropriate for study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yunru Chen</last_name>
    <phone>+862168411121</phone>
    <email>yunru.chen@impacttherapeutics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yafei Liu</last_name>
    <phone>+862168411121</phone>
    <email>lyf@impacttherapeutics.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

