<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04359238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTIVE-DCM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04359238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>activeDCM - Interventional Clinical Trial of Individualized Activity and Exercise Programs to Improve Outcome in Dilated Cardiomyopathy Guided by Longitudinal Biosensing With Apple Watch</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACTIVE-DCM</acronym>
  <official_title>activeDCM - Interventional Clinical Trial of Individualized Activity and Exercise Programs to Improve Outcome in Dilated Cardiomyopathy Guided by Longitudinal Biosensing With Apple Watch</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Heidelberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Apple Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The German Heart Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Informatics for Life</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>e-Cardiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>German Cardiac Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Deutsches Zentrum für Herz-Kreislauf-Forschung (DZHK)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Heidelberg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The influence of an individualized sports program on dilated cardiomyopathy patients will be
      investigated in a randomized, prospective intervention study. 300 patients with dilated
      cardiomyopathy are included and examined over a period of 13 months. All participants will
      receive an Apple Watch, which serves for monitoring of activity and symptoms.The primary
      endpoint of the study is the change in maximum oxygen intake. In addition, the changes in
      well-being, objective parameters of cardiac function and the subject's compliance to his
      excercise program are of interest as secondary endpoints and for further exploratory
      research. In addition, the safety of a personalized sports program is evaluated. Molecules
      circulating in the blood (including proteins, RNA) are beeing measured at the beginning and
      in the course of the training program in order to be able to derive a connection between the
      training and the changed cardiovascular function. A gene analysis will be carried out, which
      serves to identify the genetic requirements of protective excercise.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The recruited subjects (n = 300) receive routine medical care on the day of randomization in
      our outpatient clinic. Furthermore, an additional blood sample is taken (further blood
      samples are taken on month 6 and month 12), which contain 9 ml EDTA (for DNA analysis, e.g.
      whole genome sequencing), 5 ml of PaxGene (for RNA analysis), 7.5 ml of plasma (for example
      for metabolite and RNA analysis) and 7.5 ml of serum (for example for metabolite and RNA
      analysis). A detailed medical history is taken during the basic examination. This is followed
      by detailed physical examination and diagnostics. A routine blood sample is taken to
      determine the values of electrolytes, NT-ProBNP, hsTnT, creatinine, urea and the blood count.
      Finally, the patients answer a questionnaire on Quality of Life (MHLFQ: The Minnesota Living
      with Heart Failure Questionnaire) and Depression (PHQ9).

      Two thirds of the patients (n = 200; intervention groups) will regularly participate in an
      individually designed sports program for a period of 12 months. One third of the participants
      (n = 100; control group) will not participate in a sports program. As a SmartWatch is
      required for the study. SmartWatches will be made available to all subjects on the day of
      recruitment. These are Apple Watches (Series 4), which are provided by Apple Inc. On the
      Apple Watch, participants have access to an app, that was especially developed by us for the
      study. This app collects important information about the physical activity and symptoms of
      the patient (including pulse rate, duration of training, the number of floors, number of
      steps and ECGs). The Apple Watch is also used to send participants of the intervention group
      regular notifications about their training status and to remind them of their training.

      The participants present themselves 4-6 weeks after recruitment in the department of sports
      medicine to perform a spiroergometry and a sports medical evaluation. A personalized sports
      program (depending on the severity of the disease) is created for the subjects of the
      intervention groups, which consists of strength and endurance training. The sports program
      will be carried out over a period of 12 months.

      All subjects in the intervention groups receive follow-up visits on month 3, month 6, month 9
      and month 12. The sports program can be adapted on these dates. The subjects who did not
      receive a personalized training program presente themselves for the follow-up examination on
      month 6 and month 12. Unwanted events during the training (including syncope, ICD therapy,
      injuries) are documented during the follow-up visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum oxygen uptake (VO2max)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in maximum oxygen uptake (VO2max) from baseline to 12 months follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Troponin und NTproBNP</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac function</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in systolic and diastolic cardiac function</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Arrhythmias</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in frequency of arrhythmias</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in frequency of hospitalization and NYHA class</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in compliance concerning excercise program</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy, Dilated</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group with motivation messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are 100 patients in the intervention group with automated or observer initiated motivation messages. They receive an individualized training program with regular notifications about their training status via their SmartWatch.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group without motivation messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are 100 patients in the intervention group without automated or observer initiated motivation messages. They receive an individualized training program without regular notifications about their training status via their SmartWatch.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 patients are in the control group without an individualized training program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individualized excercise</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants in the intervention group carry out regularly endurance and strength exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group with motivation messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group without motivation messages</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of non-ischemic, dilated cardiomyopathy (DCM)

          -  EF ≤ 45%

          -  NYHA I-III

          -  Age 18 to 65 years

          -  The patient understood the study concept and the declaration of consent and signed and
             dated the declaration of consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Physical disability that is not compatible with exercise in the study

          -  Orthopedic diseases such as osteoarthritis or changes in the spine that lead to
             restrictions that are not compatible with exercise in the study

          -  Syncope within the past 3 months

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Benjamin Meder, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Heidelberg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin Meder, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>0049 (0)6221 56-37948</phone>
    <email>benjamin.meder@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department III of Internal Medicine, University Hospital Heidelberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>69115</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Heidelberg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Benjamin Meder</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>SmartWatch</keyword>
  <keyword>Wearables</keyword>
  <keyword>Digital Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Dilated Cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Dilated</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

