<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04350229</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NP 1521/19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04350229</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endocrinological Changes Due to Pre-medications of Chemotherapy in Patients With Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>ALTEDEXAMAMA</acronym>
  <official_title>Endocrinological Changes Due to Pre-medications of Chemotherapy in Patients With Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto do Cancer do Estado de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto do Cancer do Estado de São Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Treatment for patients with high-risk breast cancer diagnoses is based on chemotherapy drugs
      with side effects. Dexamethasone is a drug that is part of the arsenal of pre-chemotherapy
      medications to prevent adverse events resulting from treatment, however common endocrine
      pathological conditions resulting from high doses of this corticoid are clinically evident in
      these individuals. The aim of this study is to evaluate the omission of corticosteroid doses
      as a pre-medication in cancer treatment after the second week of treatment with taxane in a
      curative setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment for patients with diagnoses of high-risk breast cancer is based on chemotherapy
      drugs such as anthracyclines and taxanes and its main side effects described are cardiac
      toxicity and hypersensitivity and / or allergic reactions, respectively. Dexamethasone is a
      drug that is part of the arsenal of pre-chemotherapy medications to prevent adverse events
      resulting from treatment, however common endocrine pathological conditions resulting from
      high doses of this corticoid are clinically evident in these individuals.

      These changes certainly have a negative impact on the patient's quality of life, however,
      with early recognition and the treatment of hypercortisolemia, we can lead to a reduction in
      morbidity and mortality in cancer patients.

      The objective of this study is to evaluate whether the omission of corticosteroid doses as
      pre-medication in cancer treatment after the second week of treatment with taxane in a
      setting with curative intent can prevent or decrease the incidence of endocrinological
      changes, and what is its impact on treatment and on quality of life of the patient.

      This is a prospective, randomized clinical study, without blinding as a research strategy
      used to increase the validity of clinical trials that evaluate the effect of interventions
      (eg, drugs or exercise). The process involves randomly assigning participants to an
      intervention group or to a control group and requires that participants have an equal chance
      of being allocated to either group.

      Will be recruited 86 patients diagnosed with breast cancer with indication for neoadjuvant or
      adjuvant treatment with the standard ICESP protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 27, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 27, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence and change of endocrine dysfunction.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the incidence and reduction of endocrine dysfunction in breast cancer patients with the administration of lower doses of dexamethasone in the solutions of pre-chemotherapy medications with doxorubicin, cyclophosphamide and paclitaxel (standard protocol AC-T of the ICESP).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory markers evaluation.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate inflammatory markers that may be related to endocrine syndromes resulting from the overuse of corticosteroids, and determine their correlation with the occurrence of endocrine syndromes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the correlation between inflammatory markers and corticosteroid dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the correlation between the serum level of inflammatory marker and the total dose of corticosteroids administered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from registration to the earlier of progression or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Quality of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>On the first day of treatment, on the first day of week 3 and on the last day of the final treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in Quality of Life, as defined by the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core-30 (EORTC QLQ-C30 (Version 3) during chemotherapy. The EORTC QLQ-C30 (Version 3) uses for the questions 1 to 28 a 4-point scale. The scale scores from 1 to 4: 1 (&quot;Not at all&quot;), 2 (&quot;A little&quot;), 3 (&quot;Quite a bit&quot;) and 4 (&quot;Very much&quot;). Half points are not allowed. The range is 3.
For the raw score, less points are considered to have a better outcome. The EORTC QLQ-C30 (Version 3) uses for the questions 29 and 30 a 7-points scale.
The scale scores from 1 to 7: 1 (&quot;very poor&quot;) to 7 (&quot;excellent&quot;). Half points are not allowed. The range is 6. First of all, raw score has to be calculated with mean values. Afterwards linear transformation is performed to be comparable. More points are considered to have a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost change.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Analyze the treatment cost reduction omitting the use of dexamethasone in these patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EXPERIMENTAL GROUP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the experimental group, dexamethasone will be omitted from the second application of paclitaxel.
Pre-chemotherapy with the AC protocol: ondansetron 8mg and dexamethasone 10mg + Pre-chemotherapy with paclitaxel: ranitidine 50mg, ondansetron 8mg, diphenhydramine 50mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL GROUP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-chemotherapy with the AC protocol: ondansetron 8mg and dexamethasone 10mg + Pre-chemotherapy with paclitaxel: ranitidine 50mg, ondansetron 8mg, diphenhydramine 50mg and dexamethasone 10mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Drug omission</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug omission. In the experimental group, dexamethasone will be omitted from the second application of paclitaxel.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EXPERIMENTAL GROUP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control group</intervention_name>
    <description>No drug omission. In the control group, dexamethasone will not be omitted in the second application of paclitaxel.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL GROUP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients from the oncology services of ICESP and its Osasco unit.

          -  Over 18 years of age.

          -  Diagnosed with breast cancer who will be treated with an ACT Icesp scheme in the
             setting with curative intent (neoadjuvant and adjuvant).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with significant cognitive impairment that prevents the questionnaire from
             being applied.

          -  Patients who are not fluent in Portuguese, or illiterate, who did not sign the ICF.

          -  ECOG 3 and KPS &lt;70%.

          -  Metastatic patients, with the presence of other important morbidities that may
             interfere with laboratory findings.

          -  Patients with chronic use of steroidal and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vanessa A Scontre, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto do Cancer do Estado de São Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vanessa A Scontre, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+5511997457049</phone>
    <email>dra.vanessas@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanessa Scontre</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>01246000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vanessa A Scontre, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+5511997457049</phone>
      <email>dra.vanessas@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vanessa A Scontre, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Instituto do Cancer do Estado de São Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vanessa Armenio Scontre</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>endocrinological changes</keyword>
  <keyword>dexamethasone</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

