<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04356846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LP-108-I-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04356846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Study of LP-108 in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory B-cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Preliminary Efficacy of the Oral BCL-2 Inhibitor LP-108 in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory B-cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Guangzhou Lupeng Pharmaceutical Company LTD.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Newave Pharmaceutical Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a multi-center, open-label, single-arm phase I clinical study of LP-108.
      Patients with relapsed or refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL, arm A) and other B
      cell non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (NHL, Arm B). Each arm has a dose escalation phase (phase Ia) and
      expansion phase (phase Ib). During the dose escalation phase, the primary objectives are to
      define dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), maximum tolerated dose (MTD), and to explore a
      recommended phase II dose. Dose escalation is based on the classic &quot;3 + 3&quot; design, while
      accelerated titration is applied to the initial lower doses. After the RP2Ds are determined,
      additional patients will be enrolled in the expansion phase to further evaluation the safety,
      PK and preliminary efficacy of LP-108, each therapy can enroll 12-20 subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of dose limiting toxicity (DLT), maximum tolerated dose (MTD), recommended phase two dose (RP2D), and lead-in period regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Lead-in period (0-4 weeks) plus 3 weeks of study drug administration at the designated cohort dose.</time_frame>
    <description>Protocol-defined events, which can not be attributed by the investigator to a clearly identifiable cause such as tumor progression, underlying illness, concurrent illness, or concomitant medication, will be considered a DLT. Dose limiting toxicities of tumor lysis syndrome observed during the lead-in period will be attributed to the lead-in period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events and its frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>From first dose of study drug administration until 30 days after study drug discontinue.</time_frame>
    <description>Safety Proflie</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of plasma peak concentration (Cmax) of LP-108</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 37 for LP-108.</time_frame>
    <description>Blood and urine samples for pharmacokinetic analysis of LP-108 will be collected at designated time points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Area Under the Curve (AUC) of LP-108</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 37 for LP-108.</time_frame>
    <description>Blood and urine samples for pharmacokinetic analysis of LP-108 will be collected at designated time points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Effect - Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Pharmacokinetic (PK) parameter Cmax (maximum plasma concentration of LP-108) between each diet (LP-108 under fasting versus fed conditions)，up to week 8 for LP-108.</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples for food effect pharmacokinetic analysis of LP-108 will be collected at designated time points</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Effect - AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Pharmacokinetic (PK) parameter AUC (area under the curve of LP-108) between each diet (LP-108 under fasting versus fed conditions)，up to week 8 for LP-108.</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples for food effect pharmacokinetic analysis of LP-108 will be collected at designated time points</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary efficacy assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Designated dose starting week for clinical disease progression and tumor response; and every 4-12 weeks thereafter until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first,.assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor response or clinical disease progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal residual disease (MRD)</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 2 months after the CR, CRi criteria for tumor response are first met. Measured up to 24 months after the last subject has enrolled in the study.</time_frame>
    <description>MRD assessed in the peripheral blood and/or bone marrow (BM) either by four color flow cytometry or NGS, will be measured in CLL subjects achieving CR/CRi.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R/R CLL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Relapsed or Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>R/R NHL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Relapsed or Refractory B-cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma Patients, including SLL, FL, MZL, MCL, DLBCL, WM.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LP-108 tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Taken orally within 30 minutes after a meal at the designated dose, once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>R/R CLL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>R/R NHL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Per 2017 revised WHO lymphoma classification criteria, subject must have either:

               -  (Arm A) Diagnosed with relapsed or refractory CLL and require treatment in the
                  opinion of the Investigator.

               -  (Arm B) Diagnosed with relapsed or refractory non-Hodgkin's lymphoma associated
                  with B-cell proliferation (such as SLL \ MCL \ FL \ MZL \ DLBCL \ WM, etc.) in
                  need of treatment.

          -  Subject has an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score less than
             or equal to 1.

          -  Subject must have adequate bone marrow function independent of growth factor support
             per local laboratory reference range at Screening.

          -  Subject must have adequate coagulation, renal, and hepatic function, per local
             laboratory reference range at Screening.

          -  All acute toxicity from previous anti-tumor treatment or surgery has been alleviated
             to NCI CTCAE 5.0 ≤ Grade 1.

          -  All enrolled patients should take medically approved contraceptives during the entire
             treatment period and within 90 days after the end of treatment.

          -  Subjects must be willing to provide valid diagnostic evidence or accept bone marrow
             biopsy before treatment and accept bone marrow biopsy after treatment start.

          -  Patients with NHL who have undergone autologous stem cell transplantation must
             complete the transplantation operation for more than 6 months when enrolled, and have
             sufficient bone marrow function without relying on growth factor stimulation.

          -  Volunteer and sign informed consent, willing to follow trial protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  According to the 2017 revised WHO Lymphoma Classification Criteria, patients diagnosed
             with the following diseases: Burkitt lymphoma or Burkitt-like lymphoma, lymphoblastic
             lymphoma/leukemia, and post-transplant lymphoproliferative disease(PTLD) .

          -  Previously received other BCL-2 protein family inhibitors.

          -  CLL subject has undergone an allogeneic or autologous stem cell transplant or NHL
             subject has undergone an allogeneic stem cell transplant.

          -  Subjects who have received the following treatments within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives
             before the first dose of LP-108:

               -  Antitumor therapies including myelosuppressive chemotherapy, targeted therapy,
                  biological therapy and / or immunotherapy;

               -  Any investigational treatment;

               -  Patients who have undergone major surgery, severe trauma or radiotherapy.

          -  Subjects who have received the following treatments within 2 weeks before the first
             dose of LP-108:

               -  Steroids or traditional herbal medicine for antitumor purposes;

               -  Strong and moderate CYP3A4/5 inhibitors and inducers, P-gp inhibitors and CYP2C8
                  sensitive substrates;

               -  All drugs that may cause QTc interval prolongation or torsional tachycardia.

          -  Have had malignancies other than the indications targeted in this study in the past
             three years, except for basal cell carcinoma of the skin and cervical carcinoma in
             situ treated radically.

          -  Any serious and / or uncontrolled systemic disease.

          -  Poor cardiovascular function, in line with New York Heart Association (NYHA) cardiac
             function classification ≥ 2 or QTcF greater than 480ms on ≥ 3 independent ECG.

          -  Disease states where clinical manifestations may be difficult to control, including

               -  HIV, HBV, HCV, syphilis positive or active bacterial and fungal infections;

               -  Disease affects the central nervous system with obvious symptoms;

               -  Autoimmune hemolytic anemia or Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura.

          -  Any gastrointestinal conditions that may severely affect the study drug absorption or
             pharmacokinetic parameters.

          -  Patients who were unable to discontinue taking CYP2C8 substrate repaglinide to control
             type 2 diabetes during the study.

          -  Subjects who cannot tolerate urine collection, venipuncture, lymph node biopsy, and
             bone marrow aspiration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jianyong Li, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>025-83718836</phone>
    <email>lijianyonglm@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jianyong Li, PhD</last_name>
      <email>lijianyonglm@126.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

