<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04352374</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Cairo university P.T</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04352374</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Aerobic Exercises vs Device Guided Breathing on Gestational Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Aerobic Exercises Versus Device Guided Breathing on Gestational Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim To compare between the effect of aerobic exercise versus device guided breathing (DGB) on
      blood pressure in gestational hypertensive patients. Participants and Methods Randomized
      controlled trial, which included 60 singleton pregnant women (at 21-week gestation) diagnosed
      with gestational hypertension. They were divided into two groups: group (A) received aerobic
      exercise with a treadmill twice a week, for 45 minutes; and group (B) received Device guided
      breathing exercise for at least 40 min per week, with each session lasting at least 10 min.
      Assessment of the systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) for all
      participants in the two studied groups (A, B) was carried out at begining of the study and at
      week-36 of gestation with mercury column sphygmomanometer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sixty singleton pregnant women, diagnosed with gestational hypertension (GH) at 21- week of
      gestation, and aged between 25-35 years were randomized. GH was defined as blood pressure
      higher than 140/90 measured on two separate occasions, more than 6 hours apart, without the
      presence of protein in the urine and diagnosed after 20 weeks of gestation.

      Women with multiple pregnancies, cervical insufficiency, vaginal bleeding, heart disease,
      systemic lupus erythematosus, kidney failure, and neurologic disorders were excluded from the
      study. For inclusion in the study, pregnant women also could not be engaged in any supervised
      physical exercise, at the time of selection and when signing a free written informed consent
      term.

      Pregnant women were randomized using an opaque sealed envelope that was sequentially numbered
      and statistically generated by a computer program. The envelope contained information about
      the random allocation group: group (A), engaged in aerobic exercise twice a week under the
      supervision of a physical therapist, and group (B), engaged in device guided breathing
      exercises. Both groups received antihypertensive medications. Random allocation of the
      subjects was performed by another investigator, who did not participate directly in the
      research study.

      Exercise program for group (A) The therapist advised all participants to drink a plenty of
      water before and after the exercise session to avoid excessive loss of body water during the
      session. Pregnant women were instructed to have a light meal about one hour before the
      performance of exercise and to wear comfortable clothes.

      Participants in this group were given a Low-Intensity Aerobic Exercise with Borg scale RPE at
      11. Participants were asked to maintain this intensity of rate of perceived exertion
      throughout the 45 minutes' duration of the aerobic training.

      During the training session, the therapist stood near the patient to observe and detect signs
      of stopping the exercise. The therapist continuously asked the patient if she felt pain,
      dizzy or shortens of breath.

      Device guided breathing for group (B) The FDA approved the Resperate device as an adjunct
      anti-hypertensive treatment approach that guides home users to alter their breathing rate in
      response to instructed signals .

      At the beginning the researcher explained the device and study procedures to every
      participant of group (B).The device consists of a control box, headphones and a respiratory
      rate monitor attached as a sensor belt around the user's chest.

      The participant is instructed to alter their breathing rate, aiming for up to 10 breaths per
      minute, in response to a melody played to them via the asked to use the device for at least
      40 min per week, with each session lasting at least 10 min .

      All pregnant females of both groups were requested to maintain routine lifestyle habits with
      regard to diet intake throughout the study. All blood pressure measurements were conducted
      during the morning hours. Arterial blood pressure was measured using a standard mercury
      sphygmomanometer with appropriate cuff size, after subjects had rested in the sitting
      position for at least 5 minutes. BP was measured and presented at 20 week gestation and
      week-36 of gestation. Two readings were taken at 2 minutes interval, and the average values
      were used as the baseline value.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A total of 75 participants were initially screened. After the screening process, 60 participants were found to be eligible to participate in the study. In total, 50 (100%) participants completed the treatment program</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Pregnant women were randomized using an opaque sealed envelope that was sequentially numbered and statistically generated by a computer program. The envelope contained information about the random allocation group: group (A), engaged in aerobic exercise twice a week under the supervision of a physical therapist, and group (B), engaged in device guided breathing exercises. Both groups received antihypertensive medications. Random allocation of the subjects was performed by another investigator, who did not participate directly in the research study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>from enrollment to end of treatment at 36 week gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Arterial blood pressure was measured using a standard mercury</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension ,Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aerobic exercise group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The therapist advised all participants of this group to drink a plenty of water before and after the exercise session to avoid excessive loss of body water during the session. Pregnant women were instructed to have a light meal about one hour before the performance of exercise and to wear comfortable clothes.
Participants in this group were given a Low-Intensity Aerobic Exercise with Borg scale RPE at 11. Participants were asked to maintain this intensity of rate of perceived exertion throughout the 45 minutes' duration of the aerobic training.
During the training session, the therapist stood near the patient to observe and detect signs of stopping the exercise. The therapist continuously asked the patient if she felt pain, dizzy or shortens of breath.
No complications were observed during physical exercise sessions, for example, hypertensive crisis, hypotension, hyperthermia, musculoskeletal lesions, or other complications identified that demanded interruption of the exercise.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Device guided breathing group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At the beginning the researcher explained the device and study procedures to every participant of this group .The device consists of a control box, headphones and a respiratory rate monitor attached as a sensor belt around the user's chest.
The participant is instructed to alter their breathing rate, aiming for up to 10 breaths per minute, in response to a melody played to them via the asked to use the device for at least 40 min per week, with each session lasting at least 10 min</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aerobic exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>a Low-Intensity Aerobic Exercise with Borg scale RPE at 11.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aerobic exercise group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Device guided breathing</intervention_name>
    <description>The device consists of a control box, headphones and a respiratory rate monitor attached as a sensor belt around the user's chest.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Device guided breathing group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Sixty singleton pregnant women, diagnosed with gestational hypertension (GH) at 21-
             week of gestation, and aged between 25-35 years were randomized. GH was defined as
             blood pressure higher than 140/90 measured on two separate occasions, more than 6
             hours apart, without the presence of protein in the urine and diagnosed after 20 weeks
             of gestation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with multiple pregnancies, cervical insufficiency, vaginal bleeding, heart
             disease, systemic lupus erythematosus, kidney failure, and neurologic disorders were
             excluded from the study. For inclusion in the study, pregnant women also could not be
             engaged in any supervised physical exercise, at the time of selection and when signing
             a free written informed consent term.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Gestational hypertension</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Asmaa M Elbandrawy, Assis prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Physical Therapy, Cairo University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Giza</city>
        <state>Dokki</state>
        <zip>12612</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Asmaa Mahmoud Aly Elbandrawy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof faculty of Physical Therapy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Aerobic exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Device guided breathing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pregnancy-Induced</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>journal publication, Google Scholar, ResearchGate, LinkedIn</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

