<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03778346</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SixthAHWenzhouMU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03778346</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrin β7, BCMA, CS1, CD38 and CD138 as the Single or Compound Targets for the Fourth Genenation of CAR-T Cells</brief_title>
  <official_title>Integrin β7, BCMA, CS1, CD38 and CD138 as the Single or Compound Targets for the Fourth Genenation of CAR-T Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Sixth Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Sixth Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      According to the high expression of tumor cell-associated antigen CD138, integrin β7, CS1,
      CD38 and BCMA in patients with refractory/recurrent multiple myeloma, the fourth generation
      of CAR-T cells(simultaneously expressing IL7 and CCL19) with 10 different dual target
      combinations are used to minimize the tumor burden in the patient individually and precisely
      and improve the immunosuppressive microenvironment of the tumor , thereby effectively
      treating refractory/recurrent multiple myeloma .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma（MM） is one of the most common malignant diseases in the blood system.There
      is still no cure for the disease which only control the development of the disease in various
      ways including proteasome inhibitors and immune regulator and hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation . Combined with the advantages of multiple therapies, chimeric antigen
      receptor T cells (CAR-T) have gradually becoming one of the strongest and most powerful
      weapons against multiple myeloma.The basic principle is to use the patient's own immune cells
      to clear cancer cells.

      MM is genetically and phenotypically heterogeneous,Antigen escape and relapse after CAR-T
      treatment is a global problem， so the effective treatment of refractory/relapsing multiple
      myeloma with CAR-T cells usually requires targeting multiple antigens. The investigators use
      Integrin β7(a large family of molecules that are central regulators in multicellular biology
      and orchestrating cell-cell and cell-extracellular matrix (ECM) adhesive interactions from
      embryonic development to mature tissue function), BCMA(highly expressed on malignant MM
      plasma cells and providing a substantial antiapoptotic signal making it an encouraging target
      for BCMA-directed immunotherapy),CS1(encoded by the SLAMF7 gene,a robust marker of normal
      plasma cells and malignant plasma),CD38(encoded by the CD38 gene and functioning in cell
      adhesion, signal transduction and calcium signaling) and CD138(known as syndecan 1, a surface
      protein expressed on most healthy and malignant plasma cells as an adhesion protein, binding
      collagen and fibronectin molecules located in the extracellular matrix. ) as the Single or
      Compound Targets for the Fourth Genenation of CAR-T Cells ,thereby effectively treating
      refractory/recurrent multiple myeloma .
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events that are related to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability measured by occurrence of study related adverse effects defined by NCI-CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2 year overall survival(OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 yaers</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate 2 year overall survival(OS) after BCMA/CD138/CD38/Integrinβ7/CS1-CART infusion and sequential treatment with Relapsed/Refractory MM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3 year progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 yaers</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate 3 year progression free survival after BCMA/CD138/CD38/Integrinβ7/CS1 CART infusion and sequential treatment with Relapsed/Refractory MM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>RRMM</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CAR-T therapy in multiple myeloma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In order to assess the safety and validity of using the Fourth Genenation of CAR-T therapy refractory/rela-psed multiple myeloma patients with one kind of BCMA-CART,CD138-CART,CD38-CART , Integrin β7-CART or 10 different combinations ,subjects will receive 10^6—10^7/Kg transduced CAR-T cells at one time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CAR-T therapy in Relapsed/Refractory multiple myeloma</intervention_name>
    <description>Integrin β7, BCMA, CS1, CD38 and CD138 as the Single or Compound Targets for the Fourth Genenation of CAR-T Cells to treat Relapsed/Refractory multiple myeloma</description>
    <arm_group_label>CAR-T therapy in multiple myeloma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who meet the requirements voluntarily participate in the study and sign the
             Informed Consent Form.

          2. Age is 18 to 80 years old, gender is not limited.

          3. Patients with relapsed or refractory myeloma who meet the following criteria for
             multiple myeloma diagnostic criteria defined by the IMWG (2017): Subjects have
             received adequate prior treatment of at least 2 regimens; during the most recent
             treatment or after treatment , the disease progresses or recurs.

          4. The Eastern Cancer Cooperative Group (ECOG) scores 0 to 2 (the tumor causes bone
             pain).

          5. The expected survival period is more than 12 weeks.

          6. No other malignant tumors, severe autoimmune diseases or congenital immunodeficiency,
             serious progressive infection, cranial nerve disorder or mental illness.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or lactating women.

          2. Patients with uncontrollable active infections.

          3. Patients with systemic steroids; recent or current use of inhaled steroids is not
             excluded.

          4. Previously involved CAR-T cell therapies produced any uncontrolled disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bingmu Fang, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lishui Country People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bingmu Fang, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>0578-2780108</phone>
    <email>fbm636@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yonghua Liu, M.D</last_name>
    <email>liuyonghua2010@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jinhong Jiang</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lishui</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>323000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jiang Jinhong, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>0578-2780108</phone>
      <email>xyk1069@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jiang Jinhong, M.D</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jiang Jinhong</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Sixth Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lishui</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>323000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bingmu Fang, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>0578-2780108</phone>
      <email>fbm636@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>M.D</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bingmu Fang, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruella M, Barrett DM, Kenderian SS, Shestova O, Hofmann TJ, Perazzelli J, Klichinsky M, Aikawa V, Nazimuddin F, Kozlowski M, Scholler J, Lacey SF, Melenhorst JJ, Morrissette JJ, Christian DA, Hunter CA, Kalos M, Porter DL, June CH, Grupp SA, Gill S. Dual CD19 and CD123 targeting prevents antigen-loss relapses after CD19-directed immunotherapies. J Clin Invest. 2016 Oct 3;126(10):3814-3826. doi: 10.1172/JCI87366. Epub 2016 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27571406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adachi K, Kano Y, Nagai T, Okuyama N, Sakoda Y, Tamada K. IL-7 and CCL19 expression in CAR-T cells improves immune cell infiltration and CAR-T cell survival in the tumor. Nat Biotechnol. 2018 Apr;36(4):346-351. doi: 10.1038/nbt.4086. Epub 2018 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29505028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petrov JC, Wada M, Pinz KG, Yan LE, Chen KH, Shuai X, Liu H, Chen X, Leung LH, Salman H, Hagag N, Liu F, Jiang X, Ma Y. Compound CAR T-cells as a double-pronged approach for treating acute myeloid leukemia. Leukemia. 2018 Jun;32(6):1317-1326. doi: 10.1038/s41375-018-0075-3. Epub 2018 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>29515236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lim WA, June CH. The Principles of Engineering Immune Cells to Treat Cancer. Cell. 2017 Feb 9;168(4):724-740. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2017.01.016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28187291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hosen N, Matsunaga Y, Hasegawa K, Matsuno H, Nakamura Y, Makita M, Watanabe K, Yoshida M, Satoh K, Morimoto S, Fujiki F, Nakajima H, Nakata J, Nishida S, Tsuboi A, Oka Y, Manabe M, Ichihara H, Aoyama Y, Mugitani A, Nakao T, Hino M, Uchibori R, Ozawa K, Baba Y, Terakura S, Wada N, Morii E, Nishimura J, Takeda K, Oji Y, Sugiyama H, Takagi J, Kumanogoh A. The activated conformation of integrin β(7) is a novel multiple myeloma-specific target for CAR T cell therapy. Nat Med. 2017 Dec;23(12):1436-1443. doi: 10.1038/nm.4431. Epub 2017 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>29106400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drent E, Groen RW, Noort WA, Themeli M, Lammerts van Bueren JJ, Parren PW, Kuball J, Sebestyen Z, Yuan H, de Bruijn J, van de Donk NW, Martens AC, Lokhorst HM, Mutis T. Pre-clinical evaluation of CD38 chimeric antigen receptor engineered T cells for the treatment of multiple myeloma. Haematologica. 2016 May;101(5):616-25. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2015.137620. Epub 2016 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26858358</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brudno JN, Maric I, Hartman SD, Rose JJ, Wang M, Lam N, Stetler-Stevenson M, Salem D, Yuan C, Pavletic S, Kanakry JA, Ali SA, Mikkilineni L, Feldman SA, Stroncek DF, Hansen BG, Lawrence J, Patel R, Hakim F, Gress RE, Kochenderfer JN. T Cells Genetically Modified to Express an Anti-B-Cell Maturation Antigen Chimeric Antigen Receptor Cause Remissions of Poor-Prognosis Relapsed Multiple Myeloma. J Clin Oncol. 2018 Aug 1;36(22):2267-2280. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2018.77.8084. Epub 2018 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>29812997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bu DX, Singh R, Choi EE, Ruella M, Nunez-Cruz S, Mansfield KG, Bennett P, Barton N, Wu Q, Zhang J, Wang Y, Wei L, Cogan S, Ezell T, Joshi S, Latimer KJ, Granda B, Tschantz WR, Young RM, Huet HA, Richardson CJ, Milone MC. Pre-clinical validation of B cell maturation antigen (BCMA) as a target for T cell immunotherapy of multiple myeloma. Oncotarget. 2018 May 25;9(40):25764-25780. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.25359. eCollection 2018 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>29899820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mikkilineni L, Kochenderfer JN. Chimeric antigen receptor T-cell therapies for multiple myeloma. Blood. 2017 Dec 14;130(24):2594-2602. doi: 10.1182/blood-2017-06-793869. Epub 2017 Sep 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28928126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chmielewski M, Abken H. TRUCKs: the fourth generation of CARs. Expert Opin Biol Ther. 2015;15(8):1145-54. doi: 10.1517/14712598.2015.1046430. Epub 2015 May 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25985798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

