<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03778021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RG1001953</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>8716</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-03752</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U54CA132381-11</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03778021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Yeego! Healthy Eating &amp; Gardening</brief_title>
  <official_title>Engaging Navajo Elementary Schools in Randomized Controlled Trial of Yeego! Healthy Eating &amp; Gardening</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study we will estimate changes in healthy eating and gardening behaviors associated
      with the intervention using a randomized controlled trial design, with the comparison arm
      receiving a delayed intervention in the following school year.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The small randomized controlled trial of an intensive curriculum and school garden
      intervention will be implemented in elementary schools in two communities (Shiprock and
      Tsaile). The study will begin in year 1 with a period of engagement and recruitment of
      schools in each community; with the goal of recruiting three schools in each community to
      start the run-in phase. The run-in period will include time for greater engagement with the
      school community, an assessment of the potential garden site and an assessment of evaluation
      readiness. Depending on whether all three schools in the community qualify for the study at
      the end of run-in, or only two schools per community, we will randomize three or two schools
      to intervention or delayed intervention status in each community. We will have either two
      intervention schools and 4 delayed intervention schools, or 2 intervention schools and 2
      delayed intervention schools, depending on the run-in information. We will conduct baseline
      data collection (T1) at the beginning of the school year in Year 2 with both children and
      parents. Students in the intervention group will receive the curriculum and school garden
      during that academic school year. At the end of the school year, we will conduct the T2
      assessment in children and parents. The main evaluation period is between T1 and f2, and the
      statistical analysis methods refer to the T2 versus T1 change in outcome measures (healthy
      eating and gardening). After that, at the beginning of the next school year (Year 3), the
      delayed intervention schools will receive the intervention. During Year 3, we will also
      conduct quarterly community gardening workshops for adult family members in all schools.
      Attendance at these will be tracked. A final assessment (T3) will be conducted at the end of
      the second school year in all the randomized schools to describe behaviors in children and
      parents over time, using a quasiexperimental design that estimates change in the delayed
      intervention group between T2 and T3, attributable in part to the delayed intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child healthy eating behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess dietary intake in elementary school age children by utilizing the picture sort method to estimate the frequency of eating foods that comprise ten major food groupings of the Navajo diet</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child gardening participation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Survey children to see if they have a garden at home, and if so how often they do gardening activities there</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Gardening Self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Survey children to identify how confident they are in their abilities to perform gardening behaviors, utilizing six-item likert scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">480</enrollment>
  <condition>Dietary Habits</condition>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Eating Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students in the intervention group will receive the curriculum and school garden during the second academic school year (Year 2)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the delayed intervention group schools, students will receive the intervention at the beginning of Year 3</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral Gardening Exposure</intervention_name>
    <description>Assist with planting and maintaining the school garden, as well as observe the school garden curriculum and dietary assessment protocols</description>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Healthy Eating and Gardening Curriculum</intervention_name>
    <description>Attend 12 lessons (about 45 minutes each) throughout the school year, during the normal school day, that are focused on healthy eating and gardening, coordinated with the growing season</description>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Family Workshops</intervention_name>
    <description>During Year 3, quarterly healthy eating and gardening workshops for family and community members to attend</description>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children ages 8-12

          -  Adults ages 21-75

          -  Elementary schools in Tsaile and Shiprock will have been in existence for at least
             three years, school size (have between 40 to 100 students in grades 3 and 4 combined),
             have more than two-thirds Navajo students and satisfy a garden site checklist that can
             overcome garden barriers (e.9. have access to water)

          -  Assessment is restricted to Male/female students in grades 3 and 4 attending,
             attending school in either Tsaile or Shiprock and one family member (Navajo adult aged
             18 and older) for each child.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family member- child dyads neither of which are Navajo

          -  Family member/child dyads not expected to stay at the recruited Tsaile or Shiprock
             elementary school for the whole school year.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shirley Beresford</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shirley Beresford</last_name>
    <phone>206-667-4793</phone>
    <email>sberesfo@fredhutch.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shirley Beresford</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

