<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001626</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970117</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-H-0117</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001626</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Therapies for the Treatment of Severe Aplastic Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial of Antithymocyte Globulin and Cyclosporine Versus Cyclophosphamide and Cyclosporine in the Treatment of Severe Aplastic Anemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Severe Aplastic Anemia (SAA) is a rare and very serious blood disorder in which the bone
      marrow stops producing the cells which make up blood; red blood cells, white blood cells, and
      platelets.

      Researchers believe this is caused by an autoimmune reaction, a condition in which the
      natural defense system of the body begins attacking itself. In SAA the immune system begins
      attacking the bone marrow. Red blood cells are responsible for carrying oxygen to all of the
      organ systems in the body, and low numbers (anemia) can cause difficulty breathing and
      fatigue. Platelets are responsible for normal blood clotting and low numbers can result in
      easy bruising and bleeding which can be deadly. White blood cells are responsible for
      fighting infections, and low numbers of these can lead to frequent infections, the most
      common cause of death in patients with aplastic anemia.

      SAA can be treated by bone marrow transplant (BMT) or by drugs designed to slow down the
      immune system (immunosuppressants). BMT can be successful, but it requires a donor with
      matched bone marrow, making this therapy available only to a few patients. BMT with unmatched
      bone marrow can fail and cause dangerous side effects.

      Presently, the two drugs used to treat SAA by slowing down the immune system
      (immunosuppression) are antithymocyte globulin (ATG) and cyclosporin A (CSA). When used in
      combination these two drugs can improve most patients condition. However, one third of the
      patients who respond to this therapy experience a relapse of SAA. In addition, some patients
      treated with ATG/CSA can later develop other disorders of the blood.

      Recently, researchers have found that another immunosuppressive drug called cyclophosphamide,
      has been successful at treating patients with SAA. In addition, patients treated with
      cyclophosphamide do not experience relapses or develop other disorders of the blood.

      In this study researchers would like to compare the combinations of antithymocyte globulin
      (ATG) and cyclosporin A (CSA) to cyclophosphamide and cyclosporin A (CSA) for the treatment
      of SAA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Severe aplastic anemia (SAA) is a disorder with a poor prognosis if untreated. Current
      accepted therapeutic strategies include bone marrow transplantation (BMT) and
      immunosuppression, both offering cure or amelioration in the majority of patients. Although
      BMT is successful using human leukocyte antigen (HLA) matched sibling bone marrow, the 25%
      probability of finding an HLA identical sibling within a family renders this approach
      available to only a minority of patients. BMT utilizing HLA-matched, unrelated donors carries
      a high risk of treatment failure along with considerable toxicity. While combined
      immunosuppression with both antithymocyte globulin (ATG) and cyclosporine A (CSA) produces
      hematologic improvement in most patients, relapse is common, occurring in about a third of
      responders. Late evolution of aplastic anemia to other serious hematologic disorders is a
      significant problem following successful treatment with ATG/CSA with paroxysmal nocturnal
      hemoglobinuria (PNH) occurs in approximately 13%, myelodysplasia in about 10%, and acute
      leukemia in about 7%. Recently, results of immunosuppression in SAA with another potent
      immunosuppressive agent, cyclophosphamide, were reported in 10 patients. In this small group,
      the overall response rate was similar to that seen with ATG/CSA, but relapse and late clonal
      disease were not seen during a median follow-up of greater than 10 years. In the larger
      randomized trial proposed here, we will compare sustained hematologic response rates to
      either conventional immunosuppression with ATG/CSA or high dose cyclophosphamide and CSA.
      Secondary endpoints include response duration, event free survival, and overall survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2, 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 3, 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 20, 2001</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the sustained response proportions among patients with SAA treated with immunosuppressive therapy with either ATG/CSA or high dose cyclophosphamide and CSA.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall and event-free survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response duration. Evolution to PNH, myelodysplasia, and active leukemia.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Aplastic Anemia (SAA)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>D1-4 cyclophosphamide 50 mg/kg IV, then cyclosporine starting on d14 at 12 mg/kg/d for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ATG at 40 mg/kg/d for 4 days then cyclosporine at 12 mg /kg/d for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>antithymocyte globulin</intervention_name>
    <description>antithymocyte globulin</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>cyclophosphamide</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cyclosporine</intervention_name>
    <description>cyclosporine</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Severe aplastic anemia confirmed at NIH by:

          1. Bone marrow cellularity less than thirty percent (excluding lymphocytes).

          2. At least two of the following:

        Absolute neutrophil count less that 500/mm(3);

        Platelet count less than 20,000/mm(3);

        Reticulocyte count less than 60,000/mm(3).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Serum creatinine greater than to 2.5 mg/dl.

        Cardiac ejection fraction less than 45% by MUGA.

        Underlying carcinoma (except local cervical, basal cell, squamous cell or melanoma).

        Current pregnancy or unwilling to take oral contraceptives.

        Diagnosis of Fanconi anemia or other congenital bone marrow failure syndromes.

        Evidence of a clonal disorder on cytogenetics.

        HIV positivity.

        Inability to understand the investigational nature of the study.

        Patients who are moribund or have hepatic, renal, cardiac, metabolic or other concurrent
        diseases of such severity that death within 7-10 days is likely.

        Previous treatment with ATG, or cyclophosphamide.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neal S Young, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_1997-H-0117.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 4, 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe Aplastic Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Aplastic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antilymphocyte Serum</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

