<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005485</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN268201800010I</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN268201800011I</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN268201800012I</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN268201800013I</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN268201800014I</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN268201800015I</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005485</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Jackson Heart Study of Cardiovascular Disease Among African Americans</brief_title>
  <acronym>JHS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Jackson Heart Study of Cardiovascular Disease Among African Americans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective study of the environmental and genetic factors that influence the
      development of cardiovascular disease (CVD) in African American men and women. The cohort is
      an expansion of the Jackson, Mississippi site of the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities
      (ARIC) study and is a partnership among two minority institutions (Jackson State University
      and Tougaloo College), one majority institution in Jackson, Mississippi (the University of
      Mississippi Medical Center), the Mississippi State Department of Health, the National
      Institutes of Health (NIH) National Center on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NCMHD),
      and the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Jackson Heart Study (JHS) initiated in 1998, is a longitudinal investigation of genetic
      and environmental risk factors associated with the disproportionate burden of cardiovascular
      disease (CVD) in African-Americans. In addition, the JHS conducts community education and
      outreach activities to promote healthy lifestyles and reduce disease risk burden,
      undergraduate- and graduate-level research training programs, and high school science and
      math enrichment programs to prepare and encourage underrepresented minority students to
      pursue biomedical careers. The JHS represents an expansion of the Jackson Field Center of the
      Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities study, to broaden data collection in an African- American
      population and to increase access to and participation of African American populations and
      scientists in biomedical research and professions. The study recruited 5306 African-American
      residents living in the Jackson, MS, metropolitan statistical area (MSA) of Hinds, Madison,
      and Rankin Counties. Participants were enrolled from each of 4 recruitment pools: random,
      17%; volunteer, 30%; currently enrolled in the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC)
      Study, 31% (shared JHS/ARIC cohort); and secondary family members, 22%. Recruitment was
      limited to non-institutionalized adult African Americans 35-84 years old, except in a nested
      family cohort where those 21 to 34 years of age were also eligible. The final cohort of
      participants included 6.59% of all African American Jackson MSA residents aged 35-84 during
      the baseline exam (N-76,426, US Census 2000). Among these, approximately 3,700 gave consent
      that allows genetic research and deposition of data into dbGaP. Enrolled JHS participants
      received three back-to-back clinical examinations (Exam 1, 2000-04; Exam 2, 2005-08; and Exam
      3, 2009-13) that have generated extensive longitudinal data on: traditional and putative CVD
      risk factors, socioeconomic and sociocultural factors, and biochemical analytes; and measures
      of subclinical disease from echocardiography, cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and
      computed tomography (CT) scans of the heart, aorta, and abdomen. Stored biological samples
      have been assayed for putative biochemical risk factors and stored for future research. DNA
      has been extracted and lymphocytes cryopreserved for study of candidate genes, genome-wide
      scanning, expression, and other -omics investigations. Participants have been contacted
      annually to: update information; confirm vital statistics; document interim medical events,
      hospitalizations, and functional status; and obtain additional sociocultural information.
      Ongoing cohort surveillance includes abstraction of medical records and death certificates
      for relevant International Classification of Diseases (ICD) codes and adjudication of
      nonfatal events and deaths. The JHS serves as a resource to the scientific community for
      novel research, promotes cardiovascular health in the local community, and encourages
      underrepresented minority students to pursue biomedical careers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    COVID-19 outbreak
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>2000-2016</time_frame>
    <description>Coronary Heart Disease, Stroke, Heart Failure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>2000-2018</time_frame>
    <description>All Cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5306</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Disorders</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum, plasma, urine, DNA
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        African-American men and women residents of metropolitan Jackson, Mississippi
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  African American

          -  Residents of Jackson, Mississippi

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Institutionalization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>84 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wendy White, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tougaloo College JHS UTEC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marinelle Payton, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jackson State University JHS GTEC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adolfo Correa, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMMC JHS CC and FC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victor Sutton, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mississippi State Department of Health JHS CEC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bettina Beech, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMMC JHS GTEC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Mississippi Medical Center Department of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jackson</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.jacksonheartstudy.org/</url>
    <description>Jackson Heart Study website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sempos CT, Bild DE, Manolio TA. Overview of the Jackson Heart Study: a study of cardiovascular diseases in African American men and women. Am J Med Sci. 1999 Mar;317(3):142-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10100686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crook ED, Taylor H. Traditional and non-traditional risk factors for cardiovascular and renal disease in African Americans: a project of the Jackson Heart Study investigators. Am J Med Sci. 2002 Sep;324(3):115.</citation>
    <PMID>12240708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wyatt SB, Williams DR, Calvin R, Henderson FC, Walker ER, Winters K. Racism and cardiovascular disease in African Americans. Am J Med Sci. 2003 Jun;325(6):315-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12811228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crook ED, Taylor H. Traditional and nontraditional risk factors for cardiovascular and renal disease in African Americans (Part 2): a project of the Jackson Heart Study investigators. Am J Med Sci. 2003 Jun;325(6):305-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12811226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wyatt SB, Diekelmann N, Henderson F, Andrew ME, Billingsley G, Felder SH, Fuqua S, Jackson PB. A community-driven model of research participation: the Jackson Heart Study Participant Recruitment and Retention Study. Ethn Dis. 2003 Fall;13(4):438-55.</citation>
    <PMID>14632263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor HA Jr. Establishing a foundation for cardiovascular disease research in an African-American community--the Jackson Heart Study. Ethn Dis. 2003 Fall;13(4):411-3.</citation>
    <PMID>14632260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor HA Jr, Clark BL, Garrison RJ, Andrew ME, Han H, Fox ER, Arnett DK, Samdarshi T, Jones DW. Relation of aortic valve sclerosis to risk of coronary heart disease in African-Americans. Am J Cardiol. 2005 Feb 1;95(3):401-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15670554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carpenter MA, Crow R, Steffes M, Rock W, Heilbraun J, Evans G, Skelton T, Jensen R, Sarpong D. Laboratory, reading center, and coordinating center data management methods in the Jackson Heart Study. Am J Med Sci. 2004 Sep;328(3):131-44.</citation>
    <PMID>15367870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebrovascular Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The JHS adheres to NIH and NHLBI policies for data sharing of epidemiologic studies. Data from each cycle of an examination or follow-up component are prepared by the JHS Coordinating Center and sent to the NHLBI PO for distribution as a data set after the completion of each examination or two years after the baseline, follow-up, genetic, ancillary study, or other data set is finalized within the study for analysis for use in publication. De-identified data from Exams 1, 2 and 3 of the JHS are available and shared commonly through the JHS processes for presentation and publication, ancillary studies, and Vanguard Centers. Public datasets for Exam 1, Exam 2, and Exam 3 have been provided to BioLINCC and dbGaP.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data are currently available for exams 1, 2 and 3 and for hospitalizations for cardiovascular events (2000-2015+ for coronary heart disease and stroke; 2005-2015+ for heart failure) and mortality (2000-2017+). Data will be available indefinitely.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data can accessed from JHS with approved manuscript proposals and from dbGaP and BIOLINCC.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.jacksonheartstudy.org/</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

