<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970057</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-DC-0057</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Linkage Studies of Stuttering</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic Studies of Stuttering</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stuttering is an abnormality in speech that affects the rhythm of speech. People who stutter
      know what they wish to say, but at the time are unable to say it because of involuntary
      repetition, unnecessary lengthening (prolongation), or early stopping (cessation). Stuttering
      is characterized by repetitions or prolongation of the first syllable, or silent
      prolongations, sometimes known as blocks.

      Researcher intend on studying the genetic basis for stuttering. The goal of the study is to
      find the genes that help cause stuttering and determine regions of the human genetic make-up
      (genome) that are linked to stuttering.. To do this researchers will study the patterns of
      inheritance in families who have had members who stutter.

      The study has two objectives.

      The first objective is to develop a large collection of DNA samples from individuals in
      stuttering families, that will include both members that stutter and who do not stutter.

      The second objective of the study will be to find out the basic combination of genes
      (genotype) making up all of the participants DNA. Once this is completed researchers hope to
      map out and find areas or regions of DNA that are linked to stuttering.

      Genetic linkage is the initial step in positional cloning, and the cloning of genes which
      predispose individuals to stuttering is a long term goal of this research study.&lt;TAB&gt;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A primary goal of this study is to ascertain regions of the human genome which show genetic
      linkage to stuttering. Genetic linkage will be determined by first obtaining genomic DNA from
      both affected and unaffected adults and children from families containing pairs of
      individuals who stutter as adults. Individuals who stutter from genetically isolated
      populations will also be sampled. Phenotype will be assigned by a speech-language
      pathologist, and DNA samples will be obtained from affected and unaffected family members
      from 2 cc. of saliva or from 20 cc. of blood. These DNA samples will then be genotyped using
      markers distributed across the human genome. The genotypic information analyzed to determine
      which markers or variants show linkage to stuttering. The initial goal of this study is to
      identify specific genetic variants, which predispose individuals to stuttering. No genetic
      information will be provided back to participants. A secondary goal of the study will be to
      perform broad clinical evaluations of the individuals found to have mutations that cause
      stuttering. These will take place at the NIH Clinical Center and will include standard
      procedures including history and physical, neurological exam, audiological exam,
      ophthalmologic exam, electromyographic (EMG) exam, electroencephalography (EEG), X-rays,
      speech evaluation, and brain imaging including MRI and fMRI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 22, 2003</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify genetic mutations or variants that predispose humans to stuttering.</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>Our primary outcome measures are the observation or exclusion of genetic linkage to stuttering at a discreet locus or genetic association with stuttering with a specific genetic variant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perform clinical and physical evaluations on those individuals who stutter and possess these genetic variants</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>disorders in study subjects carrying genetic variants shown to be associated with stuttering in the primary outcome measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3044</enrollment>
  <condition>Stuttering</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with a family history of stuttering</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be selected primarily on the basis of family history of stuttering. Certain
        populations, such as those in Pakistan present increased power to detect genetic influences
        on stuttering, and such populations will be preferentially enrolled where possible and
        appropriate. No one will be excluded on the basis of gender or ethnic/racial background.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Individuals age 8 and older.

          -  Individuals age 6-8 with a family history of persistent stuttering

          -  Have stuttering that persists for a period of 6 months or more or are a family member
             of that person

          -  For the Phase 2 imaging studies, we will be enrolling up to 25 healthy volunteers to
             be controls

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Stuttering only as a young child (not beyond the age of 5)

          -  Cannot provide informed consent or have a parent/guardian to provide consent

          -  Developed stuttering following trauma to the central nervous system.

          -  Chronic medical conditions that prevent informed consent or clear evaluation of
             stuttering, including stroke, dementia, and degenerative neurological disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carter Van Waes, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Deafness and Other Communication Disorders (NIDCD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Punjab</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahore</city>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Central African Republic</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_1997-DC-0057.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 11, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DNA Samples</keyword>
  <keyword>Stuttering</keyword>
  <keyword>DNA Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Statistical Analysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Computers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stuttering</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

