<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001406</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>940079</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>94-I-0079</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001406</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Activation and Function of Eosinophils in Conditions With Blood or Tissue Eosinophilia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Eosinophil Activation and Function in Parasitic Infections and Other Conditions With Increased Tissue or Peripheral Blood Eosinophilia in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate how, why and under what conditions eosinophils (a type of white
      blood cell) become activated and will examine their function in immune reactions. Eosinophil
      counts often rise in response to allergies, asthma, and parasitic worm infections. They can
      also go up in uncommon autoimmune conditions and, rarely, in association with tumors.
      Elevated levels of these cells is called eosinophilia. Usually, eosinophilia causes no
      apparent symptoms, but in rare cases there may be local swelling and itching, allergic lung
      problems, heart disease or nerve damage caused by the release of toxic substances in these
      cells into body tissues.

      Patients 1 to 100 years of age with eosinophil counts greater than 750/ml or an abnormal
      accumulation of eosinophils in the skin or body tissues may be eligible for this study. All
      participants will have a thorough medical history, physical examination and blood tests.
      Depending on the person's age and symptoms, other diagnostic tests may be done, including
      specialized studies of the eye, lungs, skin, bone marrow, nerves or heart. This is not a
      treatment study, and no experimental treatments will be offered. Patients who require
      treatment will receive standard medical care.

      Certain other procedures may be requested solely for research purposes. All participants will
      be asked to donate extra blood for laboratory studies investigating how immune cells and
      other immune substances in the blood act to stimulate a rise in eosinophils. In addition,
      some participants may undergo one or more of the following:

        -  Annual Follow-up evaluations - Physical examinations and blood tests to evaluate changes
           in the patient's condition and eosinophil counts over time.

        -  Bone marrow biopsy and aspiration will be recommended during the initial evaluation, and
           in certain patients at other times when it is important to look directly at the newly
           developing cells in the bone marrow. For this procedure an area of skin and bone is
           anesthetized with xylocaine (an anesthetic similar to that used by dentists), and a very
           sharp needle is used to sample the bone marrow for evaluation. Bone marrow biopsy and
           aspiration can have side effects of pain and/or bleeding into the skin and soft tissues
           at the site of the procedure. Rarely the area at the biopsy site can become infected,
           and is treated with antibiotics.

        -  Genetic testing: Some of the blood drawn from you as part of this study will be used for
           genetic tests. Genetic tests can help researchers study how health or illness is passed
           on to you by your parents or from you to your children. Any genetic information
           collected or discovered about you or your family will be confidential.

        -  Leukapheresis (only patients 18 years and older) to collect large numbers of certain
           cells - In this procedure, whole blood is collected through a needle placed in an arm
           vein. The blood circulates through a machine that separates it into its components. The
           white cells are then removed and the rest of the blood is returned to the body, either
           through the same needle used to draw the blood or through a second needle placed in the
           other arm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects admitted on this protocol will have elevated eosinophil counts in the peripheral
      blood or tissues or will be relatives of subjects with eosinophilia. Eosinophilic subjects
      will undergo an extensive clinical evaluation focused on the identification of the cause of
      eosinophilia and the presence of end organ manifestations. In addition, they will be
      characterized in detail immunologically, and their blood cells and/or serum will be collected
      to provide reagents (e.g., specific antibodies, T-cell clones, etc.) that will be used in the
      laboratory to address broader questions relating to the etiology of eosinophilia, its
      immunoregulation, the degree and source of eosinophil activation, and/or the functional role
      of eosinophils in the afferent arm of those immune response where they are prominent. While
      the protocol is not primarily designed to study treatment of patients with blood and tissue
      eosinophilia, the clinical and immunological responses to various medically indicated
      therapies will be carefully monitored. The subjects themselves will be followed over time to
      determine the kinetics and nature of the factors affecting their degree of eosinophilia and
      the level of activation or degranulation of the eosinophils at various time points and in
      response to various stimuli. It is anticipated that the subjects will receive a degree of
      clinical evaluation, care and monitoring more extensive than that generally available and
      that the specimens collected from them will prove to be valuable reagents for laboratory
      studies related to eosinophilia, eosinophil activation and function. Recognized causes of
      subjects hypereosinophilia will be treated appropriately either by our own clinical service
      or by the referring physicians. Standard of care therapy may be provided when indicated for
      HES variants. This protocol will also allow clinical and laboratory evaluation of family
      members of subjects with eosinophilia in order to help identify genetic causes of
      eosinophilia and to provide controls for immunologic studies. A subset of HES patients will
      be interviewed and/or asked to fill out questionnaires to provide information about patient
      signs and symptoms for use in the development of a patient-related outcomes questionnaire for
      use in future treatment studies. Finally, adult subjects with gastrointestinal involvement
      may be asked to provide stool samples for microbiome analysis and assessment of stool levels
      of eosinophil granule proteins to explore the role of the microbiome in eosinophilic
      gastrointestinal disease. Stool samples may also be obtained from adult subjects undergoing
      endoscopy and/or colonoscopy as part of their initial evaluation and/or assessment of
      response to treatment. Potential confounding variables, including body mass index, diet,
      stool transit time and vitamin D levels will be assessed at the time of stool collection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 21, 1997</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect data and samples to enhance the understanding of the mechanisms driving eosinophilia and eosinophil activation in patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing assessment</time_frame>
    <description>Greater understanding of the mechanisms driving eosinophilia and eosinophil activationCollect data and samples to enhance the understanding of the mechanisms driving eosinophilia and eosinophil activation in patients with a wide range of eosinophilic disorders with the ultimate goal of improving diagnostics and identifying novel treatment modalities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To explore the role of the intestinal microbiome in eosinophilic gastrointestinal inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To provide information about patient signs and symptoms for use in the development of a patient-related outcomes questionnaire for use in future treatment studies</measure>
    <time_frame>12/31/2020</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study and identify genetic causes of eosinophilia</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To develop a panel of laboratory and clinical tests that will aid in categorizing various conditions associated with blood and/or tissue eosinophilia and/or in monitoring response to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To study the role of inflammation associated cytokines/chemokines on the activation of eosinophils and their recruitment to the blood and tissues</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the degree of activation of the peripheral blood and/or tissue eosinophils found in conditions characterized by elevated levels of eosinophils</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the functional role of eosinophils in immunologic and inflammatory reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine mechanisms inducing peripheral blood and tissue eosinophil responses by evaluating these cells and other immune reactants in patients with a variety of eosinophilic conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune System Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Eosinophilia</condition>
  <condition>Helminthiasis</condition>
  <condition>Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <condition>Parasitic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Volunteers with elevated eosinophil counts in the peripheral blood or tissues; or a relative of a volunteer with eosinophilia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants with marked eosinophilia, eosinophilia in tissues or suspected eosinophilic
        end organ involvement will be seen on this protocol. Evaluation of family members may be of
        interest when a genetic cause of eosinophilia in suspected in a study participant.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA (Eosinophilic Subjects):

               1. 1-100 years of age

               2. documented peripheral blood eosinophil count &gt;1500/mm^3, tissue eosinophilia
                  (abnormal accumulation of eosinophils in the skin or other body tissues) or
                  suspected eosinophilic end organ involvement

               3. has a primary (non-NIH) physician for routine medical care

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA (Eosinophilic Subjects):

        1) medical conditions or therapies that the investigator feels put the subject at
        unacceptable risk for participation in the study

        INCLUSION CRITERIA (Relatives):

          1. 1-100 years of age

          2. extended family member of a study participant in 94-I-0079

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA (Relatives):

        1) any condition that the investigator feels put the subject at unacceptable risk for
        participation in the study.

        Participation of Women:

        Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding will not be excluded, although procedures will be
        limited to those that are clinically indicated and/or pose no increased risk during
        pregnancy (such as echocardiopgraphy). Research blood collection will be limited in
        participants who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA (Hypereosinophilic Syndrome (HES) Concept Elicitation Substudy):

        Each participant must meet the following criteria to be enrolled in the study:

          1. Diagnosis of HES for at least 6 months

          2. Documentation of symptoms for a minimum of 12 months

          3. A change in symptoms that required a change in medication at least once in the past 12
             months

          4. Age 12 years or older

          5. Adequate written and oral fluency in English

          6. Willing to provide written informed consent

          7. Willing to have the interview audio-recorded

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA (Hypereosinophilic Syndrome (HES) Concept Elicitation Substudy):

        The presence of any of the following will exclude a subject from the study:

          1. Has a cognitive or physical impairment that would interfere with the subject s ability
             to complete the study.

          2. Lack of fluency in spoken English

          3. Positive for the FIP1L1-PDGFRA fusion tyrosine kinase gene translocation.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA (Development of the Hypereosinophilic Syndrome Symptom Inventory
        (HES-SI)):

          1. Have an existing diagnosis of HES

          2. Be enrolled on protocol 94-I-0079

          3. Age 12 or greater

          4. Written and oral fluency in English

          5. Willingness to provide informed consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA (Development of the Hypereosinophilic Syndrome Symptom Inventory
        (HES-SI)):

        Any condition that, in the investigator s opinion, places the subject at undue risk by
        participating in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy D Klion, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicole C Holland-Thomas, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-5969</phone>
    <email>hollandnc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amy D Klion, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-8903</phone>
    <email>aklion@niaid.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1994-I-0079.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 10, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Eosinophils</keyword>
  <keyword>Helminth Parasites</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypereosinophilia</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergy</keyword>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Helminthiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eosinophilia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immune System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parasitic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

