<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03086486</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ZeNix (B-Pa-L) NC-007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03086486</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Various Doses and Treatment Durations of Linezolid Plus Bedaquiline and Pretomanid in Participants With Pulmonary TB, XDR-TB, Pre- XDR-TB or Non-responsive/Intolerant MDR-TB (ZeNix)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3 Partially-blinded, Randomized Trial Assessing the Safety and Efficacy of Various Doses and Treatment Durations of Linezolid Plus Bedaquiline and Pretomanid in Participants With Pulmonary Infection of Either Extensively Drug-resistant Tuberculosis (XDR-TB), Pre-XDR-TB or Treatment Intolerant or Non-responsive Multi-drug Resistant Tuberculosis (MDR-TB)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Global Alliance for TB Drug Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Global Alliance for TB Drug Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability of various doses and durations of linezolid
      plus bedaquiline and pretomanid after 26 weeks of treatment in participants with either
      pulmonary XDR-TB, pre-XDR-TB, or treatment intolerant or non-responsive MDR-TB.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A phase 3, multi-center, partially-blinded, randomized clinical trial in four parallel
      treatment groups. Bedaquiline and pretomanid treatment will not be blinded. Linezolid
      treatment dose and duration will be double-blinded.

      Participants will have a screening period of up to 14 days and will be randomized to receive
      one of the 4 active treatment arms. Participants will be randomized to one of the four
      regimens in a 1:1:1:1 ratio, using an interactive voice and web response system (IXRS) which
      will utilize a randomization system using stratification with a random element to allocate
      participants evenly across the arms by HIV status and type of TB.

      Each participant will receive 26 weeks of treatment. If participant's week 16 sputum sample
      is culture positive between the week 16 and week 26 treatment visits and their clinical
      condition suggests they may have an ongoing TB infection, Investigator may consider extending
      current treatment to 39 weeks. If the culture results between week 16 and week 26 are
      contaminated, missing or considered an isolated positive without clinical significance,
      available culture results should be used to make this decision. All decisions regarding
      treatment extension should be discussed with and approved by, in consultation with the
      Sponsor Medical Monitor before implementation.

      Participants will be followed for 78 weeks after end of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 21, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of bacteriologic failure or relapse or clinical failure through follow up until 26 weeks after the end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion requires at least 2 consecutive culture negative/positive samples at least 7 days apart.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of bacteriologic failure or relapse or clinical failure through follow up until 78 weeks after the end of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>78 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion requires at least 2 consecutive culture negative/positive samples at least 7 days apart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to sputum culture conversion to negative status through the treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with sputum culture conversion to negative status at week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with sputum culture conversion to negative status at week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with sputum culture conversion to negative status at week 8</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with sputum culture conversion to negative status at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with sputum culture conversion to negative status at week 16</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with sputum culture conversion to negative status at week 26</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Culture conversion is a diagnostic criteria indicating the point at which samples taken from a patient infected with a tuberculosis can no longer produce tuberculosis cell cultures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline TB symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Severity of symptoms compared to start of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Patient Reported Health Status</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Patient Reported Health Status to start of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline weight.</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of weight from start of treatment until end of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</condition>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, Multidrug-Resistant</condition>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, MDR</condition>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <condition>Extensively Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</condition>
  <condition>Pre-XDR-TB</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1200mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 linezolid 600 mg active tablets once daily for 26 weeks plus 1 placebo linezolid 300 mg half tablet once daily for 26 weeks plus; bedaquiline 200 mg once daily for 8 weeks then 100 mg once daily for 18 weeks plus; pretomanid 200 mg once daily for 26 weeks
The above treatment schemes may require modification due to toxicities as noted below. All dose modifications should be discussed with the Sponsor Medical Monitor prior to implementation, unless a pause or dose reduction is required urgently for a safety concern; the Medical Monitor should be informed within 24 hours of the change if not discussed prior to implementation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1200 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 linezolid 600 mg active tablets once daily for 9 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 300 mg half tablet once daily for 9 weeks (for Weeks 1-9); 2 placebo linezolid 600 mg tablets once daily for 17 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 300 mg half tablet once daily for 17 weeks (for Weeks 10-26) plus; bedaquiline 200 mg once daily for 8 weeks then 100 mg once daily for 18 weeks plus; pretomanid 200 mg once daily for 26 weeks
The above treatment schemes may require modification due to toxicities as noted below. All dose modifications should be discussed with the Sponsor Medical Monitor prior to implementation, unless a pause or dose reduction is required urgently for a safety concern; the Medical Monitor should be informed within 24 hours of the change if not discussed prior to implementation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 linezolid 600 mg active tablet once daily for 26 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 600 mg tablet once daily for 26 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 300 mg half tablet once daily for 26 weeks plus; bedaquiline 200 mg once daily for 8 weeks then 100 mg once daily for 18 weeks plus; pretomanid 200 mg once daily for 26 weeks
The above treatment schemes may require modification due to toxicities as noted below. All dose modifications should be discussed with the Sponsor Medical Monitor prior to implementation, unless a pause or dose reduction is required urgently for a safety concern; the Medical Monitor should be informed within 24 hours of the change if not discussed prior to implementation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 linezolid 600 mg active tablets once daily for 8 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 600 mg half tablet once daily for 9 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 300 mg half tablet once daily for 9 weeks (for Weeks 1-9); 2 placebo linezolid 600 mg tablets once daily for 17 weeks, 1 placebo linezolid 300 mg half tablet once daily for 17 weeks (for Weeks 10-26) plus; bedaquiline 200 mg once daily for 8 weeks then 100 mg once daily for 18 weeks plus; pretomanid 200 mg once daily for 26 weeks
The above treatment schemes may require modification due to toxicities as noted below. All dose modifications should be discussed with the Sponsor Medical Monitor prior to implementation, unless a pause or dose reduction is required urgently for a safety concern; the Medical Monitor should be informed within 24 hours of the change if not discussed prior to implementation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pretomanid</intervention_name>
    <description>200mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>1200 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1200mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PA-824</other_name>
    <other_name>Pa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Linezolid</intervention_name>
    <description>Scored 600mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>1200 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1200mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>L</other_name>
    <other_name>Lin</other_name>
    <other_name>Zyvox</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bedaquiline</intervention_name>
    <description>100mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>1200 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1200mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMC-207</other_name>
    <other_name>B</other_name>
    <other_name>Sirturo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Linezolid</intervention_name>
    <description>Scored 600 mg tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>1200 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1200mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 26 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>600 mg L x 9 weeks + Pa + B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants are required to meet all of the following inclusion criteria during the
        screening period in order to be randomized.

          1. Provide written, informed consent prior to all trial-related procedures (including any
             additional consent required for participants considered as minors per applicable
             regulatory authority or ethics committee).

          2. Willingness and ability to attend scheduled follow-up visits and undergo study
             assessments.

          3. HIV testing (if an HIV test was performed within 1 month prior to screening, it should
             not be repeated as long as a documented result can be provided [ELISA and/or Western
             Blot and/or Electro-Chemiluminescence]. If HIV status is a confirmed known positive,
             repeated HIV test is not needed if ELISA and/or Western Blot and/or
             Electro-Chemiluminescence documentation of presence of HIV infection is available.

          4. Male or female, aged 14 years or older. (Male or female, aged 18 years or older in
             Moldova or Russia).

             Disease Characteristics:

          5. Participants with one of the following pulmonary TB conditions:

             a. XDR-TB with i. A documented culture positive or a molecular test positive (for MTB)
             from a sputum specimen collected within 3 months prior to screening or MTB confirmed
             in sputum based on molecular test within 3 months prior to or at screening and: ii.
             documented resistance to isoniazid, rifamycins, a fluoroquinolone AND an injectable
             during the current TB diagnosis/disease course any time prior to or during screening
             period (may be sensitive or resistant to isoniazid);

             b. Pre-XDR-TB with i. A documented culture positive or a molecular test positive (for
             MTB) from a sputum specimen collected within 3 months prior to screening or MTB
             confirmed in sputum based molecular test within 3 months prior to or at screening and;
             ii. documented resistance to rifamycins, and to a fluoroquinolone OR an injectable
             during the current TB diagnosis/disease course any time prior to or during screening
             period (may be sensitive or resistant to isoniazid);

             c. MDR-TB with i. documented by culture positive or a molecular test positive (for
             MTB) from a sputum specimen collected results within 3 months prior to screening or
             MTB confirmed in sputum based on molecular test within 3 months prior to or at
             screening and; ii. documented resistance to rifamycins, and to a fluoroquinolone OR an
             injectable during the current TB diagnosis/disease course any time prior to or during
             screening period (may be sensitive or resistant to isoniazid) and; iii. with
             documented non-response to treatment with the best available regimen for 6 months or
             more prior to enrollment who in the opinion of the Investigator have been adherent to
             treatment and will be adherent to study regimen.

             d. MDR-TB with i. documented by culture positive or a molecular test positive (for
             MTB) from a sputum specimen collected within 3 months prior to screening or MTB
             confirmed in sputum based on molecular test within 3 months prior to or at screening
             and: ii. documented resistance to isoniazid and rifamycins during the current TB
             diagnosis/disease course any time prior to or during screening period (may be
             sensitive or resistant to isoniazid) and; iii. who are unable to continue second line
             drug regimen due to a documented intolerance to:

               1. PAS, ethionamide, aminoglycosides or fluoroquinolones or;

               2. Current treatment not listed above that renders participant eligible for the
                  study in the Investigator's opinion.

          6. Chest X-Ray within 6 months prior to or at screening, obtained and read locally by
             investigator or designee with results consistent with pulmonary TB in the opinion of
             the Investigator.

             Contraception:

          7. Be of non-childbearing potential or using effective methods of birth control, as
             defined below:

        Non-childbearing potential:

          1. Participant - not heterosexually active or practices sexual abstinence; or

          2. Female participant or male participant's female /sexual partner - bilateral
             oophorectomy, bilateral tubal ligation and/or hysterectomy or has been postmenopausal
             with a history of no menses for at least 12 consecutive months; or

          3. Male participant or female participant's male /sexual partner - vasectomised or has
             had a bilateral orchidectomy at least three months prior to screening.

        Effective birth control methods:

          1. Double barrier method which can include: a male condom, diaphragm, cervical cap, or
             female condom; or

          2. Female participant: Barrier method combined with hormone-based contraceptives or an
             intra-uterine device for the female participant;

          3. Male participant's female sexual partner: Double barrier method or hormone based
             contraceptives or an intra-uterine device for the female partner.

        And are willing to continue practicing birth control methods throughout treatment and for 6
        months (female participants) and 12 weeks (male participants) after the last dose of study
        medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Participants will be excluded from participation if they meet any of the following criteria
        during the screening period:

        Medical History and Concurrent Conditions

          1. Any condition in the Investigator's opinion (i.e., an unstable disease such as
             uncontrolled diabetes or cardiomyopathy, extra-pulmonary TB requiring extended
             treatment, cancer that could affect survival through the protocol-specified follow up
             period), where participation in the trial would compromise the well-being of
             participant or prevent, limit or confound protocol specified assessments.

          2. Abuse of alcohol or illegal drugs that in the opinion of the Investigator would
             compromise the participants' safety or ability to follow through with all
             protocol-specified restrictions, visits and evaluations.

          3. In the judgment of the Investigator, the patient is not expected to survive for more
             than 6 months.

          4. Karnofsky score &lt; 60 at screening.

          5. History of allergy or known hypersensitivity to any of the trial Investigational
             Medicinal Products or related substances.

          6. Body mass index (BMI) &lt; 17 kg/m2

          7. TB infection with historic DST or MIC results with values suggesting likely resistance
             to pretomanid, delamanid, linezolid or bedaquiline.; the Sponsor Medical Monitor must
             be consulted to help interpret any available historic results.

          8. Participants who, upon the evaluation of their pulmonary disease, are expected to
             require a surgical procedure.

          9. Having participated in other clinical studies with dosing of investigational agents
             within 8 weeks prior to screening or currently enrolled in an investigational study
             that includes treatment with medicinal agents. Participants who are participating in
             observational studies or who are in a follow up period of a trial that included drug
             therapy may be considered for inclusion.

         10. Participants with any of the following at Screening:

               -  QTcF interval on ECG &gt;500 msec. Participants with QTcF &gt; 450 must be discussed
                  with and approved by the Sponsor Medical Monitor before enrollment. (Per
                  measurements and reading done from screening central ECG.)

               -  Heart failure

               -  A personal or family history of congenital QT prolongation

               -  A history of or known, untreated, ongoing hypothyroidism

               -  A history of or ongoing bradyarrhythmia

               -  A history of Torsade de Pointe

         11. (Russia only) Participants with any of the following conditions where the use of
             linezolid is contraindicated:

               -  A history of thyrotoxicosis

               -  A history of uncontrolled arterial hypertension

               -  A history of pheochromocytoma

               -  A history of carcinoid syndrome

               -  A history of bipolar disorder

               -  A history of schizoaffective disorder

         12. Females who have a positive pregnancy test at Screening or already known to be
             pregnant, breast-feeding, or planning to conceive a child during the study or within 6
             months of cessation of treatment. Males planning to conceive a child during the study
             or within 6 months of cessation of treatment.

         13. A peripheral neuropathy of Grade 3 or 4, according to DMID. Or, participants with a
             Grade 1 or 2 neuropathy which is likely to progress/worsen over the course of the
             study, in the opinion of the Investigator.

         14. (Russia only) Participants with lactose intolerance, lactase deficiency and/or
             glucose-galactose malabsorption.

             Previous and Concomitant Therapy

         15. Known (during screening) requirement for future Concomitant (during treatment) use of
             any prohibited and/or avoided medications noted in section 5.3.

         16. Prior use of Monoamine Oxidase Inhibitors (MAOIs) within 2 weeks of randomization.

         17. Prior use of serotonergic antidepressants within 3 days of randomization if
             Investigator foresees potential risks for serotonin syndrome when combined with
             linezolid.

         18. Participants who have received more than 2 weeks of bedaquiline, linezolid or
             delamanid prior to first dose of IMP.

         19. Participants with newly diagnosed tuberculosis and HIV that require initiation of
             appropriate HIV therapy before participant has received at least 2 weeks of an
             anti-tuberculosis regimen.

         20. HIV infected participants with planned continued use of zidovudine, stavudine, or
             didanosine. The antiretroviral therapy (ART) booster cobicistat should not be used.

             Diagnostic and Laboratory Abnormalities

         21. Participants with any of the following toxicities at Screening (labs may be repeated
             during screening period) as defined by the enhanced Division of Microbiology and
             Infectious Disease (DMID) adult toxicity table (November 2007):

               1. Viral load &gt;1000 copies/mL (Unless newly diagnosed HIV and not yet on ART who
                  otherwise qualify for participation);

               2. CD4+ count &lt; 100 cells/µL (HIV positive participants);

               3. Serum potassium less than the lower limit of normal for the laboratory;

               4. Hemoglobin &lt; 9.0 g/dL or 90g/L;

               5. Platelets &lt;100,000/mm3 or &lt; 100 x 10^9/L ;

               6. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1500/ mm3 or &lt; 1.5 x 10^9/L;

               7. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)

                    -  Grade 3 or greater (&gt; 3.0 x ULN) to be excluded;

                    -  Results between 1.5 x ULN and 3 x ULN must be discussed with and approved by
                       the Sponsor Medical Monitor

               8. Alanine aminotransferase

                    -  Grade 3 or greater (&gt; 3.0 x ULN) to be excluded;

                    -  Results between 1.5 x ULN and 3 x ULN must be discussed with and approved by
                       the Sponsor medical monitor;

               9. Total bilirubin

                    -  greater than 1.5 x ULN to be excluded;

                    -  1-1.5 x ULN must be discussed with and approved by the Sponsor Medical
                       Monitor

              10. Direct bilirubin

                  • Greater than ULN to be excluded

              11. Serum creatinine level greater than 1.5 times upper limit of normal

              12. Albumin &lt;3.0 g/dl or &lt; 30 g/L

        All inclusion and no exclusion criteria must be met. If no single variable/value is outside
        of the ranges of acceptability, but when multiple values are close to the limits and/or
        whenever the Investigator has reason to suspect that there might be a health problem (other
        than TB), enrolment should only be considered after discussing the case with the sponsor
        medical monitor.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Center for Tuberculosis and Lung Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tbilisi</city>
        <zip>0101</zip>
        <country>Georgia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Phthisiopneumology Chiril Draganiuc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chisinau</city>
        <zip>2025</zip>
        <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moscow City Research and Practice Tuberculosis Treatment Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>107014</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central TB Research Institute of the Federal Agency of Scientific Organizations Moscow</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>107564</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Medical Research Center of Phthisiopulmonology and Infectious Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>FSBI &quot;Saint-Petersburg Research Institute of Phthisiopulmonology&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>191036</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ural Research Institute of Phthisiopulmonology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yekaterinburg</city>
        <zip>620039</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Empilweni TB Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Elizabeth</city>
        <state>Eastern Cape</state>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tshepong Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Klerksdorp</city>
        <state>North - West</state>
        <zip>2574</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King DinuZulu Hospital Complex</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durban</city>
        <zip>4015</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical HIV Research Unit (CHRU) Sizwe Tropical Diseases Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johannesburg</city>
        <zip>2131</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Georgia</country>
    <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Multi Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Extensively Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Pretomanid</keyword>
  <keyword>PA-824</keyword>
  <keyword>Bedaquiline</keyword>
  <keyword>Linezolid</keyword>
  <keyword>NC-007</keyword>
  <keyword>TB Alliance</keyword>
  <keyword>pre-XDR-TB</keyword>
  <keyword>Sirturo</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Multidrug-Resistant</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Extensively Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Linezolid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bedaquiline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

