<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04079075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EPIUnit_MIND_2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04079075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multiple Interventions to Prevent Cognitive Decline</brief_title>
  <acronym>MIND</acronym>
  <official_title>Multiple Interventions to Prevent Cognitive Decline</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade do Porto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade do Porto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to test the feasibility of a pragmatic non-pharmacological strategy,
      that may prevent cognitive decline in patients with mild cognitive impairment. This strategy
      is based on five different interventions: cognitive training, physical activity, nutrition
      education, adaption to memory loss, diagnosis and correction of hearing impairment.

      A quasi-experimental study will be implemented in Porto (Portugal), including patients that
      fulfill all of the following criteria: a) age 18-85 years; b) Montreal Cognitive Assessment
      (MoCA) score greater than or equal to two standard deviations below the normative reference
      value for the corresponding age and education level in the Portuguese population OR diagnosis
      of Mild Cognitive Impairment, performed by a Neurologist, during the six previous months,
      considering the results of a neuropsychological battery; c) Cardiovascular Risk Factors,
      Aging and Dementia (CAIDE) Dementia Risk Score of at least six points. Patients who have any
      medical disability that contraindicates physical activity or have a lack of autonomy in daily
      activities will be excluded.

      The program will be implemented in groups of 10 participants, over a period of 10 consecutive
      months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Detailed description

      This is a quasi-experimental study in which the investigators aim to test the feasibility of
      a non-pharmacological strategy to prevent cognitive decline in patients with a diagnosis of
      mild cognitive impairment. This strategy is based on five different interventions:

      a) Cognitive training

      This comprises training using using the cogweb software, both in person and remotely:

      i) in person training: 30-minute sessions, supervised by a trained nurse, twice weekly .

      ii) remote training: unsupervised 30-minute sessions, to be performed at home at the
      participants will.

      b) Physical activity This is based on 60-minute sessions including aerobic, resistance,
      agility/balance and flexibility exercises, directed by a physical education teacher and
      supervised by a nurse, twice weekly.

      c) Nutrition education

      This is based on monthly 180-minute sessions, directed by a nutritionist, comprising:

      i) Presentation and discussion of healthy and easy to cook recipes by the nutritionist; ii)
      Preparation of healthy meals by the participants, followed by a period of social interaction
      between the participants while consuming the meals prepared.

      d) Adaptation to memory loss This is based on monthly 30-minute sessions, directed by a
      psychologist or a nurse, who will provide strategies that participants may use in their daily
      life to cope with memory loss.

      e) Diagnosis of hearing impairment Before implementing the sessions of cognitive training,
      physical activity, nutrition education and adaption to memory loss, an audiologist will
      perform an audiogram to all participants. Those with auditive performance inferior to the
      reference values will be referred for a medical appointment with an otolaryngologist.

      Strategies (a),(b), (c) and (d) will be implemented over a period of 10 months, in groups of
      10 participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive performance 1</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's cognitive performance assessed using the Montreal Cognitive Assessment, between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up. This scale varies from 0 (worst cognitive performance) to 30 points (best cognitive performance).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's body mass index between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the Mediterranean diet</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's self-reported adherence to the Mediterranean diet, assessed using the Mediterranean food pattern (PREDIMED) scale, between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up. This scale varies from 0 (lowest adherence to the Mediterranean diet) to 14 points (highest adherence to the Mediterranean diet). A score over 10 points indicates good adherence to the Mediterranean diet.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of steps</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's number of steps, assessed using a portable accelerometer, between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to each intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of adherence to each intervention and component of each intervention, calculated as the number of sessions attended/total number of sessions implemented. For remote cognitive training the outcome will be the absolute number of sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dropout</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants who dropped out of the study, calculated as the number of participants who dropped out after attending at least one session/total number of participants who attended at least one session.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive performance 2</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's cognitive performance assessed using a neuropsychological battery, between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up. This will be reported in the format of a Z-score, assuming positive and negative values. Higher scores indicate better cognitive performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory complaints</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of the self-reported memory complaints, assessed using the self-reported memory complaints scale, between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up. This scale varies from 0 (best score) to 21 points (worst score). Scores over three points indicate the presence of self-reported memory complaints.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of the anxiety and depression scores, assessed using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), between the baseline assessment and the end of follow-up. This scale varies from 0 (best score) to 21 points (worst score).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reported quality of life: EQ-5D scale</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's quality of life, assessed using the EuroQol Group scale - 5 dimensions (EQ-5D) scale, between the baseline assessment and 10 months after the beginning of the intervention. This is assessed using two subscales: a) five multiple choice questions, with five response possibilities, which produce a score that varies from 5 (best score) to 25 points (worst score); b) visual analogic scale, that varies from 0 (worst score) to 100 (best score).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Handgrip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's handgrip strength, assessed using a dynamometer, between the baseline assessment and 10 months after the beginning of the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Agility 1</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's agility and balance, assessed using the Time Up and Go Test scale, between the baseline assessment and 10 months after the beginning of the intervention. This is measured in time units (seconds) and varies from 0 (best score) to infinite (worst score).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Agility 2</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of participant's agility and balance, assessed using the One Leg Balance Test, between the baseline assessment and 10 months after the beginning of the intervention. This is measured in time units (seconds) and varies from 0 (best score) to infinite (worst score).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days between the first and the last session attended by the participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implemented sessions</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of sessions implemented, calculated as the number of sessions that the research team was able to implement/total number of sessions planned.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete assessment of participants</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>For each study outcome, proportion of participants with complete information, calculated at baseline and different moments of follow-up, as the number of participants with complete information/total number of participants evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Cognition Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Memory Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-pharmacological intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-pharmacological strategy, implemented in groups of 10 participants, over 10 consecutive months, based on five different interventions:
cognitive training, physical activity; nutrition education; adaption to memory loss; detection and correction of hearing impairment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive training</intervention_name>
    <description>This comprises training using using the cogweb software, both in person and remotely:
i) in person training: 30-minute sessions, supervised by a trained nurse, twice weekly .
ii) remote training: unsupervised 30-minute sessions, to be performed at home at the participants will.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-pharmacological intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical activity</intervention_name>
    <description>This is based on 60-minute sessions including aerobic, resistance, agility/balance and flexibility exercises, directed by a physical education teacher and supervised by a nurse, twice weekly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-pharmacological intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nutrition education</intervention_name>
    <description>This is based on monthly 180-minute sessions, directed by a nutritionist, comprising:
i) Presentation and discussion of healthy and easy to cook recipes by the nutritionist; ii) Preparation of healthy meals by the participants, followed by a period of social interaction between the participants while consuming the meals prepared.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-pharmacological intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adaption to memory loss</intervention_name>
    <description>This is based on monthly 30-minute sessions, directed by a psychologist or a nurse, who will provide strategies that participants may use in their daily life to cope with memory loss.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-pharmacological intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diagnosis of hearing impairment</intervention_name>
    <description>Before implementing the sessions of cognitive training, physical activity, nutrition education and adaption to memory loss, an audiologist will perform an audiogram to all participants. Those with auditive performance inferior to the reference values will be referred for a medical appointment with an otolaryngologist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-pharmacological intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        a) Age 18-85 years;

        b1) Montreal Cognitive Assessment score ≥ to two standard deviations below the normative
        reference value for the corresponding age and education level in the Portuguese population;

        OR

        b2) clinical diagnosis of Mild Cognitive Impairment;

        c) Cardiovascular Risk Factors, Aging and Dementia Dementia Risk Score ≥ six points.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. medical disability that contraindicates physical activity;

          2. lack of autonomy in daily activities.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>João Firmino-Machado, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto de Saúde Pública da Universidade do Porto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>João Firmino-Machado, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+351 910961236</phone>
    <email>jfdmachado@arsnorte.min-saude.pt</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Agrupamento de Centros de Saúde do Porto Ocidental</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>João Firmino-Machado, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+351 910961236</phone>
      <email>jfdmachado@arsnorte.min-saude.pt</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Portugal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Correction of Hearing Impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet, Healthy</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropsychological Tests</keyword>
  <keyword>Hearing Loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Memory Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Remediation</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Memory Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

