<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04076930</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>THOR-PD: RAS Inhibitors</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04076930</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Renin-Angiotensin System Inhibitors in Peritoneal Dialysis Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Renin-Angiotensin System Inhibitors on Mortality and Cardiovascular Outcomes in Peritoneal Dialysis Patients: A Retrospective Cohort Study in Thailand</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chiang Mai University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chiang Mai University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Among antihypertensive medications, RAS inhibitor classes, namely angiotensin-converting
      enzyme inhibitor (ACEI) and angiotensin receptor blocker (ARB) have the most prospective data
      on mortality and cardiovascular outcomes in specific high-risk populations with mild to
      moderate chronic kidney disease (CKD). Whereas, long-term data on the risks and benefits of
      ACEI/ARB usage in end-stage kidney disease (ESKD) patients undergoing peritoneal dialysis
      (PD) are limited. Recently, increasing clinical studies suggested that ACEI/ARB had a
      beneficial effect on intermediate outcomes, including short-term blood pressure variability,
      left ventricular hypertrophy, and may have an important role in the peritoneum and the kidney
      protection. Subsequently, treatment with ACEI/ARB has been recommended by the International
      Society for Peritoneal Dialysis for PD patients with significant residual kidney function
      (RKF).

      Although existing reviews demonstrated that ACEI/ARB significantly has benefit in preserving
      RKF in PD patients, evidence regarding the relative efficacy on mortality, cardiovascular
      outcomes, and adverse events is lacking. Given that there exist few controlled trials of the
      effectiveness of ACEI/ARB in PD patients, we intend to perform a retrospective cohort study
      to assess the association between the use of ACEI/ARB and the risk of long-term mortality,
      cardiovascular outcomes, and adverse events in terms of hyperkalemia.

      A retrospective cohort of Thai PD patients will be constructed by using the local joint
      registry data of adult PD patients from five centers in Thailand between 2006 to 2017 and
      followed to December 2018. We will link the following health datasets: (i) the electronic
      health records, contains outpatient and inpatient data; (ii) the Support System Pharmacy
      Dispensing extract, an administrative database which covers pharmacy dispensing; (iii) the PD
      Patient Care Database, which provides patient-level detail on sociodemographic and clinical
      characteristics as well as long-term PD care data; and (iv) the Laboratory Support System
      extract, which includes claims and routine laboratory results.

      The exposure of interest in this cohort will be the use of ACEI/ARB within a 90-day after the
      date of PD initiation. Outcomes of interest will include all-cause mortality, cardiovascular
      mortality, a composite endpoint of cardiovascular events, and adverse events in terms of
      hyperkalemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite endpoint of atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 years</time_frame>
    <description>ASCVD events of interest will include hospitalization for acute fatal and nonfatal myocardial infarction, coronary or other arterial revascularization, fatal and nonfatal stroke, transient ischemic attack, or peripheral arterial disease presumed to be of atherosclerotic origin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperkalemia</measure>
    <time_frame>12 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incident hyperkalemia will define as a serum potassium concentration of more than 5.0 mEq/L. The severity of hyperkalemia will be categorized as mild (&gt;5.0 to &lt;5.5 mEq/L), moderate (5.5 to 6.0 mEq/L), and severe (&gt;6.0 mEq/L).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1468</enrollment>
  <condition>Peritoneal Dialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACEI/ARB users</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACEI/ARB non-users</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor (ACEI) and angiotensin receptor blocker (ARB)</intervention_name>
    <description>The use of ACEI/ARB within a 90-day after the date of PD initiation (exposure ascertainment window period).</description>
    <arm_group_label>ACEI/ARB users</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult ESKD patients undergoing PD from January 1, 2006, to December 31, 2017, and followed
        to December 2018.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients aged 18 years or over at the date of PD initiation

          -  Patients with ESKD who were undergoing PD either continuous ambulatory peritoneal
             dialysis or automated peritoneal dialysis between January 1, 2006, to December 31,
             2017

          -  Received PD treatment more than 90 days in an outpatient nephrology clinic visit after
             the date of PD initiation

          -  Received of any outpatient prescriptions within 90 days after the date of PD
             initiation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously been treated by maintenance hemodialysis (for more than 90 days) or
             initiated PD for acute kidney injury or after a failed kidney transplantation

          -  Died within 90 days after the date of PD initiation

          -  Received a combination of ACEIs and ARBs therapy

          -  Received ACEIs/ARBs within 180 days before PD initiation

          -  Had no information regarding ACEI/ARB dosage regimen during the follow-up period

          -  Inadequate follow-up clinical information on blood pressure monitoring
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pharmacoepidemiology and Statistics Research Center, Faculty of Pharmacy, Chiang Mai University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chiang Mai</city>
        <zip>50200</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chiang Mai University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chidchanok Ruengorn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperkalemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Peritoneal dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Renin-angiotensin system</keyword>
  <keyword>Retrospective cohort</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Enzyme Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiotensin Receptor Antagonists</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data from the retrospective cohort study part will be made available at the end of the study, on request. Requests will subject to approval by the chief investigator, the advisory Committee and the relevant ethical bodies.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

