<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04073875</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E181981</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04073875</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>18F-GP1 PET-CT to Detect Bioprosthetic Aortic Valve Thrombosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>18F-GP1 Positron Emission Tomography-computed Tomography to Detect Bioprosthetic Aortic Valve Thrombosis; the Biothrombus Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Life Molecular Imaging SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>British Heart Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Edinburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      18F-GP1 binds with high affinity to the glycoprotein IIb/IIIa receptors on activated
      platelets. 18F-GP1 PET-CT has recently demonstrated favourable safety, pharmacokinetic,
      biodistribution and diagnostic performance for the in vivo identification of venous and
      arterial thrombemboli.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aortic stenosis is the most common reason for valvular interventions in the developed world,
      with rates projected to increase as the population ages. Aortic valve replacement remains the
      only recognised treatment available. Bioprostheses are far more common than mechanical
      prostheses, particularly with increasing rates of transcatheter heart valve use.

      Bioprothetic valves are less durable than mechanical valves and are subject to deterioration
      which may lead to clinical heart failure and the need for re-intervention. Long-term results
      with surgical bioprostheses are well reported, with valve deterioration rates of less than
      15% at 10 years. These data, however, rely on re-operation rather than echocardiographic
      measures, suggesting that the true incidence of structural valve deterioration is
      underestimated.

      Valve thrombosis is increasingly recognised as a potential contributor to leaflet
      degeneration and has been detected in participants undergoing both surgical aortic valve
      replacement and transcatheter aortic valve implantation. The role of valve thrombosis as an
      early trigger for calcification and subsequent valve degeneration has not been addressed. The
      true incidence of valve thrombosis and its impact on clinical outcomes is unknown due to the
      lack of a sufficiently sensitive non-invasive imaging modality to detect early subclinical
      thrombosis. Current observational data suggests rates of 12 to 40%, based on computed
      tomography findings. There is a clinical need for a more sensitive non-invasive method of
      detecting valve thrombosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of 18F-GP1 PET-CT bioprosthetic aortic valve uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Prevalence of 18F-GP1 PET-CT bioprosthetic aortic valve uptake as measured by standardised uptake values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensity of 18F-GP1 PET-CT activity in bioprosthetic aortic valve thrombus</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Intensity of 18F-GP1 PET-CT activity in bioprosthetic aortic valve thrombus compared to blood pool as measured by standardised uptake values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>18F-GP1 PET-CT bioprosthetic aortic valve uptake in patients with thrombus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>18F-GP1 PET-CT bioprosthetic aortic valve uptake after 3 months in patients with evidence of thrombus at baseline as measured by standardised uptake values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Thrombosis Cardiac</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Valve Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bioprosthetic aortic valve</arm_group_label>
    <description>Single 18F-GP1 PET-CT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bioprosthetic aortic valve thrombus - repeat imaging</arm_group_label>
    <description>18F-GP1 PET-CT at baseline and 3 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-GP1</intervention_name>
    <description>18F-GP1 PET-CT scan</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bioprosthetic aortic valve</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bioprosthetic aortic valve thrombus - repeat imaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients &gt;1 month post-bioprosthetic aortic valve replacement.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ability to give informed consent

          -  &gt;1 month post-surgical or transcatheter aortic valve replacement

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give informed consent

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Contraindications to iodinated contrast

          -  Contraindications to anticoagulation

          -  Use of anticoagulants during the post-operative period prior to screening

          -  Extreme claustrophobia

          -  Chronic kidney disease (with estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt;30 mL/min/1.73m2)

          -  Metastatic malignancy

          -  Inability to tolerate the supine position
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David E Newby, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David E Newby, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 131 242 6515</phone>
    <email>d.e.newby@ed.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rong Bing, MBBS</last_name>
    <email>rong.bing@ed.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Edinburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rong Bing, MBBS</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lohrke J, Siebeneicher H, Berger M, Reinhardt M, Berndt M, Mueller A, Zerna M, Koglin N, Oden F, Bauser M, Friebe M, Dinkelborg LM, Huetter J, Stephens AW. (18)F-GP1, a Novel PET Tracer Designed for High-Sensitivity, Low-Background Detection of Thrombi. J Nucl Med. 2017 Jul;58(7):1094-1099. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.116.188896. Epub 2017 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28302764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim C, Lee JS, Han Y, Chae SY, Jin S, Sung C, Son HJ, Oh SJ, Lee SJ, Oh JS, Cho YP, Kwon TW, Lee DH, Jang S, Kim B, Koglin N, Berndt M, Stephens AW, Moon DH. Glycoprotein IIb/IIIa receptor imaging with (18)F-GP1 positron emission tomography for acute venous thromboembolism: an open-label, non-randomized, first-in-human phase 1 study. J Nucl Med. 2018 Jun 29. pii: jnumed.118.212084. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.118.212084. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>29959214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chae SY, Kwon TW, Jin S, Kwon SU, Sung C, Oh SJ, Lee SJ, Oh JS, Han Y, Cho YP, Lee N, Kim JY, Koglin N, Berndt M, Stephens AW, Moon DH. A phase 1, first-in-human study of (18)F-GP1 positron emission tomography for imaging acute arterial thrombosis. EJNMMI Res. 2019 Jan 7;9(1):3. doi: 10.1186/s13550-018-0471-8.</citation>
    <PMID>30617563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee N, Oh I, Chae SY, Jin S, Oh SJ, Lee SJ, Koglin N, Berndt M, Stephens AW, Oh JS, Moon DH. Radiation dosimetry of [(18)F]GP1 for imaging activated glycoprotein IIb/IIIa receptors with positron emission tomography in patients with acute thromboembolism. Nucl Med Biol. 2019 May - Jun;72-73:45-48. doi: 10.1016/j.nucmedbio.2019.07.003. Epub 2019 Jul 10.</citation>
    <PMID>31330411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Durko AP, Osnabrugge RL, Van Mieghem NM, Milojevic M, Mylotte D, Nkomo VT, Pieter Kappetein A. Annual number of candidates for transcatheter aortic valve implantation per country: current estimates and future projections. Eur Heart J. 2018 Jul 21;39(28):2635-2642. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehy107.</citation>
    <PMID>29546396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnston DR, Soltesz EG, Vakil N, Rajeswaran J, Roselli EE, Sabik JF 3rd, Smedira NG, Svensson LG, Lytle BW, Blackstone EH. Long-term durability of bioprosthetic aortic valves: implications from 12,569 implants. Ann Thorac Surg. 2015 Apr;99(4):1239-47. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2014.10.070. Epub 2015 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>25662439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodriguez-Gabella T, Voisine P, Puri R, Pibarot P, Rodés-Cabau J. Aortic Bioprosthetic Valve Durability: Incidence, Mechanisms, Predictors, and Management of Surgical and Transcatheter Valve Degeneration. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2017 Aug 22;70(8):1013-1028. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2017.07.715. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28818190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chakravarty T, Søndergaard L, Friedman J, De Backer O, Berman D, Kofoed KF, Jilaihawi H, Shiota T, Abramowitz Y, Jørgensen TH, Rami T, Israr S, Fontana G, de Knegt M, Fuchs A, Lyden P, Trento A, Bhatt DL, Leon MB, Makkar RR; RESOLVE; SAVORY Investigators. Subclinical leaflet thrombosis in surgical and transcatheter bioprosthetic aortic valves: an observational study. Lancet. 2017 Jun 17;389(10087):2383-2392. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30757-2. Epub 2017 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>28330690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Makkar RR, Fontana G, Jilaihawi H, Chakravarty T, Kofoed KF, De Backer O, Asch FM, Ruiz CE, Olsen NT, Trento A, Friedman J, Berman D, Cheng W, Kashif M, Jelnin V, Kliger CA, Guo H, Pichard AD, Weissman NJ, Kapadia S, Manasse E, Bhatt DL, Leon MB, Søndergaard L. Possible Subclinical Leaflet Thrombosis in Bioprosthetic Aortic Valves. N Engl J Med. 2015 Nov 19;373(21):2015-24. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1509233. Epub 2015 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26436963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

