<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04071236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2019-05620</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-05620</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>10301</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>10301</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1CA186704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04071236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiation Medication (Radium-223 Dichloride) Versus Radium-223 Dichloride Plus Radiation Enhancing Medication (M3814) Versus Radium-223 Dichloride Plus M3814 Plus Avelumab (a Type of Immunotherapy) for Advanced Prostate Cancer Not Responsive to Hormonal Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized Trial of Radium-223 Dichloride, M3814, &amp;Amp; Avelumab in Advanced Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (mCRPC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the best dose of M3814 when given together with radium-223
      dichloride or with radium-223 dichloride and avelumab and to see how well they work in
      treating patients with castrate-resistant prostate cancer that had spread to other places in
      the body (metastatic). M3814 may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the
      enzymes needed for cell growth. Radioactive drugs, such as radium-223 dichloride, may carry
      radiation directly to tumor cells and not harm normal cells. Immunotherapy with monoclonal
      antibodies, such as avelumab, may help the body's immune system attack the cancer, and may
      interfere with the ability of tumor cells to grow and spread. This study is being done to
      find out the better treatment between radium-223 dichloride alone, radium-223 dichloride in
      combination with M3814, or radium-223 dichloride in combination with both M3814 and avelumab,
      to lower the chance of prostate cancer growing or spreading in the bone and if this approach
      is better or worse than the usual approach for advanced prostate cancer not responsive to
      hormonal therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of nedisertib (M3814) in combination with
      radium-223 dichloride or in combination with radium-223 dichloride and avelumab in patients
      with advanced metastatic castrate-resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC) based on dose limiting
      toxicities (DLTs) in the doublet or triplet combinations. (Phase 1) II. Radiographic
      progression free survival (rPFS) will be evaluated based on both skeletal and extraskeletal
      progression following PCWG3 methodology. (Phase 2)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the time to the first symptomatic skeletal event [SSE] (defined as 1st use of
      radiation therapy to relieve skeletal symptoms, new symptomatic pathologic vertebral or
      non-vertebral bone fractures, spinal cord compression, or tumor-related orthopedic surgical
      intervention).

      II. To determine the safety of radium-223 dichloride, M3814, and avelumab combination
      treatment.

      III. To observe and record anti-tumor activity. IV. To evaluate progression free survival
      (PFS) and overall survival (OS). V. To evaluate symptomatic skeletal events (SSE) per
      standardized Case Report Form (CRF) distinguishing between pathologic and non-pathogenic
      fractures.

      VI. To explore patient-reported symptomatic adverse events (AE) for tolerability of each
      treatment arm.

      VII. To examine the radium-223 dichloride bio-distribution and absorbed dose in each bone
      metastatic lesions as well as elsewhere in the body including critical organs using
      dosimetry.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To perform molecular profiling assays on malignant and normal tissues, including, but not
      limited to, whole exome sequencing (WES), and messenger ribonucleic acid (RNA) sequencing
      (RNAseq), in order to:

      Ia. Identify potential predictive and prognostic biomarkers beyond any genomic alteration by
      which treatment may be assigned, and Ib. Identify resistance mechanisms using genomic
      deoxyribonucleic (DNA)- and RNA-based assessment platforms.

      II. To contribute genetic analysis data from de-identified biospecimens to Genomic Data
      Commons (GDC), a well annotated cancer molecular and clinical data repository, for current
      and future research; specimens will be annotated with key clinical data, including
      presentation, diagnosis, staging, summary treatment, and if possible, outcome.

      III. To bank plasma and peripheral immune cells from patients to assess predictive biomarkers
      of response at the Experimental Therapeutics Clinical Trials Network (ETCTN) biorepository at
      Nationwide Children's Hospital.

      IV. To correlate change in level of total alkaline phosphatase, bone-specific alkaline
      phosphatase, and serum osteocalcin to rPFS and OS.

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of nedisertib, followed by a phase II
      study. Patients are randomized to 1 of 3 arms.

      ARM A: Patients receive radium-223 dichloride intravenously (IV) over 1 minute on day 1.
      Treatments repeat every 28 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM B: Patients receive radium-223 dichloride as in Arm A and nedisertib orally (PO) on days
      3-28. Treatments repeat every 28 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM C: Patients receive radium-223 dichloride as in Arm A and nedisertib as in Arm B.
      Patients also receive avelumab IV over 60 minutes on days 1 and 15. Treatments repeat every
      28 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatments, patients are followed up at 30 days and then every 3
      months for up to 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 27, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicity (Phase 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be summarized as count and percentages, overall as well as by dose level/regimen, by severity, and by patient characteristics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic progression free survival (rPFS) (Phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomization to date of scan showing either skeletal or extraskeletal progression following Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group 3 ( PCWG3) methodology or death, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Empirical survival probabilities will be estimated by the Kaplan-Meier (KM) product limit method by arms and the survival difference between arms will be compared by 1-sided log rank test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to the event of disease recurrence/progression or death due to any cause, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be similarly analyzed using the KM method, log rank test and univariate and multivariate Cox model as described for rPFS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to date of death due to any cause, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS will be similarly analyzed using the KM method, log rank test and univariate and multivariate Cox model as described for rPFS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic skeletal event (SSE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Wiil be assessed per standardized case report form (CR) distinguishing between pathologic and non-pathologic fractures. SSE rate will be estimated with 95% Clopper-Pearson exact confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicity and adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will be graded according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 5.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Reported Outcomes-Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (PRO-CTCAE) data will be evaluated for data quality, to characterize baseline symptom status of patients on study and the change over time, to explore the development of symptomatic adverse events (AEs) and the change over time, and to explore the patient scores with clinician graded AEs. PRO-CTCAE data will be summarized descriptively as the number (percent) of patients reporting each grade for individual items. Comparisons between the two treatment arms will be performed on a per question basis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Gleason score at baseline will be grouped as =&lt; 6, 7 and &gt;= 8. Prostatic specific antigen. PSA at baseline will be classified as =&lt; 10, 10~20 and &gt; 20 ng/mL. Categorical Gleason score, PSA will be summarized by counts and percentages. Fisher's exact test will be used to examine the distribution of Gleason score and PSA. Descriptive statistics will be used to summarize quantitative imaging/biomarker by arm. Multivariate Cox model will be applied to data across arms to examine the effect of Gleason score, pretreatment PSA, clinical stage etc. incorporated with adjusted HR reported with 95% confidence interval (CI).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Castration-Resistant Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Prostate Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Prostate Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (radium-223 dichloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive radium-223 dichloride IV over 1 minute on day 1. Treatments repeat every 28 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive radium-223 dichloride as in Arm A and nedisertib PO on days 3-28. Treatments repeat every 28 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib, avelumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive radium-223 dichloride as in Arm A and nedisertib as in Arm B. Patients also receive avelumab IV over 60 minutes on days 1 and 15. Treatments repeat every 28 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Avelumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib, avelumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bavencio</other_name>
    <other_name>MSB-0010718C</other_name>
    <other_name>MSB0010718C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nedisertib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib, avelumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>3-Pyridazinemethanol, alpha-(2-Chloro-4-fluoro-5-(7-(4-morpholinyl)-4-quinazolinyl)phenyl)-6-methoxy-, (alphaS)-</other_name>
    <other_name>M 3814</other_name>
    <other_name>M-3814</other_name>
    <other_name>M3814</other_name>
    <other_name>MSC 2490484A</other_name>
    <other_name>MSC-2490484A</other_name>
    <other_name>MSC2490484A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (radium-223 dichloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib, avelumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (radium-223 dichloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib, avelumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radium Ra 223 Dichloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (radium-223 dichloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C (radium-223 dichloride, nedisertib, avelumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alpharadin</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY 88-8223</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY88-8223</other_name>
    <other_name>Radium 223 Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>RADIUM RA-223 DICHLORIDE</other_name>
    <other_name>Radium-223 Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Xofigo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PHASE 1: Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 1 (Karnofsky
             &gt;= 70%)

          -  PHASE 2: ECOG performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Unless a patient has had orchiectomy by surgery, the patient is expected to be on
             antiandrogen therapy (ADT) for &quot;medical castration&quot;. ADT needs to be maintained
             throughout the study. Testosterone level should be checked, and kept consistently
             lower than 20 ng/dL, similar to that obtained with bilateral orchiectomy

          -  Progressive castration-resistant prostate cancer with two or more skeletal metastases
             identified by 99mTC bone scintigraphy. One or more lymph node metastases allowed, but
             not mandatory. Lymph node metastases in each individually must measure less than 3 cm
             in the longest dimension. Visible visceral organ metastases are not allowed. A
             diagnosis of prostate cancer must have been histologically confirmed at any time point

          -  Baseline prostatic specific antigen (PSA) level of 1 ng/mL or higher with evidence of
             progressively increasing PSA values (two consecutive increases over the previous
             reference value)

          -  Progression after abiraterone, enzalutamide, docetaxel, or other secondary hormonal
             therapy. There is no maximum number of prior therapies

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 6 months

          -  Albumin &gt; 25 g/L

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) (with the exception
             of &lt; 3 mg/dL for patients with Gilbert's disease)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)(serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT)(serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 3 x institutional ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x institutional ULN OR

          -  Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &gt;= 40 mL/min/1.73 m^2

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected patients on effective anti-retroviral
             therapy (with no medications prohibited by this protocol [e.g. drug-drug
             interactions]) with undetectable viral load within 6 months are eligible for this
             trial

          -  For patients with evidence of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection, the HBV viral
             load must be undetectable on suppressive therapy (with no medications prohibited by
             this protocol [e.g. drug-drug interactions]), if indicated

          -  Patients with a history of hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection must have been treated
             and cured. For patients with HCV infection who are currently on treatment, they are
             eligible if they have an undetectable HCV viral load (with no medications prohibited
             by this protocol [e.g. drug-drug interactions])

          -  Patients with a prior or concurrent malignancy whose natural history or treatment does
             not have the potential to interfere with the safety or efficacy assessment of the
             investigational regimen are eligible for this trial

          -  Patients with known history or current symptoms of cardiac disease, or history of
             treatment with cardiotoxic agents, should have a clinical risk assessment of cardiac
             function using the New York Heart Association Functional classification. To be
             eligible for this trial, patients should be class 2B or better

          -  Concomitant use of physiologic corticosteroids is allowed

          -  Concomitant use of bisphosphonates is allowed (use of bone health agents is mandatory
             - either denosumab (preferred) or bisphosphonates)

          -  The effects of radium-223 dichloride, M3814, and avelumab on the developing human
             fetus are unknown. Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must also agree to use
             adequate contraception prior to the study, for the duration of study participation,
             and 6 months after completion of Radium-223 dichloride, M3814, and avelumab
             administration

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Patients must be able to swallow orally administered medication

          -  Patients with asymptomatic, treated brain metastases are permitted if there is no
             evidence of progression for at least 4 weeks after central nervous system
             (CNS)-directed treatment, as ascertained by clinical examination and brain imaging
             (magnetic resonance imaging [MRI] or computed tomography [CT] scan) during the
             screening period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active autoimmune conditions or patients on chronic immunosuppression due to
             underlying autoimmune condition

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering
             the study

          -  Patients who have not recovered from adverse events due to prior anti-cancer therapy
             (i.e., have residual toxicities &gt; grade 1) with the exception of alopecia

          -  Prior therapy with radionuclides (e.g., strontium, samarium, rhenium, radium)

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients who have had previous hemibody external radiation

          -  Patients who have had systemic radiotherapy with radioisotopes

          -  Patients who have imminent/established spinal cord compression, pathological fracture
             in weight bearing bones or bone lesion with soft tissue component unless treated as
             appropriate with radiation and/or surgery before starting on trial

          -  Patients who have a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to radium-223 dichloride, M3814, or avelumab

          -  Patients unable to discontinue medications or substances that are potent inhibitors,
             inducers or sensitive substrates of CYP3A4/5 or CYP2C19 prior to study treatment are
             ineligible. Medications or substances that are strong inhibitors of CYP3A4/5 or
             CYP2C19 must be discontinued at least 1 week prior to first M3814 dose. Strong
             inducers of CYP3A4/5 or CYP2C19 must be stopped at least 3 weeks prior to the first
             dose. Drugs mainly metabolized by CYP3A with a narrow therapeutic index as judged by
             the Investigator must stop at least 1 day prior to first M3814 dose. Because the lists
             of these agents are constantly changing, it is important to regularly consult a
             frequently-updated medical reference. As part of the enrollment/informed consent
             procedures, the patient will be counseled on the risk of interactions with other
             agents, and what to do if new medications need to be prescribed or if the patient is
             considering a new over-the-counter medicine or herbal product. The primary elimination
             mechanism of avelumab is proteolytic degradation, thus there are no contraindicated
             medications with respect to avelumab. Radium-223 dichloride should not be given
             concurrently with abiraterone plus prednisone/prednisolone.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness

          -  Patients with psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Patients must not have an active infection requiring systemic treatment

          -  Patients must not use immunosuppressive medication =&lt; 7 days of registration, EXCEPT
             for the following:

               -  Intranasal, inhaled, topical steroids, or local steroid injection (e.g.,
                  intra-articular injection)

               -  Systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses =&lt; 10 mg/day of prednisone or
                  equivalent

               -  Steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., CT scan
                  premedication)

          -  Patients who cannot discontinue concomitant H2 blockers or proton-pump inhibitors
             (PPIs). Patients may confer with the study doctor to determine if such medications can
             be discontinued. These must be discontinued &gt;= 5 days prior to study treatment.
             Patients do not need to discontinue calcium carbonate

          -  Patients receiving sorivudine or any chemically related analogues (such as brivudine)
             are excluded

          -  Patients with a known history or present osteonecrosis of the jaw
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hiram A Gay</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University - Duke Cancer Institute LAO</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Radium Ra 223 dichloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>NCI is committed to sharing data in accordance with NIH policy. For more details on how clinical trial data is shared, access the link to the NIH data sharing policy page.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>https://grants.nih.gov/policy/sharing.htm</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

