<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04075175</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MBL-DIPH-19-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04075175</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate the Safety Pharmacokinetics of a Human Monoclonal Antibody S315 Against Diphtheria Toxin in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <acronym>S315</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study in Healthy Subjects to Evaluate the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of a Human Monoclonal Antibody (mAb) S315 Against Diphtheria Toxin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MassBiologics</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MassBiologics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the use of a single infusion of S315 at different doses in healthy
      volunteers to help understand its safety and tolerability. S315 is a monoclonal antibody that
      is being developed for treatment of diphtheria. The study will assess for any side effects
      when S315 and will also look at the levels of S315 in the blood over time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 7, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 7, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of Participants with adverse events as assessed by the Division of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases (DMID) Adult Toxicity Table (Draft revised November 2007) adapted by the Division of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, NIAID, NIH.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -1 through Day 60</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events assessed for safety</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serial measurements of S315 concentration in the serum.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 pre-dose and Day 1, Day 2, Day 4, Day 8, Day 15, Day 22, day 29, Day 43 and Day 60 post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Diphtheria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S315 human monoclonal antibody</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 cohorts of 8 subjects each randomized 6:2 (S315:Placebo (0.9% Sodium Chloride)) with escalation of a fixed dose of S315</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.9% sodium chloride (NaCl)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>5 cohorts of 8 subjects each randomized 6:2 (S315:Placebo(0.9% Sodium Chloride)) with escalation of a fixed dose of S315</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S315</intervention_name>
    <description>Human monoclonal antibody against Diphtheria Toxin</description>
    <arm_group_label>S315 human monoclonal antibody</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.9% Sodium Chloride (NaCl)</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo 0.9% Sodium Chloride (NaCl)</description>
    <arm_group_label>0.9% sodium chloride (NaCl)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Capable of giving written informed consent and able to effectively communicate with
             the Investigator and study personnel. A signed informed consent document (ICD) must be
             on file prior to initiating the screening procedures.

             Willing and able to complete all study requirements, restrictions, visits and
             procedures.

          2. Age 18 to 55 years, inclusive.

          3. Weight 50 kg to 90 kg, inclusive.

          4. Systolic blood pressure less than 140 mmHg and diastolic less than 90 mmHg on two
             separate readings at least one minute apart.

          5. Women of child bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant must agree not to become pregnant and must use a method of birth
             control during the entire study.

             Women of non-child bearing potential may be included. Women are considered
             post-menopausal and not of childbearing potential if, they have had 12 months of
             natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea with an appropriate clinical profile or have had
             surgical total hysterectomy or tubal ligation at least six weeks ago.

          6. Males of reproductive potential must use a barrier method of contraception during the
             course of the study.

          7. Screening laboratory values must meet the following criteria:

               -  White blood cell (WBC) 3.5 - Upper Limit of Normal (ULN)

               -  Platelets &gt; 100,000/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ Lower Limit of Normal (LLN)

               -  Creatinine ≤ ULN

               -  Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST) ≤ ULN

               -  Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ ULN

               -  Alkaline Phosphatase ≤ ULN

               -  Bilirubin ≤ ULN

               -  HgbA1c

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Previous receipt of humanized or human monoclonal antibody whether licensed or
             investigational.

             2. History of or any current medical condition that could compromise the safety of the
             participant in the study, as determined by the Investigator.

             3. History of suicidal behavior within 12 months prior to screening.

             4. Donated blood or plasma within 60 days prior to dosing.

             5. Clinically significant gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, neurologic, psychiatric,
             substance abuse, metabolic, renal, hepatic, respiratory, inflammatory, or infectious
             disease, as determined by the Investigator.

             6. Drug or alcohol abuse within previous 12 months or a positive test at screening and
             at Day -1 within 24 hours of study product administration.

             7. History of a previous severe allergic reaction with generalized urticaria,
             angioedema or anaphylaxis.

             8. Physical finding on examination considered clinically significant such as murmur
             (other than functional), hepatosplenomegaly, lymphadenopathy or focal neurological
             deficit.

             9. Urinalysis positive for &gt; trace protein, &gt; 5 Red Blood Cell (RBC)/hpf or &gt; 5
             WBC/hpf.

             10. Positive serology for HIV antibody, Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) antibody or Hepatitis
             B surface antigen at screening.

             11. Positive serum pregnancy test during screening or within 24 hours of study product
             administration, or an unwillingness to undergo pregnancy testing.

             12. Pregnant within 6 months or breast-feeding within 3 months prior to screening.

             13. Receipt of licensed vaccine containing diphtheria toxoid (Td, Tdap, pneumococcal
             conjugate vaccines, meningococcal conjugate vaccines) within the last year.

             14. Treatment with another investigational drug or other intervention within 30 days
             from screening.

             15. Any other condition that in the opinion of the investigator would jeopardize the
             safety or rights of the subject participating in the study.

             16. Safety laboratory abnormalities at Screening or Day -1, which are clinically
             significant as determined by the Investigator.

             17. Tobacco, e-cigarettes, and/or nicotine use within 30 days prior to screening
             confirmed by urine cotinine test.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Z Sullivan-Bólyai, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MassBiologics of the University of Massachusetts</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronald Goldwater, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Parexel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parexel Early Phase Clinical Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21225</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith HL, Cheslock P, Leney M, Barton B, Molrine DC. Potency of a human monoclonal antibody to diphtheria toxin relative to equine diphtheria anti-toxin in a guinea pig intoxication model. Virulence. 2016 Aug 17;7(6):660-8. doi: 10.1080/21505594.2016.1171436. Epub 2016 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>27070129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diphtheria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

