<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04071743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU-2019-0933</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04071743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Gammacore Sapphire for the Acute and Preventive Treatment of Post-Traumatic Headache (GAP-PTH)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Single-Center, Double-Blind, Parallel, Sham-Controlled Study of Gammacore Sapphire (Non-Invasive Vagus Nerve Stimulator) for the Acute and Preventive Treatment of Post-Traumatic Headache (GAP-PTH)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ElectroCore INC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this single-center, prospective, randomized, double-blind, sham controlled,
      parallel-group study is to collect clinical data related to the safety and efficacy of vagus
      nerve stimulation for the acute and preventive treatment of Post Traumatic Headache.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will enroll 60 subjects over a period of 14 weeks each. Subjects will use either a
      sham or active device to treat acute Post Traumatic Headache. Investigators will collect
      clinical data related to the use of the device.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Primary Investigator left UT Southwestern and was not replaced.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relief of Post Traumatic Headache</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease in pain between active and sham treatment groups between the baseline assessment and 60 minutes post-treatment on a subset of questions from the Sport Concussion Assessment Tool, 5th edition (SCAT5) Graded Symptom Checklist</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 14 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>• Decrease in pain (based on the 7-point NRS) at 30 and 120 minutes after initial treatment, for all treated attacks in the nVNS and sham treatment groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-Traumatic Headache</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment and Prevention with active gammacore device(vagus nerve stimulator)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment and Prevention with sham gammacore device(vagus nerve stimulator)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gammaCore Sapphire</intervention_name>
    <description>non-invasive vagus nerve stimulator</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sham gammaCore Sapphire</intervention_name>
    <description>sham gammaCore Sapphire</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Meets the ICHD-3 criteria for acute headache attributed to mild traumatic injury to
             the head

          2. Experiences a minimum of 2 headaches (migraine or probable migraine phenotype) per
             week

          3. Presentation to clinic between 2 and 4 weeks after injury

          4. Able to provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any pre-existing primary headache disorder (with the exception of infrequent episodic
             tension type headache)

          2. Any contraindication to using nVNS

          3. Initiation or change in the dosage of any medication commonly used or headache
             prophylaxis 3 months before enrollment into the study

          4. Continuous headache at the time of enrollment

          5. PTH &gt;4 weeks after injury

          6. Structural abnormality at the nVNS treatment site (e.g., lymphadenopathy, previous
             surgery, abnormal anatomy)

          7. Pain at the nVNS treatment site (e.g., dysesthesia, neuralgia, cervicalgia)

          8. Other significant pain problem (e.g., cancer pain, fibromyalgia, other head or facial
             pain disorder) that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may confound the study
             assessments

          9. Known or suspected severe cardiac disease (e.g., symptomatic coronary artery disease,
             prior myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure) or an abnormal baseline
             electrocardiogram (ECG) within the last year (e.g., second- or third-degree heart
             block, prolonged QT interval, atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, history of
             ventricular tachycardia or ventricular fibrillation, clinically significant premature
             ventricular contraction)

         10. Known or suspected cerebrovascular disease (e.g., prior stroke or transient ischemic
             attack, symptomatic carotid artery disease, prior carotid endarterectomy or other
             vascular neck surgery)

         11. Previous cervical vagotomy

         12. A relative of or an employee of the Investigator or the clinical study site

         13. Previously used gammaCore
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390-9044</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Defrin R. Chronic post-traumatic headache: clinical findings and possible mechanisms. J Man Manip Ther. 2014 Feb;22(1):36-44. doi: 10.1179/2042618613Y.0000000053.</citation>
    <PMID>24976746</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiTommaso C, Hoffman JM, Lucas S, Dikmen S, Temkin N, Bell KR. Medication usage patterns for headache treatment after mild traumatic brain injury. Headache. 2014 Mar;54(3):511-9.</citation>
    <PMID>24741687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucas S. Posttraumatic Headache: Clinical Characterization and Management. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2015 Oct;19(10):48. doi: 10.1007/s11916-015-0520-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26280569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bree D, Levy D. Development of CGRP-dependent pain and headache related behaviours in a rat model of concussion: Implications for mechanisms of post-traumatic headache. Cephalalgia. 2018 Feb;38(2):246-258. doi: 10.1177/0333102416681571. Epub 2016 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27899434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conidi FX. Interventional Treatment for Post-traumatic Headache. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2016 Jun;20(6):40. doi: 10.1007/s11916-016-0570-z. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27130542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Packard RC. Treatment of chronic daily posttraumatic headache with divalproex sodium. Headache. 2000 Oct;40(9):736-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11091292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langdon R, Taraman S. Posttraumatic Headache. Pediatr Ann. 2018 Feb 1;47(2):e61-e68. doi: 10.3928/19382359-20180131-01. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29446796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elahi F, Reddy C. High cervical epidural neurostimulation for post-traumatic headache management. Pain Physician. 2014 Jul-Aug;17(4):E537-41.</citation>
    <PMID>25054404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwedt TJ, Dodick DW, Hentz J, Trentman TL, Zimmerman RS. Occipital nerve stimulation for chronic headache--long-term safety and efficacy. Cephalalgia. 2007 Feb;27(2):153-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17257236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elahi F, Reddy C. Neuromodulation of the great auricular nerve for persistent post-traumatic headache. Pain Physician. 2014 Jul-Aug;17(4):E531-6.</citation>
    <PMID>25054403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung A, Fallah A, Shukla S, Lin L, Tsia A, Song D, Polston G, Lee R. rTMS in Alleviating Mild TBI Related Headaches--A Case Series. Pain Physician. 2016 Feb;19(2):E347-54.</citation>
    <PMID>26815263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung A, Metzger-Smith V, He Y, Cordero J, Ehlert B, Song D, Lin L, Shahrokh G, Tsai A, Vaninetti M, Rutledge T, Polston G, Sheu R, Lee R. Left Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex rTMS in Alleviating MTBI Related Headaches and Depressive Symptoms. Neuromodulation. 2018 Jun;21(4):390-401. doi: 10.1111/ner.12615. Epub 2017 May 30.</citation>
    <PMID>28557049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howland RH. Vagus Nerve Stimulation. Curr Behav Neurosci Rep. 2014 Jun;1(2):64-73.</citation>
    <PMID>24834378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuan H, Silberstein SD. Vagus Nerve and Vagus Nerve Stimulation, a Comprehensive Review: Part I. Headache. 2016 Jan;56(1):71-8. doi: 10.1111/head.12647. Epub 2015 Sep 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26364692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schachter SC. Vagus nerve stimulation therapy summary: five years after FDA approval. Neurology. 2002 Sep 24;59(6 Suppl 4):S15-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12270963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cecchini AP, Mea E, Tullo V, Curone M, Franzini A, Broggi G, Savino M, Bussone G, Leone M. Vagus nerve stimulation in drug-resistant daily chronic migraine with depression: preliminary data. Neurol Sci. 2009 May;30 Suppl 1:S101-4. doi: 10.1007/s10072-009-0073-3.</citation>
    <PMID>19415436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mauskop A. Vagus nerve stimulation relieves chronic refractory migraine and cluster headaches. Cephalalgia. 2005 Feb;25(2):82-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15658944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Follesa P, Biggio F, Gorini G, Caria S, Talani G, Dazzi L, Puligheddu M, Marrosu F, Biggio G. Vagus nerve stimulation increases norepinephrine concentration and the gene expression of BDNF and bFGF in the rat brain. Brain Res. 2007 Nov 7;1179:28-34. Epub 2007 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>17920573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korley FK, Diaz-Arrastia R, Wu AH, Yue JK, Manley GT, Sair HI, Van Eyk J, Everett AD; TRACK-TBI investigators, Okonkwo DO, Valadka AB, Gordon WA, Maas AI, Mukherjee P, Yuh EL, Lingsma HF, Puccio AM, Schnyer DM. Circulating Brain-Derived Neurotrophic Factor Has Diagnostic and Prognostic Value in Traumatic Brain Injury. J Neurotrauma. 2016 Jan 15;33(2):215-25. doi: 10.1089/neu.2015.3949. Epub 2015 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26159676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wurzelmann M, Romeika J, Sun D. Therapeutic potential of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) and a small molecular mimics of BDNF for traumatic brain injury. Neural Regen Res. 2017 Jan;12(1):7-12. doi: 10.4103/1673-5374.198964. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28250730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acheson A, Conover JC, Fandl JP, DeChiara TM, Russell M, Thadani A, Squinto SP, Yancopoulos GD, Lindsay RM. A BDNF autocrine loop in adult sensory neurons prevents cell death. Nature. 1995 Mar 30;374(6521):450-3.</citation>
    <PMID>7700353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang EJ, Reichardt LF. Neurotrophins: roles in neuronal development and function. Annu Rev Neurosci. 2001;24:677-736. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11520916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neren D, Johnson MD, Legon W, Bachour SP, Ling G, Divani AA. Vagus Nerve Stimulation and Other Neuromodulation Methods for Treatment of Traumatic Brain Injury. Neurocrit Care. 2016 Apr;24(2):308-19. doi: 10.1007/s12028-015-0203-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26399249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamb DG, Porges EC, Lewis GF, Williamson JB. Non-invasive Vagal Nerve Stimulation Effects on Hyperarousal and Autonomic State in Patients with Posttraumatic Stress Disorder and History of Mild Traumatic Brain Injury: Preliminary Evidence. Front Med (Lausanne). 2017 Jul 31;4:124. doi: 10.3389/fmed.2017.00124. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28824913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silberstein SD, Calhoun AH, Lipton RB, Grosberg BM, Cady RK, Dorlas S, Simmons KA, Mullin C, Liebler EJ, Goadsby PJ, Saper JR; EVENT Study Group. Chronic migraine headache prevention with noninvasive vagus nerve stimulation: The EVENT study. Neurology. 2016 Aug 2;87(5):529-38. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000002918. Epub 2016 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27412146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tassorelli C, Grazzi L, de Tommaso M, Pierangeli G, Martelletti P, Rainero I, Dorlas S, Geppetti P, Ambrosini A, Sarchielli P, Liebler E, Barbanti P; PRESTO Study Group. Noninvasive vagus nerve stimulation as acute therapy for migraine: The randomized PRESTO study. Neurology. 2018 Jul 24;91(4):e364-e373. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000005857. Epub 2018 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29907608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Post-Traumatic Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share data outside of study</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

