<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04075461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S-20180036</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04075461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Arthroplasty Versus Internal Fixation for Undisplaced Femoral Neck Fracture</brief_title>
  <acronym>SENSE</acronym>
  <official_title>Is arthroplaSty bEtter Than interNal Fixation in the undiSplaced Femoral nEck Fracture? A National Pragmatical Randomized Controlled Trial - the SENSE Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aalborg University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North Denmark Regional Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Slagelse Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bispebjerg Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regionshospitalet Viborg, Skive</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Randers Regional Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regionshospitalet Horsens</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital of Southern Jutland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital of South West Jutland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hvidovre University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Herlev Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hillerod Hospital, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Holbaek Sygehus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zealand University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sygehus Lillebaelt</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nykøbing Falster County Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regional Hospital West Jutland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is the world's first national orthopedic randomized controlled trial (RCT) involving 19
      out of 21 departments in Denmark. Each year, 7,000 patients suffer a hip fracture. This is a
      severe condition leading to 25% mortality after 1 year and 40% do not recover to the same
      functional level. The aim is to compare two surgical treatment methods (metal fixation versus
      artificial hip) in patients above 65 years with an undisplaced femoral neck fracture. The
      hypothesis is that even though an artificial hip is a larger surgical procedure than metal
      fixation of the broken bone, the artificial hip is more stable with less pain due the lack of
      a healing broken bone and therefore leads to a better and quicker mobilization after surgery.
      Better mobilization is one of the most important factors for decreasing mortality. We have
      chosen a pragmatic RCT design by using the local departmental implants. We hope that the
      knowledge from this study will therefore easily be implemented afterwards.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is the world's first national orthopedic randomized controlled trial (RCT) involving 19
      out of 21 departments in Denmark. The aim is to compare two surgical treatment methods
      (internal fixation (IF) versus arthroplasty) in patients above 65 years with an undisplaced
      femoral neck fracture (FNF).

      Each year, 7,000 patients suffer a hip fracture. This is a severe condition leading to 25%
      mortality after 1 year and 40% do not recover to the same functional level. Undisplaced FNF
      is treated with internal fixation in order to aid in fracture healing. However, approximately
      10% in Denmark will suffer a reoperation and two RCT's have demonstrated 20-21% reoperations.
      In comparison, the reoperation frequency was 5-7% for arthroplasty that also demonstrated
      slightly faster mobilization which is one of the most important factors for decreasing
      mortality. The hypothesis is therefore that even though arthroplasty is a larger surgery they
      benefit from the lack of fracture healing, less pain and faster mobilization.

      Patients are included in the emergency department and are electronically randomized to either
      IF or arthroplasty before the surgery. The design is a pragmatic RCT using the implants which
      are available in the departments. Furthermore, the postoperative treatment protocol is
      &quot;business as usual&quot; thereby investigating the precise effect of the intervention in real
      clinical conditions. In addition to a great external validity this allows for easy
      implemented after study results. The primary outcome is a validated functional score 1 year
      after surgery and the sample size is calculated to 330 patients. Secondary outcome measures
      are additional functional assessments and questionnaires, health related quality of life and
      pain assessment.

      We have set up a steering committee consisting of researchers and senior surgeons with a
      representative from each region. In addition, all but 1 hospital has a representative in
      project group. The project is therefore anchored in the entire Denmark.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study is designed as a national pragmatical RCT including all patients with an undisplaced FNF and a NMS score of 5 and above. The standard treatment in Denmark is internal fixation and the patients are randomized to arthroplasty or IF. The steering group have assessed the pragmatic attitude of the design and the study reaches 5 points in 7 of the 9 domains (Figure 1) (9). Reporting is performed accordingly to the extension of the CONSORT statements for pragmatical RCT (17). Using the PRECIS-2 we scored the study to 43 points out of 45 possible.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The surgeon, theater staff and patient cannot be blinded due to the nature of two very different types of surgery. However, the assessors will be blinded for type of surgery.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>New Mobility Score (NMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>NMS score the level of function with a score from 0-9 points. The best score is 9 points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol 5 domain 5 level (EQ-5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>Admission, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Health related quality of life assessment with a score from 0-1 point. The best score is 1 point</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxford Hip Score (OHS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Admission, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Specific hip function questionnaire with a score from 0-48 points. The best score is 48 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reoperation</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 year after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>New surgery in relation to the primary surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 year after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>New Mobility Score (NMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>NMS score the level of function with a score from 0-9 points. The best score is 9 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Verbal Rating Scale (VRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 and 6 weeks, 3, 6, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient reported outcome of pain assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">330</enrollment>
  <condition>Undisplaced Fracture</condition>
  <condition>Femoral Neck Fractures</condition>
  <condition>Internal Fixation; Complications</condition>
  <condition>Arthroplasty Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Undisplaced FNF + Arthroplasty</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arthroplasty is the typical surgery for a displaced femoral neck fracture</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Undisplaced FNF + Internal fixation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Internal fixation is the typical surgery for an undisplaced femoral neck fracture</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arthroplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>Arthroplasty is commonly used for a displaced femoral neck fracture.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Undisplaced FNF + Arthroplasty</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Internal fixation</intervention_name>
    <description>Internal fixation is commonly used for undisplaced femoral neck fracture</description>
    <arm_group_label>Undisplaced FNF + Internal fixation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 65 years old

          -  Undisplaced femoral neck fracture

          -  Posterior tilt (18) less than 20 degrees

          -  NMS (13) = 5 and above, indicating an ability to walk

          -  Cognitive intact in order to achieve informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The fracture is pathological

          -  The patient does not speak Danish
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bjarke Viberg, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Traumatology, Lillebaelt Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ole Brink, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Traumatology, Aarhus University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Søren Kold, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Traumatology, Aalborg University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morten S Larsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Odense University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristoffer B Hare, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Traumatology, Slagelse Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henrik Palm, MD, DmSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Traumatology, Bispebjerg Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bjarke Viberg, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 76363067</phone>
    <email>bjarke.viberg@rsyd.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anne J Hansen, Secretary</last_name>
    <phone>+45 76362333</phone>
    <email>anne.jess.hansen@rsyd.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lillebaelt Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kolding</city>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter I Andersen, MD</last_name>
      <email>peter.ivan.andersen@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anne J Hansen</last_name>
      <email>anne.jess.hansen@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Slagelse Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Slagelse</city>
        <zip>4200</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas B Bloch, MD</last_name>
      <email>tbbl@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristoffer B Hare, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>kbhr@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. Hip fracture: mangement. Clinical guideline [CG124]. National Institute for Health and Care Excellence; 2011, updated 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts KC, Brox WT, Jevsevar DS, Sevarino K. Management of hip fractures in the elderly. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2015 Feb;23(2):131-7. doi: 10.5435/JAAOS-D-14-00432. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25624365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lu Q, Tang G, Zhao X, Guo S, Cai B, Li Q. Hemiarthroplasty versus internal fixation in super-aged patients with undisplaced femoral neck fractures: a 5-year follow-up of randomized controlled trial. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 2017 Jan;137(1):27-35. doi: 10.1007/s00402-016-2591-9. Epub 2016 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27837321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dolatowski FC, Frihagen F, Bartels S, Opland V, Šaltytė Benth J, Talsnes O, Hoelsbrekken SE, Utvåg SE. Screw Fixation Versus Hemiarthroplasty for Nondisplaced Femoral Neck Fractures in Elderly Patients: A Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2019 Jan 16;101(2):136-144. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.18.00316.</citation>
    <PMID>30653043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wamper KE, Sierevelt IN, Poolman RW, Bhandari M, Haverkamp D. The Harris hip score: Do ceiling effects limit its usefulness in orthopedics? Acta Orthop. 2010 Dec;81(6):703-7. doi: 10.3109/17453674.2010.537808. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21110703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gjertsen JE, Fevang JM, Matre K, Vinje T, Engesæter LB. Clinical outcome after undisplaced femoral neck fractures. Acta Orthop. 2011 Jun;82(3):268-74. doi: 10.3109/17453674.2011.588857.</citation>
    <PMID>21619501</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zlowodzki M, Brink O, Switzer J, Wingerter S, Woodall J Jr, Petrisor BA, Kregor PJ, Bruinsma DR, Bhandari M. The effect of shortening and varus collapse of the femoral neck on function after fixation of intracapsular fracture of the hip: a multi-centre cohort study. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2008 Nov;90(11):1487-94. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.90B11.20582.</citation>
    <PMID>18978271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sikand M, Wenn R, Moran CG. Mortality following surgery for undisplaced intracapsular hip fractures. Injury. 2004 Oct;35(10):1015-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15351669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loudon K, Treweek S, Sullivan F, Donnan P, Thorpe KE, Zwarenstein M. The PRECIS-2 tool: designing trials that are fit for purpose. BMJ. 2015 May 8;350:h2147. doi: 10.1136/bmj.h2147.</citation>
    <PMID>25956159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen PK, Thillemann TM, Søballe K, Johnsen SP. Are process performance measures associated with clinical outcomes among patients with hip fractures? A population-based cohort study. Int J Qual Health Care. 2016 Dec 1;28(6):698-708. doi: 10.1093/intqhc/mzw093.</citation>
    <PMID>27591269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Morton NA, Harding KE, Taylor NF, Harrison G. Validity of the de Morton Mobility Index (DEMMI) for measuring the mobility of patients with hip fracture during rehabilitation. Disabil Rehabil. 2013 Feb;35(4):325-33. doi: 10.3109/09638288.2012.705220. Epub 2012 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22897700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Morton NA, Berlowitz DJ, Keating JL. A systematic review of mobility instruments and their measurement properties for older acute medical patients. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2008 Jun 5;6:44. doi: 10.1186/1477-7525-6-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18533045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker MJ, Palmer CR. A new mobility score for predicting mortality after hip fracture. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1993 Sep;75(5):797-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8376443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen MT, Foss NB, Kehlet H. [Timed Up and Go and New Mobility Score as predictors of function six months after hip fracture]. Ugeskr Laeger. 2005 Aug 29;167(35):3297-300. Danish.</citation>
    <PMID>16138973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen MT, Bandholm T, Foss NB, Ekdahl C, Kehlet H. High inter-tester reliability of the new mobility score in patients with hip fracture. J Rehabil Med. 2008 Jul;40(7):589-91. doi: 10.2340/16501977-0217.</citation>
    <PMID>18758678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedersen TJ, Lauritsen JM. Routine functional assessment for hip fracture patients. Acta Orthop. 2016 Aug;87(4):374-9. doi: 10.1080/17453674.2016.1197534. Epub 2016 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27329799</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zwarenstein M, Treweek S, Gagnier JJ, Altman DG, Tunis S, Haynes B, Oxman AD, Moher D; CONSORT group; Pragmatic Trials in Healthcare (Practihc) group. Improving the reporting of pragmatic trials: an extension of the CONSORT statement. BMJ. 2008 Nov 11;337:a2390. doi: 10.1136/bmj.a2390.</citation>
    <PMID>19001484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palm H, Gosvig K, Krasheninnikoff M, Jacobsen S, Gebuhr P. A new measurement for posterior tilt predicts reoperation in undisplaced femoral neck fractures: 113 consecutive patients treated by internal fixation and followed for 1 year. Acta Orthop. 2009 Jun;80(3):303-7. doi: 10.3109/17453670902967281.</citation>
    <PMID>19634021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt M, Pedersen L, Sørensen HT. The Danish Civil Registration System as a tool in epidemiology. Eur J Epidemiol. 2014 Aug;29(8):541-9. doi: 10.1007/s10654-014-9930-3. Epub 2014 Jun 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24965263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen MT. Hip fractures - Functional assessments and factors influencing in-hospital outcome, a physiotherapeutic perspective. Faculty of Medicine: Lund University; 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steihaug OM, Gjesdal CG, Bogen B, Kristoffersen MH, Lien G, Hufthammer KO, Ranhoff AH. Does sarcopenia predict change in mobility after hip fracture? a multicenter observational study with one-year follow-up. BMC Geriatr. 2018 Mar 5;18(1):65. doi: 10.1186/s12877-018-0755-x.</citation>
    <PMID>29506481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Danish Interdisciplinary Registry for Hip Fracture. National Annual Report for 2017. The Danish Healthcare Service; 2017 15.05.2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Femoral Neck Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Due to Danish regulation direct data sharing is not possible.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

