<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04072614</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LSH-19-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04072614</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Assessment of Spatial Neglect Following Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Assessment and Screening of Patients With Spatial Neglect Following Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Landspitali University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lithuanian University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Landspitali University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spatial neglect (SN) is a common heterogeneous cognitive affliction that predicts poor
      recovery after a stroke. It is important to identify SN so alliviating actions can be
      initated. Results of this cross-country study between Iceland and Lithuania should provide
      information on how to best identify SN in clinical care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spatial neglect (SN) is a common disorder following stroke, adversely affecting recovery. SN
      often involves associated symptoms, including anosognosia, extinction, difficulties with
      sustained attention and problems with emotional processing. Correct identification of SN and
      associated problems is essential for initiating alleviating strategies and for measuring
      progress. Several assessment tools exist, but psychometric testing has mostly been conducted
      in non-dynamic environments; a single country or culture. Thus non-transferable to a wider
      context and ward-based care. To optimize identification of SN and develop procedures for
      diverse healthcare settings, this cross-country study includes patients from Iceland and
      Lithuania. We will seek to maximize the clinical utility by avoiding exclusion of patients,
      e.g., with psycholinguistic difficulties and multiple strokes. We will: a) use behavioral SN
      assessment and visuo-graphic tests to validate a newly developed SN tool that incorporates
      many aspects of SN that are currently not addressed in conventional tests, b) validate
      integration of an additional component into the National Institute of Health Stroke Scale as
      a screening tool to identify SN, and c) evaluate differences in clinical characteristics
      between patients with left- and right-sided SN, and patients with and without SN.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Catherine Bergego Scale (CBS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke.</time_frame>
    <description>The Catherine Bergego Scale (CBS) reveals presence, severity and common challenges of SN. The ten items of the scale gauge; topographical orienting; navigation, underuse of hand/arm; difficulties with dressing and grooming; difficulties attending to auditory stimuli; collisions, and searching for, or identifying objects on the neglected side. Each item will be graded from zero to three. A total score of 1-10 indicates mild SN, 11-20 moderate SN and 21-30 severe SN. The CBS will be used as a clinical reference standard for SN and to evaluate change over time. Patients with SN within 5 days post stroke will be assessed with a modified version of the CBS at three months post stroke and 1-year follow up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Conventional visuo-graphic test: Star cancellation (Index test)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 days post stroke.</time_frame>
    <description>Identifying small stars among a variety of distractors (short words and big stars). Maximun score 54, cut of point for SN 51 or less cancellations of small stars or a lateralized difference of at least two stars between two calculations.
Qualitative evaluation of starting point.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Conventional visuo-graphic test: Figure copying (Index test)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 days post stroke.</time_frame>
    <description>Replication of a four-item drawing: a tree, a house, a fence, and a car. Scoring based on completion and location of drawings. A maximum score of eight corresponds to 100% failure. Any omissions of left-sided (or right-sided) features scored one. Inability to reproduce an entire figure scored as two, and drawing the left (right) side of the figure on the right (left) side of the paper was awarded with one. A score of &gt; 1 (or 12,5%) is confirmative for neglect.
Qualitative evaluation of starting point.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neglect Experience Qestionnaire (NEQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>9 item Neglect Assessment Tool (NEQ). The NEQ has been developed based on observation and interviews of 70 patients with SN and now comprises nine questions/ observations reflecting of abnormal bodily experiences associated with SN. Required observations will be collected during daily activities and combined with an approximate 5-minute interview. The NEQ will be used in the following ways: As a clinical reference standard, as an index test, and to measure change over time. Patients with SN within 5 days post stroke will be assessed with a modified version of the NEQ at three months post stroke and 1 year post stroke.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>National Institute of HealthStroke Scale (NIHSS) picture description to screen for SN (Index test)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 days post stroke.</time_frame>
    <description>The drawing used to assess for aphasia within the NIHSS will be used to screen for SN. Patients will be scored according to their ability to describe items within the picture. We will for instance evaluate ability to describe items within the contralesional and ipsilesional side of the A4 paper-sheet when the paper is aligned first to the midsaggital body plane.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke severity; National Institute of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 days post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Comprising 11 items; impaired consciousness, horizontal eye movement, visual fields (hemianopia); facial paralysis; motor strength (arms/legs), ataxia, aphasia, dysarthria, and extinction will be used. Hemianopia will be evaluated while patients have both renotopic fields within the intact hemispace. The score ranges from 0-42; a score of 0 indicated &quot;no signs of stroke&quot; and higher score designates increased severity. 0=No stroke symptoms, 1-4=Minor stroke, 5-15=Moderate stroke, 15-20=Moderate/severe stroke, 21-42=Severe stroke.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disability and dependency: Barthel Index (BI)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>The BI will be used to evaluate change in disability and dependence over time and differences between patients with and without SN. Measurement will be completed within 5 days post stroke; three-month post stroke, and at 1-year follow up.
basic activities. The score ranges from 0-100 with 5-point increments. A score of 0 denotes total dependence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participation: The modified Rankin Scale (mRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before hospital admission for stroke (recollected),5 days post stroke; three-month poststroke, and 1-year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The modified Rankin Scale (mRS) provides a score from total independence/perfect health to death/no function (0-6).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients Reported Ourcome Measures: PROMIS-10</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>PROMIS-10 provide information about perceived domains of health including overall physical health, mental health, social health, pain, fatigue, and overall perceived quality of life. Questions posed by the researcher within each of the 10 global health domains are scored by examine each item separately and score on a Likert-like scale to allow identification of specific information about perceptions of physical function, pain, fatigue, emotional distress, social health and general perceptions of health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Mortality rate within the first year</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay in days</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke re-occurence</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Number of stroke events within the first year</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Ethical approval has been obtained to conduct the data collection within the National
        University Hospital in Iceland (LUHI) and Hospital of Lithuanian University of Health
        Sciences, Kauno klinikos (LSMU-KK).

        Consecutive stroke patients will be assessed until we have included at least 1000 stroke
        patients where minimum 200 patients have SN. The yearly admissions for the years 2017 and
        2018 have been an average of 850 patients (250 NUHI; LSMU-KK; 600). By anticipating lack of
        data in 30% instances, the required number of patients should be possible to enroll withhin
        1 ½ - 2 years. Stroke patients without SN are required for evaluating the psychometric
        properties of SN tests and to enable comparison of clinical characteristics between
        patients with and without SN.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Stroke diagnosis confirmed by results of CT/MRI.

          -  Lives in Iceland or Lithuania.

          -  18 year or older.

          -  Informed consent provided by patient or proxy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Patients receiving end-of-life care
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marianne Klinke</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Landspitali</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marianne Klinke</last_name>
    <phone>+354 5254000</phone>
    <email>marianne@hi.is</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Halla Arnardottir</last_name>
    <email>hallarn@landspitali.is</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Landspitali</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reykjavík</city>
        <country>Iceland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marianne Klinke</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Iceland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Landspitali University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marianne Elisabeth Klinke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor and Academic Chair of Nursing Care and Research within Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spatial neglect</keyword>
  <keyword>Perceptual disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic techniques and procedures</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptom assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

