<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04072575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108605</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R092670PSY3016</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-004532-30</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04072575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Paliperidone Palmitate 6-Month Formulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Single-arm, Open-label Extension to a Double-blind, Randomized, Active-controlled, Parallel-group Study of Paliperidone Palmitate 6-Month Formulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is to assess the long-term safety and tolerability of
      paliperidone 6-month PP6M (Dose 1 or Dose 2 [milligram] mg eq.) and to provide access to PP6M
      in participants with schizophrenia completing the R092670PSY3015 study without relapse.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 6, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 6, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants who Receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 Paliperidone Palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 paliperidone palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants who Receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 Paliperidone Palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 183</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 paliperidone palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants who Receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 Paliperidone Palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 365</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 paliperidone palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants who Receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 Paliperidone Palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 547</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who receive 1, 2, 3, or 4 paliperidone palmitate 6-Month (PP6M) injections will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The AIMS rates 9 items about dyskinesia on scale as 0= none, 1= minimal, 2= mild, 3= moderate, and 4= severe. It rates 1 item about the participant's awareness of abnormal movements as 0= no awareness; 1= aware, no distress; 2= aware, mild distress; 3= aware, moderate distress; and 4= aware, severe distress. It has 2 yes/no questions about dental status. A total score (ranging from 0 to 28) will be calculated as the sum of items 1 to 7.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 365</time_frame>
    <description>The AIMS rates 9 items about dyskinesia on scale as 0= none, 1= minimal, 2= mild, 3= moderate, and 4= severe. It rates 1 item about the participant's awareness of abnormal movements as 0= no awareness; 1= aware, no distress; 2= aware, mild distress; 3= aware, moderate distress; and 4= aware, severe distress. It has 2 yes/no questions about dental status. A total score (ranging from 0 to 28) will be calculated as the sum of items 1 to 7.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 729</time_frame>
    <description>The AIMS rates 9 items about dyskinesia on scale as 0= none, 1= minimal, 2= mild, 3= moderate, and 4= severe. It rates 1 item about the participant's awareness of abnormal movements as 0= no awareness; 1= aware, no distress; 2= aware, mild distress; 3= aware, moderate distress; and 4= aware, severe distress. It has 2 yes/no questions about dental status. A total score (ranging from 0 to 28) will be calculated as the sum of items 1 to 7.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Abnormalities in Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 729</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormalities in vital signs including temperature, pulse/heart rate, respiratory rate, and blood pressure will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Changes in Physical Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 729</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with changes in physical examination will be reported. Physical examinations include body examination, weight, and waist circumference.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Clinical Laboratory Values</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with clinical laboratory values related to hematology, serum chemistry and urinalysis will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Mental Status Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants mental status will be performed that included domains identified on Mental Status Examination Form. These domains include: General Appearance and Behavior, Mood, Affect, Thought Process, Thought Content, Perceptions, and Insight. If suicidal ideation is present, a C‑SSRS must also be performed to assess severity and track suicidal events through any treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Injection Site Reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 729</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with injection site reactions will be reported. Participants will be asked about the pain associated with the injection by means of a 100‑mm Visual Analog Scale (VAS), scaled from &quot;no pain at all&quot; to &quot;unbearably painful'.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical event that occurs in a participant administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Clinical Global Impression Severity (CGI-S) Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Days 1, 92, 183, 274, 365, 456, 547, 638 and 729</time_frame>
    <description>The CGI-S rating scale is used to rate the severity of a participant's overall clinical condition on a 7 point scale ranging from 1 (not ill) to 7 (extremely severe). This scale permits a global evaluation of the participant's condition at a given time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Personal and Social Performance (PSP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Days 1, 365 and 729</time_frame>
    <description>The PSP scale assesses the degree of difficulty a participant exhibits over a 7-day period within 4 domains of behavior: a) socially useful activities, b) personal and social relationships, c) self-care, and d) disturbing and aggressive behavior. The results of the assessment are converted to a numerical score from 1 to 100 points, which can be interpreted in 10 point intervals as excellent functioning (91 to 100 points), good functioning (81 to 90 points), mild difficulties (71 to 80 points), Scores from 31 to 70 points indicate varying degrees of difficulty, and scores below 30 points indicate functioning so poor that intensive support or supervision is needed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants who Met the Criteria for Remission Based on Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 12, 24, and End-of-Study (Month 30)</time_frame>
    <description>The neuropsychiatric symptoms of schizophrenia will be assessed by using the 30-item Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS). The PANSS provides a total score (sum of the scores of all 30 items) ranging from 30 to 210, higher scores indicate more severe neuropsychiatric symptoms of schizophrenia. Scores for 3 subscales, that is, for positive subscale (sum of the scores of all 7 items) and negative subscale (sum of the scores of all 7 items) ranges from 7 (absent) to 49 (extreme psychopathology), and for the general psychopathology subscale (sum of the scores of all 16 items) score ranges from 16 (absent) to 112 (extreme psychopathology).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Resource Utilization Questionnaire (HRUQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 183, 365, 547 and 729</time_frame>
    <description>Medical resource utilization data will be collected using the HRUQ. This questionnaire is designed to assess utilization of the following resources: hospitalization (refers to &gt;=1 night stay), emergency room visits without hospitalization, day or night clinic stays, outpatient treatment, as well as daily living conditions and productivity of the participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Relapse is defined as achieving any of the following: psychiatric hospitalization for schizophrenia (involuntary or voluntary admission to a psychiatric hospital for decompensation of the participant's schizophrenic symptoms); emergency department/room/ward visit due to a worsening of the participant's symptoms of schizophrenia, but a psychiatric hospitalization does not occur; the participant's inflicts deliberate self-injury or exhibits violent behavior resulting in suicide, clinically significant injury to him/her self or another person, or significant property damage; participant has suicidal or homicidal ideation and aggressive behavior that is clinically significant (in frequency and severity) in the investigator's judgment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">182</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paliperidone Palmitate 6 month(PP6M)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants who enter the this open-label extension study immediately after completing Double-blind Phase Study R092670PSY3015 (previous study) will receive Paliperidone Palmitate 6 month (PP6M) intramuscular (IM) injections, dose will be selected based on the unblinded dose level (&quot;moderate&quot; or &quot;higher&quot;) that the participant received during previous study. Participants in the &quot;moderate&quot; dose level will receive PP6M Dose 1 and &quot;higher&quot; dose level will receive PP6M Dose 2 during the open-label extension. The PP6M dose level may be adjusted (to Dose 1 or Dose 2) for every 6 month at Visits 3, 5, and 7, based on clinical judgment. Participants who enter this open-label extension study later (up to 3 months after they complete previous study) and were on a moderate or higher dose of PP3M (350 or 525 mg eq.) or PP1M (100 or 150 mg eq.) will receive initial dose of PP6M IM injection (Dose 1 or Dose 2) for every 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PP6M injection Dose 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive Dose 1 PP6M intramuscular (IM) injection at Visit 1 (Day) then once every 6 month up to 24 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paliperidone Palmitate 6 month(PP6M)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>R092670</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PP6M injection Dose 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive Dose 2 PP6M IM injection at Visit 1 (Day) then once every 6 month up to 24 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paliperidone Palmitate 6 month(PP6M)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>R092670</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Completed the Double-blind Phase of Study R092670PSY3015 without relapse and continue
             to be willing to be treated with paliperidone palmitate 6 month injection (PP6M)

          -  Must, in the opinion of the investigator, be able to continue treatment at the same
             dose level (moderate or higher dose) as used during the Double-blind Phase of Study
             R092670PSY3015 at the time of screening for this study

          -  A woman of childbearing potential: a) Must have a negative pregnancy test on Day 1; b)
             Use contraception consistent with local regulations. A man must agree that during the
             study and for a minimum 12 months after receiving the last dose of the study
             intervention: a) His female partner(s) will use highly effective method pf
             contraception

          -  Sign an informed consent form (ICF) indicating that he or she understands the purpose
             of, and procedures required for, the study and is willing to participate in the study;
             and must be able to provide his or her own consent (that is, consent cannot be
             provided by a legal representative of the participant)

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, the patient would be able to participate for the
             duration of this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has any condition for which, in the opinion of the investigator, participation would
             not be in the best interest of the participant (example, compromise the well-being) or
             that could prevent, limit, or confound the protocol-specified assessments

          -  Completed R092670PSY3015 while presenting adverse events deemed clinically relevant by
             the investigator, and which may interfere with safety and well-being of the
             participant

          -  If a man, has plans to father a child while enrolled in this study or within 12 months
             after the last dose of study intervention. Must not, if a woman, have plans to become
             pregnant while enrolled in this study or within 12 months after the last dose of study
             intervention
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Contact</last_name>
    <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundación para el Estudio y Tratamiento de las Enfermedades Mentales</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires</city>
        <zip>C1133AAH</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CEN-Consultorios Especializados en Neurociencias</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cordoba</city>
        <zip>X5004FJF</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanatorio Prof. Leon S. Morra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cordoba</city>
        <zip>X5009BIN</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>INSA Instituto de Neurociencias San Agustín</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Plata</city>
        <zip>1900</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Privada de Salud Mental Santa Teresa de Ávila</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Plata</city>
        <zip>B1904ADM</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>C.I.A.P. (Centro de investigación y Asistencia en Psiquiatría)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rosario</city>
        <zip>2000</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dipartimento di Salute Mentale</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lecce</city>
        <zip>73100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seconda Universita degli Studi di Napoli - Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universita degli Studi di Roma 'La Sapienza' - Azienda Ospedaliera Sant Andrea</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00189</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mlynowamed Specjalistyczny Psychiatryczny Gabinet Lekarski Joanna Lazarczyk</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bialystok</city>
        <zip>15-404</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zespol Opieki Zdrowotnej w Chelmnie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chelmno</city>
        <zip>86-200</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centrum Badań Klinicznych PI-House sp. z o.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gdansk</city>
        <zip>80-546</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Specjalistyczna Praktyka Lekarska lek. Piotr Zalitacz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gorlice</city>
        <zip>38-300</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Niepubliczny Zaklad Opieki Psychiatrycznej MENTIS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leszno</city>
        <zip>64-100</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centrum Medyczne Luxmed Sp z o o</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lublin</city>
        <zip>20-109</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Poradnia Zdrowia Psychicznego 'Syntonia' w Pruszczu Gdanskim</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pruszcz Gdanski</city>
        <zip>83-000</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sverdlovsk Regional Clinical Psychiatric Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ekaterinburg</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nizny Novgorod clinical psychiatric hospital 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nizny Novgorod</city>
        <zip>603155</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SHI 'Saratov City Clinical Hospital 2 n.a V.I. Razumovsky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <zip>410028</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saratov Regional Psychiatric hospital named after St. Sofia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <zip>410060</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute of Mental Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tomsk</city>
        <zip>634014</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MNCE of Kyiv RC Regional Psychiatric and Narcological Medical Association</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glevakha</city>
        <zip>8630</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SI Institute of Neurology, Psychiatry and Narcology of NAMSU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kharkiv</city>
        <zip>61068</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNPE'Kherson Regional Institution of Mental Care'of Kherson Regional Council</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kherson</city>
        <zip>73488</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyiv Territorial Medical Incorporation 'Psychiatry'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyiv</city>
        <zip>04080</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CI of LRC Lviv Regional Psychoneurology Dispensary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lviv</city>
        <zip>79017</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE of the Lviv Regional Council 'Lviv Regional Clinical Psychiatric Hospital'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lviv</city>
        <zip>79021</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE Odesa regional psychiatric hospital #2 Odesa regional council</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oleksandrivka</city>
        <zip>67513</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE 'Cherkasy Regional Psychiatric Hospital of Cherkasy Regional Council'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Smila</city>
        <zip>20708</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CNCE 'Vinnytsya RC Psychoneurological Hospital n.a. O.I. Yushchenko Vinnytsya RC'</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vinnytsia</city>
        <zip>21005</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR108605</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data sharing policy of the Janssen Pharmaceutical Companies of Johnson &amp; Johnson is available at www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency.
As noted on this site, requests for access to the study data can be submitted through Yale open Data Access (YODA) Project site at yoda.yale.edu</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>https://www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

