<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04073732</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>71774006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04073732</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Family Physician Contract Services and Impacts in China Based on Physician Agency Theory</brief_title>
  <official_title>Family Physician Contract Services and Impacts in China Based on Physician Agency Theory</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In June 2016, the Health Reform Office in the State Council released &quot;the Announcement about
      Guiding Opinions of Promoting Family Physician Contract Services&quot;. Family Physician Contract
      Service is an important tool to change the health service models in primary care
      organizations in China. The relationship between patients and physicians can be regarded as
      principles and agents.

      Physician agency theory has been used to study physician behaviors in economics and
      management. Family physician contract services regulate the principle-agent relationship
      between patients and physicians using a formal contract, and there are lots of potentials to
      employ the physician agency theory to study family physician contract services in China. In
      theoretical aspects, the present project will study the analysis frameworks and methods of
      family physician contract services in China under the capitation and global budget payment
      mechanisms after systematically reviewing Chinese and English literatures about the physician
      agency theory. In empirical aspects, the present project will collect data from family
      physician contract services and examine the effects of specific contract forms, incentives,
      and fees on family physician behaviors and their impacts on health status and medical
      expenditures of hypertensive and diabetic patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. From a theoretical point of view, using the physician agency theory to construct a
           family physician contract services and a family physician (team) behavior theory
           analysis framework and research method system suitable for China's national conditions.

        2. From the empirical point of view, from the demand side, analyze the needs of the family
           physician contract service, the status quo, and the behavior of the visit; from the
           supplier, understand the behavior changes and satisfaction of the family physician
           (team) after the implementation of the family physician contract service Degree
           situation

        3. From an empirical perspective, from the level of primary medical institutions, use the
           sample area data to analyze the impact of family physicians' signing services on the
           number of visits and medical expenses;

        4. From an empirical perspective, using the constructed theoretical analysis framework to
           analyze the implementation of the Chinese family physician contract service, including
           incentive mechanism (income, incentive performance salary and contract service fee),
           family physician team composition, family bed service, etc. The impact, especially on
           the quality and quantity of services.

        5. From the empirical point of view, taking the key monitoring population (hypertension
           patients as an example) as a sample, further study the family physicians' contractual
           services, the changes in the practice behavior of family physicians to the key
           monitoring population (hypertension, diabetes patients), health outcomes, medical
           expenses The effect is to propose policy recommendations for family physicians'
           contracting services and physicians' behavior in the new medical reform in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of contracted residents</measure>
    <time_frame>2018.1-2019.6</time_frame>
    <description>Health-care quantity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average treatment time</measure>
    <time_frame>2018.1-2019.6</time_frame>
    <description>Health-care quality</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute value of diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>2018.1-2019.6</time_frame>
    <description>Health outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical expenses for patients with hypertension</measure>
    <time_frame>2018.1-2019.6</time_frame>
    <description>Health-care cost</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of service residents per day</measure>
    <time_frame>2018.1-2019.6</time_frame>
    <description>Health-care quantity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute value of systolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>2018.1-2019.6</time_frame>
    <description>Health outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2130</enrollment>
  <condition>Physician Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>family physician team</arm_group_label>
    <description>Family physician team in four regions (Beijing, Shanghai, Hangzhou and Xia'men), including general practitioners, nurses and public health personnel.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1）Family physician team participating in family physician contract services, including
        family doctors, nurses, public security personnel, etc.; 2) Residents, Residents who come
        to the community health service center
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Family physician

               1. a family doctor (general practitioner), has a formal medical license, does not
                  retire;

               2. must be directly facing the patient, participate in the patient's diagnosis,
                  prescription, treatment and return visits, with the outpatient service as the
                  main treatment;

               3. family doctors average weekly Must receive at least 20 patients and receive an
                  average of no less than 2 days per week;

               4. Signing informed consent.

          -  Residents 1) Can complete the questionnaire independently； 2）Oral participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family physician Not signing informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nhc.gov.cn/</url>
    <description>Related Info</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frølich A, Talavera JA, Broadhead P, Dudley RA. A behavioral model of clinician responses to incentives to improve quality. Health Policy. 2007 Jan;80(1):179-93. Epub 2006 Apr 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16624440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Arrow KJ. Uncertainty and the welfare economics of medical care. 1963. Bull World Health Organ. 2004 Feb;82(2):141-9. Epub 2004 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>15042238</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fang H, Liu H, Rizzo JA. Has the use of physician gatekeepers declined among HMOs? Evidence from the United States. Int J Health Care Finance Econ. 2009 Jun;9(2):183-95. doi: 10.1007/s10754-009-9060-8. Epub 2009 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>19357948</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fang H, Rizzo JA. Managed care and physicians' perceptions of drug formulary use. Am J Manag Care. 2009 Jun;15(6):395-400.</citation>
    <PMID>19514805</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wilson DM, Taylor DW, Gilbert JR, Best JA, Lindsay EA, Willms DG, Singer J. A randomized trial of a family physician intervention for smoking cessation. JAMA. 1988 Sep 16;260(11):1570-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3411737</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Avery DM Jr, Hooper DE, McDonald JT Jr, Love MW, Tucker MT, Parton JM. The economic impact of rural family physicians practicing obstetrics. J Am Board Fam Med. 2014 Sep-Oct;27(5):602-10. doi: 10.3122/jabfm.2014.05.140052.</citation>
    <PMID>25201930</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yip WC, Hsiao W, Meng Q, Chen W, Sun X. Realignment of incentives for health-care providers in China. Lancet. 2010 Mar 27;375(9720):1120-30. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60063-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20346818</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Conrad DA. The Theory of Value-Based Payment Incentives and Their Application to Health Care. Health Serv Res. 2015 Dec;50 Suppl 2:2057-89. doi: 10.1111/1475-6773.12408. Epub 2015 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26549041</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hai Fang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator,Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>family physician contract services</keyword>
  <keyword>physician agency theory</keyword>
  <keyword>physician Behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>family physician</keyword>
  <keyword>health service supply</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Contains a large amount of personal information, this research and various agencies signed a data confidentiality agreement</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

