<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04076644</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013884</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04076644</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Maintenance Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in Major Depressive Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Maintenance of Response To Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) in Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) Using Monthly TMS Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This an open label study using a FDA-cleared TMS stimulation protocols which will be used to
      treat patients who have responded or remitted from depression using acute clinical TMS
      therapy at the University of Missouri-Columbia Neuromodulation Clinic. TMS therapy will be
      given to subjects at monthly intervals. Depression severity questionnaires will be given
      monthly to determine if the subjects original response to TMS can be maintained. Subjects
      will be tapered down from antidepressant medication prior to TMS maintenance treatment.
      Results will be analyzed to determine the effectiveness and feasibility of maintenance TMS
      therapies in a clinical setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This an open label study using Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) as a maintenance
      treatment for subjects that have seen a clinically significant response or remission from
      their depressive symptoms after having had an acute clinical course of TMS. All potential
      subjects must have been treated at the University of Missouri Columbia Neuromodulation Clinic
      to qualify.

      There are 2 arms in this study. The first is a group of patients who will not receive any TMS
      treatments and will be followed for a year, and have their depression severity assessed
      monthly using the Personal Health Questionnaire (PHQ9), and the Quick Inventory of Depressive
      Symptoms.

      The second arm will receive TMS treatments 5 times/month for 12 months, be assessed for
      changes in depressive symptom severity monthly using the PHQ9 and QIDS. TMS treatment
      protocols will consist of wither the standard 20min 10Hz protocol, or a 3min theta-burst
      protocol. The protocol used will be determined by what worked for the subject when they were
      treated clinically at the University of Missouri Columbia Neuromodulation clinic. Subjects in
      this arm will be tapered of antidepressant medication prior to monthly TMS treatment and will
      remain antidepressant free for the duration of the study.

      The study will be a year long in duration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression Severity changes scored from Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ9)</measure>
    <time_frame>given at monthly intervals for 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>given at baseline and prior to every monthly TMS treatment block, scale is 0-27 with 0=no depression, 27=severe depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression Severity changes scored from Quick Inventory of Depression Symptom Questionnaire (QIDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>given two times every month (before and after TMS treatment block) for 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>given at baseline, and at the beginning and end of each monthly TMS treatment block,scale is 0-27 with 0=no depression, 27=severe depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>MDD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TMS Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive either a 20min 10hz TMS treatment, or a 3min theta-burst TMS treatment at certain monthly intervals. The TMS treatment protocol they receive depends on what they received in their acute clinical treatment. Subjects in the arm will be tapered off antidepressant medication before TMS treatment begins. Subjects will be assessed monthly for depression using QIDS and PHQ9.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No TMS Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be followed and assessed for depressive symptoms at monthly time intervals similar to the active treatment arm using QIDS and PHQ9. This group does not receive TMS treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMS treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>TMS using either a standard 10hz 20min or 3 min theta burst protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>TMS Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have recently (within 4 weeks) completed an acute TMS course (full 36 treatments)
             at the University of Missouri Columbia Neuromodulation clinic

          -  Must have clinically responded to the acute TMS treatment course (≥50% improvement
             according to the clinical depressive scale used - usually the PHQ-9)

          -  Must be able sign consent

          -  Must have a current address and phone number

          -  Must have current mental health care provider, either psychiatrist or general
             practioner who they see for mental health symptom management

          -  Must be able to taper off antidepressant medication before 1st monthly treatment block
             (treatment group only)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  - Subject that has not completed a full acute treatment course, including taper

          -  Subjects that have changed anything that may not make them safe for TMS, which are
             (all changes will be reviewed by study MD, and will not necessarily be excluded
             possibly depending on severity):

               -  Any new metal near head

               -  Any new medical devices that cannot be removed

               -  Any new pregnancies (verbally confirmed)

               -  Seizures that occurred post-acute TMS treatment

               -  Any uncontrolled cardiovascular disease

               -  Any new head trauma

               -  Any new illness causing injury to brain

               -  Any new medications which cannot be altered or lowered that may be
                  contraindicated for TMS treatment

               -  Any drug or alcohol use deemed by the study doctor as unsafe for TMS treatment

          -  Subjects unwilling to sign consent or follow study procedures

          -  Subjects with known extended travel plans which may affect study procedures and
             scheduled TMS treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Muaid Ithman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matt Schmidt, MS</last_name>
    <phone>573 882 5688</phone>
    <email>schmidtmw@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri Neuromodulation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Schmidt, MS</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Muaid Ithman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Clinical Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TMS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

