<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04070482</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016/449-LON</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04070482</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of in Utero and Breastfeeding Exposure to Tenofovir on Renal Function in HIV-exposed Uninfected Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of in Utero and Breastfeeding Exposure to Tenofovir on Renal Function in HIV-exposed Uninfected Children in Cameroon: The PREVENT-IT Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Yaounde 1</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Yaounde 1</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to determine whether and how in utero exposure to Tenofovir
      affects renal function in HIV-exposed uninfected infants
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a growing use of Tenofovir (TDF) in sub-Saharan Africa with the use of Option B+ for
      prevention of mother-to-child HIV transmission. TDF has been associated to renal function
      abnormalities both in macaques and HIV-infected adults and infants. Therefore concerns have
      been raised about its renal safety in exposed infants of women on Option B+. Data for HEU is
      sparse and routine measures of renal function (creatinine, proteinuria), may not be
      appropriate to detect TDF-associated renal injury early. The goal of our study is to assess
      whether TDF use in pregnancy and breastfeeding affects the function of the kidney function of
      the child. Pregnant women who consent during their first antenatal consultation to take
      antiretroviral drugs for PMTCT after testing positive, will be enrolled and followed till
      birth, for adherence using HPLC. Their terms infants who are HIV negative by DNA PCR at 6
      weeks (HEU), will have urine collected at 1.5, 3, 6, 9 months. Using appropriate and more
      sensitive markers (RBP4, KIM1, NAG, β2M), proximal tubular function will be assessed in 159
      HEU infants and same number of controls. Nutritional status and drug history data will be
      collected for both mother and child. RBP, KIM1, β2M will be measured using XMAP assay while
      ELISA will be used for NAG according to manufacturer recommendations. Creatinine, phosphates
      and urinary tract infection will be measured using standard methods. Values of these markers
      will be compared between the 2 groups. Results will confirm/infirm renal safety of TDF in
      pregnancy, improve prevention of long term renal injury through early detection, contribute
      to promote development of routine rapid diagnostic tests for acute renal tubular injury
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in urinary RBP, NAG, KIM-1and B2M levels at birth between neonates born to mothers living with HIV, exposed in utero to TDF and those born to mothers without HIV and not exposed to TDF</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth</time_frame>
    <description>In urine samples collected at birth from HIV-EU TDF-exposed neonates and an equal number of TDF-unexposed controls, RBP, KIM-1, B2M will be measured using multianalyte platform (xMAP) assay, while NAG will be measured using ELISA. Levels of these correlates of proximal tubular function will be compared between the two groups, adjusting for confounders</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in urinary RBP, NAG, KIM-1and B2M levels after birth and within the first year of life between HEU infants, exposed in utero to TDF and HUU infants, not exposed to TDF</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Trends in urinary RBP:Cr, NAG:Cr, KIM-1 and B2M will be tracked during and beyond breastfeeding between HIV-EU TDF+ and unexposed controls by conducting serial measurements of these markers at 6 weeks then 3, 6, 12 months using same methods described in outcome 1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV-exposed uninfected infants</arm_group_label>
    <description>These are children to women who are living with HIV but who are not infected with the virus (HIV PCR results at 6 weeks is negative)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV-unexposed uninfected infants</arm_group_label>
    <description>These are children born to women who are not infected with HIV</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tenofovir exposure in utero and during breastfeeding</intervention_name>
    <description>Exposed in utero and during breastfeeding to Tenofovir-containing antiretroviral drugs</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIV-exposed uninfected infants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Mothers: Peripheral blood (delivery) Infants: Coord blood, urine, peripheral blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Our study population will be primarily made up of mother-infant pairs with and without
        infant exposure in utero to TDF and HIV
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Mothers

               1. HIV seropositive pregnant women on Option B+ protocol containing TDF.

               2. HIV seronegative pregnant women

               3. Pregnant women who provide informed consent.

               4. Woman is living in Yaounde and is not planning to relocate in the next 2 years.
                  Children

               1. Children born to HIV-infected mothers (and HIV-uninfected mothers for controls).

               2. TDF- and HIV-exposed in utero (and age-matched unexposed controls).

               3. HIV negative after birth by DNA PCR 4.0 to 12 months of age (included in study at
                  birth and followed up till 12 months)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refusal of parent(s) to give consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>1 Year</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gabriel L Ekali, MD,MH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Yaounde 1</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CASS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yaoundé</city>
        <country>Cameroon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cité Verte DH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yaoundé</city>
        <country>Cameroon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Efoulan DH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yaoundé</city>
        <country>Cameroon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cameroon</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 26, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 26, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Yaounde 1</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gabriel Loni Ekali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tenofovir</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-exposed infants</keyword>
  <keyword>renal injury</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

