<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04076241</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018/0180</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04076241</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Complementary Therapy on Cardiopulmonary Parameters in Patients With Pulmonary Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Complementary Therapy Model on Cardiopulmonary Parameters, Nitric Oxide Levels and Quality of Life in Patients With Pulmonary Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators planned a randomised controlled study to investigate the effects of a
      complementary therapy model on cardiopulmonary parameters, nitric oxide levels and quality of
      life in patients with pulmonary hypertension. Our hypothesis is that complementary therapy
      model including osteopathic manipulative therapy and pranayama may improve cardiopulmonary
      parameters, nitric oxide levels and quality of life in patients with PH.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary hypertension (PH) is characterized by a mean pulmonary arterial pressure of 25 mmHg
      or more, measured by right heart catheterization at rest. Pulmonary arterial hypertension
      (PAH) begins in the small arteries of the pulmonary vasculature and is characterized by
      increased vasoconstriction. Pulmonary vasodilatation induced by perivascular nerve
      stimulation usually occurs with nitric oxide (NO). A decrease in the airway wall
      concentration of NO was detected in patients with PH. It has been reported that patients with
      PAH have a mild to moderate decrease in lung volumes associated with disease severity. A
      decrease in exercise capacity, respiratory muscle strength and quality of life has been
      reported in patients with PH.

      Osteopathic Manipulative Therapy (OMT) is a well-known manual therapy approved by World
      Health Organization. A single-session of OMT was found to increase pulmonary function,
      inspiratory muscle strength, oxygen saturation, and to reduce dyspnea and fatigue in
      individuals with severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. It has been observed that OMT
      increases parasympathetic activity and reduces blood pressure in patients with hypertension.

      Pranayama is an important type of breathing exercises of yoga. It has been reported that
      pranayama increases vagal tone and reduces sympathetic activity, increases vital capacity, is
      effective in controlling heart rate and blood pressure, and improves respiratory muscle
      strength and quality of life.

      No study investigating the effects of a complementary therapy model in patients with PH was
      found in the literature. The investigators aimed to investigate the effects of a
      complementary therapy model consisting of OMT and pranayama on cardiopulmonary parameters, NO
      levels and quality of life in patients with PH.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Forced Vital Capacity (FVC), Forced Expiratory Volume in One Second (FEV1) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>FVC and FEV1 were recorded in liter (l) by using spirometry (Spiro USB, CareFusion US). Measurements were performed according to American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society (ATS/ERS) recommendations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Forced Expiratory Volume in One Second/Forced Vital Capacity (FEV1/FVC) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>FEV1/FVC ratio (%) was recorded with regards to the highest FEV1 and FVC values measured by spirometry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Forced Expiratory Flow at 25-75% of FVC (FEF25-75) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>FEF25-75 was recorded in liter/second (l/s) by using spirometry (Spiro USB, CareFusion US). Measurements were performed according to American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society (ATS/ERS) recommendations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>PEF was recorded in liter/minute (l/min) by using spirometry (Spiro USB, CareFusion US). Measurements were performed according to American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society (ATS/ERS) recommendations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline FVC%, FEV1%, FEF25-75%, PEF% at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>FVC%, FEV1%, FEF25-75% and PEF% were recorded as the percentage of predicted values.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Respiratory Muscle Strength at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal inspiratory and expiratory mouth pressures (MIP and MEP) were measured with a portable mouth pressure meter (MicroRPM, Micro Medical United Kingdom), using the ATS/ERS recommendations. The highest value from three attempts was recorded in centimeter water (cmH2O).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline MIP% and MEP% at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>MIP% and MEP% were recorded as the percentage of predicted values according to age and gender, as described by Black and Hyatt.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Nitric Oxide Level at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Fractional Exhaled Nitric Oxide (FeNO) was measured according to ATS/ERS recommendations with a hand-held, portable device (NObreath, Bedfont, UK). After inhaling the ambient air for 2-3 seconds until the total lung capacity, the patient is asked to exhale into the device for more than 6 seconds at constant flow rate (50 milliliter/second) without holding breath. The mean of two technically acceptable values within 10% was recorded in parts per billion (ppb) and maximum six attempts were performed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Exercise Capacity at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Exercise capacity was measured with the 6 Minute Walk Test (6MWT) according to the ATS guidelines. The 6 minutes wallking distance (6MWD) was recorded in meters. Higher scores indicate a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline 6MWD% at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>6MWD% was recorded as the percentage of predicted distances. Higher scores indicate a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Change of Perceived Dyspnea and Change of Exertion at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived dyspnea and exertion were measured before and immediately after 6MWT with modified Borg scale ranging from 0 to 10. Higher scores indicate a worse outcome. Change of perceived dyspnea and change of perceived exertion were recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Change of Peripheral Oxygen Saturation (SpO2) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>SpO2 (%) was measured before and immediately after 6MWT by using pulse oximeter. Change of SpO2 was recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Change of Blood Pressure at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic and diastolic blood pressures were measured before and immediately after 6MWT with sphygmomanometer. Change of systolic blood pressure and change of diastolic blood pressure were recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Change of Heart Rate at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate was measured before and immediately after 6MWT with sphygmomanometer and pulse oximeter. Change of heart rate was recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQoL) at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The emPHasis-10 including 10 items, each on a scale of 0-5 was used for assessment of HRQoL. The scores of the questionnaire range from 0 (best health) to 50 (worst health).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Functional Mobility at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Five-Repetition Sit to Stand Test (5STS) was used to assess functional mobility. 5STS measures the time taken to complete 5 quick chair sit to stand to sit cycles with arms folded across the chest. The average time taken was recorded in seconds. Lower duration reflects a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Hand grip strength at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Hand grip strength was measured with a hand-held dynamometer bilaterally. Three measurements on both hands were performed and the highest values were recorded in kilograms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Physical Activity Level at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The physical activity level was assessed with the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) short form, a 7-item self report measure of physical activity. Scores for moderate and vigorous activities, and walking were calculated as metabolic equivalents-minutes per week, as well as sitting time was calculated as minutes per day. The total score ranges from 0 to the greatest durations and frequencies that the patients can spent on physical activity. The total score was calculated as sum of moderate and vigorous activities, and walking. Higher scores indicate a better level of physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Psychosocial Status at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of anxiety and depression were assessed with Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale which includes 14 questions. Scores for both anxiety and depression range from 0 to 21 and higher scores indicate greater emotional distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Cognitive Function at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) including 11 questions was used to assess cognitive function. MMSE range from 0 to 30 and a higher score represents a better cognition level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Sleep Quality at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep Quality was assessed with the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) which includes 7 components and 19 items questioning sleep quality over the past month. Each component score range from 0 to 3, thus a global score ranges from 0 to 21. A higher score indicates a poorer sleep quality and a global score greater than 5 indicates poor sleep quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Chest Wall Mobility at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Chest wall mobility was assessed circumferentially with a cloth tape measure. Axillary excursion was measured at the level of T5 spinous process and the third intercostal space at the midclavicular line. Xiphoid excursion was measured at the level of the 10th thoracic spinous process and the xiphoid process. Subcostal excursion was measured at the level of the lateral lower edge of the tenth costae. Amount of chest wall mobility was measured as the circumference difference between forced inspiration and forced expiration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Level of Dyspnea at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The Modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) Dyspnea Scale ranging from 0 to 4 was used to measure dyspnea during different levels of activity. Grade 0 represents no breathlessness and Grade 4 represents severe breathlessness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Functional Impairment at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>New York Heart Association (NYHA) / World Health Organization (WHO) Functional Class were assessed in all patients according to their perceptions of dyspnea and fatigue at different levels of physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Complementary Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Complementary therapy group consisted of 16 pulmonary hypertension (PH) patients. Three different pranayama yoga breathing exercises were applied after osteopathic manipulative treatment (OMT). This complementary therapy model was applied 2 times a week for a period of 8 weeks with a total of 16 training sessions. There remained a 3-workday gap between two sessions and every session lasted 45-60 minutes. The patients trained on specific days of the week and specific time of day throughout the study protocol. Patients in this group were thought about pathophysiology of PH, benefits of physical activity, airway clearance, oxygen therapy, and importance of proper nutrition, adequate sleep, effective breathing after baseline assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>OMT group consisted of 16 PH patients. Six different OMT techniques were applied 2 times a week for a period of 8 weeks with a total of 16 sessions. The same osteopathic manipulative treatment techniques applied to complementary therapy group were used for this study group. There remained a 3-workday gap between two sessions and every session lasts 30-40 minutes. The patients visited the clinic on specific days of the week and specific time of day throughout the study protocol. Patients in this group were thought about pathophysiology of PH, benefits of physical activity, airway clearance, oxygen therapy, and importance of proper nutrition, adequate sleep, effective breathing after baseline assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group also consisted of 16 PH patients and serves as the controls. No interventions were applied for the patients in this group. Similar with the patients in other two groups, pharmacological treatment of the patients in this group continued and they were advised for using their medication properly, Patients in this group were also thought about pathophysiology of PH, benefits of physical activity, airway clearance, oxygen therapy, and importance of proper nutrition, adequate sleep, effective breathing after baseline assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators applied six different OMT techniques including rib raising, abdominal diaphragm release, suboccipital decompression, mobilisation of 1st rib, mobilisation of mediastinum and plevrovertebral ligament release. Rib raising is used to increase the mobility of the rib cage and to reduce vasoconstriction by regulating sympathetic tone. Abdominal diaphragm release is used to increase diaphragm movement. Suboccipital decompression involves traction of the base of the skull. We aim to improve respiration with mobilisation of the 1st rib which is associated with sternum, sympathetic truncus and important vascular structures. One of the supporting ligaments of Sibson's fascia which resists intrathoracic pressure changes during respiration is pleurovertebral ligament. Finally, the goal of mobilisation of mediastinum is to increase the mobility of the rib cage by providing relaxation in the tension of the facial tissues.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Complementary Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pranayama</intervention_name>
    <description>Nadi Shodhana Pranayama (Alternate Nostril Breathing), Ujjayi Pranayama and Bhramari Pranayama were used for the study. Nadi Shodhana is one of the most common yoga breathing exercises and involves breathing through one nostril while closing the other one. The patients performed 2 sets of 7 breathing cycles with a resting time of 1 minute between the sets. Ujjayi Pranayama involves soft contraction of laryngeal muscles and the partial closure of the glottis. The patients performed 1 set of 10 breathing cycles per session with an inspiration:expiration phase as 1:2. Bhramari Pranayama includes a nasal humming sound during exhalation to create slight vibrations on the laryngeal walls, and the inner walls of the nostrils. The patients applied 1 set of 10 breathing cycles per session with a respiration rate of 3-4/min.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Complementary Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pulmonary hypertension patients that are clinically and hemodynamically stable

          -  Resting mean pulmonary arterial pressure ≥ 25 millimeter of mercury (mmHg) during a
             right heart catheterization or echocardiography

          -  Being over 18 years old

          -  Volunteering to participate in the study and to sign a written informed consent form

          -  Patients with New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional class I-II-III

          -  Stable pulmonary hypertension patients that takes medication at least 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute decompensated heart failure

          -  Unstable angina pectoris

          -  Recent thoracic or abdominal surgical procedures

          -  Using the immune system protection drugs as a result of organ or tissue transplants

          -  Severe neurological impairments causing autonomic dysfunction

          -  Severe cognitive impairment causing miscommunication

          -  Recent syncope

          -  Fractures

          -  Osteoporosis

          -  Tumors

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Baha Naci, PT, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rengin Demir, PT, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Serdar Kucukoglu, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa, Institute of Cardiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galiè N, Humbert M, Vachiery JL, Gibbs S, Lang I, Torbicki A, Simonneau G, Peacock A, Vonk Noordegraaf A, Beghetti M, Ghofrani A, Gomez Sanchez MA, Hansmann G, Klepetko W, Lancellotti P, Matucci M, McDonagh T, Pierard LA, Trindade PT, Zompatori M, Hoeper M; ESC Scientific Document Group . 2015 ESC/ERS Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension: The Joint Task Force for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Pulmonary Hypertension of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Respiratory Society (ERS): Endorsed by: Association for European Paediatric and Congenital Cardiology (AEPC), International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation (ISHLT). Eur Heart J. 2016 Jan 1;37(1):67-119. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehv317. Epub 2015 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26320113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McLaughlin VV, Archer SL, Badesch DB, Barst RJ, Farber HW, Lindner JR, Mathier MA, McGoon MD, Park MH, Rosenson RS, Rubin LJ, Tapson VF, Varga J, Harrington RA, Anderson JL, Bates ER, Bridges CR, Eisenberg MJ, Ferrari VA, Grines CL, Hlatky MA, Jacobs AK, Kaul S, Lichtenberg RC, Lindner JR, Moliterno DJ, Mukherjee D, Pohost GM, Rosenson RS, Schofield RS, Shubrooks SJ, Stein JH, Tracy CM, Weitz HH, Wesley DJ; ACCF/AHA. ACCF/AHA 2009 expert consensus document on pulmonary hypertension: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation Task Force on Expert Consensus Documents and the American Heart Association: developed in collaboration with the American College of Chest Physicians, American Thoracic Society, Inc., and the Pulmonary Hypertension Association. Circulation. 2009 Apr 28;119(16):2250-94. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.192230. Epub 2009 Mar 30. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2009 Jul 14;120(2):e13.</citation>
    <PMID>19332472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ayajiki K, Okamura T, Noda K, Toda N. Functional study on nitroxidergic nerve in isolated dog pulmonary arteries and veins. Jpn J Pharmacol. 2002 Jun;89(2):197-200.</citation>
    <PMID>12120765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Benchmarks for training in traditional/complementary and alternative medicine: benchmarks for training in osteopathy. Geneva: WHO Press; 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller MR, Hankinson J, Brusasco V, Burgos F, Casaburi R, Coates A, Crapo R, Enright P, van der Grinten CP, Gustafsson P, Jensen R, Johnson DC, MacIntyre N, McKay R, Navajas D, Pedersen OF, Pellegrino R, Viegi G, Wanger J; ATS/ERS Task Force. Standardisation of spirometry. Eur Respir J. 2005 Aug;26(2):319-38.</citation>
    <PMID>16055882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society. ATS/ERS Statement on respiratory muscle testing. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002 Aug 15;166(4):518-624.</citation>
    <PMID>12186831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Black LF, Hyatt RE. Maximal respiratory pressures: normal values and relationship to age and sex. Am Rev Respir Dis. 1969 May;99(5):696-702.</citation>
    <PMID>5772056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Thoracic Society; European Respiratory Society. ATS/ERS recommendations for standardized procedures for the online and offline measurement of exhaled lower respiratory nitric oxide and nasal nitric oxide, 2005. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2005 Apr 15;171(8):912-30.</citation>
    <PMID>15817806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ATS Committee on Proficiency Standards for Clinical Pulmonary Function Laboratories. ATS statement: guidelines for the six-minute walk test. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002 Jul 1;166(1):111-7. Erratum in: Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2016 May 15;193(10):1185.</citation>
    <PMID>12091180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yorke J, Corris P, Gaine S, Gibbs JS, Kiely DG, Harries C, Pollock V, Armstrong I. emPHasis-10: development of a health-related quality of life measure in pulmonary hypertension. Eur Respir J. 2014 Apr;43(4):1106-13. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00127113. Epub 2013 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24232702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1983 Jun;67(6):361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>6880820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bockenhauer SE, Chen H, Julliard KN, Weedon J. Measuring thoracic excursion: reliability of the cloth tape measure technique. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2007 May;107(5):191-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17596587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Folstein MF, Folstein SE, McHugh PR. &quot;Mini-mental state&quot;. A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinician. J Psychiatr Res. 1975 Nov;12(3):189-98.</citation>
    <PMID>1202204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF 3rd, Monk TH, Berman SR, Kupfer DJ. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res. 1989 May;28(2):193-213.</citation>
    <PMID>2748771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Girgis RE, Champion HC, Diette GB, Johns RA, Permutt S, Sylvester JT. Decreased exhaled nitric oxide in pulmonary arterial hypertension: response to bosentan therapy. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2005 Aug 1;172(3):352-7. Epub 2005 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>15879413</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sun XG, Hansen JE, Oudiz RJ, Wasserman K. Pulmonary function in primary pulmonary hypertension. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 Mar 19;41(6):1028-35.</citation>
    <PMID>12651053</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Desai SA, Channick RN. Exercise in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension. J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. 2008 Jan-Feb;28(1):12-6. doi: 10.1097/01.HCR.0000311502.57022.73. Review. Erratum in: J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. 2008 Mar-Apr;28(2):table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>18277824</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kabitz HJ, Bremer HC, Schwoerer A, Sonntag F, Walterspacher S, Walker DJ, Ehlken N, Staehler G, Windisch W, Grünig E. The combination of exercise and respiratory training improves respiratory muscle function in pulmonary hypertension. Lung. 2014 Apr;192(2):321-8. doi: 10.1007/s00408-013-9542-9. Epub 2013 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24338088</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mereles D, Ehlken N, Kreuscher S, Ghofrani S, Hoeper MM, Halank M, Meyer FJ, Karger G, Buss J, Juenger J, Holzapfel N, Opitz C, Winkler J, Herth FF, Wilkens H, Katus HA, Olschewski H, Grünig E. Exercise and respiratory training improve exercise capacity and quality of life in patients with severe chronic pulmonary hypertension. Circulation. 2006 Oct 3;114(14):1482-9. Epub 2006 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>16982941</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yilmaz Yelvar GD, Çirak Y, Demir YP, Dalkilinç M, Bozkurt B. Immediate effect of manual therapy on respiratory functions and inspiratory muscle strength in patients with COPD. Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis. 2016 Jun 20;11:1353-7. doi: 10.2147/COPD.S107408. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27382271</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Curi ACC, Maior Alves AS, Silva JG. Cardiac autonomic response after cranial technique of the fourth ventricle (cv4) compression in systemic hypertensive subjects. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2018 Jul;22(3):666-672. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2017.11.013. Epub 2017 Dec 9.</citation>
    <PMID>30100295</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nayar HS, Mathur RM, Kumar RS. Effects of yogic exercises on human physical efficiency. Indian J Med Res. 1975 Oct;63(10):1369-76.</citation>
    <PMID>1222951</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Singh S, Gaurav V, Parkash V. Effects of a 6-week nadi-shodhana pranayama training on cardio-pulmonary parameters. J. Phys. Educ. Sport Manag. 2: 44-47, 2011.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garg S, Chandla SS. Effect of nadi shodhan pranayama on pulmonary functions. Int J Health Sci Res. 6: 192-196, 2016.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istanbul University-Cerrahpasa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Baha Naci</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Pranayama</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitric Oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiopulmonary</keyword>
  <keyword>Complementary Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

