<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04247880</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00009270</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U60OH009762-11</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04247880</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Use of Mentoring to Promote Well-being for Female SMART Members</brief_title>
  <official_title>Advancing Women in the Sheet Metal Workers' Trade: A Coordinated Mentoring Program to Promote Safety, Health, and Well-being.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Center for Construction Research and Training (CPWR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH/CDC)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women are highly underrepresented in the construction skilled trades. In addition to facing
      the industry's well-known physical risks, women are subjected to discrimination, harassment,
      and skills under-utilization. As a result, tradeswomen have increased risk for injury,
      stress-related health effects, and high attrition rates from apprenticeship programs, thus
      perpetuating their minority status. Mentoring is a well-established technique for learning
      technical and personal navigation skills in new or challenging social environments. The
      investigators propose development and dissemination of a mentorship program through local
      unions of the International Association of Sheet Metal, Air, Rail and Transportation Workers
      (SMART), and evaluating its success in reducing women's injury and work stress, while
      improving retention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Journey-level workers will be trained on effective mentoring techniques, and matched to
      approximately 100 women apprentices within their own local union. Mentees will be followed
      for two years within the mentorship program, with another 100 women apprentices in locals not
      receiving the mentorship training similarly followed as controls. The impact of participation
      in mentoring programs will be measured through apprentices' experience of stress, coping
      mechanisms, safety climate, and retention in the apprenticeship programs. Specifically, the
      investigators propose to:

      Aim 1: Develop a mentorship training program for journey-level sheet metal workers to assist
      women apprentices in navigating the challenges faced by women in trades

      Aim 2: Disseminate the training and assist locals in developing effective mentorship programs

      Aim 3: Evaluate the effectiveness of the mentoring programs specified in Aims 1 and 2

      Aim 4: Disseminate the best practices for supporting women apprentices in the skilled trades.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>4 year period</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of feelings of stress among the female workers from validated questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Job satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>4 year period</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of job satisfaction from validated questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Social support</measure>
    <time_frame>4 year period</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of social support both in and out of work from validated questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Work-related risks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 year period</time_frame>
    <description>Knowledge, awareness, and coping mechanisms for work-related risks from validated questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention in the trades</measure>
    <time_frame>4 year period</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of the number of women who remain in the trades</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Harassment, Non-Sexual</condition>
  <condition>Harassment, Sexual</condition>
  <condition>Bullying, Workplace</condition>
  <condition>Mental Stress</condition>
  <condition>Work-Related Condition</condition>
  <condition>Work-related Injury</condition>
  <condition>Work Related Stress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mentees</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm consists of apprentice-level, female-identifying construction workers who will receive active mentorship (the intervention) for two years from trained journey-level mentors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Apprentices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm consists of apprentice-level, female-identifying construction workers who will not receive mentorship.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mentoring program</intervention_name>
    <description>Apprentice-level female construction workers will be assigned to a mentor who has gone through a rigorous mentorship training. Participants will be asked to meet with a mentor at least 4 times/year in person to discuss the challenges of being a female in construction, learn coping mechanisms, and otherwise discuss the unique challenges of the job environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mentees</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All mentors must be journey-level sheet metal workers that are members of the SMART
             (International Association of Sheet Metal, Air, Rail, and Transportation Workers)
             Union. All mentees and control apprentices must be apprentice-level sheet metal
             workers that are members of the SMART Union, and identify as woman.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No exclusions will be made on the basis of sex, race, ethnicity, age, disability or
             religion for mentors, mentees, and control apprentices. No exclusions will be made on
             the basis of gender for mentors. For mentees and control apprentices, those that do
             not identify as a woman will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Mentors can be both male- and female-identifying. Mentees and control apprentices will be all female-identifying.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marissa G Baker, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marissa G Baker, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>206-616-4709</phone>
    <email>bakermg@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Noah S Seixas, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>206-685-7189</phone>
    <email>nseixas@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marissa Baker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Occupational Stress</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bullying</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

