<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04247451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BUN 143201941164</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04247451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diabetic Foot Surgery Patients: What is Their Metabolic Profile and Are Nutritional Goals Met</brief_title>
  <acronym>DIM-SUUM</acronym>
  <official_title>Diabetic Foot Surgery Patients: What is Their Metabolic Profile and Are Nutritional Goals Met</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective interventional follow-up of diabetic foot surgery patients, their
      metabolic/nutritional profile, and the nutritional adequacy in the perioperative setting.

      Primary objective: to establish the preoperative metabolic profile of diabetic patients
      scheduled for foot surgery and determine the postoperative nutritional status. The daily
      values of caloric intake compared to caloric need and protein intake compared to protein need
      will be evaluated as primary endpoint. [Actual daily caloric and protein intake is compared
      to the calculated need.] These values will each be presented as relative %.

      Wound healing is an anabolic process that requires ample access to nutrients. Insulin is
      considered the main anabolic hormone of the body, and regulates the metabolism of
      carbohydrates, fats and proteins. Diabetic patients lack this very hormone, and in addition
      are required to follow a strict dietary regime that further limits caloric and protein
      intake. Very little research had been done to evaluate the role of malnutrition in delayed
      wound healing.

      Overall: What is the metabolic/nutritional profile of a diabetes patient with foot wounds
      undergoing surgery? Is the intake of proteins and caloric adequate in the perioperative
      setting and are nutritional goals met? Is there a possibility for iatrogenic malnutrition?
      What kind of nutrition would possibly be useful to optimize intake?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes mellitus is an important risk factor for foot ulcers often leading to minor or even
      major amputations, all with functional impairment.

      The pathophysiology of diabetic foot wounds is multifactorial, and a combination of treatment
      modalities is required to accomplish wound healing. As such, infection control (by means of
      surgery as well as antibiotics), off-loading and revascularization all contribute to a
      successful outcome.

      Wound healing invariably requires some degree of tissue regeneration, which is an anabolic
      process that requires ample access to nutrients and energy. In spite of malnutrition being
      detrimental to wound healing, the nutritional status of the diabetic foot patient is rarely
      taken into account when devising up a treatment regimen. This is remarkable, as diabetic
      patients are prone to inadequate energy intake because of three important reasons.

      First, they lack insulin, which is considered the main anabolic hormone of the body. Insulin
      regulates the uptake, storage and conversion of several crucial nutrients, like
      carbohydrates, fats and proteins, and plays such a pivotal role in energy house holding that
      diabetes affects almost all cellular processes in the body. Second, diabetic patients are
      invariably put on a dietary regime in order to maintain strict glycemia control. This
      requires a patient to schedule meals at very regularly timed intervals, of consistent caloric
      quantity. In addition, dietary intake has to be adapted to prior or scheduled physical
      exercise. The primary objective of a diabetes diet being glycemia control may consequently
      mean that it falls short as an optimal regimen for wound healing.

      Third, diabetic foot patients that undergo surgery frequently deviate from their customary
      diet. Fasting is often mandatory for anesthesia, and is usually prolonged due to neuropathic
      gastroparesis. Antibiotics may interfere with gastro-intestinal uptake. Hypermetabolic stress
      due to infection or surgery may temporarily increase energy expenditures.

      Low-extremity ulcers are an important health issue, with an extended impact on patients and
      health. Nutrition as a therapeutic intervention is well established in several domains of
      medicine, such as the treatment of critically ill patients. A nutritional treatment can alter
      outcome, when performed in an individualised, patient-tailored setting.

      In a randomized prospective way, the investigator's research group proved patient relevant
      outcome changes when an adequate nutritional therapy was applied: newly diagnosed cancer
      patients experienced significant less unplanned hospital admissions and saw a decline in the
      need of dose reduction of their anticancer treatment, as well as a rise in survival. A
      similar success was seen in a prospective intervention in patients planned for cardiac
      surgery: a program of close clinical monitoring and interventions by the use of dietary
      modifications, oral supplements or enteral or parenteral nutrition (or a combination thereof)
      resulted in a better survival of female patients and a lowered infection rate in male and
      female CABG and valve surgery patients. There were less episodes of postoperative arrhythmia,
      and the pneumonia rate went down.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficiency of nutritional therapy: Dietary intake (food diary; in Kcal) compared to caloric need (indirect calorimetry; Kcal)</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of 3 weeks (perioperative period)</time_frame>
    <description>Actual daily caloric and protein intake compared to the calculated need. These values will each be presented as relative %.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caloric needs (indirect calorimetry; Kcal) in diabetic foot surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of 3 weeks (perioperative period)</time_frame>
    <description>resting energy expenditure measured by indirect calorimetry before and after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of choice for oral nutritional supplements, enteral nutrition and parenteral nutrition (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of 3 weeks (perioperative period)</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of nutritional possibilities by health care providers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot Ulcer</condition>
  <condition>Nutrition Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nutritional intake: these data will be evaluated daily during preoperative hospitalization, at home, and during the actual hospitalization, from surgical intervention to discharge. Before the follow-up consultation, patients will keep a food diary. The dieticians will calculate intake and need.
Metabolic data: body composition using BIA (Nutrilab Akern) and REE using indirect calorimetry (Cosmed Q NRG) will be analyzed in three timepoints: preoperative, postoperative and at follow-up consultation. This measurements take maximum ten minutes and do not cause discomfort to the participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metabolic profile and nutritional goals in diabetic foot surgery patients</intervention_name>
    <description>Nutritional intake: these data will be evaluated daily during preoperative hospitalization, at home, and during the actual hospitalization, from surgical intervention to discharge. Before the follow-up consultation, patients will keep a food diary. The dieticians will calculate intake and need.
Metabolic data: body composition using Bio electrical Impedance Analysis BIA (Nutrilab Akern) and Resting Energy Expenditure REE using indirect calorimetry (Cosmed Q NRG) will be analysed in three timepoints: preoperative, postoperative and at follow-up consultation. This measurements take maximum ten minutes and do not cause discomfort to the participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Age &gt; 18years

          -  under oral or insulin therapy for diabetes mellitus

          -  patient recruitment at the multidisciplinary at the diabetic wound clinic of the
             University Hospital Brussel

          -  scheduled for surgery, with an indication related to the wound(s).

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Presence of other metabolic diseases (inborn/acquired such as hyperthyroidism)

          -  Incapacity to undergo research investigations (relative CI to body composition
             measurement by Bio electrical impedance BIA: cardiac defibrillator)

          -  Limb- or life threatening disease

          -  Patient or relatives is/are unable to accurately record dietary intake
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elisabeth De Waele, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elisabeth De Waele, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+32 (0)2 477 51 76</phone>
    <email>Elisabeth.DeWaele@uzbrussel.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Godelieve Opdenacker, study nurse</last_name>
    <phone>+32 (0)2 477 51 76</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Brussel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabeth De Waele, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+32 (0)2 477 51 76</phone>
      <email>Elisabeth.DeWaele@uzbrussel.be</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elisabeth De Waele</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Clinics ICU</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nutrition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

