<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04240119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00046030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04240119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Angiogenic Markers in Cerebrovascular Disease (ANFIS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ANFIS</acronym>
  <official_title>Angiogenic Factors in Stroke (ANFIS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial atherosclerosis (ICAS) is the most common cause of stroke worldwide. It carries
      a worse prognosis than other stroke etiologies, with an annual rate of recurrent stroke and
      death of 15% despite intensive medical management, and as high as 35% in certain populations.
      Overall, treatment and prevention of stroke due to ICAS has been unsuccessful. While two
      recent clinical trials have shown modest improvement in the efficacy of intensive medical
      treatment, these trials were terminated early given the elevated rate of complications,
      stroke, and death in the interventional arms. In fact, intensive medical management appears
      to reduce the risk of embolism; however, medical management alone does not address the
      progression of intracranial arterial stenosis or the pathophysiologic components of
      hypoperfusion and poor collateral circulation.

      Levels and types of various angiogenic factors in the blood and tissues have been proposed to
      be predictive of patient outcome after ischemic stroke and treatment for stroke. This study
      therefore pursues a new paradigm to investigate responses to ICAS treatment from the
      perspective of cerebral collateral vessel generation and the role of angiogenic factors.
      Specifically, pro- and anti-angiogenic factors in patients with ICAS are evaluated at
      baseline and longitudinally in response to both medical and surgical treatment. For this we
      have developed methodologies for the isolation and measurement of these growth factors in
      plasma of patients with ICAS. These methodologies will enable us to obtain a detailed
      understanding of the variation and dynamic properties of local and circulating angiogenic
      factors over time in response to medical and surgical treatment, and their association to
      outcome phenotypes. This analysis is complemented by studies of angiographic development of
      neovascularization. If successful, this study will help to better understand the role of
      angiogenesis in ICAS and create a foundation from which to explore therapeutic treatments for
      ICAS which harness the natural processes of angiogenesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial atherosclerosis (ICAS) is the most common cause of stroke worldwide. It accounts
      for at least 10% of all strokes in the United States and as much as 67% in countries with
      predominantly Asian, Hispanic, and Black populations. ICAS carries a worse prognosis than
      other stroke etiologies, with an annual rate of recurrent stroke and death of 15% despite
      intensive medical management, and as high as 35% in certain populations. Recent randomized
      controlled clinical trials have shown that angioplasty with stenting and bypass surgery fail
      to improve outcomes in patients with ICAS.

      Overall treatment and prevention of stroke due to ICAS has been unsuccessful. The results of
      two recent clinical trials exploring interventions for the management of cerebrovascular
      occlusive disease—bypass surgery (Carotid Occlusion Surgery Study [COSS]) and angioplasty and
      stenting (SAMMPRIS)—have shown modest improvement in the efficacy of intensive medical
      treatment. However, both trials were terminated early given the elevated rate of
      complications, stroke, and death in the interventional arms. In the medical arms of COSS and
      SAMMPRIS, the rates of stroke and death at two years were 21% and 15%, respectively.
      Intensive medical management appears to reduce the risk of embolism; however, medical
      management alone does not address the progression of intracranial arterial stenosis or the
      pathophysiologic components of hypoperfusion and poor collateral circulation. Patients with
      prior stroke had an even higher rate of stroke, 35%.

      Levels and types of various angiogenic factors in the blood and tissues have been proposed to
      be predictive of patient outcome after ischemic stroke and treatment for stroke. This study
      therefore pursues a new paradigm to investigate responses to ICAS treatment from the
      perspective of cerebral collateral vessel generation and the role of angiogenic factors.
      Specifically, pro- and anti-angiogenic factors in patients with ICAS are evaluated at
      baseline and longitudinally in response to both medical and surgical treatment. For this we
      have developed methodologies for the isolation and measurement of these growth factors in
      plasma of patients with ICAS. These methodologies will enable us to obtain a detailed
      understanding of the variation and dynamic properties of local and circulating angiogenic
      factors over time in response to medical and surgical treatment, and their association to
      outcome phenotypes. This analysis is complemented by studies of angiographic development of
      neovascularization. If successful, this study will help to better understand the role of
      angiogenesis in ICAS and create a foundation from which to explore therapeutic treatments for
      ICAS which harness the natural processes of angiogenesis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2030</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurring cerebrovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma levels of angiogenic factors</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Transient Ischemic Attack</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Intracranial Arterial Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Moyamoya</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>According to current clinical care standards</intervention_name>
    <description>Enrolled subjects may be treated with medical management or surgically using indirect revascularization surgery.</description>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients will be recruited during hospitalizations or neurological and/or neurosurgical
        office visits at Cedars Sinai Medical Center.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  70% to 99% ICAS of a major intracranial artery diagnosed by angio, TCD, MRA, or CTA.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Intracranial tumor or vascular malformation.

          -  Any hemorrhagic infarct within 14 days before enrollment or any other intracranial
             hemorrhage (subarachnoid, subdural, or epidural) within 30 days.

          -  Intracranial arterial stenosis related to arterial dissection or any known infectious
             or vasculitic disease.

          -  Presence of any unequivocal cardiac sources of embolism.

          -  Major surgery within previous 30 days before enrollment or planned in the next 180
             days after enrollment,

          -  Severe neurologic deficit that renders the patient incapable of living independently.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nestor R Gonzalez, MD., MSCR</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nestor R. Gonzalez, MD, MSCR.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurosurgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemic Attack, Transient</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data may be shared in the future, but currently no specific plans exist.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

