<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04240093</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1906002463</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Junior Investigator Award</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>5P20GM125507-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04240093</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CoMBAT Opioid Use Disorder</brief_title>
  <acronym>CoMBAT OUD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot RCT of a Combined Medication and Behavioral Activation Treatment for People Living With Opioid Use Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Boston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rhode Island Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks primarily to test, in a two-arm randomized controlled trial (RCT), the
      feasibility, acceptability, and preliminary efficacy of CoMBAT OUD, an intervention that
      integrates Behavioral Activation (BA) and substance abuse and health navigation counseling
      for individuals who are receiving medications for opioid use disorder (i.e., methadone;
      suboxone) to help them improve engagement in care and opioid use treatment outcomes.
      Participants will be randomized 1:1 to two arms: (1) the CoMBAT intervention (2 sessions of
      substance abuse and health navigation counseling + 8 sessions of BA counseling); or the (3)
      the standard of care (SOC) comparison condition, including two equivalent substance abuse and
      health navigation counseling. Participants will be followed for 6 months post-randomization,
      with assessments at months 3 and 6.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Opioid use disorder (OUD) is a chronic, relapsing disease and a major source of morbidity and
      mortality in the United States. Medications for opioid use disorder (i.e., methadone;
      buprenorphine) have been shown to reduce opioid use in diverse populations; however,
      long-term use of these medications and engagement in care are often suboptimal. Depression
      has been shown to contribute to medication discontinuation and care disengagement. Behavioral
      activation (BA) therapy is an evidence-based, behavioral treatment that has been shown to be
      effective in treating comorbid depression and substance use in diverse populations with
      smoking, alcohol, stimulant, and poly-substance use disorder. BA utilizes therapeutic
      techniques that help patients gradually increase goal-directed, potentially rewarding and
      pleasurable activities while decreasing the intensity and frequency of adverse events and
      consequences in order to improve mood. Given that BA utilizes strategies that can support
      individuals in alleviating depression and build the capacity to navigate life challenges,
      pairing BA with medications for OUD could help to ensure continued engagement in care and
      improve OUD treatment outcomes.

      This study, therefore, seeks to determine the feasibility of study procedures, enhance
      participant acceptability, and demonstrate preliminary efficacy of the CoMBAT (Combined
      Medication and Behavioral Activation Treatment) intervention. We will enroll 80 individuals
      currently being treated with methadone or buprenorphine for OUD in a pilot randomized
      controlled trial (RCT) of the CoMBAT intervention. Prior to randomization, participants will
      receive 2 health navigation and standard substance abuse counseling sessions. Participants
      will then be equally randomized to either: 1) the 8-session CoMBAT intervention; or 2)
      standard of care. The primary outcome is engagement in care. Secondary outcomes include
      self-reported days of opioid use and opioid positive urinalysis. Intervention feasibility and
      acceptability will also be assessed. Participants will complete major assessment visits
      (survey and toxicology testing) at baseline and 3- and 6-months post-randomization. Patient
      medical records and pharmacy data will also be used to verify self-reported data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two-arm RTC, randomized 1:1 to two arms: (1) the CoMBAT intervention (behavioral activation and substance abuse/health navigation) counseling, which lasts ten sessions; and (2) the standard of care comparison condition, including two equivalent substance abuse/ health navigation counseling sessions.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Days of medication use (engagement in care)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 month, 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported change in the number of days of medication use, confirmed via medical and pharmacy records</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinic visits completed (engagement in care)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 month, 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported change in the number of office visits attended, confirmed via medical records</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days of opioid use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 month, 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported change in days of opioid use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid negative urine toxicology screens</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 month, 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Number of urine toxicology screens negative for opioids (not buprenorphine or methadone)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Medication-Assisted Treatment</condition>
  <condition>Medication Adherence</condition>
  <condition>Health Care Utilization</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental: Behavioral Activation (8 sessions) + Substance Abuse and Health Navigation Counseling (2 sessions) + Meds</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Substance Abuse and Health Navigation Counseling (2 sessions) + Meds</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral Activation (BA) Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>8 sessions of behavioral activation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Substance Abuse and Health Navigation Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>2 standard substance abuse and health navigation counseling</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medications for Opioid Use Disorder</intervention_name>
    <description>Medications for opioid use disorder (i.e., buprenorphine and methadone) as prescribed by a community provider (not provided as part of the study).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or older

          -  Initiated medications for opioid use &gt;= 30 day prior to screening

          -  Current depressive symptoms

          -  Plans to stay in greater Providence area for at least 6-months

          -  Able to read, speak, and understand English

          -  Willing and able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not plan to continue taking medications for opioid use disorder

          -  Unable to provide informed consent due to severe mental or physical illness, or
             substance intoxication at the time of interview

          -  Discovery of active suicidal ideation at the time of interview

          -  In the second or third trimester of pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaclyn W Hughto, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brown University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jaclyn W Hughto, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>401-863-6580</phone>
    <email>jaclyn_hughto@brown.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jaclyn W Hughto, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>401-863-6580</phone>
      <email>jaclyn_hughto@brown.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jaclyn W Hughto, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fresh-research.com</url>
    <description>FRESH Research Lab</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Raw data for additional analysis will be available to outside individuals through contacting the Multiple Principal Investigators (MPI) at two different times. The first will be after all of the baseline data is collected. We will institute a concept plan process where internal study staff first have the availability to write papers or give presentations on particular topics. After this, if outside individuals wish to analyze data, we will welcome this collaboration. A similar process will happen for outcome data; however, this will not be possible until the publication and release of the outcome paper(s). The PI will allow access for pooled data analysis projects, or projects for outside individuals. Information regarding the availability of data for analysis will be listed on the PIs' program's web page. Contact information for the PI will be listed in all manuscripts and publications as another means to access data.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The first time point at which outside investigators may request IPD will be after all of the baseline data has been collected and internal study staff have been offered the availability to write papers or give presentations on particular topics. A similar process will take place for outcome data following publication and release of the outcome paper(s). The PI will store the data indefinitely.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Raw data for additional analysis will be available to outside individuals through contacting the Principal Investigator (PI). We will institute a concept plan process where internal study staff first have the availability to write papers or give presentations on particular topics. After this, if outside individuals wish to analyze data, we will welcome this collaboration. The PI will allow access for pooled data analysis projects, or projects for outside individuals. Information regarding the availability of data for analysis will be listed on the PI's program's web page (see below).</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://www.fresh-research.com</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

