<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04240301</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019P003567</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04240301</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Perioperative Recommendations for Medication Safety</brief_title>
  <official_title>Global PRoMiSe (Perioperative Recommendations for Medication Safety): A Consensus-Based, Generalizable Approach</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karen C. Nanji,M.D.,M.P.H.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>World Federation of Societies of Anesthesiologists</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aga Khan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Auckland, New Zealand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the proposed research is to create and disseminate expert-based
      recommendations for perioperative medication safety that are tailored to country income
      level, using the World Bank's four country income groups: high, upper-middle, lower-middle,
      and low income. The specific aims of the research are to: 1) Develop consensus-based
      perioperative medication safety recommendations, 2) Prioritize the recommendations by their
      level of clinical importance for implementation in high, upper-middle, lower-middle and low
      income countries, and disseminate the recommendations; and 3) Evaluate the initial adoption
      of the recommendations in each country income group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of the proposed research is to create and disseminate expert-based
      recommendations for perioperative medication safety that are tailored to country income
      level, using the World Bank's four country income groups: high, upper-middle, lower-middle,
      and low income. The proposed project will include the entire medication use process
      (ordering, dispensing, preparing, administering, documenting and monitoring). The specific
      aims of the research are to:

        1. Develop consensus-based perioperative medication safety recommendations. Approach: This
           study will use the extensively studied RAND-UCLA Delphi Method to achieve consensus,
           with an expert panel consisting of anesthesiologists, surgeons, nurses and medication
           safety experts from each of the World Bank's four country income groups.

        2. Prioritize the recommendations by their level of clinical importance for implementation
           in high, upper-middle, lower-middle and low income countries, and disseminate the
           recommendations. Approach: The expert panel members will rank each recommendation by its
           importance as a next step in improving medication safety in each country income group. A
           Condorcet ranking method will be used to combine individual rankings into a single list
           of recommendations ranked by the importance of implementation for each country income
           group. The investigators will then execute a comprehensive dissemination strategy.

        3. Evaluate the initial adoption of the recommendations in each country income group.
           Approach: The investigators will conduct qualitative, one-on-one, semi-structured
           interviews of the expert panel members, to evaluate their perceptions of initial
           adoption of the recommendations in each country income group. A grounded theory approach
           will be used to identify common themes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expert-based medication safety recommendations.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Four tiers of stepwise recommendations, corresponding to each of the World Bank's four country income groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Perioperative Medication Safety</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Our expert panel will consist of 120 members, 30 from each of the World Bank's four county
        country income groups: high, upper-middle, lower-middle, and low income. Expert panel
        members will be anesthesiologists, surgeons, operating room nurses, nurse anesthetists,
        pharmacists and patient safety experts.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Anesthesiologists, surgeons, operating room nurses, nurse anesthetists, pharmacists
             and patient safety experts

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen C. Nanji, M.D., M.P.H.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen C. Nanji, M.D., M.P.H.</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 724-8544</phone>
    <email>KNANJI@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.rand.org/content/dam/rand/pubs/monograph_reports/2011/MR1269.pdf</url>
    <description>The RAND/UCLA Appropriateness Method User's Manual</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merry AF, Webster CS, Hannam J, Mitchell SJ, Henderson R, Reid P, Edwards KE, Jardim A, Pak N, Cooper J, Hopley L, Frampton C, Short TG. Multimodal system designed to reduce errors in recording and administration of drugs in anaesthesia: prospective randomised clinical evaluation. BMJ. 2011 Sep 22;343:d5543. doi: 10.1136/bmj.d5543.</citation>
    <PMID>21940742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nanji KC, Patel A, Shaikh S, Seger DL, Bates DW. Evaluation of Perioperative Medication Errors and Adverse Drug Events. Anesthesiology. 2016 Jan;124(1):25-34. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000904.</citation>
    <PMID>26501385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Llewellyn RL, Gordon PC, Wheatcroft D, Lines D, Reed A, Butt AD, Lundgren AC, James MF. Drug administration errors: a prospective survey from three South African teaching hospitals. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2009 Jan;37(1):93-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19157353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orser BA, Chen RJ, Yee DA. Medication errors in anesthetic practice: a survey of 687 practitioners. Can J Anaesth. 2001 Feb;48(2):139-46.</citation>
    <PMID>11220422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shridhar Iyer U, Fah KK, Chong CK, Macachor J, Chia N. Survey of medication errors among anaesthetists in Singapore. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2011 Nov;39(6):1151-2.</citation>
    <PMID>22165377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Webster CS, Merry AF, Larsson L, McGrath KA, Weller J. The frequency and nature of drug administration error during anaesthesia. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2001 Oct;29(5):494-500.</citation>
    <PMID>11669430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wahr JA, Abernathy JH 3rd, Lazarra EH, Keebler JR, Wall MH, Lynch I, Wolfe R, Cooper RL. Medication safety in the operating room: literature and expert-based recommendations. Br J Anaesth. 2017 Jan;118(1):32-43. doi: 10.1093/bja/aew379. Epub 2016 Dec 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28039240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitaker D, Brattebø G, Trenkler S, Vanags I, Petrini F, Aykac Z, Longrois D, Loer SA, Gaszynski T, Sipylaite J, Copaciu E, Cerny V, Akeson J, Mellin-Olsen J, Abela C, Stecher A, Kozek-Langenecker S, Rätsep I; European Section and Board of Anaesthesiology of the UEMS. The European Board of Anaesthesiology recommendations for safe medication practice: First update. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2017 Jan;34(1):4-7.</citation>
    <PMID>27548778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Utley M, Gallivan S, Mills M, Mason M, Hargraves C. A consensus process for identifying a prioritised list of study questions. Health Care Manag Sci. 2007 Feb;10(1):105-10.</citation>
    <PMID>17323658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karen C. Nanji,M.D.,M.P.H.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Anesthesia at Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>medication safety</keyword>
  <keyword>anesthesiology</keyword>
  <keyword>perioperative</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No IPD will be available to other researchers. Aggregate data post-analysis may be shared with collaborators at other institutions.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

