<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04248062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10650</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04248062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient and Observer Reported Outcome Measurements in Inborn Errors of Metabolism</brief_title>
  <acronym>MetaPROM</acronym>
  <official_title>Identification and Validation of Relevant Patient and Observer Reported Outcome Measurements in Inborn Errors of Metabolism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Children's Hospital, Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Children's Hospital, Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      lnborn errors of metabolism (IEM) are a heterogeneous group of rare, sometimes debilitating
      or even fatal diseases . In IEM, both definition and assessment of meaningful outcome
      parameters is often extremely difficult resulting in a limited body of evidence. Limited
      evidence results in weak recommendations which are perceived as unbinding and thus sustains
      heterogeneous study designs, choice of outcomes and interventions again producing non-uniform
      data.

      The goal of the current study is to identify and select reliable instruments, that measure
      patients' and their parents' perception about relevant (social, emotional, cognitive and
      physical) aspects in their lives. This set of instruments will secure the comparability of
      future research findings. Furthermore this instruments will improve the screening of
      paediatric IEM patients regarding their need for additional (psychosocial or consultative)
      support in daily hospital routine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Background

           Limitations to the body of evidence on effects of interventions on important outcome
           parameters in IEM and thus to evidence-based recommendations or guidelines are manifold.
           Due to the rarity of each disease, knowledge about the natural history may be poor. Most
           IEM are clinically heterogeneous with severity of the disease determined by mutation
           type, residual enzyme activity and additional, often unidentified factors.
           Consecutively, studies in IEM are variable regarding outcome parameters, treatment
           regimens and targets. Often the evidence on meaningful outcomes is scarce because only
           small subgroups of studies address them in a structured and standardized manner. In IEM,
           there is a long-standing preference for biochemical outcome parameters, such as for
           example phenylalanine (Phe) concentrations in phenylketonuria or total homocysteine
           levels in patients with remethylation disorders. However, even these at first glance
           objective outcome parameters have their drawbacks: Phe targets differ significantly
           between countries and for the remethylation disorders there is no general agreement on
           precise target ranges for total homocysteine. Due to these circumstances, studies set
           different targets. Moreover, for same IEM no meaningful biochemical parameters are even
           available (e.g. Pompe disease). More and more Patient-reported outcome measures are
           recognized as valid additional, complementary parameters for evaluating pharmacological,
           dietary or disease-management interventions in chronic diseases. PROMs are directly
           reported by the patient (and their parents). PROMs can be used as single measurements to
           assess the patient's current situation or to report changes from a previous measure
           (e.g. following an Intervention). In contrast to the well-established parameters such as
           biochemical markers or disease-related mortality, PROMs allow direct insight into
           experience and performance of a patient and / or his caregivers in everyday life.
           Furthermore, use of PROMs in the clinical setting improves survival rates as well as
           patients' satisfaction with care, disease management as well as health-related quality
           of life (HrQoL).

        2. Current study

      In the current study the relevance of patient reported outcomes (PROs) for paediatric IEM
      patients and their families will be identified via Delphi method. 35 IEM experts (physicians,
      psychologists, nutritionists) and 30 patients and parents (anticipated 15 patients / 15
      parents) will fill out a survey including potentially relevant aspects of life in paediatric
      IEM (preselected by the interdisciplinary research team based on conducted focus groups in a
      previous study). Participants will be asked to rate every PRO regarding their relevance. A
      second survey, including only the important aspects (criteria based on Delphi manuals), will
      then be completed by the participants, to reach further deduction. Afterwards, a focus group
      with participants of the two surveys (6 metabolic experts / 3 parents / 3 patients &gt; 12
      years) will be held at the University Children's Hospital in Zurich, to discuss unclear
      ratings and additional PRO suggestions. For the remaining PROs, corresponding PROMs will be
      selected by the interdisciplinary research team based on the criteria of reliability, (face-,
      construct-) validity, quality of norm data, and frequency of usage in research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average importance of patient reported outcomes (PRO) after first Delphi survey</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes (for Delphi survey 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Average importance-rating of the PROs in the total sample (experts, patients, parents, patient representatives); 9-point Likert scale (1 = not at all important, 2 = very important); Sum-Score for each PRO divided by number of survey-participants; Consensus about the importance of a PRO achieved if at least 70% of the voting participants from each stakeholder group scored between 7 and 9</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average importance of patient reported outcomes (PRO) after second Delphi survey</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes (for Delphi survey 2)</time_frame>
    <description>Average importance-rating of the PROs in the total sample (experts, patients, parents, patient representatives); 9-point Likert scale (1 = not at all important, 2 = very important); Sum-Score for each PRO divided by number of survey-participants; Consensus about the importance of a PRO achieved if at least 70% of the voting participants from each stakeholder group scored between 7 and 9</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Inborn Errors of Metabolism</condition>
  <condition>Urea Cycle Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Maple Syrup Urine Disease</condition>
  <condition>Phenylketonurias</condition>
  <condition>Methylmalonicacidemia</condition>
  <condition>OTC Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Aminoacidopathy</condition>
  <condition>Patient Reported Outcome Measurements</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IEM experts</arm_group_label>
    <description>Heterogeneous group of health professionals (physicians, psychologists, nutritionists) working in the field of Inborn Errors of Metabolism (IEM)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paediatric IEM patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>IEM patients between 10 and 18 years</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of paediatric IEM patients and patient representatives</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parents of IEM patients (between 0 and 18 years)
Patient representatives</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Survey: 38 preselected patient and parent reported outcomes; rating scale: 9 point likert scale (1=not at all important - 9=very important)</description>
    <arm_group_label>IEM experts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Paediatric IEM patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parents of paediatric IEM patients and patient representatives</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The included groups (experts, patients, parents/patient representatives) were all not
        randomly chosen.

        Experts are recruited based on the criteria of profession, specialization, experience and
        location. A sample as balanced as possible is intended.

        Patients and their parents are recruited based on IEM disease, disease severity, Age and
        gender. A sample as balanced as possible is intended.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        *Statements above refer to IEM patients included in the study

        Inclusion Criteria (patients):

          -  Suffering from rare IEM (e.g. phenylketonuria, urea cycle disorders, maple syrup urine
             disease, methylmalonic acidemia)

          -  Ability to understand German language

          -  Cognitive ability to complete the basic survey items

        Inclusion Criteria (parents):

          -  Ability to understand German language

          -  Parents of a child suffering from IEM

        Inclusion Criteria (experts):

          -  More than 1 year of practical experience in the field of IEM

          -  Ability to understand written English

        Exclusion Criteria (patients):

          -  Older than 18 years

          -  Severe cognitive impairment (ability to complete the Survey not existent)

        Inclusion Criteria (parents):

          -  No ability to understand German language

        Exclusion Criteria (experts):

          -  Less than 1 year of practical experience in the field of IEM

          -  No ability to understand written English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martina Huemer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Children's Hospital, Zurich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Florin Bösch, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>0041 44 266 72 42</phone>
    <email>florin.boesch@kispi.uzh.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Martina Huemer, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>0041 44 266 75 93</phone>
    <email>martina.huemer@kispi.uzh.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Children's Hospital Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <zip>8032</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slade A, Isa F, Kyte D, Pankhurst T, Kerecuk L, Ferguson J, Lipkin G, Calvert M. Patient reported outcome measures in rare diseases: a narrative review. Orphanet J Rare Dis. 2018 Apr 23;13(1):61. doi: 10.1186/s13023-018-0810-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29688860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morel T, Cano SJ. Measuring what matters to rare disease patients - reflections on the work by the IRDiRC taskforce on patient-centered outcome measures. Orphanet J Rare Dis. 2017 Nov 2;12(1):171. doi: 10.1186/s13023-017-0718-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29096663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeltner NA, Landolt MA, Baumgartner MR, Lageder S, Quitmann J, Sommer R, Karall D, Mühlhausen C, Schlune A, Scholl-Bürgi S, Huemer M. Living with Intoxication-Type Inborn Errors of Metabolism: A Qualitative Analysis of Interviews with Paediatric Patients and Their Parents. JIMD Rep. 2017;31:1-9. doi: 10.1007/8904_2016_545. Epub 2016 Aug 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26983835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weldring T, Smith SM. Patient-Reported Outcomes (PROs) and Patient-Reported Outcome Measures (PROMs). Health Serv Insights. 2013 Aug 4;6:61-8. doi: 10.4137/HSI.S11093. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>25114561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phenylketonurias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urea Cycle Disorders, Inborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ornithine Carbamoyltransferase Deficiency Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Maple Syrup Urine Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolism, Inborn Errors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>In the scheduled publication, sharing of individual's voting data is not planned. The investigator's research interest refers to the average importance-voting regarding the preselected PROs.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

