<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04244058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-09020845</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04244058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Changes in Glutamatergic Neurotransmission of Severe TBI Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Pharmacologically-induced Changes in Excitatory Glutamatergic Neurotransmission of Severe TBI Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Studies in patients with disorders of consciousness (DOC) after severe brain injury implicate
      dysfunction of the anterior forebrain mesocircuit dysfunction a key underlying mechanism. The
      anterior forebrain metabolism in DOC is markedly downregulated across brain regions
      underpinning highly elaborated cognitive behaviors demonstrating a collapse of the level of
      synaptic background activity required for consistent goal-directed behavior and arousal
      regulation. Since dopamine levels are one of the primary controllers of the level of synaptic
      background activity within these forebrain structures and in regulating excitatory
      glutamatergic homeostasis, the investigators propose to investigate the specific contribution
      of presynaptic dopamine function in glutamatergic neurotransmission in posttraumatic DOC. The
      aim of the present study is to measure metabotropic glutamate receptors 5 occupancy in the
      main gutamatergic structures of the brain using
      (3-[18F]fluoro-5-(2-pyridinylethynyl)benzonitrile)-positron emission tomography (
      [18F]FPEB-PET) at rest and following a short pharmacological challenge with amantadine, an
      N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDA-R) antagonist, following L-DOPA, and amantadine + L-DOPA.
      Using this novel technique in DOC the investigators will characterize the relevance of a
      presynaptic deficiency to synthesize and/or release dopamine in the final regulation of
      excitatory interneurons of the anterior forebrain mesocircuit.

      It is unknown whether glutamatergic neurotransmission is affected across the population of
      subjects with DOC and, if this condition is secondary to a presynaptic dopaminergic failure
      of the anterior forebrain mesocircuit (i.e., down-regulation). Since the investigators
      previously identified the existence of a presynaptic dopaminergic deficit in these subjects
      due to a failure in the biosynthesis of dopamine, the investigators will evaluate if by
      providing the main biological substrate of the biosynthesis process (i.e., L-DOPA) the
      glutamatergic system regains homeostasis. The investigators therefore propose to investigate
      patients with posttraumatic DOC using [18F]FPEB-PET at rest and following short
      pharmacological challenges aimed at increasing glutamate and dopamine release.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Disorders of consciousness (DOC) produced by severe traumatic brain injuries (TBI) lack
      systematic evaluation and treatment strategies. Accumulating evidence points to the important
      and general role of impaired anterior forebrain mesocircuit function following multi-focal
      brain injuries that produce widespread deafferentation or neuronal cell loss (Schiff, 2010,
      Fridman et al. 2014). Among important sources of neuromodulation of this mesocircuit,
      alteration of dopaminergic innervations as a result of impaired biosynthesis of dopamine,
      neurotransmitter release, or its direct binding to dopamine receptors is implicated as having
      a critical contribution (Fridman and Schiff, 2014, Giacino et al. 2012). Parallel deficits of
      long-range excitatory glutamatergic neurotransmission likely play an equally crucial factor
      in all DOCs (Fridman and Schiff, 2014), as shown in non-human primates where a decrease of
      cortical glutamate levels occurs following dopamine depletion of substantia nigra (SN), and
      likely the ventral tegmentum (VT) (Fan et al., 2014). In a Phase 0 clinical trial exploring
      the pharmacodynamics underlying DOC (NINDS R21-NS093268) the investigators have shown that
      chronic TBI patients have an underlying presynaptic dopamine deficit in SN and VT that is not
      reversed by blocking only dopamine reuptake but is reversed by increasing dopamine synthesis
      using the dopamine precursor L-DOPA (Fridman et al., 2018)*. No prior studies, however, have
      provided direct measurements of glutamatergic deficits in DOC. Moreover, no systematic
      evaluation of glutamatergic neurotransmission has been carried in post-TBI DOC patients
      following dopaminergic modulation. This gap in knowledge is critically important as only one
      therapeutic intervention has shown modest effectiveness in subacute and chronic stage of TBI
      (Giacino et al., 2012) targeting glutamatergic neurotransmission without addressing impaired
      dopaminergic biosynthesis (Fridman et al., 2018)*.

      Here the investigators develop a novel and systematic assessment focusing on the role of the
      integrity of dopaminergic-glutamatergic systems in DOC. The investigators approach allows for
      evaluation of the integrity of glutamatergic innervations to key neuronal populations within
      the anterior forebrain mesocircuit. Using a similar approach (i.e., molecular neuroimaging
      and pharmacological challenges), the investigators have identified that patients with DOC
      exhibit: 1) a widespread presynaptic deficit affecting the resting dopamine synaptic
      activity; 2) a widespread presynaptic deficit affecting the induced dopamine release after
      pharmacological stimulation with amphetamine; and, 3) a partial postsynaptic deficit. The
      investigators long-term goal is to understand how neuromodulation of the anterior forebrain
      mesocircuit in DOC can be optimally manipulated for diagnosis and therapy. The investigators
      working hypothesis is that patients with DOC following TBI have alterations of glutamatergic
      function that can be partially reversed by dopamine replacement. The rationale that underlies
      the proposed research is that identification of a glutamatergic down-regulation in DOC as
      well as identification of the key regulator of this down-regulation (i.e., secondary to a
      deficit in the synthesis of dopamine) will allow the development of complementary diagnostic
      methods to predict patients' responses to specific therapies and, further improve the
      efficacy of neuropharmacological treatments to induce recovery of consciousness following
      severe TBI by rational polypharmacy. The investigators will develop quantitative measurements
      to test this hypothesis under the following Specific Aims:

      Specific Aim 1a. To identify and characterize impaired glutamatergic neurotransmission
      deficits in posttraumatic DOC.

      The investigators will assess in-vivo the availability of free metabotropic glutamate
      receptor 5 (mGluR5) at rest in patients with DOC and normal volunteers (NV) following
      N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDA-R) blockade with amantadine (AMT) utilizing
      [18F]FPEB-PET. The investigators working hypothesis is that patients with DOC will
      demonstrate:

      1) a glutamatergic deficit in anterior forebrain mesocircuit that is identified by a lower
      mGluR5 availability at rest; and 2) a failure to decrease mGluR5 occupancy following
      stimulation with AMT.

      Specific Aim 1b. To determine the reversibility of glutamatergic neurotransmission deficits
      in response to dopamine replacement in posttraumatic DOC.

      In DOC patients with a demonstrated glutamatergic deficit the investigators will assess the
      availability of free mGluR5 at rest and following NMDA-R blockade with AMT by means of
      [18F]FPEB-PET after premedication with L-DOPA. The investigators hypothesize that impaired
      glutamatergic neurotransmission in DOC can be partially restored by providing the dopamine
      precursor L-DOPA and thus supporting dopamine biosynthesis and subsequent release of a
      circuit- level inhibition at the level of the thalamus (mesocircuit hypothesis). Impaired
      biosynthesis is proposed to arise secondary to a posttraumatic enzyme tyrosine hydroxylase
      deficiency affecting the biosynthesis of dopamine.

      The investigators expected outcomes are anticipated to identify biomarkers to better define
      future therapeutic interventions in TBI patients with DOC. These results are expected to have
      an important positive impact because the identified biomarkers are highly likely to provide
      new therapeutic targets to induce recovery and therefore decrease disability and social cost
      in this large population of severe brain injured patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will be unaware of the medication used during the pharmacological challenge for the PET approach.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delta % changes in binding potential nondisplaceable (%ΔBPnd)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 2</time_frame>
    <description>BPnd induced by pharmacological challenges using AMT, L-DOPA and, AMT+L-DOPA (%ΔBPnd-AMT, L- DOPA and AMT+L-DOPA, respectively).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coma Recovery Scale Revised</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 2</time_frame>
    <description>The Coma Recovery Scale-Revised (CRS-R) is a standardized neurobehavioral assessment measure comprised of six subscales designed to assess arousal level, audition, language comprehension, visuoperceptual, motor function, oromotor capacity, expressive speech, and yes/no communication in patients with disorders of consciousness (DOC).
The scale comprises 23 items divided into 6 sub-scales. Maximal score is 23 and minimal score is 0, where 0 represents normality and 23 severe coma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Disorder of Consciousness</condition>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NMDA blocker</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Comprehensive functional analyses of dynamic [18F]FPEB-PET signal at rest will be carried out in normal volunteers and patients with DOC due to severe brain injury over a 24-month time period. In each study, we will first evaluate mGluR5 occupancy within the frontal cortex, anterior cingulate cortex, insula, striatum and thalamus. Then, a single dose of amantadine (AMT), a compound that blocks NMDA-R and increases glutamate levels at the synaptic cleft, will be given to each subject or patient and at the time corresponding to the peak of the dose, a second [18F]FPEB-PET will be acquired.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NMDA blocker + L-DOPA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All the patients with DOC that participate in ARM 1 will follow the same methodology of ARM 1: measurement of mGluR5 occupancy at rest and following NMDA-R blockade with AMT by means of [18F]FPEB-PET after premedication with L-DOPA introduced 1 hour prior each [18F]FPEB-PET acquisitions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amantadine + L-DOPA</intervention_name>
    <description>Amantadine 150 mg L-DOPA 375mg/carbidopa 75mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>NMDA blocker + L-DOPA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NMDA blocker</intervention_name>
    <description>NMDA blocker</description>
    <arm_group_label>NMDA blocker</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients Subjects with DOC

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 75 years of age, inclusive.

          -  Patients with disorder of consciousness (vegetative state, minimally conscious state,
             emerged from minimally conscious state) following severe brain injuries.

          -  Male or non-pregnant female.

          -  Medically stable.

          -  Informed consent from a Legally Authorized Representative.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Medical instability.

          -  Clinical history of moderate to severe hypertension or heart arrhythmia.

          -  Use of stimulants or dopamine blocker during the 24 hours previous to the study.

          -  Absence of a legally authorized representative (LAR) to sign the consent form.

        Normal Volunteers

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 75 years old, inclusive.

          -  Absence of cardiological, neurological and/or psychiatric diseases.

          -  Absence of familiar antecedents of sudden death of unknown reason.

          -  Male or non-pregnant female.

          -  Informed consent signed.

        Exclusion criteria:

        - Caffeine or alcohol intake in the last 24 hours previous to the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Esteban A Fridman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Cornell Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Esteban A Fridman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>347-881-6678</phone>
    <email>esf2005@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Esteban A Fridman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>347-881-6678</phone>
      <email>esf2005@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Esteban A Fridman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicholas D Schiff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonathan D Victor, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mozley D Paul, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://vivo.med.cornell.edu/display/cwid-esf2005</url>
    <description>Dr. Fridman's WCM webpage</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://casbi.weill.cornell.edu/</url>
    <description>Weill Cornell Medicine Consortium for the Advanced Study of Brain Injury (CASBI)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fridman EA, Osborne JR, Mozley PD, Victor JD, Schiff ND. Presynaptic dopamine deficit in minimally conscious state patients following traumatic brain injury. Brain. 2019 Jul 1;142(7):1887-1893. doi: 10.1093/brain/awz118.</citation>
    <PMID>31505542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fridman EA, Schiff ND. Neuromodulation of the conscious state following severe brain injuries. Curr Opin Neurobiol. 2014 Dec;29:172-7. doi: 10.1016/j.conb.2014.09.008. Epub 2014 Oct 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25285395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fridman EA, Beattie BJ, Broft A, Laureys S, Schiff ND. Regional cerebral metabolic patterns demonstrate the role of anterior forebrain mesocircuit dysfunction in the severely injured brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2014 Apr 29;111(17):6473-8. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1320969111. Epub 2014 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24733913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Positron emission tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>18F-FPEB</keyword>
  <keyword>NMDA</keyword>
  <keyword>Dopamine</keyword>
  <keyword>mGlu5-R</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular neuroimaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Traumatic brain injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Disorders of consciousness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Consciousness Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amantadine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The proposed research will involve a small sample with deficits secondary to traumatic brain injury (i.e., vegetative state and minimally conscious state). These rare disorders are associated with distinguishing features that even with the removal of all identifiers it would be difficult if not impossible to protect the identities of subjects. Thus, we will make the data and associated documentation available to users only under a data-sharing agreement that provides for: (1) a commitment to using the data only for research purposes and not to identify any individual participant; (2) a commitment to securing the data using appropriate computer technology; and (3) a commitment to destroying or returning the data after analyses are completed.
Data to be share will be 18F-FPEB raw data; CRS-R available data; anatomical data from the MRI.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available from publication date up to 3 years.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Only under a data-sharing agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

