<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04240470</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019141</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04240470</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endovascular Stroke Treatment Only (ESTO) Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endovascular Stroke Treatment Only (ESTO) Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aims of this study are to:

        1. Determine whether the endovascular treatment (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without
           using intravenous (IV) recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA) in acute
           ischemic stroke patients demonstrates &quot;promise&quot; or a lack thereof (&quot;futility&quot;) in
           deciding what would be the next phase III trial.

        2. Determine the proportion of subjects with slight or no disability (a modified Rankin
           score (mRS) of 0-2) at 3 months after receiving endovascular treatment (mechanical
           thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA and compare with historical controls who were
           treated with IV rt-PA to identify (or lack of) futility.

        3. Determine the proportion of subjects with improvement in the National Institutes of
           Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS) score of ≥8 points or achieving a score of 0-1 at 24 hours
           after the onset of stroke among subjects with acute ischemic stroke after receiving
           endovascular treatment (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA.

        4. Determine the proportion of subjects with angiographic recanalization on post procedure
           angiogram according to modified Thrombolysis in Cerebral Infarction (TICI) perfusion
           flow categories among subjects with acute ischemic stroke after receiving endovascular
           treatment (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA.

        5. Determine the proportion of subjects with treatment-related serious adverse events
           (SAEs) within 72 hours and development of symptomatic intracranial hemorrhage at 27
           ±3hrs post treatment among subjects with acute ischemic stroke after receiving
           endovascular treatment (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A phase II trial is proposed to address the question whether administration of intravenous
      (IV) recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA) in acute ischemic stroke patients who
      are candidates for endovascular treatment provides any additional value. The phase II trial
      will treat consecutive patients who are candidates for IV rt-PA and mechanical thrombectomy
      with just mechanical thrombectomy alone. Such trial will generate the necessary data for a
      definitive phase III trial. The trial is designed based on low rate of recanalization in
      patients with major arterial occlusion with IV rt-PA alone and no difference in rate of
      recanalization or distal embolization in patients who receive IV rt-PA and those who do not
      prior to mechanical thrombectomy. The rates of intracranial hemorrhage (ICH) and cost of
      hospitalization are higher when IV rt-PA is administered prior to mechanical thrombectomy.
      The trial will determine the proportion of patients with slight or no disability (a modified
      Rankin score (mRS) of 0-2) at 3 months after receiving endovascular treatment (mechanical
      thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA and compare with historical controls who were
      treated with IV rt-PA to determine futility.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be assigned to receive endovascular treatment for acute ischemic stroke (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Favorable Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) score of 0-2: 0, No symptoms at all; 1, No significant disability despite symptoms; able to carry out all usual duties and activities; 2, Slight disability; unable to carry out all previous activities, but able to look after own affairs without assistance. The modified Rankin Scale score ranges from 0, indicating no symptoms, to 6, indicating death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Angiographic Recanalization</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 6 hours of interventional treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Post procedure angiogram according to modified Thrombolysis in Cerebral Infarction perfusion flow categories:
0 = No perfusion. No antegrade flow beyond the point of occlusion.
= Perfusion past the initial obstruction but limited distal branch filling with little or slow distal perfusion
A = Perfusion of less than half of the vascular distribution of the occluded artery (eg, filling and perfusion through 1 M2 division)
2B = Perfusion of half or greater of the vascular distribution of the occluded artery (eg, filling and perfusion through 2 or more M2 divisions) 3 = Full perfusion with filling of all distal branches perfusion flow categories</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Neurological Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS) score of ≥8 points or achieving a score of 0-1 at 24 hours after the onset of stroke. NIHSS quantifies neurologic deficits in 11 categories. Level of consciousness, horizontal eye movement, visual fields, facial palsy, movement in each limb, sensation, language &amp; speech, and extinction or inattention on one side of the body are tested. Scores range from 0 to 42, with 0 indicating normal function and higher scores indicating greater deficit severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Status Using Standardized EQ-5D-3L (EuroQol Five Dimension, Three-Level) Questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D-3L questionnaire consists of 5 questions in 5 different domains and allows for responses from 1 (the best outcome) to 3 (the worst outcome) in each of five categories (mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression). Total scores range from 5 to 15, with lower scores indicating better quality of life and a higher score indicating a worse quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Status Using EQ VAS (EuroQol Visual Analog Scale) Scores.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>EuroQol outcome measurements is a printed 20 cm visual analogue scale (EQ VAS) that appears somewhat like a thermometer, on which a score from 0 (worst imaginable health state or death) to 100 (best imaginable health state) is marked by the patient (or, when necessary, their proxy) with the scale in view.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-Related Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 72 hours of interventional treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Assessement by the investigators for all patients</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic intracranial hemorrhage</measure>
    <time_frame>24 ± 3hrs post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Any hematoma within ischemic field with some mild space occupying effect but involving ≤ 30% of the infarcted area, hematoma within ischemic field with space-occupying effect involving &gt;30% of the infarcted area, any intraparenchymal hemorrhage remote from the ischemic field, subarachnoid hemorrhage, or intraventricular hemorrhage associated with a 4 points or more worsening on the NIHSS within 24 hrs</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Thrombectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive endovascular treatment (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thrombectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive endovascular treatment (mechanical thrombectomy) alone without using IV rt-PA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thrombectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Age: 18 through 90 years (i.e., candidates must have had their 18th birthday, but
             not had their 91st birthday).

               -  Symptom onset within 4.5 hours of onset of stroke symptoms. Time of onset is
                  defined as the last time when the patient was witnessed to be at baseline (i.e.,
                  subjects who have stroke symptoms upon awakening will be considered to have their
                  onset at beginning of sleep).

               -  An NIHSS ≥ 6 at the time of evaluation. Thrombolysis in Cerebral Infarction
                  (TICI) 0-1 flow in the intracranial internal carotid artery, M1 or M2 segment of
                  the middle cerebral artery (MCA), or carotid terminus confirmed by Computed
                  Tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance (MR) angiography that is accessible to the
                  stent retriever or suction thrombectomy catheter.

               -  The procedure can be initiated according to guidelines of AHA/ASA which state
                  that the treatment should be initiated (groin puncture) within 6 hours of symptom
                  onset.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical Exclusion Criteria

               -  History of stroke in the past 3 months.

               -  Previous intracranial hemorrhage, intracranial neoplasm, subarachnoid hemorrhage,
                  or ruptured brain arteriovenous malformation.

               -  Clinical presentation suggests a subarachnoid hemorrhage, even if initial CT scan
                  is normal.

               -  Severe hypertension at time of treatment; systolic blood pressure &gt; 185 or
                  diastolic &gt; 110 mm Hg that cannot be corrected prior to treatment.

               -  Presumed septic embolus.

               -  Major surgery within the previous 14 days.

               -  Recent (within 90 days) severe head trauma or head trauma with loss of
                  consciousness.

               -  Gastrointestinal malignancy or gastrointestinal hemorrhage within 21 days.

               -  Known hereditary or acquired hemorrhagic diathesis, coagulation factor
                  deficiency; or oral anticoagulant therapy with International Normalized Ratio
                  (INR) &gt; 1.7 or institutionally equivalent prothrombin time or platelets count
                  &lt;100,000 per microliter.

               -  Women of childbearing potential who are known to be pregnant and/or lactating or
                  who have positive pregnancy tests on admission.

               -  Patients with renal failure that require hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis.

               -  Low molecular weight heparins (such as Dalteparin, Enoxaparin, Tinzaparin,
                  Fondaparinux) as deep vein thrombosis (DVT) prophylaxis or in full dose within
                  the last 24 hours from screening unless anti-activated factor X (anti-factor Xa)
                  assay less than 200% of control value.

               -  Patients who have received heparin within 48 hours must have a normal partial
                  thromboplastin time (PTT) to be eligible.

               -  Patients who have received heparin or a direct thrombin inhibitor (Angiomax,
                  Argatroban, Refludan) must have a normal PTT to be eligible.

               -  Patients on dabigatran etexilate mesylate (Pradaxa), rivaroxaban (Xarelto),
                  apixaban (Eliquis), and edoxaban (Savaysa) may be considered after 48 hours after
                  last intake of medication in patients with normal renal function (CrCl &gt; 60
                  mL/minute). If moderate renal impairment, CrCl of 30-59 mL/minute, last dose
                  should be 72 hours before procedure and 96 hours in severe renal impaired
                  patients (CrCl of 15-29 mL/minute). The time interval between the last dose
                  administration and the neurointerventional procedure appears to be the most
                  reliable criterion for assessing the risk of bleeding events. Patients in whom
                  time of last dose ingestion is unknown or within last 48 hours, can be included
                  under following circumstances: normal PTT for dabigatran, normal prothrombin time
                  for rivaroxaban, or anti-activated factor X (anti-factor Xa) assay rivaroxaban
                  (Xarelto), apixaban (Eliquis), or edoxaban (Savaysa) less than 200% of control
                  value.

               -  Subjects with an arterial puncture at a non-compressible site or a lumbar
                  puncture in the previous 7 days.

               -  Patients with a seizure at onset of stroke.

               -  Patients with a pre-existing neurological or psychiatric disease that would
                  confound the neurological or functional evaluations.

               -  Other serious, advanced, or terminal illness.

               -  Current participation in another research drug treatment protocol (patient cannot
                  start another experimental agent until after 90 days).

        Informed consent is not or cannot be obtained. For example, obtunded patients are not
        automatically excluded from the study. However, if the next of kin or legal guardian (i.e.,
        the individual legally empowered in the state where the consent is obtained) cannot provide
        consent, randomization and entry into the study could not proceed.

        CT Scan Exclusion Criteria

          -  High density lesion consistent with hemorrhage of any degree.

          -  Significant mass effect with midline shift.

          -  Large (more than 1/3 of the middle cerebral artery) regions of clear hypodensity on
             the baseline CT scan or ASPECTS of &lt; 4.

          -  Sulcal effacement and / or loss of grey-white differentiation alone are not
             contraindications for treatment.

        CT Angiographic Exclusion Criteria

          -  Angiographic evidence of carotid dissection or complete cervical carotid occlusion.

          -  Arterial tortuosity, calcification, pre-existing stent, and/or stenosis, which would
             prevent the thrombectomy device from reaching the target vessel and/or preclude safe
             recovery of the endovascular devices.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adnan Qureshi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adnan R Qureshi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5738828668</phone>
    <email>qureshiai@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Iryna Lobanova</last_name>
    <phone>8039990400</phone>
    <email>lobanovai@health.missouri.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adnan Qureshi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>endovascular treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>recombinant tissue plasminogen activator</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical thrombectomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

