<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04248270</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201802151A0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04248270</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Noval Tau Tracer in Young Onset Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Noval Tau Tracer ([18F]PM-PBB3) in Young Onset Dementia: Clinical and Neuroimaging Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dementia is a clinical syndrome which characterized by progressive cognitive impairment,
      behavior disturbance and dysfunction of daily activity. In aging population, Alzheimer's
      dementia (AD) is the most common late onset dementia which occupied about 50-75%, the
      vascular dementia, frontotemporal lobardegeneration (FTLD) and corticobasal syndrome is
      followed. On the other hand, the young onset dementia (YOD), which represents the onset of
      dementia before65 years old, is only about 1/10 to 1/100 proportion of late onset dementia.
      The YOD is different from late onset dementia in the proportion of degenerative subtype (e.g.
      the FTLD is more frequent than AD). Besides, frequent atypical presentation of clinical
      syndrome in the YOD which characterize the different variant of AD made the early accurate
      diagnosis of AD is more difficult. Currently, there is no available data to describe the
      proportion of subtype in YOD in Taiwan. In AD dementia, two important biomarkers are amylod
      plaque made by ß-amyloid protein and neurofibrillary tangle made by phosphorylation tau
      protein. In the past, they only can be seen under the microscope findings at autopsy study.
      Recently, the new amyloid tracer and tau tracer had been developed and could evaluate the
      deposition of amyloid and tau protein in human brain. These progresses had substantially
      improved the accurate diagnosis of degenerative dementia. A noval tau tracer [ 18F]PM-PBB3,
      which had substantially improved the off-target binding and more clear background in human
      brain than previous tau tracer. In current project, investigator will aim to consecutive
      collect 50 YOD due to the neurodegeneration in 3 years using the NIA-AA research framework
      system(ATN system) to achieve accurate diagnosis of the dementia subtype by the detail
      clinical neurology study, neuropsychological examination, amyloid positron emission
      tomography (PET) and tau PET study. In the first year, investigator will perform feasibility
      study to explore the topographical tau distribution in different subtype of YOD. In the next
      2 years, investigator will perform a large scale study in a group of YOD to understand the
      amyloid and tau deposition and their association with clinical parameters. From current
      project, investigator could understand the tau deposition in different YOD subtype.
      Investigator also could understand the correlation between clinical phenotype and molecular
      pathology. Investigator will use a mathematic model to construct the model of diffusion
      kurtosis imaging from brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and relate the white matter
      integrity with amyloid and tau PET imaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 17, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>understand the proportion of subtype in YOD</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>investigator would be able to understand the proportion of subtype in YOD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>understand the mean tau deposition in different region of interest from subtype of YOD</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>investigator will perform image analysis to understand tau deposition in different subtype of YOD based on 18F-PM-PBB3 tau tracer image. The mean intensity from selected region of interest will be recorded for different group comparison.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>understand the mean tau intensity in different region of interest and find correlation with cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>investigator will perform association study to explore clinical measurements such as cognition and demographic data associate with tau intensity from different region of interest</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The relationship between image and AD disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>To evaluate the relationship between F-18-PMPBB3 PET image uptake pattern and AD disease classifications.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-PM-PBB3</intervention_name>
    <description>All scans will be acquired in pairs of 18F-florbetapir(18F-AV45) and/or18F-PM-PBB3 PET scans (if patient select), performed on separate days, and at least 2 days apart, with either scan performed first. The 18F-florbetapir and 18F-PM-PBB3 protocol will entail the inon of 5±2mCi of tracer followed by an uptake phase of 50 min during which time the state of the subject is not important. After 40 minutes, subjects will be positioned and 4 x 5 min frames of emission data will be collected right at 50 min after tracer injection. PET/MRI scans will precede this acquisition with a MRI scan for attenuation correction; PET-only scanners will perform a transmission scan following the emission scan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>The relationship between image and AD disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria Subjects

        Very mild to moderate stage YOD inclusion criteria:

        Age between 20-75 years old.

        YOD is defined by the dementia onset before age 65 years old. The dementia syndrome is
        based on the NIA-AA criteria of all-cause of dementia . Briefly it required:

          1. Interfere with the ability to function at work or at usual activities.

          2. Represent a decline from previous levels of functioning and performing.

          3. Cognitive impairment is detected and diagnosed through a combination of a).
             history-taking form the patient and a knowledgeable informant b). an objective
             cognitive assessment, either a 'bedside' mental status examination or
             neuropsychological testing.

          4. The cognitive or behavioral impairment involves a minimum of two of the below domains:
             impaired ability to acquire and remember new information, impaired reasoning and
             handling of complex tasks poor judgment, impaired visuospatial abilities, impaired
             language functions, changes in personality, behavior or comportment symptoms.

        The severity of dementia is limited from very mild to moderate stage in current project.
        The definition of very mild to moderate stage of dementia is based on the clinical dementia
        rating scale (CDR) from 0.5-2 YOD_2019 3 Exclusion Criteria

          1. Implantation of metal devices including cardiac pacemaker, intravascular metal
             devices.

          2. Major systemic diseases including coronary arterial disease, heart failure, uremia,
             hepatic failure, prominent strokes, acute myocardial infarction, poorly controlled
             diabetes, previous severe head injury, intracranial operation, hypoxia, sepsis or
             severe infectious diseases.

          3. Major psychiatric disorders, drug or alcohol abuse and major depression

          4. Pregnant women or breast- feeding women.

          5. Patients in whom MRI was contraindicated or patient had claustrophobia.

          6. History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions particularly to the tested drugs.

          7. History of positive test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          8. Indication of impaired liver function as shown by an abnormal liver function profile
             at screening (eg. repeated values of aspartate aminotransferase [AST] and alanine
             aminotransferase [ALT] ≧ 3X the upper limit of normal values).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hsu, Jung-Lung, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia, Vascular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

