<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04247529</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00003145</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21CA218054</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04247529</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Prior Exposure to Conflicting Health Information on Responses to Subsequent Unrelated Health Messages</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Prior Exposure to Conflicting Health Information on Responses to Subsequent Unrelated Health Messages</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many population-level public health strategies—including media campaigns and other behavioral
      interventions, screening recommendations, and vaccination policies—rely on messaging to
      promote cancer prevention and control. These strategies do not take place in a vacuum;
      rather, they occur in the context of a broader public information environment, which is
      increasingly characterized by conflicting and often controversial health information.
      Although studies have documented that such information is prevalent, a critical question
      remains unanswered: does exposure to conflicting health information in people's routine
      interactions with the broader information environment threaten the success of message-based
      population-level public health strategies? And, if so, who is most susceptible to the effects
      of such exposure? This study will provide a rigorous empirical test of these critical
      answered questions, guided by two specific aims: First, to evaluate whether prior exposure to
      conflicting health information influences responses to subsequent unrelated and uncontested
      health messages, a phenomenon that has been described as &quot;carryover effects&quot; (Primary Aim);
      and second, to identify whether there are individual-level differences in how conflict
      affects responses to these unrelated and uncontested health messages (Secondary Aim).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To accomplish these aims, an online survey-based experiment using a population-based sample
      of U.S. adults (anticipated N=1,800) will be conducted. At 2 time points across a 28-day
      period, participants will be exposed to news stories and social media posts about 6 health
      topics: mammography screening, prostate-specific antigen (PSA) testing, Vitamin D
      supplementation, carbohydrate consumption, alcohol consumption, and breastfeeding.
      Participants will be randomized to 1 of 2 treatment groups that differ only in the amount of
      conflict presented in these news and social media posts (conflict, no conflict). At a third
      time point, after the exposure to conflict period, all participants will be exposed to 3 (out
      of a possible 9) messages from existing health campaigns about 3 behaviors for which there is
      scientific consensus: fruit and vegetable consumption, colorectal cancer screening, and
      physical activity. To assess carryover effects (Primary Aim), participants' receptivity to
      these messages—as measured through several affective and cognitive responses (e.g.,
      confidence in the evidence presented)—will be measured. Message receptivity is expected to be
      lower among those who were randomized to receive conflicting health information.
      Individual-level differences in message receptivity are possible; thus exploratory analyses
      (Secondary Aim) will be conducted to assess whether carryover effects of exposure to conflict
      may be more pronounced among certain groups (e.g., those with greater trust in media sources,
      those of lower socioeconomic position).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative affective responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are asked to indicate how &quot;the ad you just saw made you feel&quot;
7 affective responses are randomly ordered: interested, frustrated, surprised, annoyed, distressed, optimistic, worried (response options: 1 &quot;very slightly or not at all&quot; to 5 &quot;extremely&quot;)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Counterarguing</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>• Participants are asked to indicate the extent to which they agree or disagree with 4 statements (randomly ordered; response options: 1 &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to 5 &quot;strongly agree&quot;):
&quot;I found myself agreeing with the ad&quot; (reverse coded)
&quot;I thought of points that went against what the ad was saying&quot;
&quot;I accepted the ad's claims&quot; (reverse coded)
&quot;While reading the ad, I was skeptical of its claims&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reactance/threat to freedom</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>• Participants are asked to indicate the extent to which they agree or disagree with the following statement (response options: 1 &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to 5 &quot;strongly agree&quot;): &quot;I felt like the ad was trying to manipulate me&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Other negative cognitive responses to ad claims</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>• Participants are asked to indicate whether &quot;the claims in the ad I just saw are&quot; (randomly ordered; response options: 1 &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to 5 &quot;strongly agree&quot;): exaggerated, flawed, believable (reverse coded), reasonable (reverse coded)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived argument strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>• Participants are asked to indicate the extent to which they agree or disagree with 2 statements (randomly ordered; response options: 1 &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to 5 &quot;strongly agree&quot;):
&quot;The ad was convincing&quot;
&quot;The ad gave me a strong reason to [engage in the behavior specified in the ad]&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>• Participants are asked to respond to two items, presented in random order:
&quot;How confident are you that there is evidence to support the ad's claims?&quot; (1 &quot;not confident at all&quot; to 7 &quot;extremely confident&quot;)
&quot;How much do you think your health would benefit if you [engaged in the behavior specified in the ad]?&quot; (1 &quot;not at all&quot; to 7 &quot;extremely&quot;)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4000</enrollment>
  <condition>Communication Research</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No exposure to conflict</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exposure to conflict</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exposure to conflicting health information</intervention_name>
    <description>At 2 time points across a ~28-day period, participants will be exposed to news stories and social media posts about 6 health topics: mammography screening, prostate-specific antigen (PSA) testing, Vitamin D supplementation, carbohydrate consumption, alcohol consumption, and breastfeeding. Participants in the conflict (experimental) group will have conflicting information added to these news and social media posts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exposure to conflict</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No exposure to conflicting health information</intervention_name>
    <description>At 2 time points across a ~28-day period, participants will be exposed to news stories and social media posts about 6 health topics: mammography screening, prostate-specific antigen (PSA) testing, Vitamin D supplementation, carbohydrate consumption, alcohol consumption, and breastfeeding. Participants in the no conflict (comparator) group will have no conflicting information included in these news and social media posts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No exposure to conflict</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18+ U.S. adults

          -  Members of NORC's AmeriSpeak Panel (https://amerispeak.norc.org/Pages/default.aspx)

          -  Able to complete web-based survey

          -  Able to read in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rebekah Nagler</last_name>
    <phone>6126259388</phone>
    <email>nagle026@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah Gollust</last_name>
    <phone>(612) 626-2618</phone>
    <email>sgollust@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Within one year of study completion, the final, cleaned, de-identified study dataset may be made available to third-party users under a data-sharing agreement that provides for: 1) a commitment to using the data only for research purposes; 2) a commitment to securing the data using appropriate information technology; and 3) a commitment to destroying or returning the data after analyses are completed. Requests for data sharing will be considered by the investigator team via in-person meetings and approved by consensus; meeting minutes will be taken to ensure transparent decision making and conflict of interest avoidance.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

