<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04240340</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PID:14574</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04240340</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Experiences of Disclosure in Adolescents With Coeliac Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Understanding Perceived Barriers to the Disclosure of Psychological Difficulties by Young People With Coeliac Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Being diagnosed with coeliac disease means that individuals can no longer consume things
      containing gluten, such as bread or cake, or they can become very ill. This can make
      situations involving food challenging, such as social situations or lunch at school. The
      investigators know that being diagnosed with coeliac disease as a teenager can be
      particularly upsetting and can lead to problems such as anxiety or low mood. Research
      suggests that when young people are worried about the impact of their condition on their
      life, they can find it challenging to tell their doctor or ask for support.

      The investigators would like to understand the experiences of young people with coeliac
      disease who attend the Paediatric Gastroenterology service at a local children's hospital.
      The investigators are particularly interested in the reasons why young people either feel
      able or unable to tell their doctor that they are experiencing difficulties relating to their
      wellbeing during their appointments, in order to improve support for young people.

      This study aims to recruit young people between the ages of 11 and 16, who are attending
      secondary school, to ask them about the things that make it easier or more difficult to share
      any concerns about their wellbeing with their doctor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background -

      Coeliac Disease is a genetic lifelong autoimmune condition whereby ingesting gluten leads to
      a range of idiosyncratic symptoms including diarrhoea, abdominal pain and chronic fatigue.
      Treatment for coeliac disease requires the individual to maintain a strict gluten free diet
      (GFD), whereby the individual must exclude foods containing wheat, barley and rye such as
      bread, pasta and baked goods.

      Research indicates that being diagnosed with coeliac disease as a young person, of secondary
      school age, poses particular challenges when adapting to the new diet and lifestyle.
      Developmentally, this age-range involves increasing autonomy from parents, growing
      responsibility for one's own wellbeing and food related activities and increasing
      peer-pressure to conform. Consequently, young people with coeliac disease can often
      experience both felt stigma (the fear of discrimination) and enacted stigma (the experience
      of discrimination) from their peers. Difficulties adapting to a diagnosis of coeliac disease
      at this age can lead to non-adherence, poor health related quality of life and psychological
      difficulties. Indeed, higher rates of anxiety, depression and somatic complaints have been
      found in young people with coeliac disease, emphasising the importance of early detection of
      psychological difficulties associated with the condition by services.

      This poses as a challenge to services, as young people may also experience increased
      difficulties disclosing psychological difficulties, which may be exacerbated by the process
      of adjusting to a chronic condition. For instance, research exploring disclosure and
      support-seeking in young people with Inflammatory Bowel Disease suggests that, despite a high
      prevalence of anxiety related to health treatments and psychosocial factors, only half of
      individuals shared these concerns during routine consultations. A recent systematic review
      suggests that the characteristics of the potential provider of help, such as credibility,
      unhelpful responses, being perceived as 'too busy', being perceived as an 'inappropriate
      source of help for mental distress', unfamiliarity and felt stigma from the source of help
      itself are possible perceived barriers to help-seeking in 11-25 year olds.

      Rationale for the current project -

      The recruiting service diagnoses approximately 30 young people with coeliac disease each year
      and follow-up an additional 75 young people living with the condition. However, only 5
      referrals for young people with coeliac disease were made by the Gastroenterology team to
      Children's Psychological Medicine in 2018.

      This raises the question of whether young people with coeliac disease feel that they have had
      the opportunity to disclose psychological distress associated with coeliac disease during
      routine consultations, or whether they too perceived barriers to disclosure. This project
      aims to address these issues systematically by providing a theoretically integrative account
      of young people's experiences of seeking psychological support from clinicians in the
      service.

      This research project thus has two principal research objectives:

        1. To understand perceived barriers to the disclosure of psychological difficulties by
           young people, aged 11-16 years, with coeliac disease.

        2. To make recommendations to the Paediatric Gastroenterology service based on these
           findings in order to promote disclosure, if it is felt to be helpful, and improve the
           identification of young people with coeliac disease who may want and benefit from
           psychological support.

      The principal research questions are as follows:

        1. What are young people's experiences of disclosing and not disclosing psychological
           difficulties associated with coeliac disease to clinicians in the service?

        2. Could specific changes be made to the service to promote disclosure and improve access
           to psychological services, if it is felt that this would be helpful for this population?

      Broadly, the results of this project could either suggest that young people feel that they
      had the opportunity to disclose psychological difficulties associated with their condition if
      they wanted to, or that they did not due to perceived barriers. The latter finding could
      prompt service improvements from each group in the following ways:

        -  The service is motivated to implement changes that further integrated care by
           acknowledging the interdependence among one's biological, social and psychological
           needs, in line with the 10-year plan. They recognise that the long-term impact of this
           could reduce non-adherence to the GFD, reduce avoidable medical utilisation and further
           complications, either medically or with regards to deteriorating mental health.

        -  Findings could improve young people's experience of the service and access to
           psychological support. It may also normalise the difficult experience of disclosing
           distress, affording therapeutic benefit.

        -  More broadly, this research has the potential to inform NICE guidance around
           post-diagnosis support for young people with this condition.

      Participants:

      Participants will be aged between 11 - 16 years and attending secondary school, with a
      diagnosis of coeliac disease. This age range was selected based on research which suggests
      that adolescents with coeliac disease are particularly at risk of developing psychological
      difficulties in relation to their health condition, and can find it particularly difficult to
      disclose psychological difficulties to healthcare professionals. This is balanced against a
      need for homogeneity in using IPA. This age range is compatible with the ages of service
      users presenting in the recruiting service.

      Participants recruited will be presenting to the Paediatric Gastroenterology department at a
      local Children's Hospital, as this project primarily aims to make improvements to this
      particular service based on its findings. The participants will have received the diagnosis
      of coeliac disease a minimum of three months prior to participation in the study. This is to
      allow time for them to process the diagnosis and for treatment to be established. They will
      also have had at least 1 follow-up appointment following diagnosis, as this will give them an
      experience to reflect on during the interview. Participants will need to speak fluent English
      as there is no funding available for interpreters or translation of documents and
      questionnaires.

      Methods:

      The chosen methodology for this qualitative study is Interpretive Phenomenological Analysis
      (IPA). IPA seeks to understand and 'give voice' to the concerns of participants then
      contextualize and 'make sense' of their worldview from a psychological perspective. IPA has
      been chosen to meet the studies aims and objectives as it allows the researchers to carry out
      an in-depth inquiry into the participants' perspectives of possible barriers to disclosing
      psychological difficulties, with special consideration of the interpersonal and
      socio-developmental context.

      Semi-structured, face-to-face interviews will be carried out, as this is the most appropriate
      method of data collection for IPA.

      Analysis:

      Interpretive Phenomenological Analysis will be used as this study seeks to provide an
      in-depth exploration of the lived experience of individuals with coeliac disease. This will
      allow researchers to maintain a rich idiographic account of each individual whilst allowing
      convergence and divergence of themes across transcripts. NVivo may be used to store and
      organise data, however no software will be used for data analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Semi-structured interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Lasts up to 90 minutes per participant.</time_frame>
    <description>Includes questions around experiences of having coeliac disease and experiences of disclosing psychological difficulties to clinicians in the service.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Celiac Disease in Children</condition>
  <condition>Celiac Disease</condition>
  <condition>Celiac</condition>
  <condition>Disclosure</condition>
  <condition>Stigma, Social</condition>
  <condition>Emotional Problem</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health Wellness 1</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>semi-structured interview</intervention_name>
    <description>Semi-structured, face-to-face interviews will be carried out with participants.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants recruited will be presenting to the Paediatric Gastroenterology department at
        a local Children's Hospital, as this project primarily aims to make improvements to this
        particular service based on its findings. The participants will have received the diagnosis
        of coeliac disease a minimum of three months prior to participation in the study. This is
        to allow time for them to process the diagnosis and for treatment to be established. They
        will also have had at least 1 follow-up appointment following diagnosis, as this will give
        them an experience to reflect on during the interview. Participants will need to speak
        fluent English as there is no funding available for interpreters or translation of
        documents and questionnaires.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All participants:

          -  Male or Female, aged 11 - 16 years

          -  Have a medical diagnosis of Coeliac Disease

          -  Attending Secondary school

          -  Able to speak fluent English

          -  Have been under the care of the Paediatric Gastroenterology service at the local
             Children's Hospital for &gt;3 months and have had &gt;1 follow-up appointment

        For participants aged 11-15 only:

          -  Willing and able to give assent for participation in the study

          -  Parent/guardian is willing and able to give informed consent for their child's
             participation in the study

        For participants aged 16:

        • Willing and able to give consent for participation in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Young people with comorbid gastro-intestinal conditions

          -  Young people currently receiving psychological support from any psychological service.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miranda Wheeler</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Miranda Wheeler</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)1865 226431</phone>
    <email>miranda.wheeler@hmc.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Annabel David</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)1865 223195</phone>
    <email>cpm@oxnet.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Hospitals Nhs Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <zip>OX3 9DU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Miranda Wheeler</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)1865 226431</phone>
      <email>miranda.wheeler@hmc.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Annabel David</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)1865 223195</phone>
      <email>cpm@oxnet.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miranda Wheeler</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashton, K., Myers, S., Whitehead, E., &amp; Sebastian, S. (2016). OC-058 Perspectives of Adolescent IBD Patients Undergoing Surgery. Gut, 65, A34. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2016-312388.57</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barratt SM, Leeds JS, Sanders DS. Factors influencing the type, timing and severity of symptomatic responses to dietary gluten in patients with biopsy-proven coeliac disease. J Gastrointestin Liver Dis. 2013 Dec;22(4):391-6.</citation>
    <PMID>24369320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green PH, Jabri B. Coeliac disease. Lancet. 2003 Aug 2;362(9381):383-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12907013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green PH, Jabri B. Celiac disease. Annu Rev Med. 2006;57:207-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16409146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gulliver A, Griffiths KM, Christensen H. Perceived barriers and facilitators to mental health help-seeking in young people: a systematic review. BMC Psychiatry. 2010 Dec 30;10:113. doi: 10.1186/1471-244X-10-113. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21192795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ludvigsson JF, Agreus L, Ciacci C, Crowe SE, Geller MG, Green PH, Hill I, Hungin AP, Koletzko S, Koltai T, Lundin KE, Mearin ML, Murray JA, Reilly N, Walker MM, Sanders DS, Shamir R, Troncone R, Husby S. Transition from childhood to adulthood in coeliac disease: the Prague consensus report. Gut. 2016 Aug;65(8):1242-51. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2016-311574. Epub 2016 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>27196596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayer M, Greco L, Troncone R, Auricchio S, Marsh MN. Compliance of adolescents with coeliac disease with a gluten free diet. Gut. 1991 Aug;32(8):881-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1885070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzone L, Reale L, Spina M, Guarnera M, Lionetti E, Martorana S, Mazzone D. Compliant gluten-free children with celiac disease: an evaluation of psychological distress. BMC Pediatr. 2011 May 27;11:46. doi: 10.1186/1471-2431-11-46.</citation>
    <PMID>21619651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NHS England (2019) The NHS Long Term Plan. Retrieved from https://www.longtermplan.nhs.uk/wpcontent/uploads/2019/01/nhs-lo ng-term-plan.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NICE. (2015). Clinical Guidelines: Coeliac Disease Recognition, assessment and management: Methods, evidence and recommendations (Standard No. NG20). Retrieved from https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng20/evidence/Full guidance-pdf- 438530077</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olsson C, Lyon P, Hörnell A, Ivarsson A, Sydner YM. Food that makes you different: the stigma experienced by adolescents with celiac disease. Qual Health Res. 2009 Jul;19(7):976-84. doi: 10.1177/1049732309338722.</citation>
    <PMID>19556403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rickwood DJ, Deane FP, Wilson CJ. When and how do young people seek professional help for mental health problems? Med J Aust. 2007 Oct 1;187(S7):S35-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17908023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rutter, M., &amp; Smith, D.J. (1995). Psychosocial Disorders in Young People: Time Trends and Their Causes. Chicester: John Wiley &amp; Lons Ltd.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schroeder, R. D., &amp; Mowen, T. J. (2014). &quot;You Can't Eat WHAT?&quot; Managing the Stigma of Celiac Disease. Deviant Behavior, 35(6), 456-474. doi: 10.1080/01639625.2014.855105</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith, J. A., Flowers, P., &amp; Larkin, M. (2009). Interpretative phenomenological analysis: Theory, method and research. London: Sage.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>coeliac disease</keyword>
  <keyword>celiac disease</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>mental health</keyword>
  <keyword>disclosure</keyword>
  <keyword>stigma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Celiac Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be kept for 5 years, separately to any identifiable information, and will then be disposed of securely. This is in accordance with Trust policy. The interviews will be deleted when the research study is finished.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

