<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04245423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UF1MH121944</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04245423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Whole Health Study: Collaborative Care for OUD and Mental Health Conditions</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Whole Health Study: Collaborative Care for OUD and Mental Health Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Collaborative care for mental health is increasingly common, but most primary care practices
      have not embraced similar models for opioid use disorder (OUD). The investigators will
      rapidly prototype and test elements of collaborative care models to optimize it for
      implementation with individuals with co-occurring mental health needs and OUD. The
      investigators will also conduct a randomized study comparing different intensities of
      collaborative care models to determine which is most effective in improving outcomes and
      examine the cost effectiveness of these different care models.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This research aims to refine and rigorously test a collaborative care model for patients with
      opioid use disorder (OUD) and major depression, post-traumatic stress disorder, or an anxiety
      disorder in primary care. The investigators will also examine clinician and practice
      characteristics associated with successful implementation and the cost effectiveness of
      different care models. The primary aims of this proposal are: (1) Rapidly prototype and test
      each element of collaborative care models to optimize it for implementation; (2) Conduct a
      randomized study of three collaborative care conditions with 39 practices to determine which
      is most effective in improving outcomes for people with OUD and mental health conditions: (a)
      Augmented Usual Care:Primary Care Physician (PCP) waivered to prescribe buprenorphine and
      mental health care manager, (b) Collaborative Care: Waivered PCP; mental health care manager
      receives OUD training; practice receives telephonic psychiatric consultation, or (c)
      Collaborative Care + Social Worker to address social determinants of health; (3) Measure
      clinician and organizational-level factors associated with implementation of each component,
      with the goal of developing strategies to increase successful implementation; and (4) Conduct
      a cost evaluation of each collaborative care model. Successful completion of the proposed
      study will provide definitive evidence regarding the most parsimonious set of elements of
      integrated collaborative care required to maximize outcomes for individuals with OUD and
      psychiatric disorders. Because of the study design, the investigators' examination of
      implementation factors, and community partnerships, the results also will have high
      probability of adoption and implementation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid use - Self-reported</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Timeline Followback</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid use - Toxicology</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Urine Drug Screens</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric Symptoms - Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric Symptoms - Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized Anxiety Disorder Screener (GAD-7)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric Symptoms - Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">587</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health Issue</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Augmented Usual Care (AUC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>If not already waivered, PCPs will be trained and waivered to treat OUD with medications. Almost all practices have hired mental health clinicians, equivalent to the care managers in the investigators' collaborative care model, to treat mild and moderate depression and anxiety. These clinicians typically are licensed clinical social workers; a few are nurses or psychologists. No care managers have received systematic training in treating patients with OUD. The clinicians will retain their role and continue to treat and monitor patients with mental health conditions in these practices. Other than that, the research team will provide no support to the PCP or practice staff. However, an addiction psychiatrist is available for consultation for OUD. Patients are informed that the primary care practice provides both OUD and mental health treatment and are referred back to their provider for referral or to schedule care. A list of available community resources are available to the patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Collaborative Care (CC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CC condition includes the following elements:
Routine, universal screening for all indicated conditions;
Personnel trained to assist with scheduling, reminders and referrals;
PCP trained and waivered to provide evidence-based pharmacotherapy for OUD;
Addictions psychiatrist with collaborative care expertise to provide treatment consultation and supervision in both OUD and psychiatric disorders;
A care manager trained in evidence-based interventions for individuals with OUD and psychiatric disorders, who provides care in the primary care practice as part of the collaborative care team;
Measurement-guided care and treat-to-target practices, using validated measures;
Electronic and in-person systematic communication regarding patient care among team members, facilitated by the electronic health record; and
Shared patient-provider decision making.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Collaborative Care + Social Worker (CC+)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to the collaborative care model described above, patients in the CC+ condition will have access to a separate social worker to assist in addressing the social determinants of health. In-person visits will consist of the care manager carrying out intervention activities followed by the social worker addressing social determinants of health (e.g. financial difficulties, housing needs, food scarcity, or unsafe neighborhoods). The goal will be to identify priorities that are likely to influence retention, engagement and adherence to treatment. For example, if the patient prioritizes housing, then the social worker will determine, with the patient, the need for referral to further services. The investigators seek to improve linkages among medical, social and community services including links to advocacy organizations, affordable housing, legal services, employment services, and financial counseling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Collaborative Care for Opioid Use Disorders and Mental Health Conditions</intervention_name>
    <description>CC is delivered using the investigators' Foundations for Integrated Care model. The first line pharmacotherapy is buprenorphine-naloxone. The second line pharmacotherapy included is extended-release injectable naltrexone. Pharmacotherapy is accompanied by brief problem-solving therapy, cognitive-behavioral therapy, and/or motivational interviewing. The primary care physician, in consultation with the addictions psychiatrist and care manager, also will provide psychotropic medications for psychiatric disorders. In-person and telephone visits consist of the care manager carrying out intervention activities over 12 months. Visits are at baseline (90-minute intake appointment), home or office induction when in moderate opiate withdrawal if buprenorphine is prescribed, twice a week for two weeks with telephone calls in between visits, then weekly, and when stable once a month. There will be a final visit at 12 months. The intervention includes routine collection of urine drug screens.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Collaborative Care (CC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Augmented Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>If not already waivered, PCPs will be trained and waivered to treat OUD with medications. All practices will have mental health clinicians to treat mild psychiatric disorders. Other than that, the research team will provide no support to the PCP or practice staff. However, an addiction psychiatrist is available for consultation for OUD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Augmented Usual Care (AUC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Collaborative Care for Opioid Use Disorders and Mental Health Conditions Plus Social Workers</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention includes the Collaborative Care Intervention plus social workers to address social determinants of health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Collaborative Care + Social Worker (CC+)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years and older;

          2. opioid use disorder and not currently receiving medication-assisted treatment

          3. major depression, post-traumatic stress disorder, or an anxiety disorder (panic
             disorder, agoraphobia, social anxiety disorder, obsessive compulsive disorder, or
             generalized anxiety disorder);

          4. able to communicate in English or Spanish; and

          5. willing to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. meet diagnostic criteria for mania or hypomania;

          2. meet diagnostic criteria for psychotic syndrome;

          3. acutely suicidal or psychotic (patients will not be randomized and PI or study
             physician covering for PI will be paged immediately);

          4. significant cognitive impairment at baseline, as assessed by a total score on the
             Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE &lt; 18);

          5. active participation in formal addiction program outside the primary care office; and

          6. lack of a phone.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Mandell, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Donna M Coviello, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-746-6713</phone>
    <email>coviello@upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Mandell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Kenneth E. Appel Professor and Director, Penn Center for Mental Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Opioid-use disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-traumatic stress disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

