<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04249817</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>238-2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04249817</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Keeping Stable Inflammatory Arthritis Patients in Their Communities With the Advanced Clinician Practitioner in Arthritis Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACPAC</acronym>
  <official_title>Keeping Stable Inflammatory Arthritis Patients in Their Communities With the Advanced Clinician Practitioner in Arthritis Care (ACPAC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Initiative for Outcomes in Rheumatology Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Ontario, rheumatology services are in short supply. Many people with inflammatory
      arthritis (IA) are traveling long distances for care and face geographical/ financial
      challenges in so doing. Travel burden may be decreased and satisfaction with care improved by
      integrating existing health care resources. A few rheumatologists in Ontario have adopted a
      video conferencing (VC) model for follow-up of stable IA patients using the Ontario
      Telemedicine Network (OTN) with Extended Role Practitioners (ERPs) doing on-site assessments.
      Anecdotal evidence suggests this model benefits both patient and rheumatologist. We will
      determine how people with stable well-controlled IA, living more than 100 km round-trip from
      the rheumatology clinic, perceive quality of life before, during and after VC with ERP
      follow-up visits compared to usual care. Disease activity, functional status, medication
      adherence, patient satisfaction, and barriers to care will also be measured.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: To determine, using a mixed-methods design, the impact of a rheumatology
      appointment via video conferencing combined with on-site pre-assessment by an Advance
      Clinician Practioner in Arthritis Care (ACPAC)-trained ERP compared to usual in-clinic care
      during a one-year period of follow-up for a cohort of persons with stable, well-controlled
      inflammatory arthritis residing in areas of low rheumatology supply.

      Research Questions: For people with stable IA residing in areas of low rheumatology supply,
      is it feasible to provide follow-up to people with stable, well-controlled IA using
      videoconferencing and an assessment by an extended role practitioner? Does VC with ERP
      pre-assessment change quality of life and barriers to care perceived by people with stable,
      well-controlled IA?

      Methods: Mixed-methods design. Randomized controlled trial with 2 groups: VC with ERP
      (VC-ERP) and usual care (UC). Pre- and Post-trial Interviews. Study procedures will be as
      follows:

        1. Pre-trial Interview - 15 minute telephone interview that will be audio taped. Will take
           place no more than one month before baseline study visit. Participant will be asked
           about experience traveling to rheumatologist and barriers to receiving care closer to
           home.

        2. Baseline visit - This visit will be a regularly scheduled appointment with the
           participant's rheumatologist. The participant will complete a package of four
           questionnaires and the rheumatologist will assess disease activity.

        3. Randomization - after completion of the baseline visit, participants will be randomized
           either to VC-ERP or UC.

        4. Follow-up Visits - There will be three follow-up visits 6, 12, and 13 months after the
           baseline study visit. Participants assigned to UC will be seen by their rheumatologist
           at the clinic as usual for all visits. At each visit, the participant wil complete a
           package of four questionnaires and the rheumatologist will assess disease activity.
           Participants assigned to VC-ERP will have their first two follow-up visits at an OTN
           site. There they will complete a package of four questionnaires, meet with the ERP for
           an assessment of disease activity, then connect with their rheumatologist by video
           conference. The final visit will take place in the rheumatologist's office, where the
           patient will complete a package of four questionnaires and the rheumatologist will
           assess disease activity.

        5. Post-trial interview - 15 minute telephone interview that will be audio taped. Will take
           place no more than one month after final follow-up visit. Participants assigned to UC,
           will be asked the same questions as first interview. Participants assigned to VC-ERP,
           will be asked questions about their experience with the therapist and OTN during the
           study period

      Significance: From perspective of people with stable, well-controlled IA, we will understand
      the barriers they perceive when travelling for rheumatology care far from their communities
      and whether this new model of care might help to mitigate some of that burden. This model
      already exists in Ontario and it's important to understand its value to people with stable IA
      and determine whether it is good use of an extended role practitioner's time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>European Quality of Life Questionnaire with 5 Dimensions and 5 Levels (EQ5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall health:
Rated in five dimensions as follows: Mobility from 1 (no problems) to 5 (unable to); Self-care from 1 (no problems) to 5 (unable to); Usual Activities from 1 (no problems) to 5 unable to); Pain/Discomfort from 1 (no pain) to 5 (extreme pain); Anxiety/Depression from 1 (not anxious/depressed) to 5 (extremely anxious/depressed)
Rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (worst health you can imagine) to 100 (best health you can imagine).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>9-item Visit Satisfaction Questionnaire (VSQ9)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>9 items on satisfaction with visit rated on a scale of 1 (poor) to 5 (excellent).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5-item Compliance Questionnaire Rheumatology</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>5 items on medication adherence rated on a scale of 1(strongly disagree) to 4 (strongly agree). Higher ratings indicate better adherence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Assessment Questionnaire Disability Index (HAQ-DI)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Disability is evaluated by:
rating 2 to 3 items in 8 dimensions (dressing &amp; grooming, arising, eating, walking, hygiene, reach, grip, activities) from 0 (without any difficulty) to 3 (unable to do)
indicating which aids, devices and assistance are needed
Rating ability to carry out daily activities from 0 (completely) to 4 (not at all)
Rating pain from 0 (no pain) to 100 (severe pain)
rating overall health from 0 (very well) to 100 (very poor)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>28-joint Disease Activity Score (DAS28- for rheumatoid arthritis)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Disease activity measure for IA patients with Rheumatoid Arthritis. Calculated with an algorithm using the following four items:
Total number of swollen joints (out of a selected 28 joints specific to the disease)
Total number of tender joints (out of a selected 28 joints specific to the disease)
Global Health rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (well) to 100 (poor)
Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (mm/hr) or C-reactive protein (mg/dl)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Activity for Psoriatic Arthritis (DAPSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Disease Activity measure for IA patients with Psoriatic Arthritis Calculated as the sum of the following five items:
Total number of swollen joints (out of a selected 66 joints specific to the disease)
Total number of tender joints (out of a selected 66 joints specific to the disease)
C-reactive protein (mg/dl)
Disease activity rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (not active) to 10 (very active)
Joint pain rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (none) to 10 (very severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ankylosing Spondylitis Disease Activity Score (ASDAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Disease activity measure for IA patients with Ankylosing Spondylitis. Calculated with an algorithm using the following five items:
Back pain rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (none) to 10 (very severe)
Peripheral pain/swelling rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (none) to 10 (very severe)
Duration of morning stiffness rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (0 hrs) to 10 (2 hrs)
Global health rated on a visual analog scale from 0 (well) to 10 (poor)
Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (mm/hr) or C-reactive protein (mg/dl)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammatory Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Video conferencing with extended role practitioner</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant goes to Ontario Telemedicine site for follow-up. At site, participant will get a physical assessment by an extended role practitioner and then will connect to their rheumatologist by videoconferencing for completion of follow-up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant goes to their rheumatologist's clinic for follow-up, including physical assessment by their rheumatologist, as they would normally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Video Conferencing with Exteneded Role Practitioner (VC-ERP)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant goes to Ontario Telemedicine site for follow-up. At site, participant will get a physical assessment by an extended role practitioner and then will connect to their rheumatologist by videoconferencing for completion of follow-up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Video conferencing with extended role practitioner</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adults ≥18 years

          -  clinical diagnosis of inflammatory arthritis (i.e. rheumatoid arthritis, psoriatic
             arthritis, or ankylosing spondylitis)

          -  inflammatory arthritis that is in remission or a low disease state as determined using
             a valid measure prior to study start

          -  travel to clinic ≥100 km round-trip

          -  able to read and write English

          -  willing/able to provide informed consent

          -  OHIP coverage.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inflammatory arthritis that is neither in remission or in a low disease state as
             determined using a valid measure prior to study start

          -  complex rheumatic disease (i.e. lupus, vasculitis)

          -  travel to clinic &lt;100 km round-trip

          -  children/youth &lt; 18 years

          -  unable to read and write English

          -  unwilling/unable to provide informed consent

          -  no OHIP coverage.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Raquel Sweezie, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(416)480-6100</phone>
    <phone_ext>3771</phone_ext>
    <email>raquel.sweezie@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mary J Bell, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(416)480-4580</phone>
    <email>Mary.Bell@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. Henry Averns</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 3E4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raquel Sweezie, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 480-6100</phone>
      <phone_ext>3771</phone_ext>
      <email>raquel.sweezie@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. Ashley Sterrett</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K2A 3Z3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raquel Sweezie, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 480-6100</phone>
      <phone_ext>3771</phone_ext>
      <email>raquel.sweezie@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Raquel Sweezie, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 480-6100</phone>
      <phone_ext>3771</phone_ext>
      <email>raquel.sweezie@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mary Bell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 480-4580</phone>
      <email>Mary.Bell@sunnybrook.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Mary Bell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

