<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04416230</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB11-00662</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04416230</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Post-Op Massage in Infants With Congenital Heart Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Massage on Pain After Pediatric Cardiothoracic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nationwide Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aims of the proposed study are to pilot test the effectiveness of daily massage
      on pain and clinical outcomes in infants who have undergone cardiothoracic surgery. The
      secondary aim is to explore relationships among massage, pain scores, and other variables
      potentially affecting pain scores, including parental anxiety, severity of cardiac defect,
      and severity of pain.

      Specific Aim 1: To compare effects of massage on infant pain and clinical outcomes between
      two groups over time: infants receiving post-operative massage seven days post-operatively
      and infants receiving a comparable time of restricted non-essential caregiving seven days
      post-operatively.

      Specific Aim 2: To compare pain scores and physiologic responses before and after
      intervention in two groups: infants receiving post-operative massage and infants receiving a
      comparable time of restricted non-essential caregiving.

      Specific Aim 3: To examine potential moderators of pain response in the massage intervention
      group before and after receiving massage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We used a two-group randomized clinical trial design with a sample of 60 infants with complex
      congenital heart disease (CCHD) between 1 day and 12 months of age following their first
      cardiothoracic surgery. Both groups received standard post-operative care. In addition, Group
      1 received a daily 30-minute restricted non-essential direct caregiving time (Quiet Time),
      and Group 2 received a daily 30-minute massage. Interventions continued for seven consecutive
      days. Pain was measured 6 times daily using the Face, Legs, Activity, Cry, Consolability Pain
      Assessment Tool (FLACC). Average daily doses of analgesics were recorded. Heart rates (HR),
      respiratory rates (RR), and oxygen saturations (SpO2) were recorded continuously. Daily
      averages and pre- and post- intervention FLACC scores and physiologic responses were analyzed
      using descriptive statistics, generalized linear mixed models (GLMM) for repeated measures,
      latent growth models, and/or regression discontinuity analysis. Fentanyl-equivalent narcotic
      values were used as a time-varying covariate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 3, 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The intervention consisted of a massage given by a licensed massage therapist on each of seven consecutive days beginning on the day of surgery (Day 1). The massage included 30 minutes of Swedish massage on the infant's accessible upper extremities, lower extremities, head, face, and back. Standard precautions were used, including proper hand hygiene and the use of gloves when needed for infection control.
Infants randomized to the comparison group received a 30 minute quiet time (QT) period during which non-essential caregiving tasks were restricted. During QT, clinicians were asked to avoid direct clinical caregiving activities, i.e. activities requiring physical contact with the infant.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Research assistants scoring participant pain were blinded to group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily average for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>FLACC score: behavioral observation of face, legs, activity, cry, consolability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post-operative pain score with intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>FLACC score: behavioral observation of face, legs, activity, cry, consolability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily average for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>heart rate in beats per minute</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily average for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>respiratory rate in breaths per minute</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen saturation</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily average for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>oxygen saturation percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate with intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>heart rate in beats per minute</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in respiratory rate with intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>respiratory rate in beats per minute</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in oxygen saturation with intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Daily for 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>oxygen saturation percentage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Massage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants randomized to the massage intervention received a 30 minute massage daily for the 7 day study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quiet Time</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants randomized to the Quiet Time intervention experienced a 30 minute time during which non-essential clinical caregiving tasks were restricted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>massage</intervention_name>
    <description>The massage included 30 minutes of gentle friction, kneading, stroking, and passive touch on the infant's accessible upper extremities, lower extremities, head, face, and back.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Massage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quiet time</intervention_name>
    <description>During quiet time, the infant received a 30 minute quiet time (QT) period during which non-essential caregiving tasks were restricted. During QT, clinicians were asked to avoid direct clinical caregiving activities, i.e. activities requiring physical contact with the infant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quiet Time</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants born with complex congenital heart disease requiring surgical intervention

          -  less than 12 months old

          -  undergoing first surgical procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  on paralytics post-operatively

          -  cardiorespiratory instability

          -  on-going cardiac pacing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tondi M Harrison, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Ohio State University and Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blakely WP, Page GG. Pathophysiology of pain in critically ill patients. Crit Care Nurs Clin North Am. 2001 Jun;13(2):167-79. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11866400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Craig KD, Whitfield MF, Grunau RV, Linton J, Hadjistavropoulos HD. Pain in the preterm neonate: behavioural and physiological indices. Pain. 1993 Mar;52(3):287-99. Erratum in: Pain 1993 Jul;54(1):111.</citation>
    <PMID>8460047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Messerer B, Gutmann A, Weinberg A, Sandner-Kiesling A. Implementation of a standardized pain management in a pediatric surgery unit. Pediatr Surg Int. 2010 Sep;26(9):879-89. doi: 10.1007/s00383-010-2642-1. Epub 2010 Jul 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20625751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kulkarni A, Kaushik JS, Gupta P, Sharma H, Agrawal RK. Massage and touch therapy in neonates: the current evidence. Indian Pediatr. 2010 Sep;47(9):771-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21048258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchinson AR, Kim HM, Rosenberg JM, Geisser M, Kirsh M, Cikrit D, Hinshaw DB. Acute postoperative pain management using massage as an adjuvant therapy: a randomized trial. Arch Surg. 2007 Dec;142(12):1158-67; discussion 1167.</citation>
    <PMID>18086982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piotrowski MM, Paterson C, Mitchinson A, Kim HM, Kirsh M, Hinshaw DB. Massage as adjuvant therapy in the management of acute postoperative pain: a preliminary study in men. J Am Coll Surg. 2003 Dec;197(6):1037-46.</citation>
    <PMID>14644293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nerbass FB, Feltrim MI, Souza SA, Ykeda DS, Lorenzi-Filho G. Effects of massage therapy on sleep quality after coronary artery bypass graft surgery. Clinics (Sao Paulo). 2010;65(11):1105-10.</citation>
    <PMID>21243280</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauer BA, Cutshall SM, Wentworth LJ, Engen D, Messner PK, Wood CM, Brekke KM, Kelly RF, Sundt TM 3rd. Effect of massage therapy on pain, anxiety, and tension after cardiac surgery: a randomized study. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2010 May;16(2):70-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2009.06.012. Epub 2009 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20347836</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albert NM, Gillinov AM, Lytle BW, Feng J, Cwynar R, Blackstone EH. A randomized trial of massage therapy after heart surgery. Heart Lung. 2009 Nov-Dec;38(6):480-90. doi: 10.1016/j.hrtlng.2009.03.001. Epub 2009 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>19944872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hernandez-Reif M, Field T, Largie S, Hart S, Redzepi M, Nierenberg B, Peck TM. Childrens' distress during burn treatment is reduced by massage therapy. J Burn Care Rehabil. 2001 Mar-Apr;22(2):191-5; discussion 190.</citation>
    <PMID>11302609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Field T, Hernandez-Reif M, Seligman S, Krasnegor J, Sunshine W, Rivas-Chacon R, Schanberg S, Kuhn C. Juvenile rheumatoid arthritis: benefits from massage therapy. J Pediatr Psychol. 1997 Oct;22(5):607-17.</citation>
    <PMID>9383925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benarroch EE. Pain-autonomic interactions. Neurol Sci. 2006 May;27 Suppl 2:S130-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16688616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kirchner A, Birklein F, Stefan H, Handwerker HO. Left vagus nerve stimulation suppresses experimentally induced pain. Neurology. 2000 Oct 24;55(8):1167-71.</citation>
    <PMID>11071495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kirchner A, Stefan H, Bastian K, Birklein F. Vagus nerve stimulation suppresses pain but has limited effects on neurogenic inflammation in humans. Eur J Pain. 2006 Jul;10(5):449-55. Epub 2005 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>16125425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diego MA, Field T, Hernandez-Reif M. Vagal activity, gastric motility, and weight gain in massaged preterm neonates. J Pediatr. 2005 Jul;147(1):50-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16027695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCain GC, Ludington-Hoe SM, Swinth JY, Hadeed AJ. Heart rate variability responses of a preterm infant to kangaroo care. J Obstet Gynecol Neonatal Nurs. 2005 Nov-Dec;34(6):689-94.</citation>
    <PMID>16282226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldman R, Eidelman AI. Skin-to-skin contact (Kangaroo Care) accelerates autonomic and neurobehavioural maturation in preterm infants. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2003 Apr;45(4):274-81.</citation>
    <PMID>12647930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weissman A, Aranovitch M, Blazer S, Zimmer EZ. Heel-lancing in newborns: behavioral and spectral analysis assessment of pain control methods. Pediatrics. 2009 Nov;124(5):e921-6. doi: 10.1542/peds.2009-0598. Epub 2009 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19841119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oberlander TF, Grunau RE, Fitzgerald C, Whitfield MF. Does parenchymal brain injury affect biobehavioral pain responses in very low birth weight infants at 32 weeks' postconceptional age? Pediatrics. 2002 Sep;110(3):570-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12205262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faye PM, De Jonckheere J, Logier R, Kuissi E, Jeanne M, Rakza T, Storme L. Newborn infant pain assessment using heart rate variability analysis. Clin J Pain. 2010 Nov-Dec;26(9):777-82.</citation>
    <PMID>20973153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Logier R, Jeanne M, Tavernier B, De Jonckheere J. Pain/analgesia evaluation using heart rate variability analysis. Conf Proc IEEE Eng Med Biol Soc. 2006;2006:4303-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17946620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand KJ, Aranda JV, Berde CB, Buckman S, Capparelli EV, Carlo W, Hummel P, Johnston CC, Lantos J, Tutag-Lehr V, Lynn AM, Maxwell LG, Oberlander TF, Raju TN, Soriano SG, Taddio A, Walco GA. Summary proceedings from the neonatal pain-control group. Pediatrics. 2006 Mar;117(3 Pt 2):S9-S22.</citation>
    <PMID>16777824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stapelkamp C, Carter B, Gordon J, Watts C. Assessment of acute pain in children: development of evidence-based guidelines. Int J Evid Based Healthc. 2011 Mar;9(1):39-50. doi: 10.1111/j.1744-1609.2010.00199.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21332662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Granot M, Ferber SG. The roles of pain catastrophizing and anxiety in the prediction of postoperative pain intensity: a prospective study. Clin J Pain. 2005 Sep-Oct;21(5):439-45.</citation>
    <PMID>16093750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalkman CJ, Visser K, Moen J, Bonsel GJ, Grobbee DE, Moons KG. Preoperative prediction of severe postoperative pain. Pain. 2003 Oct;105(3):415-23.</citation>
    <PMID>14527702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bringuier S, Dadure C, Raux O, Dubois A, Picot MC, Capdevila X. The perioperative validity of the visual analog anxiety scale in children: a discriminant and useful instrument in routine clinical practice to optimize postoperative pain management. Anesth Analg. 2009 Sep;109(3):737-44. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e3181af00e4.</citation>
    <PMID>19690240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franck LS, Ridout D, Howard R, Peters J, Honour JW. A comparison of pain measures in newborn infants after cardiac surgery. Pain. 2011 Aug;152(8):1758-65. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2011.03.017. Epub 2011 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21514052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith MC, Stallings MA, Mariner S, Burrall M. Benefits of massage therapy for hospitalized patients: a descriptive and qualitative evaluation. Altern Ther Health Med. 1999 Jul;5(4):64-71.</citation>
    <PMID>10394676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diego MA, Field T, Hernandez-Reif M, Deeds O, Ascencio A, Begert G. Preterm infant massage elicits consistent increases in vagal activity and gastric motility that are associated with greater weight gain. Acta Paediatr. 2007 Nov;96(11):1588-91. Epub 2007 Sep 21.</citation>
    <PMID>17888059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merkel SI, Voepel-Lewis T, Shayevitz JR, Malviya S. The FLACC: a behavioral scale for scoring postoperative pain in young children. Pediatr Nurs. 1997 May-Jun;23(3):293-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9220806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Voepel-Lewis T, Merkel S, Tait AR, Trzcinka A, Malviya S. The reliability and validity of the Face, Legs, Activity, Cry, Consolability observational tool as a measure of pain in children with cognitive impairment. Anesth Analg. 2002 Nov;95(5):1224-9, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>12401598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>32. Wong DL, Hockenberry-Eaton M, Wilson D, et al. Wong's essentials of pediatric nursing (6th ed.). St. Louis: Mosby; 2001.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen MP, Karoly P, O'Riordan EF, Bland F Jr, Burns RS. The subjective experience of acute pain. An assessment of the utility of 10 indices. Clin J Pain. 1989 Jun;5(2):153-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2520397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>34. Spielberger CD. Conceptual and methodological issues in anxiety research. In C. D. Spielberger (Ed.), Anxiety: current trends in theory and research (pp. 481-492). New York: Academic Press; 1972.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pagé MG, Fuss S, Martin AL, Escobar EM, Katz J. Development and preliminary validation of the Child Pain Anxiety Symptoms Scale in a community sample. J Pediatr Psychol. 2010 Nov;35(10):1071-82. doi: 10.1093/jpepsy/jsq034. Epub 2010 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>20430838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pagé MG, Campbell F, Isaac L, Stinson J, Martin-Pichora AL, Katz J. Reliability and validity of the Child Pain Anxiety Symptoms Scale (CPASS) in a clinical sample of children and adolescents with acute postsurgical pain. Pain. 2011 Sep;152(9):1958-65. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2011.02.053. Epub 2011 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21489692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenkins KJ, Gauvreau K, Newburger JW, Spray TL, Moller JH, Iezzoni LI. Consensus-based method for risk adjustment for surgery for congenital heart disease. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2002 Jan;123(1):110-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11782764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tondi Harrison</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>congenital heart disease</keyword>
  <keyword>massage</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatric pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Defects, Congenital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is not a plan to make individual participant data available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

