<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04411030</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASTX660-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04411030</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate the Effect of CYP3A4 Inhibition on the Single Dose Pharmacokinetics of ASTX660 and the Effect of a Single Dose of ASTX660 on the Pharmacokinetics of the CYP3A4 Substrate Midazolam</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Two Cohort, Open-Label, Fixed Sequence Study to Investigate the Effect of CYP3A4 Inhibition on the Single Dose Pharmacokinetics of ASTX660 and the Effect of a Single Dose of ASTX660 on the Pharmacokinetics of the CYP3A4 Substrate Midazolam</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astex Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astex Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Part 1, the primary objective is to investigate the effect of multiple doses of
      itraconazole, an inhibitor of CYP3A4, on the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of a single dose of
      ASTX660.

      In Part 2, the primary objective is to investigate the effect of a single dose of ASTX660 on
      the pharmacokinetics of the CYP3A4 substrate midazolam and its metabolite, 1-hydroxy
      midazolam.

      Safety and tolerability of a single dose of ASTX660 in the absence and presence of multiple
      doses of the CYP3A4 inhibitor itraconazole and in the presence of a single dose of the CYP3A4
      substrate midazolam will also be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 8, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of ASTX660: Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of ASTX660: AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from time zero to the last measurable concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of ASTX660: AUC0-24</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from time zero to 24 hours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of ASTX660: AUC0-inf</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of midazolam and 1-hydroxyl midazolam: Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of midazolam and 1-hydroxyl midazolam: AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from time zero to the last measurable concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of midazolam and 1-hydroxyl midazolam: AUC0-24</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from time zero to 24 hours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter of midazolam and 1-hydroxyl midazolam: AUC0-inf</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter for ASTX660: CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Total apparent clearance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter for ASTX660: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Observed terminal half-life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter for midazolam: CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Total apparent clearance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameter for midazolam: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>From predose up to Day 9</time_frame>
    <description>Observed terminal half-life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Number of participants with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 35</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral administration of ASTX660 and itraconazole at specific time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral administration of ASTX660 and midazolam at specific time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ASTX660</intervention_name>
    <description>Form: capsule; Route of administration: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam</intervention_name>
    <description>Form: syrup; Route of administration: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Itraconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Form: capsule; Route of administration: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant understands the study procedures and agrees to participate by providing
             written informed consent.

          2. Participant is willing and able to comply with all study procedures and restrictions.

          3. Participant is male aged 18 to 45 years, inclusive at Screening.

          4. Participant has a body mass index (BMI) ≥ 18.5 kg/m2 and ≤ 30.0 kg/m2 at Screening.

          5. Participant is considered medically healthy as determined by the investigator, based
             on clinical evaluations including medical history, physical examination, clinical
             laboratory tests, 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) in triplicate, and vital sign
             measurements performed at Screening.

          6. Participants must be willing to use adequate contraception (double-barrier) from
             screening until 3 months after study completion. Male vasectomy is accepted as
             contraception if the vasectomy took place ≥ 6 months prior to first dose.

          7. Participants must refrain from sperm donation, from screening until 3 months after
             study completion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant is mentally or legally incapacitated or has significant emotional problems
             at the time of Screening or is expected to have such problems during the conduct of
             the study.

          2. Participant has a clinically significant medical or psychiatric condition or disease
             (acute or chronic) that, as judged by the investigator, would make the participant
             ineligible for participation in the study (eg, compromises the study data, limits the
             participant's ability to complete and/or participate in the study).

          3. Participant has a current condition or history of significant endocrine, hepatic,
             renal, hematological, pulmonary, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, urological,
             immunological, or neurological disorders with clinical manifestations that, as judged
             by the investigator, would make the participant ineligible for participation in the
             study.

          4. Participant has a chronic disease requiring medication, dietary restriction, physical
             therapy, and/or other routine treatment that, as judged by the investigator, would
             make the participant ineligible for participation in the study.

          5. Participant has a history of gastrointestinal (GI) surgery including but not limited
             to gastric resection and/or intestinal resection that resulted in a clinically
             significant abnormality in GI function.

          6. Participant has a history or presence of cancer (with the exception of a history of
             basal cell carcinoma of the skin).

          7. Participant has a history of drug and/or alcohol addiction or is a current regular
             user (including recreational use) of any illicit drugs, has a history of drug or
             alcohol abuse, or has ever undergone drug or alcohol rehabilitation.

          8. Participant has a history of significant multiple and/or severe allergies (eg, food,
             drug, latex allergy), or has had an anaphylactic reaction or significant intolerance
             to food, prescription drugs or non-prescription (over-the-counter) drugs. Note:
             participants with seasonal allergies may participate.

          9. Participant has a known history of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) or has had
             contact with a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) positive
             or COVID-19 patient within the 4 weeks prior to admission to the study center.

         10. Participant has a QTcF interval of &gt; 450 msec at Screening.

         11. Participant has an estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 90 mL/min based on the Cockcroft
             Gault equation at Screening.

         12. Participant regularly consumes excessive amounts of caffeine, defined as &gt; 6 servings
             of coffee, tea, cola, or other caffeinated beverages, per day (1 serving is
             approximately equivalent to 120 mg of caffeine).

         13. Participant regularly consumes excessive amounts of alcohol, defined as &gt; 3 glasses of
             alcoholic beverages per day and/or refuses to refrain from consuming such products
             throughout the study.

         14. Participant has used any medication (including prescription or non-prescription drugs,
             dietary or vitamin/mineral supplements or herbal remedies that are known to induce
             drug-metabolizing enzymes) within 14 days (or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer) prior
             to study drug administration on Day 1.

         15. Participant has used any medications known to be significant CYP inducers, including
             St. John's wort, within 28 days prior to the study drug administration on Day 1.

         16. Participant has consumed grapefruit, grapefruit juice, grapefruit juice-containing
             products, Seville oranges, orange juice, and/or apple juice within 7 days prior to
             study drug administration on Day 1 and/or refuses to refrain from consuming such
             products throughout the study.

         17. Participant has consumed vegetables from the mustard green family (eg, kale, broccoli,
             watercress, collard greens, kohlrabi, Brussels sprouts, mustard) and/or charbroiled
             meats within 7 days prior to study drug administration on Day 1 and/or refuses to
             refrain from consuming such products throughout the study.

         18. Participant has used tobacco- or nicotine-containing products (eg, cigarette, pipe,
             cigar, chewing, nicotine patch, or nicotine gum) within 6 months prior to Day -1.

         19. Participant refuses to refrain from using tobacco- or nicotine-containing products
             throughout the study.

         20. Participant has a positive urine drug and/or alcohol screening test result at
             Screening or on Day -1.

         21. Participant has a positive test result for any serological test including human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antigen/antibody, Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg),
             and Hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody at Screening.

         22. Participant has a positive test result for SARS-CoV-2 antigen, either asymptomatic or
             present with COVID-19 at study check-in.

         23. Participant appears to have poor venous access.

         24. Participant has donated blood or had significant blood loss within 56 days of study
             drug administration on Day 1.

         25. Participant has donated plasma within 7 days prior to study drug administration on Day
             1.

         26. Participant has participated in any other investigational trial or has received any
             investigational drug within 28 days (or 5 half-lives of the previous investigational
             drug). The date will be derived from the last study procedure [blood collection or
             dosing] of previous trial prior to study drug administration on Day 1.

         27. Participant has any hypersensitivity to the study drugs or any of their excipients.

         28. Participant is ineligible for this study for any other reason, as judged by the
             investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harold Keer, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Astex Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michelle Fung</last_name>
    <phone>925-560-0100</phone>
    <email>michelle.fung@astx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>QPS Bio-kinetic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65802</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Principal Investigator</last_name>
      <phone>417-831-2048</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Itraconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

