<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04410575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB ID Pro00093776</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04410575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mental Health Assessment and Prescribing by Alberta Pharmacists</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAP-AP</acronym>
  <official_title>Mental Health Assessment and Prescribing by Alberta Pharmacists (MAP-AP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a clinical trial evaluating the experimental intervention of enhanced pharmacist care
      by pharmacists with additional prescribing authorization (APA) in Alberta, for patients newly
      diagnosed with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objective

      -To evaluate the effect of enhanced pharmacist care possible by community pharmacists with
      APA in comparison with usual care (standard pharmacist care and physician care) for patients
      with MDD and/or GAD initiated on pharmacotherapy, with focus on interventions that include:

      i) monitoring (lab ordering and interpretation, clinical monitoring of MDD and GAD) ii)
      patient education iii) referral facilitation (in collaboration with prescribing physician)
      iv) prescribing (dose adjustment and the addition of adjunctive medication)

      Secondary objectives

        -  To evaluate the effect of APA pharmacist interventions on:

           i)Clinical:

        -  The rate of achieving clinical response and remission of MDD and/or GAD compared to
           usual care (using PHQ-9/GAD-7)

        -  Change in the mean PHQ-9 and GAD-7 score

        -  Cognitive and functional impairment related to MDD and/or GAD

        -  The occurrence of relapse of depression and/or anxiety

        -  The proportion of patients receiving appropriate and optimized depression and anxiety
           medication

        -  Patient complaints and/or experiences of medication-related side effects during
           treatment for MDD and/or GAD (i.e. GI intolerance, dizziness, weight gain)

      ii) Process:

        -  The impact of the interventions on patient satisfaction and quality of life impact
           (Patient survey)

        -  Assure sustainability by exploring enabling (i.e. pharmacist reimbursement framework)
           and potential barrier forces (i.e. pharmacist training in managing patients with MDD and
           GAD)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multi-center randomized control trial evaluating the mean difference in depression and anxiety score with patients with major depressive disorder (MDD) and/or generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) by pharmacists with prescribing &amp; management interventions in comparison to pharmacist management per standard pharmacist care.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Stratified randomization of participants via blocking factor to either pharmacist intervention or standard pharmacist care groups.
Participants will be assigned a unique identifier number and group allocation for the duration of their participation in the study and also be recorded by the pharmacy partner in the participant's patient profile to ensure consistency of the degree of pharmacist interventions described by the group the participant is allocated to.
The participant will be sent a secured electronic link (to the contact number or email they provided in the written consent form) that will share the electronic version of the PHQ-9/GAD-7/BC-CCI/SDS questionnaire tool to complete.
The study data (from the participant's electronic questionnaire tool result) will be sent directly to a centralized and secured website/spreadsheet to ensure allocation concealment for the investigational team.
The participant will report their score to the pharmacist participant via telephone.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score difference in Patient Health Questionnaire 9-item (PHQ-9) score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean score difference in PHQ-9 score from baseline to end of study between pharmacist intervention vs standard pharmacist care group;
PHQ-9 scores reflect depression severity, ranges from 0-27 (Scores: 0-4 none/minimal, 5-9 mild, 10-14 moderate, 15-19 moderately severe, 20-27 severe)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score difference in Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean score difference in GAD-7 score from baseline to end of study between pharmacist intervention vs standard pharmacist care group;
GAD-7 scores reflect anxiety severity; Ranges from 0-21 (Scores: 0-4 none/minimal. 5-9 mild, 10-14 moderate, 15-21 severe)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in proportion of participants achieving clinically significant treatment response in Patient Health Questionnaire 9-item (PHQ-9) score between pharmacist intervention vs. standard pharmacist care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically significant treatment response for the PHQ-9 is defined as a reduction in PHQ-9 score by at least 50% from baseline;
PHQ-9 Scores reflect depression severity, ranges from 0-27 (Scores: 0-4 none/minimal, 5-9 mild, 10-14 moderate, 15-19 moderately severe, 20-27 severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in proportion of participants achieving clinically significant treatment response in Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) score between pharmacist intervention vs. standard pharmacist care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically significant treatment response for the GAD-7 is defined as a reduction in GAD-7 score by at least 50% from baseline;
GAD-7 scores reflect anxiety severity; Ranges from 0-21 (Scores: 0-4 none/minimal. 5-9 mild, 10-14 moderate, 15-21 severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the proportion of participants with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) to achieve Patient Health Questionnaire 9-item (PHQ-9) score &lt;5</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the proportion of participants with MDD to achieve PHQ-9 score &lt;5 (i.e. remission/no depression) between the pharmacist intervention and standard pharmacist care groups
PHQ-9 scores reflect depression severity; Ranges from 0-27 (Scores: 0-4 none/minimal, 5-9 mild, 10-14 moderate, 15-19 moderately severe, 20-27 severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the proportion of participants with Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) to achieve Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) score &lt;5</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the proportion of participants with GAD to achieve GAD-7 score &lt;5 (i.e. remission/no anxiety) between the pharmacist intervention and standard pharmacist care groups;
GAD-7 scores reflect anxiety severity; Ranges from 0-21 (Scores: 0-4 none/minimal. 5-9 mild, 10-14 moderate, 15-21 severe)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the proportion of participants with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and/or Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) to achieve a British Columbia Cognitive Complaints Inventory (BC-CCI) score &lt;5</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the proportion of participants with MDD and/or GAD to achieve BC-CCI score &lt;5 between the pharmacist intervention and standard pharmacist care groups
The BC-CCI consists of 6 items and scores reflect the severity of perceived cognitive difficulties; ranges from 0-18 (Scores: 0-4 broadly normal, 5-8 mild cognitive complaints, 9-14 moderate cognitive complaints, 15-18 Severe cognitive complaints)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the proportion of participants with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and/or Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) to achieve Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS) score &lt;5 on all subscales</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in the proportion of participants with MDD and/or GAD to achieve SDS score &lt;5 on all subscales between the pharmacist intervention and standard pharmacist care groups
The SDS assess the severity of functional impairment in 3 domains: work/school, social, and family life. These 3 domains are measured using 10 point sub-scales that range from 0-10 and summed into a single dimensional measure of global functional impairment that ranges from 0 (unimpaired) to 30 (highly impaired); Any sub-scale indicating a score of &gt;/= 5 are associated with significant functional impairment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage difference in self-reported safety concerns disclosed by participant to pharmacist partner, between pharmacist intervention and standard pharmacist care groups, during the study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The participant discloses to the pharmacist partner at any time during the duration of study (or at time of withdrawal) events that fit the description of a safety concern and measured via frequency of occurrence.
Safety concerns include:
1) Adverse Medication Effects 2) Suicide Ideation/attempt, 3) Withdrawal from Study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Generalized Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Pharmacist-Patient Relations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants enrolled in the intervention group will receive pharmacist interventions, in addition to standard care (as outlined in the Alberta College of Pharmacist Standards of Practice for Pharmacist and Pharmacy technicians), at enrollment (month 0) and at months 1, 3, and 6</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group (Standard Pharmacist Care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the usual care groups will receive standard pharmacy care (as outlined in the Alberta College of Pharmacist Standards of Practice for Pharmacist and Pharmacy technicians) and physician care with no specific interventions for the duration of 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Recording participant scores from the combined PHQ-9/GAD-7/BC-CCI/SDS questionnaire tool completed by the participant &amp; uf determined clinically relevant by the pharmacist partner: appearance, current mood, sleeping patterns, mental health, medical history, social history, family history, relationships with others, suicidal ideation, previous suicide attempts or hospitalizations, current employment status</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Collaboration and discussion with the patient's physician</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmacist partner initiates discussion with physician re: treatment plan (as per CANMAT guidelines) for MDD and GAD, which may include referral to psychotherapy resources (i.e. psychologist).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prescription dose adjustment and/or prescribing adjunctive therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Prescribing action by pharmacist partner to achieve clinical response and/or remission of MDD and/or GAD and establish appropriate cognitive/functional status as per CAMAT guidelines</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Communication update with physician after participant contact</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmacist partner provides communication update with the patient's family physician after each contact with the patient</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medication Counselling and Educational Support</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmacist partner provides medication counselling and educational support in person during initial interview and follow up with patient</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interim telephone follow-up</intervention_name>
    <description>Interim telephone follow-up conducted by the pharmacist partner since the last in-person follow-up &amp; a minimum of 1-2 weeks after the last in-person follow-up that involved a dose adjustment, prescribing of adjunctive medication, or discontinuation of therapy. (Note: a telephone follow-up does not replace the scheduled in-person follow-up).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychotherapy referral</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmacist partner collaborates with physician to arrange referral to psychologist/psychiatrist for psychotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Pharmacist Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard pharmacy care (as outlined in the Alberta College of Pharmacist Standards of Practice for Pharmacist and Pharmacy technicians)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group (Standard Pharmacist Care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group (Pharmacist Interventions)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Adults (≥ 18 years of age) newly diagnosed with MDD and/or GAD, including:

          -  Patients starting on medications for the management of adults with MDD

          -  Patients starting on medications for the management of GAD

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Non-Alberta residents

          -  Unwilling or unable to participate in regular follow-up visits

          -  Unwilling to participate/sign consent form

          -  ≥2 suicide attempts per year

          -  Severe, psychotic, and catatonic depression

          -  History of and/or current substance abuse, intoxication, addiction or withdrawal

          -  Patients diagnosed with comorbid anxiety disorders other than GAD, including: panic
             -disorder, agoraphobia, specific phobia, social anxiety disorder, obsessive-compulsive
             disorder, posttraumatic stress disorder

          -  Patients diagnosed with comorbid depressive disorder other than MDD, including:
             depressive disorder due to another medical condition (e.g. hypothyroidism, MS, OSA,
             -Parkinsons, stroke, TBI, Vitamin B12 insufficiency, Huntington disease, adrenal
             insufficiency, mononucleosis, systemic lupus erythematosus), adjustment disorder with
             depressed mood

          -  Patients diagnosed with concurrent ADHD, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia and
             schizoaffective disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yazid Al Hamarneh, BSc (Pharm), PhD, CDM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yazid Al Hamarneh, BSc (Pharm), PhD, CDM</last_name>
    <phone>(780) 492-9608</phone>
    <email>yazid.alhamarneh@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matthew Chow, BSc Pharm, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>(587) 999-0778</phone>
    <email>mchow1@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2R3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yazid Al Hamarneh, BSc (Pharm), PhD, CDM</last_name>
      <phone>(780) 492-9608</phone>
      <email>Yazid.Alhamarneh@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Matthew Chow, BScPharm, PharmD</last_name>
      <phone>(587)999-0778</phone>
      <email>mchow1@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacist</keyword>
  <keyword>Prescribing</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Generalized Anxiety Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Mental Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Expanded Scope</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

