<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04413773</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VideoAnx2020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04413773</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Anxiety Reduction in Children by Using Simple Explanation Videos</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Simple Explanation Videos to Reduce Perioperative Patient Anxiety in Children.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The reduction of preoperative anxiety in children and adolescents before an elective surgical
      procedure is an important clinical question in perioperative care. Adequate, age-appropriate
      patient information about the processes of the inpatient stay plays an important role in
      order to address possible worries and fears to reduce.

      The medium video is popular with children and adolescents today and offers the possibility of
      an easily understandable and vivid presentation of information.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studies by the health insurance companies, scientific publications and economic papers show
      that in times of increasing economic interests of the hospitals and the resulting necessity
      of economic working methods in the medical system, less time remains for human interaction.
      This creates areas of conflict, such as the patient's right to information regarding the time
      available to medical personnel. This in turn leads to significant stress factors in patients
      who are involved in the treatment and mostly on the communication level, such as &quot;Missing
      information&quot;, &quot;misunderstood visit&quot;, &quot;missing partnership relationship&quot; refer to what is
      reflected in patient satisfaction and fears. Studies show how important good perioperative
      psychosocial care is for reducing these circumstances in children, also and especially in the
      context of further development. The drug options for calming and reducing anxiety are already
      known, but there are also increasing numbers of non-drug approaches to reducing anxiety and
      stress in the literature. Painting therapy and clinic clowns are examples. However, access to
      such resources is limited and costs are permanently high. New technologies, e.g. mobile
      phones and tablets, with the associated media, increasingly finding their way into our
      society, are now inexpensive to buy and have become an integral part of most households. Such
      devices and media are increasingly used in clinical studies and patient care. Their use is
      tested extensively in modern medicine, e.g. to avoid unnecessary postoperative consultations
      in the emergency room or to increase cognitive learning for children. Even small children can
      use and understand these media early on. Videos are one of the most common media already
      understood by the smallest patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perioperative Anxiety in Children (T1 vs. T2, TAU vs. Video)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint was to analyze the preoperative state-anxiety in children before (t1) and after (t2) the intervention (video), compared with standard care (TAU). we use State-Trait-Anxiety-Operation-Inventory</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perioperative Anxiety in Parental Report (T1 vs. T2, TAU vs. Video)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary endpoint was to analyze the preoperative trait-anxiety in children, as well as the preoperative state- and trait-anxiety in the parental report. We use the State-Trait-Anxiety-Operation-Inventory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nurse reported anxiety before and after Intervention (T1 vs. T2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>we analyzed the nurse-reported anxiety status of the child before (t1) and after (t2) the intervention, we use a short State-Anxiety-Inventory (Krohne et al. 2005)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perioperative Anxiety separated in state and trait anxiety (T1 vs T2, TAU vs Video)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>difference between anxiety levels, again separated in state and trait, reported by children, We use the State-Trait-Anxiety-Operation-Inventory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Perioperative Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment as Usual, Explanation of standard procedures before, during and after surgery by nurse</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual + Video</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment as usual and additionally Video</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual + Video</intervention_name>
    <description>Additionally to treatment as usual a video is shown to participant about procedures on the ward before, during and after surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual + Video</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>Explanation of standard procedures before, during and after surgery by nurse</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients (children) who present themselves planned in the Altona Children's
             Hospital or in the University Clinic Hamburg Eppendorf in the course of an upcoming
             elective operation.

          2. The surgical intervention must take place in one of the following body regions:
             thorax, abdomen and / or extremities (incl. Head and neck)

          3. A signed declaration of consent from the parents or legal guardians is available

          4. The patient has given a declaration of consent

          5. No mental illnesses may be diagnosed

          6. No chronic pre-existing conditions may be diagnosed

          7. Age of the patients is between 6 and 17 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. No signed declaration of consent from the parents or legal guardians available

          2. There is no signed declaration of consent from the patient
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julian Trah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of pediatric surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Hamburg Eppendorf - Department of pediatric surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Altona Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>22763</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. med. Julian Trah</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anxiety, Video education, perioperative</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

