<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04442451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HR-2402</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04442451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanisms of Fatigability With Pre-Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanisms of Fatigability With Pre-Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Marquette University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Illinois at Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Marquette University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal of this study is determine whether vascular dysfunction at multiple levels
      along the vascular tree (macro- and micro-vasculature) contribute to greater exercise
      fatigability of lower limb muscles in people with pre-diabetes (Pre-D). Specifically, we will
      investigate endothelial function and nitric oxide-bioavailability as potential mechanism(s)
      for the fatigability in people with Pre-D. Our central hypothesis is that impaired vascular
      function impedes blood flow and blunts subsequent oxygen delivery to skeletal muscle during
      exercise, resulting in excessive exercise fatigability of lower limb muscles in people with
      Pre-D. We include people with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2D) (without neuropathy or insulin
      dependence) to understand fatigability across the disease spectrum and compare them to Pre-D
      and controls. In contrast to most of the human literature, participant groups will be matched
      for physical activity levels, age, sex, and body mass index (BMI) because these potential
      confounders are not typically controlled in these studies. We will also investigate a novel
      exercise training intervention that involves blood flow restriction (BFR) to the exercising
      leg, and is known to improve vascular function along different levels of the vascular tree in
      young and older adults, but has not been investigated in people with Pre-D or T2D. To achieve
      Aim 2, we will measure endothelial function in intact large conduit arteries and arterioles
      isolated from skeletal muscle biopsies before and after the training intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim 1: Determine if vascular dysfunction is a mechanism for excessive fatigability in people
      with Pre-D.

      Aim 1.1. Compare leg blood flow and skeletal muscle oxygenation in response to dynamic
      fatiguing exercise of the lower limb between people with Pre-D, T2D and controls. Skeletal
      muscle blood flow through the femoral artery will be quantified with Doppler ultrasonography
      and skeletal muscle oxygenation will be measured with near infrared spectroscopy (NIRS)
      during a dynamic fatiguing knee extension exercise. Hypothesis: People with Pre-D will have a
      blunted leg blood flow response and lower skeletal muscle oxygenation during dynamic
      fatiguing exercise than matched controls, but less than people with T2D.

      Aim 1.2. Determine endothelial vascular function at macro- and micro-vascular levels in
      people with Pre-D. Nitric oxide-mediated dilation will be assessed in vivo with flow-mediated
      dilation (FMD) of the femoral artery using Doppler ultrasonography and ex-vivo with both
      flow-induced and acetylcholine-induced dilation of isolated arterioles extracted from vastus
      lateralis muscle biopsies using videomicroscopy from the same participants studied in Aim
      1.1. Hypothesis: Participants with vascular dysfunction (reduced nitric oxide-mediated
      dilation in the femoral artery and isolated skeletal muscle arteriole) will have increased
      fatigability.

      Aim 2: Assess the vascular mechanisms for improved blood flow and fatigability in response to
      dynamic exercise training with blood flow restriction in people with Pre-D. People with Pre-D
      and T2D will perform 8 weeks of bilateral dynamic strength training with and without BFR.
      Hypothesis 2: Vascular function and fatigability will improve with dynamic resistance
      exercise training coupled with BRF, and these improvements will be greater than exercise
      training without BFR.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Aim 2:
Each participant will attend 3 sessions per week for 8 weeks. A training session will start with a 10-minute warm up on a bike ergometer. Each leg will then perform low-load resistance training (20% of 1-RM) for 4 sets of contractions with 15 contractions per set of contractions with a 30 second rest between each set of contractions while seated in a knee extension weight machine. One leg will be randomized to always perform the training with blood flow restriction (BFR leg) while the contralateral leg performs the exercise training without blood flow occlusion (Control leg).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Strength - One Repetition Maximum (1 RM)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 RM will be assessed on a weekly basis and the loads adjusted accordingly for the 8 weeks resistance training and before and 3-days after completion of training.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in 1 RM after 8 weeks resistance training. 1 RM is the greatest weight achieved through the full range of motion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Strength - Maximal Voluntary Contraction (MVC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in MVC after 8 weeks resistance training. MVC is the greatest force generated by isometric contraction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigability - Reduction in Power</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in power during fatiguing protocol of the knee extensors with a 20% MVC load will be performed on the Biodex dynamometer on each leg on separate days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigability - Reduction Maximal Voluntary Contraction (MVC) Force</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in MVC force following fatiguing protocol of the knee extensors with a 20% MVC load will be performed on the Biodex dynamometer on each leg on separate days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Voluntary Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification voluntary activation during maximal voluntary isometric contractions with the interpolated twitch technique using brief double pulses of electrical stimulation (Digitimer DS7AH, Welwyn Garden City, UK) at maximal levels with pad electrodes over the quadriceps.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Leg Blood Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Femoral artery mean blood velocity and femoral artery diameter will be measured using Doppler ultrasonography before and immediately after the fatiguing task in each leg.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Near-Infrared Spectroscopy (NIRS) Recording of Skeletal Muscle Oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Used to quantify blood flow kinetics of the knee extensor muscle tissue (rectus femoris and vastus lateralis) during the dynamic, fatiguing exercise in each leg.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Flow-Mediated Dilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 3-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>In vivo assessment of endothelial function of the femoral artery at rest using Doppler ultrasonography.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Flow- and Acetylcholine-Induced Vasodilation in Skeletal Muscle Arterioles Ex Vivo</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 10-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To measure flow-induced dilation, differential flow will be produced by simultaneously changing the heights of pressure reservoirs in equal and opposite directions to generate an intraluminal pressure gradient of Δ10-Δ100 cmH2O (equivalent to ~7-70 mmHg), which covers the physiological range of arteriole pressure in the human body. To measure NO bioavailability, vascular responses to the endothelium-dependent dilator acetylcholine (ACh; 10-9 -10-4 M) and endothelium-independent dilator sodium nitroprusside (SNP; 10-12-10-4 M) will be measured in the presence and absence of NO synthase (NOS) inhibitor Nω-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME; 10-4 M). Maximal vessel diameter will be determined by papaverine (10-4 M) addition at the end of each experiment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle Volume - Proton Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 2-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>MRI of the thigh to determine muscle volume of the knee extensor muscles in each leg.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle Metabolism - Phosphorus Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (31P-MRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and 2-days after completion of exercise training intervention of 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>31 P-MRS is used to noninvasively measure muscle metabolism by calculating intracellular ATP, ADP, phosphocreatine (PCr), inorganic phosphate (Pi), and pH in the quadriceps of participants. This measurement is conducted while participants perform fatiguing knee extensor exercise in the magnetic bore.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Pre-diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low-load knee extension resistance training (20% of 1-RM) without blood flow restriction. A 10-cm wide inflatable cuff will be placed around the upper portion of the thigh but not inflated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Blood Flow Restriction Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low-load knee extension resistance training (20% of 1-RM) with blood flow restriction using a 10-cm wide inflatable cuff placed around the most proximal part of the exercising thigh. Blood flow will be restricted in the BFR leg at above the limb occlusion pressure of the and this will be determined prior to the exercise while the participant is seated in the knee extensor machine. The cuff pressure during the BFR protocol will be 10 mmHg above limb occlusion pressure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Each participant will attend 3 sessions per week for 8 weeks. Participants will perform low-load knee extension resistance training (20% of 1-RM) without blood flow restriction on the designated leg for 4 sets of contractions with 15 contractions per set of contractions with a 30 second rest between each set of contractions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Flow Restriction Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Each participant will attend 3 sessions per week for 8 weeks. Participants will perform low-load knee extension resistance training (20% of 1-RM) with blood flow restriction on the designated leg for 4 sets of contractions with 15 contractions per set of contractions with a 30 second rest between each set of contractions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Blood Flow Restriction Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women adults &lt;75 years

          -  Pre-diabetes [glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) of 5.7-6.4% and fasting plasma glucose
             100-125 mg/dL at the time of initial screening]

          -  Controls [normoglycemic with a HbA1c level ≤5.6% and fasting blood glucose ≤ 99 mg/dL
             (5.5 mmol/L)]

          -  Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus [elevated glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) &gt;6.5% and &lt;10%]

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Signs or symptoms of neuropathy

          -  Medications associated with advanced stages of T2D including insulin

          -  Poor glycemic control (HbA1c&gt;10%)

          -  Peripheral edema

          -  Severe obesity (BMI, &gt;45kg·m-2)

          -  Untreated hypothyroidism

          -  Smoking

          -  Hypertension

          -  Cardiovascular or musculoskeletal disease that preclude exercise testing

          -  Hormone replacement drugs or vasoactive medications

          -  Pre-menopausal women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandra K Hunter, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>414-288-6673</phone>
    <email>sandra.hunter@marquette.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Pre-diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigability</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Flow Restriction Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular Function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

