<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04443088</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INV-1120-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04443088</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1, Multi-Center, Safety, Dose Escalation, Pharmacokinetics of INV-1120 in Adult Patients Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Multi-Center, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Preliminary Evidence of Antitumor Activity of INV-1120 as a Single Agent in Adult Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shenzhen Ionova Life Sciences Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shenzhen Ionova Life Sciences Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase 1, first-in-human, open-label dose-escalation study to determine the MTD and RP2D, and
      to assess the DLT of INV-1120 (also referred to as investigational product or IP). The
      safety, tolerability, and PK of INV-1120 will be assessed in adult patients with advanced
      solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase 1, open-label dose-escalation study to determine the MTD and RP2D, and to assess the
      DLT of INV-1120 (also referred to as investigational product or IP). The safety,
      tolerability, and PK of INV-1120 will be assessed in adult patients with advanced solid
      tumors. Increasing doses of INV-1120 will be administered to cohorts of 3-6 participants,
      until the MTD or MAD is reached. The MTD will generally be considered as the RP2D. However,
      the RP2D may also be determined based on the data of pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamic
      biomarkers in blood and the preliminary clinical activity of INV-1120, as well as the
      incidence rate and nature of the toxicities observed in subsequent cycles beyond Cycle 1.

      The total number of patients enrolled in the study will depend upon the number of
      dose-escalation cohorts. It is estimated that approximately 36 evaluable patients will be
      enrolled in the dose-escalation part of this study. This multicenter study will be conducted
      in the United States.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 26, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine DLTs and RP2Ds in INV-1120</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To evaluate dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) of INV-1120 in patients with advanced cancer and to establish a recommended Phase 2 dose (RP2D)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the PK using AUC of INV-1120</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To determine the pharmacokinetics (PK) using AUC of INV-1120 after a single dose and at steady state after multiple doses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the PK using Cmax of INV-1120</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To determine the pharmacokinetics (PK) using Cmax of INV-1120 after a single dose and at steady state after multiple doses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize investigator defined response overall response rate (ORR) using RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To characterize Investigator defined ORR using RECIST v1.1 response criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize investigator defined response duration of rate (DOR) using RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To characterize investigator defined DOR as preliminary evidence of antitumor activity of INV-1120 in length of time (in days) from last study drug administration to time patient has progressive disease using RECIST v1.1.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumor, Adult</condition>
  <condition>Cancer Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Solid Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumor, Unspecified, Adult</condition>
  <condition>Tumor, Solid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive escalating doses of INV-1120 orally once a day until un-acceptable toxicity or disease progression. Three to six patients will be enrolled per cohort to evaluate the safety and pharmacokinetics for each dose level. After the last patient in each cohort completes Cycle 1 (DLT observation period of 28 days), the Safety Evaluation Team (SET) will evaluate the safety data and pharmacokinetic collected from Cycle 1, and make the decision whether to escalate the dose before opening the second cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INV-1120</intervention_name>
    <description>INV-1120 is an investigational selective and potent small molecule indicated for the treatment of solid malignancies including, but not limited to colorectal, breast, pancreatic, lung and liver cancers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent, according to local guidelines, signed and dated by the
             patient prior to the performance of any study-specific procedures, sampling, or
             analyses;

          2. Patient must be ≥18 years-of-age at the time of signature of the informed consent form
             (ICF);

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status score of 0 or 1;

          4. Patients with histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced solid tumors which
             have progressed on or following standard therapy or for which no standard therapy
             exists;

          5. Patients with life expectancy ≥3 months;

          6. Patients with at least one measurable lesion by computed tomography (CT) or magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI), according to RECIST v1.1. Tumor lesions that have been
             irradiated ≥4 weeks before the start of treatment, and have subsequently had
             documented progression, may be chosen as target lesions in the absence of measurable
             lesions that have not been irradiated;

          7. Patients whose laboratory data at screening meet the acceptable criteria for bone
             marrow, liver function and renal function.

          8. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             (urinary or serum beta human chorionic gonadotropin [β-hCG]) during screening. A woman
             is considered of childbearing potential (fertile) following menarche and until
             becoming postmenopausal unless permanently sterile. A postmenopausal state is defined
             as no menses for 12 months without an alternative medical cause. Postmenopausal women
             can be included;

          9. Male patients with female partners of childbearing potential and female patients of
             childbearing potential are required to use two forms of acceptable contraception,
             including one barrier method, during their participation in the study and for 3 months
             following last dose. Medically acceptable contraception includes:

               -  Hormonal methods (Needs to have been instituted at least 1 month prior to the
                  first dose of study drug):

               -  Barrier methods:

               -  Abstinence, defined as refraining from sexual intercourse

         10. Male patients must also refrain from donating sperm from the first dose of study drug
             until 3 months after the last dose of study drug;

         11. Patients must be able to swallow and retain orally administered medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History (≤5 years) or current evidence of cancer that is histologically distinct from
             the cancer under study, except for cervical carcinoma in situ, superficial
             non-invasive bladder tumors, or curatively treated Stage I non-melanoma skin cancer;

          2. Known serious allergy to investigational drug or excipients (microcrystalline
             cellulose);

          3. History of severe autoimmune disease (including significant ongoing immune-related
             adverse events of prior immune-oncology therapy) or autoimmune disorder that requires
             chronic systemic corticosteroid treatment at immunosuppressive doses (prednisone &gt;10
             mg/day or equivalent);

          4. Known malignant central nervous system disease other than neurologically stable,
             treated brain metastases - defined as metastases having been treated by surgery,
             surgery plus radiotherapy or radiotherapy alone, with no evidence of progression or
             hemorrhage and off any systemic corticosteroids for at least 4 weeks prior to signing
             the consent;

          5. History (within 4 weeks of starting treatment) or evidence of active infections (Grade
             ≥2);

          6. History of seropositive status for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B
             virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus (HCV) at any time before the start of treatment:
             Testing for seropositive status during screening will be at the discretion of the
             Investigator in patients without previously reported results;

          7. History or evidence of any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other
             conditions that, in the opinion of the Investigator and Sponsor, could affect the
             patient's participation in the study, such as any disorder or surgical procedure that
             could impact the absorption of study drug from the gastrointestinal tract.

          8. History (≤6 months before the start of treatment) or evidence of any of the following:
             acute myocardial infarction, unstable angina pectoris, coronary artery bypass graft,
             cerebrovascular accident, or transient ischemic attack;

          9. Patients who have impaired cardiac function or clinically significant cardiac
             diseases, including any of the following:

               -  Congenital long QT syndrome;

               -  Significant ventricular or supraventricular arrhythmias (patients with sinus
                  arrhythmia or chronic rate-controlled atrial fibrillation in the absence of other
                  cardiac abnormalities are eligible);

               -  LVEF &lt; 50% by ECHO or MUGA;

               -  Other clinically significant heart disease such as known congestive heart failure
                  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III-IV;

         10. Patients with QT interval ≥470 msec in females and ≥450 msec in males at screening
             using Fridericia's formula (determined as the mean of 3 QTcF values from the screening
             triplicate ECG obtained with adequate quality);

         11. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

         12. WOCBP and sexually active fertile men with WOCBP partners who are unwilling or unable
             to use acceptable contraception method to avoid pregnancy for at least 1 month before
             the first dose of the study drug, during the study, and for 3 months after the last
             dose of study drug;

         13. Male patient who plans to father a child while enrolled in this study or within 3
             months after the last dose of study drug;

         14. Not recovered from toxicity from prior anticancer therapy to baseline or Grade 1
             (except toxicities which are not clinically significant such as alopecia, skin
             discoloration).

         15. History of an allogeneic bone marrow or solid organ transplant;

         16. Use of systemic anti-cancer agent (except luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH)
             agonists, bisphosphonates and denosumab) or investigational drug ≤28 days or five
             half-lives whichever is longer prior to the first dose of INV-1120;

         17. Radiation therapy ≤28 days prior to the first dose of INV-1120, or likely to require
             radiation therapy at any time until the 30 days after the last dose of INV-1120,
             except for palliative radiation therapy limited to non-target bone lesions;

         18. Major surgery within 4 weeks before enrollment or surgery with ongoing post-operative
             complications);

         19. History of transfusion of platelets ≤2 weeks before the start of treatment;

         20. Patients who start erythropoietin or granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF),
             pegfilgrastim, or filgrastim ≤2 weeks before start of treatment;

         21. Patients taking medications known to have a significant risk of causing Torsades de
             Pointes. Patients who have discontinued any of these medications must have a wash-out
             period of at least 7 days or at least 5 half-lives of the drug (whichever is longer)
             prior to the first dose of study drug.

         22. History of use of H2 blockers (&lt;24 hours before the first dose of INV-1120 and during
             the study) and proton pump inhibitors (&lt;5 days before the first dose of INV-1120 and
             during the study).

         23. Patients with recent (&lt; 6 months) history, or are currently being treated for
             gastroesophageal ulcer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monica Mehta, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1 984 710 8012</phone>
    <email>monica.mehta@syneoshealth.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>START</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angela Galindo</last_name>
      <email>Angela.Galindo@startthecure.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amita Patnaik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Manea</last_name>
      <phone>210-450-1821</phone>
      <email>Maneap@uthscsa.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Sarantopoulos, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ionova</keyword>
  <keyword>Ionova Bio</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Oncology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

