<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04446195</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20200618</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04446195</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Individualized Intervention on the Quality of Bowel Preparation</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Individualized Intervention on the Quality of Intestinal Preparation: a Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is one of the most common malignant tumors in the clinic. Colonoscopy
      is an important means of screening, diagnosis and treatment of colorectal diseases. The
      accuracy of diagnosis and the safety of treatment are closely related to the quality of
      intestinal preparation. Inadequate bowel preparation leads to poor effect of colonoscopy,
      which will reduce the effectiveness and safety of colonoscopy, increase the difficulty and
      time of colonoscopy, and increase the need of repeated colonoscopy. There are many factors
      that lead to poor bowel preparation. Recently, a number of studies at home and abroad have
      evaluated the risk factors related to insufficient bowel preparation. Obesity, men, older
      age, previous colon surgery history, accompanied by other diseases (such as diabetes,
      Parkinson's disease), taking antidepressants and other factors can affect the effect of bowel
      preparation. Although the research of intestinal preparation intervention and education
      methods has made a lot of progress, but in a series of reports, there are still a
      considerable number of patients in colonoscopy problems of intestinal preparation. At
      present, there are few researches on individualized intervention aiming at the risk factors
      of inadequate bowel preparation in China, so it is urgent to explore individualized bowel
      preparation scheme suitable for different populations. Therefore, the purpose of this
      experiment is to study individualized dryness aiming at the risk factors of insufficient
      bowel preparation in patients with the risk factors of insufficient bowel preparation The
      effect of pre-treatment on the quality of intestinal preparation can provide reference for
      improving the quality of intestinal preparation in patients with inadequate intestinal
      preparation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is a malignant tumor originates from colorectal mucosa epithelium. It
      is one of the most common malignant tumors in the world. Incidence rate of lung cancer is
      second only to lung cancer and breast cancer worldwide. In recent years, with the continuous
      improvement of people's living standard, changes in diet and diet structure and aging of
      population, the incidence rate and mortality rate of colorectal cancer in China have been
      increasing. A significant proportion of colorectal cancer patients have no characteristic
      clinical symptoms and reported symptoms. Many colorectal cancers have reached the middle and
      late stage when they are discovered, and their prognosis is poor. It can be seen that early
      prevention of colorectal cancer is very important. Timely screening for colorectal adenomas
      and endoscopic resection are the most effective measures to prevent colorectal cancer.
      Colonoscopy is currently recognized as the gold standard for colorectal cancer screening,
      which can not only detect early precancerous lesions, but also remove precancerous lesions
      and block the formation of colorectal cancer.Colonoscopy is an important means of screening,
      diagnosis and treatment of colonic diseases. The accuracy of diagnosis and the safety of
      treatment are closely related to the quality of intestinal preparation. Adequate intestinal
      preparation can make patients obtain higher intestinal cleanliness, ensure the integrity and
      correctness of colonoscopy, improve the detection rate of polyps and adenomas, increase the
      rate of cecal intubation and reduce the follow-up time The occurrence of adverse events such
      as shortened interval, intestinal perforation and missed diagnosis is of great significance
      for the realization of high-quality enteroscopy diagnosis and treatment.Bowel preparation is
      not a simple cathartic process, it involves all aspects of communication between patients and
      doctors. Good intestinal preparation includes following dietary restrictions before
      examination, applying adequate amount of appropriate cathartic drugs during intestinal
      preparation, waiting for the appropriate time interval between colonoscopies after intestinal
      preparation, and appropriate amount of active drinking water, etc. Strict dietary restriction
      and bowel cleaning are the necessary conditions to improve the quality of bowel preparation.
      Kang x et al. Showed that 18% to 30.5% of patients had insufficient bowel preparation [.
      Clinically, there may be more patients with poor bowel preparation. Inadequate bowel
      preparation will lead to longer operation time, more difficult catheterization of cecum,
      lower detection rate of adenoma and shorter follow-up time, which will increase the cost of
      colonoscopy. At present, Boston scale is widely used to evaluate the quality of intestinal
      preparation. The Boston scale divides the colon into three segments (cecum and ascending
      colon; hepatic, transverse and splenic flexure; descending, sigmoid and rectum). According to
      the worst-case to clean score, it is divided into four grades (0-3), with a total score of
      0-9. Boston scale ≥ 6 points indicates that the intestinal preparation is qualified.There are
      many factors that lead to poor bowel preparation. Recently, a number of studies at home and
      abroad have evaluated the risk factors related to insufficient bowel preparation. Obesity,
      men, older age, previous colon surgery history, accompanied by other diseases (such as
      diabetes, Parkinson's disease), taking antidepressants and other factors can affect the
      effect of bowel preparation. Combined with the literature at home and abroad and the
      characteristics of Chinese people, the guidelines for gut preparation related to the
      diagnosis and treatment of digestive endoscopy in China suggest that the following factors
      are the risk factors for inadequate gut preparation in China: chronic constipation, failure
      to prepare the gut in strict accordance with the requirements (such as high fiber diet before
      operation, insufficient peg intake), body mass index &gt; 25 kg / m2, age &gt; 70 years old, colon
      surgery history With other diseases (such as diabetes, Parkinson's disease, history of stroke
      or spinal cord injury, etc.), application of tricyclic antidepressants or anesthetics.In
      addition, the guidelines for gut preparation related to the diagnosis and treatment of
      digestive endoscopy in China suggest that if the patient's gut preparation is not sufficient
      during the endoscopic examination, it should be actively evaluated and remedial measures
      should be taken or the endoscopic examination should be rescheduled. For the patients with
      the risk factors of insufficient intestinal preparation, other auxiliary measures can be
      taken to improve the intestinal preparation, such as the 4L peg program, low residue diet
      three days before endoscopic diagnosis and treatment, gastrointestinal motility promoting
      drugs, etc.; in addition, it is also of great value to further strengthen the education
      related to the optimization of intestinal preparation for the patients.In recent years, with
      the continuous development of China's economy, the continuous improvement of people's living
      conditions, and the continuous strengthening of patients' health awareness, colonoscopy has
      become one of the necessary items for many people's routine physical examination. However, in
      most medical institutions, when guiding patients to prepare for intestinal tract, there are
      some problems, such as lack of management, lack of detailed explanation, and complex process.
      These problems lead to the lack of understanding of intestinal tract preparation process for
      patients, thus affecting the preparation work before patients' examination and the follow-up
      treatment plan. Therefore, it has become one of the most important issues to study how to
      improve the intervention and guidance methods of patients' intestinal preparation and improve
      the quality of patients' intestinal preparation.Although the research of intestinal
      preparation intervention and education methods has made a lot of progress, various methods of
      intervention and guidance for patients before colonoscopy have been proposed at home and
      abroad to improve the quality of intestinal preparation. However, in a series of reports,
      there are still a considerable number of patients in the colonoscopy problems of intestinal
      preparation.At present, there are few researches on individualized intervention aiming at the
      risk factors of inadequate bowel preparation in China, so it is urgent to explore
      individualized bowel preparation programs suitable for different populations. Therefore, in
      this experiment, we designed individualized intervention for patients with insufficient bowel
      preparation (mainly from the following aspects: chronic constipation, not strictly in
      accordance with the requirements Bowel preparation, body mass index &gt; 25 kg / m2, age &gt; 70
      years old, with other diseases such as diabetes, Parkinson's disease, history of stroke or
      spinal cord injury, application of tricyclic antidepressants or anesthetics). The purpose of
      the study is to study the effect of individualized intervention on the quality of intestinal
      preparation for patients with insufficient intestinal preparation, and to provide reference
      for improving the quality of intestinal preparation for patients with insufficient intestinal
      preparation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bowel preparation pass rate</measure>
    <time_frame>During colonoscopy, endoscopists evaluated the quality of bowel preparation according to the Boston bowel preparation scale.</time_frame>
    <description>The Boston Bowel preparation scale ≥6 indicates qualified intestinal preparation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">408</enrollment>
  <condition>Bowel Preparation Solutions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group received routine intestinal preparation education.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental group was treated with routine intestinal preparation education and individualized intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individualized Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>In this study, patients with the risk factors of insufficient intestinal preparation were treated with individualized intervention (mainly from the following aspects: chronic constipation, intestinal preparation not strictly in accordance with the requirements, body mass index &gt; 25 kg / m2, age &gt; 70 years old, with other diseases such as diabetes, Parkinson's disease, history of stroke or spinal cord injury, etc., application of tricyclic antidepressants or anesthetics).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria：

          1. Aged between 18-75

          2. Patients with insufficient bowel preparation

          3. Patients without cognitive and communication barriers

          4. Informed consent, voluntary participation in the study Exclusion criteria：

        1. Severe suppurative inflammation of anus and rectum 2. Severe acute enteritis and
        ischemic enteropathy 3. After partial colorectal resection 4. Peritonitis, intestinal
        perforation, extensive adhesion in the abdominal cavity and intestinal stenosis caused by
        various reasons 5. Large abdominal aneurysm, highly abnormal bowel flexion and late cancer
        with extensive intraperitoneal metastasis 6. Dysphagia or impaired swallowing reflex 7.
        Obvious gastroparesis or gastric outlet obstruction or intestinal obstruction 8. Severe
        chronic renal failure (creatinine clearance &lt; 30 ml / min) 9. Severe congestive heart
        failure (NYHA class III or IV) 10. Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic pressure &gt; 170 mm
        Hg, diastolic pressure &gt; 100 mm Hg) 11. Toxic colitis or megacolon 12. Disorder of water
        and electrolyte 13. Pregnancy or lactation 14. Mental patients 15. Failure to give informed
        consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jinhai Wang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University,Xi'an, Shanxi, China</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jinhai Wang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-29-13609281113</phone>
    <email>jinhaiwang@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yaqin Cai, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-29-13032920414</phone>
    <email>1610779309@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The second affiliated hospital of xi'an jiaotong university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shaanxi</state>
        <zip>710004</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jinhai Wang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86-29-13609281113</phone>
      <email>jinhaiwang@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

