<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04448938</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-A01560-39</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04448938</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RESting-state Functional MRI in Patients With Optic Neuritis for ANticipation of reCovEry</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESONANCE</acronym>
  <official_title>RESting-state Functional MRI in Patients With Optic Neuritis for ANticipation of reCovEry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondation Ophtalmologique Adolphe de Rothschild</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondation Ophtalmologique Adolphe de Rothschild</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      When patients arrive in the waiting room of the MRI department, patients will be given the
      briefing note explaining the purpose of the study and how it is going. During the
      consultation, the radiologist will check the inclusion and non-inclusion criteria, and will
      take the time to answer all of the patient's questions about the study. If the patient agrees
      to participate in the research, the investigating doctor will obtain his consent.

      The MRI examination will be performed on a 3T multi-parametric MRI. Compared to the standard
      protocol, patients will benefit from an additional sequence of f-mRI, called resting state,
      and performed before injection of gadolinium contrast agent.

      A consultation with an ophthalmologist will also be carried out the same day, at the Adolphe
      de Rothschild Foundation. During this visit, an OCT examination (optical coherence
      tomography), a visual field as well as the measurement of visual acuity will be carried out,
      in accordance with the treatment usually practiced at the Adolphe de Rothschild Foundation.

      The subjects of the control group who agreed to participate will benefit from an MRI
      examination which will include, in addition to the sequences planned for these patients
      according to their indications, the two non-injected sequences which will be performed on
      patients with suspected NO.

      The possible existence of visual problems in the subjects of the control group will also be
      asked to them by interrogation. No eye exams or follow-up visits are planned, and control
      group participation will end after the MRI scan.

      Patients with NO will be seen in consultation by an ophthalmologist during a follow-up visit
      approximately 6 months after diagnosis. During this consultation, an OCT, a visual field and
      the measurement of visual acuity will be performed. This visit and the examinations carried
      out correspond to the usual care of patients suffering from NO and followed at the Adolphe de
      Rothschild Foundation Hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The ophthalmological functional recovery at 6 months will be assessed by measuring the low contrast visual acuity on the ETDRS scale</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Determine the Prognostic Value of the Parameters Measured at the Local r-fMRI on Ophthalmological Functional Recovery at 6 Months of Patients Diagnosed With NO</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>optic neuritis</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>The MRI examination will be performed on a 3T multi-parametric MRI. Compared to the standard protocol, patients will benefit from an additional sequence of f-mRI, called resting state, and performed before injection of gadolinium contrast agent.
A consultation with an ophthalmologist will also be carried out the same day, at the Adolphe de Rothschild Foundation.
The subjects of the control group who agreed to participate will benefit from an MRI examination which will include, in addition to the sequences planned for these patients according to their indications, the two non-injected sequences which will be performed on patients with suspected NO.</description>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>optic neuritis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>visual acuity</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with NO will be seen in consultation by an ophthalmologist during a follow-up visit approximately 6 months after diagnosis. During this consultation, an OCT, a visual field and the measurement of visual acuity will be performed. This visit and the examinations carried out correspond to the usual care of patients suffering from NO and followed at the Adolphe de Rothschild Foundation Hospital</description>
    <arm_group_label>optic neuritis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with clinical suspicion of NO who must perform an MRI for the diagnosis of NO. A
        control group will also be set up to compare the visual functional networks of patients
        with NO with those of a sample of subjects free from NO.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients over 18 years of age Clinical suspicion of optic neuritis Benefiting from an MRI
        for exploration of optic neuritis Affiliate or beneficiary of a social security scheme
        Having received informed information about the study and having given their express consent
        to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Contraindication to absolute or relative MRI (in particular, pregnant or breastfeeding
        women) History of amblyopia Any pre-existing pathology leading to a decrease in vision
        (e.g. retinitis pigmentosa, AMD, etc.) Patient benefiting from a legal protection measure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondation A De Rothschild</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75019</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

