<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04443972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Furcation invlvement</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04443972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Injectable Beta-tricalcium Phosphate Clinically in Treatment of Grade II Furcation Involvement</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Injectable Beta- Tricalcium Phosphate as an Occlusive Barrier Membrane in Treatment of Grade ii Furcation Involvement (Clinical and Radiographic Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hams Hamed Abdelrahman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alexandria University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alexandria University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be conducted to evaluate clinically and radiographically the use of PD
      VitalOs cement® bone graft in the treatment of class II furcation defects comparing with
      Hydroxyapatite bone graft and biodegradable collagen membrane in the treatment of class II
      furcation defects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a randomized, controlled clinical trial. Patients were randomly divided into two
      equal groups, Group I (Test group): included seven Grade II furcation defects treated by beta
      tricalcium phosphate bone cement only.

      Group II (Control group): included seven Grade II furcation defects treated with granulated
      beta tricalcium phosphate bone graft covered by resorbable collagen membrane.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 4, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in plaque index scores (PI) according to Silness and Löe.</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Score 0 = no plaque in gingival area. Score 1= film of plaque adhering to the free gingival margin and the adjacent area of the tooth, plaque may only be recognized by running a probe across the tooth surface.
Score 2= moderate accumulation of soft deposits within the gingival pocket and on the gingival margin and/ or adjacent tooth surface which can be seen by the naked eye.
Score 3= abundant of soft matter within gingival pocket and/ or the gingival margin and adjacent tooth surface.
The scores from the four surfaces of the tooth were added and divided by (four) to give plaque index for each tooth; the plaque index score for an individual was obtained by adding the indices of the teeth and dividing by the number of the teeth examined.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in probing Pocket Depth(PPD)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The measurements were carried out to the defects selected using an 0.8 mm thick periodontal probe * with William`s calibration, which was marked from (1-10) mm, pocket depth of (1 mm) or less was recorded as (1mm),measurements exceeding (1mm) but less than (2mm) were recorded as (2mm) so that the probing pocket depth was measured to the nearest mm.
Probing pocket depth refers to the distance from the gingival margin to the bottom of the pocket. Mesial and distal pockets were measured as well as the furcation from the buccal aspect as close as possible to the contact points, facial and lingual pockets were measured at midline of roots.
Efforts were made to insert the probe parallel to the long axis of the roots. Light force was used during the introduction of the probe to the bottom of the pocket, third molars and teeth with enamel projections were excluded. (7)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in clinical Attachment Level</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The measurements were carried out to the defects selected using an 0.8 mm thick periodontal probe * with William`s calibration, which was marked from (1-10) mm, pocket depth of (1 mm) or less was recorded as (1mm),measurements exceeding (1mm) but less than (2mm) were recorded as (2mm) so that the probing pocket depth was measured to the nearest mm.
Probing pocket depth refers to the distance from the gingival margin to the bottom of the pocket. Mesial and distal pockets were measured as well as the furcation from the buccal aspect as close as possible to the contact points, facial and lingual pockets were measured at midline of roots.
Efforts were made to insert the probe parallel to the long axis of the roots. Light force was used during the introduction of the probe to the bottom of the pocket, third molars and teeth with enamel projections were excluded. (7)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in radiographic bone level (RBL)</measure>
    <time_frame>at basline, 3 and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in optical density(OD)</measure>
    <time_frame>at basline, 3 and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Furcation Defects</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD VitalOs cement® alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>class II furcation defects that will be treated with PD VitalOs cement® alone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD VitalOs cement® plus Bone graft and membrane</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PD VitalOs cement® and Hydroxyapatite bone graft and biodegradable collagen membrane in the treatment of class II furcation defects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PD VitalOs cement®</intervention_name>
    <description>PD VitalOs cement®* is a synthetic bone grafting cement designed for bone void filling and bone regeneration in dental surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD VitalOs cement® alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PD VitalOs cement® plus Bone graft and membrane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxyapatite bone graft</intervention_name>
    <description>a bioceramic bone substitute, providing a scaffold for bone deposition</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD VitalOs cement® plus Bone graft and membrane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>biodegardable collagen membrane</intervention_name>
    <description>provide efficacious barriers that were interposed between the flap and root surface.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD VitalOs cement® plus Bone graft and membrane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Presence of a lower molar with critical size grade II furcation defect (15) with a
             horizontal component of 4 mm and a vertical component of 4 to 6 mm (18), detected
             using Naber's probe and William's periodontal probe.

               -  Patient's age between 30 - 50 years.

               -  Both sexes.

               -  The patient should be psychologically accepting the procedures.

               -  Patients should be systemically free.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Uncooperative patients regarding oral hygiene measures performance.

               -  Patients with para functional habits.

               -  Smokers.

               -  Pregnant or lactating women.

               -  Patients who underwent any periodontal surgeries in the study site during the six
                  months prior to study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ahmed Hosny Elsayed, BDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>shahira Ali El Damaty, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gehan Sherif Kotry, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rania Abd El Aziz Fahmy, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Alexandria University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>outpatient clinic of oral medicine department, faculty of dentistry, Alexandria university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alexandria</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cutando A, Galindo P, Gómez-Moreno G, Arana C, Bolaños J, Acuña-Castroviejo D, Wang HL. Relationship between salivary melatonin and severity of periodontal disease. J Periodontol. 2006 Sep;77(9):1533-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16945031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowers GM, Schallhorn RG, McClain PK, Morrison GM, Morgan R, Reynolds MA. Factors influencing the outcome of regenerative therapy in mandibular Class II furcations: Part I. J Periodontol. 2003 Sep;74(9):1255-68.</citation>
    <PMID>14584858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laurell L, Gottlow J, Zybutz M, Persson R. Treatment of intrabony defects by different surgical procedures. A literature review. J Periodontol. 1998 Mar;69(3):303-13.</citation>
    <PMID>9579616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nasr HF, Aichelmann-Reidy ME, Yukna RA. Bone and bone substitutes. Periodontol 2000. 1999 Feb;19:74-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10321217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caton JG. Overview of clinical trials on periodontal regeneration. Ann Periodontol. 1997 Mar;2(1):215-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9151555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mendieta C, Williams RC. Periodontal regeneration with bioresorbable membranes. Curr Opin Periodontol. 1994:157-67. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8032456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gray JL, Hancock EB. Guided tissue regeneration. Nonabsorbable barriers. Dent Clin North Am. 1998 Jul;42(3):523-41.</citation>
    <PMID>9700453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baum BJ, Mooney DJ. The impact of tissue engineering on dentistry. J Am Dent Assoc. 2000 Mar;131(3):309-18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10715922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cury PR, Sallum EA, Nociti FH Jr, Sallum AW, Jeffcoatt MK. Long-term results of guided tissue regeneration therapy in the treatment of class II furcation defects: a randomized clinical trial. J Periodontol. 2003 Jan;74(1):3-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12593590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basten CH, Ammons WF Jr, Persson R. Long-term evaluation of root-resected molars: a retrospective study. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 1996 Jun;16(3):206-19.</citation>
    <PMID>9084307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamp SE, Nyman S, Lindhe J. Periodontal treatment of multirooted teeth. Results after 5 years. J Clin Periodontol. 1975 Aug;2(3):126-35.</citation>
    <PMID>1058213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirschfeld L, Wasserman B. A long-term survey of tooth loss in 600 treated periodontal patients. J Periodontol. 1978 May;49(5):225-37.</citation>
    <PMID>277674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kenney EB, Lekovic V, Elbaz JJ, Kovacvic K, Carranza FA Jr, Takei HH. The use of a porous hydroxylapatite implant in periodontal defects. II. Treatment of Class II furcation lesions in lower molars. J Periodontol. 1988 Feb;59(2):67-72.</citation>
    <PMID>2831333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eickholz P, Hausmann E. Evidence for healing of Class II and Class III furcations 24 months after guided tissue regeneration therapy: digital subtraction and clinical measurements. J Periodontol. 1999 Dec;70(12):1490-500.</citation>
    <PMID>10632525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Leonardis D, Garg AK, Pedrazzoli V, Pecora GE. Clinical evaluation of the treatment of class II furcation involvements with bioabsorbable barriers alone or associated with demineralized freeze-dried bone allografts. J Periodontol. 1999 Jan;70(1):8-12.</citation>
    <PMID>10052766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohura K, Bohner M, Hardouin P, Lemaître J, Pasquier G, Flautre B. Resorption of, and bone formation from, new beta-tricalcium phosphate-monocalcium phosphate cements: an in vivo study. J Biomed Mater Res. 1996 Feb;30(2):193-200.</citation>
    <PMID>9019484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flautre B, Lemaître J, Maynou C, Van Landuyt P, Hardouin P. Influence of polymeric additives on the biological properties of brushite cements: an experimental study in rabbit. J Biomed Mater Res A. 2003 Aug 1;66(2):214-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12888990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meikle MC, Papaioannou S, Ratledge TJ, Speight PM, Watt-Smith SR, Hill PA, Reynolds JJ. Effect of poly DL-lactide--co-glycolide implants and xenogeneic bone matrix-derived growth factors on calvarial bone repair in the rabbit. Biomaterials. 1994 Jun;15(7):513-21.</citation>
    <PMID>7918904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyamoto S, Takaoka K, Okada T, Yoshikawa H, Hashimoto J, Suzuki S, Ono K. Polylactic acid-polyethylene glycol block copolymer. A new biodegradable synthetic carrier for bone morphogenetic protein. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1993 Sep;(294):333-43.</citation>
    <PMID>8358939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aichelmann-Reidy ME, Yukna RA. Bone replacement grafts. The bone substitutes. Dent Clin North Am. 1998 Jul;42(3):491-503. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9700451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melcher AH. On the repair potential of periodontal tissues. J Periodontol. 1976 May;47(5):256-60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>775048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blumenthal NM. A clinical comparison of collagen membranes with e-PTFE membranes in the treatment of human mandibular buccal class II furcation defects. J Periodontol. 1993 Oct;64(10):925-33.</citation>
    <PMID>8277399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cortellini P, Prato GP. Guided tissue regeneration with a rubber dam: a five-case report. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 1994 Feb;14(1):8-15.</citation>
    <PMID>8005773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armitage GC. Development of a classification system for periodontal diseases and conditions. Ann Periodontol. 1999 Dec;4(1):1-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10863370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garrett S, Martin M, Egelberg J. Treatment of periodontal furcation defects. Coronally positioned flaps versus dura mater membranes in class II defects. J Clin Periodontol. 1990 Mar;17(3):179-85.</citation>
    <PMID>2319003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary TJ, Drake RB, Naylor JE. The plaque control record. J Periodontol. 1972 Jan;43(1):38.</citation>
    <PMID>4500182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SILNESS J, LOE H. PERIODONTAL DISEASE IN PREGNANCY. II. CORRELATION BETWEEN ORAL HYGIENE AND PERIODONTAL CONDTION. Acta Odontol Scand. 1964 Feb;22:121-35.</citation>
    <PMID>14158464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glavind L, Löe H. Errors in the clinical assessment of periodontal destruction. J Periodontal Res. 1967;2(3):180-4.</citation>
    <PMID>4237475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Alexandria University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hams Hamed Abdelrahman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Grade II Furcation defects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Furcation Defects</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

