<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04444895</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-743-3001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-004823-20</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04444895</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Long-Term Safety and Efficacy of Lanadelumab for Prevention of Acute Attacks of Non-histaminergic Angioedema With Normal C1-Inhibitor</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Long-Term Safety and Efficacy of Lanadelumab for Prevention Against Acute Attacks of Non-histaminergic Angioedema With Normal C1-Inhibitor (C1-INH)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shire</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the long-term safety and efficacy of repeated
      subcutaneous (SC) administration of lanadelumab in adolescents and adults with
      non-histaminergic angioedema with normal C1-inhibitor who completed study SHP643-303
      (NCT04206605).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study consists of 26-week treatment period (Day 0 to Day 182) and a 2-week follow-up
      period. Participants who completed the double-blind treatment period at Day 182 of Study
      SHP643-303 (NCT04206605) will enroll into this extension study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of the study up to follow up (Day 196)</time_frame>
    <description>A TEAE is defined as any event emerging or manifesting at or after the initiation of treatment with an investigational product or medicinal product or any existing event that worsens in either intensity or frequency following exposure to the investigational product or medicinal product. A SAE is any untoward clinical manifestation of signs, symptoms or outcomes (whether considered related to investigational product or not and at any dose: results in death, is life-threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization, results in persistent or significant disability/incapacity, congenital abnormality/birth defect, an important medical event. AESI will include hypersensitivity reactions, events of disordered coagulation such as bleeding AESI, hypercoagulable AESI. Number of participants with TEAEs including AESI and SAE will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Investigator-Confirmed Angioedema Attacks During the Treatment Period of Day 0 Through Day 182</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Day 182</time_frame>
    <description>An angioedema attack is defined as the symptoms or signs consistent with an attack in at least 1 of the following locations: peripheral angioedema (cutaneous swelling involving an extremity, the face, neck, torso, and/or genitourinary region), abdominal angioedema (abdominal pain, with or without abdominal distention, nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea), laryngeal angioedema (stridor, dyspnea, difficulty speaking, difficulty swallowing, throat tightening, or swelling of the tongue, palate, uvula, or larynx). Number of investigator-confirmed angioedema attacks during the treatment period of Day 0 through Day 182 will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Moderate or Severe Angioedema Attacks During the Treatment Period of Day 0 Through Day 182</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Day 182</time_frame>
    <description>The overall severity of angioedema attack will be determined by the site using following definitions: mild (transient or mild discomfort), moderate (mild to moderate limitation in activity), severe (marked limitation in activity). Number of moderate or severe angioedema attacks during the treatment period of Day 0 through Day 182 will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of High-Morbidity Angioedema Attacks During the Treatment Period of Day 0 Through Day 182</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Day 182</time_frame>
    <description>A high morbidity HAE attack is defined as any attack that has at least 1 of the following characteristics: severe, results in hospitalization (except hospitalization for observation less than (&lt;) 24 hours), hemodynamically significant (systolic blood pressure less than &lt; 90, requires intravenous (IV) hydration, or associated with syncope or near syncope) or laryngeal. Number of high-morbidity angioedema attacks during the treatment period of Day 0 through Day 182 will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) Plasma Concentrations of Lanadelumab</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 84, 140 and 182</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetic plasma concentrations of lanadelumab will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Kallikrein (pKal) Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 84, 140 and 182</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma Kallikrein activity will be measured by biomarker cleaved high molecular weight kininogen (cHMWK ) with factor XIIa activation level to assess pharmacodynamics of lanadelumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Positive Antidrug Antibodies (ADA) in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 84, 140 and 182</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with positive ADA including evaluation of neutralizing antibodies in plasma will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Angioedema Quality of life (AE-QoL) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 28, 56, 84, 112, 140 and 182</time_frame>
    <description>The AE-QoL questionnaire is a self-administered validated instrument to assess health related (HR)QoL among participants with recurrent angioedema (including HAE). The AE-QoL consists of 17 disease-specific quality-of-life items, to produce a total AE-QoL score and 4 domain scores (functioning, fatigue/mood, fear/shame, and nutrition) and each of the 17 items has a five-point response scale ranging from 1 (Never) to 5 (Very Often).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lanadelumab Injection Report During the Treatment Period of Day 0 Through Day 168</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Day 168</time_frame>
    <description>An injection report will be completed by the participant (or parent/caregiver) following each dose administration of lanadelumab injection used during the treatment period of Day 0 through Day 168 will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Angioedema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lanadelumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rollover participants from SHP643-303 (NCT04206605) will receive 300 milligram (mg) of lanadelumab solution in prefilled syringe subcutaneously (SC) for 26 weeks once every 2 weeks (Q2W) or once every 4 weeks (Q4W) if well controlled during SHP643-303 (NCT04206605) with up to 13 doses.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lanadelumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Rollover participants will receive 300 mg of lanadelumab solution in a PFS SC injection once Q2W or Q4W for 26 consecutive weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lanadelumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DX-2930</other_name>
    <other_name>SHP643</other_name>
    <other_name>TAK-743</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females, 12 years of age and older diagnosed with non-histaminergic normal
             C1-INH angioedema at the time of enrollment into the antecedent Study SHP643-303
             (NCT04206605).

          -  Participants must have completed the treatment period (through Visit 26/Day 182) of
             Study SHP643-303 (NCT04206605) without reporting a clinically significant TEAE that
             would preclude subsequent exposure to lanadelumab.

          -  Agree to adhere to the protocol-defined schedule of treatments, assessments, and
             procedures.

          -  Males, or non-pregnant, non-lactating females who are of child-bearing potential and
             who agree to be abstinent or agree to comply with the applicable contraceptive
             requirements of this protocol for the duration of the study; or females of
             non-childbearing potential, defined as surgically sterile (status post hysterectomy,
             bilateral oophorectomy, or bilateral tubal ligation) or post-menopausal for at least
             12 months.

          -  The participant (or the participant's parent/legal guardian, if applicable) has
             provided written informed consent approved by the institutional review board/research
             ethics board/ethics committee (IRB/REB/EC) at any time prior to study start. If the
             participant is a minor (i.e. lesser then (&lt;) 18 years of age), have a parent/legal
             guardian who is informed of the nature of the study provide written informed consent
             (i.e. permission) for the minor to participate in the study before any study-specific
             procedures are performed. Assent will be obtained from minor participants.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Discontinued from Study SHP643-303 (NCT04206605) after enrollment but before Visit 26
             for any reason.

          -  Presence of important safety concerns identified in Study SHP643-303 (NCT04206605)
             that would preclude participation in this study.

          -  Dosing with an investigational product (IP, not including IP defined in antecedent
             Study SHP643-303 [NCT04206605]) or exposure to an investigational device within 4
             weeks prior to Day 0.

          -  Use of any estrogen-containing medications with systemic absorption (such as oral
             contraceptives or hormone replacement therapy) within 6 months prior to Day 0.

          -  Use of long-term prophylactic therapy for angioedema attacks, eg, C1-INH, attenuated
             androgens (e.g. danazol, methyltestosterone, testosterone), or anti-fibrinolytics
             within 2 weeks prior to Day 0.

          -  Have any active infectious illness or fever defined as an oral temperature greater
             than (&gt;) 38°celsius [C] (100.4°Fahrenheit [F]), tympanic &gt; 38.5°C (101.3°F), or
             axillary &gt; 38°C (100.4°F), within 24 hours prior to the first dose of study drug on
             Day 0.

          -  Any of the following liver function test abnormalities: alanine aminotransferase (ALT)
             &gt; 3 × the upper limit of normal (ULN), or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 × ULN,
             or total bilirubin &gt; 2 × ULN (unless the bilirubin elevation is a result of Gilbert's
             syndrome).

          -  Participants has a known hypersensitivity to the investigational product or its
             components.

          -  Have any condition (surgical or medical) that, in the opinion of the investigator or
             sponsor, may compromise their safety or compliance, preclude the successful conduct of
             the study, or interfere with interpretation of the results (e.g. significant
             pre-existing illness or other major comorbidities that the investigator considers may
             confound the interpretation of study results).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shire</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shire Contact</last_name>
    <phone>+1 866 842 5335</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTransparency@shire.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Research Center of Alabama</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>205-209-4134</phone>
      <email>Janderson@alabamaallergy.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Anderson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Research of Arizona a division of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology Associates, LTD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85251</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>480-675-8982</phone>
      <email>mm@medicalresearchaz.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael E Manning</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Angioedema Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>858-657-5350</phone>
      <email>ask011@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander Kim</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asthma and Allergy Associates, PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colorado Springs</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80907</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>719-473-8330</phone>
      <email>dsoteres@aacos.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniel F Soteres</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Asthma &amp; Allergy, P.C.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chevy Chase</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20815</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>301-986-0670</phone>
      <email>hl@allergyasthma.us</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Huamin Henry Li</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Specialty Allergy Clinic and Food Allergy Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>734-936-5634</phone>
      <email>abaptist@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan Baptist</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63414</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>314-996-8339</phone>
      <email>wednerj@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>H. James Wedner</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Optimed Research, LTD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Contact</last_name>
      <phone>614-430-8022</phone>
      <email>pi@optimed.us.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald L McNeil</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Angioedema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angioedemas, Hereditary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Shire provides access to the de-identified individual participant data for eligible studies to aid qualified researchers in addressing legitimate scientific objectives. These IPDs will be provided following approval of a data sharing request, and under the terms of a data sharing agreement.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_access_criteria>IPD from eligible studies will be shared with qualified researchers according to the criteria and process described in the Data Sharing section of the www.shiretrials.com website. For approved requests, the researchers will be provided access to anonymized data (to respect patient privacy in line with applicable laws and regulations) and with information necessary to address the research objectives under the terms of a data sharing agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.shiretrials.com/en/our-commitment-to-transparency/data-sharing-with-researchers</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

