<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00027170</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>020050</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-H-0050</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00027170</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Technical Development of Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance Imaging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Technical Development of Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore new ways of using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to evaluate the
      heart and blood vessels of patients with cardiovascular disease, including better detection
      of myocardial infarction (heart attack) and blockage of heart and leg arteries.

      Patients 18 years of age and older with cardiovascular disease may be eligible for this
      study.

      All participants will have magnetic resonance imaging of the heart. MRI uses a magnetic field
      and radio waves to show structural and chemical changes in tissues. For the procedure, the
      patient lies on a table surrounded by a metal cylinder (the scanner). A 'gadolinium contrast'
      material may be injected into the patient s vein during part of the study to brighten the
      images. Patients wear earplugs during the scan to muffle loud knocking sounds caused by the
      electrical switching of the magnetic fields. They will be asked to hold their breath
      intermittently for 5 to 20 seconds during the scan. They will be monitored with an
      electrocardiogram (EKG) during the procedure and will be in contact by intercom at all times
      with the person performing the scan. Patients can request to stop the study and come out of
      the scanner at any time. The procedure may last from 30 to 90 minutes. An echocardiogram a
      test that uses sound waves to produce pictures of the heart and blood vessels-may be done to
      confirm the MRI findings. In addition, patients may undergo one or more of the following
      optional studies:

        -  Dobutamine stress MRI - This test uses dobutamine-a medicine that simulates exercise by
           increasing heart rate and heart function-to detect blockages in the coronary arteries
           (vessels that supply oxygen and nutrients to the heart) and locate areas of the heart
           that are permanently damaged, perhaps by a previous heart attack. For this test, MRI
           pictures of the heart are taken before, during and after administration of dobutamine.
           Gadolinium may be injected during part of the study to brighten the images. An EKG will
           be used to monitor the heart during the procedure.

        -  Vasodilator MRI - The procedure and objectives of this test are the same as those
           described for dobutamine stress MRI, except that this study uses dipyridamole or
           adenosine. These drugs dilate blood vessels, causing increased blood flow to the heart.

        -  Plethysmography MRI - This test determines the presence and severity of narrowing in
           arteries that supply blood to the leg. Blockage of these vessels often causes pain while
           walking. This study will compare plethysmography MRI with venous occlusion
           plethysmography, an older method of measuring blood flow in the legs. For venous
           occlusion plethysmography, a large blood pressure cuff is placed around the upper leg
           and a strain gauge (thin elastic band) is placed around the calf. The pressure cuff is
           inflated very tightly for 5 minutes to block blood flow to the leg, and another pressure
           cuff over the ankle is also inflated. When the large cuff is deflated, blood rushes to
           the leg, a smaller cuff is inflated to a low pressure, and the strain gauge measures the
           maximum blood flow to the leg for 1 or 2 more minutes. This procedure is done once or
           twice outside the MRI scanner and once or twice inside the scanner. The scans are
           performed as described above for the dobutamine and vasodilator studies. The strain
           gauge is not used for plethysmography MRI the MRI pictures are used to measure flow.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to allow development and testing of new MRI techniques
      suitable for evaluating patients with cardiovascular disease. Since such technical
      development work often depends on preliminary studies in healthy volunteers, the protocol
      also recruits healthy subjects. This protocol will provide the framework for technical
      development scans in patients with cardiovascular disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 26, 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>examine the rate of major cardiovascular events (MACE) defined as cardiac death, non- fatal myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular / transient ischemic attack, and revascularization in patients undergoing stress or rest cardiac MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>examine the rate of major cardiovascular events (MACE) defined as cardiac death, non- fatal myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular / transient ischemic attack, and revascularization in patients undergoing stress or rest cardiac MRI and to relate these events to the extent of ischemia and infarction seen on the MRI exams</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical Development of Multiecho MRI Methods</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical Developments Related to Distinguishing Fat and Water by MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8781</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance Imaging</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients may receive an intravenous injection of gadobutrol (Gadavist) not to exceed 0.2 mmol/kg of Gd per bolus injection and per examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Siemens MRI scanner</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigational or research MRI coils may be used in the protocol. The coils are noninvasive devices external to the body. The coils act as antennae to receive small radiofrequency signals out of the body. Coils of the type we use are used daily in clinical MRI practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Inclusion Criteria for All Arms of the Protocol:

               -  Subjects 18 years of age or older

               -  Written informed consent

             EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          2. Exclusion Criteria for All Arms of the Protocol:

               -  Patients with a contraindication to MRI scanning will be excluded. These
                  contraindications include patients with the following devices:

                    -  Central nervous system aneurysm clips;

                    -  Implanted neural stimulator;

                    -  Implanted cardiac pacemaker or defibrillator;

                    -  Cochlear implant;

                    -  Ocular foreign body (e.g. metal shavings);

                    -  Implanted Insulin pump;

                    -  Metal shrapnel or bullet.

          3. In addition, the following patient groups will be excluded:

               -  Pregnant women (Patients who are uncertain as to whether they are pregnant will
                  be required to have a screening urine or blood pregnancy test)

               -  Patients with active symptoms of myocardial ischemia occurring despite maximally
                  tolerated doses of oral antianginal therapy and intravenous nitroglycerin

          4. Furthermore, the following patient groups will be excluded from studies involving the
             administration of MRI contrast agents:

               -  lactating women unless they are willing to discard breast milk for 24 hours after
                  receiving gadolinium

               -  renal disease (estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) less than 30
                  ml/min/1.73 m(2) body surface area)

             The eGFR will be used to estimate renal function if reported by the laboratory, or as
             reported by NIH Clinical Center or Suburban Hospital or other clinically certified
             laboratories. Otherwise, estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) can be based on
             the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) study equation (see below) in
             subjects with stable renal function. This formula is not applicable to patients with
             acute renal insufficiency:

             eGFR (ml/min/1.73 m(2)) equal to 175 times (serum creatinine)-1.154 times (age)-0.203
             times 0.742 (if the subject is female) times1.212 (if the subject is black)

          5. Additional Exclusion Criteria for Dobutamine, or Vasodilator Stress MRI:

               -  Myocardial infarction within 48 hours

               -  Uncontrolled congestive heart failure

               -  Severe hypertension (SBP greater than 200, DBP greater than 110) (exclusion only
                  for dobutamine and bicycle)

               -  Atrial fibrillation. This exclusion only applies to Dobutamine stress.

               -  Frequent PVC s (more than 1 every 10 heart beats or non-sustained ventricular
                  tachycardia (greater than 4 beat runs) or ongoing sustained ventricular
                  tachycardia. This exclusion only applies to Dobutamine and Bicycle stress

               -  Patients with narrow angle glaucoma and known or suspected prostatic obstruction
                  will not receive atropine

          6. Additional Exclusion Criteria for PET/MR perfusion scans

               -  Pregnant patients

               -  Patients that are breast feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew E Arai, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Suburban Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2002-H-0050.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baer FM, Voth E, Theissen P, Schicha H, Sechtem U. Gradient-echo magnetic resonance imaging during incremental dobutamine infusion for the localization of coronary artery stenoses. Eur Heart J. 1994 Feb;15(2):218-25.</citation>
    <PMID>8005123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baer FM, Voth E, Schneider CA, Theissen P, Schicha H, Sechtem U. Comparison of low-dose dobutamine-gradient-echo magnetic resonance imaging and positron emission tomography with [18F]fluorodeoxyglucose in patients with chronic coronary artery disease. A functional and morphological approach to the detection of residual myocardial viability. Circulation. 1995 Feb 15;91(4):1006-15.</citation>
    <PMID>7850935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baer FM, Voth E, Theissen P, Schneider CA, Schicha H, Sechtem U. Coronary artery disease: findings with GRE MR imaging and Tc-99m-methoxyisobutyl-isonitrile SPECT during simultaneous dobutamine stress. Radiology. 1994 Oct;193(1):203-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8090892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 21, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 27, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 28, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myocardial Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Viability</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Perfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Ischemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

