<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00341302</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999902261</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-CH-N261</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00341302</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective, Observational Study of HIV-Infected Pregnant Women and Their Infants at Clinical Sites in Latin American and Caribbean Countries</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Observational Study of HIV-Infected Pregnant Women and HIV-Exposed, Uninfected Children at Clinical Sites in Latin American Countries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      By the end of 1999, it was estimated that 1.2 million children were living with HIV
      infection. During 1999 alone, 600,000 children were newly infected with HIV, mostly in
      less-developed countries. Most HIV-infected children are infected by transmission from mother
      to child during pregnancy, at birth, or through breast milk. Antiretroviral medications,
      cesarean section before rupture of membranes, and avoidance of breastfeeding are ways to
      reduce the risk of transmission. This study will determine mother-to-child transmission rates
      and the effects on infants of exposure to antiretroviral medications and mode of delivery.

      Approximately 180 to 240 HIV-infected pregnant women in Mexico and Argentina will be enrolled
      during the first year of this 5-year study. HIV-infected women will be evaluated during
      pregnancy, during delivery, and 6 months after delivery. At each visit, a history will be
      taken and physical examination given; blood will be collected for laboratory tests.

      HIV-exposed infants will be evaluated through 6 months of age. At each of 2 visits, a history
      will be taken and physical examination given; blood will be collected for laboratory tests;
      and growth will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational, prospective cohort study to describe the characteristics of
      HIV-infected pregnant women and HIV-exposed, uninfected children at participating clinical
      sites in Latin America where the following are available: 1) antiretrovirals (ARVs) for
      treatment of HIV-infected women and for prevention of mother-to-child transmission (MTCT) of
      HIV; and 2) infant formula. We will describe the utilization of interventions related to
      decreasing the risk of MTCT, including ARV prophylaxis, cesarean section before labor and
      before ruptured membranes, and complete avoidance of breastfeeding. We will describe receipt
      of maternal ARV regimens and determine rates of MTCT of HIV. This study will describe
      maternal adverse events during pregnancy and the postpartum period. In addition, the study
      will describe child outcomes potentially related to in utero and early postnatal exposure to
      ARVs. HIV-infected women will be evaluated antepartum, intrapartum, 6 months postpartum and
      then every 6 months for up to 5 years after delivery. HIV-exposed, uninfected children will
      be evaluated for up to 5 years of follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 25, 2002</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To describe the characteristics of HIV-infected pregnant women and their HIV-exposed children in Latin America, including the rates of and risk factors for mother-to-child transmission</measure>
    <time_frame>in utero, six weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the characteristics of HIV-infected pregnant women and their HIV-exposed children in Latin America, including the rates of and risk factors for mother-to-child transmission.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize adverse events according to receipt of and exposure to ARVs (by HIV- infected women during pregnancy and postpartum and by their HIV-exposed but uninfected children in utero and during the first few week</measure>
    <time_frame>in utero, six weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize adverse events according to receipt of and exposure to ARVs (by HIV- infected women during pregnancy and postpartum and by their HIV-exposed but uninfected children in utero and during the first few week</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize adverse events according to receipt of and exposure to ARVs (by HIV-infected women during pregnancy and postpartum and by their HIV-exposed but uninfected children in utero and during the first few weeks of life).</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3554</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnant HIV Positive Women</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>HIV Infected Pregnant Women</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>HIV exposed , uninfected children born to HIV infected women</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <description>HIV exposed, uninfected children 6 months to 5 years of age</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        HIV -infected pregnant women and HIV exposed, uninfected children followed at participating
        Latin American sites@@@@@@
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA: (HIV-Infected Pregnant Women)

        Pregnant women at 22 weeks of gestation or more with documentation of pregnancy, using one
        or more of the following:

        Urine HCG pregnancy test;

        Serum HCG pregnancy test;

        Positive fetal heart tones by Doppler; or

        Ultrasound.

        Documentation of HIV infection, defined by any two of the following prior to or during
        pregnancy:

        Reactive test for HIV antibody;

        Positive HIV culture;

        Positive HIV DNA PCR;

        Positive neutralizable HIV p24 antigen;

        Positive qualitative HIV RNA;

        Quantitative HIV RNA greater than or equal to 1000 copies/ml; and

        Diagnosis of AIDS-defining clinical condition.

        Willingness and intent to deliver at the participating clinical site and to be followed
        through six months postpartum at the site or associated outpatient facility.

        Willingness and ability to sign informed consent-Subject must be of an age to provide legal
        informed consent as defined by the country in which the subject resides.

        Willingness and intent to have children followed for up to 5 years.

        Subjects may be co-enrolled in clinical trials for treatment or prophylaxis of HIV
        infection, opportunistic infections, or other HIV related problems.

        Subjects may be re-enrolled with subsequent pregnancies during this study. However, if so,
        their follow-up for the previous pregnancy will be discontinued. Children from each
        pregnancy will be followed in accordance with the protocol.

        Subjects may enroll up to and prior to delivery, including during labor.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA: (Dynamic Pediatric Cohort)

        -HIV-exposed children born to enrolled HIV-infected pregnant women. Children diagnosed with
        HIV infection will be discontinued from the present protocol and(if eligible) offered
        enrollment into a concurrent NICHD-funded protocol for HIV-infected children.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA: (Static Pediatric Cohort)

        -HIV-exposed, uninfected children who are 6 months of age through 5 years 364 days of age
        and were previously enrolled in the NISDI Pediatric Protocol or NISDI Perinatal Protocol.

        And

          -  Other HIV-exposed, uninfected children who are 6 months of age through 5 years 364
             days of age at time of enrollment into this protocol.

               1. Documentation of HIV-uninfected status should be obtained from medical

                  record review.

               2. Evidence of the HIV-uninfected status of the infants and children can be
                  documented by the following:

                  --Two or more negative HIV virologic assays (e.g., HIV culture or HIV DNA PCR)
                  with one test performed at age 1 month or older and one performed at age 4 months
                  or older, and no positive virologic tests.

                  Or

                  --One or more negative HIV virologic assays performed at 1 month of age or older
                  with one or more negative HIV antibody tests (including HIV rapid tests)
                  performed at greater than or equal to 6 months of age.

                  Or

                  --One positive HIV virologic assay, with at least two later negative HIV
                  virologic tests (at least one of which is after age 4 months of age) or negative
                  HIV antibody tests (at least one of which is after 6 months of age).

               3. Documentation of HIV infection in the mother must have been obtained either prior
                  to or during pregnancy or within one month postpartum.

               4. Evidence of HIV infection in the mother can be documented by two or more of the
                  following:

                    -  Reactive test for HIV antibody;

                    -  Positive HIV culture;

                    -  Positive HIV DNA PCR;

                    -  Positive quantitative HIV p24 antigen above assay cutoff;

                    -  Positive qualitative HIV RNA;

                    -  Quantitative HIV RNA &gt;= 1000 copies/ml; and

                    -  Diagnosis of AIDS-defining clinical condition.

               5. Complete data regarding maternal medications received during pregnancy must be
                  available through medical record abstraction.

                  EXCLUSION CRITERIA: (HIV-Infected Pregnant Women)

                  Failure to meet inclusion criteria.

                  EXCLUSION CRITERIA: (Dynamic Pediatric Cohort)

          -  Failure to meet inclusion criteria

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA: (Static Pediatric Cohort)

          -  HIV infection of the child

          -  Insufficient documentation of HIV infection in the mother obtained either prior to or
             during pregnancy or within one month postpartum.

          -  Insufficient evidence of HIV infection in the mother

          -  Insufficient perinatal data

               1. Incomplete data regarding maternal medications received during pregnancy (e.g.,
                  missing start and stop dates).

               2. Incomplete data regarding postnatal ARV exposure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nahida A Chakhtoura, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General de Agudos &quot;Jose Maria Ramos Mejia&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buenos Aires</city>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade de Caxias do Sul</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caxias do Sul</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minas Gerais</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Geral Nova de Iguacu Setor De DST/AIDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nova Iguacu</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Conceicao</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Femina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Irmandade Da Santa Casa de Misericordia de</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital dos Servidores do Estado - RJ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Puericultura e Pediatria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Federal University of Sao Paulo-Escola Paulista de Medicina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital das Clinicas da Falculdade De Medinica</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unversity of San Marcos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Peru</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Bahamas</country>
    <country>Jamaica</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rates of mother-to-child transmission of HIV-1 in Africa, America, and Europe: results from 13 perinatal studies. The Working Group on Mother-To-Child Transmission of HIV. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr Hum Retrovirol. 1995 Apr 15;8(5):506-10.</citation>
    <PMID>7697448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>U.S. Public Health Service recommendations for human immunodeficiency virus counseling and voluntary testing for pregnant women. MMWR Recomm Rep. 1995 Jul 7;44(RR-7):1-15.</citation>
    <PMID>7565546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connor EM, Sperling RS, Gelber R, Kiselev P, Scott G, O'Sullivan MJ, VanDyke R, Bey M, Shearer W, Jacobson RL, et al. Reduction of maternal-infant transmission of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 with zidovudine treatment. Pediatric AIDS Clinical Trials Group Protocol 076 Study Group. N Engl J Med. 1994 Nov 3;331(18):1173-80.</citation>
    <PMID>7935654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 15, 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>Perinatal</keyword>
  <keyword>Transmission</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcomes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Seropositivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

