<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01306019</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-I-0007</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01306019</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lentiviral Gene Transfer for Treatment of Children Older Than Two Years of Age With X-Linked Severe Combined Immunodeficiency (XSCID)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lentiviral Gene Transfer for Treatment of Children Older Than 2 Years of Age With X-Linked Severe Combined Immunodeficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-randomized clinical trial of gene transfer using a self-inactivating,
      insulated, lentiviral gene transfer vector to treat 23 patients with X-linked severe combined
      immunodeficiency (XSCID, also called SCID-X1) who are between 2 and 40 years of age; who do
      not have a tissue matched sibling who can donate bone marrow for a transplant; who may have
      failed to obtain sufficient benefit from a previous half-tissue matched bone marrow
      transplant; and who have clinically significant impairment of immunity. A patient s own
      precursor cells (also called blood stem cells) that give rise in the marrow to blood and
      immune cells will have been or will be collected from the patient s blood or bone marrow. A
      patient will not proceed to gene transfer treatment in this protocol until there are at least
      3 million blood stem cells per kilogram body weight collected from the patient. At the NIH
      the patient blood stem cells will be collected from either the blood or bone marrow under
      another protocol (NIH protocol 94-1-0073 or a successor approved protocol) that is specific
      for collection of such cells. In most cases the harvested blood stem cells are put into
      frozen storage before use in this protocol. When the patient enrolled in this protocol has
      the required number of blood stem cells harvested, then the patient s blood stem cells will
      be grown in tissue culture and exposed to the lentiviral gene transfer vector containing the
      corrective gene. These gene corrected blood stem cells will be administered by vein to the
      patient. To increase engraftment of the corrected blood stem cells, patients will receive on
      2 days before the gene transfer treatment a chemotherapy drug called busulfan at a total dose
      of 6 mg/kilogram body weight (3 mg/kilogram body weight/daily times 2 days) that is a little
      more than one- third the dose used in many standard bone marrow transplants. Patients will
      also be given another drug called palifermin that helps prevent the main side effect from the
      busulfan that is a type of inflammation the mouth, stomach and bowels called mucositis. After
      this treatment, patients will be monitored to see if the treatment is safe and whether their
      immune system improves. Patients will be followed at frequent intervals for the first 2
      years, and less frequently thereafter so that the effectiveness in restoration of immune
      function and the safety of the treatment can be evaluated.

      XSCID is a genetic disease caused by defects in common gamma chain, a protein found at the
      surface of immune cells called lymphocytes and necessary to their growth and function. XSCID
      patients cannot make T-lymphocytes necessary to fight infections, and their B-cells fail to
      make essential antibodies. Without normal T- and B-lymphocyte function patients develop fatal
      infections in infancy unless they are rescued by a bone marrow transplant from a healthy
      donor. The best type of transplant is from a tissue matched healthy brother or sister, but
      most XSCID patients do not have a tissue-matched sibling, and are treated with a transplant
      from a parent who is only half- matched by tissue typing. While a half-matched transplant
      from a parent can be life-saving for an infant with XSCID, a subset of patients fail to
      achieve sufficient long lasting restoration of immunity to prevent infections and other
      chronic problems.

      Recent trials of gene transfer treatments using mouse retrovirus vectors for infants with
      XSCID have been performed and have demonstrated that this type of gene transfer can be an
      alternate approach for significantly restoring immunity to infants with XSCID. However, among
      the 18 infants with XSCID benefiting long-term from the gene transfer treatment, 5 developed
      T-lymphocyte leukemia and 1 died of this leukemia. Furthermore, when older children with
      XSCID were treated with gene transfer, the restoration of immunity was very much less than
      seen in the infants. These observations of gene transfer treatments using mouse retrovirus
      vectors to treat infants and older patients with XSCID suggests that safer and more effective
      vectors were needed, and that there also may be a need to give chemotherapy conditioning to
      increase engraftment in the marrow of the gene corrected blood stem cells. Our data and other
      published studies suggest that lentivectors that are derived from the human immunodeficiency
      virus and have the properties of our highly modified vector called CL20-4i-EF1 - h &gt;=c-OPT
      have a reduced interaction with nearby genes and therefore less of a tendency to activate
      genes that may lead to cancer formation. Also, this type of lentivector may work better at
      getting into blood stem cells.

      The study purpose is to evaluate safety and effectiveness of lentiviral gene transfer
      treatment at restoring immune function to 23 XSCID patients who are 2 to 40 years of age, and
      have significant impairment of immunity. Early evidence for effectiveness will be defined by
      appearance and expansion in ...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I/II non-randomized clinical trial of ex vivo hematopoietic stem cell (HSC)
      gene transfer treatment for X-linked severe combined immunodeficiency (XSCID, also known as
      SCID-X1) using a self-inactivating lentiviral vector incorporating additional features to
      improve safety and performance. The study will treat 13 patients with XSCID who are between 2
      and 40 years of age and who have clinically significant impairment of immunity. Patients will
      receive a total busulfan dose of ~6 mg/kg/body weight (target busulfan Area Under Curve is
      4500 min*umol/L/day) delivered as 3mg/kg body weight on day 1 and dose adjusted on day 2 (if
      busulfan AUC result is available) to achieve the target dose, to condition their bone marrow,
      and this will be followed by a single infusion of autologous transduced CD34+HSC. Patients
      will then be followed to evaluate engraftment, expansion, and function of gene corrected
      lymphocytes that arise from the transplant; to evaluate improvement in laboratory measures of
      immune function; to evaluate any clinical benefit that accrues from the treatment; and to
      evaluate the safety of this treatment. The primary endpoint of the study with respect to
      these outcomes will be at 2 years, though data relevant to these measures will be collected
      at intervals throughout the study and during the longer follow-up period of at least 15 years
      recommended by the FDA Guidance &quot;Gene Therapy Clinical Trials - Observing Subjects for
      Delayed Adverse Events&quot; http://www.fda.gov/downloads

        -  BiologicsBloodVaccines/GuidanceComplianceRegulatoryInformation / Guidances/Cellular and
           Gene Therapy

        -  ucm078719.pdf for patients participating in gene transfer clinical trials.

      XSCID results from defects in the IL2RGgene encoding the common gamma chain (yc) shared by
      receptors for Interleukin 2 (IL-2), IL-4, IL-7, IL-9, IL-15 and IL-21. At birth XSCID
      patients generally lack or have a severe deficiency of T-lymphocytes and NK cells, while
      their B- lymphocytes are normal in number but are severely deficient in function, failing to
      make essential antibodies. The severe deficiency form of XSCID is fatal in infancy without
      intervention to restore some level of immune function. The best current therapy is a
      T-lymphocyte-depleted bone marrow transplant from an HLA tissue typing matched sibling, and
      with this type of donor it is not required to administer chemotherapy or radiation
      conditioning of the patient's marrow to achieve excellent engraftment and immune correction
      of an XSCID patient. However, the great majority of patients with XSCID lack a matched
      sibling donor, and in these patients the standard of care is to perform a transplant of T-
      lymphocyte depleted bone marrow from a parent. This type of transplant is called
      haploidentical because in general a parent will be only half- matched by HLA tissue typing to
      the affected child. Whether or not any conditioning is used, haploidentical transplant for
      XSCID has a significantly poorer prognosis than a matched sibling donor transplant. Following
      haploidentical transplant, XSCID patients are observed to achieve a wide range of partial
      immune reconstitution and that reconstitution can wane over time in some patients. That
      subset of XSCID patients who either fail to engraft, fail to achieve adequate immune
      reconstitution, or lose immune function over time suffer from recurrent viral, bacterial and
      fungal infections, problems with allo- or autoimmunity, impaired pulmonary function and/or
      significant growth failure.

      We propose to offer gene transfer treatment to XSCID patients3 2 years of age who have
      clinically significant defects of immunity despite prior haploidentical hematopoietic stem
      cell transplant, and who lack an HLA-matched sibling donor. Our current gene transfer
      treatment protocol can be regarded as a salvage/rescue protocol.

      Recent successful retroviral gene transfer treatment instead of bone marrow transplant (BMT)
      in Paris and London for 20 infants with XSCID has provided proof of principle for efficacy.
      However, a major safety concern is the occurrence of 5 cases of leukemia at 3-5 years after
      treatment triggered in part by vector insertional mutagenesis activation of LMO2 and other
      DNA regulatory genes by the strong enhancer present in the long-terminal repeat (LTR) of the
      Moloney Leukemia Virus (MLV)- based vector.

      Furthermore, previous studies of gene transfer treatment of older XSCID patients with MLV-
      based vectors demonstrated the additional problem of failure of adequate expansion of gene
      corrected T- lymphocytes to the very high levels seen in infants. To reduce or eliminate this
      leukemia risk, and possibly enhance 13 performance sufficiently to achieve benefit in older
      XSCID patients, we have generated a lentivector with improved safety and performance
      features. We have generated a self-inactivating (SIN) lentiviral vector that is devoid of all
      viral transcription elements; that contains a short form of the human elongation factor 1a
      (EF1a) internal promoter to express a codon optimized yc cDNA; and that has flanking copies
      of the 400 base pair insulator fragment from the chicken HS4 (Omega)-globin locus to provide
      further protection from untoward effects on flanking cellular genes. Preclinical data from
      our own laboratories as well as from others support the hypothesis that our SIN lentiviral
      vector will be significantly less prone to activating cellular oncogenes in general, and LMO2
      (the gene responsible for most cases of gene transfer-related leukemias) in particular.
      Furthermore, our vector, designated as CL20-4i-EF1a-hyc-OPT, has established activity for
      reconstituting yc expression and signaling in human lymphocyte cell lines and has achieved a
      high level of in vivo efficacy in treatment of XSCID mice and dogs. We also established a
      novel stable producer cell line to allow efficient and safe high titer production of clinical
      lentiviral vector, greatly facilitating conduct of this clinical trial.

      Based on our previous experience in treating older patients with XSCID who are either
      partially haploidentical donor engrafted or who failed to engraft despite multiple attempts
      at haploidentical donor transplant, there appears to be a significant barrier to engraftment
      of autologous gene corrected CD34 stem cells and an associated failure of production of
      adequate numbers of gene corrected autologous lymphocytes. The targeted patients for this
      study may have some degree of lymphoid immunity either from donor lymphocytes or their own
      partially functional or autologous lymphocyes that may have played a role in the poor
      engraftment and function of their previous haploidential HSC transplant. Furthermore, some
      patients may also have some graft versus host disease as a result of previous HSC transplant.
      In addressing these barriers to engraftment in these XSCID patients, we will pre-treat with
      moderate dose (~6 mg/kg) busulfan to create space or niches in bone marrow for incoming
      autologous gene corrected HSCs.

      We plan to treat up to 23 XSCID patients, where all patients will receive the identical
      conditioning, gene transfer treatment, and follow-up evaluation. Mobilized peripheral blood
      stem cells harvested by apheresis will be the first choice source of HSC for this study, but
      patients who for any reason cannot provide sufficient HSC by this method (e.g. poor
      mobilization, inefficient apheresis separation of HSC, or inadequate central access as needed
      for apheresis), will have HSC collected by bone marrow harvest. At the NIH, patients will
      have autologous CD34+ HSC collected under a separate currently IRB approved stem cell
      collection protocol (NIH protocol 94-I- 0073; H. Malech, PI or a successor IRB-approved
      mobilization/HSC apheresis collection protocol). A patient enrolled in this protocol will not
      proceed to transduction of the autologous HSC or to busulfan conditioning (i.e. will not be
      treated with gene transfer corrected cells) until there are at least 3 x 106per kilogram body
      weight autologous CD34+HSC (from mobilized peripheral blood stem cell apheresis collection as
      method of choice, and/or by bone marrow harvest) available for gene transfer transduction.

      Patients will undergo a pre-treatment evaluation of both laboratory and clinical measures of
      immune function. Autologous CD34+HSC will be transduced ex vivo with the VSV-G pseudotyped
      CL20-4i- EF1a-hyc-OPT lentivector. All patients will receive a single intravenous infusion of
      the washed transduced cells administered intravenously on protocol Day 0. on Days -3 and -2
      patients will receive an infusion of busulfan ~3 mg/kilogram body weight/day (for a total
      dose of ~6 mg/kilogram body weight) as conditioning to enhance engraftment of gene corrected
      autologous CD34+HSC. On Days - 6, -5, -4 and 1, 2 and 3, patients will receive an infusion of
      Keratinocyte Growth Factor (palifermin) at 60 mg/kg/day. Palifermin at this dose and schedule
      is FDA approved to reduce or prevent mucositis following conditioning regimens, including
      those that use busulfan. Following the conditioning and gene transfer treatment, subjects
      will be supported through any period of cytopenia and monitored for safety and efficacy of
      the gene transfer treatment. Early evidence for efficacy will be defined by appearance and
      expansion in the circulation of autologous transduced T-lymphocytes with functional yc and
      improved laboratory measures of immune function in the interim evaluation of these parameters
      at 1 year after treatment. Endpoint evidence for efficacy at 2 years after treatment will
      include these same laboratory parameters measured at the 2 year time point plus evidence for
      clinical benefit. Evidence for safety will focus on the maintenance of polyclonality of
      vector marking, the lack of emergence of a dominant gene marked clone in any hematopoietic
      lineage, and no occurrence of either hematologic dysplasia or any leukemia or other cancer
      resulting from the gene transfer. The primary study endpoints for all laboratory and clinical
      measures of efficacy and safety will occur at 2 years after gene transfer treatment. However,
      data collection regarding efficacy will occur at frequent intervals during the 2 years
      leading up to the endpoint analysis, and long- term safety and efficacy evaluation will
      continue at intervals during the long-term follow-up recommended by FDA Guidance for gene
      transfer treatment studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 25, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Early evidence for efficacy will be defined by appearance and expansion in the circulation of autologous transduced T-lymphocytes with functional gmama-c and improved laboratory measures of immune function in the interim evaluation of these para...</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>successful, partial successful or failure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>evidence for efficacy at 2 years after treatment will include these same laboratory parameters measured at the 2 year time point plus evidence for clinical benefit</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>maintenance of polyclonality of vector marking, the lack of emergence of a dominant gene marked clone in any hematopoietic lineage, and no occurrence of either hematologic dysplasia or any leukemia or other cancer resulting from the gene transfer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>X-Linked Severe Combined Immune Deficiency (XSCID)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gene Therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palifermin</intervention_name>
    <description>Mucositis prophylaxis commenced- Infusion of keratinocyte growth factor (palifermin) at 60 mg/kg/day before (Days -6 to Day -4) administration of busulfan</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>3mg/kg per day with drug levels obtained on Day -3. Busulfan dose on day -2 will be adjusted (if busulfan AUC result is available) to achieve targeted busulfan AUC 4500 min*umol/L/day. If result is not available in time to make an adjustment, then proceed to give the standard 3mg/kg on the second day</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ex vivo culture and transduction of the patient's autologous CD34+ HSC with lentivirus vector VSV-G pseudotyped CL20- 4i-EF1a-hyc-OPT vector</intervention_name>
    <description>Transduced cell product administered intravenously over &lt;30 minutes by a PI or designated Associate Investigator at the NIH Clinical Center.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  A proven mutation in the common gamma chain gene as defined by direct sequencing of
             patient DNA

          -  HLA typing of the patient will have been performed before enrollment

          -  No available HLA matched sibling donor as determined before enrollment.

          -  Must be between 2 and 40 years of age and weigh greater than or equal to 10 kg

          -  If previously transplanted, must be greater than or equal to 18 months post
             haploidentical HSCT

          -  Expected survival of at least 120 days.

          -  Documented to be negative for HIV infection by genome PCR

          -  The patient must be judged by the primary evaluating physician to have a suitable
             family and social situation consistent with ability to comply with protocol procedures
             and the long-term follow-up requirements.

          -  Medical lab data (historical) of severe B cell dysfunction (low or absent IgG levels,
             failed immune response to vaccines); OR demonstrated requirement for intravenous gamma
             globulin (IVIG) (significant drop over 3 to 6 weeks between peak and trough IgG
             levels).

          -  Must be willing to have blood and tissue samples stored

        IN ADDITION, patients must satisfy the following Laboratory Criteria AND Clinical Criteria

        Laboratory Criteria: (greater than or equal to 1 must be present)

        i. CD4+ lymphocytes: absolute number less than or equal to 50 percent of the lower limit of
        normal (LLN)

        ii. CD4 plus CD45RA+ lymphocytes: absolute number less than or equal to 50 percent of the
        LLN OR T-cell receptor excision circles (TRECs)squared less than or equal to 5 percent of
        normal for age.

        iii. Memory B Cells: absolute numberless than or equal to 50percent of LLN

        iv. If serum IgM&lt;normal for age

        v. NK cells: absolute number less than or equal to 50 percent of LLN

        vi. Lymphocyte proliferative response to each of 2 mitogens, phytohemagglutinin (PHA) and
        concanavalin A (ConA), is squared 25 percent with a normal control.

        vii. Molecular spectratype analysis- absent or very oligoclonal (1-3 dominant peaks) in
        greater than or equal to 6 of the 24 V- Beta T-cell receptor families.

        Clinical Criteria: (greater than or equal to 1 must be present):

        i Infections (not including molluscum, warts or mucocutaneous candidiasis; see vii and viii
        below): greater than or equal to 3 significant new or chronic active infections during the
        12 months preceding evaluation for enrollment.

        Infections are defined as an objective sign of infection (fever greater than 38.3 degrees C
        [101 degrees F] or neutrophilia or pain/redness/swelling or radiologic/ultrasound imaging
        evidence or typical lesion or histology or new severe diarrhea or cough with sputum
        production). In addition to one or more of these signs/symptoms of possible infection,
        there also must be at least 1 of the following criteria as evidence of the attending
        physician s intent to treat a significant infection (a. and b.) or objective evidence for a
        specific pathogen causing the infection (c.)

        -Treatment (not prophylaxis) with systemic antibacterial, antifungal or antiviral
        antibiotics greater than or equal to 14 days

        OR

        -Hospitalization of any duration for infection

        OR

        -Isolation of a bacteria, fungus, or virus from biopsy, skin lesion, blood, nasal washing,
        bronchoscopy, cerebrospinal fluid or stool likely to be an etiologic agent of infection

        ii Chronic pulmonary disease as defined by:

        -Bronchiectasis by x-ray computerized tomography

        OR

        -Pulmonary function test (PFT) evidence for restrictive or obstructive disease that is less
        than or equal to 60 percent of Predicted for Age

        OR

        -Pulse oximetry less than or equal to 94 percent in room air (if patient is too young to
        comply with performance of PFTs).

        iii Gastrointestinal enteropathy:

        -Diarrhea-watery stools greater than or equal to 3 times per day (of at least 3 months
        duration that is not a result of infection as defined in criterion above)

        OR

        -Endoscopic evidence (gross and histologic) for enteropathy (endoscopy will only be
        performed if medically indicated)

        OR

        -Other evidence of enteropathy or bacterial overgrowth syndrome: including malabsorption of
        fat soluble vitamin(s), abnormal D-xylose absorption, abnormal hydrogen breath test,
        evidence of protein losing enteropathy (for example increasingly high or frequent dosing of
        intravenous gamma globulin supplement required to maintain blood IgG level).

        iv Poor nutrition: Requires G-tube or intravenous feeding supplement to maintain weight or
        nutrition.

        v Auto- or allo-immunity: Examples must include objective physical findings that include,
        but are not limited to any one of alopecia, severe rashes, uveitis, joint pain with redness
        or swelling or limitation of movement that is not a result of infection, lupus-like
        lesions, and granulomas (Does not include auto- or allo-immune enteropathy which is
        criterion iii). Where possible and appropriate, diagnosis will be supported by
        histopathology or other diagnostic modality.

        vi Failure to grow in height: less than or equal to 3 rd percentile for age

        vii Skin molluscum contagiosum OR warts (this criterion is satisfied if molluscum consists
        of greater than or equal to 10 lesions or there are two or more lesions at each of two or
        more widely separated anatomic sites; or there are greater than or equal to 3 warts at
        different anatomic sites at the same time; or the patient has both molluscum and warts)

        viii Mucocutaneous candidiasis (chronic oral thrush or candida esophagitis or candida
        intertriginous infection or candida nail infections; must be culture positive to satisfy
        this criterion)

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Any current or pre-existing hematologic malignancy

          -  Current treatment with any chemotherapeutic agent (becomes eligible if not on
             treatment for at least 3 months)

          -  Documented HIV-1 infection

          -  Documented active Hepatitis B infection

          -  Childhood malignancy (occurring before 18 years of age) in the patient or a first
             degree relative, or previously diagnosed known genotype of the subject conferring a
             predisposition to cancer (no DNA or other testing for cancer predisposition genes will
             be performed as part of the screen for this protocol)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suk S De Ravin, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lee C England, P.A.-C</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 858-3649</phone>
    <email>lee.england@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Suk S De Ravin, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-6772</phone>
    <email>sderavin@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2011-I-0007.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howe SJ, Mansour MR, Schwarzwaelder K, Bartholomae C, Hubank M, Kempski H, Brugman MH, Pike-Overzet K, Chatters SJ, de Ridder D, Gilmour KC, Adams S, Thornhill SI, Parsley KL, Staal FJ, Gale RE, Linch DC, Bayford J, Brown L, Quaye M, Kinnon C, Ancliff P, Webb DK, Schmidt M, von Kalle C, Gaspar HB, Thrasher AJ. Insertional mutagenesis combined with acquired somatic mutations causes leukemogenesis following gene therapy of SCID-X1 patients. J Clin Invest. 2008 Sep;118(9):3143-50. doi: 10.1172/JCI35798.</citation>
    <PMID>18688286</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang EM, Choi U, Theobald N, Linton G, Long Priel DA, Kuhns D, Malech HL. Retrovirus gene therapy for X-linked chronic granulomatous disease can achieve stable long-term correction of oxidase activity in peripheral blood neutrophils. Blood. 2010 Jan 28;115(4):783-91. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-05-222760. Epub 2009 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>19965657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cartier N, Hacein-Bey-Abina S, Bartholomae CC, Veres G, Schmidt M, Kutschera I, Vidaud M, Abel U, Dal-Cortivo L, Caccavelli L, Mahlaoui N, Kiermer V, Mittelstaedt D, Bellesme C, Lahlou N, Lefrère F, Blanche S, Audit M, Payen E, Leboulch P, l'Homme B, Bougnères P, Von Kalle C, Fischer A, Cavazzana-Calvo M, Aubourg P. Hematopoietic stem cell gene therapy with a lentiviral vector in X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy. Science. 2009 Nov 6;326(5954):818-23. doi: 10.1126/science.1171242.</citation>
    <PMID>19892975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 10, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 1, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>T cell, B cell, NK cell</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Transfer</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral Blood Stem Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Common Gamma Chain (gamma c),</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune Reconstitution</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Severe Combined Immunodeficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>X-Linked Combined Immunodeficiency Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

