<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02125461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D4191C00001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02125461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Global Study to Assess the Effects of MEDI4736 Following Concurrent Chemoradiation in Patients With Stage III Unresectable Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>PACIFIC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Randomised, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Multi-centre, International Study of MEDI4736 as Sequential Therapy in Patients With Locally Advanced, Unresectable Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (Stage III) Who Have Not Progressed Following Definitive, Platinum-based, Concurrent Chemoradiation Therapy (PACIFIC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Global Study to Assess the Effects of MEDI4736 following concurrent chemoradiation in
      Patients with Stage III Unresectable Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Phase III, Randomised, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Multi-centre, International Study
      of MEDI4736 as Sequential Therapy in Patients with Locally Advanced, Unresectable Non-Small
      Cell Lung Cancer (Stage III) Who Have Not Progressed Following Definitive, Platinum-based,
      Concurrent Chemoradiation Therapy (PACIFIC)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 7, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 13, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival Based on Blinded Independent Central Review (BICR) According to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumor scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 13 Feb 2017 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
    <description>PFS was defined as the time from randomization until the date of objective disease progression (RECIST 1.1) or death (by any cause in the absence of progression). Progression was defined using RECIST 1.1 as a 20% increase in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions, or a measurable increase in a non-target lesion, or the appearance of new lesions. PFS was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until death due to any cause. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>OS was defined as the time from the date of randomization until death due to any cause. OS was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR) Based on BICR Assesments According to RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>ORR was defined as the percentage of patients with at least one visit response of Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) per RECIST 1.1 for target lesions: CR: Disappearance of all target lesions; PR: &gt;=30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions; OR = CR + PR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DoR) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>DoR was defined as the time from date for first documented response of CR or PR until the first documented response of progression per RECIST 1.1 or death in the absence of progression. DoR was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Patients Alive and Progression Free at 12 Months From (APF12) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 13 Feb 2017 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
    <description>APF12 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive and progression free per RECIST 1.1 at 12 months after randomization per Kaplan-Meier estimate of PFS at 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of Patients Alive and Progression Free at 18 Months From (APF18) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 13 Feb 2017 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
    <description>APF18 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive and progression free per RECIST 1.1 at 18 months after randomization per the Kaplan-Meier estimate of PFS at 18 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Death or Distant Metastasis (TTDM) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>TTDM was defined as the time from the date of randomization until the first date of distant metastasis or death in the absence of distant metastasis. Distant metastasis was defined as any new lesion that was outside of the radiation field according to RECIST 1.1 or proven by biopsy. TTDM was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Patients Alive at 24 Months (OS24)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline until death due to any cause. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>OS24 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive at 24 months after randomization per the Kaplan-Meier estimate of OS at 24 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Second Progression or Death (PFS2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Following confirmed progression, patients were assessed every ~12 weeks until second disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>PFS2 was defined as the time from randomization to the time of the second progression or death. The date of second progression was recorded by the investigator and defined according to local standard clinical practice, and could have involved any of the following: objective radiological, symptomatic progression, or death. RECIST assessments were not collected for assessment of PFS2. PFS2 was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Deterioration of Global Health Status / Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQoL), Assessed Using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer 30-Item Core Quality of Life Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, every 4 weeks for first 8 weeks, then every ~8 weeks until 48 weeks, then every ~12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Global health status/HRQoL was assessed using the EORTC QLQ-C30 global QoL scale which includes 2 items from the QLQ-C30: &quot;How would you rate your overall health during the past week?&quot; (Item 29) and &quot;How would you rate your overall QoL during the past week?&quot; (Item 30). Scores from 0 to 100 were derived for each item with higher scores indicating a better health status. Time to deterioration for global health status/HRQoL was defined as time from randomization until the date of first clinically meaningful deterioration (a decrease in global health status/HRQoL from baseline of ≥10) or death (by any cause) in the absence of a clinically meaningful deterioration. Time to deterioration was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Deterioration of Primary Patient-Reported Outcome (PRO) Symptoms, Assessed Using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QoL Lung Cancer Module (EORTC QLQ-LC13)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, every 4 weeks for first 8 weeks, then every ~8 weeks until 48 weeks, then every ~12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC QLQ-LC13 is a lung cancer specific module from the EORTC comprising 13 questions to assess lung cancer symptoms (cough, hemoptysis, dyspnea, chest pain, arm/shoulder pain, and other pain), treatment related side-effects (sore mouth, dysphagia, peripheral neuropathy and alopecia) and pain medication. Scores from 0 to 100 were derived for each symptom item with higher scores representing greater symptom severity. Time to symptom deterioration was defined as time from randomization until the date of first clinically meaningful symptom deterioration (an increase in the score from baseline of ≥10) or death (by any cause) in the absence of a clinically meaningful symptom deterioration. Results are presented for time to deterioration in the following PRO endpoints identified as primary for EORTC QLQ-LC13: dyspnea, cough, hemoptysis and chest pain. Time to deterioration was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of Durvalumab; Peak and Trough Serum Concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples were collected pre-dose on Day 1 (Week 0), Week 8, Week 24 and Week 48, and post-dose on Day 1 (Week 0) and Week 24. Analysis performed at 22 Mar 2018 DCO.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate PK, blood samples were collected pre-dose and post-dose and trough and peak serum concentrations of durvalumab, respectively, were determined. Pre-dose samples were taken within 60 minutes before infusion and post-dose samples were taken within 10 minutes after the end of infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Anti-Drug Antibody (ADA) Response to Durvalumab</measure>
    <time_frame>Samples were collected pre-dose on Day 1 (Week 0), Week 8, Week 24 and Week 48. Analysis performed at 22 Mar 2018 DCO.</time_frame>
    <description>ADA positive post-baseline only was also referred to as treatment-induced ADA positive. Treatment-boosted ADA was defined as baseline positive ADA titer that was boosted by ≥4-fold following drug administration. Persistently positive was defined as positive at ≥2 post-baseline assessments (with ≥16 weeks between first and last positive) or positive at last post-baseline assessment. Transiently positive was defined as having at least 1 post-baseline ADA positive assessment and not fulfilling the conditions of persistently positive. Confirmed ADA positive samples were subsequently tested in a neutralizing antibody assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">713</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MEDI4736</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MEDI4736 (intravenous infusion)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (matching placebo for intravenous infusion)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MEDI4736</intervention_name>
    <description>MEDI4736 by intravenous infusion. Treatment from Day 1 for a maximum of 12 months or study drug withdrawal if this occurs earlier . The 2:1 ratio (MEDI4736 to placebo).</description>
    <arm_group_label>MEDI4736</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PLACEBO</intervention_name>
    <description>PLACEBO by intravenous infusion. Treatment from Day 1 for a maximum of 12 months or study drug withdrawal if this occurs earlier . The 2:1 ratio (MEDI4736 to placebo).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age at least 18 years.

          2. Documented evidence of NSCLC (locally advanced, unresectable, Stage III)

          3. Patients must have received at least 2 cycles of platinum-based chemotherapy
             concurrent with radiation therapy.

          4. World Health Organisation (WHO) Performance Status of 0 to 1.

          5. Estimated life expectancy of more than 12 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior exposure to any anti-PD-1 or anti-PD-L1 antibody.

          2. Active or prior autoimmune disease or history of immunodeficiency.

          3. Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases, including active bleeding
             diatheses or active infections including hepatitis B, C and HIV.

          4. Evidence of uncontrolled illness such as symptomatic congestive heart failure,
             uncontrolled hypertension or unstable angina pectoris.

          5. Any unresolved toxicity CTCAE &gt;Grade 2 from the prior chemoradiation therapy.

          6. Active or prior documented inflammatory bowel disease (eg, Crohn's disease, ulcerative
             colitis).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>130 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Phil Dennis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AstraZeneca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chandler</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goodyear</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85338</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fayetteville</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72703</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jonesboro</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fullerton</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92835</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxnard</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95816</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92123</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Rosa</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95403</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwich</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06360</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20057</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Myers</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32804</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Saint Lucie</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34952</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30318</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lawrenceville</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30046</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marietta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>50701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Topeka</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66604</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hazard</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>41701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21237</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20850</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salisbury</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Towson</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48910</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis Park</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55426</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Success</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11041</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pinehurst</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28374</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Easley</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29640</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chattanooga</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78731</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Worth</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tyler</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fairfax</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22031</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99208-1129</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98684</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bedford Park</city>
        <zip>5042</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bendigo</city>
        <zip>3550</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Box Hill</city>
        <zip>3128</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herston</city>
        <zip>4029</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kogarah</city>
        <zip>2217</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Launceston</city>
        <zip>7250</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Macquarie</city>
        <zip>2444</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Randwick</city>
        <zip>2031</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westmead</city>
        <zip>2145</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Woolloongabba</city>
        <zip>4102</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aalst</city>
        <zip>9300</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gilly</city>
        <zip>6060</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Libramont-Chevigny</city>
        <zip>6800</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liège</city>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 4N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 4E6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barrie</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L4M 6M2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 4L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newmarket</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L3Y 2P9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oshawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L1G 2B9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <zip>7500000</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <zip>8420383</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Viña del Mar</city>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Avignon Cedex 9</city>
        <zip>84918</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bayonne</city>
        <zip>64100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest Cedex</city>
        <zip>29609</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69008</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille Cedex 20</city>
        <zip>13915</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier Cedex</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <zip>44202</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pau Cedex</city>
        <zip>64046</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <zip>35033</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Herblain</city>
        <zip>44805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif Cedex</city>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10967</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>12351</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Esslingen</city>
        <zip>73730</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grosshansdorf</city>
        <zip>20927</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20251</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>22081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lubeck</city>
        <zip>23538</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Löwenstein</city>
        <zip>74245</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Recklinghausen</city>
        <zip>45659</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regensburg</city>
        <zip>93053</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villingen-Schwenningen</city>
        <zip>78052</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>11527</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Crete</city>
        <zip>71110</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Patras</city>
        <zip>26500</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>54645</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>57010</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <zip>1121</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <zip>1125</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gyula</city>
        <zip>5703</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miskolc</city>
        <zip>3529</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <zip>31096</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aviano</city>
        <zip>33081</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <zip>95123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cremona</city>
        <zip>26100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lecce</city>
        <zip>73100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20133</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pisa</city>
        <zip>56126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00144</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bunkyo-ku</city>
        <zip>113-8431</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bunkyo-ku</city>
        <zip>113-8603</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chuo-ku</city>
        <zip>104-0045</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <zip>812-8582</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Habikino-shi</city>
        <zip>583-8588</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hidaka-shi</city>
        <zip>350-1298</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hirakata-shi</city>
        <zip>573-1191</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hiroshima-shi</city>
        <zip>730-8518</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kanazawa</city>
        <zip>920-8641</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kashiwa</city>
        <zip>277-8577</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kitaadachi-gun</city>
        <zip>362-0806</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kurume-shi</city>
        <zip>830-0011</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Matsuyama-shi</city>
        <zip>791-0280</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nagoya-shi</city>
        <zip>460-0001</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Natori-shi</city>
        <zip>981-1293</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Okayama-shi</city>
        <zip>700-8558</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka-shi</city>
        <zip>541-8567</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osakasayama</city>
        <zip>589-8511</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ota-shi</city>
        <zip>373-8550</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sagamihara-shi</city>
        <zip>252-0375</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sakai-shi</city>
        <zip>591-8555</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sapporo-shi</city>
        <zip>003-0804</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sendai-shi</city>
        <zip>980-0873</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shinjuku-ku</city>
        <zip>162-8655</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sunto-gun</city>
        <zip>411-8777</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Takatsuki-shi</city>
        <zip>569-8686</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ube-shi</city>
        <zip>755-0241</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yokohama-shi</city>
        <zip>236-0051</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yokohama-shi</city>
        <zip>241-8515</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <zip>49201</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cheongju-si</city>
        <zip>361-711</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hwasun-gun</city>
        <zip>58128</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Incheon</city>
        <zip>405-760</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seongnam-si</city>
        <zip>13620</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>02841</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>05505</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>06351</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suwon</city>
        <zip>16247</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cuautitlan Izcalli</city>
        <zip>54769</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monterrey</city>
        <zip>64460</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oaxaca</city>
        <zip>68000</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orizaba</city>
        <zip>94300</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1066 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1081 HV</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Breda</city>
        <zip>4818 CK</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eindhoven</city>
        <zip>5623EJ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <zip>3015 CE</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tilburg</city>
        <zip>5022 GC</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <zip>LIMA 27</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gdańsk</city>
        <zip>80-214</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lublin</city>
        <zip>20-362</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warszawa</city>
        <zip>02-781</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119074</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169610</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>308433</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bardejov</city>
        <zip>08501</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kosice</city>
        <zip>041 91</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nove Zamky</city>
        <zip>94002</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trnava</city>
        <zip>91775</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <zip>7570</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pretoria</city>
        <zip>0181</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vereeniging</city>
        <zip>1930</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alicante</city>
        <zip>03010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08025</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08908</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gerona</city>
        <zip>17007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lérida</city>
        <zip>25198</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28005</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28050</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Sebastian</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zaragoza</city>
        <zip>50009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <zip>40447</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <zip>110</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>10002</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>112</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>23561</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10400</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hat Yai</city>
        <zip>90110</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muang</city>
        <zip>50200</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Adana</city>
        <zip>01130</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <zip>06490</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>34030</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>34844</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izmir</city>
        <zip>35100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Konya</city>
        <zip>42080</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malatya</city>
        <zip>44280</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <zip>G12 0YN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M20 4GJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Truro</city>
        <zip>TR1 3LJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hanoi</city>
        <zip>10000</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh</city>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Chile</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Peru</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Philippines</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.emergingmed.com/networks/AstraZeneca</url>
    <description>AstraZeneca Cancer Study Locator Service astrazeneca@emergingmed.com 1-877-400-465</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_MED_7111&amp;studyid=2582&amp;filename=d4191c00001-statistical%20analysis%20plan%20redacted%20final.pdf</url>
    <description>Related Info</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_MED_7111&amp;studyid=2582&amp;filename=d4191c00001-revised-csp-3_FOR%20JOURNAL_25July17.pdf</url>
    <description>revised CSP</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>February 13, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Locally advanced</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>MEDI4736</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-L1</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage III Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemoradiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune-mediated cancer therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Durvalumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>December 7, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/61/NCT02125461/Prot_002.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>March 22, 2017</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/61/NCT02125461/SAP_003.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Patients were randomized between 09 May 2014 and 22 Apr 2016 in 235 study centers across 26 countries. 2 interim analysis have been conducted for this study with data cut-off (DCO) dates as indicated. Results are reported for analysis of progression-free survival (PFS) (DCO: 13 Feb 2017) and analysis of overall survival (OS) (DCO: 22 Mar 2018).</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Eligible patients with locally advanced, unresectable Stage III non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) were randomized in a 2:1 ratio to receive either durvalumab (MEDI4736) 10 milligrams (mg) / kilogram (kg) every 2 weeks (Q2W) or placebo.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
          <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="476"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="237"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Full Analysis Set (FAS)</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="476"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="237"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Receieved Treatment</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="473"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="236"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Safety Analysis Set</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="475"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="234"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Completed 12 Months of Treatment</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="232"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="82"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="273"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="108"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="203"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="129"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="22"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="14"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Death</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="180"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="115"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>Baseline analysis was based on the FAS consisting of all randomized patients.</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
          <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="476"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="237"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="713"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="63.0" spread="8.66"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="62.6" spread="9.64"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="62.9" spread="8.99"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="142"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="71"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="213"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="334"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="166"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="500"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>White</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="337"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="157"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="494"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Black or African American</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Asian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="120"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="72"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="192"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Native Hawaiian or Pacific Islander</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Other</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Missing</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Smoking History</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Non-smoker</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="43"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="64"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Ex-smoker</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="354"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="178"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="532"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Current smoker</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="79"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="117"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Progression Free Survival Based on Blinded Independent Central Review (BICR) According to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1)</title>
        <description>PFS was defined as the time from randomization until the date of objective disease progression (RECIST 1.1) or death (by any cause in the absence of progression). Progression was defined using RECIST 1.1 as a 20% increase in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions, or a measurable increase in a non-target lesion, or the appearance of new lesions. PFS was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>Tumor scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 13 Feb 2017 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an intent-to-treat (ITT) basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Progression Free Survival Based on Blinded Independent Central Review (BICR) According to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1)</title>
          <description>PFS was defined as the time from randomization until the date of objective disease progression (RECIST 1.1) or death (by any cause in the absence of progression). Progression was defined using RECIST 1.1 as a 20% increase in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions, or a measurable increase in a non-target lesion, or the appearance of new lesions. PFS was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an intent-to-treat (ITT) basis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="16.8" lower_limit="13.0" upper_limit="18.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.6" lower_limit="4.6" upper_limit="7.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;0.0001</p_value>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.52</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.42</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>0.65</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Overall Survival</title>
        <description>OS was defined as the time from the date of randomization until death due to any cause. OS was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline until death due to any cause. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Overall Survival</title>
          <description>OS was defined as the time from the date of randomization until death due to any cause. OS was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="NA" lower_limit="34.7" upper_limit="NA">The median and upper limit of 95% confidence interval (CI) could not be calculated as they were not reached.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="28.7" lower_limit="22.9" upper_limit="NA">Upper limit of 95% CI could not be calculated as it was not reached.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.00251</p_value>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.68</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.53</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>0.87</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Objective Response Rate (ORR) Based on BICR Assesments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
        <description>ORR was defined as the percentage of patients with at least one visit response of Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) per RECIST 1.1 for target lesions: CR: Disappearance of all target lesions; PR: &gt;=30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions; OR = CR + PR.</description>
        <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS (which included all randomized patients) with measureable disease at baseline, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Objective Response Rate (ORR) Based on BICR Assesments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
          <description>ORR was defined as the percentage of patients with at least one visit response of Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) per RECIST 1.1 for target lesions: CR: Disappearance of all target lesions; PR: &gt;=30% decrease in the sum of the longest diameter of target lesions; OR = CR + PR.</description>
          <population>FAS (which included all randomized patients) with measureable disease at baseline, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="443"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="213"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="30.0" lower_limit="25.79" upper_limit="34.53"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="17.8" lower_limit="12.95" upper_limit="23.65"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Analysis performed using Fisher's exact test with mid p-value modification by subtracting half of the probability of the observed table from Fisher's p-value.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;0.001</p_value>
            <method>Fisher Exact</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Duration of Response (DoR) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
        <description>DoR was defined as the time from date for first documented response of CR or PR until the first documented response of progression per RECIST 1.1 or death in the absence of progression. DoR was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis. Only patients with an objective response were included in the analysis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Duration of Response (DoR) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
          <description>DoR was defined as the time from date for first documented response of CR or PR until the first documented response of progression per RECIST 1.1 or death in the absence of progression. DoR was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis. Only patients with an objective response were included in the analysis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="133"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="38"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="NA" lower_limit="27.4" upper_limit="NA">The median and upper limit of 95% CI could not be calculated as they were not reached.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="18.4" lower_limit="6.7" upper_limit="24.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Proportion of Patients Alive and Progression Free at 12 Months From (APF12) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
        <description>APF12 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive and progression free per RECIST 1.1 at 12 months after randomization per Kaplan-Meier estimate of PFS at 12 months.</description>
        <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 13 Feb 2017 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Proportion of Patients Alive and Progression Free at 12 Months From (APF12) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
          <description>APF12 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive and progression free per RECIST 1.1 at 12 months after randomization per Kaplan-Meier estimate of PFS at 12 months.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="55.9" lower_limit="51.0" upper_limit="60.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="35.3" lower_limit="29.0" upper_limit="41.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Proportion of Patients Alive and Progression Free at 18 Months From (APF18) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
        <description>APF18 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive and progression free per RECIST 1.1 at 18 months after randomization per the Kaplan-Meier estimate of PFS at 18 months.</description>
        <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 13 Feb 2017 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Proportion of Patients Alive and Progression Free at 18 Months From (APF18) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
          <description>APF18 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive and progression free per RECIST 1.1 at 18 months after randomization per the Kaplan-Meier estimate of PFS at 18 months.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="44.2" lower_limit="37.7" upper_limit="50.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="27.0" lower_limit="19.9" upper_limit="34.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Time to Death or Distant Metastasis (TTDM) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
        <description>TTDM was defined as the time from the date of randomization until the first date of distant metastasis or death in the absence of distant metastasis. Distant metastasis was defined as any new lesion that was outside of the radiation field according to RECIST 1.1 or proven by biopsy. TTDM was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>Tumour scans performed at baseline then every ~8 weeks up to 48 weeks, then every ~ 12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Death or Distant Metastasis (TTDM) Based on BICR Assessments According to RECIST 1.1</title>
          <description>TTDM was defined as the time from the date of randomization until the first date of distant metastasis or death in the absence of distant metastasis. Distant metastasis was defined as any new lesion that was outside of the radiation field according to RECIST 1.1 or proven by biopsy. TTDM was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="28.3" lower_limit="24.0" upper_limit="34.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="16.2" lower_limit="12.5" upper_limit="21.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;0.0001</p_value>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.53</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.41</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>0.68</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Patients Alive at 24 Months (OS24)</title>
        <description>OS24 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive at 24 months after randomization per the Kaplan-Meier estimate of OS at 24 months.</description>
        <time_frame>From baseline until death due to any cause. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage of Patients Alive at 24 Months (OS24)</title>
          <description>OS24 was defined as the percentage of patients who were alive at 24 months after randomization per the Kaplan-Meier estimate of OS at 24 months.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="66.3" lower_limit="61.7" upper_limit="70.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="55.6" lower_limit="48.9" upper_limit="61.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.005</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>P-value generated based on z-test where z-test statistic is the ratio of the log-transformed ratio of the cumulative hazards in the two treatment arms divided by the square root of the variance.</p_value_desc>
            <method>z-test</method>
            <method_desc>The variance was estimated using the delta method and Greenwood's formula.</method_desc>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Time to Second Progression or Death (PFS2)</title>
        <description>PFS2 was defined as the time from randomization to the time of the second progression or death. The date of second progression was recorded by the investigator and defined according to local standard clinical practice, and could have involved any of the following: objective radiological, symptomatic progression, or death. RECIST assessments were not collected for assessment of PFS2. PFS2 was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>Following confirmed progression, patients were assessed every ~12 weeks until second disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Second Progression or Death (PFS2)</title>
          <description>PFS2 was defined as the time from randomization to the time of the second progression or death. The date of second progression was recorded by the investigator and defined according to local standard clinical practice, and could have involved any of the following: objective radiological, symptomatic progression, or death. RECIST assessments were not collected for assessment of PFS2. PFS2 was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="28.3" lower_limit="25.1" upper_limit="34.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="17.1" lower_limit="14.5" upper_limit="20.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;.0001</p_value>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.58</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.46</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>0.73</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Time to Deterioration of Global Health Status / Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQoL), Assessed Using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer 30-Item Core Quality of Life Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30)</title>
        <description>Global health status/HRQoL was assessed using the EORTC QLQ-C30 global QoL scale which includes 2 items from the QLQ-C30: &quot;How would you rate your overall health during the past week?&quot; (Item 29) and &quot;How would you rate your overall QoL during the past week?&quot; (Item 30). Scores from 0 to 100 were derived for each item with higher scores indicating a better health status. Time to deterioration for global health status/HRQoL was defined as time from randomization until the date of first clinically meaningful deterioration (a decrease in global health status/HRQoL from baseline of ≥10) or death (by any cause) in the absence of a clinically meaningful deterioration. Time to deterioration was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>At baseline, every 4 weeks for first 8 weeks, then every ~8 weeks until 48 weeks, then every ~12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis. Only patients with baseline scores ≥ 10 were included in the analysis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Deterioration of Global Health Status / Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQoL), Assessed Using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer 30-Item Core Quality of Life Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30)</title>
          <description>Global health status/HRQoL was assessed using the EORTC QLQ-C30 global QoL scale which includes 2 items from the QLQ-C30: &quot;How would you rate your overall health during the past week?&quot; (Item 29) and &quot;How would you rate your overall QoL during the past week?&quot; (Item 30). Scores from 0 to 100 were derived for each item with higher scores indicating a better health status. Time to deterioration for global health status/HRQoL was defined as time from randomization until the date of first clinically meaningful deterioration (a decrease in global health status/HRQoL from baseline of ≥10) or death (by any cause) in the absence of a clinically meaningful deterioration. Time to deterioration was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis. Only patients with baseline scores ≥ 10 were included in the analysis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.4" lower_limit="5.5" upper_limit="9.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.7" lower_limit="4.2" upper_limit="10.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>The hazard ratio and CI were estimated from a stratified Cox proportional hazards model with the Breslow method to control for ties, the stratification factors age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female) and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) in the strata statement, and the CI calculated using a profile likelihood approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.664</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</p_value_desc>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.95</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.77</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>1.18</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Time to Deterioration of Primary Patient-Reported Outcome (PRO) Symptoms, Assessed Using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QoL Lung Cancer Module (EORTC QLQ-LC13)</title>
        <description>The EORTC QLQ-LC13 is a lung cancer specific module from the EORTC comprising 13 questions to assess lung cancer symptoms (cough, hemoptysis, dyspnea, chest pain, arm/shoulder pain, and other pain), treatment related side-effects (sore mouth, dysphagia, peripheral neuropathy and alopecia) and pain medication. Scores from 0 to 100 were derived for each symptom item with higher scores representing greater symptom severity. Time to symptom deterioration was defined as time from randomization until the date of first clinically meaningful symptom deterioration (an increase in the score from baseline of ≥10) or death (by any cause) in the absence of a clinically meaningful symptom deterioration. Results are presented for time to deterioration in the following PRO endpoints identified as primary for EORTC QLQ-LC13: dyspnea, cough, hemoptysis and chest pain. Time to deterioration was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
        <time_frame>At baseline, every 4 weeks for first 8 weeks, then every ~8 weeks until 48 weeks, then every ~12 weeks thereafter until confirmed disease progression. Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
        <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis. Only patients with baseline scores ≤ 90 were included in the analysis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Deterioration of Primary Patient-Reported Outcome (PRO) Symptoms, Assessed Using European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QoL Lung Cancer Module (EORTC QLQ-LC13)</title>
          <description>The EORTC QLQ-LC13 is a lung cancer specific module from the EORTC comprising 13 questions to assess lung cancer symptoms (cough, hemoptysis, dyspnea, chest pain, arm/shoulder pain, and other pain), treatment related side-effects (sore mouth, dysphagia, peripheral neuropathy and alopecia) and pain medication. Scores from 0 to 100 were derived for each symptom item with higher scores representing greater symptom severity. Time to symptom deterioration was defined as time from randomization until the date of first clinically meaningful symptom deterioration (an increase in the score from baseline of ≥10) or death (by any cause) in the absence of a clinically meaningful symptom deterioration. Results are presented for time to deterioration in the following PRO endpoints identified as primary for EORTC QLQ-LC13: dyspnea, cough, hemoptysis and chest pain. Time to deterioration was calculated using the Kaplan-Meier technique.</description>
          <population>FAS included all randomized patients, analyzed on an ITT basis. Only patients with baseline scores ≤ 90 were included in the analysis.</population>
          <units>Months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="476"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="237"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Dyspnea</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="467"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="230"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.8" lower_limit="1.9" upper_limit="3.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3.7" lower_limit="2.3" upper_limit="4.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Cough</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="442"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="216"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5.6" lower_limit="4.5" upper_limit="7.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.6" lower_limit="3.7" upper_limit="6.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Hemoptysis</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="472"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="232"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="NA" lower_limit="NA" upper_limit="NA">The median and 95% CIs could not be calculated as they were not reached.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="29.6" lower_limit="21.2" upper_limit="NA">Upper limit of 95% CI could not be calculated as it was not reached.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Chest pain</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="463"/>
                    <count group_id="O2" value="229"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="11.1" lower_limit="7.4" upper_limit="18.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="8.3" lower_limit="5.6" upper_limit="13.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Treatment comparison for dyspnea. The hazard ratio and CI were estimated from a stratified Cox proportional hazards model with the Breslow method to control for ties, the stratification factors age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female) and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) in the strata statement, and the CI calculated using a profile likelihood approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.522</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</p_value_desc>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>1.06</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.88</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>1.29</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Treatment comparison for cough. The hazard ratio and CI were estimated from a stratified Cox proportional hazards model with the Breslow method to control for ties, the stratification factors age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female) and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) in the strata statement, and the CI calculated using a profile likelihood approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.380</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</p_value_desc>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.91</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.74</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>1.12</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Treatment comparison for hemoptysis. The hazard ratio and CI were estimated from a stratified Cox proportional hazards model with the Breslow method to control for ties, the stratification factors age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female) and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) in the strata statement, and the CI calculated using a profile likelihood approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.048</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</p_value_desc>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.75</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.56</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>1.00</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Treatment comparison for chest pain. The hazard ratio and CI were estimated from a stratified Cox proportional hazards model with the Breslow method to control for ties, the stratification factors age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female) and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) in the strata statement, and the CI calculated using a profile likelihood approach.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.626</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Analysis performed using a stratified log rank test adjusting for age at randomization (&lt;65 vs ≥65), sex (male vs female), and smoking history (smoker vs non-smoker) with ties handled using the Breslow approach.</p_value_desc>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.94</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.75</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>1.19</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of Durvalumab; Peak and Trough Serum Concentrations</title>
        <description>To evaluate PK, blood samples were collected pre-dose and post-dose and trough and peak serum concentrations of durvalumab, respectively, were determined. Pre-dose samples were taken within 60 minutes before infusion and post-dose samples were taken within 10 minutes after the end of infusion.</description>
        <time_frame>Samples were collected pre-dose on Day 1 (Week 0), Week 8, Week 24 and Week 48, and post-dose on Day 1 (Week 0) and Week 24. Analysis performed at 22 Mar 2018 DCO.</time_frame>
        <population>PK analysis set included all patients who received at least 1 dose of durvalumab per the protocol, for whom any post-dose data were available, and who did not violate or deviate from the protocol in ways that would significantly affect the PK analyses.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of Durvalumab; Peak and Trough Serum Concentrations</title>
          <description>To evaluate PK, blood samples were collected pre-dose and post-dose and trough and peak serum concentrations of durvalumab, respectively, were determined. Pre-dose samples were taken within 60 minutes before infusion and post-dose samples were taken within 10 minutes after the end of infusion.</description>
          <population>PK analysis set included all patients who received at least 1 dose of durvalumab per the protocol, for whom any post-dose data were available, and who did not violate or deviate from the protocol in ways that would significantly affect the PK analyses.</population>
          <units>Micrograms per milliliter</units>
          <param>Geometric Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Geometric Coefficient of Variation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="473"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Week 0: peak concentration</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="385"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="191.00" spread="72.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 8: trough concentration</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="289"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="120.00" spread="62.2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 24: trough concentration</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="225"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="177.00" spread="47.9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 24: peak concentration</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="207"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="373.00" spread="43.6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 48: trough concentration</title>
              <analyzed_list>
                <analyzed>
                  <units>Participants</units>
                  <scope>Class</scope>
                  <count_list>
                    <count group_id="O1" value="213"/>
                  </count_list>
                </analyzed>
              </analyzed_list>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="186.00" spread="67.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Anti-Drug Antibody (ADA) Response to Durvalumab</title>
        <description>ADA positive post-baseline only was also referred to as treatment-induced ADA positive. Treatment-boosted ADA was defined as baseline positive ADA titer that was boosted by ≥4-fold following drug administration. Persistently positive was defined as positive at ≥2 post-baseline assessments (with ≥16 weeks between first and last positive) or positive at last post-baseline assessment. Transiently positive was defined as having at least 1 post-baseline ADA positive assessment and not fulfilling the conditions of persistently positive. Confirmed ADA positive samples were subsequently tested in a neutralizing antibody assay.</description>
        <time_frame>Samples were collected pre-dose on Day 1 (Week 0), Week 8, Week 24 and Week 48. Analysis performed at 22 Mar 2018 DCO.</time_frame>
        <population>ADA evaluable population included patients who had non-missing baseline ADA and at least 1 non-missing post-baseline ADA results.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
            <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Anti-Drug Antibody (ADA) Response to Durvalumab</title>
          <description>ADA positive post-baseline only was also referred to as treatment-induced ADA positive. Treatment-boosted ADA was defined as baseline positive ADA titer that was boosted by ≥4-fold following drug administration. Persistently positive was defined as positive at ≥2 post-baseline assessments (with ≥16 weeks between first and last positive) or positive at last post-baseline assessment. Transiently positive was defined as having at least 1 post-baseline ADA positive assessment and not fulfilling the conditions of persistently positive. Confirmed ADA positive samples were subsequently tested in a neutralizing antibody assay.</description>
          <population>ADA evaluable population included patients who had non-missing baseline ADA and at least 1 non-missing post-baseline ADA results.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="416"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="204"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>ADA positive at any visit</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>ADA positive post-baseline only</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Treatment-boosted ADA positive</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>ADA positive at baseline and post-baseline</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>ADA positive at baseline only</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>ADA persistently positive</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>ADA transient positive</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Neutralizing antibodies positive at any visit</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Serious and Other (non-serious) treatment-emergent adverse event (TEAE) data was observed up until 90 days following discontinuation of durvalumab/placebo or until the initiation of the first subsequent therapy (whichever occurred first). Assessed until 22 Mar 2018 DCO; up to a maximum of approximately 4 years.</time_frame>
      <desc>All-cause mortality is defined as death due to any cause (including disease progression) and is reported for the FAS. TEAE data is reported for the safety analysis set. 473 and 236 patients in the durvalumab and placebo groups, respectively, received treatment but 2 patients randomized to the placebo group inadvertently received 1 dose of durvalumab and are included in the durvalumab group of the safety analysis set.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Durvalumab (MEDI4736)</title>
          <description>Patients in the durvalumab (MEDI4736) monotherapy group were to receive durvalumab 10 mg/kg Q2W via intravenous infusion for up to 12 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Patients in the placebo group were to receive matching placebo for intravenous infusion Q2W for up to 12 months.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA 19.1</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="183" subjects_at_risk="476"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="116" subjects_at_risk="237"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="138" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="54" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombocytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute coronary syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute myocardial infarction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Angina pectoris</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arrhythmia supraventricular</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arteriospasm coronary</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Atrial fibrillation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="7" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Atrioventricular block complete</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac arrest</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac failure congestive</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiogenic shock</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiomyopathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiopulmonary failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Eosinophilic myocarditis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myocardial infarction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myocardial ischaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pericardial effusion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Right ventricular failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ventricular tachycardia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bradycardia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Eye disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Macular hole</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Abdominal pain lower</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Abdominal pain upper</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diverticulum</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Enteritis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastric ulcer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemorrhoidal haemorrhage</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Inguinal hernia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemorrhoids</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Intestinal obstruction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oesophageal stenosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oesophagitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Influenza like illness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Mucosal inflammation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Asthenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Death</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infusion site extravasation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Non-cardiac chest pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pyrexia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Hepatobiliary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cholecystitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Immune system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sarcoidosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lung abscess</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumocystis jirovecii pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="33" subjects_affected="27" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="14" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia adenoviral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia necrotising</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="3" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia pneumococcal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Septic shock</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sinusitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chest wall abscess</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Endotoxaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastroenteritis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemophilus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Herpes zoster</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Influenza</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lower respiratory tract infection bacterial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lung infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="6" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Necrotising fasciitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Peritonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia bacterial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia haemophilus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia streptococcal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Skin infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Upper respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Viral upper respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>West Nile viral infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fall</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Radiation oesophagitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Femoral neck fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infusion related reaction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Post procedural fistula</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Radiation pneumonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="17" subjects_affected="17" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="5" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal compression fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Traumatic intracranial haemorrhage</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Brain natriuretic peptide increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ejection fraction decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myocardial necrosis marker increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Iron overload</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Decreased appetite</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperkalaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Type 1 diabetes mellitus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Flank pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Musculoskeletal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Intervertebral disc degeneration</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myopathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Polymyalgia rheumatica</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (incl cysts and polyps)</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Giant cell tumour of tendon sheath</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Prostate cancer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bladder cancer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cancer pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Malignant melanoma</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Papillary thyroid cancer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Small intestine carcinoma</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Squamous cell carcinoma</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Squamous cell carcinoma of skin</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Carotid artery stenosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cerebrovascular accident</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Metabolic encephalopathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Syncope</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Adjustment disorder with mixed anxiety and depressed mood</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Alcohol withdrawal syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Renal and urinary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Glomerulonephritis membranous</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute kidney injury</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute prerenal failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nephrolithiasis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Renal tubular acidosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Reproductive system and breast disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Calculus prostatic</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchial obstruction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemoptysis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acquired tracheo-oesophageal fistula</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute interstitial pneumonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute respiratory failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchopleural fistula</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="8" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspnoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Emphysema</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypoxia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Interstitial lung disease</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pleural effusion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia aspiration</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="18" subjects_affected="17" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="8" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumothorax</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary embolism</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Respiratory distress</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Respiratory failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Aortic dissection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypertension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypotension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Jugular vein thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Peripheral ischaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Shock</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vena cava thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA 19.1</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="436" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="211" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="39" subjects_affected="35" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="32" subjects_affected="26" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Endocrine disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperthyroidism</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="39" subjects_affected="35" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypothyroidism</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="63" subjects_affected="55" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Constipation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="58" subjects_affected="56" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="27" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="135" subjects_affected="87" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="56" subjects_affected="46" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="45" subjects_affected="36" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="25" subjects_affected="19" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="88" subjects_affected="68" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="43" subjects_affected="31" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Asthenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="73" subjects_affected="51" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="50" subjects_affected="31" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="130" subjects_affected="114" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="52" subjects_affected="47" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Non-cardiac chest pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="39" subjects_affected="35" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="22" subjects_affected="21" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oedema peripheral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="41" subjects_affected="37" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="10" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pyrexia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="92" subjects_affected="70" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="23" subjects_affected="22" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Upper respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="69" subjects_affected="57" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="30" subjects_affected="24" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="44" subjects_affected="33" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="22" subjects_affected="19" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nasopharyngitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="49" subjects_affected="42" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="18" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="45" subjects_affected="39" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="9" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urinary tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="42" subjects_affected="28" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="13" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Radiation pneumonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="84" subjects_affected="80" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="33" subjects_affected="33" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Decreased appetite</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="83" subjects_affected="68" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="32" subjects_affected="29" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypokalaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="33" subjects_affected="24" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="18" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arthralgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="74" subjects_affected="59" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="28" subjects_affected="26" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Back pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="55" subjects_affected="50" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="31" subjects_affected="27" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Musculoskeletal chest pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="27" subjects_affected="25" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="21" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Musculoskeletal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="44" subjects_affected="39" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="27" subjects_affected="23" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myalgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="41" subjects_affected="38" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="13" subjects_affected="10" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pain in extremity</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="36" subjects_affected="32" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="14" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dizziness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="36" subjects_affected="33" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="25" subjects_affected="22" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Headache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="58" subjects_affected="52" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="23" subjects_affected="21" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Paraesthesia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="24" subjects_affected="22" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="13" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Insomnia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="47" subjects_affected="45" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="18" subjects_affected="17" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cough</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="216" subjects_affected="167" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="75" subjects_affected="59" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspnoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="132" subjects_affected="105" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="66" subjects_affected="56" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="46" subjects_affected="44" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="11" subjects_affected="11" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Productive cough</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="53" subjects_affected="46" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="25" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dry skin</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="38" subjects_affected="37" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="12" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pruritus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="69" subjects_affected="59" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="14" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rash</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="69" subjects_affected="58" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="22" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypertension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="29" subjects_affected="26" subjects_at_risk="475"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="8" subjects_affected="8" subjects_at_risk="234"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Results of interim PFS analysis are considered as final PFS analysis; results of interim OS analysis are considered as final OS analysis. Patients will continue to be followed for long-term survival and updated OS analysis will be reported if needed.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Global Clinical Lead</name_or_title>
      <organization>AstraZeneca</organization>
      <phone>+1 302 885 1180</phone>
      <email>ClinicalTrialTransparency@astrazeneca.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

