<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04119271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00102762</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04119271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Durham Healthy Breathing in Healthy Homes Project</brief_title>
  <acronym>DHBHH</acronym>
  <official_title>Durham Healthy Breathing in Healthy Homes Project: A Duke-Reinvestment Partners Collaborative</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Reinvestment Partners</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine if Home-based Environmental Interventions (HEI) that improve home air-quality
      problems can improve asthma outcomes. Participants will benefit through home-based
      environmental interventions that improve home air-quality problems and improve asthma
      outcomes. All participants will receive a Breath Easy at Home Kit, which could help with
      reducing environmental exposures. The primary objective is to assess the feasibility and
      acceptability of the HEI measured by the proportion of families completing intervention
      components and proportion of caregivers expressing satisfaction with intervention components.
      Secondary objective is to explore the efficacy of a HEI on reducing environmental exposures
      measured using personal wristband monitors.

      Exploratory objective is improvements in asthma control following HEI measured using asthma
      control scores and lung function. The fourth objection is to explore correlations between
      demographics, body weight, housing characteristics (smokers, electronic cigarette use, number
      of pets, housing type) with measures of acceptability, satisfaction and improved exposure
      markers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigator propses a 23-week prospective, open label, single center, environmental
      remediation intervention study in 5-16 year old children with poor asthma control. At visit
      1, wristbands will be dispensed and collected to estimate exposure to a suite of common
      organic contaminants including phthalates, organophosphate esters, several pesticides and
      polyaromatic hydrocarbons (PAH). During the initial home visit, the Healthy Homes Housing
      Specialist will conduct an environmental home assessment to identify asthma triggers in
      accordance with the EPA's recommendations for helping children with asthma. The Housing
      Specialist will follow the EPA document Home Characteristics and Asthma Triggers, and will
      provide the family with a Breathe Easy at Home Kit. The Specialist will provide training and
      instructions on how to use each of the supplies provided in the kit. If the Housing
      Specialist identifies necessary home repairs during the assessment process, the Housing
      Specialist can refer the family to organizations that offer home repairs, modifications, and
      weatherization services. The specialist will discuss the importance of clean air for
      maintaining lung health for all family members and will discuss the importance of banning of
      any indoor smoking, smoking anywhere around the household and smoking in any household
      automobiles (even when the child is not present). Follow up phone calls will be conducted to
      answer questions, complete questionnaires and complete a household environmental interview.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of completed home visits as measured by completion logs</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of completion of the post-intervention phone visit as measured by call logs</measure>
    <time_frame>Four Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of caregiver reporting satisfaction with intervention as measured by survey responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Four Month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Environmental Wristband Markers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks and 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in targeted environmental wristband markers of exposure to organic contaminants in the home environment, including phthalates, organophosphate esters, several pesticides, and polyaromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) markers evaluated using personal silicone wristband monitors. Paired t-tests (or Wilcoxon signed rank tests for non-parametric data) will be used to assess post-intervention changes in targeted wristbands toxin levels.The relationship between changes in these outcomes and measures of intervention adherence will be analyzed using Pearson correlations and ANOVA trend testing as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Indoor Air Quality measured by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks and 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sponsor developed questionnaire-15 to 20 questions asking about air quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Asthma Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in asthma symptom control measured by the asthma control questionnaire 6 (ACQ6) (ambulatory participants only).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spirometry Values as measured by spirometric measures</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Impulse Oscillometry (IOS) simply requires the child to breathe in and out through a mouthpiece for 20-30 seconds. During breathing, a loudspeaker delivers a quiet pulse-shaped pressure-flow signal to the respiratory system. Spirometric measures is the forced vital capacity (FVC),</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Asthma Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Improvements in asthma control following HEI measured using asthma control scores and lung function. For patients enrolled in the ambulatory setting, change in FEV1, FEV1/FVC by spirometry will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spirometry Values as measured by spirometric measures</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Spirometer measure is theforced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1),</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spirometry Values as measured by spirometric measures</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Spirometeric Measure is the FEV1/FVC ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spirometry Values as measured by spirometric measures</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Spirometric Measure is the forced expiratory flow average over 25-75% of FVC (FEF25-75).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Poor Asthma Control</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Breathe Easy at Home Kit Products</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Families will be provided with a Breathe Easy at Home Kit. These kits will include:
a HEPA filtered upright vacuum cleaner, a HEPA-filtered Air Purifier, a Hypoallergenic latex free mattress cover, box spring cover, and two pillow covers, Healthier alternative to most household cleaners, Non- toxic glue type pest control devices for rodent control, and a combination of safe products to locate and kill roaches.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Breathe Easy at Home Kit Products</intervention_name>
    <description>HEPA filtered upright vacuum cleaner, HEPA-filtered Air Purifier, Hypoallergenic latex free mattress cover, box spring cover, and two pillow covers, Healthier alternative to most household cleaners, Non- toxic glue type pest control devices for rodent control and a combination of safe products to locate and kill roaches.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Breathe Easy at Home Kit Products</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Parent/legal guardian has provided informed consent (child has provided assent if
             needed)

          -  5-16 years of age with physician-diagnosed asthma

          -  Evidence of poor asthma control defined as either:

        Hospitalization at Duke Children's Hospital within past 30 days or, ACQ6 &gt; 1.0 during
        ambulatory visit to Duke Asthma Center within 2 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lack of informed consent

          -  Any major chronic illness that in the opinion of the PI would interfere with
             participation in the intervention or completion of the study procedures

          -  Inability to complete baseline measurements in a satisfactory manner according to the
             judgment of the research coordinator or PI

          -  Family is planning to move households in the next 2 months

          -  Parent/Caregiver unable to consent in English

          -  Sensitivity or allergy to silicone
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jason E Lang, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nedenia C Parker, BS</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-6127</phone>
    <email>nedenia.parker@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

