<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04112602</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RIPH3-RNI19/RespiGAG</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-A01361-56</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>19.05.17.43323 RIPH 3 HPS</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04112602</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Respiratory Cathepsins, Proteases Inhibitors and Glycosaminoglycans (GAG) in Mucopolysaccharidosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>RespiGAG</acronym>
  <official_title>Respiratory Impairment in Mucopolysaccharidosis Patients: Impact of Glycosaminoglycans (GAG) on the Proteases/Antiproteases Balance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Tours</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Tours</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mucopolysaccharidosis (MPS) are a group of inherited, metabolic diseases caused by a
      deficiency of lysosomal enzymes that degrade glycosaminoglycans (GAGs). Loss of their
      activity results in cellular accumulation of GAGs fragments leading to progressive
      multi-system manifestations, with respiratory impairment. The cellular and molecular
      mechanisms responsible for the pulmonary impairment remain largely unknown. Specific GAGs,
      such as those accumulating in MPS, may act as potent inhibitors of some respiratory enzymes,
      like lysosomal cathepsins, depending on the nature of GAGs and their concentration. It is
      well established that deregulation of cathepsins levels plays a major role in the
      pathophysiology of some chronic respiratory diseases, such as cystic fibrosis. The role of
      cathepsins and their inhibitors in respiratory samples of MPS patients has never been
      studied. This study will focus on the status/activity of these proteases and their endogenous
      inhibitors in the sputum or tracheal aspiration of patients with MPS. Our main hypothesis is
      that high levels of GAGs in MPS patients impair the physiological activity of cathepsins and
      their inhibitors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Mucopolysaccharidosis (MPS) are a group of inherited, metabolic diseases caused by a
      deficiency of lysosomal enzymes that degrade glycosaminoglycans (GAGs). Loss of their
      activity results in cellular accumulation of GAGs fragments leading to progressive
      multi-system manifestations (central nervous system involvement, dysmorphism, skeletal
      abnormalities, cardiomyopathy, ear/nose/throat and respiratory problems). Impairment of
      pulmonary function is an important health problem for patients with MPS.

      Various therapeutic approaches have been developed to restore deficient enzymatic activity
      (stem cell transplantation, enzyme replacement therapy, gene therapy), but new therapeutic
      approaches may be required, in addition to these current conventional treatments. In
      particular, respiratory failure is not fully restored. The cellular and molecular mechanisms
      responsible for lung dysfunction remain today largely unknown and require additional
      investigations. It is well established that GAGs, upon specific conditions either stimulate
      or inhibit the activity of specific enzymes named cathepsins.

      Cysteine cathepsins are lysosomal proteases that can be secreted extracellularly by
      macrophages, epithelial cells and fibroblasts. Imbalance between cathepsins and their
      inhibitors in favor to proteolysis has been demonstrated in patients with chronic pulmonary
      diseases (silicosis, cystic fibrosis). By contrast, high levels of their endogenous
      inhibitors are found in idiopathic fibrosis. Interestingly, previous studies reported that
      accumulation of sulphated GAGs (chondroitin sulfate, heparan sulfate, dermatan sulfate)
      impaired the collagenolytic activity of cathepsin K in a MPS I mouse model, supporting that
      cathepsin K participates to the pathophysiology of the bone involvement in patients with MPS.
      Moreover, other related cathepsins are regulated in vitro by GAGs.

      Thus, inhibition of cathepsins may contribute to the respiratory impairment in MPS patients.
      However, their expression and their role in the airway of MPS patients are still unknown.
      Moreover, little is known on GAG levels in MPS lungs. The main hypothesis of the proposed
      research is to evaluate the levels of sulfated GAGs (heparan sulfate, chondroitin sulfate,
      dermatan sulfate) in respiratory samples of MPS patients and the ability of theses GAGs to
      modulate the proteolytic activities of lysosomal cathepsins. This would lead to an abnormal
      remodeling of the extracellular matrix architecture, contributing to the respiratory
      disorders of patients with MPS. To validate this hypothesis, a correlational study will be
      performed to find a relationship between cathepsins expression/activity, GAGs concentrations
      and respiratory function.

      This is a multicentre, prospective, non-interventional and case-control study (patients with
      MPS vs non-MPS patients). Pulmonary samples (biological waste) will be collected in patients
      after either a respiratory physiotherapy session (scheduled for routine care) or by tracheal
      aspiration when patients are intubated (intubation for imaging or surgery under general
      anesthesia). Collected samples will be used to assess the level of expression and activity of
      cathepsins and their inhibitors and the amount of sulfated GAGs.

      Patients with MPS will be recruited in some Reference and Competence Centers for Metabolic
      Diseases in France (Angers, Bordeaux, Brest, Rennes, Toulouse, Tours). The non-MPS patients
      will be recruited at the Tours University Hospital (Pediatric Resuscitation).

      Some medical data of patients with MPS will be collected retrospectively from the medical
      record. These data will be age, sex, type of MPS, respiratory assessment.

      The data collected for the non-MPS patients will be age and sex.

      The expected benefits are:

        1. Better understanding of the respiratory pathophysiology in MPS patients: by
           understanding the molecular cathepsins/GAGs interactions.

        2. Development of new therapeutic approaches for respiratory disease in patients with MPS:

           If we can prove that there is a dysregulation of pulmonary cathepsin activity in
           patients with MPS, a treatment that will restore this activity would be of great
           interest. This type of treatment is already studied in bone diseases such as
           osteoporosis. This treatment would be complementary to current conventional therapies,
           like stem cell transplant or enzyme replacement therapy.

        3. New therapeutic approaches potentially effective for other problems in patients with
           MPS:

      The mechanism of cathepsin activity inhibition by GAGs is probably not lung-specific. GAGs
      accumulation and cathepsin expression are ubiquitous in humans. The role of cathepsins
      dysregulation by GAGs has already been described to explain some bone or cardiac
      involvements. These new therapeutic approaches could therefore also have a beneficial effect
      on other organs involvement in patients with MPS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the expression of pulmonary cathepsins, proteases inhibitors and GAGs in MPS patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Detection and identification by Western blot. Results will be compared to non-MPS patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantification of pulmonary cathepsins, protease inhibitors and GAGs in MPS patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Quantification by kinetics and ELISA assays. Results will be compared to non-MPS patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary cathepsins enzymatic activity measurement.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Enzyme activity measurement by enzymatic kinetics techniques.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Mucopolysaccharidoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with MPS</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this cohort are included patients under 18 years old with MPS (all types). The objective is to be representative of the diversity of MPS, and of this evolution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-MPS patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this control group are included patients under 18 years old, with no respiratory problems, no MPS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sputum</intervention_name>
    <description>Sputum will be collected after a respiratory physiotherapy session, scheduled as part of routine care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with MPS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tracheal aspiration</intervention_name>
    <description>Tracheal aspirations will be collected in intubated patients (intubation for surgery under general anesthesia).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-MPS patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with MPS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary samples (sputum / tracheal aspiration)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with MPS:

        In this cohort are included patients under 18 years old with MPS (all types). The objective
        is to be representative of the diversity of MPS, and of this evolution.

        Non-MPS patients:

        In this control group are included patients under 18 years old, with no respiratory
        problems, no MPS.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with MPS:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with a confirmed diagnosis (enzymatic activity, and/or genotyping) of MPS, all
             types (I, II, III, IV, VI, VII, IX)

          -  Aged from 0 to 17 years old

        Non inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic respiratory disease independent of MPS disease (potential interferences with
             our analyzes)

          -  Inability to obtain pulmonary samples

          -  Refusal of the patient, parent or legal representative to participate in this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Impossibility to use pulmonary samples (insufficient volume, conservation problem,
             etc.)

        Non-MPS patients:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with no respiratory disease

          -  Aged from 0 to 17 years old

        Non inclusion Criteria:

          -  Emergency medical situation

          -  Inability to obtain pulmonary expectoration

          -  Refusal of the patient, parent or legal representative to participate in this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Impossibility to use pulmonary samples (insufficient volume, conservation problem,
             etc.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>François Labarthe, MD-PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Tours</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>François Labarthe, MD-PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0247474755</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>francois.labarthe@univ-tours.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sophie DENAMUR</last_name>
    <email>sophie.denamur@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metabolic Disease Competence Centre - Medical Genetics Department - University Hospital, Angers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Angers</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Magalie BARTH, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Magalie BARTH, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metabolic Disease Reference Centre - Medical Genetics Department - University Hospital, Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Didier LACOMBE, MD-PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Didier ACOMBE, MD-PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metabolic Disease Competence Centre - Medical Genetics Department - University Hospital, Brest</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Loïc DE PARSCAU, MD-PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Loïc DE PARSCAU, MD-PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metabolic Disease Competence Centre - Pediatrics Department - University Hospital, Rennes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lena DAMAJ, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lena DAMAJ, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metabolic Disease Reference Centre - Pediatrics Department - University Hospital, Toulouse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guy TOUATI, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guy TOUATI, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Metabolic Disease Reference Centre - Pediatrics Department - University Hospital, Tours</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tours</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>François LABARTHE, MD-PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>François LABARTHE, MD-PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Resuscitation Unit - Universty Hospital, Tours</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tours</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan SA, Peracha H, Ballhausen D, Wiesbauer A, Rohrbach M, Gautschi M, Mason RW, Giugliani R, Suzuki Y, Orii KE, Orii T, Tomatsu S. Epidemiology of mucopolysaccharidoses. Mol Genet Metab. 2017 Jul;121(3):227-240. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2017.05.016. Epub 2017 May 26.</citation>
    <PMID>28595941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rapoport DM, Mitchell JJ. Pathophysiology, evaluation, and management of sleep disorders in the mucopolysaccharidoses. Mol Genet Metab. 2017 Dec;122S:49-54. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2017.08.008. Epub 2017 Aug 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28964643</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kobayashi H. Recent trends in mucopolysaccharidosis research. J Hum Genet. 2019 Feb;64(2):127-137. doi: 10.1038/s10038-018-0534-8. Epub 2018 Nov 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30451936</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilson S, Hashamiyan S, Clarke L, Saftig P, Mort J, Dejica VM, Brömme D. Glycosaminoglycan-mediated loss of cathepsin K collagenolytic activity in MPS I contributes to osteoclast and growth plate abnormalities. Am J Pathol. 2009 Nov;175(5):2053-62. doi: 10.2353/ajpath.2009.090211. Epub 2009 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19834056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lalmanach G, Saidi A, Marchand-Adam S, Lecaille F, Kasabova M. Cysteine cathepsins and cystatins: from ancillary tasks to prominent status in lung diseases. Biol Chem. 2015 Feb;396(2):111-30. doi: 10.1515/hsz-2014-0210. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25178906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brömme D, Lecaille F. Cathepsin K inhibitors for osteoporosis and potential off-target effects. Expert Opin Investig Drugs. 2009 May;18(5):585-600. doi: 10.1517/13543780902832661 . Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19388876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baldo G, Tavares AM, Gonzalez E, Poletto E, Mayer FQ, Matte UD, Giugliani R. Progressive heart disease in mucopolysaccharidosis type I mice may be mediated by increased cathepsin B activity. Cardiovasc Pathol. 2017 Mar - Apr;27:45-50. doi: 10.1016/j.carpath.2017.01.001. Epub 2017 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28104572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sage J, Mallèvre F, Barbarin-Costes F, Samsonov SA, Gehrcke JP, Pisabarro MT, Perrier E, Schnebert S, Roget A, Livache T, Nizard C, Lalmanach G, Lecaille F. Binding of chondroitin 4-sulfate to cathepsin S regulates its enzymatic activity. Biochemistry. 2013 Sep 17;52(37):6487-98. doi: 10.1021/bi400925g. Epub 2013 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23968158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kubaski F, Tomatsu S, Patel P, Shimada T, Xie L, Yasuda E, Mason R, Mackenzie WG, Theroux M, Bober MB, Oldham HM, Orii T, Shaffer TH. Non-invasive pulmonary function test on Morquio patients. Mol Genet Metab. 2015 Aug;115(4):186-92. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2015.06.007. Epub 2015 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26116954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mucopolysaccharidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>lung cathepsins</keyword>
  <keyword>proteases inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>glycosaminoglycans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mucopolysaccharidoses</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

