<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04112550</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00022567</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04112550</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Effectiveness of Pre-operative Methadone in Single Level Lateral Transpsoas Interbody Fusions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Effectiveness of Pre-operative Methadone in Single Level Lateral Transpsoas Interbody Fusions: A Randomized, Double-blinded, Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Methodist Hospital System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spinal operations including lumbar fusions for degenerative disorders are becoming more
      prevalent as the population ages. Inadequate or excessive postoperative analgesia can result
      in medical comorbidities and prolonged hospital length of stay and patient dissatisfaction.

      Existing literature has highlighted the preoperative administration of methadone as a
      promising adjuvant for post operative pain control. Methadone has the benefit of being
      long-acting and has more stable serum concentration and a single preoperative dose may have
      significant benefits post operatively.

      Here the investigators propose a prospective parallel-group, randomized, double-blinded study
      to assess post operative analgesic requirements after preoperative administration of either
      methadone 15 mg or Oxycodone 10/325. Primary outcome will be total IV and PO narcotic
      consumption in the post operative course. Secondary outcomes examined will include time to
      mobility, need for specialist pain management consultation, early readmission (within 2
      weeks) for inadequate pain control, and complications associated with administration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lumbar spinal fusions are becoming increasingly popular and prevalent in the treatment of a
      variety of spinal pathologies, but predominantly for degenerative disease which is most
      prevalent in the obese and or older population. These operations can result in relatively
      high post operative surgical pain and necessitate significant post operative opioid
      consumption which can precipitate co-morbid medical conditions such as respiratory depression
      and failure, pneumonia, gastrointestinal ileus, deep venous thrombosis, and pulmonary
      embolism. Additionally, these medical comorbidities also represent an increased burden on
      healthcare expenditure with increased length of hospital stay, inpatient testing and
      treatment, and need for additional follow up.

      The investigators objective is to study the effect of a long term opioid analgesic,
      methadone, in a uniform population undergoing a single level minimally invasive lumbar
      fusion. The preoperative single dose administration of methadone has already been shown to be
      effective in improving post operative pain control in open multi-level spinal fusion patient
      populations and has become the standard of care in most surgical centers across the country.
      The long half-life of methadone results in improved steady state pharmacokinetics relative to
      other traditional opioids and is thought to improve pain control while decreasing
      consumption. In addition to Mu opioid receptor agonism, Methadone is thought to also have
      adjunctive analgesic and anti-tolerance effects due to CNS excitatory glutamatergic NMDA
      receptor antagonism. There are also reports of synergistic effects from serotonin and
      norepinephrine reuptake inhibition.

      The investigators predict that a single preoperative oral methadone administration can result
      in improved postoperative analgesia with requirement of less IV and PO traditional narcotics
      within the first 2 weeks post operatively and also will not increase co-morbid risks relative
      to traditional shorter acting opioid analgesics that are presently given preoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 11, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative in-hospital patient's narcotic requirement</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 0 to 4</time_frame>
    <description>The total Morphine Milligram Equivalent (MME) for each post-operative day</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in low back pain between the two cohorts as assessed by Oswestry Disbility Index (ODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change in ODI (scale from 0 to 100) from pre-op to post-op (14 days post-op)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Degenerative Disc Disease</condition>
  <condition>Spondylolisthesis, Lumbar Region</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methadone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This cohort will receive oral methadone 15mg po tablet pre-operatively</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oxycodone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This cohort will receive oxycodone/acetaminophen 10/325 po tablet pre-operatively</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methadone Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>FDA approved medication to treat pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methadone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxycodone-Acetaminophen</intervention_name>
    <description>FDA approved medication to treat pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oxycodone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 18 - 70

          -  Will undergo one level minimally invasive lumbar fusion surgery

          -  Primary symptoms are back and/or leg pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Preoperative chronic renal insufficiency or failure (defined as a serum creatinine
             more than 2 mg/dl)

          -  Significant liver disease (cirrhosis or hepatic failure)

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status IV or V

          -  Pulmonary disease necessitating home oxygen therapy

          -  Patients with acute bronchial asthma or hypercarbia

          -  Patient who has or is suspected of having a paralytic ileus

          -  Preoperative use of methadone or hydromorphone

          -  Known hypersensitivity to methadone

          -  Known hypersensitivity to oxycodone

          -  Recent history of opioid or alcohol abuse

          -  Inability to use a PCA device

          -  Inability to speak English

          -  Any patient judged by the anesthesia care team to potentially require prolonged
             postoperative intubation

          -  Participation in another clinical trial

          -  Inability of patient to provide study informed consent (including patients who are
             cognitively impaired)

          -  Presence of drug interaction between methadone/oxycodone and patient's regular or PRN
             medications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sean M Barber, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Houston Methodist</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Saeed S Sadrameli, MD, MS</last_name>
    <phone>2817431385</phone>
    <email>ssadrameli@houstonmethodist.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marcus S Wong, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8324574452</phone>
    <email>mswong@houstonmethodist.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Methodist Hospital System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>SBarber</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Neurosurgery Faculty</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lateral lumbar interbody fusion</keyword>
  <keyword>minimally invasive spinal surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intervertebral Disc Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spondylolisthesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen, hydrocodone drug combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxycodone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methadone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plans to share IPD at the moment</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

