<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04112459</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MP-21-2019-2130</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04112459</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LongVentKids Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>LVK</acronym>
  <official_title>Prolonged Mechanical Ventilation in Paediatric Intensive Care : An International Cross-Sectional Prevalence Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Justine's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Réseau en Santé Respiratoire du Québec</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fonds de la Recherche en Santé du Québec</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Women and Children's Health Research Institute, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Réseau mère-enfant de la francophonie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Justine's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Scientific advances, population growth, lower mortality, and increasing complexity of
      diseases have boosted up the number of patients requiring prolonged breathing assistance with
      mechanical ventilators in the pediatric intensive care units (PICU) in many parts of the
      developed world. Previous studies also suggest that there is a small group of children who
      actually need such a high level of support for extended periods of time, utilizing a lot of
      human and technical resources. We defined children with prolonged mechanical ventilation
      (PMV) if they required supports with a breathing machine for more than 14 days. We propose an
      international point prevalence study of children requiring PMV in PICU. We will conduct the
      study in multiple centers in several different regions, including North and South America,
      Europe, and Asian countries, with a strong relationship with local physician colleagues.
      Practice for patients requiring PMV will be examined including the type and size of local
      PICU, admission and discharge policies, and patient and treatment modalities administered to
      such patients, types of professionals looking after patients in PMV, types of health care. We
      anticipate a high variability in practices suggesting a need to further standardize the
      management of PMV.. Specifically, as an immediate consequence, by comparing and understanding
      the differences in patient demographics, practice details among PICUs in regards to the
      background factors of local PICUs and their patients, practitioners will share their way of
      dealing with such patients. In that way, this study will support the need to generate
      guidelines and lead to patient care improvement in PICUs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 4, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 3, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of PMV</measure>
    <time_frame>eight times during two-year study period</time_frame>
    <description>number of patients meet PMV criteria devided by the number of patients admitted in PICUs on the specific data collection date and time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient and treatment demographics</measure>
    <time_frame>eight times during two-year study period</time_frame>
    <description>patient demographics underlying chronic disease acute disease leading to InMV or to NIV (i.e. reason of PMV) co-morbidities (Cerebral palsy, Seizure disorder, etc.) type of airway access MV mode and the days of ventilations for each mode care providers (e.g. intensivists, pediatric intensivists, anesthesiologist, paediatrician, pulmonologist) Nurse : patient ratio failed extubations or not during PMV location of patients on PMV (PICU or step down unit under PICU staff or not)
Data from 8 study dates will be integrated into a summarized finding in the manuscript</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcomes at 90days follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days from the initial data collection</time_frame>
    <description>complications of mechanical ventilation mortality destination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>Prolonged Mechanical Ventilation in Pediatric Intensive Care Unit</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prolonged mechanical ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention will be applied in this study</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients on invasive or non-invasive mechanical ventilation on the day of the study or
        patients who had been on InMV or non-invasive ventilation (NIVs) during their PICU stays
        will be eligible. Patients who fulfill inclusion criteria and do not meet any exclusion
        criteria will be considered for inclusion in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients who are ventilated &gt;14 consecutive days (after 37 weeks postmenstrual
        post-conception age)*

          -  including for more than 6 hours per day including on InMV and NIV duration

          -  patient who have had and short interruptions (&lt;48hours) of ventilation during the
             weaning process as the same episode of ventilation can be included.

          -  InMV can be administered through an endotracheal tube or a tracheostomy tube.

          -  NIV can be managed through a nasal, full-face, total facial mask, or helmet.

          -  Patient on HFNC will be included as on respiratory support if they have a proper or a
             nasal cannula (that allows &gt;=1 liters/kg/min (LPM) and &gt;4LPM).

          -  We define nasal oxygen supply &lt;1 L/kg/min as non-NIV practice.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;18 years

          -  Already included in this study

          -  No consent if required

          -  Brain death

          -  Premature children not yet at 37 weeks gestational age.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>37 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Jouvet, MD PhD MBA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>St. Justine's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Atsushi Kawaguchi, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+1-(514)912-4247</phone>
    <email>atsushi@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Sainte Justine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T 1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Atsushi Kawaguchi</last_name>
      <email>atsushi@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Justine's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Atsushi Kawaguchi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Postdoctoral Scholar</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data sharing agreement will be mandatory to be signed between the central coordination center (CHU Sainte Justine) and the participating center.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>After all the data collection completed, summarized de-identified study result will be shared with the participating centers. Patient individual data will be shared between the central coordinating center and the center where PI of ancillary and posthoc study belongs.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>All the study protocol and CRF will be shared with the participating centers.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

