<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04112888</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEI 17/73</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04112888</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Infiltrations With Collagen in Episiotomy and Cesarean Scars</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Infiltrations With Collagen in Pelvic Pain Caused by Episiotomy and Cesarean Scars. Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Althaia Xarxa Assistencial Universitària de Manresa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Althaia Xarxa Assistencial Universitària de Manresa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One of the causes of pelvic pain is secondary to scarring due to episiotomy or cesarean after
      delivery.The pain of episiotomies or cesarean scars can be generalized at the level of the
      perineum, or more specifically at the level of the scar. For all these reasons, the presence
      of painful scars after a delivery, either by a cesarean or an episiotomy produces a
      perception of pelvic pain and change is your body schema and a series of negative
      connotations such as secondary dyspareunia, affective alterations, etc.

      To this, the investigators must add the important role that the psychological and social
      aspects can play in the development and perpetuation of a pain of these characteristics.

      The perception of pain is subjective and its intensity will be perceived based on many
      variables in each individual. The psycho-corporal representation of the episiotomy and/or
      cesarean section and its consequences will depend on each woman. In addition to the physical
      aspect, the scar of the episiotomy is the testimony of the birth and its complications. It
      causes a change in the representation of the body and the sex of the patient.

      The objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of collagen infiltrations in pelvic
      pain and the appearance of painful scars of episiotomies and/or cesareans compared to
      conventional treatment with rehabilitation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Randomized clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy of collagen infiltrations in pelvic pain
      caused by cesarean scars and/or episiotomies.

      Those patients who are referred to the Rehabilitation consultation for pelvic pain secondary
      to pain in the cesarean/episiotomy scar who meet the inclusion criteria and who agree to
      participate and sign the informed consent will be included.

      In the baseline assessment, the patient's clinical information will be collected: age,
      obstetric history, pathological history, active treatments and if they breastfeed. The
      following questionnaires will be passed: the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) and the Short Form
      McGill Pain Questionnaire (SF-MPQ) to evaluate the pain caused by the scar, the Vancouver
      Scale of Healing (VSS) and the Patient Component (PSAS) of the Patient and Observer Objective
      Assessment Scale (POSAS) for the evaluation of the scar and initial photograph of the scar. A
      physical examination of the pelvic floor will be performed and the areas to be infiltrated
      will be detected.

      Patients will be randomly assigned to a Control group, will perform the conventional
      treatment, and an Experimental Group, who will perform the conventional treatment and will
      also have 3-5 infiltrations with collagen.

      At 6 and 16 weeks to finalize the treatment, a blinded assessor will perform the final
      assessment by passing the questionnaires used in the baseline assessment. The subjective
      satisfaction of the clinician and the patient will also be assessed using the questionnaires
      Clinical Global Improvement Impression Scale (GGI-I) and the Patient Global Improvement
      Impression Scale (PGI-I).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain caused by the scar (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Pain caused by the scar according to the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). Range 0 to 10. Higher values represent worse pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain caused by the scar (MPQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Pain caused by the scar according to the Short Form McGill Pain (Questionnaire (MPQ). Range 0 to 78. Three dimensions: Sensory (12 ítems), Affective (3 ítems), Evaluative (1 ítem). Higher score higher level of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aspect of the scar (VSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Aspect of the scar according to the Vancouver Scar Scale (VSS). Range 0 to 10. 0 (representing normal skin) and 10 (representing worst scar imaginable).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aspect of the scar (PSAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Aspect of the scar according to according to the patient component (PSAS) of the Scale of objective assessment Patient and Observer (Patient and Observer Scar Assesment Scale POSAS). The PSAS consist of six parameters: scar-related pain, itchness, color, stiffeness, thickness, and irregularity. Each parameter used a 10-point scoring system, with 1 representing normal skin and 10 representing the worst scar imaginable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective satisfaction of the clinician (PGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective satisfaction of the clinician according to Patient Global Impression of Im,provement (PGI-I). Single question asking the patient to rate their satisfaction now, as compared with how it was prior to before beginning treatment on a scale from 1-Very much better to 7 -Very much worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective satisfaction of the clinician (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after the end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective satisfaction of the clinician according to Clinician Global Impression of Improvement (CGI-I). Single question asking the clinician to rate their satisfaction now, as compared with how it was prior to before beginning treatment on a scale from 1- Much better to 5-Much worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Pelvic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Collagen group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive 3 to 5 infiltrations of collagen on the scar once a week.
Patients will receive the conventional treatment of 8 rehabilitation sessions with massage therapy techniques, muscle stretches and fascial work. The rehabilitation sessions will always be carried out by the same physiotherapist specialized in pelvic floor. Two rehabilitation sessions per week during four weeks. The rehabilitation sessions will last 45 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive the conventional treatment of 8 rehabilitation sessions with massage therapy techniques, muscle stretches and fascial work. The rehabilitation sessions will always be carried out by the same physiotherapist specialized in pelvic floor. Two rehabilitation sessions per week during four weeks. The rehabilitation sessions will last 45 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Collagen</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive 3 to 5 collagen infiltrations in the scar once per week. Patients with episiotomy will receive 3 collagen infiltrations while patients who underwent a cesarean section will receive 5 collagen infiltrations. The infiltration will be done by tunneling technique, that is, it will be applied along the scar, placing the needle almost tangential to the entire length of the area, then it will be injected and at the same time the needle will be removed. Infiltrations will be carried out intradermally, previously performing asepsis in the area to be infiltrated. 2 ml syringes will be used to infiltrate the episiotomy scars (we will use 1 vial of 2 ml ) and 5 ml for cesarean scars (2 vials of 2 ml ) and sterile needles of 30G, 13mm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Collagen group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rehabilitation sessions</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive the conventional treatment of 8 rehabilitation sessions with massage therapy techniques, muscle stretches and fascial work. The rehabilitation sessions will always be carried out by the same physiotherapist specialized in pelvic floor. There will be two sessions per week for four weeks. The sessions will last 45 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Collagen group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients between 18-45 years old.

          2. Between 2 and 36 months post-partum

          3. Accept participate in the study and sign the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Mental or cognitive disorder that prevents comprehension.

          2. Being pregnant.

          3. Pacemaker carriers.

          4. On treatment with oral anticoagulants.

          5. Local infections at the point of infiltration.

          6. Total or partial denervation of the pelvic floor.

          7. Neurological diseases: AVC, LM, MS.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Georgia Romero-Culleres, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Althaia Xarxa Assistencial Universitària de Manresa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Althaia Xarxa Assistencial Universitària de Manresa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manresa</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08243</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Althaia Xarxa Assistencial Universitària de Manresa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Georgia Romero</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Episiotomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Colagen</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

