<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04117685</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H16-01794</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04117685</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International Hip Dysplasia Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>IHDR</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, International Hip Dysplasia Registry With Follow-up to Skeletal Maturity: An Analysis of Risk Factors, Screening Practices and Treatment Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH) is the most common hip condition affecting infants
      and children. DDH represents a spectrum of issues affecting the hip joint - a
      &quot;ball-and-socket&quot; joint. When the femoral head (the &quot;ball) is seated properly in the
      acetabulum (the &quot;socket&quot;), the hip is stable and can develop normally. However, when the
      femoral head is not well-seated, the hip can become unstable or dislocate. This instability
      or dislocation of the femoral head prevents the hip joint from developing normally during
      infancy and early childhood. If left undetected or untreated, it can lead to debilitating
      complications later in life.

      Development of a comprehensive, prospective international registry for all infants and
      children with DDH will provide the potential to impact all infants born, not only in British
      Columbia, but around the world. The purpose of this initiative is to identify best practices
      and standardize treatment and management strategies in order to optimize clinical and
      functional outcomes for patients with DDH. This registry includes targeted specific outcomes
      that will be investigated, in addition to the general collection of data on all patients
      diagnosed with any form of DDH up to the age of 10 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      DDH is the most common pediatric hip condition, with 1-3% of all newborns diagnosed at birth.
      However, the true incidence of DDH is difficult to quantify due to significant variations in
      diagnostic criteria, terminology, screening and monitoring procedures, as well as ethnic and
      cultural differences. The spectrum of DDH encompasses mild dysplasia or instability of a
      reduced hip, to a completely dislocated, irreducible hip. If left undetected or untreated, it
      can lead to debilitating complications later in life. Much of the evidence existing to date
      in the DDH literature is from retrospective and/or single-centre studies, and the spectral
      nature of the condition has resulted in inconsistent or ill-defined terminology to classify
      patients in regard to diagnosis and laterality. Consequently, the patient population is often
      not clearly defined or reported, making it difficult to compare or combine different study
      results in order to produce strong evidence to guide treatment and management. This issue was
      highlighted in the updated clinical practice guidelines released in partnership between the
      American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgery (AAOS) and the Pediatric Orthopaedic Society of North
      America (POSNA) in 2014. Of the nine recommendations made, only two were of moderate
      strength, while the other seven were of low strength.

      Discrepancies begin with DDH screening practices. Clinical examination for hip instability is
      a universal standard practice; however, not all cases are detectable by this method, leading
      to potential missed diagnoses or late-presentations that are more difficult to treat. Beyond
      the clinical exam, screening, management and treatment practices are highly variable across
      surgeons, centres and countries. Some countries, particularly those in Europe, employ
      universal ultrasound screening, while others use selective ultrasound screening as a
      supplement to the clinical exam for infants with specific risk factors. Defined risk factors
      that have currently been deemed to warrant further screening and monitoring include breech
      presentation, family history of DDH or a clinical history of hip instability. Regardless of
      screening program, missed or late-presentations still occur, warranting further
      investigation. Further variability is introduced with primary treatment and management.
      Bracing is the most common first-line treatment, particularly in younger patients or patients
      with unstable or reducible hips. Surgical treatment (closed or open reduction) is more often
      used as first-line treatment in older patients, or patients with more severe dislocations.
      However, significant variation is seen in practice patterns, complication rates and treatment
      success with each of these methods, and identification and analysis of prognostic factors
      have been lacking methodological rigor. Development of a comprehensive, prospective registry
      will provide a unique and unprecedented platform for examining numerous aspects of the full
      DDH spectrum, including long-term treatment outcomes and risk factors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2028</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of a general, prospective DDH registry with follow-up to skeletal maturity</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Data will be collected from patients with or at risk of DDH to create a registry. Patients will be followed up until skeletal maturity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of variation in DDH screening, diagnosis, and management protocols</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, variation in DDH screening, diagnosis, and management protocols will be identified.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of brace treatment outcomes within and across diagnostic categories</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, brace treatment outcomes within and across diagnostic categories will be compared.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of surgical treatment outcomes within and across diagnostic categories</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, surgical treatment outcomes within and across diagnostic categories will be compared.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of optimal timing of both bracing and surgical treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, optimal timing of both bracing and surgical treatment will be identified.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification and characterization of risk factors for treatment complications (i.e., AVN)</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, risk factors for treatment complications (i.e., AVN) will be identified and characterized.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of predictors of the need for hip reconstructive surgery in adolescence</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, predictors of the need for hip reconstructive surgery in adolescence will be identified.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of targeted sub-studies within the registry</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Using data from the registry, further targeted DDH sub-studies will be developed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment and analysis of risk factor screening and monitoring protocols for DDH by a non-inferiority randomized controlled trial (RCT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Risk factor screening and monitoring protocols for DDH by a non-inferiority RCT will be assessed and analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of rigid versus dynamic bracing in early treatment of DDH by RCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Rigid versus dynamic bracing in early treatment DDH by RCT will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of observation versus bracing in clinically stable, ultrasonographically dysplastic hips by RCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>Observation versus bracing in clinically stable, ultrasonographically dysplastic hips by RCT will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>An analysis of the impact of brace treatment length after hip stabilization by RCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Until study completion in 2028</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of brace treatment length after hip stabilization by RCT will be analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Dislocation, Congenital</condition>
  <condition>Hip Dysplasia, Congenital, Nonsyndromic</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Dysplasia of the Hip</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Hip Dislocation</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Hip Displacement</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Hip Dysplasia</condition>
  <condition>Dislocation Of Hip, Congenital</condition>
  <condition>Dislocation, Congenital Hip</condition>
  <condition>Displacement, Congenital Hip</condition>
  <condition>Dysplasia, Congenital Hip</condition>
  <condition>Hip Displacement, Congenital</condition>
  <condition>Hip, Dislocation Of, Congenital</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I: Prospective from diagnosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients have been enrolled and followed since diagnosis will be placed into Arm I.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II: Prior treatment at center</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who have received previous treatment and will continue to receive treatment at the participating center will be placed into Arm II.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm III: Prior treatment at outside center</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who have received previous treatment at an outside center but are continuing treatment at a participating center will be placed into Arm III.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Observational</intervention_name>
    <description>All groups will undergo observational data collection. No interventions will be made to patient care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I: Prospective from diagnosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II: Prior treatment at center</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm III: Prior treatment at outside center</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who have been referred to a participating center for DDH risk factors or patients
        with diagnosed DDH will be included in the registry. Patients will be enrolled during one
        of their routine clinic appointments at one of the participating centers.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between the ages of 0 and 10 years at time of initial diagnosis

          -  Referred for DDH screening due to specific risk factors OR diagnosed with DDH

          -  Diagnosis confirmed with appropriate ultrasonographic or radiographic imaging

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known or suspected neuromuscular, collagen, chromosomal or lower extremity congenital
             anomalies

          -  Teratologic hip dislocation (syndromic-associated dislocations)

          -  Over 10 years of age at initial diagnosis

          -  Received prior treatment for DDH without appropriate imaging or documentation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kishore Mulpuri, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily K Schaeffer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6048752359</phone>
    <email>emily.schaeffer@cw.bc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashley L Munoz, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>6048752359</phone>
    <email>ashley.munoz@cw.bc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>British Columbia Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6H 3N1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily K Schaeffer, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>6048752359</phone>
      <email>emily.schaeffer@cw.bc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ashley L Munoz, BSc</last_name>
      <phone>6048752359</phone>
      <email>eva.habib@cw.bc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kishore Mulpuri, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emily K Schaeffer, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kishore Mulpuri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hip dysplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>ddh</keyword>
  <keyword>developmental dysplasia of the hip</keyword>
  <keyword>congenital hip dysplasia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Dislocations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Dislocation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Dislocation, Congenital</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

