<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04112407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5316</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04112407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Pretreatment for Propionibacterium Acnes on Surgical Site Burden in Shoulder Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Pretreatment for Propionibacterium Acnes on Surgical Site Burden in Shoulder Arthroplasty; a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Albany Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albany Medical College</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cutibacterium acnes - formally known as Propionibacter acnes (P. acnes) is the most common
      pathogen associated with prosthetic joint infection of the shoulder. Despite current skin
      preparation techniques, P. acnes is encountered at the skin surface and at the natural
      reservoir in the sebaceous glands during the surgical exposure; current levels of exposure
      are implicated in overall prosthetic infection risk. Therefore, this study endeavors to
      decrease P. acnes burden at the surgical incision using preoperative blue light phototherapy
      and benzyl peroxide washes targeting both the skin surface and sebaceous glands.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study hypotheses will be tested using a prospective randomized-controlled trial of the
      effect of combination blue spectrum phototherapy and benzoyl peroxide on P. acnes at the
      shoulder arthroplasty surgical site. Accordingly, it will conform to the CONSORT
      (Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials) guidelines. Subjects presenting to our
      Orthopaedic department will be randomized to one of three study arms:

        1. Control: standard preparation of the surgical site without P. acnes pretreatment

        2. BPO group: Pretreatment with 2 days of washes prior to surgery

        3. BPO and Phototherapy: 2 days of washes with 3 treatments of blue spectrum phototherapy

      Patients will be seen at our office will be consented and recruited into the study. Subjects
      will have standard of care evaluation including: radiographs, preoperative labs and
      clearances. If selected and agreeable, treatment with phototherapy will involve the
      application of three sessions lasting 3 minutes preoperatively; the sessions will be
      conducted by the patient at home for two days prior to surgery and in the preoperative
      holding area. During each application, protective eyewear will be used. For patients in the
      BPO groups, a 10% benzoyl peroxide wash will be used globally on the operative shoulder and
      axilla during showering. An educational leaflet will outline the surgical field in addition
      to temporary demarcation at the time of BPO pickup at the office. Additional tests, imaging
      or procedures will be at the discretion of the treating physician and documented during the
      study. During the postoperative visit at 10-14 days, the post operative wound will be
      assessed in the standard manner. Final culture results will be recorded for each patient and
      documented in the study database.

        -  The surgical site will be prepared in usual fashion with Chloroprep and the patients
           will receive preoperative Cefazolin (or vancomycin based on penicillin allergy)

        -  Following both draping and skin incision, the surgeons gloves will be changed; any
           blades used in the skin incision will also be discarded

        -  Intraoperative cultures will be taken following established protocols, published in the
           literature: an excisional biopsy 1cm long and 3mm wide will be taken from the medial
           wound edge at the time of incision; the superficial dermal tissue will be swabbed
           immediately after the biopsy is taken and finally, a swab of the glenohumeral (shoulder)
           joint will be performed prior to closure at the end of the procedure and after insertion
           of the implant.

        -  Specimens will be transported to the laboratory adjoining the operating room at our
           institution within 1 hour of harvesting and processed by microbiology technicians in a
           laminar flow biological safety hood. Tissue from the skin edge will be homogenized in
           sterile saline solution and plated on media: blood agar, chocolate agar, Brucella agar,
           MacConkey agar, Columbia nalidixic acid agar and phenylethyl alcohol anaerobic blood
           agar. All media will be incubated at 37C for 14 days.

        -  Specimens will be incubated for 14 days in aerobic and anaerobic media to detect P acnes
           and other organisms

        -  Culture results will not be discussed with patients; patients will be consented to not
           know their results as they are not clinically significant

        -  Prophylactic antibiotic treatment of positive cultures will not be performed in any
           case.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of total culture positivity during shoulder arthroplasty</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days in culture</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the rates of P. Acnes culture positivity (including all samples) between groups. Therein, assessing the efficacy of the interventions to decrease P. Acnes burden (measured by the rate of culture positivity) in surgical field.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of the rate of superficial culture positivity and the rate deep culture positivity during shoulder arthroplasty</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days in culture</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the correlation between the rate of positive deep cultures in samples taken at the end of surgery (1 deep swab) and the rate of superficial culture positivity of samples taken at the beginning of the case (incisional biopsy and superficial dermal swab). It is theorized that P. Acnes in the superficial wound is propagated to the deeper tissues during surgery, impacting deep culture rates and possibly contributing to prosthetic joint infection risk.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Shoulder Arthroplasty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard preparation of the surgical site without P. acnes pretreatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BPO Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pretreatment with 10% Benzoyl peroxide body wash for two consecutive days of washes prior to surgery at home. The anterior shoulder area is wet before treatment; the wash is massaged in for 20 seconds producing a lather and washed off, patting dry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BPO and Phototherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 days of benzoyl peroxide washes and 3 treatments of blue light phototherapy. Pretreatment with 10% Benzoyl peroxide body wash for two consecutive days of washes prior to surgery at home. The anterior shoulder area is wet before treatment; the wash is massaged in for 20 seconds producing a lather and washed off, patting dry. The blue light phototherapy is administered to the shoulder for 3 minutes on three occasions; 2 days before, the day before surgery and in the preoperative area by the patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blue Light Phototherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Phototherapy in the blue light spectrum</description>
    <arm_group_label>BPO and Phototherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Phototherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Benzyl Peroxide</intervention_name>
    <description>Benzyl peroxide wash to be used preoperatively during showering to the operative shoulder site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BPO Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BPO and Phototherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BPO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard surgical site preparation with no P. acnes pretreatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  All patients presenting to the practice that require a shoulder arthroplasty procedure

          -  English fluency and literacy

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Older than 18 years of age

          -  Surgical indications including: primary arthritis, rotator cuff arthropathy,
             post-traumatic arthritis

          -  Primary total shoulder, hemiarthroplasty, primary reverse total shoulder or shoulder
             resurfacing

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Subjects who have had a prior infection of the affected shoulder joint

          -  Recent steroid injection to the shoulder in the past 6 months

          -  Previous open or arthroscopic procedure of the shoulder joint

          -  Recent antibiotic use (within 90 days)

          -  Prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ian D Hutchinson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Albany Medical College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albany Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albany</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ian Hutchinson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>518-262-4000</phone>
      <email>hutchii@amc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>AMC Office for Research</last_name>
      <phone>518-262-2475</phone>
      <email>IRBoard@amc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Zimmerman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ian Hutchinson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Frangiamore SJ, Saleh A, Grosso MJ, Alolabi B, Bauer TW, Iannotti JP, Ricchetti ET. Early Versus Late Culture Growth of Propionibacterium acnes in Revision Shoulder Arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2015 Jul 15;97(14):1149-58. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.N.00881.</citation>
    <PMID>26178890</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pottinger P, Butler-Wu S, Neradilek MB, Merritt A, Bertelsen A, Jette JL, Warme WJ, Matsen FA 3rd. Prognostic factors for bacterial cultures positive for Propionibacterium acnes and other organisms in a large series of revision shoulder arthroplasties performed for stiffness, pain, or loosening. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012 Nov 21;94(22):2075-83. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.K.00861.</citation>
    <PMID>23172325</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Saltzman MD, Nuber GW, Gryzlo SM, Marecek GS, Koh JL. Efficacy of surgical preparation solutions in shoulder surgery. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009 Aug;91(8):1949-53. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.H.00768.</citation>
    <PMID>19651954</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rao AJ, Chalmers PN, Cvetanovich GL, O'Brien MC, Newgren JM, Cole BJ, Verma NN, Nicholson GP, Romeo AA. Preoperative Doxycycline Does Not Reduce Propionibacterium acnes in Shoulder Arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2018 Jun 6;100(11):958-964. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.17.00584.</citation>
    <PMID>29870447</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee MJ, Pottinger PS, Butler-Wu S, Bumgarner RE, Russ SM, Matsen FA 3rd. Propionibacterium persists in the skin despite standard surgical preparation. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2014 Sep 3;96(17):1447-50. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.M.01474.</citation>
    <PMID>25187583</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Falconer TM, Baba M, Kruse LM, Dorrestijn O, Donaldson MJ, Smith MM, Figtree MC, Hudson BJ, Cass B, Young AA. Contamination of the Surgical Field with Propionibacterium acnes in Primary Shoulder Arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2016 Oct 19;98(20):1722-1728.</citation>
    <PMID>27869623</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Canavan TN, Chen E, Elewski BE. Optimizing Non-Antibiotic Treatments for Patients with Acne: A Review. Dermatol Ther (Heidelb). 2016 Dec;6(4):555-578. Epub 2016 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27541148</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kolakowski L, Lai JK, Duvall GT, Jauregui JJ, Dubina AG, Jones DL, Williams KM, Hasan SA, Henn RF 3rd, Gilotra MN. Neer Award 2018: Benzoyl peroxide effectively decreases preoperative Cutibacterium acnes shoulder burden: a prospective randomized controlled trial. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2018 Sep;27(9):1539-1544. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2018.06.012. Epub 2018 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>30054245</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dai T, Gupta A, Murray CK, Vrahas MS, Tegos GP, Hamblin MR. Blue light for infectious diseases: Propionibacterium acnes, Helicobacter pylori, and beyond? Drug Resist Updat. 2012 Aug;15(4):223-36. doi: 10.1016/j.drup.2012.07.001. Epub 2012 Jul 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22846406</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kawada A, Aragane Y, Kameyama H, Sangen Y, Tezuka T. Acne phototherapy with a high-intensity, enhanced, narrow-band, blue light source: an open study and in vitro investigation. J Dermatol Sci. 2002 Nov;30(2):129-35.</citation>
    <PMID>12413768</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ash C, Dubec M, Donne K, Bashford T. Effect of wavelength and beam width on penetration in light-tissue interaction using computational methods. Lasers Med Sci. 2017 Nov;32(8):1909-1918. doi: 10.1007/s10103-017-2317-4. Epub 2017 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>28900751</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Opländer C, Hidding S, Werners FB, Born M, Pallua N, Suschek CV. Effects of blue light irradiation on human dermal fibroblasts. J Photochem Photobiol B. 2011 May 3;103(2):118-25. doi: 10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2011.02.018. Epub 2011 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21421326</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Albany Medical College</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph Zimmerman, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Attending Orthopaedic Surgeon, Department of Surgery, Division of Orthopaedic Surgery,</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>P. Acnes</keyword>
  <keyword>shoulder arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>blue light therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>benzoyl peroxide</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Benzoyl Peroxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

