<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04111991</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00000529</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04111991</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Concussion Symptom Treatment and Education Program (C-STEP) in Post-Concussion Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Psychological Intervention for Children With Post-concussion Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sean Rose</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nationwide Children's Hospital Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chronic Brain Injury Discovery Theme - The Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nationwide Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective randomized intervention study aims to determine if the Concussion Symptom
      Treatment Program (C-STEP), a cognitive behavioral therapy, improves outcomes for children
      with post-concussion syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective randomized intervention study aims to determine if C-STEP improves outcomes
      for children with post-concussion syndrome. Forty children with post-concussion syndrome
      referred to the Nationwide Children's Hospital (NCH) Complex Concussion Clinic will be
      randomized to receive either usual care in the NCH Complex Concussion Clinic (comparison) or
      usual care in the NCH Complex Concussion Clinic plus four weekly sessions of C-STEP
      (treatment).

      C-STEP has been developed for patients with post-concussion syndrome. The CBT intervention
      involves 4 primary components: psychoeducation, activity management, sleep hygiene, and
      relaxation training (adapted from McNally et al., 2018). Psychoeducation involves providing
      patients and families with information about typical concussion symptoms and recovery, the
      role of non-injury/psychological factors in post-concussion syndrome, and information about
      the mind-body connection. Activity management involves setting specific goals to achieve a
      return to normal daily activities such as school attendance, schoolwork completion, household
      activities, and participating in social/leisure activities. The sleep hygiene component
      involves providing individualized recommendations to promote healthy sleep habits such as
      eliminating naps, keeping a consistent sleep schedule, turning off electronics at bedtime, or
      other needed modifications. Finally, relaxation training involves teaching specific
      evidence-based strategies for relaxation and coping with stress such as diaphragmatic
      breathing and progressive muscle relaxation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sport Concussion Assessment Tool- Fifth Edition (SCAT-5) Concussion Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 22-item self and parent-reported list of common concussion symptoms filled out on a 0-6 Likert scale. Scores range from 0 to 122. Higher scores are indicative of worse concussion symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory, Version 4.0 (PedsQL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 23-item self and parent-reported quality of life metric. Each item is rated on a scale of 0-4. Scores range from 0-100 for each subscale (Physical Functioning; Emotional Functioning; Social Functioning; School Functioning) and for the total score. Higher scores are indicative of better quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Brain Connectivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>An advanced neuroimaging protocol will measure brain tissue volume, microstructure, and function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Auditory Attention and Working Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>The digit span forwards and backwards subtest from Wechsler Individual Scales of Intelligence, fifth edition (WISC-V) (age 12-16) or Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scales, fourth edition (WAIS-IV) (age 17-18) will test auditory attention and working memory. Age-normed scaled scores (range 1-19, higher is better performance) will be calculated for process scores of Digits Forward and Digits backward.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Processing Speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>The processing speed index, which consists of the Coding and Symbol Search subtests from the from WISC-V (age 12-16) or WAIS-IV (age 17-18) will test processing speed. Age-normed scaled scores (range 1-19, higher is better performance) will be calculated for Coding and Symbol Search subtests. Scaled scores for these will be summed and used to calculate the Processing Speed Index standard score (range 45-155, higher is better performance).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Phonemic Verbal Fluency</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>The Phonemic Verbal Fluency (letter fluency) subtest from the Delis Kaplan Executive Function Scales (DKEFS) will test executive functioning and phonemic verbal fluency. Age-normed scaled scores (range 1-19, higher is better performance) will be calculated for the phonemic fluency subtest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cognitive Flexibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>The Letter Number Sequencing subtest from from DKEFS will test cognitive flexiblity. Age-normed scaled scores (range 1-19, higher is better performance) will be calculated for the number sequencing and letter-number sequencing trials.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Verbal Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>The Lists (immediate, delayed, and recognition) subtest from the Child and Adolescent Memory Profile (ChAMP) tests verbal memory. Age-normed scaled scores (range 1-19, higher is better performance) will be calculated for Lists, Lists Delayed, and Lists recognition subtests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Performance Validity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>The Medical Symptom Validity Test- (MSVT) will test effort/performance validity. Percentage scores for immediate recognition, delayed recognition, consistency, paired associates, and free recalls will be calculated. Performance will be classified as Pass vs. Fail.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-Concussion Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care in the NCH Complex Concussion Clinic</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care + C-STEP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care in the NCH Complex Concussion Clinic, plus 4 weekly sessions of C-STEP</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual care in the NCH in the Complex Concussion Clinic involves assessment and treatment with a neurologist for medical management of concussion, weekly sessions with an athletic trainer for exercise therapy, and physical therapy sessions depending on need</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care + C-STEP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C-STEP (Cognitive Behavioral Therapy)</intervention_name>
    <description>The C-STEP intervention involves 4 primary components: psychoeducation, activity management, sleep hygiene, and relaxation training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care + C-STEP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children age 12-17 years or adults age 18 years (total age range 12-18) at the time of
             the enrollment visit

          -  Diagnosed concussion occurring between 1 month and 6 months prior to the enrollment
             visit

          -  Endorsing at least 2 symptoms on the SCAT-5 symptom checklist

          -  Participated in the &quot;Predicting outcomes from multi-disciplinary care for
             post-concussion syndrome&quot; study

          -  Intent to participate in the full CCC treatment program (including exercise visits
             once per week)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults unable to consent, Prisoners, Females currently known to be pregnant,
             Non-English speaking patient

          -  Anticipated inability to complete surveys or other study procedures (due to cognitive
             or other disability)

          -  Anticipated inability to complete a brain MRI (due to claustrophobia, implanted
             hardware or other contraindications)

          -  Primary residence more than 60 miles from the NCH Westerville Sports Medicine building

          -  Pre-injury severe mental illness (defined as inpatient psychiatric hospitalization,
             suicide attempt, history of psychotic symptoms, or bipolar disorder)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sean Rose, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sean Rose, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6147224625</phone>
    <email>Sean.Rose@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tyler Busch</last_name>
      <phone>614-722-2000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sean Rose</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Behavior Therapy, Cognitive</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-Concussion Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Post-Concussion Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

