<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04116801</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-000515-16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04116801</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Resection Quality of Cerebral Metastases Using Fluorescence Guided Surgery: a Prospective Randomised Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>Fluomet</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Resection Quality of Cerebral Metastases Using Fluorescence Guided Surgery: a Prospective Randomised Study- Fluomet Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ramsay Générale de Santé</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dr Philippe METELLUS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ramsay Générale de Santé</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Few studies have evaluated the use of fluorescein sodium for the resection of brain tumours
      (especially glioblastomas) but also cerebral metastases. We therefore propose to evaluate the
      technique of fluorescence guided microsurgery (fluorescein sodium) compared to the
      conventional microsurgical technique in the resection of cerebral metastases in adults in
      order to specify, by a prospective and randomised study, the assistance provided by this
      technique in the quality of resection and the gain in terms of overall survival and local
      control of brain disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cerebral metastases are a major public health problem in cancer patients. They are the most
      common brain tumours in adults. It is estimated that approximately 20-40% of patients with
      primary malignant neoplasia will develop cerebral metastasis during the course of their
      illness. In addition, the incidence of brain metastases is increasing due, in particular, to
      the aging of the population, as well as to the improvement of the overall management of
      cancer patients (cytotoxic or targeted systemic treatment) and easier access to magnetic
      resonance imaging (MRI), which improves patient survival. The prognosis of patients with
      brain metastases is still poor and the median overall survival of these patients is of the
      order of a few months. Although the management of brain metastases is multidisciplinary, the
      benefit of surgery has been clearly demonstrated in the literature. Consequently, it is
      demonstrated that the quality of the tumour excision and in particular the carrying out of
      the complete excision of contrast enhancement on the MRI is correlated with improved overall
      survival (especially in case of single metastasis) and improved local control of the disease
      or progression-free survival, but also a better quality of life. It is therefore essential to
      perform the most complete excision possible while minimising the associated morbidity. For
      this purpose, various tools for surgical resection have been developed and are available,
      including intraoperative fluorescence guided surgery. Sodium fluorescein is a fluorochrome
      that accumulates, after intravenous injection, into vascularised tumour tissues and is
      revealed intraoperatively by a light source of suitable wavelength (560 nm) using a set of
      lenses included in the microscope. The resection is thus guided by this fluorescence, the
      complete disappearance of which will translate into a complete tumour resection. Its interest
      is twofold: to increase the percentage of complete tumour resection and to improve survival
      without recurrence and overall survival.Few studies have evaluated the use of fluorescein
      sodium for the resection of brain tumours (especially glioblastomas) but also cerebral
      metastases. If two studies on brain metastases showed a complete resection rate greater than
      80% and a better rate of local control of brain disease, it is important to note that these
      studies were not randomised (with a control arm), they did not really prove the effectiveness
      of this technique under fluorescence, hence the need to set up a randomised study. We
      therefore propose to evaluate the technique of fluorescence guided microsurgery (fluorescein
      sodium) compared to the conventional microsurgical technique in the resection of cerebral
      metastases in adults in order to specify, by a prospective and randomised study, the
      assistance provided by this technique in the quality of resection and the gain in terms of
      overall survival and local control of brain disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 19, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality excision</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the quality of excision in both neurosurgical techniques, in terms of complete resection of cerebral metastases, objectified by the absence of quantifiable tumour residues on early postoperative MRI (before 48 hours) in both groups, evaluated by one of the neuroradiologists associated with the project.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Metastases</condition>
  <condition>Fluorescence Guided Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluorescence arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>fluorescence guided microsurgical resection (under 560 nm filter) in addition to the usual techniques, after iv injection of 200 mg (i.e. 3-4 mg/kg) of fluorescein sodium at the time of skin incision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard excision</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>microsurgical resection with usual techniques</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>microsurgical resection</intervention_name>
    <description>resection of cerebral metastases by microsurgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fluorescence arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard excision</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subject over the age of 18 and under the age of 85

          -  Subject presenting 1 to 5 cerebral secondary locations of which one lesion (contrast
             enhancement of at least 1 cm) is accessible to the most complete excision possible

          -  Unprotected adult within the meaning of the law

          -  Subject belonging to a health insurance scheme

          -  Absence of medical contraindications to surgery and anaesthesia

          -  Absence of medical contraindications to performing an MRI

          -  Known absence of allergy to the injectable form of Fluorescein sodium

          -  Subject having signed their written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject who is a minor, pregnant, parturient or breastfeeding woman

          -  Adult subject under legal protection, guardianship or deprivation of liberty by
             judicial or administrative decision

          -  Subject hospitalised without consent

          -  Anatomical localisation (cerebral trunk, diencephalon) of the cerebral metastasis
             counter-indicating a wide excision at the discretion of the neurosurgeon

          -  Subject participating in a clinical trial or any other research involving human beings

          -  Subject taking beta-blockers

          -  Subject who has not signed a written informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean Francois OUDET</last_name>
    <phone>+33683346567</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33683346567</phone_ext>
    <email>jeanfrancois.oudet@free.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marie Barba</last_name>
    <phone>+330664888704</phone>
    <phone_ext>+330664888704</phone_ext>
    <email>mh.barba@ecten.eu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clairval Private Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <state>Paca</state>
        <zip>13009</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Barba</last_name>
      <phone>+330664888704</phone>
      <phone_ext>+330664888704</phone_ext>
      <email>mh.barba@ecten.eu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jean Francois OUDET</last_name>
      <phone>+33683346567</phone>
      <email>jeanfrancois.oudet@free.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

