<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04118062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IC 2018-09</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04118062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Communicating With Patients on Cancer Resistance to Treatment: the Development of a Communication Tool. (HECTOR)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Communicating With Patients on Cancer Resistance to Treatment: the Development of a Communication Tool. A Qualitative Cross-sectional Study of Professionals, Patients, Parents of Sick Children, and Expert Patients, in the Context of Triple Negative or Luminal B Breast Cancer, Metastatic Uveal Melanoma and Pediatric Cancers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut Curie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut Curie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Resistance to treatment is one of the major themes in cancer research. Despite this, the
      definition and clinical implications of resistance to treatment remain under-explored, and
      patient-physician communication in this context still constitutes a challenge. When
      resistance to cancer treatments occurs, physicians not only have to explain to the patient
      the phenomenon of resistance, often based on complex results (biological results, genomic
      tests, imaging, etc.), but also need to offer alternative therapies, whilst fostering shared
      medical decision-making. These different tasks are particularly challenging for clinicians,
      especially since there are large individual differences at patient level. Indeed, each
      patient has his or her own unique information needs, capacity for understanding, and level of
      desire to participate in treatment decisions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although a challenge, better communicating around resistance to treatment carries many
      potential benefits. Indeed, in similar contexts of announcement of bad news and choice of
      care, Parker and collaborators (1) have highlighted the positive impact of individualized
      care, respecting the needs, quality of care, and quality of life of patients. Given the
      clinical stake, and the lack of scientific knowledge devoted to communication in the context
      of resistance to treatment, it appears necessary to better understand its modalities. In this
      perspective, research has proven the value of tools for supporting communication, including
      the issue of question booklets for patients. These tools provide patients with a list of
      questions submitted to them before the medical consultation, and which they can ask during
      the consultation, and throughout the treatment. This tool fosters communication by helping
      the patient obtain a level of information that is adapted to his or her needs and experience,
      and thus, to be better prepared for care. Despite significant interest for these booklets in
      the field of oncology, none has yet been developed in the specific context of resistance to
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>To meet our objectives, the research team has developed a cross-sectional and mixed exploratory research according to three successive steps :
Step 1: Questionnaires and semi-structured individual interviews will : (a) to identify patients' needs and (b) to build the initial contents of the tool, items and issues. Four patients' populations will be recruited in this step : metastatic uveal melanoma, triple negative breast cancer, luminal B breast cancer, and pediatric cancer. This step will be conducted in parallel with these populations.
Step 2 : Focus groups : to evaluate the acceptability and applicability of the tool in this clinical context with expert patients, researchers and clinicians.
Step 3 : The DELPHI consensus method : to validate the contents of the booklet for patients with expert patients, researchers and clinicians.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>List of patients' needs, particularly regarding communication with physicians</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>List of patients' needs in support, and information delivered by physicians in consultation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Items of communication booklet</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number and content of items, number of categories / themes,</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of the booklet evaluated</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Items and issues revised and reformulated by the experts. Application of the booklet in the determined clinic: Modes of administration of the booklet and patients concerned identified. Implementation of the tool and relevant patients identified</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Content of communication booklet validated</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Consensus criteria: Consensus can be considered to have been reached if the majority of participants (70% or more) rank an item similarly</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Uveal Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Triple Negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Luminal B Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pediatric Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metastatic Uveal Melanoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires and semi-structured individual interviews with patients with Metastatic Uveal Melanoma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Triple Negative Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires and semi-structured individual interviews with patients with Triple Negative Breast Cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Luminal B Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires and semi-structured individual interviews with patients with Luminal B Breast Cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires and semi-structured individual interviews with parents of children with cancer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Expert Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Focus groups (or group interviews) and DELPHI consensus method with expert patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Researchers and Clinicians</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Focus groups (or group interviews) and DELPHI consensus method with Researchers and Clinicians</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaires</description>
    <arm_group_label>Luminal B Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Metastatic Uveal Melanoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triple Negative Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Semi-structured individual interviews</intervention_name>
    <description>Semi-structured individual interviews</description>
    <arm_group_label>Luminal B Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Metastatic Uveal Melanoma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triple Negative Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Focus Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Focus Group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Expert Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Researchers and Clinicians</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DELPHI Consensus Method</intervention_name>
    <description>DELPHI Consensus Method</description>
    <arm_group_label>Expert Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Researchers and Clinicians</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients:

               1. To be 18 years of age or older ;

               2. To have metastatic uveal melanoma (MUM) or triple negative or luminal B breast
                  cancer ;

               3. To have received the information that the disease is resistant to treatment ;

               4. To have read the information and signed the informed consent.

          -  Parents of a sick child:

               1. To be a parent (parental authority holder) of a child with cancer ;

               2. To have received the information that the child disease is resistant to treatment
                  ;

               3. To have read the information and signed the informed consent.

          -  Expert patients:

               1. To be 18 years of age or older ;

               2. To have had cancer (regardless the cancer site) ;

               3. To participated to an expert patient training (fine knowledge of the illness,
                  experience with the disease) ;

               4. To have read the information and signed the informed consent.

          -  Professionals:

               1. To be an oncologist (medical oncologist, surgeon, radiotherapist, supportive care
                  specialist) and/or to be a researcher in oncology (doctor, biologist, geneticist
                  ...) ;

               2. To have patients with a triple-negative or luminal B breast cancer or metastatic
                  uveal melanoma which is resistant to anti-tumor treatments and/or to take part to
                  a research on resistance to cancer treatment;

               3. To have read the information and signed the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &amp; parents of a sick child:

               1. To have difficulties in understanding the French language.

               2. Have or have had cancer (criteria only for parents);

               3. Pregnant woman, likely to be pregnant or breastfeeding (criteria only for
                  patients).

               4. Persons deprived of their liberty or under guardianship;

               5. Impossibility of study requirements respect for geographical, social or
                  psychological reasons.

          -  Expert patients:

               1. To have difficulties in understanding the French language ;

               2. Currently being undergoing anti-tumor treatment.

          -  Professionals:

               1. To have difficulties in understanding the French language ;

               2. Not to be confronted in professional practice with resistance to anti-tumor
                  treatments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sylvie DOLBEAULT, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institut Curie</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne BREDART, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institut Curie</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Léonore ROBIEUX, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>1 44 32 42 71</phone>
    <phone_ext>0033</phone_ext>
    <email>leonore.robieux@curie.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Souhir NEFFATI, Ms</last_name>
    <phone>1 56 24 59 44</phone>
    <phone_ext>0033</phone_ext>
    <email>souhir.neffati@curie.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Curie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75005</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

