<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04114942</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11934</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04114942</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PEERS© for Careers</brief_title>
  <official_title>PEERS© for Careers: An Evidence-based Social Skills Treatment for Post-secondary Employment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current study proposes to investigate the effectiveness of PEERS© adapted to target
      postsecondary students with ASD as they prepare for careers (PEERS© for Careers). Building
      upon the PEERS© evidence base, PEERS© for Careers will target the development of social
      competence and related skills as they pertain to the work setting in a 20-week didactic
      course and subsequent 10-week internship. In the first phase of the study, participants will
      be randomized to be paired with a career coach to support practicing and generalizing the
      skills learned within the didactics portion of the program or to receive the didactic
      training without a career coach. In the second phase of the study, participants will be
      re-randomized to either a career coach or no coach condition and will complete a 10-week
      internship.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Young adults with autism spectrum disorder (ASD) often experience poor postsecondary
      employment outcomes; significantly worse than would be expected based upon their cognitive
      abilities. Social skills deficits are a major contributor to the challenges young adults with
      ASD experience obtaining and maintaining employment. Across studies, research indicates rates
      of unemployment from 40 to 75% for the ASD population, compared to 18.5% for the general
      population of young adults in the same year. Data from a nationally representative survey of
      young adults indicated that only 53.4% of individuals with ASD had ever worked for pay since
      high school, and only 33.6% were currently employed. This reflects a rate of unemployment
      that is four times higher than individuals with intellectual disability, and six to 12 times
      higher than individuals with prior special education services under categories other than
      &quot;Autism,&quot; even after adjusting for covariates such as adaptive skills and conversational
      ability.

      Despite this substantial gap in employment attainment for individuals with ASD, there are
      limited services available to support the transition from post-secondary education to the
      workforce. Existing services often focus on vocational training and supports, rather than
      underlying social skill deficits, and are typically designed for individuals with comorbid
      intellectual disabilities. Recently, a randomized control trial was conducted using the
      Project SEARCH intervention, which was modified for high school seniors with ASD. Results
      were promising, including higher rates of job attainment and higher wages after the
      intervention.

      It is clear that additional intervention development and rigorous research is needed to
      address the ASD employment gap, particularly for individuals who have completed high school
      and have age-typical intellectual abilities. The Program for the Education and Enrichment of
      Relational Skills (PEERS©) is one of the only evidence-based social skills interventions for
      adolescents and adults with ASD. PEERS© has been disseminated world-wide with consistent
      positive outcomes that are maintained over time, including improvements in social
      responsiveness, cooperation, and self-control, as well as increased frequency of peer
      get-togethers and a reduction in ASD-related mannerisms and preoccupations.

      While social skills interventions have helped young adults with ASD improve friendship
      skills, there is a paucity of comprehensive evidence-based treatments focused on the social
      skills young adults need to obtain and maintain employment. The success of the PEERS© program
      in improving friendship-related social skills, coupled with the significant employment
      challenges experienced by this population, was the impetus for the development of the
      comprehensive employment transition program PEERS© for Careers.

      The current study proposes to investigate the effectiveness of PEERS© adapted to target
      post-secondary students with ASD as they prepare for careers (PEERS© for Careers). Building
      upon the PEERS© evidence base, PEERS© for Careers will target the development of social
      competence and related skills as they pertain to the work setting in a 20-week didactic
      course and subsequent 10-week internship. In the first phase of the study, participants will
      be randomized to be paired with a career coach to support practicing and generalizing the
      skills learned within the didactics portion of the program or to receive the didactic
      training without a career coach. In the second phase of the study, participants will be
      re-randomized to either a career coach or no coach condition and will complete a 10-week
      internship.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A sequential multiple assignment randomized trial (SMART) will be conducted, with data collected at 4 major time points (baseline, post P1 (20 weeks), post P2 (10 weeks), 10-week follow up). After baseline assessments, participants will be randomized to receive the 20-week didactic training either with the assistance of a career coach or without (Phase 1). In Phase 2, individuals will be re-randomized to either receive assistance from a career coach during their 10-week internship or complete the internship alone. A follow-up, 10-weeks post internship, will be conducted to measure maintenance of treatment gains.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Employment-related Social Skills Knowledge as Assessed by Test of Employment Social Skills (TESS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (entry), after 20-week didactic (20 weeks after entry), after 10-week internship (30 weeks after entry), at 10-week follow-up (40 weeks after entry)</time_frame>
    <description>The Test of Employment Social Skills (TESS) is a novel, 36-item criterion-referenced measure created to assess young adults' knowledge of the specific social and employment-related skills taught during the intervention. Changes from baseline in TESS scores after 20-week didactic, 10-week internship, and 10-week follow-up will be compared across different interventions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Employment-related Social Skills Knowledge as Assessed by Adapted Contextual Assessment of Social Skills (CASS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (entry), after 20-week didactic (20 weeks after entry), after 10-week internship (30 weeks after entry), at 10-week follow-up (40 weeks after entry)</time_frame>
    <description>The Contextual Assessment of Social Skills (CASS) is a role-play assessment of conversational skills for verbally-fluent adolescents and young adults with ASD which is systematically behaviorally coded. The CASS will be adapted for a work-setting scenario. Change from baseline in CASS scores after 20-week didactic, 10-week internship, and 10-week follow-up will be compared across different interventions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Social Skills Knowledge as Assessed by Social Responsiveness Scale (SRS-2)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (entry), after 20-week didactic (20 weeks after entry), after 10-week internship (30 weeks after entry), at 10-week follow-up (40 weeks after entry)</time_frame>
    <description>The Social Responsiveness Scale (SRS-2) is a standardized, validated measure of severity of ASD symptoms as they occur in natural settings. Changes from baseline in SRS-2 scores after 20-week didactic, 10-week internship, and 10-week follow-up will be compared across different interventions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autism Severity as Assessed by Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence (WASI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (entry)</time_frame>
    <description>The Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence (WASI-II) is a standardized, abbreviated measure of cognitive ability. Scores on the WASI-II at baseline will be analyzed to test whether autism severity at baseline moderates the effect of the intervention as assessed by changes in TESS, CASS, and SRS-2 scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autism Severity as Assessed by Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule (ADOS-2)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (entry)</time_frame>
    <description>The ADOS assesses the presence of ASD in children, adolescents, and adults. Scores on the ADOS-2 at baseline will be analyzed to test whether autism severity at baseline moderates the effect of the intervention as assessed by changes in TESS, CASS, and SRS-2 scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Constant Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomized to have coach during didactic training and internship.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Didactic Only Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomized to have coach during didactic only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Internship Only Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomized to have coach during internship only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Never Coach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomized to never have coach.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Never Coach</intervention_name>
    <description>20 weeks of didactic training and 10 weeks of internship, but no coaching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Never Coach</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Internship Only Coach</intervention_name>
    <description>20 weeks of didactic training with no coaching and 10 weeks of internship with coaching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Internship Only Coach</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Didactic Only Coach</intervention_name>
    <description>20 weeks of didactic training with coaching and 10 weeks of internship with no coaching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Didactic Only Coach</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Constant Coach</intervention_name>
    <description>20 weeks of didactic training and 10 weeks of internship, with coaching throughout.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Constant Coach</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria - Participants will be eligible if they meet the following criteria:

          -  graduated from high school (GED or diploma)

          -  between the ages of 18-35

          -  currently or have history of enrollment in post-secondary education (e.g. junior
             college, community college, 4-year university)

          -  have a pre-existing ASD diagnosis without severe co-morbid mental health disorders
             that may actively impair their ability to participate in the PEERS© for Careers
             program (e.g., psychosis)

          -  have intellectual functioning at or above the average range (&gt;85).

        Exclusion Criteria - Participants will NOT be eligible if they:

          -  have not graduated from high school (GED or diploma)

          -  are not between the ages of 18-35

          -  are not currently of have a history of enrollment in post-secondary education (e.g.
             junior college, community college, 4-year university)

          -  do not have a pre-existing ASD diagnosis, or they have a severe co-morbid mental
             health disorders that may actively impair their ability to participate in the PEERS©
             for Careers program (e.g., psychosis)

          -  have intellectual functioning below the average range (&lt;85).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amanda C Gulsrud, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth A Laugeson, PsyD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katherine H Tsai, BS</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 825-4734</phone>
    <email>katherinehtsai@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elizabeth M Denluck</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 825-3478</phone>
    <email>edenluck@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA CAN Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Shavers</last_name>
      <phone>310-794-4008</phone>
      <email>MShavers@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA PEERS Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katherine Sung, BS</last_name>
      <phone>310-267-3377</phone>
      <email>katherinesung@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laugeson EA, Gantman A, Kapp SK, Orenski K, Ellingsen R. A Randomized Controlled Trial to Improve Social Skills in Young Adults with Autism Spectrum Disorder: The UCLA PEERS(®) Program. J Autism Dev Disord. 2015 Dec;45(12):3978-89. doi: 10.1007/s10803-015-2504-8.</citation>
    <PMID>26109247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohl A, Grice Sheff M, Small S, Nguyen J, Paskor K, Zanjirian A. Predictors of employment status among adults with Autism Spectrum Disorder. Work. 2017;56(2):345-355. doi: 10.3233/WOR-172492.</citation>
    <PMID>28211841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roux AM, Shattuck PT, Cooper BP, Anderson KA, Wagner M, Narendorf SC. Postsecondary employment experiences among young adults with an autism spectrum disorder. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2013 Sep;52(9):931-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jaac.2013.05.019. Epub 2013 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23972695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor JL, Seltzer MM. Employment and post-secondary educational activities for young adults with autism spectrum disorders during the transition to adulthood. J Autism Dev Disord. 2011 May;41(5):566-74. doi: 10.1007/s10803-010-1070-3.</citation>
    <PMID>20640591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amanda Gulsrud, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>young adult</keyword>
  <keyword>college</keyword>
  <keyword>transitions</keyword>
  <keyword>career development</keyword>
  <keyword>social skills</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

