<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04116333</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-79</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04116333</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Using Endotracheal Tube Introducer for Intubation During Mechanical Chest Compressions in a Manikin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Using Endotracheal Tube Introducer for Intubation During Mechanical Chest Compressions in a Manikin: Randomized, Prospective, Crossover Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Derince Training and Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Derince Training and Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study was to compare the impact of using ETI with the Macintosh laryngoscope
      on first pass success rates of the final year students of medical school on a manikin during
      continuous chest compressions with mechanical compression device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fifty-two final year students of Kocaeli University Medical School will participate to the
      study. The participants will complete the one-hour training lecture on the use of the
      Macintosh laryngoscope (ML) and the endotracheal tube introducer (ETI) that will be
      instructed by an emergency medicine specialist. The information section will be followed by a
      chance of practice each endotracheal intubation method once by using the ML with and without
      the ETI on the manikin.

      Mechanical compression device will be used to perform chest compressions. The manikin will be
      placed on an ambulance stretcher in a supine position. Airway interventions will be performed
      in a sitting position on a seat that will be adjusted to the same height with the ambulance
      seat. The airway kit will be placed beside the head of the manikin.

      Each participant will perform 2 airway interventions. Participants will be allowed for
      maximum 2 attempts for each method. Each procedure will be recorded to the video camera. The
      participants will be aware of the video camera. Following the interventions each participant
      will be asked to grade the difficulty of the both methods on a 5-point Likert scale defined
      as 1: very easy, 2: easy, 3: moderate, 4: difficult and 5: very difficult. The participants
      will be asked for whether they have prior clinical experience or not with ML or/and ML with
      ETI use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 9, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 10, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized to perform either Macintosh laryngoscope or Macintosh laryngoscope with endotracheal tube introducer first, using the envelope method. After completing these initial interventions, they will use the second method.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will be aware of the general nature of the study, but they will be blinded to specific objectives of the study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>First pass success</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the first pass success of the Macintosh laryngoscope and Macintosh laryngoscope with endotracheal tube introducer groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to endotracheal intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>The mean time to successful endotracheal intubation of Macintosh laryngoscope and Macintosh laryngoscope with endotracheal tube introducer groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Second endotracheal intubation attempt success rates</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Second endotracheal intubation attempt success rates of Macintosh laryngoscope and Macintosh laryngoscope with endotracheal tube introducer groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difficulty level of each method according to the Likert scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Grading the difficulty of the Macintosh laryngoscope and Macintosh laryngoscope with endotracheal tube introducer on a 5-point Likert scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Intubation, Intratracheal</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Cardiac Life Support</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ML + ETI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intubation with using endotracheal tube introducer with the Macintosh laryngoscope on a manikin during continuous chest compressions with mechanical compression device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ML</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intubation with using the Macintosh laryngoscope on a manikin during continuous chest compressions with mechanical compression device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endotracheal tube introducer</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of endotracheal tube introducer with the Macintosh laryngoscope on a manikin during continuous chest compressions with mechanical compression device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ML + ETI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Macintosh laryngoscope</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of the Macintosh laryngoscope on a manikin during continuous chest compressions with mechanical compression device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ML</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ML + ETI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who want to participate the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who do not want to participate the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>ASIM E OZBEK, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+1-443-800-0458</phone>
    <email>drenesozbek@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benjamin EJ, Blaha MJ, Chiuve SE, Cushman M, Das SR, Deo R, de Ferranti SD, Floyd J, Fornage M, Gillespie C, Isasi CR, Jiménez MC, Jordan LC, Judd SE, Lackland D, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth L, Liu S, Longenecker CT, Mackey RH, Matsushita K, Mozaffarian D, Mussolino ME, Nasir K, Neumar RW, Palaniappan L, Pandey DK, Thiagarajan RR, Reeves MJ, Ritchey M, Rodriguez CJ, Roth GA, Rosamond WD, Sasson C, Towfighi A, Tsao CW, Turner MB, Virani SS, Voeks JH, Willey JZ, Wilkins JT, Wu JH, Alger HM, Wong SS, Muntner P; American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart Disease and Stroke Statistics-2017 Update: A Report From the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2017 Mar 7;135(10):e146-e603. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000485. Epub 2017 Jan 25. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2017 Mar 7;135(10 ):e646. Circulation. 2017 Sep 5;136(10 ):e196.</citation>
    <PMID>28122885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McNally B, Robb R, Mehta M, Vellano K, Valderrama AL, Yoon PW, Sasson C, Crouch A, Perez AB, Merritt R, Kellermann A; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Out-of-hospital cardiac arrest surveillance --- Cardiac Arrest Registry to Enhance Survival (CARES), United States, October 1, 2005--December 31, 2010. MMWR Surveill Summ. 2011 Jul 29;60(8):1-19.</citation>
    <PMID>21796098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Link MS, Berkow LC, Kudenchuk PJ, Halperin HR, Hess EP, Moitra VK, Neumar RW, O'Neil BJ, Paxton JH, Silvers SM, White RD, Yannopoulos D, Donnino MW. Part 7: Adult Advanced Cardiovascular Life Support: 2015 American Heart Association Guidelines Update for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2015 Nov 3;132(18 Suppl 2):S444-64. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000261. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2015 Dec 15;132(24):e385.</citation>
    <PMID>26472995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kleinman ME, Perkins GD, Bhanji F, Billi JE, Bray JE, Callaway CW, de Caen A, Finn JC, Hazinski MF, Lim SH, Maconochie I, Nadkarni V, Neumar RW, Nikolaou N, Nolan JP, Reis A, Sierra AF, Singletary EM, Soar J, Stanton D, Travers A, Welsford M, Zideman D. ILCOR Scientific Knowledge Gaps and Clinical Research Priorities for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care: A Consensus Statement. Circulation. 2018 May 29;137(22):e802-e819. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000561. Epub 2018 Apr 26. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2018 Jul 31;138(5):e77.</citation>
    <PMID>29700123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brooks SC, Anderson ML, Bruder E, Daya MR, Gaffney A, Otto CW, Singer AJ, Thiagarajan RR, Travers AH. Part 6: Alternative Techniques and Ancillary Devices for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation: 2015 American Heart Association Guidelines Update for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2015 Nov 3;132(18 Suppl 2):S436-43. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000260. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26472994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le DH, Reed DB, Weinstein G, Gregory M, Brown LH. Paramedic use of endotracheal tube introducers for the difficult airway. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2001 Apr-Jun;5(2):155-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11339725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kovacs G, Law JA, McCrossin C, Vu M, Leblanc D, Gao J. A comparison of a fiberoptic stylet and a bougie as adjuncts to direct laryngoscopy in a manikin-simulated difficult airway. Ann Emerg Med. 2007 Dec;50(6):676-85. Epub 2007 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>17681639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park L, Zeng I, Brainard A. Systematic review and meta-analysis of first-pass success rates in emergency department intubation: Creating a benchmark for emergency airway care. Emerg Med Australas. 2017 Feb;29(1):40-47. doi: 10.1111/1742-6723.12704. Epub 2016 Oct 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27785883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Derince Training and Research Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>ASIM ENES ÖZBEK</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

