<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04118452</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-001556</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>7R01HD092406-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04118452</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Achieving My Potential: A Randomized, Controlled Trial of a Telephone-Based Developmental Care Coordination System</brief_title>
  <acronym>AMP</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled Trial of a Telephone-Based Developmental Care Coordination System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Information and Referral Federation of Los Angeles County (211 LA County)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed project is a randomized controlled trial of a telephone-based early childhood
      developmental care coordination system, in partnership with 2-1-1 Los Angeles County (211LA),
      part of a national network of 2-1-1 call centers covering 93% of the US population. The study
      will test the effectiveness of 211LA in increasing referrals for developmental evaluation,
      increasing the numbers of children deemed eligible for services, and increasing the number of
      children actually receiving interventions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial will enroll 662 children ages 1-3 years who receive well-child care at one of 10
      partner clinic sites (belonging to 4 partner clinic systems). The research study team will
      conduct developmental screening on all children using the Parental Evaluation of
      Developmental Status (PEDS) Online system, and randomize children 1:1 into intervention
      (connection to 211LA for developmental care coordination + usual care) or control (usual care
      alone, with developmental care coordination conducted by clinic staff).

      Primary outcomes will include referrals to early intervention evaluations, eligibility for
      intervention services, and receipt of services. The investigators will measure these outcomes
      through parent report, medical record review, and 211LA data, at 6 months after enrollment.
      For children with elevated developmental risk based on the PEDS Online results, the study
      will assess development using the PEDS:DM-AL (Parents' Evaluation of Developmental Status:
      Developmental Milestones - Assessment Level), conducted at baseline as well as 12 and 24
      months after enrollment. For all children, research study team personnel will administer the
      language subscale of the PEDS:DM-AL at baseline, 12 months and 24 months, to evaluate
      development over time in the two groups. The investigators will measure behavioral outcomes
      for all children using the externalizing behavior subscale of the Child Behavior Checklist.

      Expected findings include higher rates of referrals, eligibility, and receipt of intervention
      services among intervention group participants, and greater developmental gains among
      children in the intervention group. The study will also examine the costs of the program in
      relation to these outcomes, to estimate the costs and potential long-term benefits of this
      model. If effective, the model has the potential to disseminate rapidly throughout the 2-1-1
      network and transform developmental care coordination in the US.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Referral to, eligibility for, and receipt of early childhood developmental services 6 months after enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be assessed by 1) the percentage of children who are successfully referred to early childhood service organizations for evaluation, 2) the percentage of children who are deemed eligible for services by service organizations, and 3) the percentage of children who receive services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Developmental Outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in child developmental assessment score between baseline and 24 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The PEDS:DM-AL (Parents' Evaluation of Developmental Status: Developmental Milestones - Assessment Level) will be used to determine developmental assessment scores. All children will receive the language sub-scale of this instrument, and those children who screened positive (at high or moderate risk on the PEDS Online) will receive the full assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Cost / Benefit Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention costs per child screened are composed of the 211LA program costs for care coordination and the costs of services received. Intervention benefits are the long-term benefits of service receipt in terms of potential changes in employment, income, crime, and life expectancy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of referrals, number of children eligible for services, and number of children who have received services</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcome will be assessed by the average number of 1) referrals made, 2) services for which children are deemed eligible, and 3) services received for each family; the investigators will primarily consider referrals to high-level intervention services for developmental and behavioral problems, but will also track referrals to development-related preventive and support services.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">662</enrollment>
  <condition>Child Development</condition>
  <condition>Health Services Research</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention + Usual Care + Developmental Screening Results</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention group families will receive usual care and developmental screening results will be shared with each child's primary care provider. In addition, they will be connected via telephone to 2-1-1 prior to their scheduled well-child visit for the telephone-based early childhood development care coordination intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care + Developmental Screening Results</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive usual care. In addition, developmental screening results will be shared with each child's primary care provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone-based early childhood developmental care coordination</intervention_name>
    <description>The 211LA care coordinator will review developmental screening results and provide referral recommendations to the family and use 211LA's extensive resource directory and agency relationships to identify appropriate referrals. The 211LA care coordinator will provide a report to the clinical provider containing recommendations for follow-up and a care coordination plan. The report will be scanned into the EMR by clinic staff and be available for provider review. The 211LA care coordinator will also make all recommended referrals and will call the family monthly until 1) children begin receiving services, 2) families refuse services, or 3) children are deemed ineligible by service providers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention + Usual Care + Developmental Screening Results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A patient in one of the four partner community clinic systems (ChapCare, Kaiser
             Permanente LA Medical Center, South Central Family Health Center, and Via Care)

          -  A patient with an upcoming one- to three-year old well child appointment scheduled

          -  Child aged 11-42 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parent who does not speak English or Spanish

          -  Child with history of developmental and/or behavioral diagnosis or having been
             referred to or received developmental and/or behavioral services.

          -  Child has a sibling already enrolled in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>42 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul J Chung, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Central Family Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90011</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Via Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90022</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Los Angeles Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ChapCare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pasadena</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson BB, Thompson LR, Herrera P, Biely C, Arriola Zarate D, Aceves I, Estrada I, Chan V, Orantes C, Chung PJ. Telephone-Based Developmental Screening and Care Coordination Through 2-1-1: A Randomized Trial. Pediatrics. 2019 Apr;143(4). pii: e20181064. doi: 10.1542/peds.2018-1064.</citation>
    <PMID>30894408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Chung</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Adjunct Professor of Pediatrics and Health Policy &amp; Management</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>early childhood development</keyword>
  <keyword>developmental screening</keyword>
  <keyword>care coordination</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data for all primary and secondary outcome measures will be shared.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be shared within 2 years of study completion.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Proposals should be directed to lindseythompson@mednet.ucla.edu. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement. Data are available for 5 years at a third party website, to be provided when requests are approved.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

