<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04111575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19.04.2017/No:7-35</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04111575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Music Therapy for Women, Delivered Via Cesarean Section</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Turkish Classical Music on Postpartum Pain and Anxiety in Women Who Delivered Via Cesarean Section</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kahramanmaras Sutcu Imam University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kahramanmaras Sutcu Imam University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Musical therapy is a type of therapy which is performed under a regular method by adjusting
      the physiological and psychological effects of musical tones and melodies in accordance with
      various situations. Therefore, the study was carried out as a randomized controlled trial in
      order to evaluate the effect of music therapy on the level of pain and anxiety in the
      postpartum period in women who delivered via cesarean section.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: The study was carried out in order to determine the effect of music therapy on
      the level of postpartum pain and anxiety in women who delivered via cesarean section.

      Design, setting and subjects: The randomized controlled trial was conducted on 126 women who
      delivered via cesarean section in a tertiary hospital. The subjects were allocated to three
      groups (n=42 each) Interventions: In the experimental group 1 (once a day) and group 2 (twice
      a day) were made to listen to music for 30 minutes for two consecutive days. The control
      group routine care of 30 min a day in bed rest. The Personal Information Form, Visual Analog
      Scale, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory were administered to participants. In the analysis of
      the data, one-way ANOVA, paired t-test, Kruskal Wallis-H and Wilcoxon tests were used.

      Main outcome measures: State anxiety level and pain level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 26, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Design, setting and subjects: The randomized controlled trial was conducted on 126 women who delivered via cesarean section in a tertiary hospital. The subjects were allocated to three groups (n=42 each) Interventions: In the experimental group 1 (once a day) and group 2 (twice a day) were made to listen to music for 30 minutes for two consecutive days. The control group routine care of 30 min a day in bed rest. The Personal Information Form, Visual Analog Scale, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory were administered to participants.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>On the first and second days after C-section, change from first anxiety level at 30 minutes.The inventory has a Likert type scale of 20 items which aim to measure the state anxiety level.Higher scores indicate greater anxiety</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety level by State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>On the first and second days after C-section, change from first pain level at 30 minute.The patient marks the pain he/she feels on a scale of 10 cm (100 mm), pain point 1 means &quot;no pain&quot;, pain point 10 means &quot;worst pain possible.&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Pain Level by Visual Analog Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Section</condition>
  <condition>Postpartum Period</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>music therapy group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mothers in the experimental group 1 received music therapy for 30 minutes a day.They listened music for two consecutive days, considering the first day after the C-section as the beginning day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>music therapy group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mothers in the experimental group 1 received music therapy for 30 minutes twice a day. They listened music for two consecutive days, considering the first day after the C-section as the beginning day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the control group were made to rest in bed for 30 minutes a day for two consecutive days, considering the first day after the C-section as the beginning day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Music Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Music Therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>music therapy group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>music therapy group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>musicotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  being at the age of 18 and above,

          -  being healthy,

          -  having given a live birth,

          -  having no hearing impairment,

          -  complication not having developed either in the mother or the baby

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  being at the age of 17 and below,

          -  being unhealthy,

          -  having given a stillbirth,

          -  having hearing impairment,

          -  complication having developed either in the mother or the baby
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eylem TOKER</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kahramanmaraş</city>
        <state>Dulkadiroglu</state>
        <zip>46100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/112738/1/9789240692671_eng.pdf?ua=1.</url>
    <description>The World Health Statistics 2014. Accessed from: 2018</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hips.hacettepe.edu.tr/tnsa2013/rapor/TNSA_2013_ana_rapor.pdf</url>
    <description>Turkey Demographic and Health Survey 2013. Hacettepe University Institute of Population Studies; 2014; Ankara, Turkey. Accessed from: 2018</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu J, Chaplin W, Amico J, Butler M, Ojie MJ, Hennedy D, Clemow L. Music for surgical abortion care study: a randomized controlled pilot study. Contraception. 2012 May;85(5):496-502. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2011.09.018. Epub 2011 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22079604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bally K, Campbell D, Chesnick K, Tranmer JE. Effects of patient-controlled music therapy during coronary angiography on procedural pain and anxiety distress syndrome. Crit Care Nurse. 2003 Apr;23(2):50-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12725195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ebneshahidi A, Mohseni M. The effect of patient-selected music on early postoperative pain, anxiety, and hemodynamic profile in cesarean section surgery. J Altern Complement Med. 2008 Sep;14(7):827-31. doi: 10.1089/acm.2007.0752.</citation>
    <PMID>18803492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tournaire M, Theau-Yonneau A. Complementary and alternative approaches to pain relief during labor. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2007 Dec;4(4):409-17. doi: 10.1093/ecam/nem012.</citation>
    <PMID>18227907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toker E, Kömürcü N. Effect of Turkish classical music on prenatal anxiety and satisfaction: A randomized controlled trial in pregnant women with pre-eclampsia. Complement Ther Med. 2017 Feb;30:1-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2016.11.005. Epub 2016 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28137517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bekiroğlu T, Ovayolu N, Ergün Y, Ekerbiçer HÇ. Effect of Turkish classical music on blood pressure: a randomized controlled trial in hypertensive elderly patients. Complement Ther Med. 2013 Jun;21(3):147-54. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2013.03.005. Epub 2013 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23642944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shin HS, Kim JH. Music Therapy on Anxiety, Stress and Maternal-fetal Attachment in Pregnant Women During Transvaginal Ultrasound. Asian Nurs Res (Korean Soc Nurs Sci). 2011 Mar;5(1):19-27. doi: 10.1016/S1976-1317(11)60010-8. Epub 2011 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25029946</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laopaiboon M, Lumbiganon P, Martis R, Vatanasapt P, Somjaivong B. Music during caesarean section under regional anaesthesia for improving maternal and infant outcomes. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Apr 15;(2):CD006914. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006914.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19370660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Handan E, Sahiner NC, Bal MD, Dissiz M. Effects of Music during Multiple Cesarean Section Delivery. J Coll Physicians Surg Pak. 2018 Mar;28(3):247-249. doi: 10.29271/jcpsp.2018.03.247.</citation>
    <PMID>29544589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hepp P, Hagenbeck C, Gilles J, Wolf OT, Goertz W, Janni W, Balan P, Fleisch M, Fehm T, Schaal NK. Effects of music intervention during caesarean delivery on anxiety and stress of the mother a controlled, randomised study. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2018 Nov 3;18(1):435. doi: 10.1186/s12884-018-2069-6.</citation>
    <PMID>30390639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moradipanah F, Mohammadi E, Mohammadil AZ. Effect of music on anxiety, stress, and depression levels in patients undergoing coronary angiography. East Mediterr Health J. 2009 May-Jun;15(3):639-47.</citation>
    <PMID>19731780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrer AJ. The effect of live music on decreasing anxiety in patients undergoing chemotherapy treatment. J Music Ther. 2007 Fall;44(3):242-55.</citation>
    <PMID>17645387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tseng YF, Chen CH, Lee CS. Effects of listening to music on postpartum stress and anxiety levels. J Clin Nurs. 2010 Apr;19(7-8):1049-55. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2702.2009.02998.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20492049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kafali H, Derbent A, Keskin E, Simavli S, Gözdemir E. Effect of maternal anxiety and music on fetal movements and fetal heart rate patterns. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2011 Mar;24(3):461-4. doi: 10.3109/14767058.2010.501122. Epub 2010 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>20608798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang M, Li L, Zhu H, Alexander IM, Liu S, Zhou W, Ren X. Music therapy to relieve anxiety in pregnant women on bedrest: a randomized, controlled trial. MCN Am J Matern Child Nurs. 2009 Sep-Oct;34(5):316-23. doi: 10.1097/01.NMC.0000360425.52228.95.</citation>
    <PMID>19713801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vianna MN, Barbosa AP, Carvalhaes AS, Cunha AJ. Music therapy may increase breastfeeding rates among mothers of premature newborns: a randomized controlled trial. J Pediatr (Rio J). 2011 May-Jun 8;87(3):206-12. doi: 10.2223/JPED.2086. Epub 2011 Apr 1. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>21461451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai HL, Chen CJ, Peng TC, Chang FM, Hsieh ML, Huang HY, Chang SC. Randomized controlled trial of music during kangaroo care on maternal state anxiety and preterm infants' responses. Int J Nurs Stud. 2006 Feb;43(2):139-46. Epub 2005 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>15996669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whipple J. The effect of parent training in music and multimodal stimulation on parent-neonate interactions in the neonatal intensive care unit. J Music Ther. 2000 Winter;37(4):250-68.</citation>
    <PMID>11281808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimber L, McNabb M, Mc Court C, Haines A, Brocklehurst P. Massage or music for pain relief in labour: a pilot randomised placebo controlled trial. Eur J Pain. 2008 Nov;12(8):961-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ejpain.2008.01.004. Epub 2008 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18304848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bulfone T, Quattrin R, Zanotti R, Regattin L, Brusaferro S. Effectiveness of music therapy for anxiety reduction in women with breast cancer in chemotherapy treatment. Holist Nurs Pract. 2009 Jul-Aug;23(4):238-42. doi: 10.1097/HNP.0b013e3181aeceee.</citation>
    <PMID>19574761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nilsson U. The anxiety- and pain-reducing effects of music interventions: a systematic review. AORN J. 2008 Apr;87(4):780-807. doi: 10.1016/j.aorn.2007.09.013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18395022</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang SC, Chen CH. Effects of music therapy on women's physiologic measures, anxiety, and satisfaction during cesarean delivery. Res Nurs Health. 2005 Dec;28(6):453-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16287051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin HH, Chang YC, Chou HH, Chang CP, Huang MY, Liu SJ, Tsai CH, Lei WT, Yeh TL. Effect of music interventions on anxiety during labor: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. PeerJ. 2019 May 15;7:e6945. doi: 10.7717/peerj.6945. eCollection 2019.</citation>
    <PMID>31143552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reza N, Ali SM, Saeed K, Abul-Qasim A, Reza TH. The impact of music on postoperative pain and anxiety following cesarean section. Middle East J Anaesthesiol. 2007 Oct;19(3):573-86.</citation>
    <PMID>18044285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Şahin, NH. Cesarean Section: Prevalence and Consequences. Journal of Maltepe University Nursing Science and Art 2009;2:93-98.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altuntaş H., Dansuk R., Köse O. Evaluation of Cesarean Ratios in Terms of Several Variables. KÜ Tıp Fak Derg 2013;15: 1-7.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yüksel N. Anxiety disorders. In: Yüksel N, ed. Mental Disorders. 3rd ed. Ankara:MN Medikal &amp; Nobel; 2006:143-182.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gürkan A, Bilge A. Alternative therapies and psychiatric nursing. Ege Univ JNurs High School. 2006;22:225-232.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt LA, Trainor LJ. Frontal brain electrical activity (EEG) distinguishes valence and intensity of musical emotions. Cogn Emot. 2001;15:487-500.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chlan L. A review of the evidence for music intervention to manage anxiety in critically ill patients receiving mechanical ventilatory support. Arch Psychiatr Nurs. 2009 Apr;23(2):177-9. doi: 10.1016/j.apnu.2008.12.005.</citation>
    <PMID>19327560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wakim JH, Smith S, Guinn C. The efficacy of music therapy. J Perianesth Nurs. 2010 Aug;25(4):226-32. doi: 10.1016/j.jopan.2010.05.009. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20656259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Procelli DE. The effects of music therapy and relaxation prior to breastfeeding on the anxiety of new mothers and the behavior state of their ınfants during feeding. F.S.U. College of Music, MA Thesis, Florida, United States; 2005.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mamuk R, Davas Nİ. Non-pharmacological relaxation and sensual stimulation methods used in the control of delivery pain. Med Bull Sisli Etfal Hosp. 2010;44:137-144.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ersanlı C. The effect of music listened by primigravidae treated with induction of labor through training during labor on delivery process. M.U. Health Sciences Institute, MA Thesis, Istanbul, Turkey; 2007.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Çatalgöl Ş. The effect of ney sound listened by primigravidae treated with induction of labor through training during labor on delivery process. E U. Health Sciences Institute, MA Thesis, İzmir; 2013</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Simavli S, Gumus I, Kaygusuz I, Yildirim M, Usluogullari B, Kafali H. Effect of music on labor pain relief, anxiety level and postpartum analgesic requirement: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Gynecol Obstet Invest. 2014;78(4):244-50. doi: 10.1159/000365085. Epub 2014 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25227477</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kahramanmaras Sutcu Imam University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eylem Toker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cesarean section</keyword>
  <keyword>Music therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

