<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04111731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1200</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04111731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Left Atrial Arrhythmia Substrate Identification After Confirmed durABLE Pulmonary Vein Isolation</brief_title>
  <acronym>LAUDABLE</acronym>
  <official_title>Left Atrial Arrhythmia Substrate Identification by Ultra-high Density Mapping After Confirmed durABLE Pulmonary Vein Isolation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Scientific Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Under current practice, patients with persistent atrial fibrillation, can be offered one of
      two types of ablation treatment. Both of these treatments are aimed at electrically isolating
      the 4 pulmonary veins (PVs) at the back of the heart which connect it to the lungs. These PVs
      have been identified to serve as the sites where the abnormal heart rhythm is generated. One
      of the treatments is called radiofrequency (RF) catheter ablation, where 'heat energy' is
      delivered through the tip of a catheter to make tiny burns (ablation lesions) around the
      outlines of the 4 PVs at their bases. The other treatment technique utilises a 'cold balloon'
      (Cryoenergy or cryoballoon ablation) to freeze the bases of the 4 PVs to achieve the
      electrical isolation. Sometimes the treated tissues develop reconnections that can lead to a
      recurrence of the abnormal heart rhythm, and thus the need for a repeat procedure.

      In this study, participants will receive a second treatment 2 months after the first one.
      During the second treatment, investigators will check to identify areas that have developed
      reconnections since the first treatment; these will be treated again. This will increase the
      chances of all participants having a complete treatment.

      In order to improve understanding of how best to treat this condition, investigators will
      also carry out some further measurements within the heart during the repeat procedure. During
      these measurements, investigators will check to see if treatment has succeeded in reducing
      the occurrence of an abnormal heart rhythm. In the group of participants in whom RF energy is
      used for the initial procedure, investigators will also treat the back wall of the heart, and
      repeat these measurements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Persistent atrial fibrillation (PeAF) is defined as continuous atrial fibrillation for 7 days
      or more. Approximately 10% of people are diagnosed with atrial fibrillation (AF) by age 80
      years; and among people of European descent, 26% of men and 23% of women have a lifetime risk
      of developing AF after age 40.

      Catheter ablation by pulmonary vein isolation is the usual approach employed for PeAF. This
      involves making lesions within the pulmonary veins to achieve electrical isolation.
      Electrical isolation cuts off abnormal electrical triggers originating from the pulmonary
      veins. However, treatment outcomes are less than optimal with a lot of variability in success
      rates for different techniques. Hence, the optimal treatment strategy for patients with PeAF
      is not clear.

      In this pilot study, investigators aim to study two different treatment modalities of
      catheter ablation: cold balloon (cryoballoon, Group 1) and hot tip (radiofrequency ablation,
      Group 2) used in (electrically) isolating the pulmonary veins. There will be 1:1
      randomisation to either of the two modalities. All participants will subsequently undergo a
      repeat procedure 2 months later to identify reconnections and to re-isolate the veins using
      the hot tip (radiofrequency ablation) guided by an ultra-high density mapping technology.
      During the repeat procedure, investigators will perform further electrophysiological studies
      including assessing arrhythmia inducibility and measuring the extent of isolated areas. For
      participants in Group 2, investigators will also make some lesions in the back wall of the
      heart (posterior wall isolation) and recheck arrhythmia inducibility.

      All participants will be given a handheld ECG recording (Omron) device. Participants will be
      shown how to use the device to make daily 30-second recordings and when they have symptoms,
      to be reviewed. Follow up will be at 3, 6 and 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 3, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A randomised, controlled multi-centre pilot study. Forty participants with persistent atrial fibrillation will have an equal chance of being randomised to receive either of two treatment techniques of pulmonary vein isolation:
Cryoballoon (Group 1) or Radiofrequency ablation (Group 2). Subsequently, all patients will undergo a repeat procedure 2 months later to assess for reconnections requiring further treatment.
In Group 2 participants, there will also be lesions made to the back wall of the heart (left atrial posterior wall isolation).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of late pulmonary vein re-connections</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 months after index ablation procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Number of late pulmonary vein re-connections at repeat electrophysiological study as identified by ultra-high density mapping: comparison between the 80 pulmonary veins in each group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of radiofrequency energy needed to re-isolate the veins</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the index ablation procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of radiofrequency energy needed at repeat electrophysiological study to re-isolate the pulmonary veins</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area of low voltage</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the index ablation procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Area of left atrial low voltage at start of repeat electrophysiological study under ultra-high density mapping guidance in each group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of arrhythmia inducibility before and after left atrial posterior wall isolation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the index ablation procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of arrhythmia inducibility after complete posterior wall isolation as compared to after pulmonary vein isolation alone assessed during an electrophysiological study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of peri-procedural complications</measure>
    <time_frame>From index procedure to after repeat procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of peri-procedural complications such as tamponade, major bleeding, myocardial infarction, requirement for permanent pacemaker, stroke, death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of renal function impacting on left atrial electrical properties</measure>
    <time_frame>At the index procedure and 2 months after the index procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of renal function impacting on electrical properties of the left atrium and arrhythmic substrate: assessed at baseline and during repeat electrophysiological study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total length of time free from atrial arrhythmia estimated with the Omron device</measure>
    <time_frame>At the 12th month follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>Freedom from atrial arrhythmia at 12 months following the 2 procedures: comparison between groups. Time period free from atrial arrhythmia in minutes/hours/days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life assessment: validated questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At the index procedure and at the 6th month and 12th month follow-up appointments</time_frame>
    <description>At baseline, 6 months and at 12 months using a validated questionnaire with 2 components: descriptive system and visual analogue scale. Descriptive system has 5 dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression. Each has 5 levels: no problems (level 1), slight problems (2), moderate problems (3), severe problems (4), and extreme problems (5). The digits for the 5 dimensions will be combined into a 5-digit number describing the participant's health state - a total of 3125 possible health states. The health state will be converted to a single index value using conversion tables, and summarised as means or medians. Visual analogue scale records the participant's self-rated health on a 20 cm vertical scale with endpoints 'the best health you can imagine' and 'the worst health you can imagine'. It will be summarised as means or medians.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clot formation and fibrinolysis assessment using turbidimetric analyses</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, 2 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clot formation (lag time, rate of clot formation, maximum absorbance) and rate of fibrinolysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fibrin permeation testing</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, 2 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Permeation constant (Ks)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Persistent Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group one</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cryoballoon pulmonary vein isolation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group two</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cryoballoon pulmonary vein isolation</intervention_name>
    <description>Catheter ablation using cryoballoon pulmonary vein isolation. Utilisation of a 'cold balloon' (Cryoenergy or cryoballoon ablation) to freeze the bases of the 4 pulmonary veins to achieve electrical isolation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group one</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation</intervention_name>
    <description>Catheter ablation using radiofrequency energy to achieve pulmonary vein isolation. Radiofrequency energy is delivered through the tip of a catheter to make tiny burns (ablation lesions) around the outlines of the 4 pulmonary veins at their bases</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group two</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Repeat electrophysiological study</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will receive a repeat electrophysiological study 2 months after the index procedure during which radiofrequency catheter ablation guided by ultra-high density mapping will be used to identify regions of reconnection that need re-isolation; other tests will be carried out including testing for arrhythmia inducibility</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group one</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group two</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Repeat catheter ablation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Left atrial posterior wall isolation</intervention_name>
    <description>The left atrial posterior wall will be isolated in Group 2 participants (those who received radiofrequency ablation at the index procedure) during the repeat electrophysiological study in 2 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group two</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Posterior wall isolation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 to 80 years

          2. Evidence of persistent Atrial Fibrillation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any previous catheter (or surgical) ablation for atrial fibrillation or cryoballoon
             pulmonary vein isolation

          2. An indwelling atrial septal defect (ASD) occluder device or anatomical structure that
             pre-vents free access to the left atrium

          3. Left atrial diameter on transthoracic echo (Parasternal long axis, M-mode) &gt; 5.5cm

          4. Recent stroke/Transient Ischaemic Attack within 3 months

          5. Inability, unwillingness or absolute contraindication to taking oral anticoagulant
             medication

          6. Severe kidney impairment (estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate &lt; 30ml/min)

          7. Morbid obesity (Body Mass Index ≥40)

          8. Extreme frailty

          9. Severe valvular heart disease of any kind as assessed by the investigator, with or
             without prosthetic valve in place

         10. Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dhiraj Gupta, MBBS MD FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wern Yew Ding, MBChB</last_name>
    <phone>0151 600 1251</phone>
    <email>wding@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dhiraj Gupta, MBBS MD FRCP</last_name>
    <phone>0151 600 1251</phone>
    <email>dhiraj.gupta@lhch.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L14 3PE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wern Yew Ding, MBChB</last_name>
      <phone>0151 600 1251</phone>
      <email>wding@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dhiraj Gupta, MBBS MD FRCP</last_name>
      <phone>0151 600 1251</phone>
      <email>Dhiraj.Gupta@lhch.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Snowdon, MBChB MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M13 9WL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gwilym Morris, MD MRCP PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0161 276 3336</phone>
      <email>Gwilym.Morris@mft.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gwilym Morris</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Newcastle Upon Tyne Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, Freeman Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle Upon Tyne</city>
        <zip>NE7 7DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Moloy Das, MBBS MD(Res)</last_name>
      <phone>01912137483</phone>
      <email>Moloy.Das@nuth.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Moloy Das, MBBS MD(Res)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiofrequency catheter ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Cryoballoon pulmonary vein isolation</keyword>
  <keyword>Rhythmia</keyword>
  <keyword>Orion catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>Posterior wall isolation</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrophysiological study</keyword>
  <keyword>Omron device</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

