<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04110314</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01AI135029</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04110314</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Portal Reminder/Recall for Influenza Vaccination in a Health System- RCT 2</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Influenza Vaccination Delivery Across a Health System by the Electronic Health Records Patient Portal- RCT #2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial is taking place in Los Angeles, CA among patients from primary care practices
      within the UCLA Health System.

      Despite the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) recommendation in 2010 that
      all people above 6 months of age should receive an annual flu vaccine, vaccination rates
      remain low. The investigators will assess the effectiveness of message-framing (gain-framed,
      loss-framed messages, no messages), as well as the effectiveness of a pre-commitment prompt
      (pre-commitment prompt, no prompt) asking about a patient's intention to get the influenza
      vaccination, using a 3 x 2 factorial design.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sub-optimal vaccination rates are a significant problem in the U.S., despite their
      effectiveness in preventing morbidity and mortality from vaccine-preventable illness. For
      influenza specifically, annual epidemics of influenza cause substantial morbidity in the U.S.
      with up to 40,00-80,000 deaths/year and many hospitalizations, emergency and outpatient
      visits, and significant costs.

      Reminder/recall (R/R), sent by phone, mail or other modality, can improve child and adult
      influenza vaccination rates. However, the majority of pediatric or adult primary care
      practices to not conduct R/R. Barriers are lack of finances, personnel, and algorithms to
      identify eligible patients.

      A technological breakthrough that might overcome these barriers involves patient portals--
      secure, web-based communication systems, embedded within electronic health records (EHRs),
      for patients and providers to communicate with each other via email and the internet. Portals
      are used by about half of Americans and half of UCLA patients.

      There has been considerable research on how best to communicate about vaccines with families.
      A number of studies have examined the impact of gain-framed (messages emphasizing the
      benefits of vaccination) versus loss-framed (messages emphasizing the risks of not getting
      vaccinated); however, the findings have been inconsistent across studies and by
      sub-population.

      In addition to framing, another potential influence on the decision to vaccinate is
      pre-commitment. Previous studies suggest that, upon being prompted, indicating an intention
      to do something increases the likelihood of following through. Therefore, a pre-commitment
      prompt is being asked of half the participants in each arm to evaluate its impact on
      influenza vaccination.

      The purpose of this randomized controlled trial is to evaluate the impact of gain-framed and
      loss-framed reminder-recall messages sent via the patient portal, pre-commitment prompts sent
      via the patient portal, and the interactions between the two type of messages and
      pre-commitment on influenza vaccination among UCLA Health System's primary care patients aged
      6 months and older.

      The proposed design of this randomized-controlled trial is a 3 x 2 factorial design.

      Standard of care control (no reminder messages, no pre-commitment prompt) No portal messages,
      pre-commitment prompt Gain-framed portal messages, pre-commitment prompt Gain-framed portal
      messages, no pre-commitment prompt Loss-framed portal messages, pre-commitment prompt
      Loss-framed portal messages, no pre-commitment prompt

      Hyp 1. Vaccination rates will differ by receipt of no reminders, gain-framed reminders and
      loss-framed reminders.

      1a. Vaccination rates will be higher among patients receiving gain-framed reminders than
      among patients receiving no reminders.

      1b. Vaccination rates will be higher among patients receiving loss-framed reminders than
      among patients receiving no reminders.

      1c. Vaccination rates will be higher among patients receiving gain-framed reminders than
      among patients receiving loss-framed reminders.

      Hyp 2. Vaccination rates will be higher among patients receiving a pre-commitment prompt than
      among patients not receiving any prompt.

      For relevant study arms, the first R/R messages will be sent in October 2019.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of the annual influenza vaccine among index patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Receipt of the annual influenza vaccination (between 10/2/19 - 4/1/20) among index patients. Outcomes will be assessed via vaccine data extraction from the electronic health record and external claims and pharmacy data.
Index patients will be randomly selected individuals within an included household, eligible for the following groups (age &lt;18, 18-64 non-diabetic, 65+ non-diabetic, and 18+ diabetic). One index patient per group may be selected from each household.
The index patients must also be an active UCLA Health MyChart user (&gt;= 1 login over the last 12 months from 8/1/19, excluding activity on the user's initial profile activation date). Individuals not affiliated with any primary care practice will be excluded from the primary analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Receipt of annual influenza vaccine among all included patients in identified households.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Receipt of annual influenza vaccine (between 10/2/19 - 4/1/20) among all included patients in identified households. Outcomes will be assessed via vaccine data extraction from the electronic health record and external claims and pharmacy data.
All enrolled study participants, excluding unaffiliated patients and infants &lt; 4 months, will be included in this secondary analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">480000</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Tract Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gain-framed portal reminders + Pre-commitment Prompts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive gain-framed reminder/recall messages regarding influenza vaccination via the patient portal and a pre-commitment prompt asking if they plan to receive the influenza vaccine in the upcoming season</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gain-framed portal reminders + No pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive gain-framed reminder/recall messages regarding influenza vaccination via the patient portal and no pre-commitment prompt asking if they plan to receive the influenza vaccine in the upcoming season</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Loss-framed portal reminders + Pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive loss-framed reminder/recall messages regarding influenza vaccination via the patient portal and a pre-commitment prompt asking if they plan to receive the influenza vaccine in the upcoming season</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Loss-framed portal reminders + No pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive loss-framed reminder/recall messages regarding influenza vaccination via the patient portal and a no pre-commitment prompt asking if they plan to receive the influenza vaccine in the upcoming season</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No portal reminder + Pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants do not receive any reminder/recall messages regarding influenza vaccination via the patient portal but do receive a pre-commitment prompt asking if they plan to receive the influenza vaccine in the upcoming season</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No portal reminders + No pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants do not receive any reminder/recall messages regarding influenza vaccination via the patient portal and do not receive a pre-commitment prompt asking if they plan to receive the influenza vaccine in the upcoming season</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Portal Reminders for Influenza Vaccination: Gain-framed</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive gain-framed reminder/recall messages via the patient portal to get an influenza vaccination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gain-framed portal reminders + No pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Gain-framed portal reminders + Pre-commitment Prompts</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Portal Reminders for Influenza Vaccination: Loss-framed</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive loss-framed reminder/recall messages via the patient portal to get an influenza vaccination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Loss-framed portal reminders + No pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Loss-framed portal reminders + Pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre-commitment prompt</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive a pre-commitment prompt asking about their intention to get an influenza vaccination</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gain-framed portal reminders + Pre-commitment Prompts</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Loss-framed portal reminders + Pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No portal reminder + Pre-commitment prompt</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A patient within the UCLA Health System identified as a primary care patient per an
             internal algorithm,

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A patient within the UCLA Health System not identified as a primary care patient per
             an internal algorithm
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California LA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>99095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter G Szilagyi, MD MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>Reminder recall</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Portal</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

