<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04111523</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SY007001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04111523</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single-dose Incremental Intravenous Injection of SY-007 in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Clinical Study to Evaluate Safety, Tolerance and Pharmacokinetics of SY-007 After Single-dose Incremental Intravenous Injection in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Suzhou Yabao Pharmaceutical R&amp;D Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Suzhou Yabao Pharmaceutical R&amp;D Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a single-dose incremental, randomized, double-blind, parallel,
      placebo-controlled study on safety, tolerance and pharmacokinetics healthy subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Six dose-group trials are planned: 1 mg,4 mg,10 mg,20 mg,30 mg,and 45 mg.When the dose
      reaches 45mg, if the standard of increasing dose termination is still not reached, the
      researcher and the sponsor shall decide whether to continue the increasing dose after
      reviewing the previous study data, and each increasing dose shall not exceed 33.3% (e.g.,
      60mg) of the previous dose group. In the process of dose increasing, when the dose exceeds 20
      mg, if the dose level reaches the dose termination standard, an intermediate dose is set
      between this dose and the previous dose, and the study is returned to the intermediate dose
      group.In this study, a parallel design was adopted, in which each subject received only one
      dose of drug from one dose group, which ensured the safety of the subject to the greatest
      extent, and also avoided the interference of safety and PK results caused by possible
      insufficient elution or other factors.Among them, 1 mg dose group was the starting dose
      group, and 6 subjects were randomly assigned into sy-007 group for injection or placebo group
      at a ratio of 2:1. Only 2 subjects were given the drug for the first time. One day after the
      first two subjects were given the drug, after ensuring the safety of the first two subjects,
      the drug was given to the remaining 4 subjects.In other dose groups, sentry administration
      was also used. The first 2 subjects received sy-007 injection or placebo respectively. After
      3 days of hospitalization observation, the safety data of the first 2 cases were reviewed by
      the researcher and the sponsor, and the remaining subjects in this dose group were determined
      accordingly.Pharmacokinetic biological samples were collected from all dose groups and their
      safety was assessed.A total of 66~90 healthy subjects will be enrolled.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel, Placebo control</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events of SY-007</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events of SY-007, collecting number of subjects with adverse events as assessed by CTCAE V5.0. Number of subjects with adverse events, major adverse events, serious adverse events, pregnancy events, abnormal laboratory values, abnormal vital signs, abnormal physical examination, abnormal ECG data.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under curve (AUC) of SY-007 following injection of single dose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To mearsure the study drug concentration in blood samples which collected after injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax of SY-007 following injection of single dose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To mearsure the study drug concentration in blood samples which collected after injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax of SY-007 following injection of single dose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To mearsure the study drug concentration in blood samples which collected after injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/2 of SY-007 following injection of single dose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To mearsure the study drug concentration in blood samples which collected after injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Apoplexy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be intiated in healthy subjects at a 1mg dose. Six subjects will be envolved in this study, and the proportion of subjects injected SY-007 to placebo is 2:1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be intiated in healthy subjects at a 4mg dose. Twelve subjects will be envolved in this study, and the proportion of subjects injected SY-007 to placebo is 5:1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be intiated in healthy subjects at a 10mg dose. Twelve subjects will be envolved in this study, and the proportion of subjects injected SY-007 to placebo is 5:1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be intiated in healthy subjects at a 20mg dose. Twelve subjects will be envolved in this study, and the proportion of subjects injected SY-007 to placebo is 5:1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be intiated in healthy subjects at a 30mg dose. Twelve subjects will be envolved in this study, and the proportion of subjects injected SY-007 to placebo is 5:1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be intiated in healthy subjects at a 45mg dose. Twelve subjects will be envolved in this study, and the proportion of subjects injected SY-007 to placebo is 5:1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SY-007</intervention_name>
    <description>A single dose of SY-007 or placebo injection(1mg-45mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SY-007 dose 6</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adults aged 18-45 (including two values);

          -  Both men and women have the same dose, and the number of single-sex subjects in the
             same dose group is not less than one third of the number in the dose group;

          -  During the screening period, the body weight of male subjects is greater than or equal
             to 50kg, and that of female subjects is greater than or equal to 45kg, with a body
             mass index (BMI = weight/height squared (kg/m2)) in the range of 18 to 26 (including
             both ends);

          -  Medical history, physical examination, other laboratory examination items and
             examination related to the test before the test. All the tests were normal or not
             clinically significant mild abnormalities, clinical research doctors judged that
             qualified.

          -  No cardiovascular, liver, kidney, digestive tract, mental nerve, hematology, metabolic
             abnormalities and other diseases medical history.

          -  The venous channel is normal and blood samples can be fully collected according to the
             plan;

          -  Subjects must give informed consent to this study before the study and voluntarily
             sign a written informed consent;

          -  Subjects are willing to take effective contraceptive measures, and have pregnancy
             plane during and within 3 months after the stud. Female subjects should be
             non-lactating, have negative pregnancy test, or have no fertility potential. Women who
             have been without a uterus for at least 12 months or are considered to have no
             potential pregnancy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  He/she who has the disease of the nervous system, such as basal ganglia disease,
             alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease, Parkinson's disease, epilepsy history or
             family history, or who is at risk of the disease through the investigation of Magnetic
             Resonance Imaging (MRI)/Electroencephalogram (EEG);

          -  Those who have a history of drug or other allergies, or may be allergic to the study
             drug or any component of the study drug in the judgment of the researcher;

          -  Those who have participated in the clinical trial of any drug or medical device within
             3 months prior to the screening, or who are still within 5 half-lives of the drug
             before the screening (the half-lives of the drug under test are longer, and the
             half-lives of the drug under test are more than 3 months), are judged not suitable for
             this study by the researchers;

          -  Have a history of alcohol abuse and drug abuse;

          -  Those who donated blood at least 400 mL within the first 4 weeks of screening, had
             severe blood loss and the blood loss was at least 400 mL, or had received blood
             transfusion within 8 weeks;

          -  Women who consume more than 15 g of alcohol a day and men who consume more than 25 g
             of alcohol (15 g of alcohol is equivalent to 450 mL of beer, 150 mL of wine or 50 mL
             of low-alcohol liquor) twice a week;Participants were reluctant to stop drinking
             between 24 hours before the study began and the end of the study;

          -  Those who smoke more than 5 cigarettes a day or are unwilling/unable to stop nicotine
             intake during the study period;

          -  Abnormal chest X-ray examination with clinical significance;

          -  12-lead ecg showed clinically significant abnormalities. After correction of QTc
             interphase &gt;450 msec, the researcher believed that participating in the experiment
             would increase the risk of subjects;

          -  Viral serological evidence during screening: patients with positive hepatitis b
             surface antigen (HBsAg), positive anti-hcv, or positive anti-HIV antibody of human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV), or positive anti-tp antibody of treponema pallidum;

          -  Patients who have undergone major surgery within 4 weeks before drug administration;

          -  Those who have been screened for the first 4 weeks or plan to receive live
             (attenuated) vaccines during the trial;

          -  Fertile eligible subjects (male and female) will not agree to use a reliable
             contraceptive method (hormone or barrier method or abstinence) during the study period
             and at least 3 months after administration;

          -  The blood pregnancy test of women of child-bearing age was positive.A woman who is
             pregnant or breast-feeding;

          -  Those who have used other drugs (including prescription drugs, over-the-counter drugs,
             Chinese herbal medicines and dietary supplements, etc.) within one week prior to the
             screening;

          -  History of malignant tumor diseases;

          -  Patients with acute disease and medication 2 weeks before the test;

          -  The sponsor or the investigator decides that the investigator is not suitable to
             participate in the study; Women who have been without a uterus for at least 12 months
             or are considered to have no potential pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zheng Li, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>West China Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zheng Li, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>028-85423655</phone>
    <email>18980601950@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wang Zhenlei, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>028-85423655</phone>
    <email>zhenleiwang@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West China Hospital of Sichuan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chendu</city>
        <state>Sichuan</state>
        <zip>610041</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zheng Li, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>028-85423655</phone>
      <email>18980601950@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Wang Zhenlei, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>028-85423655</phone>
      <email>zhenleiwang@qq.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zheng Li, Doctor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wang Zhenlei, Doctor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

