<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02140554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HGB-206</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02140554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of the LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product in Severe Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Study Evaluating Gene Therapy by Transplantation of Autologous CD34+ Stem Cells Transduced Ex Vivo With the LentiGlobin BB305 Lentiviral Vector in Subjects With Severe Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>bluebird bio</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>bluebird bio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-randomized, open label, multi-site, single dose, Phase 1/2 study in
      approximately 50 adults and adolescents with severe SCD. The study will evaluate
      hematopoietic stem cell (HSC) transplantation (HSCT) using LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subject participation for this study will be 2 years post-transplant. Subjects who enroll in
      this study will be asked to participate in a subsequent long-term follow up study that will
      monitor the safety and efficacy of the treatment they receive for up to 13 years
      post-transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>a. Weighted average HbAT87Q percentage of total Hb ≥30% AND b. Weighted average total Hb increase of ≥3 g/dL compared to baseline total Hb OR weighted average total Hb ≥10 g/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects must meet these criteria for a continuous period of ≥6 months at any time after drug product infusion (starting ≥60 days after last pRBC transfusion)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>severe vaso-occlusive event (sVOE)-75</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>A 75% reduction in annualized severe VOEs in the 24 months after drug product treatment versus the 24 months prior to Informed Consent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Annualized sVOE</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>A reduction in the annualized number of severe VOEs in the 24 months after drug product infusion as compared to the 24 months prior to informed consent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>sVOE-CR</measure>
    <time_frame>6 - 24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Complete resolution of severe VOE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>sVOE-90</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>A reduction in the annualized number of severe VOEs of at least 90% in the 24 months after drug product infusion compared to the 24 months prior to Informed Consent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success and kinetics of HSC engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as 3 consecutive ANC ≥0.5 × 109/L laboratory values obtained on different days by Day 43 post-infusion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute (≥Grade 2) and/or chronic graft-versus-host disease (GVHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 - 24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>As defined in the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will have rescue cells collected by bone marrow harvest, and will receive treatment of LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product manufactured with autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells collected by bone marrow harvest transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene.
*No Longer Recruiting</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group B1:
Subjects will have rescue cells collected by bone marrow harvest, and will receive treatment of LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product manufactured with autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells collected by bone marrow harvest transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene.
*No Longer Recruiting
Group B2:
Plerixafor mobilization and apheresis will be used for collection of rescue cells and exploratory manufacturing development. Subjects will receive treatment of LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product manufactured with autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells collected by bone marrow harvest transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene.
*No Longer Recruiting</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Plerixafor mobilization and apheresis will be used for collection of rescue cells, and subjects will receive treatment of LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product manufactured with autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells collected by plerixafor mobilization and apheresis transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</intervention_name>
    <description>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product is administered by IV infusion following myeloablative conditioning with busulfan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plerixafor</intervention_name>
    <description>Plerixafor is administered by subcutaneous injection prior to apheresis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Be ≥12 and ≤50 of age at time of consent.

          2. Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (SCD), with either βS/βS or βS/β0 or βS/β+ genotype.

          3. Have severe SCD. i.e., in the setting of appropriate supportive care measures for SCD
             (e.g.,pain management plan) have experienced at least 4 severe VOEs in the 24 months
             prior to informed consent.

             For the purposes of this study, a severe VOE is defined as an event with no medically
             determined cause other than a vaso-occlusion, requiring a ≥ 24-hour hospital or
             Emergency Room (ER) observation unit visit or at least 2 visits to a day unit or ER
             over 72 hours with both visits requiring intravenous treatment. Exception: priapism
             does not require hospital admission but does require a medical facility visit; 4
             priapism episodes that require a visit to a medical facility (without inpatient
             admission) are sufficient to meet criterion.

          4. Karnofsky performance status of ≥ 60 (≥16 years of age) or a Lansky performance status
             of ≥60 (&lt;16 years of age).

          5. Have either experienced hydroxyurea (HU) failure at any point in the past or must have
             intolerance to HU (defined as patient being unable to continue to take HU per PI
             judgement).

          6. Have been treated and followed for at least the past 24 months prior to Informed
             Consent in medical center(s) that maintained detailed records on SCD history.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Positive for presence of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 or 2 (HIV-1 and HIV-2),
             hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C (HCV).

          2. Clinically significant and active bacterial, viral, fungal, or parasitic infection.

          3. Inadequate bone marrow function, as defined by an absolute neutrophil count of &lt;
             1000/µL (&lt; 500/µL for subjects on HU treatment) or a platelet count &lt; 120,000/µL
             (without hypersplenism).

          4. Any history of severe cerebral vasculopathy: defined by overt or hemorrhagic stroke;
             abnormal transcranial Doppler [≥200 cm/sec] needing chronic transfusion; or occlusion
             or stenosis in the polygon of Willis; or presence of Moyamoya disease. Subjects with
             radiologic evidence of silent infarction in the absence of any of the above criteria
             would still be eligible

          5. Advanced liver disease, defined as:

               1. Persistent aspartate transaminase, alanine transaminase, or direct bilirubin
                  value &gt;3× the upper limit of normal (ULN), or

               2. Baseline prothrombin time or partial thromboplastin time &gt;1.5× ULN, suspected of
                  arising from liver disease, or

               3. Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) of the liver demonstrating clear evidence of
                  cirrhosis, or

               4. MRI findings suggestive of active hepatitis, significant fibrosis, inconclusive
                  evidence of cirrhosis, or liver iron concentration ≥15 mg/g require follow-up
                  liver biopsy in subjects ≥18 years of age. In subjects &lt;18 years of age, these
                  MRI findings are exclusionary, unless in the opinion of the Investigator, a liver
                  biopsy could provide additional data to confirm eligibility and would be safe to
                  perform. If a liver biopsy is performed based on MRI findings, any evidence of
                  cirrhosis, bridging fibrosis, or significant active hepatitis will be
                  exclusionary.

          6. Any contraindications to the use of plerixafor during the mobilization of
             hematopoietic stem cells and any contraindications to the use of busulfan and any
             other medicinal products required during the myeloablative conditioning, including
             hypersensitivity to the active substances or to any of the excipients.

          7. Any prior or current malignancy or immunodeficiency disorder, except previously
             treated, non-life threatening, cured tumors such as squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin.

          8. Prior receipt of an allogeneic transplant.

          9. Immediate family member with a known or suspected Familial Cancer Syndrome.

         10. Diagnosis of significant psychiatric disorder of the subject that, in the
             Investigator's judgment, could seriously impede the ability to participate in the
             study.

         11. Pregnancy or breastfeeding in a postpartum female or absence of adequate contraception
             for fertile subjects.

         12. Participation in another clinical study with an investigational drug within 30 days of
             Screening.

         13. Prior receipt of gene therapy.

         14. Patients needing curative anticoagulation therapy during the period of conditioning
             through platelet engraftment (patients on prophylactic doses of anticoagulants are
             eligible).

         15. Unable to receive RBC transfusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sunita Goyal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>bluebird bio, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hyde Park</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plerixafor octahydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

