<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03945682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>227917</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03945682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The ASsessment and Physiotherapy managEment of Ataxia in Children Following Surgical Resection of Posterior Fossa Tumour</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASPECT</acronym>
  <official_title>The ASsessment and Physiotherapy managEment of Ataxia in Children Following Surgical Resection of Posterior Fossa Tumour (ASPECT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alder Hey Children's NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alder Hey Children's NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of the study is to determine the feasibility of conducting a randomised
      controlled trial (RCT) studying the effectiveness of physiotherapy intervention (virtual
      training) in children with ataxia following surgical resection of posterior fossa tumour
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Brain tumours are the most common group of solid tumours in children accounting for nearly a
      quarter of all childhood cancers. There are approximately 500 new cases of central nervous
      system (CNS) tumours in children/adolescents reported in the UK per year. Although prognosis
      has improved over the last 30 years, brain tumours remain the leading cause of
      tumour-associated death in children. Surgical resection is a mainstay of management of
      children with brain tumours, as for several tumour types there is strong evidence that
      survival and progression free survival are influenced by the degree of resection. Therefore
      extensive tumour removal is an operative goal, but the morbidity of surgery along with any
      subsequent oncological treatment should also be considered. The NICE guidelines for improving
      outcomes in children and young people with cancer identify that 'Survivors of CNS malignancy
      are among the neediest of all cancer survivors, because of the effects of the tumour and
      multimodality therapy, all of which affect neurological, psychological, endocrine and
      academic function and become more evident with increasing age'.

      Children with posterior fossa tumours (PFT), which account for approximately 50% of all
      childhood brain tumours, have a distinctive set of issues e.g. potential for gross change
      pre/post operatively, rapid onset of ataxia, hydrocephalus and increased intra-cranial
      pressure adding deficits distinct from ataxia, in addition to potential problems from any
      subsequent oncological management such as radiotherapy. Of these issues, ataxia is the
      predominant motor problem in children with posterior fossa tumours. Ataxia can describe a
      related number of impairments including upper limb control, balance, gait difficulties, eye
      movement issues and speech problems. It is a presenting sign in 58-90% of children with
      posterior fossa tumours. Ataxia and balance problems also persist long term following
      surgery, Piscione et al found 70% of children with posterior fossa tumours will have long
      term post-operative balance problems. Lannering et al specified that truncal ataxia was the
      most disabling motor impairment in children with brain tumours.

      Access to neuro-rehabilitation is recognized as crucial in paediatric neuro-oncology with
      physiotherapy integral to this; yet there is no consensus as to the type, intensity or timing
      of interventions. A literature review of physical therapy/physiotherapy for children with
      ataxia (of any origin) was carried out in preparation for this project to confirm the
      literature gap, and consider interventions that have been of value in other pathologies
      causing ataxia. Ten papers in total were identified which included three review papers that
      covered adult and paediatric literature though the data were not separated in the studies to
      enable consideration of paediatrics as a distinct group. Overall the reviews concurred there
      was a suggestion of the benefit of physiotherapy (including treadmill training,
      rehabilitation, virtual training) though treatment modalities were often not consistently
      defined and evidence was typically of low quality (level III/IV). The recommendations from
      these reviews are that the next step would be to undertake RCTs (randomised controlled
      trials) in more homogenous patient groups. Looking at the paediatric literature, there were
      three case studies identified (and one case series with a population of three adolescents)
      again in differing diagnoses though none were examining children with brain tumours that is
      the most common acute cause for ataxia in the paediatric population. The largest paediatric
      study (n=10) identified through the literature review was a cohort study by Ilg et al
      evaluating the effect of virtual training. Virtual training refers to the use of computer
      technologies that provide an interactive environment that requires limb movement to react to
      on screen game play. Ilgs study found positive results and proposed that virtual training
      should then complement/supplement therapy treatment tailored according to the individual and
      continued in the home environment. Virtual training has also been explored in other
      paediatric populations e.g. cerebral palsy.

      Overall the literature review highlighted that there is a gap in the literature regarding
      physiotherapy intervention for children with ataxia, in particular there is no literature on
      effectiveness of physiotherapy for children with brain tumours. However, there is an emerging
      evidence base in adults with ataxia and to a lesser extent paediatric populations as
      described above, from similar (though non acute) lesions in the cerebellum reporting the
      benefits of balance therapies including virtual training. This suggests the potential for
      recovery from ataxia in similar conditions i.e. children with damage to the cerebellum
      following surgical resection of posterior fossa tumour.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomised to one of 2 groups 1. Intervention arm 2. Usual standard of care.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>No study drug as part of this RCT</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Process Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients identified who meet the inclusion criteria and are then subsequently recruited will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Process Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients who complete all sessions of the intervention will be recorded and the patient's adherence to treatment in the home setting will be noted.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SARA</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Scale for the Assessment and Rating of Ataxia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BARS</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Brief Ataxia Rating Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>9HPT</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Nine hole peg test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PEDI</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Paediatric Evaluation of Disability Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PedsQL</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Brain Tumour Module</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BBS</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Berg Balance Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>INAS</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Inventory of Non Ataxia Signs. Assessment of compliance (diary)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Impact</measure>
    <time_frame>32 months</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective Impact Likert Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Ataxia</condition>
  <condition>Posterior Fossa Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention therapist at 2 centres providing 8 week intervention programme 50% embedded qualitative study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants continue with usual care and existing therapy recorded in study diary</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapist</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention therapist at 2 centres providing 8 week intervention programme 50% embedded qualitative study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapist</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Child or young person (4-&lt;18 years) demonstrating ataxia. (For this study, ataxia is
             currently defined as SARA greater than 2. This definition is taken from data from the
             CARS study to date, from the cut off threshold value distinguishing no ataxia from
             mild ataxia)

          -  12 months to 3 years following surgical resection of posterior fossa tumour. (This
             time frame has been selected as this covers the time when the children will typically
             have completed any adjunct oncology treatment and therefore more emphasis is dedicated
             to rehabilitation).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medically unstable/currently undergoing adjunctive treatment e.g. radiotherapy or
             chemotherapy

          -  Less than 4 years of age (due to inability to complete standardized assessments)

          -  Aged 18 or over

          -  Unable to stand independently for less than one minute or SARA gait item score over 4,
             either of which would inhibit capacity to complete the training session.

          -  Presence of co-morbities with the potential to affect the safety of training, such as
             congenital or acquired disorders causing high risk of falls or lack of comprehension
             of training tasks, or current musculoskeletal impairments (such as a non-union
             fracture or fracture currently healing limiting weight-bearing)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Helen Hartley</last_name>
    <phone>0151 252 5660</phone>
    <email>helen.hartley@alderhey.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Research Alder Hey</last_name>
    <phone>0151 252 5570</phone>
    <email>research@alderhey.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alder Hey Children's NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>Merseyside</state>
        <zip>L12 2AP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Research Alder Hey</last_name>
      <phone>0151 252 5570</phone>
      <email>research@alderhey.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>surgical resection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infratentorial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ataxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebellar Ataxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

