<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03940313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ICMS-2019-004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03940313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biotensegrity: Thoracolumbar Fascial Integrity in Chronic Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Biotensegrity: Thoracolumbar Fascial Integrity in Chronic Low Back Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ProloAustin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ProloAustin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective study on chronic low back pain patients aimed at investigating how
      findings on a physical examination and musculoskeletal ultrasound may correlate with
      myofascial damage in the lower back. By comparing these findings with a control group and
      collecting follow up data on patients treated in the course of normal clinical practice, the
      investigators will be able to discern if fascial pathology contributes to chronic low back
      pain and if this treatment approach may provide clinical benefit to patients in the form of
      pain reduction and/or reduction in pain medication use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, observational clinical study that will be run through a private
      practice clinic.

      New patients to the clinic that complain of chronic lower back pain will be evaluated for
      inclusion and exclusion criteria and appropriately recruited and enrolled into the study. The
      baseline evaluation will take approximately 1.5hours to complete, and will include the
      following: a standardized pain scale questionnaire; a baseline questionnaire that assesses
      duration of current pain and previous interventions; physical examination with novel
      techniques to assess strength; and musculoskeletal ultrasound in the lower back.

      Specific physical examination techniques will assess strength of the subject on both prone
      straight leg raise as well as hip external rotation. Then, the investigators will test how
      adding myofascial tension along the lower back may affect these results. Musculoskeletal
      ultrasound will examine specifically the aponeurosis of the erector spinae and the posterior
      layer of the thoracolumbar fascia at T11, T12, and L1. These areas will be graded on a
      4-point scale (0 to 3), evaluating compressibility and heterogeneity of the tissue.

      Participants who have myofascial damage identified on ultrasound and are scheduled for
      injection treatment as part of normal clinical care will have a diagnostic injection of
      prolotherapy (0.3% lidocaine + 15% dextrose) in those areas as the first step of the
      procedure. Pre and post injection muscle testing will be performed. The treatment session
      then will be completed per normal clinical care; this may include injection at other
      locations and injection of autologous platelet-rich plasma. Routine follow-up will be
      scheduled at 3 months.

      At 3 months, the follow-up visit will include the following: the same pain scale
      questionnaire; a follow-up questionnaire to assess changes in function and pain medication;
      physical examination as before; musculoskeletal ultrasound in the specified areas.

      New patients to the clinic who do not have chronic low back pain &gt;12 weeks will be asked to
      participate as controls, and will undergo a similar questionnaire, and the same physical
      examination and musculoskeletal ultrasound.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 22, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 3 month follow-up.</time_frame>
    <description>Improved lower back pain / functionality.
Pain will be discerned on a scale from 0 to 10, with 0 being no pain and 10 being the worst pain the participant has experienced. There will be no subscales provided, and only whole numbers will be allowed to be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MSK Ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 3 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Musculoskeletal ultrasound will evaluate specific areas in the lower back on a 4-point scale (0 to 3), evaluating compressibility and heterogeneity of the tissue. The scale is described as follows:
0= No significant compressibility (well defined)
Mild compressibility but no translation (heterogeneous)
Moderate compressibility, mild translation (heterogeneous, poorly organized)
Significant compressibility and translation (heterogeneous, poorly organized)
The results from each of the areas evaluated will then be summed for a total composite score. All values, including the individual area score and total composite score, will be recorded. Higher scores are considered worse outcomes. The results of the ultrasound evaluation will be determined solely by the principal investigator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medications</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 3 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Reduced use (dose or frequency) of pain medications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Musculoskeletal Pain</condition>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Myofascial Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants &gt;18 years old who meet inclusion and exclusion criteria, and have findings on physical exam and ultrasound that suggest potential benefit from prolotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants &gt;or =18 years old who do not complain of lower back pain, but consent to have physical examination testing and musculoskeletal ultrasound of the lower back to evaluate these areas.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prolotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Musculoskeletal injection of lidocaine + 15% dextrose into damaged tissue</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>injection therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adults with chronic lower back pain that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; or = 18 years old

          -  Chronic lower back pain &gt; or = 12 weeks duration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of stroke preventing bilateral muscle strength testing

          -  History of scoliosis that may affect myofascial dynamics

          -  Acute radiculopathy/sciatica or pain that limits movement for physical examination

          -  Unable to lie prone for physical examination
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bradley Fullerton, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ProloAustin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bradley Fullerton, MD</last_name>
    <phone>512-347-7246</phone>
    <email>info@proloaustin.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ProloAustin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78746</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bradley Fullerton, MD</last_name>
      <phone>512-347-7246</phone>
      <email>info@proloaustin.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://proloaustin.com/</url>
    <description>Clinical facility for study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dischiavi SL, Wright AA, Hegedus EJ, Bleakley CM. Biotensegrity and myofascial chains: A global approach to an integrated kinetic chain. Med Hypotheses. 2018 Jan;110:90-96. doi: 10.1016/j.mehy.2017.11.008. Epub 2017 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>29317079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swanson RL 2nd. Biotensegrity: a unifying theory of biological architecture with applications to osteopathic practice, education, and research--a review and analysis. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2013 Jan;113(1):34-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23329804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fullerton BD, Reeves KD. Ultrasonography in regenerative injection (prolotherapy) using dextrose, platelet-rich plasma, and other injectants. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2010 Aug;21(3):585-605. doi: 10.1016/j.pmr.2010.06.003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20797551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Todorov PT, Nestorova R, Batalov A. Diagnostic value of musculoskeletal ultrasound in patients with low back pain - a review of the literature. Med Ultrason. 2018 Feb 4;1(1):80-87. doi: 10.11152/mu-1245. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29400373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>ProloAustin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bradley D. Fullerton, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Adjunct Assistant Professor, Texas A&amp;M College of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Low Back Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Myofascial pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Tensegrity</keyword>
  <keyword>Prolotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet-Rich Plasma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Musculoskeletal Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

