<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03946137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Complutense University</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03946137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chest Therapy and Postural Education in Children With Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Chest Therapy and Postural Control in Children With Crhonic Neurological Patology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION: Neurological Chronic disease leads to motor disability and associated
      pathologies. Numerous studies agree that the lack of prevention and treatment in pulmonary
      health in children with disabilities results in increased morbidity and mortality, increased
      medical care and costs in care, and, for patients and their caregivers, decrease in their
      quality of life OBJECTIVE: The objective of this study is to assess if children with chronic
      neurological disease and respiratory disease benefit from airway clearance techniques and
      postural hygiene workshops to optimize their respiratory status and quality of life. PATIENTS
      AND METHODS: Multicenter experimental study before-after with intervention of chest therapy
      and workshops of postural hygiene in 30 children from 0 to 6 years with chronic neurological
      affectation and respiratory complications. Respiratory clinical variables, volume of
      expectorated secretions, PedsQL pediatric quality of life questionnaires were evaluated and
      the number of exacerbations due to respiratory complications was recorded.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are few studies that apply and evaluate respiratory physiotherapy and / or postural
      hygiene in children with neurological affections. This study aims to improve the quality and
      effectiveness of physiotherapy interventions in paediatric patients with neurological
      problems and respiratory symptomatology, providing scientific evidence to respiratory
      physiotherapy protocols that are carried out in daily clinical practice and implementing the
      practice of therapeutic education on postural hygiene.

      HYPOTHESIS: Children with neurological chronic disease and respiratory affection benefit from
      mucociliary clearance techniques and workshops on postural hygiene to optimize respiratory
      status and quality of life.

      OBJECTIVES

        -  To evaluate the effectiveness of mucociliary clearance techniques in improving
           respiratory clinical signs and to increase expectoration of bronchial secretions in
           children with chronic neurological disease.

        -  To analyse the effectiveness of mucociliary clearance techniques combined with workshops
           to improve the quality of life of children with chronic neurological disease with
           respiratory complications.

        -  Establish the effectiveness of mucociliary clearance techniques and workshops to reduce
           the number of exacerbations due to respiratory infection in children with chronic
           neurological disease.

        -  To determine the effectiveness of mucociliary clearance techniques and workshops to
           reduce hospital admissions for respiratory complications in children with chronic
           neurological disease.

        -  MATERIAL AND METHODS It is an experimental study before - after a single group of
           children with non-progressive chronic neurological affectation (Cerebral Palsy, Down
           Syndrome, encephalopathies, ...) and respiratory involvement with intervention of chest
           therapy and workshops of postural hygiene directed to their parents or guardians Each
           individual has been their own control in the successive evaluations. The physiotherapist
           who has performed the techniques of chest therapy and workshops has been the same as the
           physiotherapist evaluator, so that there has been neither simple nor double blind.

      The project was previously approved by the Clinical Research Ethics Committee of the San
      Carlos Clinical University Hospital (internal code nº 15/152-E); He was awarded the 2014
      Research Fellowship of the Spanish Society of Pulmonology and Thoracic Surgery (SEPAR).

      ESTIMATION OF SAMPLE SIZE The sample size necessary to obtain a good internal validity was
      calculated, considering a normal distribution of the data, making a population estimate
      according to Granmo for paired means (repeated in a group). And the Bonferroni correction was
      taken into account, that is, the significance of at least 0.05 divided by the number of
      comparisons (in this case 8) was considered for each contrast.

      So, estimating a significance of 0.00625 (0.05 / 8) and a power of 0.8, in a bilateral
      contrast, 27 subjects are required to detect a difference equal to or greater than 3.5 units.
      A standard deviation of 5 is assumed.

      The participants were recruited from four centres of early care and foundations of the
      Community of Madrid. From their respective centres, all the parents of children with chronic
      neurological syndromes, who could enter the study according to the inclusion and exclusion
      criteria previously described, participated in the project.

      The informed consent of the parents or guardians of each participant was filed outside their
      medical history and they were informed of the confidentiality of the data according to the
      Organic Law 15/99 of December 13 of Data Protection of personal character.

      Subsequently, a first evaluation of the participants was performed, in which the descriptive
      data, the clinical exams, the number of exacerbations that each participant underwent during
      the 6 months prior to the beginning of the study were collected and the PedsQL quality of
      life questionnaires Through a personal interview with the parents.

      After this first evaluation, the clinical evaluations were performed, including the clinical
      exams of the participants before and after each session. And, after each session, the volume
      of secretions expectorated by each participant was measured. In the last session (session 6)
      the PedsQL quality of life questionnaires were completed again.

      Finally, in the evaluation of evolutionary control, clinical examinations were performed, the
      PedsQL quality of life questionnaires were again completed and the number of exacerbations
      due to respiratory complications that each participant had during the six months after the
      study was started.

      Chest therapy was performed twice a month. The intervention of the workshops was done every 3
      months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multicentric experimental study before-after with intervention of Chest physiotherapy and workshops of postural hygiene in 30 children from 0 to 6 years with chronic neurological diseases and respiratory complications.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Quality of Life Related to Health (HRQoL) at 6 month</measure>
    <time_frame>The PedsQL questionnaires were completed at the beginning of the study, at 6 months after the start of the study.</time_frame>
    <description>It was objectified through a personal interview with the parents, the PedsQL ™ Questionnaire on Pediatric Life Quality in Spanish version was used with the corresponding permission of use. The PedsQL ™ Generic Module investigates four areas or dimensions of the child's HRQoL: Physical, Emotional, Social and School Functioning. To calculate the HRQoL measure, the items were linearly transformed using a five-point Likert scale, on a scale of 0-100.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from number of hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>The number of hospitalizations for respiratory complications that each participant had during the six months before and after the start of the study was recorded.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of admissions due to respiratory complications. It was valued through a personal interview with the parents.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary auscultation</measure>
    <time_frame>It was assessed through study completion, an average of 6 month .</time_frame>
    <description>The presence or absence of adventitious noises was assessed. The conserved vesicular murmur corresponds to normal respiratory noise and indicates good pulmonary ventilation. The adventitious sounds assessed are crackles, wheezing and hypoventilation, indicating poor pulmonary ventilation and bronchial obstruction. The auscultation was assessed using the 3M ™ Littmann® Classic II Pediatric Stethoscope.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulsoximetry</measure>
    <time_frame>It was evaluated through study completion, an average of 6 month .</time_frame>
    <description>It was measured by the finger Pulsioximetro, M-Pulse ™ pediatric.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>It was measured through study completion, an average of 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>It was evaluated using the finger Pulse Oximeter, M-Pulse ™ pediatric</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>It was measured through study completion, an average of 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of breathing cycles was valued with the help of a crono for 60 seconds in the rest of the participants, in a noise-free environment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>It was measured through study completion, an average of 6 month .</time_frame>
    <description>It was measured in millimeters of secretions with a millimetric glass.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of emergency visits</measure>
    <time_frame>The number of visits to the emergency department due to respiratory complications that each participant had during the six months before and after the study was recorded.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of emergency visits due to respiratory complications. It was valued through a personal interview with the parents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of visits to pediatrician</measure>
    <time_frame>The number of pediatric visits for respiratory complications that each participant had during the six months before and after of the study was recorded.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of visits to pediatrician due to respiratory complications. It was valued through a personal interview with the parents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Thoracic mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>It was measured through study completion, an average of 6 month.</time_frame>
    <description>The measurement of maximal inspiration, maximal expiration and the difference between both (thoracic expansion) in the sitting position was made using a tape measure marked in increments of 0.1 cm at the level of the fourth intercostal space.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurologic Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Complication</condition>
  <condition>Child</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sample</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 patients of both sexes aged between 0 and 6 years with chronic neurological involvement with respiratory complications.
Individual sessions of chest therapy every fifteen days for three months, in total 6 respiratory physiotherapy sessions of 30 minutes each were performed. And the postural hygiene workshops were given to the parents, this educational intervention was carried out at the beginning of the study, at 3 months and at 6 months from the beginning. Each intervention lasted 4 hours with theoretical and practical part.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chest Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The sessions of chest therapy were based on airway clearance techniques (hyper manual insufflations, abdominal thoracic compressions and manually assisted cough)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sample</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Airways clearance techniques</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Postural Hygiene</intervention_name>
    <description>Postural hygiene workshops were taught through a theoretical presentation with the help of slides and practical exercises in small groups (2-4 parents per group).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sample</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Postural hygiene workshop</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients whose parents or guardians have signed informed consent.

          -  Patients of both sexes whose ages are between 0 and 6 years.

          -  Diagnosis of PC, encephalopathies and syndromes with non-progressive chronic
             neurological involvement, with respiratory complications (Pneumonias or Bronchitis).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients affected by immunodeficiency or hemato-oncological process.

          -  Previous respiratory pathology in itself (not consistent with its underlying
             pathology)

          -  Patients with cardiovascular instability.

          -  Patients with drained pneumothorax.

          -  Patients with recent pneumonectomy.

          -  Patients with severe bullae.

          -  Patients with hemoptysis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Inmaculada M Moreno, Doctora</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sociedad Española de Cirugía y neumología Torácica</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3960574/</url>
    <description>Tenenbaum A, Hanna RN, Averbuch D, Wexler ID, Chavkin M, Merrick J. Hospitalization of children with down syndrome. Front Public Health. 2014 Mar 20;2:22. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2014.00022. eCollection 2014.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3938214/</url>
    <description>Al-Khaledi B, Lewis M, Maclean JE. Case 2: Recurrent lower respiratory tract infections in a child with Down syndrome. Paediatr Child Health. 2014 Jan;19(1):19-21.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://reader.elsevier.com/reader/sd/pii/S0012369215528572?token=4FEE1F512EDFA9B8CAA325CD6B7EB0E5E721A9C793847B626815B799CF43AC2A26442DD8C68B01BD2A2140A60DAC10ED</url>
    <description>McCool FD, Rosen MJ. Nonpharmacologic airway clearance therapies: ACCP evidence-based clinical practice guidelines. Chest. 2006 Jan;129(1 Suppl):250S-259S. doi: 10.1378/chest.129.1_suppl.250S. Review.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4075822/pdf</url>
    <description>Ortiz Tde A, Forti G, Volpe MS, Carvalho CR, Amato MB, Tucci MR. Experimental study on the efficiency and safety of the manual hyperinflation maneuver as a secretion clearance technique. J Bras Pneumol. 2013.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.clinicalkey.com/#!/content/playContent/1-s2.0-S1526054208000729?returnurl=https:%2F%2Flinkinghub.elsevier.com%2Fretrieve%2Fpii%2FS1526054208000729%3Fshowall%3Dtrue&amp;referrer=https:%2F%2Fwww.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov%2Fpubmed%3Fterm%3DAssessing%2Band%2Bmanaging%2Blung%2Bdisease%2Band%2Bsleep%2Bdisordered%2Bbreathing%2Bin%2Bchildren%2Bwith%2Bcerebral%2Bpalsy%26TransSchema%3Dtitle%26cmd%3Ddetailssearch</url>
    <description>Fitzgerald DA, Follett J, Van Asperen PP. Assessing and managing lung disease and sleep disordered breathing in children with cerebral palsy. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2009</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flores JC, Carrillo D, Karzulovic L, Cerda J, Araya G, Matus MS, Llévenes G, Menchaca G, Vargas NA. [Children with special health care needs: prevalence in a pediatric hospital and associated risks]. Rev Med Chil. 2012 Apr;140(4):458-65. doi: 10.4067/S0034-98872012000400006. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>22854691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marks JH. Pulmonary care of children and adolescents with developmental disabilities. Pediatr Clin North Am. 2008 Dec;55(6):1299-314, viii. doi: 10.1016/j.pcl.2008.08.006.</citation>
    <PMID>19041459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schechter MS. Airway clearance applications in infants and children. Respir Care. 2007 Oct;52(10):1382-90; discussion 1390-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17894905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hess DR. Airway clearance: physiology, pharmacology, techniques, and practice. Respir Care. 2007 Oct;52(10):1392-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17894906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tenenbaum A, Hanna RN, Averbuch D, Wexler ID, Chavkin M, Merrick J. Hospitalization of children with down syndrome. Front Public Health. 2014 Mar 20;2:22. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2014.00022. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24688981</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hill CM, Parker RC, Allen P, Paul A, Padoa KA. Sleep quality and respiratory function in children with severe cerebral palsy using night-time postural equipment: a pilot study. Acta Paediatr. 2009 Nov;98(11):1809-14. doi: 10.1111/j.1651-2227.2009.01441.x. Epub 2009 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19627261</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Littleton SR, Heriza CB, Mullens PA, Moerchen VA, Bjornson K. Effects of positioning on respiratory measures in individuals with cerebral palsy and severe scoliosis. Pediatr Phys Ther. 2011 Summer;23(2):159-69. doi: 10.1097/PEP.0b013e318218e306.</citation>
    <PMID>21552079</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Al-Khaledi B, Lewis M, Maclean JE. Case 2: Recurrent lower respiratory tract infections in a child with Down syndrome. Paediatr Child Health. 2014 Jan;19(1):19-21.</citation>
    <PMID>24627649</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kwon YH, Lee HY. Differences of respiratory function in children with spastic diplegic and hemiplegic cerebral palsy, compared with normally developed children. J Pediatr Rehabil Med. 2013;6(2):113-7. doi: 10.3233/PRM-130246.</citation>
    <PMID>23803344</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McCool FD, Rosen MJ. Nonpharmacologic airway clearance therapies: ACCP evidence-based clinical practice guidelines. Chest. 2006 Jan;129(1 Suppl):250S-259S. doi: 10.1378/chest.129.1_suppl.250S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16428718</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lagerkvist AL, Sten G, Westerberg B, Ericsson-Sagsjö A, Bjure J. Positive expiratory pressure (PEP) treatment in children with multiple severe disabilities. Acta Paediatr. 2005 May;94(5):538-42.</citation>
    <PMID>16188740</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ortiz Tde A, Forti G, Volpe MS, Carvalho CR, Amato MB, Tucci MR. Experimental study on the efficiency and safety of the manual hyperinflation maneuver as a secretion clearance technique. J Bras Pneumol. 2013 Mar-Apr;39(2):205-13. doi: 10.1590/S1806-37132013000200012. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>23670506</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>de Godoy VC, Zanetti NM, Johnston C. Manual hyperinflation in airway clearance in pediatric patients: a systematic review. Rev Bras Ter Intensiva. 2013 Jul-Sep;25(3):258-62. doi: 10.5935/0103-507X.20130043. Review. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>24213091</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barks L, Shaw P. Wheelchair positioning and breathing in children with cerebral palsy: study methods and lessons learned. Rehabil Nurs. 2011 Jul-Aug;36(4):146-52, 174.</citation>
    <PMID>21721395</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fitzgerald DA, Follett J, Van Asperen PP. Assessing and managing lung disease and sleep disordered breathing in children with cerebral palsy. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2009 Mar;10(1):18-24. doi: 10.1016/j.prrv.2008.10.003. Epub 2009 Jan 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19203740</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Moreno Bermejo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physiotherapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurological chronic disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Child</keyword>
  <keyword>Chest therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Educational intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Postural hygiene</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

