<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03942575</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>METCZ20190024</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03942575</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Risk of Postoperative Wound Complications Following the Use of Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Patients Undergoing Mastectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>ALEX</acronym>
  <official_title>The Risk of Postoperative Wound Complications Following the Use of Avelle Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Patients Undergoing Mastectomy and Flap fiXation: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zuyderland Medisch Centrum</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zuyderland Medisch Centrum</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the risk of postoperative wound complications following the use of Avelle
      negative pressure wound therapy in patients undergoing mastectomy and flap fixation, which
      might serve as a basis for a randomized controlled trial
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale:

      Patients and breast cancer surgeons are frequently confronted with complications after
      mastectomy. These complications are manifold and mainly consist of: surgical site infections,
      seroma, wound dehiscence and wound necrosis. These complications are caused by numerous
      variables and therefore a multifactorial approach is required. Due to extensive research over
      the years, insight has been gained in how to reduce the rate of surgical site infections and
      wound healing problems. For example, pre-operatively and intra-operatively the complication
      rate can partly be influenced by optimizing intrinsic patient factors before surgery and
      using prophylactic antibiotics (1). There is however room for improvement in the
      postoperative phase. Negative pressure wound therapy (NPWT) has proven to be useful in
      reducing wound complications in all sorts of wounds. Limited evidence has been published on
      NPWT after breast cancer surgery and the effect of such in reducing wound complications.

      This is a pilot study to evaluate the effect of negative pressure wound therapy in reducing
      postoperative wound complications after mastectomy, which might serve as a basis for a
      randomized controlled trial..

      Objective:

      To evaluate the risk of postoperative wound complications following the use of Avelle
      negative pressure wound therapy in patients undergoing mastectomy and flap fixation, which
      might serve as a basis for a randomized controlled trial

      Study design:

      A prospective cohort will be compared to a historical control group. Fifty consecutive
      patients will undergo mastectomy with flap fixation using tissue glue and skin sutures,
      closed suction drainage AND Avelle negative pressure wound therapy.

      These results will be compared to the results of a historical control group consisting of 112
      patients who have undergone mastectomy with flap fixation using tissue glue and sutures and
      closed suction drainage and in whom negative wound pressure therapy was omitted.

      Follow-up will be conducted for three months post mastectomy.

      Study population:

      Female patients &gt; 18 years diagnosed with invasive breast cancer or DCIS ( ductal carcinoma
      in situ) with an indication to perform mastectomy.

      Intervention (if applicable):

      Application of Avelle negative pressure wound therapy after standard mastectomy with flap
      fixation and closed suction drainage.

      Main study parameters/endpoints:

      Patients with postoperative wound complications during the first three postoperative months.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness:

      Patients will be informed about the study before inclusion in the outpatient clinic. Informed
      consent will be obtained in the outpatient clinic a week after patients were initially
      informed. Postoperative check-ups will be done more frequently. Standard postoperative
      check-ups are planned at one week and three months. Additional study postoperative check-up
      will be performed at six weeks. Therefore, patients will be required to undergo one
      additional check-up. During out patients' visits, wound complication will be evaluated.
      Application of Avelle negative pressure wound therapy is expected to reduce wound
      complications and thereby benefit the post mastectomy wound healing process. The only
      potential risk for the patient is that the wound therapy would be ineffective or that the
      patient could develop an allergic reaction to the product. The latter is also a known risk of
      standard wound dressings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A prospective cohort will be compared to a historical control group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with post-operative wound complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first three postoperative months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with post-operative wound complications defined as follows:
Surgical site infection (SSI) is defined as redness, pain, heat or swelling at the site of the incision or by the drainage of pus. Infection rate will be measured by A) the need for antibiotics, B) seroma aspiration due to infection or C) surgical drainage during the first three postoperative months.
Wound necrosis. Defined as a wound with necrotic tissue that consists of an accumulation of dead cells, tissue and cellular debris and often requires debridement.
Wound dehiscence or breakdown defined as a wound that ruptures along a surgical incision and the edges of the wound no longer align.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of unplanned visits to the ER or breast cancer clinic</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first three postoperative months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of unplanned visits to the ER or breast cancer clinic. Planned visits are standard follow-up outpatient clinic visits which are defined preoperatively. Unplanned visits are defined as any visit to the outpatient clinic which is necessary due to an adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with clinically significant seroma</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first three postoperative months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with clinically significant seroma. This is defined as:
Wound healing is at risk due to seroma (wound break down, seroma leakage, necrosis)
There is discomfort or pain caused by large amounts of seroma, characterised by tenseness of the skin.
There is contaminated/ infected seroma and aspiration is necessary to treat infection. All patients that undergo seroma aspiration due to infection will also be treated with a one week course of Augmentin 625 mg 3 times daily.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Wound Complication</condition>
  <condition>Wound Infection</condition>
  <condition>Wound Dehiscence</condition>
  <condition>Wound Necrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No negative pressure wound therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Historical cohort: patients who underwent mastectomy with flap fixation using tissue glue and sutures and closed suction drainage and where negative wound pressure therapy has been omitted</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Negative pressure wound therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prospective cohort: patients who underwent mastectomy with flap fixation using tissue glue and sutures and closed suction drainage with negative wound pressure therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Negative pressure wound therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Wound dressing with negative pressure on closed incisions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Negative pressure wound therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Older than 18 years

          -  Female sex

          -  Indication for mastectomy or modified radical mastectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing breast conserving therapy

          -  Patients undergoing direct breast reconstruction

          -  Unable to comprehend implications and extent of study and sign for informed consent

          -  Participation in other study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zuyderland Medisch Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sittard</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>6162 BG</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Zuyderland Medisch Centrum</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James van Bastelaar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Surgeon, Principal Investigator, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Negative pressure wound therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wound Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Necrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

