<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03948139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHLA-18-00233</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03948139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Femur Fracture: Functional Bracing vs. Hip Spica Cast</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Randomized Study Comparing Functional Bracing vs. Hip Spica Cast in Pediatric Femur Fractures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pediatric Orthopaedic Society of North America</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spica casting is the current standard of care when treating pediatric diaphyseal femur
      fractures in the 0-5 year age group. A study conducted by Kramer et al. suggests there are
      both clinical and financial benefits of functional bracing when compared to spica casting. To
      this date there have been no prospective trials to evaluate these two treatment options. The
      investigators plan to conduct a multi-center randomized-control trial that will compare the
      subjective, objective and financial aspects of functional bracing and spica casting for
      pediatric femur fractures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Femur fractures are the most common orthopedic injury for which children are hospitalized in
      the United States. Traditional spica casts, the current standard of care for diaphyseal
      femoral shaft fractures with minimal shortening in children age 0-5 years old. Although spica
      cast immobilization is standard of care for femur fractures in young children, caring for a
      child in a spica cast presents a significant socioeconomic burden on families and the
      healthcare system. Basic hygiene and transportation for a child in a spica cast requires
      burdensome adjustments for caretakers, as well as the added expenses of specialized car seats
      or transportation services. Improper spica cast care can lead to skin complications,
      additional visits for cast adjustments, or even revision casting in the operating room.

      Functional bracing plays an established role in the non-operative management of other long
      bone fractures in pediatric patients, and offers numerous advantages, including being
      lightweight, simple to apply, and conducive to hygienic skin care. A study conducted by
      Kramer et al. suggests there are both clinical and financial benefits of functional bracing
      when compared to spica casting for femur fractures, including increased patient/parent
      satisfaction and better cost effectiveness. To date, there have been no prospective trials to
      confirm these initial findings.

      While previous work by Kramer et al demonstrated the advantages of functional bracing when
      compared to traditional spica casting, the ability to generalize this to other pediatric
      practices has been limited due to the challenges of making braces in a timely fashion. The
      braces utilized by Kramer et al require a carver to create a brace with a foot plate that
      improves rotational control for femur fractures. The cost of a carver is approximately
      $125,000, and thus few orthotists have access to this piece of equipment. This limits the
      ability for many pediatric orthopaedists to incorporate functional bracing into their
      practice.

      To make this treatment option more cost effective and accessible, the investigators propose
      to generate five standardized sized braces based on measurements from prior scans that will
      be stocked at each institution and modified by the local orthoptist to fit the needs of each
      patient. This will facilitate expedited care while obtaining the same clinical and
      radiographic results as the fully customized braces. This idea has the potential to be
      extrapolated to the wider clinical community, creating a true shift in pediatric orthopaedic
      clinical practice throughout the country.

      The investigators hypothesize that functional bracing will demonstrate equivalent objective
      outcomes with respect to leg length, time to union, rate of malunion, number of radiographs,
      and number of clinic visits. The investigators also hypothesize that functional bracing will
      demonstrate superior economic costs with respect to operating room cost and work days lost
      for parents, as well as subjective outcomes with respect to Pediatric Outcome Data Collection
      Instrument, patient/parent satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Subjects and parents are blinded until after consent to the study in which they are randomized into the functional brace group or spica cast group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Leg Length</measure>
    <time_frame>Radiographs will be reviewed at the pre-op and clinical follow-ups up to 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>After treatment, leg length will be measured using clinical radiographs to determine if there are any changes to leg length and determine if there are discrepancies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in union/rate of malunion</measure>
    <time_frame>Radiographs will be reviewed at the pre-op and clinical follow-ups up to 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measuring the length of time and changes in union of bone, and to see if the bone has not healed properly.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of radiographs and clinic visits</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be reviewed and counted for up to 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be used to determine which arm had less radiation from radiographs and less visits with the surgeon.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic costs (operating room cost)</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be examined at the 1 day of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be to compare the economic costs between the administration of a spica cast vs. a functional brace.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Work days lost for parents</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be surveyed at the 6 week post-intervention visit.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be collected from a parent reported outcome survey which will help determine the amount of days a parent lost to work due to their child's condition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Work days lost for parents</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be surveyed at the 1 year post-intervention visit.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be collected from a parent reported outcome survey which will help determine the amount of days a parent lost to work due to their child's condition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pediatric Outcome Data Collection Instrument (PODCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be surveyed at the 6 week post-intervention visit.</time_frame>
    <description>The PODCI is a validated quality of life and outcome questionnaire used for various pediatric orthopaedic studies. It will allow the study team to determine the subjective outcomes of the subject.This will also be completed by the parent.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pediatric Outcome Data Collection Instrument (PODCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be surveyed at the 1 year post-intervention visit.</time_frame>
    <description>The PODCI is a validated quality of life and outcome questionnaire used for various pediatric orthopaedic studies. It will allow the study team to determine the subjective outcomes of the subject.This will also be completed by the parent.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Pediatric Femur Fracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Functional Bracing Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>In a presented abstract, the functional brace group has been to shown equivalent outcomes to the hip spica cast. Subject will be administered the functional brace without going to the operating room to be put under full anesthesia. Most cases will not require any sedation in this group (in some cases, light sedation may be needed). Brace will be used for up to 8 weeks post-administration, until adequate callous formation is confirmed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spica Cast Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>If subject is randomized into the hip spica cast group, subject will proceed to the operating room and be given general anesthesia to administer the spica cast. Cast will be used for up to 8 weeks, until adequate callous formation is confirmed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Functional Brace</intervention_name>
    <description>The study will generate five standardized sized braces based on measurements from prior scans that will be stocked at each institution and modified by the local orthotist to fit the needs of each patient. This will facilitate expedited care while obtaining the same clinical and radiographic results as the fully customized braces. This idea has the potential to be extrapolated to the wider clinical community, creating a true shift in pediatric orthopaedic clinical practice throughout the country.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Functional Bracing Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hip Spica Cast</intervention_name>
    <description>Traditional spica casts, the current standard of care for diaphyseal femoral shaft fractures with minimal shortening in children age 0-5 years old. Although spica cast immobilization is standard of care for femur fractures in young children, caring for a child in a spica cast presents a significant socioeconomic burden on families and the healthcare system. Basic hygiene and transportation for a child in a spica cast requires burdensome adjustments for caretakers, as well as the added expenses of specialized car seats or transportation services. Improper spica cast care can lead to skin complications, additional visits for cast adjustments, or even revision casting in the operating room.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Spica Cast Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ages 0-5 years with an isolated diaphyseal femur fracture. Parents =18 years
             of age who are cognitively able to take a survey.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &gt;5 years of age without a diagnosis of an isolated diaphyseal femur fracture
             or polytrauma and those with medical co-morbidities that may affect fracture healing.
             Parents &lt;18 year of age and unable to take a survey.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joshua Yang</last_name>
    <phone>323-361-5139</phone>
    <email>josyang@chla.usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joshua Yang</last_name>
      <phone>323-361-5139</phone>
      <email>josyang@chla.usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lindsay M Andras, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eun Bi Kim</last_name>
      <phone>720-777-8026</phone>
      <email>Eun.Kim@childrenscolorado.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julia Sanders, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lindsay Andras</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Orthopaedic Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Fracture</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Brace</keyword>
  <keyword>Hip Spica Cast</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Femoral Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

