<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03943862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>345/18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03943862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Share Or Not To Share</brief_title>
  <acronym>2Share</acronym>
  <official_title>To Share or Not To Share (2Share) - Group Intervention to Support Disclosure Decisions After Suicide Attempt</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Ulm</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Ulm</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate the group-based intervention &quot;To Share Or Not To
      Share&quot; in a German clinical setting. Feasibility and efficacy of the program will be tested
      in a pilot randomized-controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      People who have survived a suicide attempt often face public and self-stigma, and secrecy is
      a common strategy to minimize the risk of being labeled. Both secrecy and disclosure have
      pros and cons. The decision whether, when, and to whom to disclose a previous suicide attempt
      is complex. Interventions can provide guidance for systematic consideration and a well
      informed decision. Potentially, it may not be disclosure itself, but the empowered decision
      for or against disclosure of a previous suicide attempt that reduces distress and leads to
      beneficial outcomes.

      The manualized peer-led group intervention &quot;Honest, Open, Proud&quot; (HOP) supports people with
      mental illness in their decision whether to disclose mental illness. Research showed positive
      effects of the intervention on stigma stress, disclosure-related distress and quality of
      life. Based on HOP, &quot;To Share Or Not To Share&quot; (2Share) was developed to systematically guide
      suicide attempt survivors through their decision whether and how to disclose a previous
      suicide attempt.

      2Share led to significant reductions in self-stigma and depressive symptoms, as well as
      increased self-esteem in a recent pilot randomized-controlled trial (RCT) in the US. The aim
      of the current study is to evaluate 2Share in a German clinical setting. Feasibility and
      efficacy of 2 Share will be tested in a pilot RCT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The study was terminated due to a small number of study participants.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-stigma related to suicide attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-Stigma of Suicide Attempt Survivor Scale (SSSAS), 14-item apply subscale (Sheehan et al, 2018); each item is rated from 1-9, we will calculate a sum score accross all items (range 9-126) with higher scores indicating more self-stigma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-stigma related to suicide attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-Stigma of Suicide Attempt Survivor Scale (SSSAS), 14-item apply subscale (Sheehan et al, 2018); each item is rated from 1-9, we will calculate a sum score accross all items (range 9-126) with higher scores indicating more self-stigma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Stigma (alienation) related to suicide attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Internalized Stigma of Mental Illness scale (ISMI), 6-item alienation subscale (Ritsher et al. 2003) adapted for suicide attempt, 6 items rated from 1-4, we will calculate a mean score accross all items (range: 1-6) with higher scores indicating more self-stigma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stigma stress related to suicide attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stigma Stress Scale (Rüsch et al., 2009a,b) adapted for suicide attempt, 8-items rated from 1-7 with 4 items measuring the primary appraisal of stigma as harmful and 4 items measuring the secondary appraisal of perceived resources to cope with stigma-related harm, for each of the two subscales we will calculate a mean score (range 1-7) and a total stigma stress score will be caclulated by subtracting perceived resources from perceived harm with higher difference scores (range -6 to +6) indicating more stigma-stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secrecy about suicide attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Secrecy Scale (Link et al., 1991) adapted for suicide attempt, 5 items rated from 1-6, we will calculate a mean score accross all items (range 1-6) with higher scores indicating more secrecy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General disclosure distress</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Distress Disclosure Index (Kahn et al., 2001), 12 items rated from 1-5, we will calculate a sum score accross all items (range 12-60) with higher scores indicating more disclosure distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Help-seeking for suicidality</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>General Help-Seeking Questionnaire - suicidal ideation subscale (GHSQ-SI) (Wilson et al., 2005), 10 items rated from 1-7, we will calculate mean scores (range 1-7) for items related to social contacts (items 1-4) and care providers (items 5,7,10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression Scale - short form (CES-D) (Hautzinger et al., 1993), 15 items rated from 0-3, we will calculate a sum score accross all items (range 0-45) with higher scores indicating more depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Suicidal ideation</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Suicidal Ideation Attributes Scale (SIDAS) (Spijker et al., 2014), 5 items rated from 0-10, we will calculate a total sum score accross all items (range 0-50) with higher scores indicating more suicidality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Recovery Assessment Scale - short version (RAS-G) (Corrigan et al., 2004), 24 items rated from 1-5, we will calculate a mean score accross all items (range 1-5) with higher scores indicating more recovery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-esteem</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rosenberg's Self-Esteem Scale (RSE) (Collani et al., 2003), 10 items rated from 0-3, we will caculate a sum score accross all items (range 0-30) with higher scores indicating more self-esteem.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>EUROHIS Quality of Life Index (EUROHIS-QOL) (Brähler et al., 2007), 8 items rated from 1-5, we will calculate a sum score accross all items (range 8-40) with higher scores indicating more quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>History of Suicide Attempt</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (2Share) + treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants randomized to the experimental group receive the intervention (2Share) while maintaining their current treatment (treatment as usual). 2Share is a peer-led group intervention containing three two-hour sessions within two weeks plus an additional booster session four weeks later.
Fidelity to manual is rated in each session by study staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the control group do not receive the group program but maintain their current treatment (treatment as usual).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2Share</intervention_name>
    <description>The peer-led group program contains of three lessons plus one booster session:
Lesson 1: Consider the pros and cons of disclosing: Participants reflect on their experience of self-stigma and weigh their pros and cons of (non-)disclosing a suicide attempt.
Lesson 2: Different ways to disclose: Participants learn about the different ways to disclose and their respective pros and cons. Afterwards participants develop strategies to choose a person to disclose to, and discuss possible responses they might experience.
Lesson 3: Telling your story: Participants learn how to tell their own story.
In a booster session, participants will discuss their experiences with disclosure or non-disclosure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (2Share) + treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current inpatient, outpatient or day clinical treatment at the Bezirkskrankenhaus
             Günzburg, Germany

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  At least one previous suicide attempt

          -  Positive screening for disclosure distress (1 item: &quot;In general, how distressed or
             worried are you in terms of secrecy or disclosure of your suicide attempt?&quot;,
             self-report, persons with a score ≥ 4 on a scale from 1-7 are included)

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Sufficient German language skills

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current suicidality (1 item: &quot;Have you had thoughts that you would be better off dead
             for at least several days during the last week?&quot;, self-report, persons responding with
             yes will be excluded and will be offered support)

          -  Suicide attempt within the last four weeks

          -  Dementia or organic disease (ICD-10: F0)

          -  Primary substance dependence (ICD-10: F1x.2)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ulm and BKH Günzburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89073</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sheehan L, Oexle N, Dubke R, Wan HT, Corrigan PW. The Self-Stigma of Suicide Attempt Survivors. Arch Suicide Res. 2020 Jan-Mar;24(1):34-47. doi: 10.1080/13811118.2018.1510797. Epub 2018 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>30142296</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rüsch N, Corrigan PW, Powell K, Rajah A, Olschewski M, Wilkniss S, Batia K. A stress-coping model of mental illness stigma: II. Emotional stress responses, coping behavior and outcome. Schizophr Res. 2009 May;110(1-3):65-71. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2009.01.005. Epub 2009 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19237266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rüsch N, Corrigan PW, Wassel A, Michaels P, Olschewski M, Wilkniss S, Batia K. A stress-coping model of mental illness stigma: I. Predictors of cognitive stress appraisal. Schizophr Res. 2009 May;110(1-3):59-64. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2009.01.006. Epub 2009 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19269140</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Link BG, Mirotznik J, Cullen FT. The effectiveness of stigma coping orientations: can negative consequences of mental illness labeling be avoided? J Health Soc Behav. 1991 Sep;32(3):302-20.</citation>
    <PMID>1940212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahn JH, Hessling RM. Measuring the tendency to conceal versus disclose psychological distress. J Soc Clin Psychol. 2001;20(1):41-65. doi:10.1521/jscp.20.1.41.22254</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilson CJ, Deane FP, Ciarrochi JV, Rickwood D. Measuring help seeking intentions: properties of the General Help Seeking Questionnaire. Canadian Journal of Counselling. 2005;39(1):15-28. doi:10.1080/09638237.2017.1370642.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hautzinger M, Bailer M. Allgemeine Depressions-Skala [The German version of the Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression scale]. Weinheim: Beltz; 1993.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Spijker BA, Batterham PJ, Calear AL, Farrer L, Christensen H, Reynolds J, Kerkhof AJ. The suicidal ideation attributes scale (SIDAS): Community-based validation study of a new scale for the measurement of suicidal ideation. Suicide Life Threat Behav. 2014 Aug;44(4):408-19. doi: 10.1111/sltb.12084. Epub 2014 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24612048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corrigan PW, Salzer M, Ralph RO, Sangster Y, Keck L. Examining the factor structure of the recovery assessment scale. Schizophr Bull. 2004;30(4):1035-41.</citation>
    <PMID>15957202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collani G v., Herzberg PY. Eine revidierte Fassung der deutschsprachigen Skala zum Selbstwertgefühl von Rosenberg [A revision of the German Rosenbergs self-esteem scale]. Zeitschrift für Differentielle und Diagnostische Psychologie. 2003;24(1):3-7. doi:10.1024//0170-1789.24.1.3</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brähler E, Mühlan H, Albani C, Schmidt S. Teststatistische Prüfung und Normierung der deutschen Versionen des EUROHIS-QOL Lebensqualität-Index und des WHO-5 Wohlbefindens-Index [Psychometrics and standardization of the German version of EUROHIS-QOL quality of life index and WHO-5 wellbeing index]. Diagnostica. 2007;53(2):83-96. doi:10.1026/0012-1924.53.2.83</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ritsher JB, Otilingam PG, Grajales M. Internalized stigma of mental illness: psychometric properties of a new measure. Psychiatry Res. 2003 Nov 1;121(1):31-49.</citation>
    <PMID>14572622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Ulm</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nathalie Oexle</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stigma</keyword>
  <keyword>Suicide attempt survivor</keyword>
  <keyword>Secrecy</keyword>
  <keyword>Group intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Disclosure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Suicide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicide, Attempted</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

