<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03947112</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019/260</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03947112</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Activity Level of Norwegian Boys With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Physical Activity Level of Norwegian Boys With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy - a Cross Sectional Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Norwegian School of Sport Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Haukeland University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this population based study is to examine, quantify and describe physical activity
      level in Norwegian boys with DMD, and to compare the level of physical activity level between
      boys with DMD and age matched healthy boys. A co-project will validate ActiGraph
      accelerometry to measure physical activity in boys with DMD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      International guidelines recommend regular physical activity for boys with DMD, and
      participation in physical activity plays a key role in the management. Paradoxically,
      patients with severe neuromuscular disease like DMD, have considerable limitations to
      participate in such activities. Limitation may be muscle weakness, pain, fatigue, reduced
      mobility and overall function, and also limited knowledge of physical activity benefits among
      health care personnel. Limited participation leads to a sedentary lifestyle, and gradual
      under-use of still functioning muscles may cause secondary deterioration in DMD.

      The current physical activity level amongst Norwegian DMD`s are unknown, and physical
      activity registration and self-reported questionnaire will be examined in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity registration</measure>
    <time_frame>Seven days</time_frame>
    <description>An Actigraph will be provided and worn at pre set time frame (Seven days including weekend). Data extracted are counts per minutes, and are measurements of movement performed in both vertical and horizontal axis. The counts will be used to quantify the time the participant is inactive, low, moderate and / or in vigorous physical active.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Leisure time physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The UngKan-3 questionnaire is a self-reported/parent-reported instrument, developed to measure leisure time physical activity, diet, media habits and sleep routine. The questionnaire is former used in a national cross-sectional survey amongst Norwegian school students, developed by the Norwegian School of Sport Sciences and Norwegian Institute of Public Health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Reported Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Self-administrated questionnaire developed to describe participants function, on-going treatment, movement aid, types of physical activities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity diary</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>During physical activity registration with use of ActiGraph monitor, the participants and parents are asked to fill out a diary, describing type of physical activity been performed, for how long the physical activity was performed, how tired the participants became, and how did the participant enjoy the activity being performed. In addition the participants is asked to give a summary of the week regarding to name the most enjoyable activity this week and the reason why, and to describe if there occurred something unusual that increased or decreased their physical activity level more than regular.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Norwegian population with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Boys with DMD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical activity registration</intervention_name>
    <description>At start, participants and parents fills out a Self-report questionnaire and the UngKan-3 Questionnaire, before a seven day physical activity registration takes place by use og ActiGraph. A physical activity diary are filled out every evening while the physical activity registration takes places.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Norwegian population with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Self-report Questionnaire</other_name>
    <other_name>Physical activity diary</other_name>
    <other_name>UngKan-3 Questionnaire</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population will be requited from all the Norwegian regional pediatric rehabilitation
        centre`s out patient clinics. Verbal and written information about the study will be
        provided if inclution criteria to be met.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Boys with conclusive diagnosis of Duchenne Muscular disease, attending Norwegian
             pediatric rehabilitation clinics.

          -  Signed written consent

          -  Able to answer questionnaires with help from parents, care giver(s) or health care
             professional with regular follow up of the participants.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lack of consent.

          -  Language difficulties

          -  Cognitive dysfunction or mental retardation leading to difficulties in answering the
             questionnaires adequately
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>DMD is X-linked disease</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tiina M Andersen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Physiotherapy, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stian Hammer, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+4790186485</phone>
    <email>stian.hammer@helse-bergen.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tiina M Andersen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+47 55978486</phone>
    <email>tiina.andersen@helse-bergen.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haukeland University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <state>Hordaland</state>
        <zip>5021</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heutinck L, Kampen NV, Jansen M, Groot IJ. Physical Activity in Boys With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy Is Lower and Less Demanding Compared to Healthy Boys. J Child Neurol. 2017 Apr;32(5):450-457. doi: 10.1177/0883073816685506. Epub 2017 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>28112012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birnkrant DJ, Bushby K, Bann CM, Apkon SD, Blackwell A, Brumbaugh D, Case LE, Clemens PR, Hadjiyannakis S, Pandya S, Street N, Tomezsko J, Wagner KR, Ward LM, Weber DR; DMD Care Considerations Working Group. Diagnosis and management of Duchenne muscular dystrophy, part 1: diagnosis, and neuromuscular, rehabilitation, endocrine, and gastrointestinal and nutritional management. Lancet Neurol. 2018 Mar;17(3):251-267. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30024-3. Epub 2018 Feb 3. Review. Erratum in: Lancet Neurol. 2018 Apr 4;:.</citation>
    <PMID>29395989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical activity level</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

