<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03948542</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F.o.t.H. Version 1.0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03948542</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fractures of the Humeral Shaft With Primary Radial Nerve Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fractures of the Humeral Shaft With Primary Radial Nerve Palsy: Do Injury Mechanism, Fracture Type, or Treatment Influence Nerve Recovery: A Retrospective Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study addresses the question if patients with fractures of the humeral shaft and primary
      radial nerve palsy gain nerve recovery.

      Additionally the influence of injury mechanism, fracture type, and treatment modality on
      nerve recovery should be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adult fractures of the humeral shaft account for approximately 3% of all fractures; most can
      be treated nonoperatively. Due to the anatomy of the radial nerve and the entrapment between
      fragments in spiral fractures of the humerus, these injuries are associated with primary
      radial nerve palsy in up to 18%.

      Therefore, the purpose of this study was to assess the influence of injury mechanism,
      fracture type, and type of surgical treatment on time to onset of nerve recovery and time to
      full nerve recovery in patients with humeral shaft fractures and concomitant primary radial
      nerve palsy.

      A retrospective analysis of prospectively collected data for all patients treated with
      humeral shaft fracture and primary radial nerve palsy at an academic Level-I trauma center
      was performed. Between 1994 and 2013 a total of 615 patients with traumatic humeral shaft
      fractures were treated at the department. The dataset was examined for completeness and
      accuracy. Patients with an incomplete dataset, those with a pathologic or periprosthetic
      fracture, patients with non-surgical treatment, or who were younger than 18 years of age were
      excluded from this series. According to these criteria, a total of 50 patients with a humeral
      shaft fracture and primary radial nerve underwent surgical treatment
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in nerve recovery; Nerve recovery after humeral shaft fracture and surgical treatment, Functional assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, from date of inclusion till first documented changes in nerve recovery, from date of admission assessed up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional assessment was routinely performed at all follow up visits including a clinical evaluation and muscle strength (M0-M5) with a manual muscle test that was graded according to Daniels and Worthingham.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nerve conduction studies (NCV) were performed routinely at two weeks following onset of radial nerve palsy and after 4 months in case of delayed recovery.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Nerve conduction studies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic examination via X-ray in two planes</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 12 months after trauma</time_frame>
    <description>X-ray in two planes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Radial Nerve Palsy</condition>
  <condition>Functional Outcome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Outcome</arm_group_label>
    <description>Nerve conduction studies (NCV) Functional assessment according to Daniels and Worthingham</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Outcome</intervention_name>
    <description>Nerve Recovery
NCV
Funcional assessment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Outcome</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population will include patients treated with humeral shaft fracture and primary
        radial nerve palsy between 1994 and 2013 at the Department of Trauma Surgery, Medical
        University of Vienna
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients treated with humeral shaft fracture and primary radial nerve palsy between
             1994 and 2013 at the Department of Trauma Surgery, Medical University of Vienna

          -  surgical treatment

          -  complete data sets

          -  minimum 18 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with an incomplete dataset

          -  those with a pathologic or periprosthetic fracture

          -  patients with non-surgical treatment

          -  or who were younger than 18 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas Tiefenboeck, M.D., MSc</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intramedullary nailing</keyword>
  <keyword>ORIF</keyword>
  <keyword>Humeral shaft fracture</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Radial Neuropathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be available on request from the corresponding author in a blinded version</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

