<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03944226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2-114-18</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>17/049</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03944226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Is Dietary Nitrate Effective in Reducing Aerobic Glycolysis in Breast Cancer?</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEET</acronym>
  <official_title>Is Dietary Nitrate Effective in Reducing Aerobic Glycolysis (AG) in Breast Cancer? - A Longitudinal Study Using Specialist Magnetic Resonance (MR) Methods</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aberdeen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NHS Grampian</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aberdeen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is the most prevalent cancer affecting women, with 1 in 8 women in the UK
      developing breast cancer in their life time. Chemotherapy drugs, currently used for locally
      advanced breast cancers, are associated with side effects while dietary supplements have
      complex effects with a relatively small effect size.

      Breast tumours have different metabolism compared to healthy tissue, including elevated
      lactate production by aerobic glycolysis (AG), an underpinning feature of metabolism in
      breast cancer cells. Dietary nitrate, contained in leafy green vegetables and beetroot, has
      been shown to improve energy efficiency in exercising skeletal muscle, positioning itself as
      a disruptor of AG.

      The purpose of this study is to examine if dietary nitrate can disrupt AG and as a result to
      halt or even reverse tumour progression and survival. This study will look at scans of breast
      tumours using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). Changes to tumour related biochemical
      substances will be measured by advanced magnetic resonance spectroscopy and changes to tissue
      structure will be measured by advanced diffusion MRI techniques.

      In this study, 16 patients undergoing surgery will be recruited for two MRI scans following a
      5 day intervention programme.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this longitudinal study, the investigators propose to examine the changes in lipid
      composition and microstructure in breast tumours at baseline and post dietary nitrate
      intervention through the applications of novel non-invasive magnetic resonance spectroscopy
      (MRS) methods and diffusion and lipid profiling MR imaging methods in patients. The
      investigators hypothesise that dietary nitrate disrupts tumour progression in breast cancer.

        1. Is there a significant difference in lipid composition in the tumour measured by MRS
           between baseline and post dietary nitrate intervention?

        2. Is there a significant difference in lipid composition in the whole breast tissue
           surrounding tumour measured by MRI between baseline and post dietary nitrate
           intervention?

        3. Is there a significant difference in tissue microstructure measured by MRI between
           baseline and post dietary nitrate intervention in the breast tissue?

      To assess the effect of dietary nitrate on tumour progression, paired t-tests will be
      performed on lipid composition measured from tumour between baseline and post intervention.
      To assess the effect of dietary nitrate on tumour progression, paired t-tests will be
      performed on lipid composition in the whole breast tissue surrounding tumour between baseline
      and post intervention. To assess the effect of dietary nitrate on tissue microstructure
      paired t-tests will be performed on water displacement measured from tumour between baseline
      and post intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 26, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single Group: trials with a single arm</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Single group with no masking</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline: Lipid composition in tumour</measure>
    <time_frame>Scan one day before intervention (Day 0)</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid peak volume with units of ratio</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post intervention: Lipid composition in tumour</measure>
    <time_frame>Scan one day after completion of intervention (Day 6)</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid peak volume ratio with units of ratio</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline: Lipid composition in whole breast tissue surrounding tumour</measure>
    <time_frame>Scan one day before intervention (Day 0)</time_frame>
    <description>fat fraction with units of %</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post intervention: Lipid composition in whole breast tissue surrounding tumour</measure>
    <time_frame>Scan one day after completion of intervention (Day 6)</time_frame>
    <description>fat fraction with units of %</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline: Water displacement in tumour</measure>
    <time_frame>Scan one day before intervention (Day 0)</time_frame>
    <description>Water displacement with units of micrometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post intervention: Water displacement in tumour</measure>
    <time_frame>Scan one day after completion of intervention (Day 6)</time_frame>
    <description>Water displacement with units of micrometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Breast Tissue Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Beetroot</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>16 patients confirmed with a diagnosis of invasive ductal carcinoma who will undergo wide local excision surgery or mastectomy. All patients in the single arm will undergo a 5 day intervention drinking concentrated beetroot juice and 2 magnetic resonance imaging scan sessions pre and post intervention. MRI scan sessions will be composed of research scans including diffusion and lipid profiling MR imaging methods and MR spectroscopy (MRS) methods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Beetroot juice</intervention_name>
    <description>The patient will follow a 5 day dietary nitrate intervention programme, taking 3 doses of 7cl (0.4 g nitrate per dose) concentrated beetroot juice (SPORT shot, James White Drinks, Suffolk, U.K.) a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Beetroot</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with pathologically confirmed invasive ductal carcinoma (Grade 2 or 3)

          -  Undergoing wide local excision surgery or mastectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Started hormone or chemotherapy treatment before recruitment.

          -  Undergoing treatment for concurrent cancer diagnosis.

          -  Taking antibiotics, proton pump or vegetable dietary supplement.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jiabao He, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vasiliki Mallikourti, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vasiliki Mallikourti, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)1224 438351</phone>
    <email>r02vm16@abdn.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jiabao He, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)1224 43-7321</phone>
    <email>jiabao.he@abdn.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aberdeen Biomedical Imaging Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aberdeen</city>
        <zip>AB25 2ZD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vasiliki Mallikourti, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)1224 438351</phone>
      <email>r02vm16@abdn.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vasiliki Mallikourti, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham LJ, Shupe MP, Schneble EJ, Flynt FL, Clemenshaw MN, Kirkpatrick AD, Gallagher C, Nissan A, Henry L, Stojadinovic A, Peoples GE, Shumway NM. Current approaches and challenges in monitoring treatment responses in breast cancer. J Cancer. 2014 Jan 5;5(1):58-68. doi: 10.7150/jca.7047. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24396498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baker J, Ajani J, Scotté F, Winther D, Martin M, Aapro MS, von Minckwitz G. Docetaxel-related side effects and their management. Eur J Oncol Nurs. 2009 Feb;13(1):49-59. doi: 10.1016/j.ejon.2008.10.003. Epub 2009 Feb 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19201649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gatenby RA, Gillies RJ. Why do cancers have high aerobic glycolysis? Nat Rev Cancer. 2004 Nov;4(11):891-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15516961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones AM. Dietary nitrate supplementation and exercise performance. Sports Med. 2014 May;44 Suppl 1:S35-45. doi: 10.1007/s40279-014-0149-y. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24791915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McMahon NF, Leveritt MD, Pavey TG. The Effect of Dietary Nitrate Supplementation on Endurance Exercise Performance in Healthy Adults: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Sports Med. 2017 Apr;47(4):735-756. doi: 10.1007/s40279-016-0617-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27600147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bentley R, Gray SR, Schwarzbauer C, Dawson D, Frenneaux M, He J. Dietary nitrate reduces skeletal muscle oxygenation response to physical exercise: a quantitative muscle functional MRI study. Physiol Rep. 2014 Jul 22;2(7). pii: e12089. doi: 10.14814/phy2.12089. Print 2014 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>25052493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Beetroot juice</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

