<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03946059</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BrainE_TMS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03946059</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Measuring Plasticity in SFC/dACC Following Theta-Burst-Stimulation Using TMS</brief_title>
  <acronym>BTMS</acronym>
  <official_title>Estimating the Sensitivity of a Mobile Neuro-cognitive Platform (&quot;BrainE&quot;) to Detect Neural Plasticity and Cognitive Enhancements Following Theta-burst Stimulation to Superior Frontal/dACC TMS Stimulation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study to determine whether particular forms of brain-stimulation, applied to
      superior frontal cortex/preSMA can affect cognition and associated frontal theta
      oscillations. To perform this study, the investigators will first measure brain
      activity/cognitive performance using &quot;BrainE&quot;, a rapid series of cognitive tests measuring
      sustained attention, behavioral inhibition, working memory and interference/distractor
      processing. Next, the investigators will apply brain-stimulation over a mid-frontal region
      most strongly associated with these tasks (mid-line frontal activity overlying superior
      frontal cortex/pre-SMA area). Finally, human subjects will perform BrainE assessments again
      immediately after the brain-stimulation. The investigators will compare the effects of brain
      stimulation on frontal activity evoked on the cognitive tasks, and on behavioral performance
      across these tasks. The investigators will further compare two types of brain-stimulation
      against each other: continuous Theta-Burst-Stimulation (a stimulation protocol designed to
      inhibit brain activity) and intermittent Theta-Burst Stimulation (a protocol designed to
      excite brain activity).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Brain/Behavior Recordings: to measure brain activity as described above, the
           investigators will first ask subjects to engage in a cognitive battery while measuring
           EEG activity. For this study, the battery consists of the following tasks: (1) a
           go/no-go task to study sustained attention and behavioral inhibition; (2) a
           visuo-spatial working-memory task; (3) a Flanker interference task and (4) a
           emotional-distractor task. A breath monitoring task is also included as a measure of
           internal attention/distraction. This battery takes about 30 minutes to complete. 24
           channel EEG recordings will be performed during this task. Subjects will perform BrainE,
           will receive brain-stimulation, and will then immediately be tested on the BrainE tasks
           again.

        2. Brain-Stimulation: Each subject will be asked to come in twice for this study, separated
           by 1 week. On week one they will receive one stimulation protocol; and on the subsequent
           week they will receive the other (order determined randomly for each subject). The
           continuous Theta-Burst-Stimulation protocol (cTBS) consists of a burst of three
           stimulation pulses, applied 20ms apart; with each burst occurring every 200ms. Thus,
           every second participants receive 5 bursts. This continues for 40 seconds, such that
           participants in total receive 200 bursts or 600 pulses. The intermittent
           Theta-Burst-Stimulation protocol (iTBS) consists of a similar burst pattern (3
           stimulation pulses 20ms apart; each burst applied every 200ms). However, after 10 bursts
           (2 seconds of stimulation) there is a pause for 8 seconds. 200 bursts are still applied,
           however due to the inter-burst intervals, this paradigm takes 200 seconds.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The investigators will test the effects of two different interventions (iTBS, cTBS) on cognitive control. Each participant will receive both interventions, labeled A &amp; B, separated a week apart.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Investigators will assess for each subject whether they have any guess, a priori, as to hypothesized effects of the interventions (improve, impair or no change on cognition). Participant/care provider will know which stimulation is being applied (iTBS, cTBS based on labels A &amp; B), but will not know the hypothesized effects of these two interventions. Interventions will be masked as &quot;treatment A&quot; and &quot;treatment B&quot;, prior to handing the data over to PI/outcomes assessor. Analyses will thus be performed to assess whether treatment &quot;A&quot; or treatment &quot;B&quot; has an effect on cognition; and whether there are differences between these treatments. After the trial is finished, treatments will be un-masked.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in mid-frontal theta oscillations</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately before and immediately after the intervention on the same day</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in frontal task-evoked theta oscillations across four cognitive tasks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in cognitive performance</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately before and immediately after the intervention on the same day</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in performance efficiency (ratio of accuracy to response time) on tested cognitive tasks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Control</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iTBS over superior frontal cortex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>intermittent Theta-Burst-Stimulation (iTBS) entails a 2 second train of stimuli (stimuli occurring as a 50 Hz burst of three pulses separated by 200ms). Each 2 second train is followed by an 8 second pause, followed by another 2 second train. In total, 20 trains will be delivered, for a total of 200 bursts and 600 total pulses.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cTBS over superior frontal cortex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>continuous Theta-Burst-Stimulation (cTBS) consists of a continuous stimulus train (stimuli occurring as a 50 Hz burst of three pulses separated by 200ms). In total, 200 bursts and 600 total pulses will be delivered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rTMS - iTBS</intervention_name>
    <description>repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation applied with intermittent theta-burst stimulation protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>iTBS over superior frontal cortex</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rTMS - cTBS</intervention_name>
    <description>repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation applied with continuous theta-burst stimulation protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>cTBS over superior frontal cortex</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Adequate decisional capacity to make a choice about participating in this research study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No major active neurologic/psychiatric disease

          -  No contraindications for rTMS

          -  No behavioral/medical factors that increase risk of seizure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jyoti Mishra, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Altman Clinical &amp; Translational Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 16, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jyoti Mishra</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Asst Professor IR</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

