<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03947099</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KRP002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03947099</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ketamine Infusion Therapy for the Treatment of PTSD in Paramedics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ketamine Infusion Therapy for the Treatment of PTSD in Paramedics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Klarisana Physician Services PLLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Klarisana Physician Services PLLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational study to assess the change in several psychological screening tools
      before and after a series of six ketamine infusions in paramedics who suffer from post
      traumatic stress disorder as a result of working in emergency medical services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Working as a paramedic in a prehospital emergency medical services system (EMS) has been
      shown to lead to increased incidence of post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and increased
      risk of suicide in prehospital personnel. In recent years a growing body of literature has
      shown that ketamine hydrochloride can be an effective treatment for PTSD. This study seeks to
      look specifically at paramedic level emergency medical technicians (&quot;paramedics&quot;) with PTSD
      related to their prehospital work and assess whether ketamine infusion therapy can be an
      effective treatment for them. This is an observational study where the results of
      psychological screening tools that are administered before and after a six-infusion series
      are reported. Additionally the same assessment tools will be administered again 30 days after
      the final treatment to measure the durability of any changes. The participants will receive
      the Periodic Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9), the PTSD Checklist for Diagnostic and
      Statistical Manual, DSM-5 (PCL-5), the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT), and
      the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI) before the infusions, after the series of six, and thirty
      days later. Additionally, after the series of six infusions, participants will receive the
      Revised Mystical Experience Questionnaire-30 (RMEQ-30) and a one question survey to assess
      the impact of the experiential aspect of ketamine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PHQ-9 Score to assess for symptoms of depression</measure>
    <time_frame>three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assess for an improvement in the Periodic Health Questionnaire nine (PHQ-9) score after a series of six ketamine infusions. The PHQ-9 is a nine question scale followed by a single question that assesses functional impairment. Each of the nine questions are scored on a basis of zero to four. The higher the score the more severe the symptoms of depression are. The highest score is 27 and the lowest is zero.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PCL-5 Score to assess for symptoms of PTSD</measure>
    <time_frame>three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assess for an improvement in the PTSD Checklist for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual version five (PCL-5) score after a series of six ketamine infusions. The PCL-5 is a 20 question scale and each question is scored on a zero to four scale. A higher score indicates more severe symptoms of PTSD. The highest score possible is 80 and the lowest is zero.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the experiential impact of ketamine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>three weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators seek to determine the role that the experiential (psychedelic) aspect of ketamine plays in the treatment of PTSD. This will utilize the Mystical Experience Questionnaire 30. This is a 30 question screening instrument where each question is scored on a scale of one to five. The maximum score is 150. A higher score indicates that the participant reports a more powerful mystical experience. There is also a single question that asks the participants to rate on a scale of one to five how important they feel the experiential (or psychedelic) aspect of the therapy was to their treatment. Five would indicate that they felt it was an important part of the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorders</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are treated with six one-hour infusions of ketamine hydrochloride over a three week period in hopes of treating symptoms of PTSD.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Men and women who are trained as paramedics (EMT-P) and have worked in 911 emergency
        medical service systems for at least five years.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have worked as a paramedic (EMT-P) on a 911 prehospital service for at least five
             years.

          -  Must be diagnosed with post traumatic stress disorder that happened as a result of
             working as a paramedic

          -  Diagnosis must have been made by a mental health professional

          -  The symptoms of PTSD must be having a significant adverse effect on the subject's life

          -  Subjects must be able to speak and read English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently participating in another PTSD treatment program and/or research study

          -  Diagnosis of psychosis

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension or a history of heart failure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carl J Bonnett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Klarisana Physician Services PLLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carl J Bonnett, MD</last_name>
    <phone>210-556-1430</phone>
    <email>info@klarisana.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klarisana</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carl J Bonnett, MD</last_name>
      <phone>210-556-1430</phone>
      <email>info@klarisana.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gerson Barahona</last_name>
      <phone>210-556-1430</phone>
      <email>info@klarisana.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carl J Bonnett, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.klarisana.com</url>
    <description>The sponsoring treatment facility for this study</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Luftman K, Aydelotte J, Rix K, Ali S, Houck K, Coopwood TB, Teixeira P, Eastman A, Eastridge B, Brown CV, Davis M. PTSD in those who care for the injured. Injury. 2017 Feb;48(2):293-296. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2016.11.001. Epub 2016 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>27871770</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jacobowitz W. PTSD in psychiatric nurses and other mental health providers: a review of the literature. Issues Ment Health Nurs. 2013 Nov;34(11):787-95. doi: 10.3109/01612840.2013.824053. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24131410</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stanley IH, Hom MA, Joiner TE. Suicide mortality among firefighters: Results from a large, urban fire department. Am J Ind Med. 2016 Nov;59(11):942-947. doi: 10.1002/ajim.22587. Epub 2016 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27219513</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bing-Canar H, Ranney RM, McNett S, Tran JK, Berenz EC, Vujanovic AA. Alcohol Use Problems, Posttraumatic Stress Disorder, and Suicide Risk Among Trauma-Exposed Firefighters. J Nerv Ment Dis. 2019 Mar;207(3):192-198. doi: 10.1097/NMD.0000000000000947.</citation>
    <PMID>30724832</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abdallah CG, Roache JD, Averill LA, Young-McCaughan S, Martini B, Gueorguieva R, Amoroso T, Southwick SM, Guthmiller K, López-Roca AL, Lautenschlager K, Mintz J, Litz BT, Williamson DE, Keane TM, Peterson AL, Krystal JH; Consortium to Alleviate PTSD. Repeated ketamine infusions for antidepressant-resistant PTSD: Methods of a multicenter, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Contemp Clin Trials. 2019 Jun;81:11-18. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2019.04.009. Epub 2019 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>30999057</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>ptsd</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>prehospital</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

