<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03940508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R34MH119290-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R34MH119290-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03940508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Engaging Black Youth in Depression and Suicide Prevention Treatment Within Urban Schools</brief_title>
  <official_title>Engaging Black Youth in Depression and Suicide Prevention Treatment Within Urban Schools: A Preliminary Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Completing evidence-based treatments for depression has been shown to be particularly
      problematic for Black adolescents. If Black adolescents' depression treatment needs are to be
      met, the engagement challenges and the factors that lessen the success of treatment in the
      &quot;real world&quot; must be addressed. The investigators will examine the effectiveness of the
      Making Connections Intervention (MCI) and investigate key mediators of both engagement and
      response to treatment for depression. The MCI is a 1-2 session, evidence-based intervention
      designed to improve engagement, perceived relevance, and treatment satisfaction among
      depressed, Black adolescents. The study also uses tailored outreach strategies for
      adolescents and parents by including innovative digital content such as a web page/app along
      with other digital products.

      This study will address an important public health issue: How best to connect Black
      adolescents with depression to treatment in clinically meaningful ways, and how best to
      deliver evidence-based treatment to them through school-based services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Completing evidence-based treatments for depression has been shown to be particularly
      problematic for Black adolescents. Their rates of participation in treatments for depression
      are lower due to negative perceptions of services and providers, and their reluctance to
      acknowledge the presence of symptoms.

      If Black adolescents' depression treatment needs are to be met, the engagement challenges and
      the factors that lessen the success of treatment in the &quot;real world&quot; must be addressed. This
      research examines the effectiveness of the Making Connections Intervention (MCI) and
      investigates key mediators of both engagement and response to treatment for depression. The
      MCI is a 1-2 session, evidence-based intervention designed to improve engagement, perceived
      relevance, and treatment satisfaction among depressed, Black adolescents. The study also uses
      tailored outreach strategies for adolescents and parents by including innovative digital
      content such as a web page/app along with other digital products.

      The investigators previously performed a small pilot study that used the MCI as an add-on to
      the IPT-A, an evidence-based intervention for depression delivered in schools typically over
      12 sessions. The results suggested that MCI has a positive impact on many aspects of change
      associated with treatment engagement and clinical outcomes.

      This study will be a randomized controlled trial. It will examine the effectiveness of the
      MCI in a multi-school trial involving adolescents in grades 6-12 who attend New York City
      (NYC) Department of Education (DOE) Public Schools. The investigators will randomly assign 60
      Black students with depression symptoms to two conditions: MCI+IPT-A vs. IPT-A-alone. The
      investigators will also do qualitative research, like interviews, before the digital content
      is created. This will enhance the relevance of the MCI. The main outcomes are adolescent-and
      caregiver-level engagement and adolescent depression. Suicidal ideation is a secondary
      outcome. This study will also test related factors, like adolescent helping-seeking behavior
      and parental knowledge of mental health services, that can account for treatment outcomes and
      that will allow the MCI to be strengthened in future roll-outs of the intervention in school
      settings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barriers for Adolescents Seeking Health (BASH)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report questionnaire that targets barriers to seeking professional psychological help</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Child Help-Seeking Scale (HSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report 28-item questionnaire designed to measure children's and adolescents' willingness to seek help for psychosocial problems from adults in the school setting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Attitudes Toward Psychological Help Scale (ATPHS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>This scale assesses psychological factors, including stigma, perceived relevance of treatment, etc., that impact one's perceptions of and attitudes about using formal mental health treatment services.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Stages of Change (SOC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>32-item instrument for assessing the readiness for changes in relation to general problems, or problems associated with participation in psychotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Penn Helping Alliance (Haq-R)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire collects data from both the therapist and patient to measure the strength of the bond between therapist and patient, called the &quot;therapeutic alliance.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MCI Integrity Scale (MCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1</time_frame>
    <description>To measure treatment integrity in Making Connections Intervention (MCI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in IPT-A Fidelity Form (IPT-A)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of the first weekly therapy session until the course of IPT-A treatment is completed, approximately 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>To measure treatment integrity in IPT-A and maintain treatment effectiveness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barriers to Treatment Participation Scale (BTPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>To test whether perceived barriers to treatment influence dropping out and other measures of participation in treatment. To assess a broad range of barriers evident over the course of treatment, including four thematic areas: stressors and obstacles that compete with treatment, treatment demands and issues, perceived relevance of treatment, and relationship with the therapist.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Understanding Mood Disorders Questionnaire (UMDQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>Designed to measure family members' attributions about and knowledge of symptoms, course, and treatment of mood disorders</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Therapy Survey (TS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>To measure change in expectations about treatment at a children's psychiatric clinic about a week before their first therapy and counseling sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Progress of Treatment (POT)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of the first weekly therapy session until the course of IPT-A treatment is completed, approximately 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>To measure adolescent engagement in treatment in order to control for the common factors of psychotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Engagement Measure (EM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 and Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>An 11-item measures for engagement, which includes six dimensions: Appointment keeping (two items); Client-therapist interaction (one item); Communication/Openness (three items); Client's perceived usefulness of treatment (one item); Collaboration with treatment (three items) and Compliance with medication (one item)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Evidence-Based Practice Attitude Scale (EBPAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses mental health service provider attitudes toward adopting evidence-based practices.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Service use logs (SUL)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of the first weekly therapy session until the course of IPT-A treatment is completed, approximately 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Measures the change in attendance of treatment session by therapists.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Termination form (TF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Measures the termination of treatment session by therapists</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HRSD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 1, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>Determines a patient's level of depression before, during, and after treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression Scale (CES-DC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screen, baseline, weeks 4,8,12</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item self-report scale designed to measure depressive symptomatology in the general population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire-Junior (SIQ-Jr)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12</time_frame>
    <description>A 15-item self-report measure developed specifically for identifying and assessing current suicidal ideation among young adolescents that requires approximately five to eight minutes to complete.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the severity and lethality of suicidal behaviors and ideations, and can be used to monitor treatment outcomes and establish suicide risk in a variety of research and clinical settings.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Global Assessment Scale for Children (C-GAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12</time_frame>
    <description>To reflect the lowest level of functioning for a child or adolescent during a specified time period, or on a hypothetical continuum of health-illness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Therapist Satisfaction Questionnaire (TSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, week 12</time_frame>
    <description>A 5-point questionnaire filled by therapists to indicate their satisfaction of the therapy (e.g., &quot;the sense of comfort&quot; and &quot;nervousness&quot;).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic Form (DF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To measure participants' demographic characteristics</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>School records (GL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To measure youth's school records</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in School Performance- GPA, Number of Suspensions, and School attendance (SP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, weeks 4, 8, 12</time_frame>
    <description>To measure students' school performance, number of suspensions, and school attendance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Suicidal Ideation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MCI + IPT-A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the Making Connections Intervention (MCI) in addition to IPT-A for depression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IPT-A Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive IPT-A for depression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Making Connections Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The MCI is a one to two session intervention that addresses barriers to mental health treatment and helps adolescents build skills to get the most out of their treatment experience. It is designed to be delivered by a trained clinician in conjunction with an evidence-based treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MCI + IPT-A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IPT-A</intervention_name>
    <description>IPT-A is a time-limited, manualized treatment for depression focused on maladaptive communication patterns and interpersonal interactions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IPT-A Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MCI + IPT-A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Interpersonal Psychotherapy for Depressed Adolescents</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Must identify as Black and/or African American

          2. Must be enrolled in grades 6-12 (except 12th graders in their last semester)

          3. Must be able to speak English

          4. Must have received caregiver consent and have assented to participate

          5. Must meet depression and global functioning levels indicated by a CES-D score ≥16, a
             Hamilton Rating Scale of Depression (HRSD) Score ≥ 10, and a Global Assessment Scale
             for Children (C-GAS) score ≤ 65 at baseline

          6. Students who are currently on a stable dose of anti-depressant medication, but still
             meet inclusion criteria, can be enrolled in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Actively suicidal with intent or plan

          2. Intellectually disabled

          3. Have a life threatening medical illness

          4. Have a current primary substance abuse diagnosis in the moderate to severe range,
             schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, any evidence of psychosis, a primary diagnosis of
             anorexia

          5. Currently in active treatment for depression (excluding medication) at baseline
             assessment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael A Lindsey, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Silver School of Social Work</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael A Lindsey, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 998-5927</phone>
    <email>michael.lindsey@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tracy M Grogan, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 992-6902</phone>
    <email>tmg374@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Mufson, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>646-774-5791</phone>
      <email>Laura.Mufson@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laura Mufson, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McSilver Institute for Poverty Policy and Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tracy M Grogan, MS</last_name>
      <phone>212-992-6902</phone>
      <email>tmg374@nyu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael A Lindsey, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(212) 998-5927</phone>
      <email>michael.lindsey@nyu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael A Lindsey, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1049731517703747</url>
    <description>Lu W, Lindsey M, Irsheid S, Nebbitt V. Psychometric properties of the center for epidemiological studies-depression Scale (CES-D) among Black adolescents. Journal of the Society for Social Work and Research. 2017.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gunlicks-Stoessel M, Mufson L, Jekal A, Turner JB. The impact of perceived interpersonal functioning on treatment for adolescent depression: IPT-A versus treatment as usual in school-based health clinics. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2010 Apr;78(2):260-7. doi: 10.1037/a0018935.</citation>
    <PMID>20350036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mufson L, Moreau D, Weissman MM, Wickramaratne P, Martin J, Samoilov A. Modification of interpersonal psychotherapy with depressed adolescents (IPT-A): phase I and II studies. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1994 Jun;33(5):695-705.</citation>
    <PMID>8056733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mufson LH, Dorta KP, Olfson M, Weissman MM, Hoagwood K. Effectiveness research: transporting interpersonal psychotherapy for depressed adolescents (IPT-A) from the lab to school-based health clinics. Clin Child Fam Psychol Rev. 2004 Dec;7(4):251-61.</citation>
    <PMID>15648279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindsey MA, Chambers K, Pohle C, Beall P, Lucksted A. Understanding the Behavioral Determinants of Mental Health Service Use by Urban, Under-Resourced Black Youth: Adolescent and Caregiver Perspectives. J Child Fam Stud. 2013 Jan 1;22(1):107-121. Epub 2012 Oct 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23355768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindsey MA, Joe S, Nebbitt V. Family Matters: The Role of Mental Health Stigma and Social Support on Depressive Symptoms and Subsequent Help Seeking Among African American Boys. J Black Psychol. 2010 Nov 1;36(4):458-482.</citation>
    <PMID>20953336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breland-Noble AM, Bell CC, Burriss A; AAKOMA Project Adult Advisory Board. &quot;Mama just won't accept this&quot;: adult perspectives on engaging depressed African American teens in clinical research and treatment. J Clin Psychol Med Settings. 2011 Sep;18(3):225-34. doi: 10.1007/s10880-011-9235-6.</citation>
    <PMID>21512751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindsey MA, Korr WS, Broitman M, Bone L, Green A, Leaf PJ. Help-seeking behaviors and depression among African American adolescent boys. Soc Work. 2006 Jan;51(1):49-58.</citation>
    <PMID>16512510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindsey MA, Brown DR, Cunningham M. Boys do(n't) cry: Addressing the unmet mental health needs of African American boys. Am J Orthopsychiatry. 2017;87(4):377-383. doi: 10.1037/ort0000198.</citation>
    <PMID>28691838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ellis ML, Lindsey MA, Barker ED, Boxmeyer CL, Lochman JE. Predictors of engagement in a school-based family preventive intervention for youth experiencing behavioral difficulties. Prev Sci. 2013 Oct;14(5):457-67. doi: 10.1007/s11121-012-0319-9.</citation>
    <PMID>23420474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael A. Lindsey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Executive Director, McSilver Institute for Poverty Policy and Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment engagement</keyword>
  <keyword>adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Black youth</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Suicidal Ideation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Submit data in compliance with NIMH Data Archive data submission agreement.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>By the end of data collection, March 2022.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>In accordance with the NIMH Data Archive requirements.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>April 17, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/08/NCT03940508/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

