<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03941834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BHV3000-202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03941834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial for Treatment Refractory Trigeminal Neuralgia</brief_title>
  <official_title>BHV3000-202: Phase 2: A Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled, Crossover Trial of BHV-3000 (Rimegepant) for Treatment Refractory Trigeminal Neuraligia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biohaven Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biohaven Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of BHV3000 compared to placebo for
      subjects with treatment refractory Trigeminal Neuralgia as measured by a 2-point or greater
      reduction in the average Numeric Pain Rating Scale between the two-week treatment phases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 25, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BHV-3000 compared to placebo in providing symptomatic pain relief in patients with refractory Trigeminal Neuralgia, as measured by a 2-point or greater reduction in the average Numeric Pain Rating Scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to End of Randomization Phase, up to 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in mean NPRS between the treatment phase. Pain will be measured on a 4 point Likert scale (0=none, 1=mild, 2=moderate, 3=severe)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability (Incidence of treatment emergent adverse events) of BHV-3000 relative to placebo in patients with Trigeminal Neuralgia</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to End of Randomization Phase up to 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be measured by the frequency and severity of adverse events and discontinuations due to adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BHV-3000 vs placebo for improving physical function in Trigeminal Neuralgia patients as measured by the Penn Facial Pain Scale-Revised</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to End of Randomization Phase</time_frame>
    <description>12 questions in which the higher the score the more pain and disability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BHV-3000 vs placebo for improving functional disability in Trigeminal Neuralgia patients as measured by the Pain Disability Index</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to End of Randomization Phase, up to 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>7 question's that are Scored 0-10, ten being more disabled.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BHV-3000 vs placebo on global functioning as measured by the Patient Global Impression of Change Scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to End of Randomization Phase, up to 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by a likert scale from No change to a great deal better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BHV-3000 vs placebo in providing symptomic pain relief as captured by daily rating of worst pain episode as measured by the 11 point numeric rating scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to End of Randomization Phase, up to 5 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>11 point numeric rating scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Trigeminal Neuralgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BHV3000</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rimegepant</intervention_name>
    <description>BHV3000 (rimegepant) 75mg tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>BHV3000</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with a clinical diagnosis of typical or atypical classical trigeminal
             neuralgia based on the International Classification of Headache Disorders, 3rd
             edition, beta version.

          2. Trigeminal neuralgia symptoms for a minimum of 8 weeks prior to randomization visit.

          3. Neuroimaging to exclude another cause for the neuralgia, other than neurovascular
             compression.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has a structural lesion on neuroimaging, other than vascular compression of
             the trigeminal nerve or nerve root that would explain the neuralgia

          2. Subject has a clinically evident neurologic deficit on neurologic exam of the cranial
             nerves

          3. Subjects with a history of HIV disease

          4. Subject history with current evidence of uncontrolled, unstable or recently diagnosed
             cardiovascular disease, such as ischemic heart disease, coronary artery vasospasm, and
             cerebral ischemia. Subjects with Myocardial Infarction (MI), Acute Coronary Syndrome
             (ACS), Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PCI), cardiac surgery, stroke or transient
             ischemic attack (TIA) during the 6 months prior to screening

          5. Uncontrolled hypertension (high blood pressure) at screening

          6. Subject has a current diagnosis of major depression, other pain syndromes, psychiatric
             conditions (e.g., schizophrenia), dementia, or significant neurological disorders
             (other than migraine) that, in the Investigator's opinion, might interfere with study
             assessments

          7. Subject has a history of gastric, or small intestinal surgery (including Gastric
             Bypass, Gastric Banding, Gastric Sleeve, Gastric Balloon, etc.), or has a disease that
             causes malabsorption

          8. Subject has a history or diagnosis of Gilbert's Syndrome or any other active hepatic
             or biliary disorder

          9. The subject has a history or current evidence of any significant and/or unstable
             medical conditions (e.g., history of congenital heart disease or arrhythmia, known
             suspected infection, hepatitis B or C, or cancer) that, in the investigator's opinion,
             would expose them to undue risk of a significant adverse event (AE) or interfere with
             assessments of safety or efficacy during the course of the trial

         10. History of, treatment for, or evidence of, alcohol or drug abuse within the past 12
             months or subjects who have met DSM-V criteria for any significant substance use
             disorder within the past 12 months from the date of the screening visit

         11. Hematologic or solid malignancy diagnosis within 5 years prior to screening. Subjects
             with a history of localized basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer are eligible for
             the study if they are cancer-free prior to the screening visit in this study.

         12. Hematologic or solid malignancy diagnosis within 5 years prior to screening. Subjects
             with a history of localized basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer are eligible for
             the study if they are cancer-free prior to the screening visit in this study.

         13. Body mass index &gt;33kg/m²

         14. History of gallstones or cholecystectomy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elyse Stock, MD</last_name>
    <phone>203-404-0410</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@biohavenpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Whitney Isennock</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-7008</phone>
      <email>wwebb10@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Trigeminal Neuralgia, Pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trigeminal Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

