<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03942900</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P/2018/381</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03942900</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunomonitoring and Biomarker Research in Patients With Squamous Cell Anal Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>LAND</acronym>
  <official_title>Immunomonitoring and Biomarker Research Based on Tumor and Blood Samples in Patients With Squamous Cell Anal Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Besancon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Besancon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Even if squamous cell carcinoma of the anal canal (SCCA) is a rare disease, its incidence
      increases worldwide. SCCA is mostly induced by Human papillomavirus (HPV) infections and
      HPV-related oncoproteins (E6 and E7) are expressed in more than 90% of SCCA. T stage and N
      stage are recognized prognostic factors for local and/or distant recurrence in SCCA patients
      treated by chemoradiotherapy. In fact, ≥T3 or ≥N1 anal cancers are associated with as high as
      50% of disease recurrence rate at 2 years.

      The University Hospital of Besançon with the Gercor conducted a prospective clinical trial
      (Epitopes HPV02 study) including 69 advanced SCCA patients and established a new standard of
      care based on Docetaxel, Cisplatin and 5-FU (5-FluoroUracil) chemotherapy (DCF). Among 69
      patients treated with DCF regimen, 66 patients were evaluable for efficacy end-points. The
      objective response rate was 86% including 44% of complete response, and 47% of patients were
      progression-free at 12 months of follow-up from the first cycle of DCF treatment. Thus, the
      &quot;Epitopes-HPV02&quot; trial has demonstrated a high response rate of the DCF regimen with a higher
      than expected 12 months progression-free survival rate.These results raised the hypothesis of
      DCF being an immunogenic chemotherapy and in that demonstrating a possibly new role of
      taxane-based chemotherapy in SCCA patients. More than 50% of patients in complete remission
      had a detectable immunological response against peptides derived from HPV oncoproteins (E6 or
      E7) or from the telomerase antigen (which is transactivated by E6).

      LAND study will enroll patients with locally advanced SCCA enrolled in OPTIMANAL clinical
      trial. OPTIMANAL study will assess the feasibility and efficacy to combine nivolumab to mDCF
      chemotherapy, followed by the standard chemo-radiotherapy, in high risk locally advanced SCCA
      patients with T3/T4 N1a or N1b/N1c disease.

      LAND study is an exploratory translational study, which will analyze the biological
      mechanisms of action and our ability to track the immune responses against HPV and
      telomerase. The investigator group will take advantage of the presence of HPV antigens in
      most patients to set up a specific immunomonitoring program based on tumor samples and
      blood-derived lymphocytes to better understand the potential synergisms between immunogenic
      chemotherapy and anti-PD1 (Programmed Death-1), and to identify valuable biomarkers of
      treatment efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral CD4 anti-telomerase immunity and MDSC (Myeloid-Derived Suppressor Cells) analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of both peripheral CD4 anti-telomerase immunity and MDSC with progression-free survival.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Anal Canal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort LAND</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients enrolled in OPTIMANAL clinical trial</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Additional biological samples</intervention_name>
    <description>Biomonitoring blood sample will be collected: 6 EDTA tubes (6 mL) for PBMC (peripheral blood mononucleated cell), 1 EDTA tube (6 mL) for plasma freezing and 2 EDTA tubes (4 mL) for ctDNA:
at baseline,
at first tumor assessment (phase 2 in OPTIMANAL study),
at second tumor assessment (phase 4 in OPTIMANAL study),
at end-point visit.
A tumor biopsy or archived tumor sample will be mandatory at baseline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort LAND</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      -  A tumor biopsy or archived tumor sample will be mandatory at baseline. Tumor samples
           will be collected for HPV, p53 testing and translational research.

        -  Biomonitoring blood sample will be collected: 6 EDTA (ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid)
           tubes (6 mL) for PBMC, 1 EDTA tube (6 mL) for plasma freezing and 2 EDTA tubes (4 mL)
           for circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA):

             -  at baseline,

             -  at first tumor assessment (phase 2 in OPTIMANAL study),

             -  at second tumor assessment (phase 4 in OPTIMANAL study),

             -  at end-point visit
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with locally advanced squamous cell anal carcinoma enrolled in OPTIMANAL clinical
        trial, and given consent for LAND-translational study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female, age ≥18 years,

          2. Patients enrolled in OPTIMANAL trial

          3. Signed and dated informed consent for LAND-translational study

          4. Histologically proved squamous cell anal carcinoma.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient with any medical or psychiatric condition or disease, which would make the
             patient inappropriate for entry into this study,

          2. Patient under guardianship, curators or under the protection of justice.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christophe BORG, Pr</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>CHU Besançon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stefano KIM, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>0381668166</phone>
    <email>stefanokim@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christophe BORG, Pr</last_name>
    <phone>0381668166</phone>
    <email>christophe.borg@efs.sante.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Besançon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besançon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefano KIM, Dr</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Nord Franche-Comté</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montbéliard</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christophe BORG, Pr</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim S, Jary M, André T, Vendrely V, Buecher B, François E, Bidard FC, Dumont S, Samalin E, Peiffert D, Pernot S, Baba-Hamed N, El Hajbi F, Bouché O, Desrame J, Parzy A, Zoubir M, Louvet C, Bachet JB, Nguyen T, Abdelghani MB, Smith D, De La Fouchardière C, Aparicio T, Bennouna J, Gornet JM, Jacquin M, Bonnetain F, Borg C. Docetaxel, Cisplatin, and 5-fluorouracil (DCF) chemotherapy in the treatment of metastatic or unresectable locally recurrent anal squamous cell carcinoma: a phase II study of French interdisciplinary GERCOR and FFCD groups (Epitopes-HPV02 study). BMC Cancer. 2017 Aug 25;17(1):574. doi: 10.1186/s12885-017-3566-0.</citation>
    <PMID>28841909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernard-Tessier A, Jeannot E, Guenat D, Debernardi A, Michel M, Proudhon C, Vincent-Salomon A, Bièche I, Pierga JY, Buecher B, Meurisse A, François É, Cohen R, Jary M, Vendrely V, Samalin E, El Hajbi F, Baba-Hamed N, Borg C, Bidard FC, Kim S. Clinical Validity of HPV Circulating Tumor DNA in Advanced Anal Carcinoma: An Ancillary Study to the Epitopes-HPV02 Trial. Clin Cancer Res. 2019 Apr 1;25(7):2109-2115. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-18-2984. Epub 2018 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>30504426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kim S, François E, André T, Samalin E, Jary M, El Hajbi F, Baba-Hamed N, Pernot S, Kaminsky MC, Bouché O, Desrame J, Zoubir M, Ghiringhelli F, Parzy A, De La Fouchardiere C, Smith D, Deberne M, Spehner L, Badet N, Adotevi O, Anota A, Meurisse A, Vernerey D, Taieb J, Vendrely V, Buecher B, Borg C. Docetaxel, cisplatin, and fluorouracil chemotherapy for metastatic or unresectable locally recurrent anal squamous cell carcinoma (Epitopes-HPV02): a multicentre, single-arm, phase 2 study. Lancet Oncol. 2018 Aug;19(8):1094-1106. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(18)30321-8. Epub 2018 Jul 2.</citation>
    <PMID>30042063</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>locally advanced SCCA</keyword>
  <keyword>DCF</keyword>
  <keyword>radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>nivolumab</keyword>
  <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

