<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03943706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8841</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03943706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>E-Cigarette and Cigarette Nicotine Delivery and Abuse Liability in Cigarette Smokers and Dual Users</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Electronic Cigarette and Cigarette Nicotine Delivery and Abuse Liability in Cigarette Smokers and Dual Users</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oklahoma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oklahoma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The FDA has shown clear interest in strategies that will reduce the public health burden of
      tobacco use. One proposed strategy includes banning the sale of fully nicotinized cigarettes
      and only allowing VLNCs (Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes) to be sold. While there are concerns
      regarding the unintended consequences (e.g., black market sales of fully nicotinized
      cigarettes) of such bans, research is needed to understand how smokers and dual users will
      act in the potential market. The overall aim of the current research is to understand
      purchasing and product choice behaviors of tobacco/nicotine users if the proposed ban were to
      go into effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tobacco use continues to be the leading cause of preventable death in the US, with the
      majority of deaths due to combustible tobacco use. Electronic cigarettes (e-cigarettes) may
      represent a nicotine delivery device that addresses cravings and nicotine withdrawal and is
      much less harmful compared to cigarettes, particularly if completely substituted for
      cigarettes. The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) recently set forth plans that include the
      possibility of regulating the level of nicotine in combustible cigarettes to make them
      non-addictive and disallowing the sale of fully nicotinized cigarettes. While studies have
      shown that lowering the level of nicotine in cigarettes leads to high quit rates and would
      likely have a positive overall public health impact, there are concerns that doing so will
      lead to a black market for purchasing fully nicotinized cigarettes. However, no empirical
      evidence currently exists regarding this possible unintended consequence of the proposed
      regulation and the current project aims to fill this gap. Current smokers and dual cigarette
      and e-cigarette users will complete three in-lab study visits. Following screening and
      practice with all study products, participants will complete standardized 10-puff bouts for
      three e-cigarettes, the VLNCs (Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes), and their usual brand
      cigarette. They will then complete three concurrent choice tasks. The tasks will simulate 1)
      the current market, in which e-cigarettes and fully nicotinized cigarettes are available, 2)
      the potential future market in which e-cigarettes and VLNC (Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes) are
      freely available and nicotinized cigarettes are banned, and 3) the potential future market in
      which only tobacco flavored e-cigarettes and VLNCs (Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes) are freely
      available and nicotinized cigarettes are banned. Understanding, in an environment where VLNCs
      (Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes) are the only cigarettes available, current smokers' and dual
      users' product choices will fill an important gap in the research and inform regulation of
      these products.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nicotine delivery measured by serum (blood) nicotine</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete one standardized puffing bout (10 puffs) with each of the three electronic cigarettes, usual brand cigarette and Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes (VLNCs). Serum nicotine will be measured throughout each standardized puffing bout. Greater levels of serum nicotine will be indicative of greater nicotine delivery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of puffs earned and allocated to each product in three hypothetical tobacco regulatory scenarios</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete three computer tasks simulating hypothetical regulatory scenarios and will earn and allocate puffs to study products. A greater proportion of puffs allocated will indicate greater demand for the product in that hypothetical scenario</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Tobacco Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exclusive cigarette smokers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Exclusive cigarette smokers must smoke at least 10 cigarettes per day for the past three months and have exhaled carbon monoxide (eCO) levels of at least 6 ppm at the screening visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dual (Electronic cigarette and cigarette smoking) users</arm_group_label>
    <description>Dual e-cigarette and cigarette users must have smoked at least 5 cigarettes per day for the last 3 months and use e-cigarettes at least 15 days per month for the last 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      During their PK (Pharmacokinetics) visits, Blood will be collected during specific time
      points and plasma will be extracted from the blood. Plasma will be used to analyze the levels
      of nicotine in it.

      Urine will be collected from female participants in order to confirm their pregnancy status.
      Saliva will be collected during their screening visit to analyze for cotinine levels in order
      to check their smoking status.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A sample of 40 current cigarette smokers (n=20) and dual e-cigarette and cigarette users
        (n=20) who are willing to use/try an alternative nicotine-delivery device will be recruited
        via advertisements/ recruitment materials (e.g., craigslist, ads on OSU, OU, and UCO
        campuses, OUHSC, email) and referrals. Participants will live in the Oklahoma City, OK
        metro area. Participants will be provided information about the study and provide initial
        consent for screening via an online screener.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be at least 18 years old

          -  live within 30 miles of the research site

          -  interested in/willing to use an e-cigarette during study visits

          -  be willing and able to complete study procedures including specimen collection, survey
             completion, and remaining nicotine abstinent for 12 hours prior to each study visit

          -  speak and understand English

          -  willing to provide informed consent

          -  bring usual brand cigarettes to screener study visit.

        Additional Inclusion criteria for smokers:

          -  smoke at least 10 cigarettes per day for the past three months,

          -  exhaled more than equal to 6 ppm carbon monoxide at the screener visit.

        Additional Inclusion criteria for dual users:

          -  smoke more than equal to 5 tobacco cigarettes per day for the last 3 months,

          -  use e-cigarettes at least 15 days per month for the last 3 months, and

          -  bring e-cigarette device to screener study visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  currently suffering from lung disease including asthma, cystic fibrosis (CF), or
             chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), unless it is well-controlled,

          -  currently pregnant or breast-feeding or have plans to become pregnant or begin
             breast-feeding at any point during the study,

          -  intoxicated at study visits (breath alcohol testing and clean urine drug screen),

          -  any known allergies or sensitivity to the known major constituents contained in the
             aerosol of the study e-cigarette devices (e.g., flavorants, vegetable glycerin,
             propylene glycol),

          -  User of zero-nicotine e-cigarettes,

          -  smokes mentholated cigarettes regularly,

          -  history of cardiac event or distress within the past 3 months.

        Additional Exclusion criteria for smokers:

          -  have previously used any e-cigarette device (cig-a-like, pen style, mod, APV) for
             longer than 30 days

          -  use of an e-cigarette device over the past 14 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Theodore Wagener, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oklahoma</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Theodore Wagener, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>405-271-8001</phone>
    <phone_ext>50486</phone_ext>
    <email>theodore-wagener@ouhsc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Toral R Mehta, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>405-271-8001</phone>
    <phone_ext>50497</phone_ext>
    <email>Toral-Mehta@ouhsc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center Oklahoma Tobacco Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Theodore Wagener</last_name>
      <phone>405-271-8001</phone>
      <phone_ext>50486</phone_ext>
      <email>theodore-wagener@ouhsc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>e-cigarettes</keyword>
  <keyword>JUUL brand e-cigarette</keyword>
  <keyword>NJOY brand e-cigarette</keyword>
  <keyword>EVOLV brand mod e-cigarette</keyword>
  <keyword>Very Low Nicotine Cigarettes (VLNCs)</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

