<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03945201</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17P.652</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03945201</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Virtual Reality-enhanced Exercise and Education in Cardiac Rehabilitation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of a Virtual Reality-enhanced Exercise and Education Intervention on Patient Engagement and Learning in Cardiac Rehabilitation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study incorporates a virtual reality (VR) simulated walking environment, with audio
      component of patient education, into the treadmill portion of outpatient cardiac
      rehabilitation (CR). The VR program was developed by Plas.MD and is named Bionautica Trails.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 29, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 29, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Consent and enrollment process does not mention virtual reality to maintain blinding between control and intervention arms.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Participant 6-minute Walk Test Improvement Between Control and Intervention Groups</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment through study completion, an average of 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Each participant will complete a 6MWT at both their first and last cardiac rehab treatment sessions. Distance improvement between first and last treatment session is expected for all participants. Average distance improvement (measured in feet) between study arms will be compared to evaluate effectiveness of interventions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Satisfaction with Cardiac Rehab Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>At completion of cardiac rehab treatment, an average of 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>All participants are asked to complete a satisfaction survey, utilizing likert scales and location specific questions to evaluate their satisfaction with treatment. Questions delineate the differences between experiences part of standard of care and those specific to the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Cardiac Education Retention</measure>
    <time_frame>At enrollment; at date of treatment completion, average of 12 weeks; two months following treatment completion</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a brief, 5-question, education quiz at several times throughout their rehabilitation treatment. The quiz will be administered to establish a baseline of their cardiac knowledge prior to treatment, at the end of their treatment to evaluate primary comprehension, and again after treatment to evaluate longterm retention of information. Quiz scores and trends will be compared between study arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Adherence, Patient</condition>
  <condition>Motivation</condition>
  <condition>Satisfaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive normal cardiac rehabilitation according to approved standard of care. They use multiple pieces of exercise equipment at each session for increasing amounts of time and at incrementally increasing levels of difficulty. After establishing a baseline, participants are allowed to use the treadmill for &quot;up to 15 minutes&quot; at each session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual walking trails</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants use multiple pieces of exercise equipment at each session for increasing amounts of time and at incrementally increasing levels of difficulty. After establishing a baseline, participants are allowed to use the treadmill for &quot;up to 15 minutes&quot; at each session. The treadmill is positioned in front of a vertically oriented high definition television screen showing Bionautica Trails, virtual walking trails created by Plas.md.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual walking trails</intervention_name>
    <description>During time on the treadmill, participants walk in front of Bionautica Trails, the virtual walking trails created by Plas.md. Participants can select between seven trails including various nature themed trails and a space setting. While walking, participants wear wireless headphones that provide audio of cardiac rehabilitation education at random intervals. These education pieces cover six categories of information: Understanding Your Heart Condition, Diet, Exercise, Medication, Managing Risk Factors, and Emotional Health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual walking trails</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bionautica Trails</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of care</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive normal standard of care cardiac rehabilitation, completing multiple pieces of exercise equipment at increasing intervals according to the Jefferson Methodist Cardiac Rehabilitation program's protocols. Participants are given the option to use the treadmill for &quot;up to&quot; 15 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must independently choose or be referred to Jefferson Health Methodist
             Cardiac Rehabilitation Program for outpatient cardiac rehabilitation.

          -  Participants must have a referring cardiac condition requiring cardiac rehabilitation
             therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Physical inability to use treadmill

          -  Medically unsafe to use a treadmill for 15 minutes

          -  Inability to understand English

          -  Unable to provide consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jefferson Health Methodist Cardiac Rehabilitation Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19145</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ades PA, Keteyian SJ, Wright JS, Hamm LF, Lui K, Newlin K, Shepard DS, Thomas RJ. Increasing Cardiac Rehabilitation Participation From 20% to 70%: A Road Map From the Million Hearts Cardiac Rehabilitation Collaborative. Mayo Clin Proc. 2017 Feb;92(2):234-242. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2016.10.014. Epub 2016 Nov 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27855953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davies P, Taylor F, Beswick A, Wise F, Moxham T, Rees K, Ebrahim S. Promoting patient uptake and adherence in cardiac rehabilitation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Jul 7;(7):CD007131. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD007131.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014;6:CD007131.</citation>
    <PMID>20614453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kerins M, McKee G, Bennett K. Contributing factors to patient non-attendance at and non-completion of Phase III cardiac rehabilitation. Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs. 2011 Mar;10(1):31-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ejcnurse.2010.03.006. Epub 2010 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20457543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mikkelsen T, Korsgaard Thomsen K, Tchijevitch O. Non-attendance and drop-out in cardiac rehabilitation among patients with ischaemic heart disease. Dan Med J. 2014 Oct;61(10):A4919.</citation>
    <PMID>25283618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vieira Á, Gabriel J, Melo C, Machado J. Kinect system in home-based cardiovascular rehabilitation. Proc Inst Mech Eng H. 2017 Jan;231(1):40-47. doi: 10.1177/0954411916679201. Epub 2016 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27913628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dithmer M, Rasmussen JO, Grönvall E, Spindler H, Hansen J, Nielsen G, Sørensen SB, Dinesen B. &quot;The Heart Game&quot;: Using Gamification as Part of a Telerehabilitation Program for Heart Patients. Games Health J. 2016 Feb;5(1):27-33. doi: 10.1089/g4h.2015.0001. Epub 2015 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26579590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lynggaard V, Nielsen CV, Zwisler AD, Taylor RS, May O. The patient education - Learning and Coping Strategies - improves adherence in cardiac rehabilitation (LC-REHAB): A randomised controlled trial. Int J Cardiol. 2017 Jun 1;236:65-70. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2017.02.051. Epub 2017 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>28259552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dankner R, Drory Y, Geulayov G, Ziv A, Novikov I, Zlotnick AY, Moshkovitz Y, Elami A, Schwammenthal E, Goldbourt U. A controlled intervention to increase participation in cardiac rehabilitation. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2015 Sep;22(9):1121-8. doi: 10.1177/2047487314548815. Epub 2014 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25183694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shema SR, Brozgol M, Dorfman M, Maidan I, Sharaby-Yeshayahu L, Malik-Kozuch H, Wachsler Yannai O, Giladi N, Hausdorff JM, Mirelman A. Clinical experience using a 5-week treadmill training program with virtual reality to enhance gait in an ambulatory physical therapy service. Phys Ther. 2014 Sep;94(9):1319-26. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20130305. Epub 2014 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24786944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sloot LH, van der Krogt MM, Harlaar J. Effects of adding a virtual reality environment to different modes of treadmill walking. Gait Posture. 2014 Mar;39(3):939-45. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2013.12.005. Epub 2013 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24412269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meng K, Seekatz B, Haug G, Mosler G, Schwaab B, Worringen U, Faller H. Evaluation of a standardized patient education program for inpatient cardiac rehabilitation: impact on illness knowledge and self-management behaviors up to 1 year. Health Educ Res. 2014 Apr;29(2):235-46. doi: 10.1093/her/cyt107. Epub 2014 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24399262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cardiac rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>virtual reality</keyword>
  <keyword>VR</keyword>
  <keyword>treadmill</keyword>
  <keyword>education retention</keyword>
  <keyword>patient education</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified participant data will be made available for all gathered data, including primary and secondary outcomes, by request.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available by request indefinitely.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data will be available by request.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

