<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03949712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB18-0178</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03949712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Transcranial Static Magnetic Field Stimulation to Improve Motor Learning</brief_title>
  <acronym>PSTIM</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Transcranial Static Magnetic Field Stimulation (tSMS) on Motor Learning and Cortical Neurophysiology in the Developing Brain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Non-invasive brain stimulation (NIBS) is a safe, painless way to improve brain function. It
      is used for many conditions, including to help children with disabilities. However, it can be
      challenging to apply NIBS in very young children and infants. A new, simple form of NIBS
      called transcranial static magnetic field stimulation (tSMS) is a promising tool for early
      brain stimulation. tSMS in adults has been shown to be safe, tolerable and have the desired
      effects on brain activity when applied to the motor cortex of the brain. However, how tSMS
      affects on motor function is not understood. This research will use tSMS to target the motor
      cortex which is responsible for voluntary movement. The study will determine if tSMS can
      improve motor learning in healthy children. It is hypothesized that application of tSMS on
      the right motor cortex will decrease excitability of the motor cortex and will lead to
      improved motor learning in the right hand. tSMS has the potential to become a safe,
      inexpensive, home-based way to enhance personalized rehabilitation for disabled children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will receive all 3 treatment arms (Right M1 tSMS, Left M1 tSMS, sham tSMS) in a randomized order.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in amplitude of motor evoked potentials (MEPs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to immediately following the tSMS intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline data will be collected through application of single Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) pulses used to assess cortical excitability within one hemisphere. For this, two stimulators (Magstim and Bistim) are connected by an adaptor. A single flat iron Magnstim TMS coil is held over the right hotspot, and pairs of pulses is delivered from this coil. 10 test pulses at an intensity of 120% of resting motor threshold (RMT) are applied. These pulses will be randomized with other paired-pulses to collect other outcome measures (described in the secondary outcome measures section)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left-hand Purdue Pegboard Test (PPT) score.</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in left-hand Purdue Pegboard Test (PPT) score from baseline to after the tSMS intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A &quot;baseline&quot; trial will be performed. During the intervention, participants will perform 25 repetitions. A &quot;post&quot; trail will be performed following the neurophysiology measurements after the tSMS intervention. An increase in score on the PPT would be indicative of improved performance on the task.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in short-interval intracortical inhibition (SICI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to immediately following the tSMS intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline data will be collected through application of paired TMS pulses used to assess cortical excitability within one hemisphere. For this, two stimulators (Magstim and Bistim) are connected by an adaptor. A single flat iron Magnstim TMS coil is held over the right hotspot, and pairs of pulses is delivered from this coil. A conditioning pulse is applied to the left hemisphere at an intensity of 80% RMT, followed by a test pulse over the right hemisphere at an intensity of 120% RMT. 10 pairs of pulses are applied with an interstimulus interval of 2 ms to test for SICI These pulses will be randomized with other paired-pulses and single pulses to collect other outcome measures (described in the primary and secondary outcome measures section)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intracortical facilitation (ICF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to immediately following the tSMS intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline data will be collected through application of paired TMS pulses used to assess cortical excitability within one hemisphere. For this, two stimulators (Magstim and Bistim) are connected by an adaptor. A single flat iron Magnstim TMS coil is held over the right hotspot, and pairs of pulses is delivered from this coil. A conditioning pulse is applied to the left hemisphere at an intensity of 80% RMT, followed by a test pulse over the right hemisphere at an intensity of 120% RMT. 10 pairs of pulses are applied with an interstimulus interval of 10 ms to test for ICF. These pulses will be randomized with other paired-pulses and single pulses to collect other outcome measures (described in the primary and secondary outcome measures section)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Pediatrics</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Right motor cortex (M1) tSMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>tSMS will be applied to the right motor cortex for 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Left motor cortex (M1) tSMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>tSMS will be applied to the left motor cortex for 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tSMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham tSMS will be applied to the left or right motor cortex (randomized) for 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial Static Magnetic Field Stimulation (tSMS)</intervention_name>
    <description>tSMS consists of a small compact cylindrical neodynium magnet (S-45-30-N, Supermagnete) with an estimated strength of up to 0.5 Tesla and a size of 30 mm x 45 mm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Left motor cortex (M1) tSMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Right motor cortex (M1) tSMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Transcranial Static Magnetic Field Stimulation (tSMS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham tSMS consists of a small compact metal cylinder, identical in appearance to the real tSMS device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tSMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. informed consent/assent

          2. age between 8 and 18 years

          3. right-handedness

          4. normal development

          5. absence of neuropsychiatric diagnoses or medications

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. diagnosis of a neurological, psychiatric or developmental disorder

          2. metal in mouth, implanted pacemakers, or other contraindications for brain stimulation

          3. confirmed or potential pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adam Kirton, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alberta Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T3B 6A8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliviero A, Mordillo-Mateos L, Arias P, Panyavin I, Foffani G, Aguilar J. Transcranial static magnetic field stimulation of the human motor cortex. J Physiol. 2011 Oct 15;589(Pt 20):4949-58. doi: 10.1113/jphysiol.2011.211953. Epub 2011 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21807616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliviero A, Carrasco-López MC, Campolo M, Perez-Borrego YA, Soto-León V, Gonzalez-Rosa JJ, Higuero AM, Strange BA, Abad-Rodriguez J, Foffani G. Safety Study of Transcranial Static Magnetic Field Stimulation (tSMS) of the Human Cortex. Brain Stimul. 2015 May-Jun;8(3):481-5. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2014.12.002. Epub 2014 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25595064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Calgary</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Kirton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics, Radiology, and Clinical Neurosciences; Director of Calgary Pediatric Stroke Program and N3; Pediatric Neurologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

