<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03944499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FS-CY1502-Ph1-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03944499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Study of FS-1502 in Patients With HER2 Expressed Advanced Solid Tumors and Local Advanced or Metastatic, HER2 Positive Breast Cancer.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Multicenter, Open-label, Single-arm Study: A Dose-escalation Phase (Phase 1a) Evaluating FS-1502 in Patients With HER2 Expressed Advanced Solid Tumors; and a Dose-expanded Cohort (Phase 1b) Evaluating FS-1502 in Patients With Local Advanced or Metastatic, HER2 Positive Breast Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Fosun Pharmaceutical Development Co, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Fosun Pharmaceutical Development Co, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done for the following reasons:

        -  The study has two parts. The purpose of the first part (Phase 1a) of the study is to
           find out the highest dose of FS-1502 (Trastuzumab Monomethyl Auristatin F), an Anti-HER2
           Antibody Drug Conjugate (ADC) that can be given safely.

        -  The purpose of the second part of the study (Phase 1b) is to observe the treatment
           effect of Recommended Phase 2 Dose (RP2D) of FS-1502 in patients with HER2+ breast
           cancer who are relapsed or refractory to the previous anti-HER2 therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed as an open label, single arm, Phase 1a/1b study with a dose-escalation
      phase to evaluate FS-1502 in patients with HER2 expressed advanced malignant solid tumors
      (phase 1a) and an expanded cohort (phase 1b) to evaluate FS-1502 in patients with metastatic,
      HER2-positive breast cancer. The primary aim of the phase 1a portion of this study is to
      determine the safety and tolerability of FS-1502. The primary aim of the phase 1b portion is
      to demonstrate efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicity (DLT) within 28 days of first single dose of FS-1502.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of Cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days).</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate dose limiting toxicity (DLT) within 28 days from first dose according to DLT criteria per protocol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR) by measurement of target lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Assess ORR per 2 cycles according to RECIST 1.1 criteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence Rate and type of treatment emergent adverse event (Safety)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate according to CTCAE version 5.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with serious adverse events and adverse reactions that leading to treatment permanent discontinuation of FS1502.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of deaths and causes within 30 days after the last dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 3 years.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year overall survival (OS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DoR)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Length of time response continued</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit response (CBR)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants achieve clinical benefit (complete response (CR), partial response (PR) or stable disease (SD) more than 6 months) from the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the AUC of FS-1502 and it metabolites (MMAF).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the Cmax of FS-1502 and it metabolites (MMAF).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to maximum concentration (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the tmax of FS-1502 and it metabolites (MMAF).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination half life (T1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the T1/2 of FS-1502 and it metabolites (MMAF).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance (Cl)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the Clearance of FS-1502 and it metabolites (MMAF).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-FS-1502 antibody</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the anti-FS-1502 antibody to demonstrade the immunogenicity of FS-1502.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FS-1502</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FS-1502</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug: FS-1502 Dose-Escalation Phase (Phase 1a) - FS-1502 Dose-escalation will be proceeded on standard 3+3 design with starting dose of 0.1 mg/kg, IV, once per 28 days, 28 days as a cycle.
Dose level 1: 0.1 mg/kg; Dose level 2: 0.2 mg/kg; Dose level 3: 0.4 mg/kg; Dose level 4: 0.6 mg/kg; Dose level 5: 0.8 mg/kg; Dose level 6: 1.0 mg/kg; Dose level 7: 1.3 mg/kg.
Dose-expansion Phase (Phase 1b) -RP2D determined in phase 1a, IV, once per 28 days, 28 days as a cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FS-1502</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥18 years and ≤ 70 years at the time of study registration (men and women
             eligible);

          2. Phase Ia dose-escalation study:

             Patients with HER2 expressed advanced malignant solid tumor had failed to standard
             therapy (including surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy or biotherapy), or no
             standard therapy is available.

               1. HER2 overexpression: IHC3+, IHC2+/FISH+, or FISH+

               2. HER2 low expression: IHC1+, IHC2+/FISH-

             Phase Ib dose-expanded study:

             Histologically or cytologically confirmed breast cancer patients who have failed to
             prior trastuzumab treatment. Including patients with locally advanced or metastatic
             breast cancer and those who have relapsed after standard adjuvant chemotherapy
             (treatment for more than 3 months). Details as follows:

               1. HER2 positive (defined as IHC3+ or IHC2+/FISH+);

               2. At least one standard trastuzumab treatment or other biosimilar has been received
                  and the treatment failed.

               3. Provide evidence of disease progression or intolerable toxicity as confirmed by
                  the investigator or medical history recorded prior to enrollment.

             The enrollment can be based on written HER2 test report from certified local lab, but
             sufficient paraffin sections or fresh tumor tissue specimens must be provided to the
             central laboratory for confirmation.

          3. The ECOG performance status must be 0 or 1.

          4. Expected survival for at least 12 weeks.

          5. Has adequate organ and bone marrow function: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥
             1.5x109/L; hemoglobin ≥ 90g/L (without red blood cell infusion within 14 days);
             platelet count ≥ 100x109/L; Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5x upper limit normal (ULN), or ≤ 3x
             ULN if with Gilbert syndrome; aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5x ULN; AST and ALT ≤ 5x ULN if liver metastasis; Serum
             creatinine &lt; 1.5x ULN and creatinine clearance ≥ 60mL/min (Cockroft-Gault formula
             calculation); albumin ≥ 3g/dL; left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;50%.

          6. Has at least one measurable lesion by RECIST version 1.1.

          7. Male or female patients with fertility must agree to use effective contraceptive
             methods during the study period and within 30 days of the last dose of study therapy,
             such as dual barrier contraceptive methods, condoms, oral or injectable
             contraceptives, and intrauterine devices.

          8. Ability to understand and voluntarily sign written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who received chemotherapy, radiotherapy, major surgery or other anti-tumor
             treatment within 4 weeks prior to the start of dosing.

          2. Patients who have participated in other clinical trials 4 weeks before the start of
             study drug administration or within 5 drug half-life periods; patients who have
             received similar treatments.

          3. Uncontrolled central nervous system metastasis or injury (Patients who have been
             treated with gamma knife and have a stable disease for more than 3 months are allowed
             to enroll).

          4. Patients with uncontrolled diabetes mellitus (Patients who are receiving an insulin
             regimen or a hypoglycemic regimen and are evaluated as having good glycemic control by
             a specialist are allowed to enroll).

          5. Has not recovered from previous anti-tumor treatment-related toxic reactions (&gt;
             NCI-CITCAE 5.0 Grade 2), except for hair loss. The neurotoxicity of patients who have
             previously received chemotherapy needs to be restored to NCI-CTCAE 5.0 level 2 or
             below.

          6. Patients who have used potent CYP3A inhibitors within 14 days prior to the start of
             dosing (Boprevir, cobaster, cognac, dannoprevir and ritonavir (j), ethiravir and
             ritonavir (j), indinavir and ritonavir ( j), posaconazole and ritonavir (j), lopinavir
             and ritonavir (j), saquinavir and ritonavir (j), telanavir and ritonavir (j), parylene
             and ritonavir and (obivir and or dasab) (j), grapefruit, itraconazole, ketoconazole,
             telaprevir, vinegar Orchard, voriconazole, clarithromycin, diltiazem, aldelis,
             nefazodone, nelfinavir) or strong inducer (carbamazepine, enzalutamide, mitoxantrone,
             phenytoin, rifampicin, St. John's wort, etc.); P-gp transporter inducer or inhibitor;
             (j) indicates inhibition of CYP3A when in combination with ritonavir.

          7. Patients who are taking medications that prolong the QTc interval (mainly Ia, Ic, and
             III antiarrhythmic drugs) or patients with risk factors for QTc interval prolongation,
             such as uncorrectable hypokalemia, hereditary long QT syndrome. Drugs that potentially
             prolong the QTc interval can be found at
             https://crediblemeds.org/index.php/tools/pdfdownload?f=cql_en

          8. Cardiac function and disease meeting one of the following conditions:

               1. Three 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) measurements at the research center during
                  the screening period. Calculate the average of three measurements based on the
                  QTc formula, QTc &gt; 470 milliseconds.

               2. New York Heart Association (NYHA) graded ≥3 congestive heart failure.

               3. Clinically significant arrhythmias, including but not limited to complete left
                  bundle branch conduction abnormality, II degree atrioventricular block.

          9. Pregnant or lactating woman.

         10. Allergic to any excipients of FS-1502.

         11. Clinically significant active bacterial, fungal or viral infections, including
             hepatitis B (hepatitis B virus surface antigen positive and hepatitis B virus DNA over
             1000 IU/ml) or hepatitis C (hepatitis C virus RNA positive), human immunodeficiency
             virus infection ( HIV positive).

         12. Any other disease or condition of clinical significance (eg, active or uncontrollable
             infection, etc.) considered by investigator that may affect protocol compliance or
             affect patient signature of ICF.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>BINGHE XU, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Center/Cancer Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>BINGHE XU, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>010-87788826</phone>
    <email>xubingheBM@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>QIAO LI, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>18500027849</phone>
    <email>Liqiaopumc@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

