<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03940716</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00104549</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23DA039341</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03940716</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Project IntERact Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>M-Health to Decrease Youth Substance Misuse &amp; High-Risky Illegal Firearm Behaviors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will use a randomized control trial design (RCT) to pilot test a multisession
      remote therapy behavioral intervention for risky firearm behaviors and associated
      behaviors/consequences among adolescents. The study will pilot a state-of-the-art
      intervention delivery approaches (e.g., remote therapy, smartphone-based APP intervention
      content delivery) for reducing violence and associated behaviors among urban youth. Given the
      significant morality and mortality associated with firearm violence, the study will have
      significant impact by identifying optimal intervention strategies for future large-scale
      behavioral intervention trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this pilot study is to pilot test an m-health intervention, as compared
      to enhanced usual care [n=70; 35/group], with eligible youth to assess intervention
      acceptability, feasibility, and fidelity, as well as trends towards decreased risky firearm
      behaviors, substance use, and criminal justice involvement. Specifically, 70 youth (ages
      16-24) in the ED screening positive for firearm carriage and smartphone ownership will be
      randomly assigned (stratified by age/gender) to either the IntERact group or the control
      group. IntERact group participants will receive an Emergency Department (ED) session of
      behavioral therapy, followed by five additional remote therapy sessions of behavioral therapy
      delivered over the 5 weeks following their ED visit. Behavioral therapy will be comprised of
      motivational interviewing (MI), cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), and strengths-based care
      management (CM). In addition, youth in the IntERact group will also receive a smartphone APP
      that will be downloaded to their phone. The APP will deliver daily surveys, daily tailored MI
      and CBT messages in response to survey results, one-touch access to pro-social supports,
      psycho-educational materials, GPS-enabled message alerts, and facilitated access to CM
      resources. Youth enrolled in the control group will receive a pamphlet with local violence,
      substance use, and mental health resources. A follow-up assessment will be completed in each
      group at 4 months post-ED visit. Pilot data will aid in refining and clarifying content and
      clinical trial design elements for a future fully powered randomized control trial of the
      intervention (i.e., R01 proposal).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 27, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability: enrollment rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability will be measured at baseline using study enrollment rates</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Satisfaction (Helpfulness/Likability)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Participant satisfaction measures of helpfulness and likability will be assessed for individual intervention sessions and content (measured during post-tests after each session and at the 4-month follow-up).
Measures have been used in prior work (Walton 2010) and each item is scored on a 5-point likert scale (1=not at all; 5=extremely) with % of enrolled patients who completed sessions reporting scores of 4 or 5 reporting high likability or helpfulness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Daily Assessments: completion rates of daily assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Post-Intervention (~5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be measured during the course of the study by examining completion rates of daily assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Remote Sessions: Completion rates for Remote Therapy Sessions</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Post-Intervention (~5 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Completion rates for Remote Therapy Sessions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of 4-month follow-ups: % of eligible enrolled youth who complete follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>4-month Follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Completion rates for 4-month follow-up assessments (i.e., % of eligible enrolled youth who complete follow-up).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fidelity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4-month Follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Fidelity will be measured using standard therapy adherence measures coding audio tapings of remote therapy sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Risky Firearm Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4-month Follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Composite measure used in prior work (Carter 2019). Composite measure uses items from the Tulane University Youth Study and Conflict Tactics Scale capturing frequency and severity of firearm-related behaviors (e.g., carriage, threats, use, etc.). Items will be summed to create a summary score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Violence</condition>
  <condition>Substance Use</condition>
  <condition>Criminal Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IntERact</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this condition will receive behavioral therapy comprised of motivational interviewing, cognitive behavioral skills therapy, and care management. Youth will receive a total of six sessions, one delivered in the emergency department at the time of recruitment and five delivered over the five subsequent weeks after the ED visit (i.e., baseline). Participants will also receive a smartphone APP that will deliver intervention content between therapy sessions, including tailored MI+CBT messages (tailored by daily survey responses), one-touch pro-social contact, psycho-educational materials, GPS-enabled &quot;just-in-time&quot; tailored alerts, and facilitated access to care management resources.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Usual Care Condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this condition will receive a pamphlet with violence, mental health, and substance use resources.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IntERact</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention integrates motivational interviewing, cognitive behavioral skills therapy, and care management into a single behavioral counseling intervention delivered by a therapist. The intervention is delivered either in the emergency department or remotely over the subsequent 5 weeks for a total of six therapy sessions (~30 min each). A smartphone app is also loaded on the participant's phone and delivers additional behavioral intervention content, including tailored MI+CBT messages (tailored by daily survey responses), one-touch pro-social contact encouragement, psycho-educational materials, GPS-enabled &quot;just-in-time&quot; tailored alerts, and facilitated access to care management resources.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IntERact</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Past 4-month firearm carriage

          -  Ownership of a smartphone with APP capabilities

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-english speaking patients

          -  Patients unable to provide informed consent due to mental incompetence, incarceration
             (i.e., active police custody), medically unstable (abnormal vital signs requiring
             urgent resuscitation)

          -  Patients presenting for acute suicidal ideation or acute suicide attempt, child abuse
             or sexual assault.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrick M Carter, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>734-647-6125</phone>
    <email>cartpatr@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kaneesha Wallace, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>734-615-3044</phone>
    <email>kaneeshw@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hurley Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Flint</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick Carter</last_name>
      <phone>734-647-6125</phone>
      <email>cartpatr@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Patrick Carter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Emergency Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

