<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03940339</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMDU/IEC/1369</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1232-1359</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03940339</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Suboccipitalis Myofascial Release in Hamstring Tightness in Patients With Anterolisthesis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Suboccipital Muscle Myofascial Release on Hamstring Muscle Length, Pain and Disability in Patients With Anterolisthesis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asir John Samuel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maharishi Markendeswar University (Deemed to be University)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Anterolisthesis presents with tightness of hamstring muscle which is a major contributing
      factor for low back pain and disability. Suboccipital Myofascial release decreases the
      tension in the fascia and helps to amend the muscle imbalance. There is a presence of
      superficial backline between suboccipitalis and hamstring muscle.

      Aim:

      The purpose of the study is to find out the effect of sub occipital myofascial release on
      hamstring tightness along with pain and disability associated with it in Anterolisthesis.

      Methods:

      The study will recruit individuals with Anterolisthesis between the age of 35- 55.
      Pathologies which will limit or interfere with the test outcome shall be excluded. The
      samples will be collected using criterion based sampling. Procedure will be explained prior
      to the intervention

      Data analysis:

      Normality of the collected data will be established by Shapiro Wilk Test. Based on the
      normality, descriptive statistics data will be expressed as mean ± standard deviation or
      median and intra quartile range. Within group comparison will be done by paired t test or
      Wilcoxon signed rank test and between group comparison will be done through independent t
      test or Mann Whitney U test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Introduction:

           Anterolisthesis refers to an anterior displacement of a vertebra over subjacent vertebra
           causing low back pain, radiculopathy and hamstring tightness. Hamstring tightness causes
           improper patterns in the lumbopelvic region. There is a dura matter which connects
           suboccipitalis and hamstring muscle and reduction in the tone of suboccipitalis will
           thus cause decrease in tone of hamstring muscle. Myofascial release is a manipulative
           treatment that attempts to release tension in fascia and has an effect to decrease
           soreness of muscle.

           1.1.Problem statement: Generally in patients with anterolisthesis a single component is
           considered as a treatment, this study thus aims to be a bridge filling the gap in the
           scientific cognizance

           1.2.Purpose of the study:The target of the study is to see the outcome of sub
           occipitalis myofascial release on tightness of hamstring muscle, pain and disability.

           1.3.Objectives of the study: To evaluate the efficacy of suboccipital myofascial release
           and conventional physiotherapy treatment in tightness of hamstring muscle, pain and
           disability

        2. Procedure:

      Total male (n) and female (n) patients between the age of 35 and 55 years with grade 1 and 2
      Anterolisthesis will be selected on the basis of inclusion and exclusion criteria. The
      suitable sample will be randomly allocated into 2 groups - experimental and control group
      respectively. The popliteal angle test will be carried out to assess hamstring length and
      modified oswestry disability index will be used to quantify disability for low back pain.
      Visual analogue scale will be used to measure intensity of pain. All the necessary measures
      will be taken among the participants of experimental group.The MFR technique will be given in
      the upper cervical region with the patient in supine position. The MFR will be given for
      three repetitions per session, three times per week for the period of four weeks. The control
      group will be receiving conventional physiotherapy treatment for hamstring tightness which
      includes static stretching, modified hold-relax stretching and contract relax technique.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Due to COVID-19 lockdown
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 19, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 18, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two group pretest posttest randomized control design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Single blinded participants will be recruited</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Popliteal Angle Test</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Popliteal angle is an assessment of the tone of the hamstring muscles. The thigh is flexed on the abdomen with one hand and then the other hand straightens the leg by pushing on the back of the ankle until there is firm resistance to the movement. Popliteal angle is measured in degrees.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Oswerstry Disability Index</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It is an extremely important tool used to measure a patient's permanent functional disability. The total score range from 0-50.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analogue Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It is a quantifying instrument for subjective characteristics or attitudes of pain that cannot be directly measured. The total score range from 0-10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Anterolisthesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Suboccipital myofascial release</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment will be given for 3 minutes, 3 days per week for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Coventional Physiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment will be given for 3 days per week for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Suboccipital myofascial release</intervention_name>
    <description>The MFR technique will be given in the upper cervical region with the patient in supine position. The MFR will be given for three repetitions per session, three times per week for the period of four weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Suboccipital myofascial release</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Physiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group will be receiving conventional physiotherapy treatment for hamstring tightness which includes static stretching, modified hold-relax stretching and contract relax technique.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Coventional Physiotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        Patients aged between 35-55 years Both male and female Individuals with Hamstring tightness
        Individual with Anterolisthesis Individual with pain and disability

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Individuals with neck pain Patients with history of neck trauma Fracture of lower limb
        Cervical ligament instability Spinal fractures in the past 6 months Open wounds and skin
        allergies in the back
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bishaka Pradhan, BPT, (MPT)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Musculoskeletal Physiotherapy, MMIPR</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maharishi Markandeshwar Hospital, Mullana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ambala</city>
        <state>Haryana</state>
        <zip>133207</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vatsal DK, Kainth R, Kainth R, Husain PM. Original Article A clinico-etiological study of spondylolisthesis in north Indian population. Int J Med Sci Clin Invent. 2017;4(5):2884-7.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maharishi Markendeswar University (Deemed to be University)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Asir John Samuel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Supervisor and Associate Professor, Department of Pediatric and Neonatal Physiotherapy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hamstring muscles</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain measurement</keyword>
  <keyword>Low back pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spondylolisthesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>It is not yet decided</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

