<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03947970</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR845-100302</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03947970</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics and Metabolism of [14C] CR845 (Difelikefalin) in Patients With End Stage Renal Disease on Hemodialysis and in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Single-Dose Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics and Metabolism of [14C] CR845 in Patients With End Stage Renal Disease on Hemodialysis and in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cara Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cara Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this study are to evaluate the in vivo metabolite profiling and
      characterization of CR845 administered intravenously (IV) in patients on hemodialysis (HD)
      and in healthy subjects; and to determine the pharmacokinetics of radiolabeled [14C] CR845
      administered as a single IV bolus in patients on HD and in healthy subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, open-label, single-radiolabeled dose, non-randomized study in 6 male
      patients on HD and 6 healthy male subjects. The study will consist of a Screening Period, a
      Study Period, and an End-of-Study assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 6, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 6, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of the [14C] CR845 and total radioactivity (total [14C] CR845-equivalents) in plasma, urine, feces, and dialysate will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to up to 7 days post dose in healthy volunteers and Day 1 to up to 14 days post dose in patients on HD</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of recovery of [14C] CR845 and radioactivity related to [14C] CR845 in plasma, urine, feces, and dialysate, as applicable, will be derived.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to up to 7 days post dose in healthy volunteers and Day 1 to up to 14 days post dose in patients on HD</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative amount of [14C] CR845 and [14C] CR845-equivalents in urine and feces over the collection period will be calculated.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to up to 7 days post dose in healthy volunteers and Day 1 to up to 14 days post dose in patients on HD</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of possible CR845 metabolites will be assessed.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to up to 7 days post dose in healthy volunteers and Day 1 to up to 14 days post dose in patients on HD</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitation of possible CR845 metabolites will be assessed.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to up to 7 days post dose in healthy volunteers and Day 1 to up to 14 days post dose in patients on HD</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and severity of adverse events by treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to up to 7 days post dose in healthy volunteers and Day 1 to up to 14 days post dose in patients on HD</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemodialysis</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>[14C] CR845</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single dose of [14C] CR845 IV solution administered as an IV bolus on Day 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[14C] CR845</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single dose of 230 mcg CR845 solution containing 100 microcuries [14C] CR845, administered via IV bolus (the total dose of CR845 will range from 1.7 to 3.1 mcg/kg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>[14C] CR845</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria for Healthy Subjects

          -  Body mass index (BMI) within the range of 18 to 30 kg/m2, inclusive, and body weight
             not less than 75 kg;

          -  Vital signs at Screening must be within the following ranges and stable (measured in
             sitting position after at least 5 minutes' rest);

               -  Systolic blood pressure (SBP) ≥100 and ≤140 mmHg;

               -  Diastolic blood pressure (DBP) ≥50 and ≤90 mmHg;

               -  Heart rate (HR) ≥50 and ≤100 beats per minute (bpm).

          -  Must be in good health as determined by past medical history, physical examination,
             ECG, vital sign assessments, and clinical laboratory tests at Screening. Any subjects
             with abnormalities noted at Screening or at any time before dosing on Day 1 must be
             approved by the Investigator and Medical Monitor.

        Key Inclusion Criteria for patients on HD

          -  If taking concurrent medications, must be on a stable dose for at least 14 days prior
             to dosing and the dosing regimen should remain stable for the duration of the study;

          -  Prescription dry body weight of ≥75 kg and ≤135 kg at Screening;

          -  Must be receiving HD 3 times weekly and have been on dialysis for at least 3 months
             prior to Screening;

          -  For a minimum of 1 month before Day 1, must have stable controlled blood pressure that
             in the Investigator's opinion will not interfere with study conduct;

          -  Demonstrated adequate dialysis measurements (at least two Kt/V measurements ≥1.2 or
             two urea reduction ratio [URR] measurements ≥65%) during the 3 months prior to
             Screening

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has a concomitant disease or any medical condition that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, could pose undue risk to the patient, impede completion of the study
             procedures, or would compromise the validity of the study measurements, including, but
             not limited to:

               -  Known or suspected history of alcohol, narcotic, or other drug abuse, or
                  substance dependence within 12 months prior to Screening;

               -  Significant systolic or diastolic heart failure (eg, New York Heart Association
                  Class IV congestive heart failure [Appendix 1]);

               -  Severe mental illness or cognitive impairment (eg, dementia);

               -  Any other relevant acute or chronic medical or neuropsychiatric condition.

          -  History of important drug or other allergy (except for untreated, asymptomatic
             seasonal allergies at time of dosing) unless deemed not clinically significant by the
             Investigator;

          -  Use of any beverages and foods containing alcohol, quinine (tonic water), grapefruit,
             broccoli, Brussels sprouts, Seville oranges, pomegranate, star fruit, char-grilled
             meat, or caffeine/xanthine from 48 hours prior to dosing with study medication without
             evaluation and approval by the Investigator;

          -  Use of any over-the-counter (OTC) medication (including nutritional or dietary
             supplements, herbal preparations, or vitamins, chapparal, comfrey, germander, gin bu
             huan, kava, pennyroyal, skullcap, St. John's Wort, or valerian) within 7 days prior to
             dosing with study medication;

          -  Use of any new prescription medication from 14 days prior to dosing with study
             medication without evaluation and approval by the Investigator;

          -  Has been treated with any known drugs that are moderate or strong inhibitors/inducers
             of cytochrome P450 (CYP) enzymes (e.g., barbiturates, phenothiazines, cimetidine,
             carbamazepine) within 30 days prior to dosing with study medication, and that, in the
             Investigator's judgment, may impact subject safety or the validity of the study
             results;

          -  Positive results for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or hepatitis B surface antigen
             (HBsAg);

          -  Is a healthy subject with positive results for hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody at
             Screening. Note: Subjects with HD who test positive for HCV antibody may be allowed to
             enroll at the discretion of the Principal Investigator if their liver function tests
             are not otherwise clinically significant;

          -  Has donated blood or has had an acute loss of blood (˃500 mL) during the 3 months
             prior to study drug administration;

          -  Previous administration of any [14C] labeled drug substance within 1 year of study
             drug administration;

          -  Has irregular bowel habits. &quot;Irregular&quot; being defined for the purpose of this study as
             NOT having a bowel movement at least every 2 days.)

          -  Has been involved in an occupation that requires monitoring for radiation exposure
             (eg, X-ray technician);
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frédérique Menzaghi, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cara Therapeutics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cara Therapeutics Study Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78217</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 13, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Difelikefalin</keyword>
  <keyword>Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>CR845</keyword>
  <keyword>CKD</keyword>
  <keyword>ESRD (end stage renal disease)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

