<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03949153</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03949153</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cryotherapy With in Situ Immunotherapy in Melanoma Metastasis</brief_title>
  <acronym>CRIRIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Cryotherapy Under Interventional Radiology Combined With in Situ Ipilimumab and a Flat Dose of Nivolumab in Stage IIIB/C Melanoma. Prospective Proof of Concept Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Strasbourg, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Strasbourg, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Melanoma is the deadliest form of skin cancer and its incidence has doubled every 20 years in
      France, where this cancer is responsible of more than 1600 deaths each year.

      Patients with early diagnosis have good prognosis and can be generally cured by surgery only.
      Advanced melanoma however has a very bad prognosis.

      Loco-regional lymph nodes are usually the first distant localization in metastatic melanoma.
      Lymph node dissection is then the recommended treatment, although it's impact on survival has
      never been proven.

      In the same way, the benefit risk profile of interferon as adjuvant treatment after lymph
      node dissection is still much debated.

      Recently, new treatments either with immunotherapy (ipilimumab, nivolumab) or by the targeted
      therapy dabrafenib/trametinib in patients with BRAF mutation have shown an impact on survival
      in the adjuvant setting after lymph node dissection.

      But, it has not yet been established if this strategy has a benefit gain compared to starting
      those treatments only in the metastatic setting after watchful follow-up.

      Moreover, if these novel therapies (targeted therapies: TT, immunotherapies : IT)
      demonstrated for the first time a real benefit in terms of survival or of responses rates in
      melanoma, physicians and patients had to address new problems, such as the management of
      unusual adverse events.

      Partial and dissociated responses can also be seen with those new treatments. Some patients
      will have complete response in some lesions, stabilization in others and progression in a
      few. It is to be expected that one of the real key points of this therapy is to be found
      here, as this situation is commonly seen, and it would probably be a poor choice to stop a
      treatment that is globally effective for progression of only 1 or 2 lesions, in a patient
      otherwise stabilized.

      That is the context in which interventional radiology (IR) should be considered as an
      extremely efficient option. IR is a real medical revolution in the last 2 decades.

      It provides not only the opportunity to determine the characteristics of residual lesion
      (fibrosis, necrosis, metastasis, or sarcoidosis,…) by biopsy, but allows also their targeted
      destruction through different technics (cryotherapy, radiofrequency, laser,…).

      The investigators are fortunate to have in their institution one of the best IR department of
      the world (headed by Prof. Afshin GANGI), with a technical platform unique in Europe that
      allows IR through ultrasound, scan, petscan and MRI.

      To the best of their knowledge, Immunotherapy associated with IR has not been performed so
      far.

      This association could in theory:

        1. Combine immunotherapy with tumoral necrosis, which inherently increases the effects of
           immunotherapy by massive tumoral leakage of danger signals and tumoral antigens;

        2. Allow direct injection in targeted zones, where the beneficial effect is desired, and
           thus increase the expected immune response;

        3. Reduce side effects related to immunotherapy, by reducing quantities injected; which
           seems particularly important in the (neo)-adjuvant setting.

      That's why the investigators are willing to conduct this pilot project, the objectives of
      which are:

        1. Providing a proof of the feasibility of this association,

        2. Obtaining preliminary insights on the effects on non-targeted lesions,

        3. Adding a translational research to establish the effect on tumor antigenic expression
           and the immune response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of failures linked to the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (cryoablation) or Day 2 (ipilimumab injection)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of failures linked to the procedure, from all causes (unless the patient changes his/her mind = withdrawal from the study). In the context of this study, failure is defined as follows:
Technically impossible to perform the cryoablation procedure, or
Impossible to inject at least 2 ml of ipilimumab into the treated lymphadenopathy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of target and non-targeted lymphadenopathies</measure>
    <time_frame>before (inclusion visit) and 4 to 7 weeks after the procedure (V5 visit).</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall and progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>All along the study, until the end of study visit (6 months after the procedure)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall and progression-free survival of this cohort with a recent historical cohort (similar patients at stages IIIB/C treated in the dermatology clinic 1 year earlier).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 0 to the end of study visit (6 months after the procedure)</time_frame>
    <description>Number, nature and severity of adverse events and serious adverse events (according to NCI CTCAE) related to immune therapy and cryoablation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma (Skin)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single Nivolumab 240 mg infusion at D0, followed by cryotherapy using interventional radiology of metastatic lymphadenopathy at D1 and in situ injection with ipilimumab at D2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab 10 MG/ML Intravenous Solution [OPDIVO]</intervention_name>
    <description>Single Nivolumab 240 mg infusion at D0</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cryotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Cryotherapy using interventional radiology of metastatic lymphadenopathy at D1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>In situ injection with ipilimumab at D2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject with previously treated (or unknown) primary stage IIIB/IIIC melanoma with
             lymph node metastases, with at least one ≥1 cm3 that is accessible to cryotherapy
             under interventional radiology (IR), assessed at the inclusion visit (V1).

          2. ECOG performance status (0 to 2) at the selection visit (V0)

          3. Woman or man of reproductive age with no desire to procreate for the duration of their
             participation in the study, agreeing to use a highly effective contraception method*,
             with at least one barrier method (condom or diaphragm), and for 5 months after the
             infusion of Nivolumab for women and 7 months for men

          4. Leukocytes &gt;2000/mm3, neutrophils &gt;1500/mm3, platelets &gt;100,000/mm3, haemoglobin
             &gt;9g/dl at the selection visit (V0)

          5. Total bilirubin &lt;1.5 mg/dl except for patients with Gilbert's syndrome who may have
             total bilirubin &lt;3.0 mg/dl at the selection visit (V0)

          6. Liver function: SGOT, SGPT, ALP &lt;2.5 N, if liver metastases SGOT and SGPT &lt;5 N at the
             selection visit (V0)

          7. Serum creatinine &lt;1.5 N or creatinine clearance &gt;40 ml/min (using the Cockcroft-Gault
             equation) at the selection visit (V0)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy (women of childbearing potential : positive blood pregnancy test at the
             selection visit (V0) or breastfeeding

          2. History of hypersensitivity to ipilimumab, nivolumab or one of the excipients

          3. History of severe hypersensitivity to a monoclonal antibody

          4. History of positive tests for HIV or Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (HIV assessed
             at the selection visit (V0))

          5. Positive tests for HCV or HBV indicating an acute or chronic infection at the
             selection visit (V0)

          6. Patient presenting with an active, known or suspected autoimmune disease. The
             following, however, may participate:

               -  patient with type 1 diabetes or hypothyroidism requiring substitute hormone
                  therapy only;

               -  patient with psoriasis, vitiligo or alopecia;

               -  patient with conditions that are not known to reoccur without an exogenous
                  triggering agent.

          7. History of active neoplasia during the last 3 years with the exception of localised
             curable cancers considered to be cured, such as basal or squamous cell carcinomas,
             superficial bladder cancer and prostate, colon or breast carcinoma in situ.

          8. Active systemic infection

          9. Patient with a condition requiring systemic steroid treatment (at a dose &gt;10
             mg/prednisone equivalent or at unstable dose) or another immunosuppressant
             within/following 14 days of study drugs administration. Inhaled steroids and treatment
             for adrenal insufficiency, however, are permitted.

         10. Contraindication for the cryotherapy procedure as assessed by the radiologist (due to
             tumour size or proximity to a vascular or nerve structure giving the procedure an
             unacceptable level of risk) at the inclusion visit (V1)

         11. Clotting disorder that may interfere with the cryoablation, assessed at the selection
             visit (V0)

         12. Contraindication for MRI with gadolinium-based contrast media

         13. History of uveal melanoma

         14. Patient having received prior treatment for their melanoma, in particular, patient
             previously treated with interferon fewer than 3 months ago or with an anti-PD-1,
             anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti-CD-137 or anti-CTLA-4 antibody. Patients who have
             undergone primary melanoma surgery and the excision of in-transit metastases, as well
             as adjuvant therapy with interferon if completed over 3 months ago are eligible.

         15. Contraindication for general and/or local anaesthesia

         16. Patient operated on under general anaesthesia, within the 4 weeks prior to the planned
             Nivolumab infusion.

         17. Patient operated on epidural anaesthesia, within the 72 h prior to the planned
             Nivolumab infusion.

         18. History of anterior organ transplantation, including allograft stem cell
             transplantation.

         19. History of interstitial lung disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dan LIPSKER, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dan LIPSKER, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 3 88 11 61 79</phone>
    <email>dan.lipsker@chru-strasbourg.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique Dermatologique/Radiologie Interventionnelle/Urologie/Gynécologie-Hôpitaux Universitaires de Strasbourg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <zip>67091</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dan LIPSKER, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 3 88 11 61 79</phone>
      <email>dan.lipsker@chru-strasbourg.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cédric LENORMAND</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Nicolas SCRIVENER</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guillaume HAZEMANN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Afshin GANGI</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julien GARNON</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean CAUDRELIER</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roberto Luigi CAZATTO</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pierre AULOGE</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guillaume KOCH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alice KIENY</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hervé LANG</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mousselim GHARBI</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dan LIPSKER</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lise LECOINTRE</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ipilimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

