<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03517917</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATX-TBL-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03517917</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Tissue Collection Research Protocol</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Tissue Collection Research Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Achilles Therapeutics Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Achilles Therapeutics Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to collect matched donor tissue and blood to enable the development of a
      manufacturing process for potential immunotherapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study intends to collect blood and tumour samples from consenting patients for the
      development of manufacturing processes for potential immunotherapies.

      Visit 1: Suitable patients will provide consent at the first patient visit, followed by
      baseline assessments as per standard of care and per protocol. Details will also be collected
      about current medical conditions and procedures and current medications. Patients will be
      tested for infectious diseases e.g. Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Human T-cell
      lymphotropic virus (HTLV), Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C and Syphilis.

      Visit 2: Procured tumour samples will be obtained during the patients standard of care
      surgery, or the patient may provide a superficial skin or subcutaneous lymph node disease
      sample strictly for the purposes of the trial. All patients will also donate a whole blood
      sample conducted as a non-standard of care procedure.

      All donated samples will be couriered to a specialist Sponsor laboratory with appropriate
      oversight maintained.

      Visit 3: Following the surgical procedure patients will receive their standard follow up
      care. Under this protocol a follow up telephone call will be made to ensure patients have
      recovered fully.

      For those patients who do not plan to undergo the leukapheresis procedure, visit 3 concludes
      the patients study participation.

      Visit 3 may also serve as a re-confirmation of eligibility to undergo leukapheresis if the
      procedure is planned within 14 days of visit 2.

      Visit 4: For those patients planned to undergo leukapheresis greater than 28 days post visit
      2, this visit should be conducted as a re-confirmation of eligibility.

      Visit 5: The leukapheresis procedure is conducted, providing the patient consents and is
      deemed fit by their treating physician to undergo the procedure.

      Visit 6: A leukapheresis safety follow up visit is conducted. For those patients who undergo
      leukapheresis visit 6 concludes the patients participation in the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 8, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Obtaining samples for research</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>This protocol does not have an analysis primary outcome measure but rather will be conducted in accordance with Good Clinical Practice (GCP), solely for the purpose of obtaining samples for research.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Tumour tissue collection and blood collection to enable a manufacturing process for immunotherapies to be developed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumour tissue collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Collection of tumour tissue and blood</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blood collection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with solid tumour scheduled for either biopsy or resection of their tumour(s) as
        part of their standard of care, and patients with superficial skin or subcutaneous lymph
        node metastasis that can be safely accessed for the purposes of the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient must be at least 18 years old at the Screening Visit.

          2. Written informed patient consent for tissue, blood collection or leukapheresis,
             including storage and manipulation.

          3. Suspected or confirmed diagnosis of non-small cell lung cancer, melanoma, renal
             cancer, head and neck or triple negative breast cancer with either primary, recurrent
             or metastatic disease.

          4. Patient is scheduled for surgical excision and/or collection of multiple tissue
             samples via image or device guided biopsy, has a superficial skin or subcutaneous
             lymph node metastasis that can be safely accessed for the purposes of the study.

          5. Haemoglobin(Hb) ≥ 10g/dL without transfusion support for at least 3 weeks.

          6. White cell count ≥ 3 x 10^9/L

          7. Negative laboratory test for blood borne pathogens (see exclusion criterion).

          8. Non Small Cell Cancer (NSCLC) patients should be current or ex-smokers.

        Additional criteria for patients undergoing leukapheresis to be tested within 14 days of
        leukapheresis as per standard local procedures:

          1. Haematocrit (HCT)&gt;38%.

          2. Hb ≥ 10g/dL without transfusion support for at least 3 weeks.

          3. White Blood Cells (WBC) ≥ 3.0 x 109/L.

          4. Neutrophils ≥ 1.0 x 109/L.

          5. Platelets ≥50 x 109/L.

          6. No coagulopathy and PT and APTT &lt; 1.5x ULN.

          7. Albumen &gt;20g/l.

          8. AST or ALT ≤ 2.5x ULN.

          9. Bilirubin &lt; 1.5x ULN (&lt; 3x ULN in Gilbert's Syndrome).

         10. Creatinine clearance/estimated GFR ≥ 60 mL/min.

         11. Blood Pressure ≥110/70mmHg and &lt;160/100mmHg.

         12. Weight &gt;120lbs (8.5 stone/ 55 kg).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinical status precludes surgical removal of, or collection of multiple biopsies
             from, accessible tumour tissue.

          2. Inadequate peripheral venous access precluding collection of blood.

          3. Pregnant or breast feeding women.

          4. Patients with acral melanoma.

          5. Non Small Cell Cancer (NSCLC) patients with a known driver mutation in EGFR, ROS-1 or
             ALK.

          6. Renal cancer patients with predominantly chromophobe tumours.

          7. Known/laboratory confirmed diagnosis of an active infectious disease preventing
             inclusion of tissue into cell manufacturing suite.

          8. As a minimum, the patient will undergo specific screening for the following
             infections, including as a minimum serology for Hepatitis B and C, human
             immunodeficiency virus infection (HIV1/2), Human t-lymphotropic virus (HTLV I/II) and
             syphilis. Other tests may be performed per local site SOP's. If performed, any
             positive test results must be reported to the study sponsor.

          9. Patients who are currently participating in a clinical trial involving an unlicensed
             medical product.

         10. Patients who have received any anti-cancer therapy (including investigational
             products) within three weeks prior to tissue procurement.

         11. Patients receiving immunosuppressive treatments or who require regular treatment with
             steroids at a dose higher than prednisolone 10 mg/day (or equivalent).

         12. Any medical reason why, in the opinion of the investigator, the patient should not
             participate in this study.

         13. Patients who elect to undergo leukapheresis:

               1. must not have received any chemotherapy within 3 weeks prior to the procedure.

               2. must have no evidence of any skin infection at the time of the procedure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shreenal Patel, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0044 1438 906 854</phone>
    <email>info@achillestx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Achilles Investigator site 01</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shreenal Patel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 1438 906 854</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Achilles Investigator site 02</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shreenal Patel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 1438 906 854</phone>
      <email>info@achillestx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Achilles Investigator site 04</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shreenal Patel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 1438 906 854</phone>
      <email>info@achillestx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Achilles Investigator site 03</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shreenal Patel, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0044 1438 906 854</phone>
      <email>info@achillestx.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

