<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03887416</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAPA-ESR-16-12460</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-002125-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03887416</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Dapagliflozin on Nighttime Blood Pressure in Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Dapagliflozin on Nighttime Blood Pressure in Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>LM Diagnósticos S.L.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>LM Diagnósticos S.L.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Centres: Three university hospitals and the primary care centres in their area in Madrid
      (Clínico San Carlos, La Paz, 12 de Octubre) Type of study: Randomized, multicentric,
      placebo-controlled, single-blind pilot study Main outcome: Nighttime blood pressure in type 2
      diabetic patients Objective: To investigate the effect of the addition of 10 mg daily of
      dapagliflozin to the treatment of diabetic patients compared to the addition of placebo on
      the change in nighttime blood pressure (measured by ABPM) over 12 weeks among patients
      withalbuminuria levels ≥ 30 and &lt; 3000 mg/g creatinine and estimated glomerular filtration
      rate ≥ 60 mL/min/1.73 m2..

      Patients: 225 patients with a previous diagnosis of type 2 diabetes and eGFR&gt; 30mL/min
      x1,73m2, office BP above 140/70 mmHg, HbA1C 7.5-10%, albuminuria levels between 30 mg/g
      creatinine and 3000 mg/g creatinine and estimated glomerular filtration rate ≥ 60 mL/min/1.73
      m2.

      Intervention: 10 mg once daily of dapagliflozin or placebo resembling dapagliflozin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Effect of dapagliflozin on nighttime blood pressure in type 2 diabetes

      TYPE OF STUDY: Randomized, multicentric, placebo-controlled, single-blind pilot study.

      CENTRES: Three university hospitals and the primary care centres in their area in Madrid
      (Clínico San Carlos, La Paz, 12 de Octubre)

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      To investigate the effect of the addition of 10 mg daily of dapagliflozin to the treatment of
      diabetic patients compared to the addition of placebo on the change in nighttime blood
      pressure (measured by ABPM) over 12 weeks among patients with albuminuria levels ≥ 30 and &lt;
      3000 mg/g creatinine and estimated glomerular filtration rate ≥ 60 mL/min/1.73 m2.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

        -  To investigate the effect of the addition of 10 mg daily of dapagliflozin to the
           treatment of diabetic patients compared to the addition of placebo on the change in
           nighttime blood pressure (measured by ABPM) over 12 weeks in the subgroup of patients
           with high (30-300 mg/g creatinine) albuminuria levels.

        -  To investigate the effect of the addition of 10 mg daily of dapagliflozin to the
           treatment of diabetic patients compared to the addition of placebo on the change in
           nighttime blood pressure (measured by ABPM) over 12 weeks in the subgroup of patients
           with very high (&gt;300 mg/g creatinine) albuminuria levels.

        -  Changes in albuminuria, office BP and HBA1C in the two subgroups of patients
           investigated

      METHODS:

      This clinical trial will be conducted according to this Protocol, under the Regulation (EU)
      No 536/2014 and all regulatory requirements applicable to clinical trials and following the
      principles of Good Clinical Practice.

      PATIENTS:

      Type 2 diabetic patients recruited in the primary care setting in the area of three
      university hospitals in Madrid, irrespectively of the time since diagnosis and type of
      treatment received for their diabetes.

      DESCRIPTION OF THE INTERVENTION: The drug under evaluation, dapagliflozin, is approved to be
      used in adults who are 18 or older with type 2 diabetes mellitus for improving glycemic
      control and can be used in monotherapy when diet and exercise alone do not achieve good
      glycemic control and metformin use is not indicated due to intolerance, or in combination
      with other hypoglycemic agents, including insulin, when these, added to diet and exercise do
      not achieve good glycemic control. In this study it will be used in agreement with the terms
      in which its use is authorized.

      The participants in the study, in addition to the treatment for their diabetes that were
      receiving from their attending physician, will receive 10 mg once daily of dapagliflozin or
      placebo resembling dapagliflozinin. The randomization scheme follows below.

      RANDOMIZATION:

      Two strata will be considered based on albuminuria levels:

        -  High albuminuria (30-300 mg/g creatinine)

        -  Very high (&gt;300 mg/g creatinine) Patients will be randomized to either dapagliflozin or
           placebo in a 2:1 ratio.

      Total number of patients: 225; distributed as:

        -  150 diabetic patients treated with dapagliflozin (10mg/day in a single dose), half of
           them with high albuminuria levels (albuminuria 30-300 mg/g of creatinine) and half with
           very high albuminuria levels (albuminuria &gt; 300 mg/g of creatinine)

        -  75 diabetic patients treated with placebo, half of them with high albuminuria levels
           (albuminuria 30-300 mg/g of creatinine) and half with very high albuminuria levels
           (albuminuria &gt; 300 mg/g of creatinine) Randomization will be stratified by albuminuria
           strata and participating hospital (three hospitals); center specific randomization lists
           (active treatment or placebo) will be prepared centrally at the project office with a
           treatment code assigned to each patient. Allocation will be concealed by means of
           sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes that contain the medication code
           assigned. The envelopes have to be opened sequentially and only after the participant's
           name is written on the appropriate envelope.

      VISITS, VARIABLES AND MEASUREMENTS:

      Four clinical visits are planned in every patient at 0 (recruitment and randomization), 4, 8
      and 12 weeks. Information on personal and family history of disease, clinical examination
      (including office BP determination), ABPM and blood and urine samples will be obtained on
      visits 0. The variables measured in the blood and urine samples depend on the criterium of
      the attending physician. For this trial, only HbA1c, serum creatinine, estimated glomerular
      filtration rate (eGFR) and albuminuria are mandatory. All this information, except personal
      and family history of disease, will also be collected at week 12. Thirty days after the end
      of the medication (visit of week 12) all participants will be contacted by telephone to
      assess safety. For the initial laboratory data required in the CRF, data obtained in primary
      care in the previous 3 months could be valid. These data will be repeated at the end of the
      study. Informed consents for the study will be signed by the patients before coming to the
      hospital. Blood samples extractions included in this protocol will be done, handled and
      analyzed at each clinical setting according to usual clinical practice. No blood sample
      storage will be needed in this study.

      ABPM will be measured using Mobil-o-Graph that will give us 24 hours brachial and central BP
      as well as pulse wave velocity and heart rate. As diary of activity of the patient will not
      be recorded, in this study, nocturnal (or nighttime) blood pressure refers to measurements
      within the period from 12.00 p.m. to 6.00 a.m.

      SAMPLE SIZE CONSIDERATIONS: For the main objective of the study, changes in mean nocturnal
      systolic blood pressure will be compared between the active treatment and placebo groups.

      The use of SGLT2 inhibitors has been reported to be associated with reductions in office
      blood pressure of 4-8 mmHg, reductions that could be even higher with the use of ambulatory
      BP monitoring.15 Accepting an alpha error of 0.05 in a two-sided test, 150 patients are
      needed in the active treatment group and 75 in the placebo group (2:1 randomization) to have
      an 80% power (beta error=0.2) to detect as statistically significant a difference greater
      than or equal to 5 mmHg in mean nocturnal BP between placebo and active treatment
      (conservative estimate of the expected effect). The standard deviation is assumed to be 12
      mmHg and it is expected a drop-out rate of 9%.

      In the prespecifiedsubgroup analysis by albuminuria levels, this sample size (75 in active
      treatment and 37 in placebo) allows to detect as statistically significant, within each
      albuminuria stratum and with the same asumptions and alfa and beta errors, a difference
      greater than or equal to 7,1 mmHg in the reduction of mean nocturnal BP between both groups
      (active treatment and placebo), an effect still within what can be expected.

      DATA MANAGEMENT: Data will be collected in an electronic CRF by participating doctors and
      nurses both at the hypertension units and at primary care centers. A range of acceptable
      values and logical rules among variables will be implemented to improve quality of data and
      reduce the need of queries.

      The processing, communication and transfer of data will be in accordance with the provisions
      of the Organic Law 15/1999, December 13th, on the protection of personal data.

      Trial documentation will be kept and storaged in each site for 25 years after completion of
      the study.

      PLAN OF ANALYSIS: The main analysiswill compare baseline and final visit values of nocturnal
      blood pressure and all the rest of quantitative variables of interest within each stratum of
      albuminuria by means of paired t-test. Changes of nighttime blood pressure from baseline to
      final visit among patients with high and very high albuminuria levels will be compared to
      placebo with t-test.

      Variables will be described by means of mean (and standard deviation) or proportion depending
      on the type of variable considered. Whenever the test of hypothesis may involve discrete
      variables, chi-squared testwill be used.

      Comparability of treatment and placebo groups will be tested (t-student or chi-squared test,
      depending on the variable) to assess randomization, and linear regression will be used to
      adjust for potential confounders, if needed; stratum of albuminuria at randomization will be
      forced in the model.

      To respond to secondary objectives, the same analyses will be done for each stratum of
      albuminuria at randomization.

      Only patients that complete the 3-month follow-up will be analyzed. Patients who do not
      complete the follow-up will be compared to those who adhere to the protocol.

      No interim analysis is planned. A p value&lt;0.05 will be considered as statistically
      significant.

      END OF THE TRIAL:

      The trial will end with the last visit of the last patient recruited. The study may be
      terminated if the study procedures are not being performed according to Good Clinical
      Practice (GCP). The promotor also may terminate the entire study prematurely if concerns for
      safety arise within this study or in any other study with dapagliflozin.

      ETHICAL ISSUES:

      At the recruitment visit, all patients meeting criteria and invited to participate will
      receive adequate written information on the study and will have the opportunity to ask the
      investigator any question regarding their participation and will be given enough time to make
      a decision. Following all this, they will sign and date their acceptance to participate in it
      prior to randomization. This is a trial proposed as &quot;low level of intervention trial&quot; [&quot;RD
      1090/2015 de 4 de diciembre&quot;] and every participant will be covered by an insurance for this
      instances.

      This study will be done conforming to the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki and
      posterior amendments, Good Clinical Practice and the applicable legislation including the
      requirements of the Spanish law of data protection (&quot;Reglamento General de Protección de
      Datos (Reglamento (UE) 2016/679 del Parlamento Europeo y del Consejo, de 27 de abril de
      2016&quot;, &quot;Ley Orgánica 15/1999 de 13 de diciembre, de protección de datos de carácter
      personal&quot;, and &quot;RD1720/2007&quot;), as described in the &quot;Information for the patient sheet&quot;. Data
      will be entered online and stored securely in a centralized database in a devoted server. To
      access the eCRF, an user name and password with limited access to allow the development of
      the study will be assigned to every investigator in the trial (including coordinators and
      CRO). All personal identification data of the patients will be dissociated from the rest of
      the data and only the attending physicians will have access to that information to allow the
      follow-up. All data will be treated anonymously in the analysis and no report from the study
      will contain any information that allows to identify the patients.

      The clinical study will be reviewed by health authorities and an ethic committee and the
      study will only be started when the approval from the regulatory authorities and the ethic
      committee is obtained.

      At the end of follow-up, every patient will be informed of the treatment group in which he
      remained during the study and continue the standard care for his/her condition by his/her
      attending physician.

      POTENTIAL RISKS AND BENEFITS OF THE STUDY: The drug under investigation is accepted and of
      common use in Spain for the treatment of the type of patients that will be included. It will
      be administered as approved in its specifications. Its use is evidence based and its safety
      and efficacy are well documented.

      All tests and procedures included in the study are normal clinical practice in the diabetic
      patient with the exception of ABPM that poses no risk for the patient and is basic for the
      main outcome of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Type of study: Randomized, multicentric, placebo-controlled, single-blind pilot study.
Primary Objective: To investigate the effect of the addition of 10 mg daily of dapagliflozin to the treatment of diabetic patients compared to the addition of placebo on the change in nighttime blood pressure (measured by ABPM) over 12 weeks among patients with albuminuria levels ≥ 30 and &lt; 3000 mg/g creatinine and estimated glomerular filtration rate ≥ 60 mL/min/1.73 m2.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in nighttime blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in mean nighttime blood pressure (systolic and diastolic) between baseline and last visit (units: mmHg)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in office blood pressure. Both systolic and diastolic blood pressure will be assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in office blood pressure. Both systolic and diastolic blood pressure will be assessed (units: mmHg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in albuminuria</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in albuminuria (units:mg/g creatinine)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in HBA1C</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in HBA1C (units: %)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">225</enrollment>
  <condition>Type2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dapagliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigational medicinal product (IMP) is Dapagliflozin 10 MG Oral Tablet [Farxiga] given once daily (film coated tablets, oral use).
Dapagliflozin 10 MG Oral Tablet [Farxiga] will be administered through out the planned intervention period of the study (12 weeks).
Dosage form and strength: 10 mg, Green, plain, diamond shaped, film coated tablet (orally)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo matching dapagliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The comparator will be placebo oral tablet matching dapagliflozin 10 mg. Placebo will be administered through out the planned intervention period of the study (12 weeks).
Dosage form and strength: Green, plain, diamond shaped, film coated tablet (orally). Does not contain active ingredient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dapagliflozin 10 MG Oral Tablet [Farxiga]</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigational medicinal product (IMP) is dapagliflozin10 mg given once daily (film coated tablets, oral use).
Dapagliflozin will be administered through out the planned intervention period of the study (12 weeks).
Dosage form and strength: 10 mg, Green, plain, diamond shaped, film coated tablet (orally)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dapagliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dapagliflozin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Oral Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>The comparator will be placebo oral tablet matching dapagliflozin 10 mg. Placebo will be administered through out the planned intervention period of the study (12 weeks).
Dosage form and strength: Green, plain, diamond shaped, film coated tablet (orally). Does not contain active ingredient</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo matching dapagliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients with a previous diagnosis of type 2 diabetes and

          -  Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) ≥ 60 mL/min x1.73m2and

          -  Diagnosis of essential hypertension established at least one year before inclusion
             visit and suboptimal BP control (office BP above 140/70 mmHg)

          -  HbA1C 7.5-10%

          -  Albuminuria levels ≥ 30 mg/g of creatinine

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years old or ≥ 75 years old.

          -  Women of childbearing potential. A woman is considered of childbearing potential
             (WOCBP), i.e. fertile, following menarche and until becoming post-menopausal unless
             permanently sterile. Permanent sterilisation methods include hysterectomy, bilateral
             salpingectomy and bilateral oophorectomy. A postmenopausal state is defined as no
             menses for 12 months without an alternative medical cause.

          -  Type 1 diabetes

          -  Albuminuria above 3000 mg/g of creatinine

          -  Established cardiovascular disease (stable heart failure, peripheral arterial disease
             or myocardial infarction or stroke within the previous 6 months)

          -  Intolerance to dapagliflozin

          -  On treatment with loop diuretic

          -  On treatment with SGLT2 inhibitors.

          -  On treatment with pioglitazone.

          -  Patients diagnosed of hereditary problems of galactose intolerance, Lapp lactase
             deficiency or glucose-galactose malabsorption.

          -  Patients who routinely work during nightime (period between 11.00 p.m. and 7.00 a.m.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis M Ruilope Urioste</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre de Madrid</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis M Ruilope Urioste</last_name>
    <phone>629175770</phone>
    <email>ruilope@icloud.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico San Carlos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28040</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José A García Donaire</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julián M Segura de la Morena</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario La Paz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aquilino Sánchez</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawes CM, Vander Hoorn S, Rodgers A; International Society of Hypertension. Global burden of blood-pressure-related disease, 2001. Lancet. 2008 May 3;371(9623):1513-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60655-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18456100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lim SS, Vos T, Flaxman AD, Danaei G, Shibuya K, Adair-Rohani H, Amann M, Anderson HR, Andrews KG, Aryee M, Atkinson C, Bacchus LJ, Bahalim AN, Balakrishnan K, Balmes J, Barker-Collo S, Baxter A, Bell ML, Blore JD, Blyth F, Bonner C, Borges G, Bourne R, Boussinesq M, Brauer M, Brooks P, Bruce NG, Brunekreef B, Bryan-Hancock C, Bucello C, Buchbinder R, Bull F, Burnett RT, Byers TE, Calabria B, Carapetis J, Carnahan E, Chafe Z, Charlson F, Chen H, Chen JS, Cheng AT, Child JC, Cohen A, Colson KE, Cowie BC, Darby S, Darling S, Davis A, Degenhardt L, Dentener F, Des Jarlais DC, Devries K, Dherani M, Ding EL, Dorsey ER, Driscoll T, Edmond K, Ali SE, Engell RE, Erwin PJ, Fahimi S, Falder G, Farzadfar F, Ferrari A, Finucane MM, Flaxman S, Fowkes FG, Freedman G, Freeman MK, Gakidou E, Ghosh S, Giovannucci E, Gmel G, Graham K, Grainger R, Grant B, Gunnell D, Gutierrez HR, Hall W, Hoek HW, Hogan A, Hosgood HD 3rd, Hoy D, Hu H, Hubbell BJ, Hutchings SJ, Ibeanusi SE, Jacklyn GL, Jasrasaria R, Jonas JB, Kan H, Kanis JA, Kassebaum N, Kawakami N, Khang YH, Khatibzadeh S, Khoo JP, Kok C, Laden F, Lalloo R, Lan Q, Lathlean T, Leasher JL, Leigh J, Li Y, Lin JK, Lipshultz SE, London S, Lozano R, Lu Y, Mak J, Malekzadeh R, Mallinger L, Marcenes W, March L, Marks R, Martin R, McGale P, McGrath J, Mehta S, Mensah GA, Merriman TR, Micha R, Michaud C, Mishra V, Mohd Hanafiah K, Mokdad AA, Morawska L, Mozaffarian D, Murphy T, Naghavi M, Neal B, Nelson PK, Nolla JM, Norman R, Olives C, Omer SB, Orchard J, Osborne R, Ostro B, Page A, Pandey KD, Parry CD, Passmore E, Patra J, Pearce N, Pelizzari PM, Petzold M, Phillips MR, Pope D, Pope CA 3rd, Powles J, Rao M, Razavi H, Rehfuess EA, Rehm JT, Ritz B, Rivara FP, Roberts T, Robinson C, Rodriguez-Portales JA, Romieu I, Room R, Rosenfeld LC, Roy A, Rushton L, Salomon JA, Sampson U, Sanchez-Riera L, Sanman E, Sapkota A, Seedat S, Shi P, Shield K, Shivakoti R, Singh GM, Sleet DA, Smith E, Smith KR, Stapelberg NJ, Steenland K, Stöckl H, Stovner LJ, Straif K, Straney L, Thurston GD, Tran JH, Van Dingenen R, van Donkelaar A, Veerman JL, Vijayakumar L, Weintraub R, Weissman MM, White RA, Whiteford H, Wiersma ST, Wilkinson JD, Williams HC, Williams W, Wilson N, Woolf AD, Yip P, Zielinski JM, Lopez AD, Murray CJ, Ezzati M, AlMazroa MA, Memish ZA. A comparative risk assessment of burden of disease and injury attributable to 67 risk factors and risk factor clusters in 21 regions, 1990-2010: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010. Lancet. 2012 Dec 15;380(9859):2224-60. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61766-8. Erratum in: Lancet. 2013 Apr 13;381(9874):1276. Lancet. 2013 Feb 23;381(9867):628. AlMazroa, Mohammad A [added]; Memish, Ziad A [added].</citation>
    <PMID>23245609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewington S, Clarke R, Qizilbash N, Peto R, Collins R; Prospective Studies Collaboration. Age-specific relevance of usual blood pressure to vascular mortality: a meta-analysis of individual data for one million adults in 61 prospective studies. Lancet. 2002 Dec 14;360(9349):1903-13. Erratum in: Lancet. 2003 Mar 22;361(9362):1060.</citation>
    <PMID>12493255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collins R, Peto R, MacMahon S, Hebert P, Fiebach NH, Eberlein KA, Godwin J, Qizilbash N, Taylor JO, Hennekens CH. Blood pressure, stroke, and coronary heart disease. Part 2, Short-term reductions in blood pressure: overview of randomised drug trials in their epidemiological context. Lancet. 1990 Apr 7;335(8693):827-38. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1969567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mancia G, Fagard R, Narkiewicz K, Redon J, Zanchetti A, Böhm M, Christiaens T, Cifkova R, De Backer G, Dominiczak A, Galderisi M, Grobbee DE, Jaarsma T, Kirchhof P, Kjeldsen SE, Laurent S, Manolis AJ, Nilsson PM, Ruilope LM, Schmieder RE, Sirnes PA, Sleight P, Viigimaa M, Waeber B, Zannad F, Redon J, Dominiczak A, Narkiewicz K, Nilsson PM, Burnier M, Viigimaa M, Ambrosioni E, Caufield M, Coca A, Olsen MH, Schmieder RE, Tsioufis C, van de Borne P, Zamorano JL, Achenbach S, Baumgartner H, Bax JJ, Bueno H, Dean V, Deaton C, Erol C, Fagard R, Ferrari R, Hasdai D, Hoes AW, Kirchhof P, Knuuti J, Kolh P, Lancellotti P, Linhart A, Nihoyannopoulos P, Piepoli MF, Ponikowski P, Sirnes PA, Tamargo JL, Tendera M, Torbicki A, Wijns W, Windecker S, Clement DL, Coca A, Gillebert TC, Tendera M, Rosei EA, Ambrosioni E, Anker SD, Bauersachs J, Hitij JB, Caulfield M, De Buyzere M, De Geest S, Derumeaux GA, Erdine S, Farsang C, Funck-Brentano C, Gerc V, Germano G, Gielen S, Haller H, Hoes AW, Jordan J, Kahan T, Komajda M, Lovic D, Mahrholdt H, Olsen MH, Ostergren J, Parati G, Perk J, Polonia J, Popescu BA, Reiner Z, Rydén L, Sirenko Y, Stanton A, Struijker-Boudier H, Tsioufis C, van de Borne P, Vlachopoulos C, Volpe M, Wood DA. 2013 ESH/ESC guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension: the Task Force for the Management of Arterial Hypertension of the European Society of Hypertension (ESH) and of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Eur Heart J. 2013 Jul;34(28):2159-219. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/eht151. Epub 2013 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23771844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruilope LM. Current challenges in the clinical management of hypertension. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2011 Oct 25;9(5):267-75. doi: 10.1038/nrcardio.2011.157. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22027655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruiz-Hurtado G, Ruilope LM, de la Sierra A, Sarafidis P, de la Cruz JJ, Gorostidi M, Segura J, Vinyoles E, Banegas JR. Association Between High and Very High Albuminuria and Nighttime Blood Pressure: Influence of Diabetes and Chronic Kidney Disease. Diabetes Care. 2016 Oct;39(10):1729-37. doi: 10.2337/dc16-0748. Epub 2016 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27515965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lurbe E, Redon J, Kesani A, Pascual JM, Tacons J, Alvarez V, Batlle D. Increase in nocturnal blood pressure and progression to microalbuminuria in type 1 diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2002 Sep 12;347(11):797-805.</citation>
    <PMID>12226150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andrassy KM. Comments on 'KDIGO 2012 Clinical Practice Guideline for the Evaluation and Management of Chronic Kidney Disease'. Kidney Int. 2013 Sep;84(3):622-3. doi: 10.1038/ki.2013.243.</citation>
    <PMID>23989362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajasekeran H, Lytvyn Y, Cherney DZ. Sodium-glucose cotransporter 2 inhibition and cardiovascular risk reduction in patients with type 2 diabetes: the emerging role of natriuresis. Kidney Int. 2016 Mar;89(3):524-6. doi: 10.1016/j.kint.2015.12.038.</citation>
    <PMID>26880444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verma S, Garg A, Yan AT, Gupta AK, Al-Omran M, Sabongui A, Teoh H, Mazer CD, Connelly KA. Effect of Empagliflozin on Left Ventricular Mass and Diastolic Function in Individuals With Diabetes: An Important Clue to the EMPA-REG OUTCOME Trial? Diabetes Care. 2016 Dec;39(12):e212-e213. Epub 2016 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27679584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrannini E, Mark M, Mayoux E. CV Protection in the EMPA-REG OUTCOME Trial: A &quot;Thrifty Substrate&quot; Hypothesis. Diabetes Care. 2016 Jul;39(7):1108-14. doi: 10.2337/dc16-0330.</citation>
    <PMID>27289126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zinman B, Wanner C, Lachin JM, Fitchett D, Bluhmki E, Hantel S, Mattheus M, Devins T, Johansen OE, Woerle HJ, Broedl UC, Inzucchi SE; EMPA-REG OUTCOME Investigators. Empagliflozin, Cardiovascular Outcomes, and Mortality in Type 2 Diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2015 Nov 26;373(22):2117-28. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1504720. Epub 2015 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26378978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wanner C, Inzucchi SE, Lachin JM, Fitchett D, von Eynatten M, Mattheus M, Johansen OE, Woerle HJ, Broedl UC, Zinman B; EMPA-REG OUTCOME Investigators. Empagliflozin and Progression of Kidney Disease in Type 2 Diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2016 Jul 28;375(4):323-34. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1515920. Epub 2016 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>27299675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imprialos KP, Sarafidis PA, Karagiannis AI. Sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 inhibitors and blood pressure decrease: a valuable effect of a novel antidiabetic class? J Hypertens. 2015 Nov;33(11):2185-97. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000000719. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26372321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weber MA, Mansfield TA, Cain VA, Iqbal N, Parikh S, Ptaszynska A. Blood pressure and glycaemic effects of dapagliflozin versus placebo in patients with type 2 diabetes on combination antihypertensive therapy: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 3 study. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2016 Mar;4(3):211-220. doi: 10.1016/S2213-8587(15)00417-9. Epub 2015 Nov 27. Erratum in: Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2016 Mar;4(3):e3. Erratum in: Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2016 Mar;4(3):e3.</citation>
    <PMID>26620248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parati G, Stergiou G, O'Brien E, Asmar R, Beilin L, Bilo G, Clement D, de la Sierra A, de Leeuw P, Dolan E, Fagard R, Graves J, Head GA, Imai Y, Kario K, Lurbe E, Mallion JM, Mancia G, Mengden T, Myers M, Ogedegbe G, Ohkubo T, Omboni S, Palatini P, Redon J, Ruilope LM, Shennan A, Staessen JA, vanMontfrans G, Verdecchia P, Waeber B, Wang J, Zanchetti A, Zhang Y; European Society of Hypertension Working Group on Blood Pressure Monitoring and Cardiovascular Variability. European Society of Hypertension practice guidelines for ambulatory blood pressure monitoring. J Hypertens. 2014 Jul;32(7):1359-66. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000000221.</citation>
    <PMID>24886823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cerezo C, Ruilope LM, Segura J, Garcia-Donaire JA, de la Cruz JJ, Banegas JR, Waeber B, Rabelink TJ, Messerli FH. Microalbuminuria breakthrough under chronic renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system suppression. J Hypertens. 2012 Jan;30(1):204-9. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0b013e32834d9e0f.</citation>
    <PMID>22080225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruiz-Hurtado G, Condezo-Hoyos L, Pulido-Olmo H, Aranguez I, Del Carmen Gónzalez M, Arribas S, Cerezo C, Segura J, Praga M, Fernández-Alfonso MS, Ruilope LM. Development of albuminuria and enhancement of oxidative stress during chronic renin-angiotensin system suppression. J Hypertens. 2014 Oct;32(10):2082-91; discussion 2091. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000000292.</citation>
    <PMID>25033166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pulido-Olmo H, García-Prieto CF, Álvarez-Llamas G, Barderas MG, Vivanco F, Aranguez I, Somoza B, Segura J, Kreutz R, Fernández-Alfonso MS, Ruilope LM, Ruiz-Hurtado G. Role of matrix metalloproteinase-9 in chronic kidney disease: a new biomarker of resistant albuminuria. Clin Sci (Lond). 2016 Apr 1;130(7):525-38. doi: 10.1042/CS20150517. Epub 2016 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26733721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baldan-Martin M, de la Cuesta F, Alvarez-Llamas G, Gonzalez-Calero L, Ruiz-Hurtado G, Moreno-Luna R, Mourino-Alvarez L, Sastre-Oliva T, Segura J, Padial LR, Vivanco F, Ruilope LM, Barderas MG. Prediction of development and maintenance of high albuminuria during chronic renin-angiotensin suppression by plasma proteomics. Int J Cardiol. 2015 Oct 1;196:170-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2015.05.148. Epub 2015 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26119064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baldan-Martin M, Mourino-Alvarez L, Gonzalez-Calero L, Moreno-Luna R, Sastre-Oliva T, Ruiz-Hurtado G, Segura J, Lopez JA, Vazquez J, Vivanco F, Alvarez-Llamas G, Ruilope LM, de la Cuesta F, Barderas MG. Plasma Molecular Signatures in Hypertensive Patients With Renin-Angiotensin System Suppression: New Predictors of Renal Damage and De Novo Albuminuria Indicators. Hypertension. 2016 Jul;68(1):157-66. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.116.07412. Epub 2016 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>27217411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de la Cuesta F, Baldan-Martin M, Mourino-Alvarez L, Sastre-Oliva T, Alvarez-Llamas G, Gonzalez-Calero L, Ruiz-Hurtado G, Segura J, Vivanco F, Ruilope LM, Barderas MG. [Cardiovascular risk study in patients with renin-angiotensin system blockade by means of the proteone of circulating extracellular vesicles]. Hipertens Riesgo Vasc. 2016 Jan-Mar;33(1):21-7. doi: 10.1016/j.hipert.2015.07.003. Epub 2015 Sep 19. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>26826536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wei W, Tölle M, Zidek W, van der Giet M. Validation of the mobil-O-Graph: 24 h-blood pressure measurement device. Blood Press Monit. 2010 Aug;15(4):225-8. doi: 10.1097/MBP.0b013e328338892f.</citation>
    <PMID>20216407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 3, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nighttime blood pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Dapagliflozin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>2-(3-(4-ethoxybenzyl)-4-chlorophenyl)-6-hydroxymethyltetrahydro-2H-pyran-3,4,5-triol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>October 19, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/16/NCT03887416/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

