<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03889418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01DA045029-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03889418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Opioid Treatment and Recovery Through a Safe Pain Management Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>Opioid Treatment and Recovery Through a Safe Pain Management Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ochsner Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tulane University School of Public Health and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harvard University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ochsner Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Opioid prescription drug abuse has become a major public health concern in the United States
      with mortality rates from fatal overdoses reaching epidemic proportions. This opioid crisis
      coincides with national efforts to improve management of chronic non-cancer pain. The net
      result, however, has been ever-growing increases in medical expenditures related to
      prescription costs and increased healthcare service utilization among opioid abusers.
      Healthcare provider prescribing pattern, especially among non-pain management specialists
      such as primary care, is a major factor. Louisiana is a major contributor to the epidemic
      with the 7th highest opioid prescribing rates accompanied by a 12% increase in fatal
      overdoses.

      Providers are overdue for implementing safe opioid management strategies in primary care to
      combat the opioid crisis. Recent practice guidelines provide recommendations on what to do
      for safe prescribing of opioids, but they do not provide guidance on how to translate them
      into practice. Health systems must find ways to accelerate guideline adoption in primary care
      in the face of an overdose crisis. Research that examines a combination workflow- and
      provider-focused strategies are needed. Given the high prevalence of psychiatric disorders
      among patients with chronic non-cancer pain, care team expansion with integration of
      collaborative mental/behavioral health services may be the solution. Collaborative care can
      extend opioid management beyond standardized monitoring of risk factors for opioid misuse or
      abuse and set clear protocols for next steps in management.

      This study is aligned with the National Institute on Drug Abuse's interest in health systems
      research that examines approaches to screening, assessment, prevention, diagnosis and
      treatment for prescription drug abuse. It will examine the primary care practice redesign of
      managing chronic non-cancer pain within a large health system whose 40+ Accountable Care
      Network-affiliated, adult primary care clinics may serve as an example for transforming
      opioid management in primary care practices across the country. This four-year stepped wedge
      cluster randomized control trial is designed to compare the clinical and cost effectiveness
      of electronic medical record-based clinical decision support guided care versus additional
      integrated, stepped collaborative care for opioid management of primary care patients with
      chronic non-cancer pain (clinical pharmacist for medication management; licensed clinical
      social worker for cognitive behavioral therapy and community health worker care
      coordination); and to examine facilitators and barriers to implementing this multi-component
      intervention. Investigators anticipate that our study results will elucidate the role of
      technology versus care team optimization in changing provider opioid prescribing behaviors.
      Investigators further anticipate that results of our study will demonstrate that integrated
      mental/behavioral health care for opioid management of chronic non-cancer pain increases
      value-based care and leads to greater efficiencies in the way that care is delivered.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This proposal is a 4-year stepped wedge cluster randomized control (cRCT) trial to evaluate a multi-component intervention to: electronic medical recorded (EMR)clinical decision support (CDS) guided care; and stepped opioid collaborative care model (CCM) to improve opioid management of primary care patients with chronic non-cancer pain. The stepped wedge cRCT design will allow us to examine the clinical impact of the intervention as the two components are implemented in a stepwise fashion across the health system. The EMR CDS guided care component went live in all primary care clinics as the health system's standard of practice in October 2017. The stepped opioid CCM component will require 15 months to scale up in 3-month intervals across five geographic regions of the health system in the state of Louisiana. We will randomize the order in which stepped opioid CCM becomes available in each region</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of high dose opioid prescribing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-months, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in percent patients with Morphine equivalent daily dose (MEDD) &gt;=90</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in average daily opioid prescription dosage</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-months, 12-month</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the population average MEDD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of inpatient hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in rate of inpatient hospitalization visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of emergency department use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in rate of emergency department visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of depression symptom response to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-months, 6-months, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Patient Health Questionnaire-9 scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of anxiety symptom response to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-months, 6-months, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient rating of Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-months, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Global Health-10 scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient rating of pain control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3-months, 6-months, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Pain, Enjoyment, General Activity-3 scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of practice guideline adherence for pain agreements</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in proportion of patients with pain agreements</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of practice guideline adherence for urine drug screening</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in proportion of patients with urine drug screening</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of practice guideline adherence for naloxone prescriptions</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in proportion of high risk patients with naloxone prescriptions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of patient report of opioid misuse</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6-months, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Current Opioid Misuse Measure-9 scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of referral to specialty care</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in proportion of patients referred to specialists for pain management</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in rate of non-opioid prescriptions for pain management</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in proportion of patients with non-opioid prescriptions for pain management</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in provider experience with managing mental health conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in provider ratings of their experience</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1750</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Electronic medical recorded clinical decision support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>stepped opioid collaborative care model</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care AND collaborative care with behavioral health integration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic medical recorded clinical decision support [EMR CDS]</intervention_name>
    <description>The opioid management tool has quick links to the Opioid Risk Tool (ORT), health maintenance reminders for risk mitigation tasks (pain management agreements; urine drug screening; prescribing naloxone); Pain Scale and depression/anxiety screen. The frequency with which providers are prompted to complete mitigation tasks is based on patients' level of risk for aberrant drug behavior defined by the ORT score. Additionally, the EMR CDS flags patients as high risk if one of the following criteria are met: (1) co-prescriptions for benzodiazepines; (2) active diagnosis of substance abuse in the last 12 months; or (3) MEDD &gt;=90 mg. The ORT score, morphine equivalent daily dose (MEDD), and hyperlinks to the Louisiana pharmacy drug monitoring program data are visible in the prescription writer. If MEDD &gt;=90 mg, the calculated MEDD is displayed in red font to alert the prescribing provider of high dosage. An Epic banner appears in charts to alert providers of existing pain management agreements.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Electronic medical recorded clinical decision support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>stepped opioid collaborative care model</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stepped opioid collaborative care model [CCM]</intervention_name>
    <description>The licensed clinical social worker (LCSW) will provide counseling services as indicated (behavioral activation, psychotherapy, crisis planning, facilitating connection to substance abuse counseling and treatment); meet weekly with the consulting psychiatrist for complex case review and care plan adjustments; and supervise the community health worker (CHW) case management and depression/anxiety care management activities. The CHW will update assets and barriers to recovery and self-management and help patients navigate community resources. The clinical pharmacist will review and reconcile active medication lists, assess medication side effects, drug interactions and adverse events; monitor analgesia; recommend algorithm based anti-depression medication titration as indicated. The consulting psychiatrist will directly co-manage patients with severe mental illness, substance abuse and complex medication regimens.</description>
    <arm_group_label>stepped opioid collaborative care model</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 and older

          2. Have a primary care provider at any of the study clinics

          3. Receiving chronic opioid prescriptions (3 of the prior 4 months) for chronic
             non-cancer pain

          4. Have a diagnosis of depression or anxiety

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age less than 18 years

          2. Active cancer or undergoing cancer treatment

          3. Chronic cancer-related pain

          4. Having a terminal illness

          5. Receiving hospice care
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Principal Investigator</last_name>
    <phone>504-842-8265</phone>
    <email>eboni.pricehaywood@ochsner.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Research Coordinator</last_name>
    <phone>504-842-8604</phone>
    <email>jewel.hardenbarrios@ochsner.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ochsner Health System - Research Dept</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jewel Harden-Barrios, MEd</last_name>
      <phone>504-842-8604</phone>
      <email>jewel.hardenbarrios@ochsner.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stephanie Gaudreau</last_name>
      <email>sgaudreau@ochsner.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eboni Price-Haywood, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lydia Bazzano, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lizheng Shi, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Lefante, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Jamison, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alessandra Bazzano, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price-Haywood EG, Robinson W, Harden-Barrios J, Burton J, Burstain T. Intelligent Clinical Decision Support to Improve Safe Opioid Management of Chronic Noncancer Pain in Primary Care. Ochsner J. 2018 Spring;18(1):30-35.</citation>
    <PMID>29559866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 15, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 15, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ochsner Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eboni Price-Haywood</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

