<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03882268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>InternationalFPRI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03882268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrating MIYCN Counseling in Urban Health Services</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility Study of Integrating Maternal, Infant and Young Child Nutrition (MIYCN) Counseling Services in Urban Maternal, Neonatal and Child Health (MNCH) Services in Bangladesh: A Cluster-randomized Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Food Policy Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Food Policy Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed intervention will examine the feasibility of standardizing MIYCN counseling
      services in existing health facilities with a view to improving the quality of such services.
      It will also examine the impact of standardized and upgraded services on client utilization,
      knowledge and behavior. 10 health facilities run by 2 NGOs in urban Dhaka will be randomly
      selected to receive intensified MIYCN interventions, while another 10 health facilities run
      by same NGOs will serve as a comparison group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of the proposed evaluation are to answer the following questions using
      a cluster-randomized evaluation design:

        -  Is it feasible to standardize the delivery of MIYCN counseling services in existing
           urban health facilities?

        -  Can quality of MIYCN counseling service be improved by upgrading and standardizing
           existing MIYCN counseling service in urban health facilities?

        -  What are the impacts of standardized and upgraded MIYCN counseling service on
           utilization of MIYCN services?

        -  What are the impacts of standardized and upgraded MIYCN counseling service on knowledge
           and behaviors of clients including: Pregnant women - 1) consumption of diversified
           foods; 2) intake of IFA and calcium supplements during pregnancy; Mothers of children &lt;1
           y - age-appropriate infant feeding

      The study will use a cluster-randomized design with mixed methods of data collection
      including 1) Light baseline data collection to assess facility comparability, 2)
      Facility-based endline data collection and 3) Community-based endline survey.

      A total of 10 health facilities from two NGOs in Dhaka urban areas will be randomly allocated
      to receive intensified MIYCN interventions. Another 10 health facilities from the same two
      NGOs will be randomly allocated to the comparison groups. The list of the 20 facilities will
      be chosen by A&amp;T, and catchment areas for the finalized list will be identified.
      Characteristics of women (such as age, education, socio-economic status) in these catchment
      areas will then be compared with urban women in other areas using DHS data (if data
      available), to check for comparability between our sample versus the general urban
      population.

      The study will use mixed data collection methods including: 1) facility assessment; 2)
      provider survey; 3) case observations (include ANC visits, child visits [both sick child and
      immunization], and counseling section), and 4) client interviews. The baseline survey will be
      started in June-July 2019, and an end-line survey is planned to be conducted in
      August-September 2020 for facility-based data collection and November- December 2020 for
      community-based data collection. Due to budget constrains, baseline data collection will
      focus to assess facility comparability, but not include client data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A total of 10 health facilities from two NGOs in Dhaka urban areas will be randomly allocated to receive intensified MIYCN interventions. Another 10 health facilities from the same two NGOs will be randomly allocated to the comparison groups. Health workers and clients at these facilities will be participants in the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge of provider on topics related to maternal and child nutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for August-September 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Total standardized scores (range 0-10) of correct answers to questions related to maternal and child nutrition, with higher scores represent higher knowledge.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of counselling on maternal and child nutrition by health staff</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for August-September 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Total standardized scores (range 0-10) of correct messages related to maternal and child nutrition that health staff provided during counselling sessions. Higher scores represent higher quality of counseling.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge of pregnant women/mothers on topics related to maternal and child nutrition</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for November-December 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Total standardized scores (range 0-10) of correct answers to questions related to maternal and child nutrition, with higher scores represent higher knowledge.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet diversity among pregnant women</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for November-December 2020</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of pregnant women who received foods from 5 or more food groups on the day preceding the interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal consumption of IFA supplementation</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for November-December 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Number of IFA consumed during pregnancy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal consumption of calcium</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for November-December 2020</time_frame>
    <description>Number of calcium consumed during pregnancy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Exclusive breastfeeding among children aged 0-5.9 months</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for November-December 2020</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of infants aged less than 6 months who were exclusively breastfed on the day preceding the interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum dietary diversity among children aged 6-23.9 months</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months after baseline in a cross-sectional endline survey scheduled for November-December 2020</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of children aged 6-23.9 months who received foods from 4 or more food groups on the day preceding the interview.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Maternal Nutrition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MIYCN interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 facilities run by 2 NGOs that will be randomly selected to receive intensified MIYCN interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison facilities</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 facilities run by same 2 NGOs that run the intervention facilities, which will not receive any standardized MIYCN interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MIYCN interventions</intervention_name>
    <description>Capacity building for health provider and nutritional counselors (training on MIYCN SBCC from A&amp;T)
Available and dedicated space for MIYCN counseling with standard layout, logo and specifications.
Availability of standardized MIYCN-specific BCC materials and job aids
Regular counseling services offered by a dedicated counselor hired by A&amp;T
Routine counselling on IFA and calcium supplementation from dedicated counselor during ANC contact
Counseling on weight monitoring and availability of standard weighing scales
Breastfeeding and complementary feeding related counseling regularly offered as a service by a dedicated counselor
Dedicated community worker to identify and mobilize beneficiaries needing services in the community; use of mass media to improve awareness; scheduled follow ups</description>
    <arm_group_label>MIYCN interventions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women who are visiting the health facilities for ANC visits (around half of
             clients)

          -  Mothers with children &lt;12 months of age who are visiting the health facilities for
             health check-ups

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women with severe illness or complications

          -  Mothers with severely ill children
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Purnima Menon, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IFPRI</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Phuong H Nguyen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 202-862-5600</phone>
    <email>P.H.Nguyen@cgiar.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Urban</keyword>
  <keyword>Maternal Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition Counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavior change</keyword>
  <keyword>Infant and young child feeding</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

