<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03888027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ReDA 6072</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03888027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>WalkMORE: A Volunteer-driven Walking Intervention</brief_title>
  <acronym>WalkMORE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of a Volunteer-driven Walking Intervention to Improve Hospital-associated Deconditioning and Frailty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lawson Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lawson Health Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients admitted to hospital typically experience periods of decreased activity or bed-rest.
      This reduced activity level leads to deconditioning - a loss of muscle mass, muscle strength
      (by 2-5% per day), and muscle shortening. Even among patients who were ambulatory at the time
      of admission, deconditioning has been linked with deleterious effects, such as increased
      rates of falls, functional decline, and frailty. Furthermore, it has been suggested that the
      physiological stresses associated with hospitalization - including deconditioning, as well as
      sleep deprivation and poor nutrition - makes discharged patients vulnerable to recurrent or
      new illnesses and to frailty. This physiological stress-induced vulnerability has been coined
      &quot;post-hospital syndrome&quot; and is thought to have a role in most hospital readmissions. The
      investigators hypothesize that by engaging ambulatory patients to walk with trained
      volunteers, patients will increase their amount of walking, have less deconditioning and
      functional decline, and consequently, fewer falls. Furthermore, the investigators anticipate
      that patients who walk with a trained volunteer will have reduced length-of-stay in hospital
      and decreased likelihood of readmission. Finally, as shown in other similar programs, the
      investigators anticipate an overall improvement in the patient experience. The investigator's
      novel initiative focuses on a single, volunteer-based intentional ambulation program that can
      deliver the benefits of early mobility in a cost-effective way. The program design engages
      trained volunteers to increase patient ambulation in a way that both increases patient
      mobility and reduces healthcare professionals' workload.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      WalkMORE is a single-center randomized controlled trial. The investigators will enroll up to
      800 ambulatory patients admitted to the Internal Medicine unit (located on the 4th floor of
      University Hospital) who are &gt;18 years of age and are anticipated to require a &gt;48 hour
      hospital admission. A maximum of 6 patients will be assigned to each treatment arm at any
      given time. The investigators will recruit patients into the WalkMORE program over a 2 year
      period. The research coordinator (RC) will screen patients admitted to the Internal Medicine
      unit in the preceding 24-hour period to identify patients who fulfill the eligibility
      criteria. Patients will be randomized via REDCap (Research Electronic Data Capture), a
      secure, centralized web-based randomization module to:

        1. Standard of care; or

        2. WalkMORE Ambulation program + Standard of care. Patients will ambulate with a trained
           WalkMORE Volunteer two times per day; once in the morning (0900-1200 hrs) and once in
           the afternoon (1300-1600 hrs), Monday- Friday, until hospital discharge. Patients
           randomized to the WalkMORE intervention will be assessed daily by the RC to ensure
           patients remain fit for independent ambulation. The duration of each walking session
           will be determined daily by the RC and the medical team.

      After obtaining written informed consent from eligible patients the RC will randomize
      patients, collect demographics and hospital admission details from patients' hospital charts
      and perform the Barthel Index and complete the Charlson Comorbidity Index (CCI) for all
      patients. The Barthel Index (BI) measures the extent to which patients can function
      independently and has mobility in their activities of daily living (ADL). The Charlson
      Comorbidity Index categorizes and scores the comorbidities of patients. The CCI can be used
      to predict short term and long-term outcomes such as function, hospital length of stay and
      mortality rates. The CCI will be completed using information gathered from patients' hospital
      chart.with all patients.

      All patients will be assigned a scientific pedometer on the day of randomization. The modus
      Health StepWatch™ is an activity monitor worn on the ankle via a velcro strap. It is a small,
      lightweight device that will count and record patients' steps throughout hospital stay,
      ending at hospital discharge. Research personnel will be responsible for fitting the
      StepWatch monitor to patients' ankle. The device is smaller than a deck of cards (7.5 x 5.0 x
      2.0 cm) and weighs 38 grams.

      Frailty and de-conditioning will be measured on Study Day 3. Frailty will be assessed using
      the Jamar Hand Dynamometer. Patients are instructed to squeeze the handle of the instrument
      with their maximum force for three seconds; the peak-hold (in kilograms) is recorded on the
      instrument. Three successive peak-hold measurements will be recorded. The device measures 10
      x 20 x 33cm and weighs 1.3 kg. Deconditioning will be measured using the Timed Up and Go
      (TUG) test, patients will be asked to stand up from a chair, walk three metres, turn around,
      and walk back to the chair and sit.

      After hospital discharge the RC will follow up with patients for 2 brief telephone
      interviews. On the third day after discharge, Patient Satisfaction surveys will be conducted
      by the RC to assess patient satisfaction with their hospital experience and with the WalkMORE
      program. On day 30 after randomization, the RC will contact patients to conduct a brief
      interview consisting of: a health status survey (EQ-5D), a functional status assessment
      (Barthel Index) and to collect data regarding clinical outcomes (ER visits,
      re-hospitalizations, and falls). Each telephone interview is expected to last approximately
      10 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be randomized via REDCap (Research Electronic Data Capture), a secure, centralized web-based randomization module to:
Standard of care; or
WalkMORE Ambulation program + Standard of care. Patients will ambulate with a trained WalkMORE Volunteer Coach two times per day; once in the morning (0900-1200hrs) and once in the afternoon (1300-1700hrs), Monday- Friday, until hospital discharge. Patients randomized to the WalkMORE intervention will be assessed daily by the Research Coordinator to ensure patients remain fit for independent ambulation. The duration of each walking session will be determined daily by the RC and the medical team.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients re-admitted to hospital</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presentation to emergency department</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients seen in the hospital emergency department</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prolonged index hospital admission</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with extended length of hospital admission</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay for index hospital admission</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days patient was hospitalized</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-discharge Falls</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Composite of number of readmissions and emergency room visits secondary to patients experiencing a fall post-discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed-Up-And-Go</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of de-conditioning between the two study arms using</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>ordinal scale used to measure performance in activities of daily living. Minimum score is zero and maximum score is 100, higher score represent better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of frailty between the two study arms using the Jamar Hand Dynamometer data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Deconditioning</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>total steps as measured by pedometer as a measure of deconditioning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increased number of steps</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>proportion of patients who increase step count by 200 steps per day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>A STANDARDIZED INSTRUMENT FOR USE AS A MEASURE OF HEALTH OUTCOME. The EQ-VAS scale ranges from a minimum of zero and a maximum of 100 and is the participants subjective score of how good or poor their health is at the time the scale is presented to them. Higher values represent a better outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Frailty</condition>
  <condition>Deconditioning</condition>
  <condition>Early Ambulation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>WalkMORE group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized via REDCap (Research Electronic Data Capture), a secure, centralized web-based randomization module to:
Standard of care; or
WalkMORE Ambulation program + Standard of care. Patients will ambulate with a trained WalkMORE volunteer two times per day; once in the morning (0900-1200hrs) and once in the afternoon (1300-1700hrs), Monday- Friday, until hospital discharge. Patients randomized to the WalkMORE intervention will be assessed daily by the Research Coordinator to ensure patients remain fit for independent ambulation. The duration of each walking session will be determined daily by the RC and the medical team.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>WalkMORE group</intervention_name>
    <description>Hospitalized Internal Medicine patients will walk with trained volunteers twice daily until hospital discharge.</description>
    <arm_group_label>WalkMORE group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Capable and appropriate for independent ambulation (with or without gait aids) as
             determined daily by the health care team

          2. Cognitively safe for participation

          3. Anticipated to remain hospitalized ≥48 hours

          4. Inpatient, admitted to Internal Medicine at University Hospital

          5. Age &gt;18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Preexisting condition precludes patient from independent ambulation at time of
             admission

          2. Active medical condition precludes patient from safely participating

          3. Preexisting condition or active medical condition renders patient unfit to participate
             as judged by the admitting team

          4. Patients who refuse to participate or are unable to provide informed consent.

          5. Communication barrier (due to hearing/vision impairment, or language barrier)

          6. Patients receiving treatment from an LHSC inpatient Physiotherapist.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>STEPHANIE HANDSOR, BA</last_name>
    <phone>5196858500</phone>
    <phone_ext>34390</phone_ext>
    <email>stephanie.handsor@lhsc.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Erin Spicer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5196633171</phone>
    <email>erin.spicer@lhsc.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LHSC-University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 5A5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie N Handsor, BA</last_name>
      <phone>519-685-8500</phone>
      <phone_ext>34390</phone_ext>
      <email>stephanie.handsor@lhsc.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Frailty</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

