<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03882437</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP-A501-0219</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03882437</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gene Therapy for Male Patients With Danon Disease Using RP-A501; AAV9.LAMP2B</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gene Therapy for Danon Disease (DD): A Clinical Study Evaluating the Infusion of a Recombinant Adeno-Associated Virus Serotype 9 (rAAV9) Capsid Containing the Human Lysosome-Associated Membrane Protein 2 Isoform B (LAMP2B) Transgene (RP-A501; AAV9.LAMP2B) in Male Patients With Danon Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rocket Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rocket Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-randomized open-label Phase 1 study to evaluate the safety and toxicity of gene
      therapy using a recombinant adeno-associated virus serotype 9 (AAV9) containing the human
      lysosome-associated membrane protein 2 isoform B (LAMP2B) transgene (investigational product
      (IP), RP-A501) in male patients with Danon Disease (DD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a non-randomized open-label Phase I clinical trial to characterize the safety
      and toxicity associated with infusion of a recombinant adeno-associated serotype 9 (rAAV9)
      capsid containing the human lysosome-associated membrane protein 2 isoform B (LAMP2B)
      transgene (investigational product (IP), RP-A501) in male patients with Danon Disease (DD).

      During the course of the study, approximately 12-24 subjects will receive a single
      intravenous (IV) infusion of the IP, with up to 4 specific cohorts receiving RP-A501 at
      sequentially higher dose levels. Two dose levels are planned to be investigated in 4 distinct
      cohorts:

        -  Cohort 1: Age 15 years and older: Low Dose (n=3-6 subjects)

        -  Cohort 2: Age 15 years and older: High Dose (n=3-6 subjects)

        -  Cohort 3: Age 8-14 years: Low Dose (n=3-6 subjects)

        -  Cohort 4: Age 8-14 years: High Dose (n=3-6 subjects)

      Pending determination of safety in Cohort I, concomitant enrollment in Cohorts 2 and 3 is
      permissible.

      The study will also enable an initial evaluation of whether or not the investigational
      therapy results in cardiomyocyte and skeletal muscle transduction and gene expression and
      preliminary assessment of the extent of cardiomyocyte and histologic correction.
      Additionally, a preliminary evaluation of clinical stabilization following infusion will also
      be made.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Subjects will receive RP-A501 according to a 3+3 dose escalation design as follows:
Cohort 1: Age 15 years and older: Low Dose (n=3-6 subjects)
Cohort 2: Age 15 years and older: High Dose (n=3-6 subjects)
Cohort 3: Age 8-14 years: Low Dose (n=3-6 subjects)
Cohort 4: Age 8-14 years: High Dose (n=3-6 subjects)
Evaluation of RP-A501 in pediatric patients (ages 8-14) at either dose level will commence only pending determination of safety in the older (adult and age ≥15 and generally capable of providing assent) population.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by United States (US) National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria (NCI CTCAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of safety associated with RP-A501</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants within each dose level cohort with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by United States (US) National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria (NCI CTCAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of safety at both doses (single IV administration)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of target tissue transduction following administration of RP-A501</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of target tissue transduction by gene expression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of cardiomyocyte histologic correction following administration of RP-A501 via endomyocardial biopsy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of cardiomyocyte histologic correction following administration of RP-A501 via endomyocardial biopsy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary evaluation of clinical stabilization of cardiomyopathy following administration of RP-A501 via cardiopulmonary testing</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of clinical stabilization of cardiomyopathy following infusion of RP-A501 via cardiopulmonary testing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the percentage of patients in whom RP-A501 resulted in a sustained improvement or stabilization in cardiovascular pathophysiology</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of sustained improvement or stabilization in cardiovascular pathophysiology as assessed by medical evaluation, radiographic evaluation of cardiac structure and function, and cardiopulmonary exercise/physiologic parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the percentage of patients in whom cardiomyocytes corrected LAMP2B gene and/or protein</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the percentage of patients in whom cardiomyocytes contain the corrected LAMP2B gene and/or protein and improvement in DD-associated histologic abnormalities and when feasible to quantify the extent of genetic and histologic correction in the myocardium.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of serologic markers of muscle injury and congestive heart failure following administration of RP-A501</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of serologic markers (creatinine phosphokinase, brain natriuretic peptide, etc) will be performed as potential surrogates of clinical, structural and histologic modification of DD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination and characterization of immunologic response to RP-A501</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of potential immunogenicity to the components of the investigational product</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patient-reported outcomes/quality-of-life (PRO/QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of PRO/QOL will be performed via the Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PRO/QOL</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of PRO/QOL will be performed via the Pediatric Cardiac Quality of Life Inventory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the percentage of patients who require and/or receive treatment for heart failure following RP-A501</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the percentage of patients who require and/or receive subsequent cardiac transplantation, left ventricular assist device (LVAD), implantable cardioverter-defibrillator or pacemaker placement, electrophysiologic ablative procedure for cardiac conduction aberrancy or subsequent hospitalizations for heart failure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of overall survival post RP-A501</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the percentage of patients with stabilization in neuromuscular function via timed test of essential neuromuscular activities</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the percentage of patients with stabilization in neuromuscular function via timed test of essential neuromuscular activities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the percentage of patients with stabilization in ophthalmologic function via ophthalmologic examination</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the percentage of patients with stabilization in ophthalmologic function via ophthalmologic examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Danon Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RP-A501</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RP-A501 is a gene therapy product consisting of a rAAV9 capsid containing the human LAMP2B transgene which will be administered as a single intravenous (IV) infusion. Subjects will receive one of two dose levels depending on the cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RP-A501</intervention_name>
    <description>RP-A501 is a gene therapy product consisting of a rAAV9 capsid containing the human LAMP2B transgene which will be administered as a single IV infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RP-A501</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. DD diagnosis with any confirmed LAMP2 mutation(s).

          2. Cardiac involvement as documented by at least one abnormal finding on
             electrocardiogram (ECG), echocardiogram, gadolinium-enhanced cardiac magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI) or electrophysiology study.

          3. Age ≥15 years for cohorts 1 and 2; 8-14 years for cohorts 3 and 4.

          4. Male gender.

          5. New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class of II or III. Patients with NYHA Class I are
             eligible if unable to walk ≥450 meters during the 6-Minute Walk Test (6MWT).

          6. Adequate hematologic function as defined by:

               1. Hemoglobin ≥10 g/dL (6.2 mmol/L; Grade ≤ 1 anemia, per National Cancer Institute
                  Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE), version 5.0).

               2. Absolute neutrophil count ≥1500/mm^3 (1.5×10^9/L; Grade ≤1 neutropenia).

               3. Platelet count ≥75,000/mm^3 (75×10^9/L; Grade ≤1 thrombocytopenia).

          7. Hepatic function as defined by:

               1. AST and ALT ≤10×ULN (transaminase elevations in DD are considered largely to
                  result from muscle injury; hence the relatively high upper limit for these
                  parameters, and the presence of additional hepatic eligibility markers of
                  bilirubin and PT/INR).

               2. Serum bilirubin ≤1.5×ULN (i.e., Grade ≤1 bilirubin increase).

               3. PT/INR ≤1.5×ULN (in the absence of anticoagulation).

               4. Absence of cirrhosis on liver ultrasound.

          8. Renal function as follows: creatinine ≤1.5×ULN; (if creatinine is &gt;1.5×ULN, then
             creatinine clearance ≥50 mL/min/1.73m^2 is required, as calculated by Modification of
             Diet in Renal Disease equation (Stevens 2006), the revised Schwartz formula (for
             patients under 18 years old) (Schwartz 2009), or 24-hour urine collection).

          9. Ability to provide informed consent (for adult patients and parents/legal guardians of
             pediatric patients) and assent (for patients age 15-17).

         10. Ability to comply with study procedures including investigational therapy and
             follow-up evaluations.

         11. Able to walk &gt;150 meters unassisted during the 6MWT.

         12. Patient has received meningococcal vaccination recommended by Centers for Disease
             Control as appropriate for age and health condition.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. IV therapy with positive inotropes, vasodilators or diuretics within the 30 days prior
             to enrollment (i.e. patient must be stable on oral medical therapy).

          2. Prior cardiac transplantation or prior transplant of other organ (lung, liver, other).

          3. Cardiac surgery, percutaneous cardiac intervention or valvuloplasty within 30 days
             prior to enrollment.

          4. Presence or requirement of a LVAD.

          5. Myocardial infarction, unstable angina, stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA)
             within 90 days prior to enrollment.

          6. Significant (greater than moderate) valvular stenosis or regurgitation on
             echocardiogram.

          7. Requires mechanical ventilation.

          8. Anti-AAV9 neutralizing antibody titer &gt;1:5.

          9. Concurrent enrollment in any other clinical investigation involving use of an
             investigational agent for the treatment of congestive heart failure or cardiomyopathy.

         10. Active hepatitis B or C infection (including patients with positive HBsAg, HBeAg or
             detectable HBV or HCV viral load). Patients with previous, adequately resolved HBV or
             HCV are eligible.

         11. Significant medical conditions including documented HIV infection, active viral or
             other hepatitis, poorly-controlled hypertension or diabetes, poorly controlled cardiac
             arrhythmia or uncontrolled viral, bacterial or fungal infection.

         12. Any concomitant medical or psychiatric condition that in the opinion of the
             investigator renders the patient unfit for study participation or at higher than
             acceptable risk for study participation.

         13. Active hematologic or solid organ malignancy, not including non-melanoma skin cancer
             or other carcinoma in situ. Patients with previously resected solid organ malignancies
             or definitively treated hematologic malignancies may be eligible if there has been no
             evidence of active malignancy during the prior 3 years.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical Information</last_name>
    <phone>646-901-9276</phone>
    <email>Danonclinicaltrial@rocketpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>HCM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glycogen Storage Disease Type IIb</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

