<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03885297</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GD410218</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>250896</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03885297</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>3mg Liraglutide for Overweight or Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of the Metabolic Effects of 3mg Liraglutide on Patients With Overweight or Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kingston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Warwick</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study investigators will investigate the beneficial metabolic sequelae of Liraglutide
      in patients with obesity or overweight; including changes in vital signs, anthropometric
      characteristics (weight, body mass index and body composition), biochemical parameters,
      metabolomics and micro-ribonucleotide acid (miRNA) molecules from blood tests. Liraglutide is
      a commercially available analogue of a gut hormone physiologically produced in our bowel in
      response to food, licenced for the treatment of overweight or obesity. Liraglutide will be
      offered to patients attending National Health System (NHS) or private clinics within
      indication and according to their agreed clinical management. Investigators aim to collect
      real-life information for this study along with planned clinical management from patients who
      agree to their treatment and to take part in our study. Patients will be able to withdraw
      from treatment and study at any time without giving any explanation.

      If successful, this study will help us combine clinical, biochemical and molecular
      information which will allow us to gain deeper understanding on the mechanisms behind the
      beneficial metabolic effects of Liraglutide in overweight and obesity. Data generated from
      this study will hopefully help us acquire funding for a larger multicentre study; the results
      of which can have substantial impact on millions of people with overweight or obesity around
      the world.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1) Obesity is a global pandemic with debilitating consequences. It affects both adults and
      children; however, the prevalence of overweight and obesity among children and adolescents
      aged 5-19 has risen dramatically from just 4% in 1975 to just over 18% in 2016, highlighting
      the seriousness of this problem. The rise has occurred similarly among both boys and girls:
      in 2016 18% of girls and 19% of boys were overweight. While just under 1% of children and
      adolescents aged 5-19 were obese in 1975, more 124 million children and adolescents (6% of
      girls and 8% of boys) were obese in 2016.

      Obesity is a major risk factor for noncommunicable diseases such as:

        1. Cardiovascular diseases (mainly heart disease and stroke), which were the leading cause
           of death in United States of America(USA);

        2. Diabetes Mellitus

        3. Musculoskeletal disorders (especially osteoarthritis - a highly disabling degenerative
           disease of the joints);

        4. Some forms of malignancy (including endometrial, breast, ovarian, prostate, liver,
           gallbladder, kidney, and colon);

        5. Infertility in both women and men. The risk for these noncommunicable diseases
           increases, with increases in Body Mass Index (BMI).

      2) Liraglutide is a derivative of human incretin (metabolic hormone) glucagon-like peptide-1
      (GLP-1) that is used as a long-acting glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonist, binding to
      the same receptors as does the endogenous metabolic hormone GLP-1 that stimulates insulin
      secretion. Liraglutide is licenced in USA and in European Union (EU), including United
      Kingdom (UK) for the management of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM) and Obesity or overweight
      when one or more metabolic co-morbidities are present.

      Saxenda (3mg Liraglutide once daily) is an Food &amp; Drug Administration (FDA)-approved,
      prescription injectable Glucagon Like Peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonist that, when used with
      a low-calorie diet and increased physical activity, can reduce excess weight in patients who
      are overweight (BMI ≥27Kg/m2) and additionally have weight-related medical problems (such as
      high blood pressure, high cholesterol, or insulin resistance/pre-diabetes), or obesity (BMI:
      &gt;30Kg/m2) to lose weight. Saxenda is licensed and available in the UK for the management of
      obesity and overweight.

      3) Metabolomics is the scientific study of chemical processes involving metabolites, the
      small molecule intermediates and products of metabolism. Specifically, metabolomics is the
      &quot;systematic study of the unique chemical fingerprints that specific cellular processes leave
      behind&quot;, the study of their small-molecule metabolite profiles. The metabolome represents the
      complete set of metabolites in a biological cell, tissue, organ or organism, which are the
      end products of cellular processes. This in emerging area of metabolic research and in this
      study, will provide insight into the mechanisms through which 3mg Liraglutide improves weight
      and other metabolic sequelae (i.e glucose and lipids homeostasis) in humans during treatment.
      To the extend of our knowledge, there is a very limited number of such studies; none of which
      reporting on the effects of 3mg Liraglutide. Our collaborator Professor Gyanendra Tripathi
      has kindly agreed to fund costs for metabolomics analysis of our human samples. Metabolomics
      analysis of human serum or plasma samples is going to be performed by applying Ultra
      Performance Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (UPLC-MS). UPLC-MS assay will provide
      untargeted study of water-soluble metabolites (HILIC LCMS) and untargeted study of lipid
      metabolites (C18 reversed phase LCMS). Analysis is going to be performed at School of
      Biosciences, University of Birmingham.

      4) MicroRNA (abbreviated miRNA) is a small non-coding RNA molecule (containing about 22
      nucleotides) found in plants, animals and some viruses, that functions in RNA silencing and
      post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression. While most miRNAs are located within the
      cell, some miRNAs, commonly known as circulating miRNAs or extracellular miRNAs, have also
      been found in extracellular environment, including various biological fluids and cell culture
      media. MiRNAs play crucial roles in the regulation of stem cell progenitors differentiating
      into adipocytes. Studies to determine what role pluripotent stem cells play in adipogenesis,
      were examined in the immortalized human bone marrow-derived stromal cell line hMSC-Tert20.
      Decreased expression of miRNA-155, miRNA-221, and miRNA-222, have been found during the
      adipogenic programming of both immortalized and primary human Mesenchymal Stem Cells (hMSCs),
      suggesting that they act as negative regulators of differentiation. Conversely, ectopic
      expression of the miRNAs 155,221, and 222 significantly inhibited adipogenesis and repressed
      induction of the master regulators Peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma(PPARγ)
      and CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein alpha (CEBPA). This paves the way for possible genetic
      obesity treatments. Our goal is however to see if treatment with 3mg Liraglutide will
      influence circulating miRNA levels. To the extent of our knowledge there is currently no
      study reporting this.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 18, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 18, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight changes related to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Weight reduction in kilograms from baseline while on treatment with 3mg Liraglutide once daily in patients with overweight (BMI: ≥27Kg/m2) or obesity (BMI: ≥30Kg/m2) with regards to:</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in fat and lean mass while on treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fat and lean mass changes in percentages from baseline using air displacement plethysmography and bioelectrical impedance techniques while on treatment with 3mg Liraglutide once daily for overweight and obesity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in an untargeted study of water-soluble metabolites (HILIC LCMS) while on treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ultra Performance Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (UPLC-MS) will be performed to measure plasma changes of water-soluble metabolites (HILIC LCMS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in an untargeted study of lipid metabolites (C18 reversed phase LCMS) while on treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ultra Performance Liquid Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (UPLC-MS) will be performed to measure plasma changes of lipid metabolites (C18 reversed phase LCMS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the expression of miRNA-155 while on treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Decreased expression of miRNA-155 has been found during the adipogenic programming of both immortalized and primary hMSCs, suggesting that it acts as negative regulators of fat cell differentiation. We will measure this in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the expression of miRNA-221 while on treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Decreased expression of miRNA-221 has been found during the adipogenic programming of both immortalized and primary hMSCs, suggesting that it acts as negative regulators of fat cell differentiation. We will measure this in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the expression of miRNA-222 while on treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Decreased expression of miRNA-222, has been found during the adipogenic programming of both immortalized and primary hMSCs, suggesting that it acts as negative regulators of fat cell differentiation. We will measure this in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in glucose and insulin from baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure changes in serum glucose and insulin from baseline while on treatment using ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in systolic blood pressure.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure systolic blood pressure changes from baseline while on treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes diastolic blood pressure.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure diastolic blood pressure changes from baseline while on treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in heart rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure heart rate changes from baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Infertility, Female</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will be recruited prospectively from the weight management and Polycystic Ovary Syndrome (PCOS) clinics at University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire (UHCW) NHS Trust following discussion with their treating physician, who will also be a member of the research team and joint agreement on initiation of treatment with 3mg Liraglutide once daily as per clinical management plan. Patients will additionally receive standard NHS Tier 3 lifestyle advice and support for the duration of the study. Lifestyle modification aimed at weight loss will be delivered by a dietician or other trained health care professional within individual sessions for a period of 6 months. Finally, all patients will be able to withdraw from treatment and/or the study at any point without giving any explanation. This will have no impact in their clinical management.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saxenda</intervention_name>
    <description>Obesity pharmacotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle modification</intervention_name>
    <description>Tier 3 NHS weight management</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metabolomics</intervention_name>
    <description>Small molecule intermediates and products of metabolism</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>miRNA</intervention_name>
    <description>Small non-coding RNA molecules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Investigators don't anticipate any specific difficulties with recruitment for this study as
        overweight and obesity are very common conditions, and there are very few licensed medical
        options offering substantial weight loss. Liraglutide is one of them. Additionally,
        investigators don't see any specific difficulties in managing this study as it will be &quot;
        part and parcel&quot; of our patients' routine clinical visits. Liraglutide is going to be
        offered to our patients as per clinical need and the decision to treat them with
        liraglutide is going to be made before their potential participation in our study. Patients
        therefore are not going to be receiving treatment because of their participation in our
        study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult participants [age ≥18 y.o without upper age limit (to the discretion of the
             investigators)].

          -  Body mass index (BMI) ≥ 30 kg/m2 without coexisting comorbidities or BMI ≥27Kg/m2 with
             comorbidities like hypertension, hyperlipidaemia, prediabetes or obstructive sleep
             apnoea.

          -  Willing to comply with study requirements and able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 or Type 2 diabetes mellitus

          -  History of chronic or acute pancreatitis

          -  Known active hepatitis or active liver disease

          -  Symptomatic gallstones or kidney stones, acute cholecystitis or history of duodenal
             inflammatory diseases including Crohn's Disease and Celiac Disease

          -  Persistent anaemia, defined as haemoglobin&lt;10 g/dl

          -  Chronic or acute renal impairment (eGFR &lt;30 ml/min/1.73m2)

          -  Active systemic infection (sepsis)

          -  Active malignancy within the last 5 years, including any form of thyroid cancer
             (including sporadic or familial medullary thyroid cancer) or personal, or family
             history of Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia type 2.

          -  Active illicit substance abuse or alcoholism

          -  Current pregnancy or breastfeeding at screening or 6 months previously

          -  Donated blood during the preceding 3 months or intention to do so before the end of
             the study.

          -  Any other mental or physical condition which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             makes the subject a poor candidate for clinical trial participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Georgios K. Dimitriadis</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Georgios K. Dimitriadis, MD, MSc, PhDc</last_name>
    <phone>02476965249</phone>
    <phone_ext>25249</phone_ext>
    <email>georgios.dimitriadis@uhcw.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Diane Sambrook</last_name>
    <phone>02476965249</phone>
    <phone_ext>02476965249</phone_ext>
    <email>diane.sambrook@uhcw.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>WISDEM Centre, University Hospitals Coventry and Warwickshire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Coventry</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>CV2 2DX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diane Sambrook</last_name>
      <phone>00442476965249</phone>
      <phone_ext>25249</phone_ext>
      <email>diane.sambrook@uhcw.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Danielle Bate</last_name>
      <phone>00442476966019</phone>
      <phone_ext>26019</phone_ext>
      <email>danielle.bate@uhcw.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>James WP. WHO recognition of the global obesity epidemic. Int J Obes (Lond). 2008 Dec;32 Suppl 7:S120-6. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2008.247. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19136980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>WHO annual report 2017; Obesity update - © OECD 2017</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>http://www.fda.gov/NewsEvents/Newsroom/PressAnnouncements/2010/ucm198638.htm</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>FDA approves weight-management drug Saxenda</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daviss, Bennett (April 2005).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jordan KW, Nordenstam J, Lauwers GY, Rothenberger DA, Alavi K, Garwood M, Cheng LL. Metabolomic characterization of human rectal adenocarcinoma with intact tissue magnetic resonance spectroscopy. Dis Colon Rectum. 2009 Mar;52(3):520-5. doi: 10.1007/DCR.0b013e31819c9a2c.</citation>
    <PMID>19333056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ambros V. The functions of animal microRNAs. Nature. 2004 Sep 16;431(7006):350-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15372042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bartel DP. MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function. Cell. 2004 Jan 23;116(2):281-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14744438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Extracellular/Circulating MicroRNAs: Release Mechanisms, Functions and Challenges</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>liraglutide</keyword>
  <keyword>saxenda</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolomics</keyword>
  <keyword>miRNA</keyword>
  <keyword>weight loss</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility, Female</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liraglutide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

