<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03889132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI18/01022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03889132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glucose, Brain and Microbiota</brief_title>
  <acronym>IRONMEt+CGM</acronym>
  <official_title>Integrated Analysis of the Interactions Between Glycemia and Microbiota Composition, and Their Impact on Brain Iron Deposition and Cognition in Subjects With Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut d'Investigació Biomèdica de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut d'Investigació Biomèdica de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The accumulation of iron is known to affect the functions of the liver, adipose tissue and
      muscle. The brain is a well-known place of iron deposition, which is associated with
      cognitive parameters of subjects with obesity.

      The hypothesis is that certain parameters related to glucose metabolism (glycemic
      variability, the circulating concentration of AGE receptor agonists, pentosidine and HbA1c)
      are associated with cognitive function, brain iron content and gut microbiota composition in
      subjects with obesity.

      The study includes both a cross-sectional (comparison of subjects with and without obesity)
      and a longitudinal design (evaluation one year after weight loss induced by bariatric surgery
      or by diet in patient with obesity) to evaluate the associations between continuous glucose
      monitoring, brain iron content (by magnetic resonance), cognitive function (by means of
      cognitive tests) and the composition of the microbiota, evaluated by metagenomics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects and methods:

      A. Cross-sectional study:

      Patients with obesity previously scheduled at the Service of Endocrinology, Diabetes and
      Nutrition (UDEN) of the Hospital &quot;Dr. Josep Trueta&quot; of Girona (Spain) will be recruited and
      studied. Subjects without obesity will also be recruited through a public announcement.

      A blood glucose sensor will be implanted for ten days, as well as a physical activity monitor
      to record physical activity during this period of time. Interstitial subcutaneous glucose
      concentrations will be monitored on an outpatient basis for a period of time of 10
      consecutive days using a glucose sensor validated by the FDA (Dexcom G6 ®). The sensor will
      be implanted in on day 0 and will retire on day 10 midmorning. Glucose records will
      preferably be evaluated on days 2 to 9 to avoid the bias caused by the insertion and removal
      of the sensor, which prevents a sufficient stabilization of the monitoring system. The
      characteristic glycemic pattern of each patient will be calculated on average from the
      profiles obtained on days 2 to 9.

      At the end of the week an magnetic resonance imaging will be done to evaluate the iron
      content in the brain and parameters of &quot;Diffusion Tensor Imaging&quot; in different brain
      territories.

      Cognitive tests will be carried out and feces will be collected for the study of the
      microbiota.

      The project will be carried out in subjects with obesity (20 men, 20 premenopausal women and
      20 women postmenopausal, BMI &gt; = 30kg/m2) and subjects without obesity, similar in age, sex
      and menopausal status (20 men, 20 premenopausal women and 20 postmenopausal women, BMI
      &lt;30kg/m2).

      B. Longitudinal study:

      After one year of follow-up, in which, subjects with obesity will undergo conventional
      treatment (hypocaloric diet and physical activity advise) or bariatric surgery for weight
      loss, a second visit will be carried out.

      For comparison, the same protocol of the cross-sectional study will be done again. See
      information above.

      Data collection of subjects of cross-sectional and longitudinal studies:

        -  Subsidiary data: Age, sex and birth date.

        -  Clinical variables: Weight, height, body mass index, waist and hip perimeters,
           waist-to-hip ratio, blood pressure (systolic and diastolic), fat mass and fat free-mass
           (bioelectric impedance and DEXA), smoking status, alcohol intake, registry of usual
           medicines and registry of antecedent relatives with obesity, diabetes and comorbidities.

        -  Laboratory variables: 15cc of blood will be extracted from fasted subjects to determine
           the following variables using the usual routine techniques of the clinical laboratory
           (hemogram, glucose, bilirubin, aspartate aminotransferase (AST/GOT), alanine
           aminotransferase (ALT/GPT), gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT), urea, creatinine, uric
           acid, total proteins, albumin, total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, LDL cholesterol,
           triglycerides, glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c), ferritin, soluble transferrin receptor,
           ultrasensitive C reactive protein, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, lipopolysaccharide
           binding protein, free thyroxine (free T4), thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) and
           baseline cortisol). An additional 15cc of blood (plasma-EDTA) will be extracted for
           further analyses.

        -  Stool samples collection: A stool sample will be provided from each patient. The sample
           should be collected at home or in the hospital, sent to the laboratory within 4 hours
           from the collection, fragmented and stored at -80ºC.

        -  Magnetic Resonance Imaging: All MRI examinations will be performed on a 1.5-T scanner
           (Ingenia ®; Philips Medical Systems). First, fluid-attenuated inversion recovery (FLAIR)
           sequence will be used to exclude subjects with preexisting brain lesions. Brain iron
           load will be assessed by means of R2* values. T2* relaxation data will be acquired with
           a multi-echo gradient-echo sequence with 10 equally spaced echoes (first echo=4.6ms;
           inter echo spacing=4.6ms; repetition time=1300ms). T2* will be calculated by fitting the
           single exponential terms to the signal decay curves of the respective multi-echo
           data.R2* values will be calculated as R2*=1/T2* and expressed as Hz. In addition, R2*
           values will be converted to μmol Fe/g units as previously validated on phantom tests.
           Brain iron images from control subjects will be normalized to a standard space using a
           template image for this purpose (EPI MNI template). Subsequently, all normalized images
           will be averaged for the determination of normal iron content. Normal values (mean and
           SD) will be also calculated for anatomical regions of interest using different atlas
           masks, addressing possible differences between gender and age. The brain iron comparison
           between control and obese subjects will be performed using voxel-based analysis.
           Obese-subjects images will be normalized to a standard space. The normalized image will
           be compared to normal population using t-test analysis with age and sex as co-variables.
           As result, a parametric map will show individual differences in iron deposition. Based
           on previous observational studies showing increased brain iron load at some specific
           regions and the evidence suggesting hippocampal and hypothalamic changes in association
           with obesity and insulin resistance, the statistical and image analyses will be focused
           on iron differences at the caudate, lenticular, thalamus, hypothalamus, hippocampus, and
           amygdala.

        -  Neuropsychological examination: General cognitive functioning will be measured using the
           Vocabulary and Similarities subtests of the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale-III
           (WAIS-III); attention and working memory by the Forward and Backward Digit Span subtest
           of the WAIS-II; memory using the California Verbal Learning Test II; executive functions
           by the Trail Making Test, the Color-Word Stroop Test and the Verbal Fluency; mood using
           the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 and impulsive behaviors using the Iowa Gambling Task.

        -  Microbiota composition: the microbiota composition will be analyzed according to a
           previous described protocol. 16s rRNA qPCR and LPS-binding protein in blood samples will
           be used for detection of bacterial translocation.

      The information will remain registered in a notebook and will be computerized in the database
      of the study.

      Statistical methods:

      Sample size: There are no previous data showing expected differences for sample size
      estimation regarding glucose variability, physical activity, composition of gut microbiota
      and cognitive function. In a previous study, differences in brain iron content were observed
      in 20 obese vs. 20 nonobese subjects. Thus, the proposed sample size is at least 20
      individuals per group, with balanced age and gender (pre- and postmenopausal women)
      representation.

      Statistical analyses: Firstly, normal distribution and homogeneity of variances will be
      tested. To determine differences between study groups, it will be used χ2 for categorical
      variables, unpaired Student's t-test in normal quantitative and Mann-Whitney U test for
      non-normal quantitative variables. Nonparametric Spearman analysis will be used to determine
      the correlation between quantitative variables. The same tests will also be used to study
      differences before and after follow-up. The significant associations, whether positive or
      negative, will be explored more-in-depth (simple and multivariate linear regression
      analyses).

      The microbiota composition will be analyzed and compared using HeatMaps, Principal Component
      Analysis (PCA) and PLSDA. For multivariate statistics (PLSDA and hierarchical clustering),
      variables comprising morphological tissue characteristics, gut microbiota and functional test
      will be log transformed, filtered using interquartile range estimate and scaled using
      auto-scaling calculation (mean-centered and divided by the standard deviation of each
      variable) by using the Metaboanalyst ® platform, the R ® package ropls and MATLAB ® scripts.
      Alpha and beta biodiversity will be compared according to obesity, insulin resistance and
      iron status. It will also be used SPSS ® statistical software and Minitab ®.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of advanced glycation end products (AGE) receptor agonists.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic variability.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean and standard deviation of glucose measures in mg/dL using a continuous glucose monitoring during 10 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on memory function</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>California Verbal Learning Test (CVLT): Measures verbal memory (Total score of the 12 trials); a higher score reflects a better memory function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on brain structure.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Brain structure will be assessed using magnetic resonance imaging.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on gut microbiota.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Gut microbiota will be analysed by metagenomics and metabolomics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline in circulating concentration of AGE receptor agonists and glycemic variability one year of follow-up after weight loss in association with changes in brain structure and gut microbiota.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects with obesity will be undertaken conventional treatment or bariatric surgery for weight loss; controls will not undergo any additional measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>6</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal women with obesity</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal women with obesity</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Men with obesity</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal women without obesity</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal women without obesity</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Men without obesity</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bariatric Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects with obesity (N=60) will be undertaken a hypocaloric diet and a periodic follow up, also 30 of them will undergo bariatric surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Men with obesity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Postmenopausal women with obesity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Premenopausal women with obesity</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with obesity, without known type 2 diabetes, previously scheduled at the Service
        of Endocrinology, Diabetes and Nutrition (UDEN) of the Hospital &quot;Dr. Josep Trueta&quot; of
        Girona (Spain) will be recruited and studied.

        Subjects without obesity will also be recruited through a public announcement.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Caucasian men and women aged 30-65 years.

          2. Informed consent for participation in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Serious systemic disease unrelated to obesity such as cancer, severe kidney, or liver
             disease, known type 1 or type 2 diabetes.

          2. Systemic diseases with intrinsic inflammatory activity such as rheumatoid arthritis,
             Crohn's disease, asthma, chronic infection (e.g., HIV, active tuberculosis) or any
             type of infectious disease.

          3. Pregnancy and lactation.

          4. Patients with severe disorders of eating behaviour.

          5. Persons whose liberty is under legal or administrative requirement.

          6. Clinical symptoms and signs of infection in the previous month.

          7. Antibiotic, antifungal or antiviral treatment in the previous 3 months.

          8. Anti-inflammatory chronic treatment with steroidal and/or non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs.

          9. Major psychiatric antecedents.

         10. Excessive alcohol intake, either acute or chronic (alcohol intake greater than 40 g a
             day (women) or 80 g/day (men)) or drugs abuse.

         11. Serum liver enzymes (AST, ALT) activity over twice the upper limit of normal.

         12. History of disturbances in iron balance (e.g., genetic hemochromatosis, hemosiderosis
             from any cause, atransferrinemia, paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>José Manuel Fernández-Real, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Biomèdica de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>José Manuel Fernández-Real, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+34 972 94 02 00</phone>
    <email>jmfreal@idibgi.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>María Arnoriaga Rodríguez, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+34 972 94 02 00</phone>
    <phone_ext>2325</phone_ext>
    <email>marnoriaga@idibgi.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut d'Investigació Biomèdica de Girona (IDIBGI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Girona</city>
        <zip>17007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yenny Leal</last_name>
      <phone>0034 972940200</phone>
      <phone_ext>2325</phone_ext>
      <email>yleal@idibgi.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marzena Wos</last_name>
      <phone>0034 972940200</phone>
      <phone_ext>2325</phone_ext>
      <email>mawos@idibgi.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finch C. Regulators of iron balance in humans. Blood. 1994 Sep 15;84(6):1697-702. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8080980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Real JM, Ricart-Engel W, Arroyo E, Balançá R, Casamitjana-Abella R, Cabrero D, Fernández-Castañer M, Soler J. Serum ferritin as a component of the insulin resistance syndrome. Diabetes Care. 1998 Jan;21(1):62-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9580307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Real JM, López-Bermejo A, Ricart W. Cross-talk between iron metabolism and diabetes. Diabetes. 2002 Aug;51(8):2348-54. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12145144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Real JM, Manco M. Effects of iron overload on chronic metabolic diseases. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2014 Jun;2(6):513-26. doi: 10.1016/S2213-8587(13)70174-8. Epub 2013 Dec 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24731656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Real JM, Blasco G, Puig J, Moreno M, Xifra G, Sánchez-Gonzalez J, Maria Alustiza J, Pedraza S, Ricart W, María Moreno-Navarrete J. Adipose tissue R2* signal is increased in subjects with obesity: A preliminary MRI study. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2016 Feb;24(2):352-8. doi: 10.1002/oby.21347. Epub 2015 Dec 26.</citation>
    <PMID>26813526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno-Navarrete JM, Blasco G, Xifra G, Karczewska-Kupczewska M, Stefanowicz M, Matulewicz N, Puig J, Ortega F, Ricart W, Straczkowski M, Fernández-Real JM. Obesity Is Associated With Gene Expression and Imaging Markers of Iron Accumulation in Skeletal Muscle. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2016 Mar;101(3):1282-9. doi: 10.1210/jc.2015-3303. Epub 2016 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26765579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno-Navarrete JM, Moreno M, Puig J, Blasco G, Ortega F, Xifra G, Ricart W, Fernández-Real JM. Hepatic iron content is independently associated with serum hepcidin levels in subjects with obesity. Clin Nutr. 2017 Oct;36(5):1434-1439. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2016.09.022. Epub 2016 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27745814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno-Navarrete JM, Rodríguez A, Becerril S, Valentí V, Salvador J, Frühbeck G, Fernández-Real JM. Increased Small Intestine Expression of Non-Heme Iron Transporters in Morbidly Obese Patients With Newly Diagnosed Type 2 Diabetes. Mol Nutr Food Res. 2018 Jan;62(2). doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201700301. Epub 2017 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>29082606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno-Navarrete JM, López-Navarro E, Candenas L, Pinto F, Ortega FJ, Sabater-Masdeu M, Fernández-Sánchez M, Blasco V, Romero-Ruiz A, Fontán M, Ricart W, Tena-Sempere M, Fernández-Real JM. Ferroportin mRNA is down-regulated in granulosa and cervical cells from infertile women. Fertil Steril. 2017 Jan;107(1):236-242. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2016.10.008. Epub 2016 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>27842994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geijselaers SLC, Sep SJS, Stehouwer CDA, Biessels GJ. Glucose regulation, cognition, and brain MRI in type 2 diabetes: a systematic review. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2015 Jan;3(1):75-89. doi: 10.1016/S2213-8587(14)70148-2. Epub 2014 Aug 24. Review. Erratum in: Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2015 Jan;3(1):e1.</citation>
    <PMID>25163604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geijselaers SLC, Sep SJS, Claessens D, Schram MT, van Boxtel MPJ, Henry RMA, Verhey FRJ, Kroon AA, Dagnelie PC, Schalkwijk CG, van der Kallen CJH, Biessels GJ, Stehouwer CDA. The Role of Hyperglycemia, Insulin Resistance, and Blood Pressure in Diabetes-Associated Differences in Cognitive Performance-The Maastricht Study. Diabetes Care. 2017 Nov;40(11):1537-1547. doi: 10.2337/dc17-0330. Epub 2017 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28842522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luchsinger JA, Ma Y, Christophi CA, Florez H, Golden SH, Hazuda H, Crandall J, Venditti E, Watson K, Jeffries S, Manly JJ, Pi-Sunyer FX; Diabetes Prevention Program Research Group. Metformin, Lifestyle Intervention, and Cognition in the Diabetes Prevention Program Outcomes Study. Diabetes Care. 2017 Jul;40(7):958-965. doi: 10.2337/dc16-2376. Epub 2017 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>28500216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kharabian Masouleh S, Beyer F, Lampe L, Loeffler M, Luck T, Riedel-Heller SG, Schroeter ML, Stumvoll M, Villringer A, Witte AV. Gray matter structural networks are associated with cardiovascular risk factors in healthy older adults. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2018 Feb;38(2):360-372. doi: 10.1177/0271678X17729111. Epub 2017 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28857651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ryan CM, Freed MI, Rood JA, Cobitz AR, Waterhouse BR, Strachan MW. Improving metabolic control leads to better working memory in adults with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2006 Feb;29(2):345-51.</citation>
    <PMID>16443885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weinstein G, Maillard P, Himali JJ, Beiser AS, Au R, Wolf PA, Seshadri S, DeCarli C. Glucose indices are associated with cognitive and structural brain measures in young adults. Neurology. 2015 Jun 9;84(23):2329-37. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000001655. Epub 2015 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25948725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rolandsson O, Backeström A, Eriksson S, Hallmans G, Nilsson LG. Increased glucose levels are associated with episodic memory in nondiabetic women. Diabetes. 2008 Feb;57(2):440-3. Epub 2007 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>17977953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marden JR, Mayeda ER, Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ, Kawachi I, Glymour MM. High Hemoglobin A1c and Diabetes Predict Memory Decline in the Health and Retirement Study. Alzheimer Dis Assoc Disord. 2017 Jan-Mar;31(1):48-54. doi: 10.1097/WAD.0000000000000182.</citation>
    <PMID>28225507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spauwen PJ, van Eupen MG, Köhler S, Stehouwer CD, Verhey FR, van der Kallen CJ, Sep SJ, Koster A, Schaper NC, Dagnelie PC, Schalkwijk CG, Schram MT, van Boxtel MP. Associations of advanced glycation end-products with cognitive functions in individuals with and without type 2 diabetes: the maastricht study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2015 Mar;100(3):951-60. doi: 10.1210/jc.2014-2754. Epub 2014 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25459912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chavan SS, Huerta PT, Robbiati S, Valdes-Ferrer SI, Ochani M, Dancho M, Frankfurt M, Volpe BT, Tracey KJ, Diamond B. HMGB1 mediates cognitive impairment in sepsis survivors. Mol Med. 2012 Sep 7;18:930-7. doi: 10.2119/molmed.2012.00195.</citation>
    <PMID>22634723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández Real JM, Moreno-Navarrete JM, Manco M. Iron influences on the Gut-Brain axis and development of type 2 diabetes. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2019;59(3):443-449. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2017.1376616. Epub 2017 Oct 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28886251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blasco G, Puig J, Daunis-I-Estadella J, Molina X, Xifra G, Fernández-Aranda F, Pedraza S, Ricart W, Portero-Otín M, Fernández-Real JM. Brain iron overload, insulin resistance, and cognitive performance in obese subjects: a preliminary MRI case-control study. Diabetes Care. 2014 Nov;37(11):3076-83. doi: 10.2337/dc14-0664. Epub 2014 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25125507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blasco G, Moreno-Navarrete JM, Rivero M, Pérez-Brocal V, Garre-Olmo J, Puig J, Daunis-I-Estadella P, Biarnés C, Gich J, Fernández-Aranda F, Alberich-Bayarri Á, Moya A, Pedraza S, Ricart W, López M, Portero-Otin M, Fernandez-Real JM. The Gut Metagenome Changes in Parallel to Waist Circumference, Brain Iron Deposition, and Cognitive Function. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2017 Aug 1;102(8):2962-2973. doi: 10.1210/jc.2017-00133.</citation>
    <PMID>28591831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kau AL, Ahern PP, Griffin NW, Goodman AL, Gordon JI. Human nutrition, the gut microbiome and the immune system. Nature. 2011 Jun 15;474(7351):327-36. doi: 10.1038/nature10213. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21677749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedersen HK, Gudmundsdottir V, Nielsen HB, Hyotylainen T, Nielsen T, Jensen BA, Forslund K, Hildebrand F, Prifti E, Falony G, Le Chatelier E, Levenez F, Doré J, Mattila I, Plichta DR, Pöhö P, Hellgren LI, Arumugam M, Sunagawa S, Vieira-Silva S, Jørgensen T, Holm JB, Trošt K; MetaHIT Consortium, Kristiansen K, Brix S, Raes J, Wang J, Hansen T, Bork P, Brunak S, Oresic M, Ehrlich SD, Pedersen O. Human gut microbes impact host serum metabolome and insulin sensitivity. Nature. 2016 Jul 21;535(7612):376-81. Epub 2016 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27409811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gera T, Sachdev HP. Effect of iron supplementation on incidence of infectious illness in children: systematic review. BMJ. 2002 Nov 16;325(7373):1142. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12433763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang SS, Jeraldo PR, Kurti A, Miller ME, Cook MD, Whitlock K, Goldenfeld N, Woods JA, White BA, Chia N, Fryer JD. Diet and exercise orthogonally alter the gut microbiome and reveal independent associations with anxiety and cognition. Mol Neurodegener. 2014 Sep 13;9:36. doi: 10.1186/1750-1326-9-36.</citation>
    <PMID>25217888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zeevi D, Korem T, Zmora N, Israeli D, Rothschild D, Weinberger A, Ben-Yacov O, Lador D, Avnit-Sagi T, Lotan-Pompan M, Suez J, Mahdi JA, Matot E, Malka G, Kosower N, Rein M, Zilberman-Schapira G, Dohnalová L, Pevsner-Fischer M, Bikovsky R, Halpern Z, Elinav E, Segal E. Personalized Nutrition by Prediction of Glycemic Responses. Cell. 2015 Nov 19;163(5):1079-1094. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2015.11.001.</citation>
    <PMID>26590418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quince C, Walker AW, Simpson JT, Loman NJ, Segata N. Corrigendum: Shotgun metagenomics, from sampling to analysis. Nat Biotechnol. 2017 Dec 8;35(12):1211. doi: 10.1038/nbt1217-1211b.</citation>
    <PMID>29220029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Biomèdica de Girona Dr. Josep Trueta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>José Manuel Fernández-Real</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator, clinical professor, section chief of Endocrinology and Nutrition Department of Josep Trueta University Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Continous Glucose Monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Iron content</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

