<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03881189</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E1518</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03881189</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Tolerance Evaluation of an Injective Treatment for the Area Around the Eyes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Tolerance Evaluation of an Intradermal Injective Treatment for the Area Around the Eyes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Derming SRL</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Derming SRL</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Efficacy and tolerance evaluation of an intradermal injective HA and aminoacids based
      treatment for the area around the eyes
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary end point of this study was to evaluate clinically and by non-invasive instrumental
      measurements the aesthetic performance on the area around the eyes of the&quot;SUNEKOS® 200&quot;
      injective treatment. Precisely three micro-injection sessions with an interval of 15 days
      were performed by a specialized dermatologist using periosteal and subepidermal injection
      techniques, on the area around the eyes of female volunteers with dark circles.

      An additional aim of this study is to evaluate the product tolerance by both the investigator
      and volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 28, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 12, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 12, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of wrinkles grade around the eyes</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline), T3i+1 (1 day after the 3rd injection treatment with Sunekos 200), T2M (after 2 months), T3M (after 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Visual score of crow's feet, according to a reference photographic scale from 0 (no wrinkles) to 7 (very marked wrinkles)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of dark circles grade</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline), T3i+1 (1 day after the 3rd injection treatment with Sunekos 200), T2M (after 2 months), T3M (after 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Visual score of dark circles grade, according to a reference photographic scale from 0 (absent) to 4 (very marked)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of roughness profilometric parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline), T3i+1 (1 day after the 3rd injection treatment with Sunekos 200), T2M (after 2 months), T3M (after 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Crow's feet profilometric parameters measured by Primos compact portable device (GFMesstechnik). Ra is average roughness of the analysed profile, Rt is wrinkles total high, Rv is wrinkles maximum depth.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of dark circles colorimetric parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline), T3i+1 (1 day after the 3rd injection treatment with Sunekos 200), T2M (after 2 months), T3M (after 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Dark circles colorimetric measured by Chroma Meter CR-200® . L* represent the lightness of the colour, a* represent the red component of the colour, b* represent the dark component of the colour</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of spectrophotometrical value</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline), T3i+1 (1 day after the 3rd injection treatment with Sunekos 200), T2M (after 2 months), T3M (after 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Dark circles spectrophotometrical color value measured by a visible-UV-IR spectrophotometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change from of photographic documentation</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (baseline), T3i+1 (1 day after the 3rd injection treatment with Sunekos 200), T2M (after 2 months), T3M (after 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Photographic documentation of the area around the eyes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Under-eyes Dark Circles</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SUNEKOS ® 200</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 1st intradermal treatment (T1i) with &quot;Sunekos ® 200&quot; was carried out during the basal visit (T0), after basal evaluations planned by the study procedure, and then repeated 2 more times with an interval of 15 days (T2i and T3i)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SUNEKOS® 200</intervention_name>
    <description>The intradermal injection procedure was performed bilaterally, on the area around the eyes including the eyelids, using periosteal and subepidermal injection techniques. This injective procedure consists of micro-wheals of 0.2 ml just above the periosteum and micro-wheals of 0.1 ml very superficially, just under epidermis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SUNEKOS ® 200</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  female sex,

          -  30-65 years,

          -  dark circles,

          -  available and able to return to the study site for the post-procedural follow-up
             examinations;

          -  agreeing to present at each study visit without make-up;

          -  accepting to not change their habits regarding food, physical activity, make-up use,
             face cosmetic and cleansing products;

          -  accepting not to expose their face to strong UV irradiation (UV session, or sun
             bathes) during the entire duration of the study, without appropriate sun protection;

          -  accepting to sign the informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy;

          -  lactation;

          -  smokers;

          -  alcohol or drug abusers;

          -  subjects not in menopause who do not use adequate contraceptive precautions in order
             to avoid pregnancies during the study;

          -  subjects not in menopause who do not accept to perform the pregnancy test at T0
             (before the 1st aesthetic procedure) and at T3i (1 month after the 1st injection
             treatment execution, before the 3rd aesthetic procedure);

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) variation (± 1) during the study period;

          -  performing skin treatments for aesthetic correction (biomaterials implants, face
             lifting, botox injections, laser, chemical peeling) in the 6 months prior to the study
             start;

          -  performing permanent filler in the past;

          -  change in the normal habits regarding food, physical activity, face cosmetic,
             cleansing and make-up use during the month preceding the test;

          -  sensitivity to the test product or its ingredients (to be assessed by the investigator
             during the baseline visit);

          -  subjects whose insufficient adhesion to the study protocol is foreseeable;

          -  participation in a similar study currently or during the previous 9 months.

          -  Dermatitis;

          -  presence of cutaneous disease on the tested area, as lesions, scars, malformations;

          -  recurrent facial/labial herpes;

          -  clinical and significant skin condition on the test area (e.g. active eczema,
             psoriasis, severe rosacea, scleroderma, local infections and severe acne).

          -  Diabetes;

          -  endocrine disease;

          -  hepatic disorder;

          -  renal disorder;

          -  cardiac disorder;

          -  pulmonary disease;

          -  cancer;

          -  neurological or psychological disease;

          -  inflammatory/immunosuppressive disease;

          -  drug allergy.

          -  Anticoagulants and antiplatelet drugs, anti-histaminic, topic and systemic
             corticosteroids, narcotic, antidepressant, immunosuppressive drugs (with the except of
             contraceptive or hormonal treatment starting more than 1 year ago);

          -  using of drugs able to influence the test results in the investigator opinion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DERMING</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20159</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Derming SRL</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adele Sparavigna</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

