<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03881267</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STE-VLU-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03881267</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SkinTE™ in the Treatment of Venous Leg Wounds</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-center, Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial Evaluating the Effects of SkinTE™ in the Treatment of Venous Leg Ulcers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PolarityTE</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Professional Education and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PolarityTE</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, multi-center, randomized controlled trial designed to collect
      patient outcome data on a commercially available human autologous homologous skin construct
      with SOC dressing compared to SOC dressings alone in the treatment of Venous Leg Wounds
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, multi-center, Randomized Controlled Trial ( RCT ) designed to
      collect patient outcome data on a commercially available human autologous homologous skin
      construct (SkinTE™) with SOC dressing compared to SOC dressings alone in the treatment of
      Venous Leg Wounds (VLU) .The trial will be single blinded in regard to wound healing
      assessment (another clinician, other than the investigator at each site will assess wound
      healing) and confirmation of wound healing will be overseen by an independent adjudication
      committee made up of wound care experts. The study will last thirteen weeks, with a two week
      screening period prior to enrollment.

      There are two arms in the study:

      Arm 1: The Experimental Arm , that will include SOC Therapy. SOC therapy in this study is
      appropriate sharp or surgical debridement, infection management (systemic antibiotics only in
      conjunction with debridement) and the experimental wound care covering with human
      autologous,homologous skin construct (SkinTE™) followed by a moisture retention dressing and
      a padded 3-layer dressing comprised of 4x4 gauze pads, soft roll and compression wrap
      (DynaflexTM or equivalent).

      Arm 2: The Standard of Care Arm. The SOC therapy in this study is appropriate sharp or
      surgical debridement, infection management (systemic antibiotics only in conjunction with
      debridement) and wound care covering with calcium alginate Fibracol dressing followed by a
      moisture retentive dressing and a padded 3-layer dressing comprised of 4x4 gauze pads, soft
      roll and compressive wrap (DynaflexTM or equivalent).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multi-center, Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial Evaluating the Effect of Human Homologous Autologous Skin Construct (SkinTE™) in the Treatment of Venous Leg Ulcers</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of index ulcers healed at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>examine percent of ulcers healed at week twelve</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage area reduction at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>examine percent of wound reduction at 4 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage area reduction at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>examine percent of wound reduction at 6 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage area reduction at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>examine percent of wound reduction at 8 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage are reduction at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>examine percent of wound reduction at 12 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in quality of life using Wound Quality of Life Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Wound-QoL, or wound quality of life questionnaire, measures the disease-specific, health-related quality of life of patients with chronic wounds. It consists of 17 items on impairments which are always assessed in retrospect to the preceding seven days. This questionnaire will be given to clinical trial participants at each visit, with the scale scores recorded. Each question is scored. Answers to each item are coded with numbers (0='not at all' to 4='very much'). As noted above the score will be reported with a minimam score of &quot;0&quot; and a maximum score of 68</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain levels during trial, using the FACES pain scales which measure pain on a range of 0-10, zero being no pain and 10 being the most severe pain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The FACES pain scale will be administered to the clinical trial participants at each visit. The trial participant will select their pain level with a series of faces that correspond to a number between 0 which implies no pain , up to 10 which implies the most severe pain. The scores will be recorded for each clinical trial participant on each visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Visible Graft Take at each visit</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Examine the take or the bodies ability to accept the Skin TE</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Leg Ulcer</condition>
  <condition>Venous Stasis</condition>
  <condition>Venous Stasis Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Human Autologous Homologous Skin Construct (SkinTE™)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SkinTE™, is an autologous, homologous, FDA-registered, cutaneous human cellular and tissue-based product (HCT/P) that can be used an adjunct to standard of care, for skin coverage in patients who have suffered from a venous leg wound in conjunction with standard wound care and Additional (outer) Dressing Application with moisture retention dressing and compression</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fibracol Wound Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A commercially available wound dressing to be used per manufacturer's instructions for use on venous leg wounds in conjunction with standard wound care and Additional (outer) Dressing Application with moisture retention dressing moisture retention dressing and compression</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Human Autologous Homologous Skin Construct</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of a autologous human derived skin polar units</description>
    <arm_group_label>Human Autologous Homologous Skin Construct (SkinTE™)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SkinTE™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Additional Outer Dressing Application</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of Moisture retentive dressing, and a multi-layer compression dressing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fibracol Wound Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Human Autologous Homologous Skin Construct (SkinTE™)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>•Outer protective and compressive dressing</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fibracol Wound Dressing</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of Collagen Alginate Dressing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fibracol Wound Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Collegen Alginate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least 18 years old.

          -  Presence of a VLU on the leg, below the knee but above the aspect of the medial
             malleolus, extending at least through the dermis or subcutaneous tissue but not
             involving tendon, muscle, or bone.

          -  The index ulcer will be the largest ulcer if two or more VLUs are present and will be
             the only one evaluated in the study. If other ulcerations are present on the same
             foot, they must be more than 2 cm distant from the index ulcer.

          -  Index ulcer (i.e. current episode of ulceration) has been present for greater than
             four weeks prior to the initial screening visit, as of the date subject consents for
             study.

          -  Index ulcer is a minimum of 2.0 cm2 and a maximum of 20 cm2 at first screening visit
             (SV1) and first treatment visit (TV1).

          -  Adequate circulation to the affected extremity as documented by a dorsal
             transcutaneous oxygen measurement (TCOM) or a skin perfusion pressure (SPP)
             measurement of ≥ 30 mmHg, or an Ankle Branchial Index (ABI) between ≥ 0.7 and ≤ 1.2 or
             Arterial Doppler with a minimum of biphasic flow within 3 months of SV1, using the
             affected study extremity.

          -  The index ulcer has been treated with high compression for at least 14 days prior to
             randomization (30-40 mm Hg).

          -  Females of childbearing potential must be willing to use acceptable methods of
             contraception (birth control pills, barriers or abstinence) during the course of the
             study and undergo pregnancy tests.

          -  Subject understands and is willing to participate in the clinical study and can comply
             with weekly visits and follow-up regimen.

          -  Subject has read and signed the IRB/IEC approved Informed Consent Form before
             screening procedures have been completed.

          -  The index ulcer has a clean granular base, is free of necrotic debris, and appears to
             be healthy vascularized tissue at time of placement of treatment product.

          -  Subject is deemed healthy and stable for treatment based per PI discretion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with a BMI ≥45

          -  Index ulcer(s) deemed by the investigator to be caused by a medical condition other
             than venous insufficiency.

          -  Known allergy to the components of the multi-layer compression bandaging, or who
             cannot tolerate multi-layer compression therapy.

          -  Index ulcer, in the opinion of the investigator, is suspicious for cancer and should
             undergo an ulcer biopsy to rule out a carcinoma of the ulcer.

          -  Subjects on any investigational drug(s) or therapeutic device(s) within 30 days
             preceding the first Screening Visit (SV1).

          -  History of radiation at the ulcer site (regardless of time since last radiation
             treatment).

          -  Index ulcer has been previously treated or will need to be treated with any prohibited
             therapies, such as chlorhexidine or collagenase. (See Section 7.3 of this protocol for
             a list of prohibited medications and therapies).

          -  Subjects with a history of more than two weeks treatment with immunosuppressants
             (including systemic corticosteroids &gt; 10mg daily dose), cytotoxic chemotherapy, or
             application of topical steroids to the ulcer surface within one month prior to first
             Screening visit, or who receive such medications during the screening period, or who
             are anticipated to require such medications during the study.

          -  Study ulcer requiring negative pressure wound therapy during the course of the trial.

          -  Ulcers on the dorsum of the foot or with more than 50% of the ulcer below the
             malleolus are excluded.

          -  Presence of any condition(s) which seriously compromises the subject's ability to
             complete this study or has a known history of poor adherence with medical treatment.

          -  Subject is pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Presence of diabetes with poor metabolic control as documented with an HbA1c ≥12.0
             within 30 days of randomization.

          -  Subjects with end stage renal disease as evidenced by a creatinine greater than
             3.0mg/dl within 120 days of randomization.

          -  Target wound has presence of local active soft tissue infection involving the
             treatment site.

          -  Index ulcer has reduced in area by 30% or more after 14 days of SOC from SV1 to the
             TV1/randomization visit.

          -  In the opinion of the Investigator, evidence of unstable human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV), hepatitis B or hepatitis C at screening.

          -  Vascular surgery; arterial or venous to the affected extremity within 30 days of
             screening
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Armstrong, DPM, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>USC/ Salsa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nikolai A Sopko, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8005603983</phone>
    <email>clinicalresearch@polarityte.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashlee Fishleigh, BS</last_name>
    <phone>8005603983</phone>
    <email>clinicalresearch@polarityte.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martinsville Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Martinsville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23116</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kim Young</last_name>
      <email>kyoung@periedu.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nathan Young, DPM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Professional Education and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roanoke</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles Zelen, DPM</last_name>
      <phone>540-797-2726</phone>
      <email>cmzelen@periedu.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Morgan Stepanek, MBA</last_name>
      <phone>540 797 2726</phone>
      <email>mstepanek@periedu.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chalres m Zelen, DPM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>VLU</keyword>
  <keyword>Ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>SkinTE™</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

