<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03882034</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>190071</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-CH-0071</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03882034</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Pegvisomant in Children With Growth Hormone Excess</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Phase 3 Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Pegvisomant in Children With Growth Hormone Excess</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      For children with gigantism, too much growth hormone (GH) in the body causes abnormal growth
      and many other problems. Current treatments often don t work; no medical treatment is
      approved by FDA. Researchers want to see if the drug pegvisomant can help.

      Objective:

      To test the role of pegvisomant in children and adolescents with gigantism.

      Eligibility:

      People ages 2-18 with GH excess for whom usual treatments have not worked or who are not
      eliginle for them

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with a medical history.

      The study will last 60 weeks and include at least 3 visits: baseline, 6-month, and 12-month
      visits. For the baseline visit, participants will stay a few nights for testing. They may
      stay overnight for the other visits.

      All visits will include:

      Medical history

      Physical exam

      Questionnaires

      Heart and liver tests

      Participants may be photographed in their underwear if they agree.

      Blood tests: Participants will get a catheter: A small plastic tube will be placed in an arm
      vein. For some tests, the blood may be drawn every 30 minutes over 3 hours. For other tests,
      blood will be drawn every 20 minutes over 12 hours. Only clinically necessary tests will be
      done in each patient.

      At the baseline visit, participants will have the study drug injected under the skin. They
      will learn to take the injection at home. They will take the injection daily during the
      study.

      The baseline and 12-month visits will include:

      MRI: Participants will have a dye injected into a vein. They will lie in a machine that takes
      pictures of the body.

      Hand X-ray

      Participants must get their height and weight at their local doctor s office monthly.

      Participants must have blood and urine tests at their local lab monthly for the first 6
      months then every 3 months until the study ends.

      ...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Growth hormone excess is a rare and potentially lethal condition associated with
      hypersecretion of growth hormone (GH), usually by a pituitary tumor or hyperplasia. When it
      occurs prior to the complete fusion of growth plates, it leads to pathological tall stature,
      and it is called gigantism. After the fusion of the growth plates, it is called acromegaly.
      It may be associated with debilitating cardiovascular disease and/or diabetes. Children and
      adolescents with gigantism are currently treated with surgery, radiation therapy, and
      medications, such as octreotide, to reduce hypersecretion of GH; however, these treatments
      may lack efficacy and have significant side effects. Pegvisomant is a genetically engineered
      GH-receptor (GHR antagonist that blocks the action of GH. In adults with acromegaly,
      pegvisomant has been shown to effectively reduce serum insulin-likegrowth factor type 1
      (IGF-1) concentrations and lead to clinical improvement. However, experience in children and
      adolescents is limited to a small number of case series. We propose the initiation of a new
      protocol at the NICHD, NIH, to treat children and adolescents with GH excess that is
      refractory to surgical therapy and/or radiation therapy, or in children and adolescents where
      the above therapies are contraindicated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change of IGF-1 z-score from baseline to end of study (12 month visit).</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is decrease in IGF-1 z-score &gt;50% from baseline. This criterion will be used to determine efficacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety and tolerability of pegvisomant in children with GH excess</measure>
    <time_frame>During 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be determined by the periodical description of vital signs, laboratory and imaging studies, and other reported side effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Normalization of IGF-1 for age and sex from baseline to end of study (12 month visit)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Normalization of the IGF-1 for age and sex from baseline to end of study (normal value defined as +/- 2 SD from the mean).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Normalization of growth velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in growth velocity to a near-normal range (+/- 1 SD) according to the Tanner and Davies growth velocity curves for age, sex, and stage of puberty, when comparing the 6-month period prior to the study drug initiation to the growth velocity between 6 and 12 months on the study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in signs and symptoms of GH excess and quality of life from baseline to end of study (12 month visit)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement in signs and symptoms of GH excess that are common in the pediatric population (headaches, excessive perspiration, fatigue, increased appetite) and the quality of life of the patients from baseline to the end of the study (12 month visit).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular ejection fraction change on echocardiogram from baseline to end of study (12 month visit).</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement of the cardiac structure and function: reduction of the left ventricular mass index (LVMi), and change of the left ventricular ejection fraction (EF) on echocardiogram from baseline to the end of the study (12 month visit).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of the left ventricular mass index (LVMi) on echocardiogram from baseline to end of study (12 month visit)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>(LVMi), and change of the left ventricular ejection fraction (EF) on echocardiogram from baseline to the end of the study (12 month visit).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pituitary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention arm, Patient received pegvisomant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pegvisomant</intervention_name>
    <description>A fixed dose of pegvisomant 10-mg started on Day 1 of intervention and continued daily afterwards, will be administered subcutaneously according to manufacturer's recommendations. Adjustment of the dose will occur as per protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Males and females 24 months to &lt;18 years at informed consent

          -  Active GH excess as demonstrated by the following:

               -  IGF-1 greater than the upper limit of normal for age and sex during screening
                  (&gt;+2 SD) and

               -  Abnormal GH levels as demonstrated by inability to suppress to &lt;1 ng/mL within 2
                  hours during Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT) after the administration of
                  1.75gr/kg (max 75gr) of glucose or elevated GH secretion profile during overnight
                  sampling.

          -  History of inadequate response to trans-sphenoidal surgery or radiation therapy for GH
             secreting pituitary tumor, or inability to tolerate surgery or radiation therapies or
             patient deemed inappropriate candidate for surgery and/or pituitary radiation therapy,
             as determined by review of the medical records by the Principal Investigator. The
             evaluation of the patient should be performed at least 3 months after the surgery date
             in order to ensure that there is persistent GH excess after the transsphenoidal
             resection of the tumor. If the patient has received irradiation, there is no minimium
             time to be considered before enrolling in the study. The effects of radiation therapy
             take place over many years after receiving it (mean time to remission for stereotactic
             radiation therapy of 12-60 months), and, thus, a medical therapy is required during
             that period.

          -  Willingness to discontinue other medications for the treatment of GH excess for a
             6-week washout period prior to initiating pegvisomant

          -  Able to provide consent/assent if developmentally appropriate

          -  Willing to use non-hormonal method of contraception in patients of reproductive
             potential. Females of reproductive age (Tanner 3 or more, and/or having menstrual
             cycle) will be educated on the risks of unknown potential fetal harm while using the
             investigational medication, and they will be educated on the alternative preventative
             methods for contraception (condoms). Females already receiving oral contraceptive
             pills (OCPs) will be evaluated by gynecology consult service to discuss effective
             non-hormonal contraception. Sexually active female subjects must agree to use an
             effective non-hormonal contraception for the duration of the study.

          -  Have a primary health care provider in home location who will perform monthly height
             and weight measurements, vital signs, and safety labs.

        Height and weight will be requested to be performed according to the published methods
        included in the CDC-NHANES manual on anthropometry procedures manual (Supplementary
        Material).

        They will be plotted on the respective growth charts produced by the CDC for the US
        population (Supplementary Material).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Liver function abnormalities (ALT, AST) greater than or equal to 3 times ULN

          -  Positive pregnancy test in females, current pregnancy and/or female patients who are
             breastfeeding.

          -  Patients currently using opioids. Opioids induce altered metabolism of pegvisomant.
             Since this is a phase 3 study, opioids may affect the PK studies to be performed and,
             thus, chronic use of opioids (&gt;2 weeks) will be an exclusion criterion.

          -  Patients with any medical, physical, psychiatric, or social condition, which, in the
             opinion of the investigators, would make participation in this protocol not in their
             best interest, will be excluded from the study. Patients who are critically ill,
             unstable, or with severe organ failure that may affect/limit the endocrine evaluation
             and place unsustainable demands on CC or NICHD resources will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Constantine A Stratakis, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christina Tatsi, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-7170</phone>
    <email>christina.tatsi3@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2019-CH-0071.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trainer PJ, Drake WM, Katznelson L, Freda PU, Herman-Bonert V, van der Lely AJ, Dimaraki EV, Stewart PM, Friend KE, Vance ML, Besser GM, Scarlett JA, Thorner MO, Parkinson C, Klibanski A, Powell JS, Barkan AL, Sheppard MC, Malsonado M, Rose DR, Clemmons DR, Johannsson G, Bengtsson BA, Stavrou S, Kleinberg DL, Cook DM, Phillips LS, Bidlingmaier M, Strasburger CJ, Hackett S, Zib K, Bennett WF, Davis RJ. Treatment of acromegaly with the growth hormone-receptor antagonist pegvisomant. N Engl J Med. 2000 Apr 20;342(16):1171-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10770982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lodish MB, Trivellin G, Stratakis CA. Pituitary gigantism: update on molecular biology and management. Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes. 2016 Feb;23(1):72-80. doi: 10.1097/MED.0000000000000212. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26574647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katznelson L, Laws ER Jr, Melmed S, Molitch ME, Murad MH, Utz A, Wass JA; Endocrine Society. Acromegaly: an endocrine society clinical practice guideline. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2014 Nov;99(11):3933-51. doi: 10.1210/jc.2014-2700. Epub 2014 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25356808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 30, 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Gigantism</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth Hormone</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acromegaly</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

