<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03881202</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NHC-TBI-PoNS-CE OHSU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03881202</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PoNS Clinical Experience Program (TBI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Study of Safety and Effectiveness of the Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS®) Treatment for Subjects With a Chronic Balance Deficit Due to Mild-to-moderate Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neurohabilitation Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Neurohabilitation Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      - Brief Summary: Prospective, cohort, open-label study. The cohort consists of people who
      have a chronic balance dysfunction due to a mild to moderate traumatic brain injury (TBI).
      All participants will participate in a 14-week PoNS Treatment protocol - a combination of
      symptom specific physical exercises and repeated use of the PoNS device.

      Subjects who meet the initial screening entrance criteria will be scheduled for a baseline
      assessment to evaluate balance and gait. Subjects will then begin the PoNS Treatment program
      and re-perform some assessments at 2, 5 and 14 weeks evaluating their functional
      improvements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in balance score (SOT) from baseline to the end of 14 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 5 weeks and 14 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild to Moderate Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PoNS Treatment will consist of three stages: an in-clinic training program, a home training program, and an extended home training program. During all stages of the study, subjects will complete three training sessions per day, morning, afternoon and evening, 6 days per week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PoNS Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>PoNS Treatment will consist of three stages: an in-clinic training program, a home training program, and an extended home training program. During all stages of the study, subjects will complete three training sessions per day, morning, afternoon and evening, 6 days per week.
Daily Training Program: The same daily training program will be performed during all stages with the exception of the morning BAT session, which is not performed during stage 2 or 3:
Morning:
Warm Up Exercises without the PoNS Balance Training with PoNS Gait Training with PoNS Breathing and Awareness Training (BAT) with PoNS 3- to 4-hour break between morning and afternoon sessions
Afternoon:
Balance Training with PoNS Movement Control Training without PoNS Gait Training with PoNS
Evening:
Breathing and Awareness Training with PoNS To be performed at home during all stages</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Criteria for Inclusion/Exclusion:

        Subjects must present with a chronic balance deficit due to mild-to-moderate TBI. However,
        other potentially related symptoms, such as gait disturbance, mild to moderate recurrent
        headaches, sleep, memory, attention, and cognitive deficits, will be noted on the data
        collection form at screening and each subsequent evaluation.

        Inclusion Criteria: Subjects must meet all of the following criteria to be included in the
        study:

          1. At least 18 years of age, inclusive, at the time of screening.

          2. Acceptable results (as determined by the investigator) of a full history and physical
             performed or supervised by the investigator at each site. This will include a careful
             examination of the tongue and oral cavity for any abnormalities. History should
             include the nature and duration of any prior physical therapy program the subject may
             have participated in to address the balance and/or gait symptoms of their TBI. Prior
             participation in therapy is not a prerequisite for enrollment in the program

          3. Documentation on the history of a qualifying TBI, mild to moderate in severity. For
             reference, the Armed Forces Health Surveillance Branch (AFHSB) definitions of mild and
             moderate TBI will be used. The definitions are as follows:

          4. Mild TBI: Confused or disoriented state which lasts less than 24 hours; or loss of
             consciousness for up to 30 minutes, or memory loss lasting less than 24 hours.
             Excludes penetrating TBI.

          5. Moderate TBI: Confused or disoriented state which lasts more than 24 hours; and/or
             loss of consciousness for more than 30 minutes but less than 24 hours, or memory loss
             lasting greater than 24 hours but less than seven days; or meets criteria for Mild TBI
             except an abnormal CT scan is present. Excludes penetrating TBI.

             The investigator will ascertain whether the prior medical records and information
             collected during the clinical interview are sufficiently detailed to support the
             classification of the TBI.

          6. Acceptable results from within the last three (3) months as determined by the site
             investigator of basic standard blood work to include CBC, TSH, HbA1C, Liver and Kidney
             panels, and a 12-lead ECG with automated reporting capability. Any abnormal result
             that is judged clinically significant by the investigator will be communicated to the
             subject and if treated by their personal physician and deemed recovered, the subjects
             may be reconsidered for inclusion. If the investigator is uncertain he or she will
             communicate with the Sponsor's Medical Officer.

          7. If female, the subject is not pregnant, not breastfeeding and has a negative pregnancy
             test prior to receipt of the PoNS device

             - Note: Pregnancy testing will be repeated at end-of-study (EOS) (i.e., end of at-home
             period).

          8. If female is of childbearing potential, the subject agrees to use adequate
             contraception from screening and throughout the study period.

             A female of non-childbearing potential is defined as a subject who is postmenopausal
             (continuous amenorrhea for 12 months) or surgically sterile (defined as bilateral
             tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or hysterectomy).

          9. Balance disorder as indicated by the NeuroCom® Sensory Organization Test (SOT)
             composite score at least 16 points below normal [adjusted for age and height, based on
             normative data] due to a mild-to-moderate traumatic brain injury (TBI).

         10. At least three (3) months post most recent TBI at the time of screening.

         11. Stable neurologic status, as determined from subject's medical records and the study
             physician's opinion based on no new or changing symptoms.

         12. Qualifying MRI report to be entered into the data collection form. For all
             participants who do not have a qualifying MRI, a new MRI will be obtained.

         13. Ambulatory and able to walk continuously over-ground or on a treadmill for 20 minutes,
             level grade (no inclination) and at any speed, with support, if needed.

         14. Able to understand the study procedures and give informed consent.

         15. Willing and able to adhere to the study schedule.

         16. Willing to complete a neuropsychological evaluation if deemed necessary by the
             investigator prior to inclusion in the study.

             Exclusion Criteria: Subjects meeting any of the following criteria will be excluded
             from the study:

         17. Medical findings from screening history, physical examination or radiological test
             that the investigator deems clinically significant or that would otherwise impact
             patient safety or data integrity.

        2. Planned use or use of any investigational product (i.e., not approved by the FDA),
        pharmaceutical or device, within 30 days preceding receipt of the PoNS device and during
        the entire period of subject participation.

        3. Any previous use of the Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS)

        4. Balance or gait deficits due to lower extremity injury or neurological condition other
        than TBI.

        5. Severe TBI defined as an injury with a confused or disoriented state which lasts more
        than 24 hours; and/or loss of consciousness for more than 24 hours, or memory loss for more
        than seven days.

        6. Penetrating brain injury, refractory subdural hematoma, tumor, other space occupying
        lesion, arteriovenous malformation or craniotomy unrelated to the resolution of qualifying
        traumatic brain injury. Investigator discretion may be exercised on an individual case
        where surgery was performed that did not remove or significantly alter brain tissue (e.g.,
        to treat a brain aneurysm). Surgery must have been performed at least 6 months prior to
        screening and a CT scan must be provided to demonstrate no large residual lesions.

        7. Oral health problems active at the time of recruitment. Any history of oral health
        problems (e.g., gum disease or cankers) will be noted on the data collection form.

        8. Oral surgery within 3 months of screening. 9. History of oral cancer. 10. Non-removable
        metal orthodontic devices (e.g., braces) or oral cavity piercings that could interfere with
        PoNS use.

        11. Presence of metallic implant or other MRI-incompatible device. 12. Known allergy to
        gold, nickel or copper. 13. Blood pressure abnormalities considered clinically significant
        by the study physician. If the subject has an average systolic blood pressure of &lt;100 mmHg,
        they will be evaluated for orthostatic hypotension and if the investigator deems this a
        risk for the subject's health or safety they will be excluded. If systolic blood pressure
        &gt;160 mm Hg (average of 3 measurements) at screening and the subject is on medications, the
        subject will be re-evaluated once the treating physician deems them to have stable blood
        pressure.

          -  Note: BP should be measured seated, legs uncrossed, after resting for 5 minutes, with
             measurements taken 2 minutes apart. Two BP readings should be taken and averaged. If
             the first two readings differ by &gt;5 mm Hg, a third measurement should be taken and an
             average calculated for all 3 values.

             14. Use of Coumadin or any other anticoagulant other than aspirin in the last six
             months.

             15. Untreated or undiagnosed diabetes - the subject will be referred to their family
             physician and may be re-evaluated at a later date. Undiagnosed diabetes is defined as
             an HbA1C taken during screening above the upper limit of normal at the study site.

             16. Diabetic neuropathy. 17. Active or recent (within 1 year) treatment for any
             cancer, excluding basal cell carcinoma.

             18. Neurological disorders other than those attributed to the primary diagnosis,
             (e.g., neurodegenerative diseases such as Multiple Sclerosis (MS), Parkinson's disease
             (PD), Alzheimer's disease (AD) or other dementia, Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS).

             19. History of epileptic or other seizure disorders. 20. Known ischemic heart disease
             (angina, stent, history of myocardial infarction, &gt;70% stenosis or cardiovascular
             imaging) and/or history or atrial or ventricular arrhythmias with or without syncope.
             Any abnormality on the screening ECG will be referred to the subject's family
             physician for evaluation and clearance and then the subject can be re-evaluated for
             inclusion in the study.

             21. Any other untreated or unstable acute or chronic, clinically significant medical
             condition for which the subject is currently undergoing treatment (e.g., autoimmune or
             immunodeficient disorders) and that the investigator deems unsuitable for inclusion.

             22. Use of a lower extremity biomechanical prosthetic with the exception of a splint
             to address foot drop.

             23. Chronic use of any potentially interfering drug such as a neuroactive (ototoxic,
             anti-seizure, anti-convulsive) medication, or chronic/PRN use of any medication that
             would, in the opinion of the investigator, compromise the subject's ability to
             function or perform the study activities.

             24. Addition of and/or major change in type or dosage of any prescription medication
             within 3 months prior to receipt of the PoNS device at the time of screening, subject
             to physician discretion.

             25. Active alcoholism documented by the investigator at the time of screening. The
             investigator will have the right to exclude subject participation if, in their
             opinion, the subject seems intoxicated at time of screening and/or during any study
             appointment.

             26. History of drug abuse as documented by the investigator at the time of screening.
             The investigator will have the right to exclude subject participation if, in their
             opinion, the subject seems intoxicated at time of screening or presentation for
             treatment 27. Recent (6 months) history of smokeless tobacco use (i.e., chewing
             tobacco, oral tobacco, spit or spitting tobacco, dip, chew, snuff*) (*NCI definition)

          -  Note: Cigarette, cigar, pipe, and/or e-cigarette use is not exclusionary 28. Any
             reason, considered by the principal investigator or designee to preclude subject
             enrollment in the study that might represent a threat to health, safety, or an
             inability to comply with the study protocol.

             29. Subject is incompatible with the device. 30. Subject is currently in a focused
             physical rehabilitation program for balance or gait symptoms resulting from their TBI
             and has not been deemed by their treating clinician to have reached a plateau.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Natalie Pettigrew</last_name>
    <phone>503-418-0206</phone>
    <email>terwilln@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

