<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03887663</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CPDR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03887663</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chinese PD Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>CPDR</acronym>
  <official_title>The Chinese Parkinson's Disease Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the Chinese Parkinson's disease Registry (CPDR) is to develop a database of
      patients with Parkinson's disease in China.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) is the second most common disorder among degenerative neurological
      diseases. PD is a complicated disease which consists of different subtypes. A certain type of
      parkinsonism has its unique clinical feature and genetic basis. Standards of classification
      and prognosis in different PD subtypes are still poorly understood. Investigators aim to
      establish a database of longitudinal recruited PD cohort ,and characterize the clinical
      feature, genetic basis, environmental factors and their interactions among different PD
      subtypes in China, identify natural history of a highly-presentative Chinese PD cohort and to
      discern major milestones in the disease process which indicates disease progression.

      Data were collected at baseline, 12±1 months during the routine follow-up visits. Information
      about detailed disease history, level of education, significant chronic comorbidities,
      physical examination, medication history, family history, living habits and toxic exposure
      history, which include smoking, drinking tea, alcoholic consumption, drinking coffee,
      exposure to pesticide or occupational solvent, history of carbon monoxide poisoning and
      recurrent head trauma will be recorded at baseline. For each evaluation, the same
      questionnaires will be conducted. A standardized neurological assessment according to the
      recommendation of Consensus on the construction of clinical database of Parkinson's disease
      and movement disorders in China. The Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) part
      III is conducted for motor assessment, all the patients are evaluated in &quot;OFF&quot; state. The
      clinical stage of PD is assessed by Hoehn and Yahr scale (H-Y). The non-motor symptoms are
      evaluated by Non-motor Symptom Scale (NMSS), autonomic symptoms are evaluated by The Scale
      for outcomes in Parkinson disease for Autonomic Symptoms (SCOPA-AUT). Constipation was
      diagnosed by Functional Constipation Diagnostic Criteria Rome Ⅲ. The 39-item Parkinson's
      Disease Qestionnaire (PDQ-39) was used to assess the quality of life. Sleep quality was
      evaluated by Parkinson's Disease Sleep Scale (PDSS) and excessive daytime sleepiness by
      Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS). Probable rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder (p-RBD)
      was diagnosed by rapid eye movement sleep behavior questionnaire-Hongkong (RBDQ-HK). Restless
      leg syndrome (RLS) was diagnosed with the Cambridge Hopkins Restless Leg syndrome
      questionnaire (CH-RLSq). Cognitive assessment was used the previously validated scale, Mini
      Mental State Examination (MMSE). Olfaction test was carried out by Hyposmia Rating Scale
      (HRS), a proportion of patients was also ascertained by Sniffin's Sticks. Depression was
      diagnosed by Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD). Symptom of fatigue was measured by PD fatigue
      severity scale (PFS). Wearing-off was evaluated by WOQ-9 and freezing gait by new freezing
      gait questionnaire scores (NFOGQ). Dyskinesis was evaluated by Rush Dyskinesia Rating Scale.
      DNA samples extracted from peripheral blood and all the PD patients will be examed by Whole
      Exome Sequencing or Whole-genome sequencing. All the participants are scanned by structural
      MRI to exclude obvious intracranial lesions and other parkinsonism such as MSA, PSP and WD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale for evaluating motor subtypes</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>The UPDRS is made up of four parts, 55 items in total. Total score varies from 0 to 199. Part I: evaluation of behavior and mood, which consists of 4 items, score varies from 0-16; Part II: self-evaluation of the activities of daily life, which consists of 13 items,score varies from 0-52; Part III: motor evaluation, which consists of 27 items, score varies from 0-108; Part IV: complications of therapy, which consists of 11 items,score varies from 0-23. All the patients are evaluated in &quot;OFF&quot; state. The ratio of the mean tremor score (scores of item-16, item-20, and item-21 will be added: ) to the mean postural instability/gait disorder (PIGD) score (scores of item-13, item-14, item-15, item-29, item-30 will be added: ) was used to classify motor subtype. Patients with a ratio value &lt; 1.0 were defined as PIGD, and those with values from 1.0 to 1.5 were categorized as intermediate, while those with values ≥1.5 were classified as tremor dominant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The clinical stage of PD is assessed by Hoehn and Yahr scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>The H-Y scale ranges from 1 to 5. Early PD is defined as H-Y stage 1 to 2.5, advanced PD is defined as H-Y stage 3-5.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Autonomic symptoms are evaluated by The Scale for outcomes in Parkinson disease for Autonomic Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 25 items assessing the following regions: gastrointestinal (7 items), urinary (6 items), cardiovascular (3 items), thermoregulatory (4 items), pupillomotor (1 items), and sexual dysfunction(2 items for men and 2 items for women). Scores in each region should be added. The score of the answers ranges from 0 to 3 for each item and the total score ranges from 0 to 69, where higher scores reflect worse autonomic functioning.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The non-motor symptoms are evaluated by Non-motor Symptom Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 30 items which is divided into 9 domains. Total score varies from 0-360. Higher score indicates severer symptoms. Domain 1 evaluates cardiovascular system symptoms. Score of domain 1 varies from 0-24. Domain 2 evaluates sleep condition. Score of domain 2 varies from 0-48. Domain 3 evaluates cognitive function. Score of domain 3 varies from 0-72. Domain 4 evaluates illusion. Score of domain 4 varies from 0-36. Domain 5 evaluates attention and memory. Score of domain 5 varies from 0-36. Domain 6 evaluates gastrointestinal symptoms. Score of domain 6 varies from 0-36. Domain 7 evaluates urinary symptoms. Score of domain 7 varies from 0-36. Domain 8 evaluate sensory symptoms. Score of domain 8 varies from 0-24. Domain 9 evaluates other non-motor symptoms. Score of domain 9 varies from 0-48.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Constipation was diagnosed by Functional Constipation Diagnostic Criteria Rome III.</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>The diagnostic criteria must include two or more of the following
Straining during at least 25% of defecations
Lumpy or hard stools in at least 25% of defecations
Sensation of incomplete evacuation for at least 25% of defecations
Sensation of anorectal obstruction/blockage for at least 25% of defecations
Manual maneuvers to facilitate at least 25% of defecations (e.g., digital evacuation, support of the pelvic floor)
Fewer than three defecations per week 2. Loose stools are rarely present without the use of laxatives 3. Insufficient criteria for irritable bowel syndrome * Criteria fulfilled for the last 3 months with symptom onset at least 6 months prior to diagnosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The PDQ-39 was used to assess the quality of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 39 items assessing the following regions: mobility (10 items), activities of daily living (6 items), emotional well-being (6 items), stigma (4 items), social support (3 items), cognitions (4 items), communications (3 items) and bodily discomfort (3 items). Alternatively, the sum of the scores can assess the overall health-related quality of life profile of the individual questioned. Scores in each region should be added. The score of the answers ranges from 0 to 4 for each item and the total score ranges from 0 to 116, where higher scores reflect worse life quality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality is evaluated by Parkinson's Disease Sleep Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 15 items that address eight aspects of sleep disturbances in PD, including overall quality of night's sleep (item 1)), score of item 1 less than 6 is defined as sleep disorder. Score of all the questions will be summed. The score of the answers ranges from 0 to 10 for each item and the total score ranges from 0 to 150, where higher scores reflect better sleep condition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Excessive sleepiness is evaluated by Epworth Sleepiness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 8 items. Score of all the questions will be summed. All items were rated on a 4-point scale (0-3), with a minimal score of 0, and maximum total score of 24. A higher score demonstrates more severe excessive daytime sleepiness. Participants were classified as showing excessive daytime sleepiness if their total score ≥10 .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Probable rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder was diagnosed by Probable rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder Questionnaire -Hongkong</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 13 items. Score of all the questions will be summed. Total score of the answers ranges from 0 to 100, where higher scores reflect severer rapid eye movement sleep behavior disorder.The optimal cutoff value for the overall scale is 17; subjects were classified as showing RBD when they reached the above score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Restless leg syndrome (RLS) was diagnosed with the Cambridge Hopkins Restless Leg syndrome questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>have, or have you had, recurrent uncomfortable feelings or sensations in your legs while you are sitting or lying down
have, or have you had, a recurrent need or urge to move your legs while you were sitting or lying down
more likely to have these feelings when you are resting
If you get up or move around when you have these feelings, these feelings get better
these feelings in your legs most likely to occur at mid-day or afternoon or evening or night
Simply changing leg position by itself once without continuing to move usually relieve these feelings usually don't relieves
These feelings are not or not always due to muscle cramps</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive condition is assessed by Mini Mental State Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 30 items. Score of all the questions will be summed. All items were rated on a 2-point scale (0-1), with a minimal score of 0, and maximum total score of 30. A higher score demonstrates more better cognitive condition. The definition of cognitive disorder differs in education level. For illiteracy, presence of cognitive impairment is defined as MMSE score. For those only receive elementary education, the cut-off value is 20. For other patients, presence of cognitive impairment was defined as MMSE scores less than 25.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Olfaction test was measured by Hyposmia Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 6 items. Score of all the questions will be summed. All items were rated on a 4-point scale (1-4), with a minimal score of 6, and maximum total score of 24. A higher score demonstrates more worse sense of olfaction. The cutoff value HRS is 22.5.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression was diagnosed by Hamilton and Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 17 items. Score of all the questions will be summed. Total score ranges from0-53. A higher score demonstrates more severer depression. The study participants were defined to be not depressed (scores 0-6) , to have minor depression(scores 7-14), or to have major depression (scores above 14) at the different visits during follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom of fatigue was measured by PD fatigue severity scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale includes 9 items. Score of all the questions will be summed. All items were rated on a 7-point scale (1-7). Total score ranges from0-63. A higher score demonstrates more severer fatigue.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>freezing gait by new freezing gait questionnaire scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>Parts II and III provides a total summed score between 0 and 28. Part II (items 2-6, scoring range 0-19) rated the severity of FOG based on its duration and frequency in its most common manifestation. Total score will be calculated for comparison.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dyskinesia was evaluated by UPDRS part III</measure>
    <time_frame>12±1 months</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of dyskinesia is evaluated by the doctor and recordsed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hypertension</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Diastolic blood pressure ≥140 mmHg, or systolic blood pressure ≥90 mmHg in at least three different days; or self-reported hypertension diagnosed by physicians, or taking BP-lowering medications at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type II diabetes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Type II diabetes can be diagnosed if any of the requirements are met: The test result of serum Hemoglobin A1c level conducted in the hospital is higher than 6.5%, fasting plasma glucose level ≥7.0mmol/l, or oral glucose tolerance test results ≥11.1mmol/l, results confirmed by repeated testing, or random plasma glucose level ≥11.1mmol/l in a patient with classic symptoms of hyperglycemia or hyperglycemic crisis; or self-reported type II diabetes diagnosed by physicians, or taking hypoglycemic agent or insulin at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperlipidemia</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Total cholesterol ≥6.2mmol/L or low-density lipoprotein ≥4.1mmol/L or triglyceride ≥2.3mmol/L; or self-reported hyperlipidemia diagnosed by physicians, or taking lipid-lowering drugs at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Extraction of DNA from peripheral blood of patients.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Most of the PD patients comes from mainland China, especially from Hunan Province, Hubei
        Province, Jiangxi Province and Guizhou Province. The proportion of male patients is
        slightly dominant than that of female patients. The age of PD patients ranges from 13 to
        more than 90 years old.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with PD by UK Brain Bank Diagnostic Criteria and other standard
             criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lack of capacity to consent to participate in the project
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Qiying Sun, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+8615874907260</phone>
    <email>sunqiying2015@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Beisha Tang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8613974856709</phone>
    <email>bstang7398@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changzhi</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410008</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Qiying Sun, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>+8615874907260</phone>
      <email>sunqiying2015@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jifeng Guo, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>+8613974936815</phone>
      <email>guojifeng2003@163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Motor symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonmotor symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese longitudinal cohort</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural history</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

