<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03887546</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>24121989</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03887546</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inspiratory Muscle Training in Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of a 12-week Inspiratory Muscle Training Program With Low Resistance in Patients With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Salamanca</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Salamanca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness of a low-intensity protocol of inspiratory muscle
      training (IMT) to improve respiratory strength, spirometric parameters and dyspnea in
      patients with multiple sclerosis (MS).

      Design: Clinical trial. Randomized. Participants: 67 patients with MS, distributed in two
      groups, intervention and control.

      Intervention: Intervention group train using IMT for 12 weeks, 5 days/week, 15 minutes/day
      (20% maximum inspiratory pressure (MIP) during the first two weeks and 30% MIP after the
      second week). Control group follow a respiratory exercise program involving nasal breathing
      and maximum exhalation during 12 weeks, 5 days/week, 15 minutes/day.

      Evaluations: Determination of the MIP and the maximum expiratory pressure (MEP); spirometry -
      maximum voluntary ventilation (MVV), peak expiratory flow (PEF), tidal volume (TV); dyspnea
      using the Borg scale and clinical evaluations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants:

      Patients from two MS associations will be recruited to participate in a 12-week randomized
      trial.

      The sample size calculation determine that 31 participants in each group are required to
      observe a minimum difference in the maximum inspiratory pressure (MIP) of 12 cm H2O,
      considering a power of 90%, a safety of 95% and a 10% dropout rate.

      The participants in the study are diagnosed with MS, are over 18 years old, have a disability
      lower than 9 in the Expanded disability status scale (EDSS) and are able to understand the
      objectives of the study. Those participants with a current or past neurological pathology
      other than MS will be excluded from the study, as well as those who had had a relapse of MS
      or any respiratory pathology during the 4 weeks prior to the start of the study, or any other
      complication that may have impeded the performance of the evaluation tests or breathing
      techniques. All patients will be asked to carry out the 5-day weekly program at home, and a
      recording sheet will be provided to each participant so they will can record the time of each
      daily respiratory training session. All participants signed an informed consent form.

      The patients will be assigned to the two groups randomly. The main researcher doesn´t meet
      any of the participants until the initial assessment will be carried out. The intervention
      group (n = 36) will receive a training protocol of IMT, while the control group (n = 31) will
      follow a program of nasal breathing and maximum exhalations.

      Evaluation:

      The participants are evaluated at the beginning and end of the intervention period.

      The evaluation of MIP and MEP is performed using a pressure transducer, Elka 15, which
      obtains each measurement in millibar and converts it into the reference unit of centimeter of
      water (cm H2O) (1 mbar = 1.01973 cm H2O .), following the rules of the American thoracic
      society/European respiratory society (ATS / ERS) [19]. The procedure will be repeated until 3
      values were obtained with a difference of less than 5%, and the highest value will be used
      for the analysis. The MIP of the intervention group will be assessed every 2 weeks to set the
      IMT workload.

      Lung volumes are assessed using a datospir touch spirometer with a turbine transducer with a
      maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules will be followed [19],
      and the highest value of three correct measurements will be chosen. Data is collected for the
      following parameters: maximum voluntary ventilation (MVV), forced expiratory volume in the
      first second (FEV1), peak expiratory flow (PEF), mean expiratory flow (FEF25-75), vital
      capacity (VC), tidal volume (TV) and forced vital capacity (FVC).

      Dyspnea will be measured using the modified Borg scale [20]. All evaluations will be done in
      the corresponding center, during the same time slot and by the same examiner for both groups.

      Intervention:

      For the intervention group, a protocol different from those referred to in the literature has
      been designed to cover the respiratory deficiencies of MS patients using IMT. The device
      incorporates a unidirectional valve independent of flow to guarantee constant resistance and
      includes a specific pressure setting (in cm H2O). During the first two weeks a MIP load of
      20% will be used, followed by a load of 30% for the rest of the training period. The protocol
      includes 15 cycles lasting 1 minute, twice a day: one in the morning and one in the
      afternoon. The participants rest for 1 minute between each cycle. In total, the protocol
      includes 30 minutes of daily respiratory training. The patients will be instructed to inhale
      with enough force to reach the opening of the valve.

      The training program of the control group involves nasal inhalations and maximum exhalations.
      The following types of breathing exercises will be carried out for 3 minutes each with a 1
      minute pause for resting: abdominal breathing, chest breathing, breathing and shoulder
      flexion, shoulder breathing and abduction, breathing and shoulder abduction in the transverse
      plane. The complete protocol involves 30 minutes of daily respiratory training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 24, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients are assigned randomly to the two working groups, each patient only receives one of the two protocols.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>The principal investigator doesn´t know the group of the patients until the study ends.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation is performed using a pressure transducer, Elka 15, which obtainer each measurement in millibar and converted it into the reference unit of centimeter of water (cm H2O) (1 mbar = 1.01973 cm H2O), following the rules of the ATS / ERS. The procedure was repeated until 3 values were obtained with a difference of less than 5%, and the highest value was used for the analysis. The MIP of the intervention group was assessed every 2 weeks to set the IMT workload.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal expiratory pressure (MEP)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation is performed using a pressure transducer, Elka 15. It is evaluated at the beginning and at the end of the interventional phase. Measure: cm H20</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Dyspnea is assessed using modified Borg scale. It is a scale between 1-10 points, 1 is the minimum and 10 is the maximum level of dyspnea or fatigue. More punctuation in the scale, more dyspnea.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum voluntary ventilation (MVV)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: Liter(L) / minute(m)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced expiratory volume in the first second (FEV1)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak expiratory flow (PEF)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: L / second (s)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean expiratory flow (FEF25-75)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: L / s</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital capacity (VC)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tidal volume (VT)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced vital capacity (FVC)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 minute</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometer with a turbine transducer with a maximum flow of 16 l/s and a maximum volume of 10 l. The ATS/ERS rules were followed [19], and the highest value of three correct measurements was chosen. Measure: L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">67</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention is administrated with Inspiratory Muscle Trainer. 20% maximum inspiratory pressure (MIP) during the first two weeks and 30% MIP after the second week.
12 weeks, 5 days/week, 15 minutes/day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Respiratory exercise program involving nasal breathing and maximum exhalation during 12 weeks, 5 days/week, 15 minutes/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inspiratory muscle trainer</intervention_name>
    <description>The device incorporate a unidirectional valve independent of flow to guarantee constant resistance and included a specific pressure setting (in cm H2O).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Respiratory exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Respiratory exercise program involving nasal breathing and maximum exhalation during 12 weeks, 5 days/week, 15 minutes/day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Diagnosed with MS

          -  Over 18 years old

          -  Disability lower than 9 in the EDSS

          -  Be able to understand the objectives of the study

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Participants with a current or past neurological pathology other than MS

          -  Relapse of MS or any respiratory pathology during the 4 weeks prior to the start of
             the study

          -  Any other complication that may impede the performance of the evaluation tests or
             breathing techniques
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>ANA MARIA MARTIN-NOGUERAS, DR</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Salamanca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>CARLOS MARTIN SANCHEZ, DOCTOR</last_name>
    <phone>+34646774655</phone>
    <email>carlos_ms@usal.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Salamanca</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>CARLOS MARTIN SANCHEZ</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiration</keyword>
  <keyword>Breathing exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigue</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

