<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03883880</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>082-011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03883880</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Salivary Interactions With Chemosensations</brief_title>
  <official_title>Salivary Interactions With Chemosensations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Purdue University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Purdue University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A counterbalanced, crossover design will be used to evaluate whether exposure to flavors vs.
      a control over time alters the perception of the flavor by changing an individual's salivary
      protein profile. Participants will complete 3 acute tasting protocols (baseline, after
      intervention 1, after intervention 2). The interventions will be with the flavor
      (epigallocatechin gallate, linolenic acid, capsaicin) or a control, in counterbalanced order,
      and will involve swishing and swallowing a solution of that sample 5 times per day for two
      weeks. Each of these flavors will be a separate sub-study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to test the relationship between salivary proteins, flavor sensation,
      and flavor exposure. For this study, we will test the bitterness/astringency of
      epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG, a polyphenol), the oleogustus (fatty acid taste) of linolenic
      acid, and the spiciness of capsaicin in conjunction with the concentration of specific
      salivary proteins (initially: salivary proline rich proteins for EGCG intervention,
      lipocalin-1 for the other two, but other proteins may be identified in the post-hoc analysis
      of the salivary proteome). We will test whether higher expression of these specific salivary
      proteins correlates with lower intensity of these flavors. We will further attempt to confirm
      the role of these salivary proteins using food-sourced functional analogs for these proteins.
      We would expect the food-sourced protein to have the same effect on flavor as the salivary
      protein if our hypotheses about salivary proteins' influence on flavor are correct. Finally,
      we will also use denatured versions of the food-sourced proteins to again confirm that
      effects are due to the function of these proteins binding the flavor.

      Additionally, we will repeatedly expose individuals to the flavors by having them rinse and
      swallow solutions of the flavor compounds multiple times per day for two weeks. We will then
      re-evaluate the sensory ratings and salivary protein profiles. Two weeks of rinsing and
      swallowing a control solution will be used as a control during this intervention (for each of
      the flavors of interest).

      To collect saliva and establish bitterness/astringency perception, we will use an acute
      tasting protocol. Participants will rinse with water, then taste and swallow, then taste and
      expectorate a solution of the flavor of interest. Saliva will be frozen for later proteomic
      analysis. Next participants will taste solutions of: flavor, flavor with food analog, the
      flavor with denatured food analog, water, water with the food analog, and water with
      denatured food analog. The participants will rank these solutions in order from least intense
      to most intense for the flavor quality of interest (bitterness/astringency for EGCG). After
      this, participants will taste all 6 samples again, and rate each individually for the
      intensity of the bitterness/astringency. After a short wait, this tasting and intensity
      rating will be repeated. All tastings will be done in counterbalanced order, and solutions
      will be labeled with randomized 3-digit codes.

      This acute tasting protocol will be done: at baseline, after 2 weeks on one intervention
      (repeated tasting of flavor or control), after 2 weeks on the other intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary proteins</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months per sub-study (intervention type)</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects saliva will be collected at baseline, after the flavor intervention, and after control intervention (two weeks each, order counterbalanced) for each type of intervention (epigallocatechin gallate, linoleic acid, capsaicin). The proteomic composition of the saliva samples will be established, and used to evaluate relationships with other outcome measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Flavor intensity ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months per sub-study (intervention type)</time_frame>
    <description>Flavor intensities for the flavor of interest (bitterness/astringency, oleogustus, and spiciness) will be collected at baseline, after the flavor intervention, and after control intervention (two weeks each, order counterbalanced) for each type of intervention (epigallocatechin gallate, linoleic acid, capsaicin). Subjects will rate (in duplicate) the intensity of flavor from the following solutions: flavor in water, flavor in water with food-sourced salivary protein analog, flavor in water with denatured food-sourced salivary protein analog, water, water with food-sourced salivary protein analog , water with denatured food-sourced salivary protein analog. These ratings will be evaluated in context of the timeline of the exposure as well as the salivary proteome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Flavor rankings</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months per sub-study (intervention type)</time_frame>
    <description>Flavor rankings for the flavor of interest (bitterness/astringency, oleogustus, and spiciness) will be collected at baseline, after the flavor intervention, and after control intervention (two weeks each, order counterbalanced) for each type of intervention (epigallocatechin gallate, linoleic acid, capsaicin). Subjects will rank the following solutions from most to least intense: Flavor in water, flavor in water with food-sourced salivary protein analog, flavor in water with denatured food-sourced salivary protein analog, water, water with food-sourced salivary protein analog , water with denatured food-sourced salivary protein analog. These ranking data will be used an another method to gather information on what solutions are most intense to the subject, as the intensity ratings may have complications due to order effects during tastings. These rankings will also be evaluated in context of the timeline of the exposure as well as the salivary proteome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Diet, Food Choice, Taste</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epigallocatechin gallate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Epigallocatechin gallate solutions will be provided to participants to rinse with daily for two weeks. A control solution will be provided for two weeks as well. Order will be counterbalanced across participants and groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Linoleic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Linoleic acid emulsion will be provided to participants to rinse with daily for two weeks. A control solution will be provided for two weeks as well. Order will be counterbalanced across participants and groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Capsaicin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Capsaicin solutions will be provided to participants to rinse with daily for two weeks. A control solution will be provided for two weeks as well. Order will be counterbalanced across participants and groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epigallocatechin gallate</intervention_name>
    <description>Colored solution prepared with epigallocatechin gallate to be consumed daily for two weeks during the epigallocatechin gallate intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epigallocatechin gallate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epigallocatechin gallate control</intervention_name>
    <description>Colored control solution to be consumed daily for two weeks during the epigallocatechin gallate intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epigallocatechin gallate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Linoleic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Colored emulsion prepared with linoleic acid to be consumed daily for two weeks during the linoleic acid intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Linoleic acid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Linoleic acid control</intervention_name>
    <description>Colored control solution to be consumed daily for two weeks during the linoleic acid intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Linoleic acid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capsaicin solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Colored solution prepared with capsaicin to be consumed daily for two weeks during the capsaicin intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Capsaicin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capsaicin control</intervention_name>
    <description>Colored control solution to be consumed daily for two weeks during the capsaicin intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Capsaicin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Agree to maintain current diet throughout intervention

          -  Agree to inform us if medication use changes during study.

          -  Willing and able to taste and consume samples, as well as take pictures to document
             use of the flavor during intervention.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known issues with salivation, taste, or smell

          -  Taking medications other than birth control

          -  User of tobacco products or electronic cigarettes within the last 30 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cordelia Running, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Purdue University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cordelia Running, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>765-494-2282</phone>
    <email>crunning@purdue.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Purdue University</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Lafayette</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>47907</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cordelia Running, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>765-494-2282</phone>
      <email>runninglab@purdue.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cordelia Running, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Purdue University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cordelia Running, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Prof. Nutrition Science</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>food choice</keyword>
  <keyword>taste</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epigallocatechin gallate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Capsaicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

