<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03883438</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AZETR201520171001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03883438</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cor Adv Flap Plus Ac Derm Matrix in Thin Phenotype Multiple Recessions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Coronally Advanced Flap and Envelope Type of Flap Plus Acellular Dermal Matrix Graft for the Treatment of Thin Phenotype Multiple Recession Defects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aziz Aliyev Azerbaijan State Advanced Training Institute for Doctors</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Altinbas University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidade Ibirapuera</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidad El Bosque, Bogotá</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aziz Aliyev Azerbaijan State Advanced Training Institute for Doctors</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical evaluation of conventional and modified coronally advanced flaps combined with
      acellular dermal matrix graft
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study was to evaluate the effectiveness of vertical incisions in the
      management of multiple gingival recessions (Miller Class I&amp;II ≥3 mm) treated with coronally
      advanced flap (CAF) and acellular dermal matrix graft (ADMG) in 22 eligible participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 15, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A total of 22 patients with 55 recessions were included in this single blind randomized controlled trial. Each patient had at least two recessions with a depth of ≥ 3 mm (Miller Class I&amp;II) in the upper jaw. The entry criteria were esthetic indication for root coverage; absence of caries or restorations at the selected sites; no history of previous mucogingival therapy; being a non-smoker and a systemically healthy patient.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>A computer program was used to randomize 22 volunteers to treatment groups by a person who was not involved in the study. The result of this randomization process was written on a paper and then put in the sealed opaque envelope by a blinded examiner, in which the treatment procedure for the specific patient was defined. The envelope was opened by surgeon, immediately before starting the surgical procedure.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete root coverage</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Complete defect coverage was calculated as the percentage of patients with defects having complete coverage achieved as the gingival margin at cemento-enamel junction or coronal level.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Root coverage esthetic score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Root coverage esthetic score (RES) was used as a scoring system to assess the esthetic outcomes following root coverage procedures on Miller Class I &amp; II gingival recession defects through the evaluation of clinical cases. Gingival margin level, marginal tissue contour, soft tissue texture, mucogingival junction alignment and gingival color were evaluated without magnification. Zero, 3 and 6 points were used for the evaluation of the position of the gingival margin, whereas a score 0 or 1 point was used for each of the other variables.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient was questioned about his/her satisfaction with regard to the following patient-centered criteria:
Root coverage attained, relief from dentinal hypersensitivity, color of gums, shape and contour of gums, surgical procedure in terms of pain during surgery and the discomfort experienced related to the duration of the procedure and handling by the operator, post surgical phase in terms of the pain, swelling, and postoperative complications; and cost effectiveness in terms of the time and money spent for the treatment.
Patient satisfaction was assessed using a three-point rating scale: fully satisfied (3 points); satisfied (2 points); and unsatisfied (1 point).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plaque Index</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Teeth were isolated by cotton rolls and after drying by air syringe, the microbial dental plaque was evaluated by the explorer from 4 tooth surfaces (mesio-buccal, mid-buccal, disto-buccal and mid-palatinal) and scores between 0- 3 were given for each point.
Scoring was made as follows:
0 - No microbial dental plaque in the gingival area
- A film of microbial dental plaque adhering to the free gingival margin and adjacent area of the tooth, recognized only by running a probe across the tooth surfaces.
- Moderate accumulation of soft deposits within the gingival pocket and on the gingival margin and/or adjacent tooth surfaces that can be seen by the naked eye.
- Abundance of soft matter within the gingival pocket and/or on the gingival margin and adjacent tooth surface.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gingival Index</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The periodontal probe was used to assess the bleeding potential of the tissues from 4 tooth surfaces (mesio-buccal papilla, mid-buccal margin, disto- buccal papilla and mid-palatinal margin) and scores between 0 - 3 were given for each point.
Scoring was made as follows: 0 - Normal gingiva
- Mild inflammation, slight change in color, slight edema; no bleeding on probing (BoP)
- Moderate inflammation, redness, edema, and glazing; bleeding on probing
- Severe inflammation, marked redness and edema, ulcerations; tendency to spontaneous bleeding.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding on Probing</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The periodontal probe was used to assess the percentage of bleeding after probing from 4 tooth surfaces (mesio-buccal papilla, mid-buccal margin, disto-buccal papilla and mid-palatinal margin) and scored as positive (+) or negative (-) bleeding for each point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing Depth</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Probing Depth of the recession defect was measured in mm by the periodontal probe at the mid buccal surface of the related tooth as the distance between the gingival margin and the bottom of the gingival sulcus.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Attachment Level</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Attachment Level of the recession defect was measured in mm by the periodontal probe at the mid-buccal surface of the related tooth and it was defined as the distance between the cemento-enamel junction and the bottom of the gingival sulcus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recession Depth</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Recession Depth was measured in mm by the periodontal probe at the mid-buccal surface of the related tooth as the distance between the cemento-enamel junction and the most apical point of the gingival margin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recession Width</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Recession Width of the defect was measured in mm by the periodontal probe as the horizontal distance from one border of the recession to another in mesio-distal direction at the level of the cemento-enamel junction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gingival Thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Gingival Thickness was measured in mm at the mid-point location between the gingival margin and mucogingival junction, using an #25 endodontic spreader. Under the local anesthesia, the spreader was pierced perpendicularly to the mucosal surface, through the soft tissue with light pressure until hard surface was felt. The silicone disk stop was placed in tight contact with the external soft tissue surface. After carefully removing the spreader, penetration depth was measured with a digital caliper5 with 0.05 resolution.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Keratinized Tissue Width</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Keratinized Tissue Width of the recession defect was measured in mm by the periodontal probe at the same point as the probing depth, clinical attachment level and recession depth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Gingival Recession, Generalized</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Coronally advanced flap and acellular dermal graft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In CAF group, after local anesthesia oblique beveled vertical incisions were made at the most mesial and distal line angles of the recessions. These two incisions were connected with an intra-sulcular and interdental sub-marginal incisions in order to create the external surgical papillae. Then the flap was elevated as a split-full-split approach. The apical portion of the flap was reflected as close to the periosteum as possible by mesio-distal and apical sharp dissection parallel to the mucosa to release residual muscle tension and extended beyond the muco-gingival junction to facilitate the passive coronal replacement of the flap over the defects. In both groups ADMG was used as a sub-epithelial graft considering the manufacturer's instructions. The graft was positioned at the level of cemento-enamel junction and extended to the surrounding bone in the apical direction with full closure of the exposed root surfaces.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Modified coronally advanced flap and acellular dermal graft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Test group received CAF avoiding vertical releasing incisions (mCAF).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified coronally advanced flap and acellular dermal matrix graft</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of the effectiveness of vertical incisions in the management of multiple gingival recessions (Miller Class I&amp;II ≥3 mm) treated with coronally advanced flap and acellular dermal matrix graft</description>
    <arm_group_label>Coronally advanced flap and acellular dermal graft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Modified coronally advanced flap and acellular dermal graft</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Systemically healthy patients

          -  Miller Class I &amp; II multiple buccal recession defects ≥ 3 mm on maxillary incisors,
             canines or premolars

          -  Esthetic indication for root coverage

          -  Probing depth &lt; 3mm at the recession sites

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Smokers

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Bruxism and occlusal trauma

          -  Previous root coverage procedure

          -  Endodontically treated teeth at the recession sites

          -  Caries or restorations at the recession sites

          -  Use of antibiotics over the previous 3 months prior to treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cavid Ahmedbeyli, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aziz Aliyev Azerbaijan State Advanced Training Institute for Doctors</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aziz Aliyev Azerbaijan State Advanced Training Institute for Doctors</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baku</city>
        <country>Azerbaijan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ibirapuera University</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Paolo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>El Bosque University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bogota</city>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Altinbas University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Azerbaijan</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Colombia</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Aziz Aliyev Azerbaijan State Advanced Training Institute for Doctors</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cavid Ahmedbeyli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gingival recession</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Tooth root</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical flaps</keyword>
  <keyword>Acellular dermis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingival Recession</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

