<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03888521</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18895</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03888521</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the GN ReSound Relief App Using task-and Rest-based fMRI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating the GN ReSound Relief App Using task-and Rest-based fMRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GN Hearing A/S</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main goal of this study is to assess the effectiveness of the Resound Relief app in
      alleviating problems associated with tinnitus, using both behavioral assessment and brain
      imaging. Subjective tinnitus (&quot;ringing in the ears&quot;) is the false perception of sound in the
      absence of an external stimulus. It often causes emotional distress and, in severe cases,
      interferes with daily activities and can lead to anxiety and depression. Sound therapy and
      relaxation techniques have been widely used as prominent interventions to ameliorate the
      adverse effects of tinnitus on overall health and psychological variables. The Resound Relief
      app combines the merit of these two kinds of therapy to allow the patients to alternate
      between therapies and manipulate them according to their specifics and needs. To assess the
      efficacy of the Resound Relief app in relieving tinnitus, the investigators will perform an
      interventional study in which tinnitus patients will use the app installed on their smart
      phones for six months. The effects of this intervention will be quantified via audiological
      and cognitive assessments, administering questionnaires and surveys, and MRI scanning
      sessions. Audiological and cognitive assessments, and MRI scanning will be conducted before
      and six months after the use of the Resound Relief app. Tinnitus-related questionnaires will
      be administered before, two, four, and six months after beginning use of the app. A short
      survey will be filled out every week regarding participants' experience with the app,
      tracking changes in the users' tinnitus, hearing loss and general emotional well-being.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 3, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Efficacy of a non-invasive intervention is being tested, while exploratory data is also being collected to better understand tinnitus</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>All participants receive the intervention, serving as their own controls</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduced tinnitus annoyance measured via Tinnitus Functional Index</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 months, 4 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Tinnitus Functional Index (TFI) is a tinnitus questionnaire, widely used to quantify tinnitus annoyance. It contains 25 questions, each of which participants rate from a scale of 0-10. The scores are then averaged, to give an overall score from 0 to 100. Higher values indicate higher disturbance and annoyance from tinnitus.
There are also 8 subscales in the questionnaire, which are each also averaged to give scores from 0 to 100. The subscales look at various aspects of tinnitus annoyance, specifically (1) intrusiveness, (2) reduced sense of control, (3) cognitive interference, (4) sleep disturbance, (5) auditory difficulties, (6) interference with relaxation, (7) reduced quality of life and (8) emotional distress.
The questionnaire will be completed by participants before (baseline), and 2, 4 and 6 months after using the app for a minimum of 1 hour a day, 5 days a week. The investigators hope to see reduction in the reported annoyance of tinnitus in participants' lives.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduced tinnitus annoyance measured via Iowa Tinnitus Primary Function Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 months, 4 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Tinnitus Primary Function Questionnaire (TPFQ) is a tinnitus questionnaire, widely used to quantify tinnitus annoyance. It contains 20 questions, each of which participants rate from a scale of 0-100. The scores are then averaged, to give an overall score from 0 to 100. Higher values indicate higher disturbance and annoyance from tinnitus.
There are also 4 subscales in the questionnaire, which are each also averaged to give scores from 0 to 100. The subscales look at various aspects of tinnitus annoyance, specifically (1) difficulties in concentration, (2) emotional distress, (3) hearing difficulties, and (4) sleep difficulties.
The questionnaire will be completed by participants before (baseline), and 2, 4 and 6 months after using the app for a minimum of 1 hour a day, 5 days a week. The investigators hope to see reduction in the reported annoyance of tinnitus in participants' lives.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduced tinnitus annoyance measured via Tinnitus Handicap Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 months, 4 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Tinnitus Handicap Inventory (THI) is a tinnitus questionnaire, widely used to quantify tinnitus annoyance. It contains 25 questions, each of which participants rate one of &quot;Yes,&quot; &quot;Sometimes,&quot; or &quot;No.&quot; Any &quot;Yes&quot; response is scored as 4 points, &quot;Sometimes&quot; is scored as 2 points, and &quot;No&quot; is scored as 0 points. The totals are then added up, giving an overall questionnaire score that can range from 0-100. Higher values indicate higher disturbance and annoyance from tinnitus.
The questionnaire will be completed by participants before (baseline), and 2, 4 and 6 months after using the app for a minimum of 1 hour a day, 5 days a week. The investigators hope to see reduction in the reported annoyance of tinnitus in participants' lives.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analyzing changes in neural gray matter using voxel-based morphometry (VBM)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Voxel-based morphometry (VBM) is a computational analytical technique that measures differences in local concentrations of brain tissue. VBM is applied to high-resolution anatomical images collected via magnetic resonance imaging. The unit of this measurement is mm3 of original grey matter per mm3 of spatially normalised space within the participant's brain image.
Whole-brain VBM comparisons will be applied within each participant's data, comparing their total gray matter brain volume before use of the smartphone app to total gray matter brain volume after 6 months of using the app.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analyzing changes in neural white matter using diffusion tensor imaging (DTI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) is a magnetic resonance imaging technique which enables the measurement of the movement of water molecules within tissue, allowing us to track a white matter tract and calculate its microstructural integrity.
Fractional anisotropy (FA), which is a scalar value ranging from 0 to 1, is a DTI measure which allows us to calculate how freely the water molecules within a measured tissue can move. Tractography is a modeling technique used to visually represent nerve tracts within the brain, which is derived from the DTI data collected.
FA will be calculated, and tractography modeled, for each participant, comparing their total white matter microstructural integrity before use of the smartphone app and after 6 months of using the app.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analyzing changes in resting state neural networks using functional magnetic resonance imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Resting state functional connectivity is a functional magnetic resonance imaging technique used to evaluate interactions between various brain regions while the brain is at waking rest. The technique measures the haemodynamic response of the brain after magnetic pulses are sent by the scanner. This response is measured on a scale known as the Blood Oxygen Level Dependent (BOLD) signal, which is relative. Correlations of activity seen between brain regions is believed to be indicative of neural networks.
The resting state functional connectivity will be measured for each participant, before, and after 6 months of using the app.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Tinnitus, Subjective</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Resound Relief</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants are in the same group, and receive the same intervention - use of the Resound Relief smartphone app for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resound Relief smartphone app</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is a smartphone app which has been developed to include a wide range of sounds and techniques aimed at reducing the impact of tinnitus.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Resound Relief</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Screening questionnaires:

               -  Tinnitus and Hearing Healthcare History (THH) form: This form is intended to
                  assess subjects' healthcare history. The manner in which it is used to exclude
                  subjects due to health issues other than tinnitus and hearing loss is described
                  in the exclusion criteria.

        For the purpose of this study (i.e. intervention), the investigators will include
        participants with managed depression or anxiety, as it may be difficult to recruit
        participants with severe tinnitus that do not have one or both of those conditions.
        However, only subjects aged between 21- 70 years old will be included.

          -  Tinnitus Functional Index (TFI): The investigators will recruit participants with
             varying degrees of tinnitus severity, reflecting the real-world usage of the app, but
             with a preference that at least 50% of the subjects have bothersome tinnitus defined
             as greater than 25 on the TFI scale (0-100).

          -  Audiometric evaluation (described in research procedures): The audiometric evaluation
             will primarily be used to obtain participants' hearing profiles. Subjects who have
             normal hearing thresholds (defined as less than or equal to 30 dB HL) up to 1 kHz in
             at least one ear will be included. Subjects who do not meet the defined normal hearing
             thresholds will be assessed on a case by case basis to ensure they can communicate
             without assistance with the investigators during scanning.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Screening questionnaires:

               -  Tinnitus and Hearing Healthcare History (THH) form: This form contains questions
                  regarding confounding variables such as traumatic brain injury (TBI),
                  post-traumatic stress disorder, Ménière's disease, drug and alcohol use, and
                  neurological or psychiatric health issues such as epilepsy. In the event that a
                  participant has any of the described conditions or uses drugs/drinks to excess,
                  those participants will be excluded from the study.

        Drug/alcohol abuse will be assessed by questions 31 and 32 in the THH Form. If a subject
        indicates 'yes' to question 32, indicating that they have abused drugs or alcohol within
        the last 2 years, those participants will be excluded from the study. Studies have shown
        that a history of drug or alcohol abuse affects brain patterns as measured by MRI. Because
        the investigators need to average in order to report our results, outliers can change our
        results. For this reason, the investigators ask question 31 regarding past drug and alcohol
        use to better understand our data set. Exclusion, however, will only be based on usage
        within the last 2 years (question 32). The questionnaire also asks for a list of
        medications currently being used; some are known to affect tinnitus, and participants using
        such medications will be excluded.

          -  BDI and BAI: If a subject presents with significant depression and/or anxiety those
             participants will be excluded. This is demonstrated via a score above 30 on the Beck
             Depression Inventory (BDI) and/or above 25 on the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI).
             Further, the BDI contains a question (#9) asking about suicidal thoughts. This
             question will not be asked and has been deleted from the questionnaire given to the
             subjects.

          -  Mini-Mental State Examination: Participants will be excluded from the study if they do
             not have normal cognition, i.e. if a given score of 27 out of 30 or lower is achieved
             on the Mini-Mental State Examination.

          -  BIC safety screening form: This questionnaire contains questions regarding
             claustrophobia and whether there are any metal implants or pieces (such as metal
             flakes in the eyes from metal work) that may pose a health risk under the strong
             magnetic fields used in MRIs. Participants that indicate having metal in their bodies
             will be excluded. Those that indicate claustrophobia will be assessed for inclusion
             via the mock scan (see below).

               -  Audiometric evaluation:

          -  Participants with hearing aids will be evaluated on a case-by-case basis as to their
             communication abilities without hearing aids.

          -  Loudness Discomfort Level: Loudness Discomfort Levels (LDLs) measured during the
             assessment will be used to verify whether participants will be able to tolerate the
             noise level of the scanner. Hearing protection will be provided during the MRI scans;
             however, participants with low LDLs may still experience discomfort. For their
             comfort, if participants report that a sound is uncomfortable at an LDL of 75 dB HL or
             quieter, those participants will be excluded from the MRI scanning portion of the
             study. If a participant has an LDL between 76 and 90 dB HL, they will be assessed on a
             case by case basis for comfort within the MRI scanner (the investigators will play
             scanner noise for the participants, take into consideration any past MRIs participants
             have had, etc.). If participants have an LDL of 90 dB HL or higher, those participants
             will be able to tolerate the noise level of the scanner and will be included.

               -  MRI Scans (described in research procedures):

          -  Mock scan: If participants meet the above criteria, they will be asked to complete a
             mock MRI scan. During this mock scan, participants will be placed inside a non-
             operational model of the MRI magnet to verify they are not claustrophobic and will be
             comfortable during the MRI scans.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fatima Husain, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Department of Speech and Hearing Science</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</name>
      <address>
        <city>Urbana</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>61801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fatima Husain</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Department of Speech and Hearing Science</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Relief</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tinnitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

