<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03884699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OMFS 3-3-7</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03884699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Waferless One Stage Segmental Lefort I Maxillary Positioning in Transverse Deficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Accuracy of Waferless One Stage Segmental Lefort I Maxillary Positioning in Transverse Deficiency Using CAD/CAM Patient Specific Titanium Implants (Case Series Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Maxillary transverse deficiency, is waverless lefort I multiple pieces osteotomy using
      virtually planned patient specific titanium implants feasible and does it provide accuracy?

      This prospective case series study evaluating the postoperative outcomes and accuracy of
      preoperatively planned positional changes together with virtually designed drilling and
      fixation guides for the waferless positioning and fixation of the multiple pieces Le Fort I
      of the maxilla using CAD-CAM designed patient-specific implants.

      The purpose of this study is to develop and validate an orthognathic CAD/CAM patient specific
      implant together with template that can guide both the osteotomy and the repositioning of the
      maxilla during the correction of transverse maxillary deficiency.

      Thus, the traditional model and the additional preparation for CAD/CAM surgical splints
      including scanning dental casts, and recording and moving virtual dental casts, were not
      required. The preoperative and laboratory procedures were simplified, and the intermediate
      splint technique was eliminated, so the associated potential errors were avoided.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the accuracy of planned waferless positioning of lefort
      I multiple piece osteotomy in maxillary deficient patients using CAD-CAM patient-specific
      implants together with virtually designed drilling and fixation guides.

      Interventions

        1. Diagnostic procedures:

           All Patients will be selected according to inclusion and exclusion criteria &amp;
           Comprehensive clinical examination and understanding of patients' chief complains and
           needs will be carried out Preoperative patient photographs (Frontal, Profile, 45°,
           smile, and dental occlusion) Alginate Impressions† of upper &amp; lower jaws for acquiring
           diagnostic dental casts Cone Beam Computed Topography (CBCT) for the patients §

        2. Planning procedures:

      Computer-aided planning: All planning will be done using specialized Mimics software** Import
      CBCT into virtual planning software. Segmentation: highlighting and selection of the bony
      anatomy based on bone density (Hounsfield Units).

      3D reconstruction: virtual 3D model. CT scanning of the dental stone casts. Image fusion: to
      combine the virtual casts onto the 3D bony model to obtain a composite artifact-free skull
      model.

      Virtual planning: based on clinical evaluation and 3D cephalometric analysis. Virtual
      osteotomies mimicking segmental Lefort I and a bilateral sagittal split osteotomy.

      Designing the virtual cutting guide. Virtual movement into the desired positions of the
      segmented maxilla and mandible, based on: clinical evaluation, 3D cephalometric analysis and
      the desired occlusion.

      Once the optimal position of the maxilla is achieved, a patient specific implant will be
      virtually designed to fix the segmented maxilla in its new position.

      Fabrication of the cutting guide using additive manufacturing technique from polymer
      material.

      Fabrication of PSI from titanium alloy using additive manufacturing technique.

      3. Intra operative procedures The surgical procedures will be carried out by RT under the
      supervisor of AH in the Oral &amp; Maxillofacial operating floor on the 8th floor of the faculty
      of Oral &amp; Dental Medicine new building.Scrubbing and draping of the patient will be carried
      out in a standard fashion according to Anon 2006.

      Local anesthesia (lidocaine 2%, 1/100000 adrenaline) will be injected intraorally along the
      incision lines for hemostasis.

      Access through a vestibular intraoral incision for maxilla &amp; Sagittal split incision for
      mandible will carried out. Dissection and reflection to reach the bone.

      Bilateral Sagittal Split mandibular osteotomies will carried out. The osteotomy guide 2 parts
      will into fit the left and right side the anterior maxillary walls separately during the
      operation for ease of use.

      Le Fort I Maxillary osteotomies will carried out using the osteotomy guide. Complete
      mobilization of maxillary segments. Reposition and fixation of the maxillary segments into
      the planned position will be done by the Patient Specific Implant (PSI) using the drilling
      site done by the osteotomy guide.

      Reposition and fixation of the mandibular segments using bicortical screws. The incisions
      will be closed with continuous mattress absorbable sutures††. 4. Postoperative care &amp; Follow
      up Post-operative treatment will start immediately postoperative (4 hours) Patients will
      start antibiotics 4 hours after the last intraoperative dose (Amoxicillin / Clavulanic acid
      625 mg every 8 hours) for 5 days Patients will start analgesics (NSAIDs every 6 hours) for 3
      days Mouthwash (Chlorhexidine 0.12%) will be prescribed for 2 more weeks. The patients will
      be scheduled for follow-up visits weekly for a month then on a monthly basis for 5 more
      months.

      At 1 to 3 weeks postoperatively CBCT using same parameters will be ordered to calculate the
      difference between surgical plan and actual outcome will be evaluated.

      Patient will be referred back to the orthodontist to receive his postsurgical orthodontics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transverse dimension of maxilla on virtual plan and postoperative</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>8 Reference points will be chosen below the osteotomy line on the maxilla (4 dental and 4 bony), and the distances between these points and the Frankfort, the midfacial, and the coronal planes, to show the vertical, horizontal, and axial positions of the maxilla, respectively.
These distances will be measured on the postoperative CT data and their deviations from the virtual plan will illustrate the accuracy of our procedure.
The 4 bony reference points are :
PF: Piriform at the widest point ; J: The junction between the maxillary tuberosity outline and the zygomatic process (63); and GPF: Greater palatine foramen.
The 4 dental reference points are:
A3L: Cusp of the left maxillary canine; A3R: Cusp of the right maxillary canine; A6L: Mesiobuccal cusp of the left first maxillary molar; and A6R: Mesiobuccal cusp of the right first maxillary molar.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Planning &amp; surgical times: estimated time to the actual time</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using chronometer, the time from the start of virtual plan &amp; design, and the time of the surgery will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Lefort I Osteotomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Segmental maxillary lefort I re-positioning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Accuracy of the planned virtually re-positioned segmental Lefort I maxilla using a specifically designed patient implant, comparing the virtual plan to the actual postoperative position.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Accuracy of planned transverse Maxillary distance using Mimics software after fixation using Patient specific implant</intervention_name>
    <description>Virtual planning: based on clinical evaluation and 3D cephalometric analysis. Virtual osteotomies mimicking segmental Lefort I and a bilateral sagittal split osteotomy.
Designing the virtual cutting guide. Virtual movement into the desired positions of the segmented maxilla and mandible, based on: clinical evaluation, 3D cephalometric analysis and the desired occlusion.
Once the optimal position of the maxilla is achieved, a patient specific implant will be virtually designed to fix the segmented maxilla in its new position.
Fabrication of the cutting guide using additive manufacturing technique from polymer material.
Fabrication of PSI from titanium alloy using additive manufacturing technique.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Segmental maxillary lefort I re-positioning</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suffering from transverse and anteroposterior maxillary discrepancy.

          -  Patients requiring bimaxillary orthognathic surgery.

          -  Patients should be free from any systemic disease that may affect normal healing and
             predictable outcome.

          -  Patients who will agree to the consent and will commit to follow-up period.

          -  Highly motivated patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are younger than 14 years.

          -  Patients having a significant systemic disease that may affect normal healing.

          -  Intra-bony lesions or infections that may retard the osteotomy healing.

          -  Patients receiving chemo or radiotherapy.

          -  Known allergies or sensitivities to dental materials, including Titanium or general
             anesthesia agents.

          -  Patient with bad oral hygiene.

          -  Pregnant females.

          -  Inability to return for follow up visits.

          -  Refusal of participation from the patient.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rasha Taman, Msc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sherif Hassan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00201001932020</phone>
    <email>sherif.ali@dentistry.cu.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Adel Abou-ElFetouh, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00201018871899</phone>
    <email>ahfotouh@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rasha Anwar Ibrahim Taman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Orthognathic Surgery</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

