<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03881917</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Renal markers in thalassemia.</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03881917</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cystatin c and Beta 2 Microglobulin in Thalassemic Children.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cystatin C and Beta 2 Microglobulin as Biochemical Markers for Early Detection of Renal Impairment in Children With Beta Thalassemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Beta thalassemia has many complications on many systems as the renal system.So early
      detection of renal impairment is required in those children to decrease complications of this
      nephropathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thalassemia syndromes are the most common single gene disorders worldwide especially in
      developing countries. The use of regular and frequent blood transfusions in patients with
      beta thalassemia major has improved patients' life spans and quality of life, but can lead to
      chronic iron overload. Many factors contribute to the functional abnormalities found in beta
      thalassemia patients such as decreased red cell life span, rapid iron turnover, tissue
      deposition of excess iron and also, specific iron chelators can affect kidneys. The success
      in management of patients of beta thalassemia has led to chronic hemosiderosis in different
      organs like liver and heart and long-term complications in other organs like pancreas and
      kidneys have recently been studied. The evidence of proximal tubular damage has been observed
      in beta thalassemia patients. Also, low-molecular-weight proteinuria has been found in almost
      all patients. Unlike other organs, it is unclear whether kidney damage results solely from
      intravascular haemolysis, chronic transfusion or as a complication of iron chelation therapy.
      Although the early identification of patients at high risk of renal impairment is of great
      importance as it may allow specific measures to be taken to delay renal impairment, there are
      limited studies about renal dysfunction in pediatric thalassemic patients. Thus, in this
      study we will use different measurements for early detection of renal impairment even if the
      patients have no symptoms to handle with the disease in its reversible stage before being
      irreversible. Beside the usual investigations of renal function we will measure cystatin c
      and beta2 microglobulin as early markers of renal impairment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean difference of cystatin c and beta 2 microglobulin concentrations with normal range</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of the results to differentiate the affected from non affected patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cystatin c and beta 2 microglobulin kits</intervention_name>
    <description>Kits for measurement concentration</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children with beta thalassemia from the age of 1 year to 18 years.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with beta thalassemia from the age of 1 year to 18 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children who have other hematological or chronic disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mohamed Naguib Khairy, M.B.B.Ch</last_name>
    <phone>+201091921973</phone>
    <email>mohamed_ibrahim@med.au.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>den Bakker E, Gemke RJBJ, Bökenkamp A. Endogenous markers for kidney function in children: a review. Crit Rev Clin Lab Sci. 2018 May;55(3):163-183. doi: 10.1080/10408363.2018.1427041. Epub 2018 Feb 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29388463</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Annayev A, Karakaş Z, Karaman S, Yalçıner A, Yılmaz A, Emre S. Glomerular and Tubular Functions in Children and Adults with Transfusion-Dependent Thalassemia. Turk J Haematol. 2018 Mar 1;35(1):66-70. doi: 10.4274/tjh.2017.0266. Epub 2017 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>28753129</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Behairy OG, Abd Almonaem ER, Abed NT, Abdel Haiea OM, Zakaria RM, AbdEllaty RI, Asr EH, Mansour AI, Abdelrahman AM, Elhady HA. Role of serum cystatin-C and beta-2 microglobulin as early markers of renal dysfunction in children with beta thalassemia major. Int J Nephrol Renovasc Dis. 2017 Sep 11;10:261-268. doi: 10.2147/IJNRD.S142824. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28979155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Deveci B, Kurtoglu A, Kurtoglu E, Salim O, Toptas T. Documentation of renal glomerular and tubular impairment and glomerular hyperfiltration in multitransfused patients with beta thalassemia. Ann Hematol. 2016 Feb;95(3):375-81. doi: 10.1007/s00277-015-2561-2. Epub 2015 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26596972</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hashemieh M, Radfar M, Azarkeivan A, Hosseini Tabatabaei SMT, Nikbakht S, Yaseri M, Sheibani K. Renal Hemosiderosis among Iranian Transfusion Dependent β-Thalassemia Major Patients. Int J Hematol Oncol Stem Cell Res. 2017 Apr 1;11(2):133-138.</citation>
    <PMID>28875008</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ali BA, Mahmoud AM. Frequency of glomerular dysfunction in children with Beta thalassaemia major. Sultan Qaboos Univ Med J. 2014 Feb;14(1):e88-94. Epub 2014 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24516760</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bakr A, Al-Tonbary Y, Osman G, El-Ashry R. Renal complications of beta-thalassemia major in children. Am J Blood Res. 2014 Sep 5;4(1):1-6. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25232499</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Uzun E, Balcı YI, Yüksel S, Aral YZ, Aybek H, Akdağ B. Glomerular and tubular functions in children with different forms of beta thalassemia. Ren Fail. 2015;37(9):1414-8. doi: 10.3109/0886022X.2015.1077314. Epub 2015 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26365703</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nickavar A, Qmarsi A, Ansari S, Zarei E. Kidney Function in Patients With Different Variants of Beta-Thalassemia. Iran J Kidney Dis. 2017 Mar;11(2):132-137.</citation>
    <PMID>28270645</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mohamed Naguib Khairy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>renal impairment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cystatins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

