<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04453020</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Obesity IDE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04453020</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Deep Brain Stimulation Effects in Patients With Chronic Refractory Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study to Evaluate Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) of the Lateral Hypothalamic Area (LHA) on Energy Balance and Feeding Behavior in Patients With Chronic Refractory Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Donald M. Whiting, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Scientific Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Allegheny Singer Research Institute (also known as Allegheny Health Network Research Institute)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of deep brain stimulation (DBS) of
      the lateral hypothalamic area (LHA) as a treatment for chronic refractory obesity. This study
      will include 6 individuals with chronic refractory obesity, that have failed other treatments
      including gastric bypass surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Six (N = 6) subjects with chronic refractory obesity will receive bilateral DBS implants in
      the LHA using the Boston Scientific Vercise Gevia DBS system. The primary objective is to
      evaluate the safety of DBS of the LHA using the current-driven Boston Scientific device and
      compare that to the safety data for our previous pilot using the voltage-driven DBS system
      for the treatment of chronic refractory obesity. The primary efficacy objective is to
      determine if DBS of the LHA can affect energy balance (i.e. energy intake and/or energy
      expenditure) in these patients. Secondary outcomes include quality of life outcomes and
      changes in feeding behaviors. Study participants will undergo a two-part DBS implantation
      procedure for placement of DBS electrodes in the LHA. Following this procedure, subjects with
      complete resting metabolic rate (RMR) testing to determine the optimal settings for the LHA
      stimulation. If effective, DBS technology might offer severely obese adults (BMI of ≥50
      kg/m2), who have failed traditional therapy, a non-destructive, adaptable, reversible
      neurosurgical option for altering eating habits leading to sustained weight loss in the
      long-term.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety - Complication Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse Events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resting metabolic rate (RMR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months, 4-5 months and 20 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>RMR assessment of energy expenditure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Energy intake</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of energy intake through ad libitum test meals</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of weight on quality of life: IWQOL-Lite</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of Weight on Quality of Life Questionnaire (IWQOL-Lite). [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 31 items by which the subject will respond to statements under 5 domains. Responses include: Always true, Usually true, Sometimes true, Rarely true, and Never true. All responses are totaled for a final score. Scores range from 0 to 100, with 100 representing the best quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Binge Eating Scale (BES)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Eating Habits Checklist/Binge Eating Scale (BES). [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 16 items that subjects will respond to. Each question has 3-4 separate responses assigned a numerical value. The score range is from 0-46. Higher scores equate to greater binging behavior.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Yale Food Addiction Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Yale Food Addiction Scale. [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 25 self-reported questions in dichotomous and Likert-type format. Food addiction is recognized when a subject meets at least three of the symptom criteria. The more symptoms met, the more severe the food addiction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Power of Food Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Power of Food Scale. [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 21 items that subjects will assign a response to. The scale is as follows: 1=I don't agree at all, 2=I agree a little, 3=I agree somewhat, 4=I agree, 5=I strongly agree. All items are scored so that a higher item score indicates a greater responsiveness to the food environment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Eating Inventory (EI). [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 51 items consisting of three subscales. Scores range from a minimum of 0-0-0 to a maximum of 21-16-14. Higher scores are indicative of a greater level of the eating habits for the respective subscales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body shape perception</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Body Shape Questionnaire (BSQ). [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 34 items that subjects will assign a response to. The scale is as follows: 1=Never, 2=Rarely, 3=Sometimes, 4=Often, 5=Very Often, 6=Always. The maximum score is 204, and a higher score indicates more dissatisfaction and discomfort with the body experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food craving inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Food Craving Inventory. [Feeding behavior assessment]. For each of the foods listed (37), subjects will rate the frequency of cravings. The scale is as follows: A=Never, B=Rarely (once or twice), C=Sometimes, D=Often, E=Always/almost every day. Cravings are measured for five types of foods. A total score is also obtained that measures the general construct of food cravings. Higher scores are indicative of more intense cravings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food preferences</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Food Preference Questionnaire. [Feeding behavior assessment]. Subjects rate their liking of 62 individual foods on a 5-point Likert scale. The scale is as follows: 1=Dislike a lot, 2=Dislike a little, 3=Neither like nor dislike, 4=Like a little, 5=Like a lot. Higher scores indicate a higher preference.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delayed reward discounting</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Monetary Choice Questionnaire. [Feeding behavior assessment]. There are 21 items that subjects will indicate a response. The scale is as follows: 0=smaller reward today, 1=larger reward in the specified number of days. The questionnaire is scored by calculating where the respondent's answers place them amid reference discounting curves, where placement amid steeper curves indicates higher levels of impulsivity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Appetitive sensations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analog scale (VAS) assessment. [Feeding behavior assessment]. Subjects will rank appetitive sensations on a scale from 0-10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life measure: SF-36</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Short Form-36 (SF-36). Subjects will rate responses to each of 36 items, (Likert and yes/no responses). Scores for each scale range from 0-100. The lower the score the more disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II). There are 21 items where subjects will rate their responses on a Likert scale from 0-3. Total scores range from 0-63. Higher total scores indicate more severe depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in metabolic hormone profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Biochemical battery of tests. Blood draw for GLP1, PYY, Ghrelin (total and active) - Fasting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 2 weeks, 2 months, 4-5 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months, 15 months, 18 months, 20 months and 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Body Mass Index (BMI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in DXA body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months and 4-5 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Change in body composition. Measured by dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LHA DBS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive bilateral DBS of the LHA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DBS of the LHA</intervention_name>
    <description>Deep Brain Stimulation of the Lateral Hypothalamic Area</description>
    <arm_group_label>LHA DBS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vercise Gevia™ Deep Brain Stimulator System</other_name>
    <other_name>Suretek Model DB-4600-C</other_name>
    <other_name>Vercise Cartesia Directional Leads Model DB-2202-45</other_name>
    <other_name>OR Cable and Extension Model DB-4100A</other_name>
    <other_name>8 Contact Extension Model NM-3138-55</other_name>
    <other_name>Vercise Charging System Model DB-64125-US</other_name>
    <other_name>Vercise Gevia 16 Contact IPG Kit Model DB-1200-S</other_name>
    <other_name>Vercise DBS Remote Control 3 Kit Model DB-5552-1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female patients age ≥ 22 years and &lt; 65 years old with a BMI of ≥ 50 kg/m2.

          2. Failure of bariatric surgery (gastric bypass) and subjects who have no endoscopically
             or surgically correctable causes for failed bariatric surgery. &quot;Failed bariatric
             surgery&quot; is determined using the modified Reinhold classification as patients who are
             currently more than 50% over ideal body weight at least 24 months after a technically
             successful surgery (as confirmed by a esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) within the 6
             months prior to ICF).

          3. Stable at their present weight (+/- 3 kg) for a 12-month period.

          4. Neuropsychiatric evaluation must not reveal any issues that will be an impediment to
             subject's participation (as listed in Exclusion Criteria 2, 3 and 4).

          5. Karnofsky Performance Score &gt;60.

          6. Platelet count &gt;125,000 per cubic mm.

          7. Prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) within normal limits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any intracranial abnormality or medical condition that would contraindicate DBS
             surgery.

          2. Have a history that includes a prior suicide attempt.

          3. Have any significant psychiatric condition likely to compromise the subject's ability
             to comply with requirements of the study protocol (e.g. bipolar, schizophrenia, mood
             disorder with psychotic features, cluster B personality disorders) or have any prior
             history of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder or active psychotic episodes.

          4. Have a current diagnosis of major depressive episode per DSM-IV (Diagnostics and
             Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders) criteria or has a current BDI-II score ≥ 17.

          5. Any current drug or alcohol abuse, per DSM-IV criteria or any history of substance
             abuse (alcohol or other drug) or dependence during the past 12 months.

          6. Any history of recurrent or unprovoked seizures.

          7. Any history of hemorrhagic stroke.

          8. Any diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction or cardiac arrest within previous 6
             months.

          9. Any diagnosis of a neurological disorder, such as multiple sclerosis, stroke,
             Parkinson's disease, severe brain atrophy or the presence of subdural hygromas or
             subdural hematomas.

         10. Any history of hypothyroidism.

         11. Any history of demonstrated binge eating.

         12. Concurrent use of weight-loss prescription drug therapy or the use of over-the-counter
             weight loss preparations.

         13. Any prior intracranial surgery or device implantation.

         14. Any other active implanted devices (e.g., spinal cord stimulator, cochlear implant,
             pacemaker, vagus nerve stimulator) and /or drug delivery pumps, whether turned on or
             off. Passive implants (e.g., knee prostheses) would be allowed provided that they
             would not interfere with the DBS.

         15. Any previously implanted Vagus Nerve Stimulation (VNS) patients.

         16. A condition requiring or likely to require the use of Magnetic Resonance Imaging
             (MRI), diathermy or electroconvulsive therapy (ECT).

         17. Likely to require the use of monopolar cautery, radio-frequency (RF) procedures,
             external defibrillation, lithotripsy, radiation therapy or transcranial stimulation.

         18. Currently on any anticoagulant medications that cannot be discontinued during
             perioperative period.

         19. Have any significant medical condition that is likely to interfere with study
             procedures or likely to confound evaluation of study endpoints, (e.g. hepatitis or
             HIV).

         20. Any terminal illness with life expectancy of &lt; 1 year.

         21. Any diagnosis of malignancy (except basal cell of skin) within the past five years.

         22. Any unresolved infection, a coagulopathy or significant cardiac or other medical risk
             factor for surgery.

         23. Current or future risk of being immunocompromised (due to medications, disease
             factors, illness, etc.) that might significantly increase risk of infection.

         24. Participation in any other clinical trial (e.g. drug, device, or biologics)
             concurrently or within the preceding 30 days. Participation in any other study will be
             allowed per investigator/sponsor discretion only.

         25. Plan to receive any procedure that involves sudden jerking motions of the head or neck
             (e.g. certain chiropractic therapies) or massage and manipulation directly over the
             leads in the scalp, neck or chest, at any time during the study.

         26. A female who is breastfeeding or of child-bearing potential with a positive urine
             pregnancy test or not using adequate contraception.

         27. Not able to speak, write and read in English language as determined by the
             investigator.

         28. Overall intellectual abilities below a standard score of 80 based on results from the
             Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence (WASI; Wechsler, 1999)

         29. Unable to fit into MRI or CT (Maximum weight limit is 180 kg (396 lb.).

         30. Plasma pre-albumin &lt; 14 mg/dL

         31. Obesity as part of another medical condition, neurological injury or lesions, related
             to medication side effect, or as part of a genetic syndrome (i.e. Prader-Willi
             Syndrome, Leptin deficiency, etc.)

         32. Be eligible for bariatric surgery revision including gastric outlet exclusion,
             gastrogastric fistula or other reasons that would qualify for a revision of their
             gastric bypass

         33. Unable or unwilling to follow up for scheduled clinic visits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald Whiting, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Allegheny Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Donald Whiting, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-359-6200</phone>
    <email>donald.whiting@ahn.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nestor Tomycz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-359-6200</phone>
    <email>nestor.tomycz@ahn.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allegheny General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Polaski, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>412-359-4604</phone>
      <email>anna.polaski@ahn.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald Whiting, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nestor Tomycz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Allegheny Singer Research Institute (also known as Allegheny Health Network Research Institute)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Donald M. Whiting, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep Brain Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Lateral Hypothalamic Area</keyword>
  <keyword>Feeding Behaviors</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy Balance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

