<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04450654</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00009143</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04450654</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Monotherapy IVIG Gamunex-C for HMG-CoA Reductase Auto-Antibody Positive Necrotizing Myopathy Treatment (The MIGHT Trial)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Monotherapy IVIG Gamunex-C for HMG-CoA Reductase Auto-Antibody Positive Necrotizing Myopathy Treatment (The MIGHT Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Grifols Biologicals, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 2, pilot, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of Gamunex-C IVIG as
      mono-therapy for HMGCoA reductase auto-antibody positive (HMGCR) necrotizing myopathy. The
      trial will test the feasibility and initial efficacy of Gamunex-C IVIG mono-therapy in HMGCR
      necrotizing myopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 2, double-blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled, multi-center trial of
      Gamunex-C IVIG as mono-therapy for HMGCR necrotizing myopathy. Up to 10 treatment-naïve
      patients will be enrolled and randomized to receive either Gamunex-C IVIG dosed at 2g/kg or
      placebo at week 0 and week 4. The primary efficacy outcome is the percentage of patients at
      week 8 with at least minimal improvement per the 2016 ACR/EULAR myositis clinical response
      criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled phase 2 trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ACR/EULAR 2016 Clinical Response Criteria for Myositis</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients in each arm with at least a minimal response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Manual Muscle Strength Testing (MMT-8) score</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Manual muscle strength testing in 8 muscle groups will be scored. Range 0-160, with higher scores reflecting increased muscle strength.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ACR/EULAR Clinical Response Criteria for Myositis Total Improvement Score</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8</time_frame>
    <description>The total improvement score based on ACR/EULAR 2016 criteria will be calculated. Range 0-100, with higher scores reflecting greater improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HMG-CoA Reductase Auto-antibody titer level</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Autoantibody titer level will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Creatine kinase</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Serum creatine kinase level will be measured</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients screened to achieve planned enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days needed to enroll planned sample</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of enrolled patients completing all primary and secondary measures</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Immune-Mediated Necrotizing Myopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gamunex-C IVIG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gamunex-C IVIG dosed at 2g/kg will be given on week 0 and week 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Albumin in a 1% solution at an equivalent volume to the corresponding Gamunex-C IVIG dose will be given at week 0 and week 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gamunex-C</intervention_name>
    <description>Gamunex-C IVIG will be given at week 0 and week 4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gamunex-C IVIG</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IVIG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albumin</intervention_name>
    <description>1% albumin solution dosed at equivalent volume to the corresponding weight-based Gamunex-C IVIG dose will be given at week 0 and week 4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        A subject must meet all of the following inclusion criteria at screening to be eligible for
        participation in this study:

          -  Anti-HMGCR positive. Patients will be screened by commercially-available ELISA.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Demonstrable proximal muscle weakness: score of &lt;135 on the Proximal Manual Muscle
             Strength Testing 8-Muscle Group Assessment (MMT-8) (range 0-160).

          -  Serum creatinine kinase (CK) more than 5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  Muscle biopsy will not be required for eligibility in order to minimize the time to
             enrollment and initiation of treatment. Muscle biopsy will be obtained whenever
             possible as part of the standard of care.

          -  Subjects must be willing and able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A subject meeting any of the following exclusion criteria at screening is NOT eligible for
        participation in this study:

          -  Disease duration greater than 36 months.

          -  Currently taking glucocorticoids.

          -  Participants will need to be tapered off all glucocorticoids by their treating
             physician over an interval deemed appropriate, and be free of steroid use for at least
             14 days prior to the time of study screening in order to be eligible.

          -  Exposure to immunoglobulin treatment (IV, IM, or SubQ) in the prior 3 months

          -  Exposure to plasma exchange (PEX) in the prior 3 months

          -  Exposure to other immunosuppressive medications (e.g. methotrexate, leflunomide,
             azathioprine, mycophenolate mofetil) in the prior 6 months

          -  Exposure to rituximab or any monoclonal antibody in the prior 12 months

          -  Exposure to a statin in the prior 3 months

          -  History of dermatomyositis rash (either biopsy-proven, or history of photosensitive
             rash).

          -  Presence of respiratory or swallowing dysfunction due to HMGCR myopathy

          -  Inadequate venous access

          -  History of anaphylactic reactions or severe reactions to any blood-derived product

          -  History of intolerance to any component of the IP

          -  History of thrombotic complication to polyclonal IVIG therapy

          -  History of pulmonary embolism or deep venous thromboembolism

          -  History of hyperviscosity or hypercoagulable state

          -  History of myocardial infarction or stroke in the last 12 months

          -  Currently receiving anti-coagulation therapy (vitamin K antagonists, non-vitamin K
             oral anticoagulants [e.g. dabigatran, rivaroxaban, apixaban], parenteral
             anticoagulants [e.g fondaparinux]. Note that oral anti-platelet agents are allowed
             (e.g. aspirin, clopidogrel, ticodipine).

          -  Females of child-bearing potential who are pregnant, have a positive serum pregnancy
             test (human chorionic gonadotropin [HCG]-based assay), breastfeeding, or are unwilling
             to practice a highly effective method of contraception (oral, injectable or implanted
             hormonal methods of contraception, placement of an intrauterine device or intrauterine
             system, condom or occlusive cap with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository, male
             sterilization, or true abstinence*) throughout the study.

             * True abstinence: When this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of the
             subject. (Periodic abstinence [e.g., calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
             post-ovulation methods], declaration of abstinence for the duration of a trial, and
             withdrawal are not acceptable methods of contraception.)

          -  Renal impairment (i.e., serum creatinine exceeds more than 1.5 times the upper limit
             of normal [ULN] for the expected normal range for the testing laboratory)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels exceeding
             more than 2.5 times the ULN for the expected normal range for the testing laboratory.

          -  Hemoglobin level &lt;9 g/dL

          -  Known Immunoglobulin A (IgA) deficiency and anti-IgA serum antibodies

          -  History of chronic alcoholism or illicit drug abuse (addiction) in the prior 12 months

          -  Active psychiatric illness that interferes with compliance or communication with
             healthcare personnel

          -  Currently receiving, or having received, within 1 month prior any investigational
             medicinal product or device. In the case of an investigational medicinal product
             trial, at least five half- lives (if known) must have elapsed prior to Screening.

          -  Any medical condition which makes the clinical trial participation unadvisable or
             which is likely to interfere with the evaluation of the study treatment and/or the
             satisfactory conduct of the clinical trial according to the investigator's judgment.
             Any factor that in the opinion of the investigator would compromise the ability of the
             subject to complete the trial

          -  Weight &gt; 120kg. Individuals weighing &gt;100kg and ≤120kg will be eligible at the
             discretion of the investigators.

          -  History of angina pectoris or transient ischemic attack (TIA) in the last 12 months

          -  Wells Criteria Score for DVT of 2 or more at the time of screening.

          -  Wells Criteria Score for PE of 4 or more at the time of screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James S Andrews, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leslie Thorn</last_name>
    <phone>206-295-4425</phone>
    <email>lazthorn@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jennifer Schaeffer</last_name>
    <phone>206-616-5330</phone>
    <email>jennif6@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James S. Andrews</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, School of Medicine: Rheumatology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HMG-CoA Reductase Auto-Antibody Necrotizing Myopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

