<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04457596</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A011801</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2020-03770</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA180821</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04457596</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>T-DM1 and Tucatinib Compared With T-DM1 Alone in Preventing Relapses in People With High Risk HER2-Positive Breast Cancer, the CompassHER2 RD Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>The CompassHER2 Trials (Comprehensive Use of Pathologic Response Assessment to Optimize Therapy in HER2-Positive Breast Cancer) CompassHER2 Residual Disease (RD), a Double-Blinded, Phase III Randomized Trial of T-DM1 Compared With T-DM1 and Tucatinib</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seattle Genetics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase III trial studies how well trastuzumab emtansine (T-DM1) and tucatinib work in
      preventing breast cancer from coming back (relapsing) in patients with high risk, HER2
      positive breast cancer. T-DM1 is a monoclonal antibody, called trastuzumab, linked to a
      chemotherapy drug, called DM1. Trastuzumab is a form of targeted therapy because it attaches
      to specific molecules (receptors) on the surface of cancer cells, known as HER2 receptors,
      and delivers DM1 to kill them. Tucatinib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some
      of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving T-DM1 and tucatinib may work better in
      preventing breast cancer from relapsing in patients with HER2 positive breast cancer compared
      to T-DM1 alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To determine if the invasive disease-free survival (iDFS) with T-DM1 and tucatinib is
      superior to the iDFS in the control arm (T-DM1 + placebo) when administered to high risk
      patients with HER2-positive breast cancer and residual disease after neoadjuvant
      HER2-directed therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate whether treatment with tucatinib plus T-DM1 compared to treatment with T-DM1
      alone (T-DM1 plus placebo) improves the following:

      Ia. Breast cancer free survival (BCFS). Ib. Distant recurrence-free survival (DRFS). Ic.
      Brain metastases-free survival (BMFS). Id. Overall survival (OS). II. To evaluate whether
      treatment with tucatinib plus T-DM1 compared to treatment with T-DM1 alone (T-DM1 plus
      placebo) reduces the incidence of brain metastases.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive T-DM1 intravenously (IV) over 30-90 minutes on day 1 and placebo
      orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 14
      cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients receive T-DM1 IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1 and tucatinib PO BID on days
      1-21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 14 cycles in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days, then every 6 months
      for 10 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2035</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2028</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified invasive disease-free survival (iDFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to one of the following events: invasive local, regional or distant recurrence, invasive contralateral breast cancer or death from any cause, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>A Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate the survival curves and a stratified log-rank test will be used to compare the invasive disease-free survival (iDFS) of the two arms. A stratified Cox model will be used to estimate the hazard ratio. If there appears to be clinically significant imbalances of baseline variables between the treatment arms, a secondary analysis of the primary endpoint will use stratified Cox model to compare the treatment effects that include the variables that are deemed imbalanced between the arms as adjusting variables. The randomization stratification variables will be the stratified variables in the model.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unmodified invasive disease-free survival (iDFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be defined as the time from randomization to one of the following events: invasive local, regional or distant recurrence, invasive contralateral breast cancer secondary primary invasive cancer (other than basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix), or death from any cause, assessed up to 10 years. A Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate the survival curves and a stratified log-rank test will be used to compare the iDFS of the two arms. A stratified Cox model will be used to estimate the hazard ratio.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast cancer-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to invasive local, regional, or distant recurrence, or invasive contralateral breast cancer, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with Kaplan-Meier curves and compared between the arms using a stratified log-rank test and stratified Cox model. If there are clinically significant imbalances in baseline characteristics between the treatment arms, a second analysis will be done using a stratified Cox model with the variables that are imbalance added as adjusting variables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distant recurrence-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to the first incidence of distant recurrence, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with Kaplan-Meier curves and compared between the arms using a stratified log-rank test and stratified Cox model. If there are clinically significant imbalances in baseline characteristics between the treatment arms, a second analysis will be done using a stratified Cox model with the variables that are imbalance added as adjusting variables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brain metastases-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to documentation of involvement of the central nervous system by metastatic cancer including parenchymal brain and spinal cord metastases as well as leptomeningeal carcinomatosis, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with Kaplan-Meier curves and compared between the arms using a stratified log-rank test and stratified Cox model. If there are clinically significant imbalances in baseline characteristics between the treatment arms, a second analysis will be done using a stratified Cox model with the variables that are imbalance added as adjusting variables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization until death from any cause, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with Kaplan-Meier curves and compared between the arms using a stratified log-rank test and stratified Cox model. If there are clinically significant imbalances in baseline characteristics between the treatment arms, a second analysis will be done using a stratified Cox model with the variables that are imbalance added as adjusting variables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of brain metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>An incident of brain metastases is documentation of involvement of the central nervous system by metastatic cancer including parenchymal brain and spinal cord metastases as well as leptomeningeal carcinomatosis. The cumulative incidence of brain metastases will be determined as the crude cumulative incidence as well as with incidence with competing risks where the competing event is death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 cycles of treatment (each cycle is 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy (FACT)-Breast Cancer (B) Trial Outcome Index questionnaire. The mixed model will compare the cycle 9 day 1 and cycle 14 day 1 time points between randomized arms. In addition to a randomized arm covariate, the model will include a randomized arm-by-time interaction term and will use the planned cycle of assessment as the categorical time value. Unstructured covariance will initially be used, though alternative covariance structures will be investigated with the final covariance structure selected based on minimization of the Akaike information criterion. A contrast will be used to compare mean change from baseline at cycle 9 day 1 between arms. If the two-sided 95% confidence interval excludes a difference of 5 favoring the trastuzumab emtansine (T-DM1) + placebo arm, then non-inferiority will be concluded.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 13 cycles of treatment (each cycle is 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy (FACT)-Breast Cancer (B) Trial Outcome Index questionnaire. The mixed model will compare the mean change from baseline at cycle 14 day 1 between arms. If the two-sided 95% confidence interval excludes a difference of 5 favoring the T-DM1 + placebo arm, then non-inferiority will be concluded at this time point.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1031</enrollment>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage IA Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage II Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage IIA Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage IIB Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage III Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage IIIA Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage IIIB Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Anatomic Stage IIIC Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>HER2 Positive Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Invasive Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Multifocal Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage I Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IA Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IB Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage II Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IIA Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IIB Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage III Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IIIA Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IIIB Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Prognostic Stage IIIC Breast Cancer AJCC v8</condition>
  <condition>Synchronous Bilateral Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (trastuzumab emtansine, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive T-DM1 IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1 and placebo PO BID on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 14 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (trastuzumab emtansine, tucatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive T-DM1 IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1 and tucatinib PO BID on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 14 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trastuzumab Emtansine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (trastuzumab emtansine, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (trastuzumab emtansine, tucatinib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (trastuzumab emtansine, placebo)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tucatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (trastuzumab emtansine, tucatinib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (trastuzumab emtansine, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (trastuzumab emtansine, tucatinib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (trastuzumab emtansine, placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (trastuzumab emtansine, tucatinib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HER2-positive status will be based on pretreatment biopsy material and defined as an
             immunohistochemistry (IHC) score of 3+ and/or positive by in situ hybridization (ISH)
             according to current American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) College of American
             Pathologists (CAP) guidelines. Central testing is not required

             * Known hormone receptor (HR) status as defined by ASCO/CAP guidelines. Hormone
             receptor positive status can be determined by either known positive estrogen receptor
             (ER) or known positive progesterone receptor (PR) status; hormone receptor negative
             status must be determined by both known negative ER and known negative PR

          -  Patients with residual HR-negative, HER2 positive (+) disease in the breast and/or
             lymph nodes per the surgical pathology report are eligible; however, patients with HR+
             HER2+ cancers must have node-positive residual disease per the surgical pathology
             report in order to qualify for the study. The presence of residual invasive disease in
             the breast is not mandatory for these patients. Note: The presence of micrometastases
             in lymph nodes after preoperative therapy counts as residual disease, whereas the
             presence of isolated tumor cells does not

          -  Patients with synchronous bilateral invasive disease are eligible provided both
             lesions were confirmed to be HER2-positive, and at least one of the lesions meets the
             criteria outlined above. Multifocal disease is allowed, as long as the largest
             biopsied breast tumor was HER2-positive

          -  Patients with clinical stage T1-4, N0-3 disease at presentation and residual invasive
             disease postoperatively as defined above are eligible. (Note: Patients with T1a/bN0
             tumors are not eligible)

          -  Patients must have received neoadjuvant chemotherapy with one of the following
             regimens: docetaxel/trastuzumab/pertuzumab (THP), paclitaxel/methotrexate/cisplatin
             (TMP), doxorubicin/cyclophosphamide/paclitaxel/trastuzumab/pertuzumab (AC-TH(P));
             docetaxel/carboplatin/trastuzumab/pertuzumab (TCH(P));
             fluorouracil/doxorubicin/cyclophosphamide-docetaxel/trastuzumab/pertuzumab
             (FAC-TH(P)), or
             fluorouracil/epirubicin/cyclophosphamide-docetaxel/trastuzumab/pertuzumab (FEC-TH(P)).
             Note: apart from TCHP, where T is docetaxel, treatment with docetaxel or paclitaxel is
             acceptable

          -  Patients may have received =&lt; 2 cycles of T-DM1 in the adjuvant setting. Note: These
             patients will be randomized to receive a further 14 cycles of T-DM1 and
             tucatinib/placebo as tolerated. The most recent cycle of T-DM1 should have been
             administered =&lt; 5 weeks prior to registration

             * N.B: Both of the following two criteria need to be met for the patient to be
             eligible for this study

               -  An interval of no more than 12 weeks between the completion date of the last
                  definitive treatment (e.g. postoperative chemotherapy or radiation, or if neither
                  given, breast surgical date) and the date of registration

               -  Patients must be registered on study within =&lt; 180 days of the date of the most
                  recent definitive breast cancer surgery (not including reconstructive surgery)

          -  All systemic chemotherapy should have been completed preoperatively unless
             participating in EA1181 (CompassHER2 pathologic complete response [pCR])

          -  Toxicities related to prior systemic treatment should have resolved or be at baseline,
             apart from alopecia and peripheral neuropathy =&lt; grade 1

          -  Adequate excision: surgical removal of all clinically evident disease in the breast
             and lymph nodes as follows:

               -  Breast surgery: total mastectomy with no gross residual disease at the margin of
                  resection, or breast-conserving surgery with histologically negative margins of
                  excision

               -  For patients who undergo breast-conserving surgery, the margins of the resected
                  specimen must be histologically free of invasive tumor and ductal carcinoma in
                  situ (DCIS) as determined by the local pathologist. If pathologic examination
                  demonstrates tumor at the line of resection, additional operative procedures may
                  be performed to obtain clear margins. If tumor is still present at the resected
                  margin after re-excision(s), the patient must undergo total mastectomy to be
                  eligible. Patients with margins positive for classic lobular carcinoma in situ
                  (LCIS) are eligible without additional resection

               -  Lymph node surgery ** The axilla needs to be evaluated with either sentinel node
                  biopsy or axillary lymph node dissection. If patients have a sentinel lymph node
                  biopsy and sentinel nodes are negative, no further axillary treatment is
                  necessary. If patients have isolated tumor cells (ITCs) in the setting of
                  residual breast disease, at least one of the following is required: axillary
                  lymph node dissection (ALND) or planned nodal irradiation. If patients have
                  micro- or macro-metastatic nodal disease, an ALND is required

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL (Note: packed red blood cells [PRBC] transfusion is not permitted
             to achieve eligibility)

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or direct bilirubin within the
             institutional normal range for patients with Gilbert's syndrome

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x upper limit
             of normal (ULN)

          -  Screening left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;= 50% on echocardiogram (ECHO) or
             multiple-gated acquisition (MUGA) after receiving neoadjuvant chemotherapy and no
             decrease in LVEF by more than 15% absolute points from the pre-chemotherapy LVEF. Or,
             if pre-chemotherapy LVEF was not assessed, the screening LVEF must be &gt;= 55% after
             completion of neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Note: LVEF assessment may be repeated once up
             to 3 weeks following the initial screening assessment to assess eligibility

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior receipt of T-DM1 in the neoadjuvant setting is not allowed

               -  Systemic therapy must have consisted of at least 9 weeks of preoperative taxane
                  and trastuzumab (or Food and Drug Administration [FDA]-approved biosimilar) with
                  or without pertuzumab. Patients who have received at least 9 weeks of
                  preoperative taxane, pertuzumab and margetuximab are also eligible. Note:
                  Patients who complete at least nine of a planned twelve doses of weekly
                  paclitaxel, or three of a planned four doses of docetaxel, but discontinue
                  prematurely due to toxicity (i.e. peripheral neuropathy =&lt; grade 1) are eligible.
                  Patients receiving dose-dense chemotherapy regimens are also eligible. Prior use
                  of nab-paclitaxel (Abraxane) instead of paclitaxel or docetaxel is permitted.
                  Prior use of subcutaneous trastuzumab (Hylecta) is also allowed

               -  Patients who received neoadjuvant systemic therapy which included experimental
                  HER2-targeted therapy/therapies are potentially eligible, as long as the
                  investigational agent was not a HER2-targeted antibody-drug conjugate (e.g.
                  T-DM1, DS-8201a [trastuzumab deruxtecan]) or a HER2 targeted tyrosine kinase
                  inhibitor (TKI) (e.g. tucatinib, lapatinib, neratinib)

          -  No adjuvant treatment with any anti-cancer investigational drug within 28 days prior
             to registration

          -  Not pregnant and not nursing, because this study involves an agent that has known
             genotoxic, mutagenic and teratogenic effects. Therefore, for women of childbearing
             potential only, a negative serum pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration
             is required

          -  Patients with known active and/or untreated hepatitis B or hepatitis C or chronic
             liver disease are ineligible. Patients with a diagnosis of hepatitis B or C that has
             been treated and cleared and normal liver function are eligible to participate in the
             study if the other eligibility parameters are met

          -  Stage IV (metastatic) breast cancer

          -  History of any prior (ipsi- or contralateral) invasive breast cancer within 3 years of
             registration

          -  Patients with ER+ HER2+ residual invasive disease that is lymph node-negative per the
             surgical pathology report

          -  Evidence of recurrent disease following preoperative therapy and surgery

          -  Patients for whom radiotherapy would be recommended for breast cancer treatment but
             for whom it is contraindicated because of medical reasons (e.g., connective tissue
             disorder or prior ipsilateral breast radiation)

          -  History of exposure to the following cumulative doses of anthracyclines: doxorubicin &gt;
             240 mg/m^2; epirubicin or liposomal doxorubicin-hydrochloride (Myocet) &gt; 480 mg/m^2.
             For other anthracyclines, exposure equivalent to doxorubicin &gt; 240 mg/m^2

          -  Cardiopulmonary dysfunction as defined by any of the following:

               -  History of National Cancer Institute (NCI) CTCAE version (v) 5.0 grade &gt;= 3
                  symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHF) or New York Heart Association (NYHA)
                  criteria class &gt;= II

               -  Angina pectoris requiring anti-anginal medication, serious cardiac arrhythmia not
                  controlled by adequate medication, severe conduction abnormality, or clinically
                  significant valvular disease

               -  High-risk uncontrolled arrhythmias: i.e., atrial tachycardia with a heart rate &gt;
                  100/min at rest, significant ventricular arrhythmia (ventricular tachycardia) or
                  higher-grade atrioventricular block (AV)-block (second degree AV-block type 2
                  [Mobitz 2] or third degree AV-block)

               -  Significant symptoms (grade &gt;= 2) relating to left ventricular dysfunction,
                  cardiac arrhythmia, or cardiac ischemia while or since receiving preoperative
                  therapy

               -  History of a decrease in left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) to &lt; 40% with
                  prior trastuzumab treatment (e.g., during preoperative therapy)

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt; 180 mmHg and/or diastolic
                  blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg)

          -  Current severe, uncontrolled systemic disease

          -  Major surgical procedure unrelated to breast cancer or significant traumatic injury
             within 28 days prior to registration or anticipation of the need for major surgery
             during the course of study treatment

          -  History of intolerance, including grade 3 to 4 infusion reaction or hypersensitivity
             to trastuzumab or murine proteins or any components of the product

          -  Peripheral neuropathy of any etiology that exceeds grade 1

          -  Assessment by the investigator as being unable or unwilling to comply with the
             requirements of the protocol

          -  Use of a strong CYP3A4 or CYP2C8 inhibitor within 2 weeks, or use of a strong CYP3A4
             or CYP2C8 inducer within 5 days prior to registration is prohibited. Please note that
             use of sensitive CYP3A substrates should be avoided two weeks before registration and
             during study treatment. Additionally, CYP3A4 or CYP2C8 inducers are prohibited as
             concomitant medications within 5 days following discontinuation of tucatinib treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ciara C. O'Sullivan, MB, BCh, BAO</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ciara C. O'Sullivan, MB, BCh, BAO</last_name>
    <phone>507-293-0526</phone>
    <email>osullivan.ciara@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ado-trastuzumab emtansine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Maytansine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

