<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04455841</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INCB 00928-104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04455841</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>INCB000928 Administered as a Monotherapy or in Combination With Ruxolitinib in Participants With Anemia Due to Myeloproliferative Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Open-Label, Multicenter Study of INCB000928 Administered as a Monotherapy or in Combination With Ruxolitinib in Participants With Anemia Due to Myeloproliferative Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Incyte Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Incyte Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase 1/2, open-label, dose-finding study is intended to evaluate the safety and
      tolerability, PK, PD, and efficacy of INCB000928 administered as monotherapy or in
      combination with ruxolitinib in participants with MF who are transfusion-dependent or
      presenting with symptomatic anemia. This study will consist of 2 parts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 19, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the safety and tolerability of INCB000928 administered as monotherapy (TGA) or in combination with ruxolitinib (TGB).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anemia Response</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as an increase in hemoglobin level of 1.5 g/L for 12 weeks in participants who are transfusion independent at baseline or achieving transfusion independency for 12 weeks if participants are transfusion dependent at baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duartion of Anemia Response</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of anemia response in transfusion dependent and transfusion independent participants at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Change of Hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in hemoglobin levels from baseline over 12-week treatment periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of RBC transfusion</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the average number of RBC units per participant-month during the treatment period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TGB only -Splenic Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the proportion of participants achieving a ≥ 35% reduction in spleen volume at Week 24 relative to baseline as measured by MRI or CT scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TGB Only - Splenic Length</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately Up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the proportion of participants achieving a ≥ 50% reduction in spleen length at any visit relative to baseline as measured by palpation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TGB only - Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the proportion of participants with Complete Response or Partial Response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TGB only - Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately up to 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the interval from the first dose of study treatment until the first documented progression or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TGB only - Leukemia Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately upto 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the interval from the first dose of study treatment until the first documented leukemia transformation or death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle after cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Area Under the Plasma Concentration versus Time curve of INCB 00928-104</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle after cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Time to reach maximum (peak) plasma concentration of INCB 00928-104</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle after cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time = 0 to the last measurable concentration at time = t.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepcidin levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle after cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Effect of INCB000928 administered as monotherapy (TGA) or in combination with ruxolitinib (TGB) on hepcidin levels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Iron Homeostasis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle after cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Effect of INCB000928 administered as monotherapy (TGA) or in combination with ruxolitinib (TGB) on iron homeostasis parameters such as TSI, ferritin, transferrin, TSAT, TIBC, UIBC, and serum NTBI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Erythropoesis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle after cycle 1 (each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Effect of INCB000928 administered as monotherapy (TGA) or in combination with ruxolitinib (TGB) on erythropoiesis parameters such as RC, NRBC, MCV, MCH, Hgb, Hct, RBC count, MCHC, and RDW.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Post-essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Post-polycythemia Vera Myelofibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group A (TGA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This part of the study will follow a BOIN design.
INCB000928 will be administered once daily( QD). The dose level of the next subsequent cohort will be based on the type and severity of the toxicity and on the available PK data observed during at least the first cycle (ie, 28 days, from Cycle 1 Day 1 to Cycle 1 Day 28) in at least 3 participants included in the previous cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group B (TGB)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INCB000928 will be administered in combination with ruxolitinib. The starting dose of INCB000928 will depend on monotherapy data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INCB000928</intervention_name>
    <description>INCB000928 Dose Escalation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group A (TGA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group B (TGB)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ruxolitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>INCB000928 +ruxolitinib Dose Expansion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group B (TGB)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with MF who are transfusion-dependent or present with symptomatic anemia,
             defined as follows:

               1. Anemia: An Hgb value &lt; 10 g/dL demonstrated during screening recorded on 3
                  separate occasions with at least 7 days between measurements (Note: RBC
                  transfusion must be at least 2 weeks before the Hgb measurement during
                  screening).

               2. Transfusion-dependent: Participant has received at least 4 units of RBC
                  transfusions during the 28 days immediately preceding Cycle 1 Day 1 OR has
                  received an average of at least 4 units of RBC transfusions in the 8 weeks
                  immediately preceding Cycle 1 Day 1, for an Hgb level of &lt; 8.5 g/dL, in the
                  absence of bleeding or treatment-induced anemia. In addition, the most recent
                  transfusion episode must have occurred in the 28 days before Cycle 1 Day 1.

          -  ECOG performance status score of the following:

               1. 0 or 1 for the dose-escalation stages.

               2. 0, 1, or 2 for the dose-expansion stage.

          -  Life expectancy is greater than 6 months

          -  Agreement to avoid pregnancy or fathering children.

          -  Ineligible to receive or have not responded to available therapies for anemia such as
             ESAs.

          -  For TGA:

          -  Participants previously treated with JAK inhibitors for at least 12 weeks.

          -  Participants with intermediate-2 or high DIPSS MF according to IWG-MRT criteria.

          -  For TGB:

          -  Participants must have been on a therapeutic and stable regimen of ruxolitinib for at
             least 12 consecutive weeks immediately preceding the first dose of study treatment.

          -  Participants with intermediate-1, intermediate-2, or high DIPSS MF according to
             IWG-MRT criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergone any prior allogenic or autologous stem cell transplantation or a candidate
             for such transplantation.

          -  Any prior chemotherapy, immunomodulatory drug therapy, immunosuppressive therapy,
             biological therapy, endocrine therapy, targeted therapy, antibody or hypomethylating
             agent to treat the participant's disease, with the exception of ruxolitinib for TGB
             only, within 5 half-lives or 28 days (whichever is shorter) before the first dose of
             study treatment.

          -  Laboratory Values outside of protocol defined range at screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Incyte Corporation Call Center (US)</last_name>
    <phone>1.855.463.3463</phone>
    <email>medinfo@incyte.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Incyte Corporation Call Center (ex-US)</last_name>
    <phone>+800 00027423</phone>
    <email>eumedinfo@incyte.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polycythemia Vera</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Myelofibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polycythemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocythemia, Essential</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myeloproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Incyte shares data with qualified external researchers after a research proposal is submitted. These requests are reviewed and approved by a review panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations.
The trial data availability is according to the criteria and process described on https://www.incyte.com/our-company/compliance-and-transparency</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be shared after the primary publication or 2 years after the study has ended for market authorized products and indications.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data from eligible studies will be shared with qualified researchers according to the criteria and process described in the Data Sharing section of the www.incyteclinicaltrials.com website. For approved requests, the researchers will be granted access to anonymized data under the terms of a data sharing agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.incyte.com/our-company/compliance-and-transparency</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

