<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04458974</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>tDCS-neglect</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04458974</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>tDCS in Post-stroke Neglect Rehabilitation</brief_title>
  <acronym>tDCS-Neglect</acronym>
  <official_title>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation as Coadjuvant Intervention in Post-stroke Neglect Rehabilitation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brain Damage Unit. Hospital beata María Ana (Madrid)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidad Francisco de Vitoria</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction

      Stroke is the main cause of disability in the world and its sequelae have a great impact in
      the functional independence and quality of life of patients and families. Unilateral spatial
      neglect is one of the most frequent cognitive deficits after stroke, and its maintenance is
      associated with poor functional outcome of the rehabilitation process.

      For many years clinical research has been conducted to develop new and effective
      rehabilitation strategies for neglect. Noninvasive brain stimulation (NIBS) techniques are
      important tools in this regard, and it should be considered as a therapeutic intervention
      used in combination with conventional neuropsychological approaches. Transcranial direct
      current stimulation (tDCS) is a noninvasive, safe, neurophysiological technique able to
      modulate cortical activity by inducing a weak electric current into the brain.

      The studies focused on neglect symptoms treatment by means of tDCS over the lesional and
      contralesional hemisphere have shown promising results and its combination with conventional
      neglect therapies may enhance treatment efficacy and speed the recovery.

      Objectives

      To improve neglect symptoms by reducing the pathological hyperactivity of the undamaged
      hemisphere after right medial cerebral artery stroke, through the application of multisite
      tDCS, and to validate a NIBS protocol for the enhancement of conventional neuropsychological
      rehabilitation outcome.

      Methods

      The sample will be composed by 30 patients with spatial neglect secondary to a ischemic
      stroke in the middle cerebral artery in subacute stage (3 to 12 months since the event). The
      patients will be randomly assigned to one experimental group (Active, Sham, and Control).

      The intervention protocol consists in a two weeks intervention (10 sessions, 45 min, Monday
      to Friday) of tDCS and neuropsychological rehabilitation applied concurrently. In each
      session a 20 min tDCS at 2 milliamps (m will be applied over P3 according to 10/20 EEG
      international system (cathodal) with return electrodes placed in C3,CP5,CP1,Pz,PO3,PO7,P7
      (10/20 EEG). StarStim® tDCS 8 channels Multisite device will be used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) is a safe and non-invasive neurophysiological
      technique with enough scientific literature that supports its effectiveness and safety, both
      in healthy subjects and in different neurological pathologies.

      However, it has not been consolidated yet as a real clinical alternative for other
      pathologies different from depression, due to the impossibility of establishing specific
      intervention protocols given the heterogeneity of the samples and the methods of assessment
      of the results used in the different studies.

      Regarding stroke, although there is large empirical evidence of its effectiveness in motor
      rehabilitation, there are few studies to date focused on cognitive rehabilitation, such
      neglect rehabilitation.

      Hypothesis

      The main hypothesis is that patients who receive a treatment based on tDCS in combination
      with conventional neuropsychological intervention for the recovery of neglect will have a
      greater improvement in neglect symptomatology in comparison to patients who receive the
      conventional treatment in isolation.

      Objectives

      The main objective of the project is to validate a protocol for the enhancement of
      conventional neuropsychological rehabilitation using tDCS in a group of patients with spatial
      neglect secondary to a cortical ischemic stroke in the middle cerebral artery (MCA) in a
      subacute phase (3 to 12 months since the event).

      Specific objectives:

        -  To demonstrate that non-invasive neuromodulation by means of tDCS enhances the efficacy
           of the conventional neuropsychological rehabilitation.

        -  Identify clinical and neurophysiological variables of the patients are the best
           predictors of the efficacy of the combined treatment.

        -  To verify the greater impact of the combined treatment in the improvement of the
           symptomatology of neglect as well as in the patient's quality of life in comparison with
           the conventional intervention.

      Methods

      Design:

      The present study is a parallel, randomized, controlled and triple blind experimental study.
      The patients included in the sample will be randomly distributed into three groups (Exp, Sham
      and Control) that will be blind to the patients, to the researchers who apply the tDCS and to
      the pre and post intervention evaluators.

        -  Experimental group (Exp): active tDCS + conventional neuropsychological rehabilitation.

        -  Control group placebo-tDCS (Sham): placebo tDCS (sham) + conventional neuropsychological
           rehabilitation.

        -  Control group (Control): conventional neuropsychological rehabilitation without tDCS.

      The duration of the study will be 3 years.

      Sample:

      The sample will consist of 30 volunteer patients randomly distributed to one of the
      experimental condition (1:1:1) with blind of the randomization sequence. Randomization will
      be done with the help of the research support department of the Francisco de Vitoria
      University. Patients will be recruited in the Brain Damage Unit of Beata María Ana Hospital
      by the unit neurologist and neuropsychologists among those patients who meet the inclusion
      criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel, randomized, controlled and triple blind experimental study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hemispatial neglect symptomatology</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hemispatial neglecteglect sympthomatology assessed by The Bell Test (Gauthier, Dehaut, and Joanette 1989)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hemispatial neglect symptomatology</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hemispatial neglecteglect sympthomatology assessed by Copy of drawings subtest Barcelona test (Peña Casanova 2005)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hemispatial neglect symptomatology</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hemispatial neglecteglect sympthomatology assessed by Line bisection test (Schenkenberg, Bradford, and Ajax 1980)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hemispatial neglect symptomatology</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in hemispatial neglecteglect sympthomatology assessed by The motor-free visual perception test (MVPT): (Colarusso, Hammill, and Academic Therapy Publications 1995)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional independence</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in functional independence assessed by The Catherine Bergego Scale (Azouvi et al. 2003)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional independence</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in functional independence assessed by Barthel Index (Mahoney and Barthel 1965)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in general cognitive functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in general cognitive functioning assessed by Mini-mental state examination (MMSE) (Folstein, Folstein, and McHugh 1975)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in neurophysiological assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post intervention (3 days after the end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in neurophysiological assessment through a resting state EEG acquisition. EEG will be recorded at rest using 64 electrodes in a system 10-20 distribution. An actiCHamp amplifier (Brain Vision LLC, North Carolina, United States) will be used to amplify and digitize the EEG data at a sampling frequency of 512 Hz. Alpha, Beta, Theta and Gamma bands will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects and patient comfort assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post session (before and at the end of every session - 1 min after the end of the session)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the presence or not of side effects and comport or discomfort of the patient during the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Neglect, Hemispatial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group (Exp)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active tDCS + conventional rehabilitation therapy (physiotherapy and neuropsychological rehabilitation)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-tDCS (Sham)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham tDCS + conventional rehabilitation therapy (physiotherapy and neuropsychological rehabilitation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (Control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional rehabilitation therapy (physiotherapy and neuropsychological rehabilitation) without tDCS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial direct current stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists in two-weeks treatment, 10 consecutive sessions of tDCS ( Monday to Friday) applied concurrently to neuropsychological rehabilitation.
The tDCS Multisite StratStim® 8-channel device (Neuroelectrics) will be used for tDCS stimulation. The duration of the stimulation will be 20 minutes at 2 mA. The tDCS will be applied with the cathode positioned in P3 (following the international 10/20 EEG system), and the return electrodes will be placed in C3, CP5, CP1, Pz, PO3, PO7, P7.
The sessions will last 1 hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group (Exp)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-tDCS (Sham)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuropsychological rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>The neuropsychological rehabilitation protocol has been designed for the recovery of neglect symptomatology. Each session will consist on the performance of different cognitive stimulation tasks aimed at improving attention and visoperceptive abilities. The tasks will be applied through the NeuronUp neurorehabilitation platform in order to achieve maximum homogeneity and objectivity across patients.
The neuropsychological rehabilitation will last 30min (in 1h intervention session).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (Control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group (Exp)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-tDCS (Sham)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hemorrhagic or ischemic stroke in the right hemisphere.

          -  Stroke 3 to 12 months since the event (regardless of whether or not they have received
             prior rehabilitation).

          -  18 to 99 years-old.

          -  Neuroimaging study.

          -  Absence of previous strokes.

          -  Functional capacity that allows him/her to remain seated and active for one hour
             (Barthel Index score greater than 5 in the item of transfers between chair and bed;
             this item can be scored from 0 to 15, being 0 totally dependent and 15 totally
             independent).

          -  Right-handed manual dominance

          -  Neglect scores on at least two of the three tests administered for the assessment of
             visuospatial neglect.

          -  Signature of informed consent by the patient or his/her legal guardian.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dermatological problems (psoriasis, dermatitis on the scalp or face).

          -  Presence of implants or metal parts in the head excluding fillings.

          -  Pacemakers, medication pumps, stimulators (vagal, cerebral, transcutaneous),
             ventriculoperitoneal shunts or aneurysm clips.

          -  Presence of previous strokes.

          -  Neurological disease other than stroke described in the inclusion criteria.

          -  Severe cognitive impairment assessed using the Mini-mental state examination (MMSE),
             excluding patients with scores under 24 (the score of MMSE are between 0 and 30, being
             0 severe cognitive impairment and 30 no cognitive impairment).

          -  Significant language difficulties that not allow proper understanding of activities or
             severely limit expression.

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse.

          -  Moderate or severe active depression.

          -  Uncontrolled medical problems (pathologies in acute phase without medical or
             pharmacological treatment with proven efficacy or pathologies with imminent life
             risk).

          -  Pregnancy or suspected pregnancy that will be checked by pregnancy test at the
             beginning of the study in patients of childbearing age and with the recommendation of
             the use of contraceptive methods until the end of the intervention.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elena M Marron, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34620912976</phone>
    <email>emunozmarr@uoc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Beata María Ana (Brain Damage Unit)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juan Pablo Romero, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34914090903</phone>
      <email>p.romero.prof@ufv.es</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitat Oberta de Catalunya</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elena Munoz Marron</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neglect</keyword>
  <keyword>neuropsychological rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>non-invasive brain stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>transcranial direct current stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>tDCS</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Perceptual Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

