<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04450264</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 17-2188</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21MD012863-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04450264</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Increasing African Immigrant Women's Participation in Breast Cancer Screening</brief_title>
  <acronym>AIBCS</acronym>
  <official_title>Increasing African Immigrant's Breast Cancer Screening</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      New York City (NYC) is home to a large and diverse immigrant population. Many of these groups
      face significant barriers to preventive health care, including lack of insurance, poor health
      care access and language difficulties. Most African immigrant women are likely to live below
      the poverty line and have low health literacy, are less likely to have health insurance and
      visit a doctor, particularly for primary/preventive care. Without access to primary care,
      many preventive services, such as breast cancer screenings go unattended. The barriers and
      facilitators to breast cancer screening for other minority groups from underserved
      populations, such as African Americans and Latina women have been studied. Less is known
      about these for African immigrant women and how to most effectively engage their
      participation in regular screening. Data of over 2,000 African-born immigrants living in NYC
      show that 77% report not having health insurance; 75% do not have a primary care physician;
      and 57% have less than a high school education. As for cancer screening, when corrected for
      age, 44% have never had a mammogram. Through the study team's unique collaboration with the
      African Services Committee and the African Advisory Council of the Bronx, two
      non-governmental community-based service organizations, the study team is poised to have a
      significant impact on these immigrant women, who have emigrated from more than 20 countries
      in Africa. This is a population with great need for increased breast cancer knowledge, access
      to breast cancer screening, and basic medical care. The Health Belief Model (HBM) provides a
      framework for addressing cultural health barriers by positing that making a decision to
      engage in a health behavior is determined by weighing perceived threats versus benefits. The
      long term goal of the proposed project is to conduct a randomized clinical trial that tests
      the adapted intervention to increase breast cancer screening rates for African-born
      immigrants. In the short term, the study team plans to pursue the following specific aims:
      (1) Identify barriers and facilitators to breast cancer screening among African-born
      immigrants and (2) Culturally adapt and pilot test the Witness Project breast cancer
      education program for African-born women. Thus, the study team will culturally adapt an
      effective, innovative intervention to address this significant health disparity in
      African-born immigrant communities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of Aim 1 is to collect formative data via a mixed methods approach and use those
      results to culturally adapt the Witness Project for African immigrant populations. Cultural
      adaptation will follow the stage model outlined by Barrera et al.48 The model includes five
      stages: 1) information gathering to determine which intervention components to modify; 2)
      preliminary adaptation design that integrates information from stage 1 to inform preliminary
      modification of the original intervention; 3) preliminary adaptation tests to pilot the
      intervention for feasibility and acceptability, 4) adaptation refinement with decisions
      informed a leadership team/advisory board; and 5) cultural adaptation trial to test the
      effectiveness of the intervention in changing health outcomes. As this is the first step in
      this line of research, the proposed study will only follow stages 1-4. The Witness Project
      has three main components that will be culturally adapted: 1) educational presentation
      addressing myths, barriers and values related to breast cancer and mammography, 2) culturally
      matched, peer led narrative about breast cancer experience, 3) experiential education about
      breast anatomy and self-examination. The quantitative surveys will be conducted first. The
      results will inform the refinement of the focus group guide and in-depth interview questions.
      The &quot;point of interface&quot; (i.e., merging quantitative and qualitative data) will be
      associations between mammography screening and HBM constructs (e.g., perceived risk,
      self-efficacy) and any socio-demographic characteristics (i.e., preferred language, health
      literacy level). The quantitative results will inform the refinement of the qualitative
      questions. For example, if an association is found between self-efficacy and screening, the
      study team will ask in-depth questions about self-efficacy and suggestions for how it could
      be improved in this population.

      Participant Recruitment for Focus Groups, Interviews and Surveys. There is a tremendous
      diversity of African nations and languages; focusing research on individual African nations
      and/or native languages is not feasible within the proposed study. Given that French and
      English are the most prevalent non-native languages spoken by African immigrants in New York
      City, the study team has chosen to focus on targeting individuals who speak these languages
      as a first step in this line of research. All participants will be recruited from African
      immigrant communities in NYC. Based on the prior experience of the study team's community
      partners, the majority of the populations that they serve are from Senegal, Mali, Ivory
      Coast, and Burkina Faso. In anticipation of wide variations in cultural values, barriers and
      benefits, the study team will thus use a maximum variation sampling approach to allow
      discovery of central themes, core elements and/or shared dimensions that cut across a diverse
      sample of participants. The study team has a well-established collaborative relationship with
      gatekeepers (see Letters of Support) in the African immigrant community and have successfully
      recruited African-born persons into prior studies49 and therefore anticipate successful
      recruitment for this proposed research. Participants will be recruited for in-depth
      interviews, focus groups, and surveys through IRB approved flyers at community sites. All
      participants will receive $30 for their participation. HIPAA authorization and informed
      consent will be obtained prior to participation. Quantitative Surveys: The study team will
      conduct surveys (N=50) to assess predictors of breast cancer screening among African
      immigrant women. The survey will be conducted by a bilingual RA an take about 15-30 minutes
      to complete and participants will receive $30. Measures: Sociodemographic data will be
      collected for all participants and will include age, gender, education level, primary
      language spoken, marital status, health insurance status and income (see Appendix). The
      survey will include questions about breast cancer knowledge, self-efficacy, fear, mistrust,
      perceived risk, benefits/barriers to screening, fatalism, screening intention, acculturation,
      and health literacy(see Appendix; Table of Measures). Focus Groups: The study team will
      conduct three focus groups (n=24) with African immigrant gatekeepers and stakeholders,
      including African immigrant women. The study team will ask the community partners to assist
      us with identifying potential participants for the focus groups. The goal of the focus groups
      is to gather rich, qualitative data from African immigrant stakeholders and gatekeepers about
      the breast cancer screening needs of women within their communities. The study team will
      deliver informational presentations about the focus groups and the proposed study at events
      and meetings held by the community partners. The study team will conduct one focus group with
      gatekeepers and stakeholders (in English) and the other two focus groups will be conducted
      with African immigrant women (in French and English). The focus groups will take 75-90
      minutes to complete and will be conducted by a bilingual RA. In-depth Interviews: The study
      team will conduct in-depth interviews (n=20; see Appendix) to identify breast cancer
      screening barriers and facilitators (e.g., age, gender, country of origin) among eligible
      African-born immigrant women. An RA will approach potential participants and explain the
      purpose of the study, verify eligibility and obtain informed consent. Participants will be
      asked to discuss their beliefs about barriers and facilitators patients may face as they
      consider breast cancer screening. The duration of the in-depth interview and focus group will
      be approximately one hour including the interview and completion of a demographic
      questionnaire. Quantitative Data Analysis: As the assessment will be administered as an
      interview, The study team does not anticipate much missing data. As needed, missing data will
      be imputed and then be used to estimate the parameter values for each of scales. The study
      team estimates that the sample size of 64 participants will generate a +/- 11% margin of
      error at a 90% confidence level. The primary outcomes are screening status (up-to-date with
      for mammography screening) and HBM constructs. As screening status is dichotomous, a logistic
      regression analysis will be conducted using socio-demographics and HBM constructs (e.g.,
      self-efficacy, perceived risk, perceived benefits) as explanatory variables. Since Aim 1 is
      designed to provide information to inform the adaptation of the subsequent intervention and
      education, the study team shall adopt a less conservative criterion for statistical
      significance using a p-value equal to or less than 0.15.

      Qualitative Data Analysis. The PEN-3 model25 will guide the interpretation and analysis of
      the focus groups and in-depth interviews. Using this model as a framework, the analysis
      approach will identify the unique barriers and facilitators related to African-born
      immigrants' health care engagement. Transcripts will be reviewed using the N'Vivo qualitative
      data management software. 50 Analysis will use tri-phasic coding - including open, axial and
      selective coding. In the open coding phase, transcripts will be examined for salient
      categories of information supported by the text (e.g., barriers and facilitators to uptake of
      cancer screening in African immigrants). Themes that are extensively discussed by
      participants will be coded. Using a constant comparative approach, categories will be
      saturated until new information is no longer added. The research team will meet prior to
      conducting analysis to define coding labels and definitions. Potential labels and definitions
      will be drawn from identified barriers and facilitators for other preventive cancer screening
      exams (e.g., pap test, colonoscopy). All transcripts (including those translated from French
      to English) will be independently coded by PI Sly and Co-I Jandorf using the same framework
      to ensure consistency. They will meet multiple times to discuss the coding strategy for the
      first focus group and first half of the interviews and discuss and resolve any coding
      discrepancies prior to coding of the remaining focus groups and interviews, and again to
      resolve any remaining discrepancies by consensus. When there is disagreement on coding
      labels, the research team will meet to discuss reasons for disagreement and modify coding
      labels appropriately. Analyses will also examine subgroup differences (i.e., country of
      origin), age, and language. The study team's proposed sample size of 24 focus group
      participants and 20 in-depth interview participants will be stratified by language and the
      study team anticipate achieving saturation with these sample sizes. If saturation is not
      achieved with the 44 participants, the study team will recruit more participants with
      collaborators and community partners.

      The educational aspect of the program will be modeled after the study team's current
      community based programs, as noted above, using narrative formats through stories from role
      models who have undergone breast cancer screenings. The programs will disseminate relevant,
      up-to-date information for breast cancer to eligible African-born immigrant women.

      Recruitment and Iterative Program Development: After the completion of the interviews and
      focus groups in Aim 1, a 3×3 table of themes categorized using the PEN-3 model 25 will be
      produced for each of the three components of the Witness Project: 1) addressing myths,
      barriers and values, 2) culturally relevant breast cancer narrative, 3) experiential breast
      education. Themes will be categorized in the following domains: cultural empowerment and
      relationships and expectations. These themes will inform how the intervention components for
      the educational narrative program should be adapted for an African immigrant audience. The
      themes will first be categorized according to barriers and facilitators to screening and then
      the team will decide which themes are appropriate. For example, barriers and facilitators
      from the cultural empowerment domain may include concerns about deportation, modesty,
      religiosity and healthcare screenings and will be addressed in the Witness Project component
      1. Another example might be that barriers and facilitators from the relationships domain
      could include concerns about the role of patriarchy in women's healthcare decision making -
      such as having a mammogram. This could potentially be addressed in the culturally relevant
      narrative (component 2). The cultural facilitators to screening identified in the interviews
      will be incorporated into the program by highlighting them as reasons to participate in
      screening. Cultural barriers identified will also be addressed in the culturally relevant
      narrative by providing examples and suggestions for coping with these perceived risks. The
      study team will invite participants (N=20) to give feedback on the first iteration of the
      educational program components, procedures and feasibility and
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mammogram intention</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' intentions to complete breast cancer screening by responding to How likely or unlikely is it that you will have a mammogram in the next 12 months? a. Very unlikely b. Unlikely c. Likely d. Very Likely</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mammogram location and appointment</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' intentions to complete breast cancer screening: Have you thought about where you will have your next mammogram? a. Yes b. No Have you thought about making the appointment? a. Yes b. No</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Risk</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' perceived risk of developing breast cancer: What do you think are the chances that you will have breast cancer at some point in your life? 1. Very low 2. Somewhat low 3. Moderate 4. Somewhat high 5. Very high</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison Perceived Risk</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate</time_frame>
    <description>Participants' perceived risk of developing breast cancer: Compared to the average person your age and gender, would you say that you are... 1. Less likely to get breast cancer 2. About as likely to get breast cancer 3. More likely to get breast cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Efficacy for Mammography</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate</time_frame>
    <description>Ten items will be used to examine participants' self-efficacy for undergoing mammography using a 5-point Likert-type scale. Full scale from 1 to 5, with higher score indicating greater self-efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        African Immigrant women living in NYC - community sample.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  40 years of age

          -  Women born in Africa

          -  Read and speak English or French

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;40 years of age

          -  Cannot read and speak English or French
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamilia R Sly, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jamilia R Sly, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-824-7813</phone>
    <email>jamilia.sly@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jamilia R Sly, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>212-824-7813</phone>
      <email>jamila.sly@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lina Jandorf, MA</last_name>
      <email>lina.jandorf@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jamilia R Sly, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erwin DO, Johnson VA, Trevino M, Duke K, Feliciano L, Jandorf L. A comparison of African American and Latina social networks as indicators for culturally tailoring a breast and cervical cancer education intervention. Cancer. 2007 Jan 15;109(2 Suppl):368-77.</citation>
    <PMID>17173279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saad-Harfouche FG, Jandorf L, Gage E, Thélémaque LD, Colón J, Castillo AG, Treviño M, Erwin DO. Esperanza y Vida: training lay health advisors and cancer survivors to promote breast and cervical cancer screening in Latinas. J Community Health. 2011 Apr;36(2):219-27. doi: 10.1007/s10900-010-9300-3.</citation>
    <PMID>20711645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hurtado-de-Mendoza A, Song M, Kigen O, Jennings Y, Nwabukwu I, Sheppard VB. Addressing cancer control needs of African-born immigrants in the US: a systematic literature review. Prev Med. 2014 Oct;67:89-99. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2014.07.006. Epub 2014 Jul 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25034729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wafula EG, Snipes SA. Barriers to health care access faced by black immigrants in the US: theoretical considerations and recommendations. J Immigr Minor Health. 2014 Aug;16(4):689-98. doi: 10.1007/s10903-013-9898-1.</citation>
    <PMID>24006174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janz NK, Becker MH. The Health Belief Model: a decade later. Health Educ Q. 1984 Spring;11(1):1-47. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6392204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreuter MW, Green MC, Cappella JN, Slater MD, Wise ME, Storey D, Clark EM, O'Keefe DJ, Erwin DO, Holmes K, Hinyard LJ, Houston T, Woolley S. Narrative communication in cancer prevention and control: a framework to guide research and application. Ann Behav Med. 2007 Jun;33(3):221-35. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17600449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreuter MW, Holmes K, Alcaraz K, Kalesan B, Rath S, Richert M, McQueen A, Caito N, Robinson L, Clark EM. Comparing narrative and informational videos to increase mammography in low-income African American women. Patient Educ Couns. 2010 Dec;81 Suppl:S6-14. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2010.09.008. Epub 2010 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21071167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillard AJ, Fagerlin A, Dal Cin S, Zikmund-Fisher BJ, Ubel PA. Narratives that address affective forecasting errors reduce perceived barriers to colorectal cancer screening. Soc Sci Med. 2010 Jul;71(1):45-52. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2010.02.038. Epub 2010 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>20417005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larkey LK, Lopez AM, Minnal A, Gonzalez J. Storytelling for promoting colorectal cancer screening among underserved Latina women: a randomized pilot study. Cancer Control. 2009 Jan;16(1):79-87.</citation>
    <PMID>19078934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jandorf L, Braschi C, Ernstoff E, Wong CR, Thelemaque L, Winkel G, Thompson HS, Redd WH, Itzkowitz SH. Culturally targeted patient navigation for increasing african americans' adherence to screening colonoscopy: a randomized clinical trial. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2013 Sep;22(9):1577-87. doi: 10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-12-1275. Epub 2013 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23753039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sriphanlop P, Jandorf L, Kairouz C, Thelemaque L, Shankar H, Perumalswami P. Factors related to hepatitis B screening among Africans in New York City. Am J Health Behav. 2014 Sep;38(5):745-54. doi: 10.5993/AJHB.38.5.12.</citation>
    <PMID>24933144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreuter MW, Lukwago SN, Bucholtz RD, Clark EM, Sanders-Thompson V. Achieving cultural appropriateness in health promotion programs: targeted and tailored approaches. Health Educ Behav. 2003 Apr;30(2):133-46.</citation>
    <PMID>12693519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bollinger S, Kreuter MW. Real-time moment-to-moment emotional responses to narrative and informational breast cancer videos in African American women. Health Educ Res. 2012 Jun;27(3):537-43. doi: 10.1093/her/cys047. Epub 2012 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22498923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erwin DO, Treviño M, Saad-Harfouche FG, Rodriguez EM, Gage E, Jandorf L. Contextualizing diversity and culture within cancer control interventions for Latinas: changing interventions, not cultures. Soc Sci Med. 2010 Aug;71(4):693-701. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2010.05.005. Epub 2010 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>20646810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crookes DM, Njoku O, Rodriguez MC, Mendez EI, Jandorf L. Promoting colorectal cancer screening through group education in community-based settings. J Cancer Educ. 2014 Jun;29(2):296-303. doi: 10.1007/s13187-013-0599-1.</citation>
    <PMID>24385340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jamilia Sly</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>African Immigrant</keyword>
  <keyword>Women</keyword>
  <keyword>New York City</keyword>
  <keyword>French</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 3 months and ending 5 years following article publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Anyone who wishes to access the data.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

