<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04456296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EN3000-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04456296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of the Effect of Testosterone Replacement Therapy on Blood Pressure in Adult Male Participants With Hypogonadism</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Randomized, Parallel-Group, Three Treatment Arm, Multicenter Study on Hypogonadal Males to Evaluate the Effect on 24-Hour Ambulatory Blood Pressure After 16-Week Continuous Administration With Marketed Testosterone Products</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Endo Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Endo Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Testosterone is the principal androgen produced by the male testes. Hypogonadism is the
      result of inadequate production of testosterone by the Leydig cells of the testes and is
      reflected by serum concentrations of testosterone of &lt; 300 ng/dL, with no discernible diurnal
      pattern. The etiology of hypogonadism may be primary or secondary. The treatment of males
      with primary, and in some cases, secondary Hypogonadism includes administration of
      testosterone.

      Testim® and Fortesta® are topical creams that when applied daily help to increase the total
      testosterone levels in the blood through skin absorption. Aveed® is an injectable form of
      testosterone treatment and subjects randomized to this treatment arm will receive 3
      injections over the course of 16 weeks.

      This study is designed to evaluate the effect on blood pressure of approved testosterone
      products (Testim®, Fortesta®, and Aveed®) after 16 weeks of therapy using 24-hour Ambulatory
      blood pressure (ABPM) to reveal shifts in BP levels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to end of Treatment in 24-hour average systolic ambulatory blood pressure (BP).</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 16 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">729</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypogonadism</condition>
  <condition>Hypogonadism, Male</condition>
  <condition>Hypogonadotropic Hypogonadism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone undecanoate injection (AVEED)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fixed dosage level of 750mg/3mL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone gel (FORTESTA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>40mg once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone gel (TESTIM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>50mg once daily (titrated)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aveed Injectable Product, Fortesta or Testim</intervention_name>
    <description>Depending on the treatment arm, the daily dose of the study drug will be either a fixed dosage or titrated for each subject, according to approved dosage and administration instructions, if necessary, until the circulating testosterone concentrations of the subject reaches normal concentrations (300-1000 ng/dL).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone gel (FORTESTA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone gel (TESTIM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone undecanoate injection (AVEED)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Have a diagnosis of primary hypogonadism OR hypogonadotropic hypogonadism.

          2. Have a total serum testosterone at screening &lt; 300 ng/dL.

          3. Be naïve to androgen replacement or washout of 12 weeks following intramuscular
             androgen injections; 4 weeks following topical or buccal, nasal, or oral androgens.

          4. Have a screening Blood Pressure at rest of less than 140 mm Hg for Systolic Blood
             Pressure and less than 90 mm Hg for Diastolic Blood Pressure.

          5. Be judged to be in good health.

          6. Subjects enrolled in the Testim or Fortesta treatment arms: take necessary precautions
             to avoid skin-to-skin contact and potential transfer and if male use effective
             contraception.

          7. Be willing and able to cooperate with the requirements of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Is from a vulnerable population, as defined by the US Code of Federal Regulations
             (CFR) Title 45, Part 46, Section 46.111(b) and other local and national regulations,
             including but not limited to, employees (temporary, part-time, full time, etc) or a
             family member of the research staff conducting the study, or of the sponsor, or of the
             contract research organization, or of the Institutional Review Board/Independent
             Ethics Committee (IRB/IEC).

          2. Has a history of significant sensitivity or allergy to the study drugs, including
             androgens, or product excipients.

          3. Has a history of or medical examination findings renal, hepatic, neurologic,
             hematologic, endocrine, oncologic, pulmonary, immunologic, psychiatric conditions,
             cardiovascular disease/dysrhythmia) or any other condition(s) that restricts study
             participation.

          4. Is not on a stable medication regimen for at least 3 months for the treatment of a
             chronic condition.

          5. Has had a cardiovascular and/or cerebrovascular event within the last 6 months.

          6. Needs Blood Pressure cuff size larger than 50 cm.

          7. Works a night shift or performs heavy manual labor.

          8. Has any known contraindication(s) to active study treatment including, but not limited
             to: known or suspected carcinoma of the prostate or breast, previous history of cancer
             (except basal cell carcinoma of the skin) liver disease, active deep vein thrombosis,
             atrial fibrillation, untreated sleep apnea, or is immune compromised.

          9. Uses known inhibitors (eg, ketoconazole) or inducers of cytochrome P450 3A (eg,
             dexamethasone, phenytoin, rifampin, carbamazepine) of cytochrome P450 3A (CYP3A)
             within 30 days prior to study drug administration and through the end of the study.

               1. Uses any of the above listed drugs within 5 half lives of the last dose in the
                  past 6 months prior to study drug administration.

               2. Has received any of the above listed drugs by injection within 30 days or 10 half
                  lives (whichever is longer) prior to study drug administration.

               3. Uses Neutraceuticals or homeopathic compounds.

         10. Has a history of drug or alcohol abuse within 6 months prior to study drug
             administration.

         11. Has untreated moderate to severe depression.

         12. Has any skin lesions/cuts/injury at the application site.

         13. Has suspected reversible hypogonadism.

         14. Donated blood or blood products or experienced significant blood loss within 90 days
             prior to study drug administration.

         15. Intends to conceive at any time during the study.

         16. Donated bone marrow within 6 months prior to study drug administration.

         17. Has participated in a previous investigational study or received treatment with an
             investigational product within 30 days of screening.

         18. Has a diagnosis of, is undergoing therapy for, or has received therapy for a
             hematologic malignancy in the 5 years prior to screening.

         19. Has a positive test on a urine drug screen for drugs of abuse.

         20. Abnormal ECG (QT prolongation with QTc ≥450 ms).

         21. Has any other condition that might indicate the subject to be unsuitable for the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis Ortega</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Endo Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Deanna Lutte</last_name>
    <phone>800-462-3636</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials@Endo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Davina Cupo</last_name>
    <phone>800-462-3636</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials@Endo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endo Clinical Trial Site #1</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypogonadism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eunuchism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

