<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04454866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>202055076</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04454866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Penehyclidine for Prevention of Nausea and Vomiting After Bimaxillary Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Penehyclidine in Preventing Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting in Patients Underging Bimaxillary Surgery: A Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University First Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Peking University Hospital of Stomatology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University First Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) is a common complication after surgery. Patients
      undergoing orthognathic surgery are reported to have a high rate of PONV, especially those
      undergoing bimaxillary surgery. Activation of cholinergic system plays an important role in
      the development of PONV. Penehyclidine is an muscarinic antagonists which selectively block
      M1 and M3 receptors and is commonly used to decrease oral secretion. The investigators
      hypothesize that continuously administrated penehyclidine during perioperative period can
      reduce the incidence of PONV in patients undergoing bimaxillary surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) is one of the most frequently occurred complications
      after surgery, and are associated with patients' dissatisfaction after anesthesia and
      surgery. Orthognathic surgery is widely performed for the correction of dentofacial
      deformities. Despite of improved anti-emetic prophylaxis, patients undergoing orthognathic
      surgery are reported to have a high incidence of PONV, especially those after bimaxillary
      surgery.

      It is known that activation of central cholinergic system plays an important role in the
      development of PONV. Muscarinic antagonists such as scopolamine can block muscarinic
      receptors in the cerebral cortex and produce anti-emetic effects. Penehyclidine is a new
      muscarinic antagonists which selectively block M1 and M3 receptors. Our previous study
      indicated that single-dose of penehyclidine injected before anesthesia induction was
      associated with a reduced risk of PONV during the first 6 h postoperatively.The mean
      elimination half-life of penehyclidine following single administration is about 10.35 h.
      Hence, a single-dose penehyclidine may only produce a short duration of antiemetic effect.

      The investigators hypothesize that continuously administrated penehyclidine during
      perioperative period reduces PONV more effectively than single-dose injection in patients
      undergoing bimaxillary surgery. The purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of
      continuous administered penehyclidine in preventing PONV in patients undergoing bimaxillary
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 7, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) within 72 hours after bimaxillary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Nausea was assessed by direct questioning. Vomiting was diagnosed when patients retched or expulsed intra-gastric contents.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensity of nausea within 72 hours after bimaxillary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Intensity of nausea is assessed with the numerical rating scale (NRS; an 11-point scale where 0=no nausea and 10=the worst nausea).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of PONV within 72 hours after bimaxillary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Level I: Absence of any emetic symptoms and nausea during the entire study period.
Level II: Occurrence of mild nausea or one episode of vomiting if caused by an exogenous stimulus (e.g., drinking or movement).
Level III: Patient vomits up to 2 times or experiences nausea that required a rescue antiemetic therapy only once.
Level IV: Patient is suffered more than two emetic episodes or necessitating more than one dose of a rescue antiemetic.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of rescue antiemetics within 72 hours after bimaxillary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and dose of antiemetics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of delirium within the first 5 days after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of delirium within the first 5 days after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in hospital after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in hospital after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of complications with 30 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of complications with 30 days after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause 30-day mortality.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause 30-day mortality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive function on the 30th day after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive function is assessed with the modified Telephone Interview for Cognitive Status (TICS-m; a 12-item questionnaire that provides an assessment of global cognitive function by verbal communication via telephone. The score ranges from 0 to 50, with higher score indicating better function).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity within 72 hours after bimaxillary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity is assessed with the numerical rating scale (NRS; an 11-point scale where 0=no pain and 10=the worst pain).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective sleep quality within 3 days after bimaxillary surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>In the morning of the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective sleep quality is assessed with the numeric rating scale (NRS; an 11-point scale where 0=the best sleep and 10=the worst sleep).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">354</enrollment>
  <condition>Penehyclidine</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <condition>Bimaxillar Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For patients in the control group, a dose of placebo (normal saline 5 ml) is injected intravenously before anesthesia induction. A patient-controlled intravenous analgesia pump is provided after surgery, which is established with a mixture of placebo (normal saline 5 ml), sufentanil (1.25-1.5 ug/kg) and tropisetron 10 mg, diluted with normal saline to 100 ml, and programmed to administer a continuous infusion at a rate of 2 ml/h for 48 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single injection group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For patients in this group, a dose of penehyclidine (0.5 mg/5 ml) is injected intravenously before anesthesia induction. A patient-controlled intravenous analgesia pump is provided after surgery, which is established with a mixture of placebo (normal saline 5 ml), sufentanil (1.25-1.5 ug/kg) and tropisetron (10 mg), diluted with normal saline to 100 ml, and programmed to administer a continuous infusion at a rate of 2 ml/h for 48 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous infusion group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For patients in this group, a dose of penehyclidine (0.25 mg/5 ml) is injected intravenously before anesthesia induction. A patient-controlled intravenous analgesia pump is provided after surgery, which is established with a mixture of penehyclidine (0.25 mg/5 ml), sufentanil (1.25-1.5 ug/kg) and tropisetron (10 mg), diluted with normal saline to 100 ml, and programmed to administer a continuous infusion at a rate of 2 ml/h for 48 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Single injection of penehyclidine</intervention_name>
    <description>A dose of penehyclidine hydrochloride (0.5 mg/5 ml) is injected intravenously before anesthesia induction. A patient-controlled intravenous analgesia pump is provided after surgery, which is established with a mixture of placebo (normal saline 5 ml), sufentanil (1.25-1.5 ug/kg) and tropisetron (10 mg), diluted with normal saline to 100 ml, and programmed to administer a continuous infusion at a rate of 2 ml/h for 48 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single injection group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Penehyclidine hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous infusion of penehyclidine</intervention_name>
    <description>A dose of penehyclidine hydrochloride (0.25 mg/5 ml) is injected intravenously before anesthesia induction. A patient-controlled intravenous analgesia pump is provided after surgery, which is established with a mixture of penehyclidine hydrochloride (0.25 mg/5 ml), sufentanil (1.25-1.5 ug/kg) and tropisetron (10 mg), diluted with normal saline to 100 ml, and programmed to administer a continuous infusion at a rate of 2 ml/h for 48 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous infusion group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Penehyclidine hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>A dose of placebo (normal saline 5 ml) is injected intravenously before anesthesia induction. A patient-controlled intravenous analgesia pump is provided after surgery, which is established with a mixture of placebo (normal saline 5 ml), sufentanil (1.25-1.5 ug/kg) and tropisetron (10 mg), diluted with normal saline to 100 ml, and programmed to administer a continuous infusion at a rate of 2 ml/h for 48 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normal saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥18 years but &lt;60 years; body mass index ≥18 but &lt;30 kg/m2;

          2. Scheduled to undergo elective bimaxillary surgery under general anesthesia;

          3. Planned to use patient-controlled intravenous analgesia (PCIA) after surgery;

          4. Provide written informed consents.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of glaucoma;

          2. Allergic to penehyclidine, atropine, scopolamine or other anticholinergic drugs;

          3. Acute or chronic nausea and/or vomiting, or gastrointestinal motility disorders before
             surgery;

          4. Preoperative antiemetic therapy within 12 hours;

          5. History of schizophrenia, Parkinson's disease or profound dementia, or language
             barrier;

          6. Severe hepatic dysfunction (Child-Pugh class C), severe renal dysfunction (requirement
             of renal replacement therapy before surgery) or American Society of Anesthesiologists
             physical status ≥IV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+861083572784</phone>
    <email>wangdongxin@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Li-Kuan Wang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8613488702143</phone>
    <email>wanglikuan3@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking Univeristy Hospital Stomatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100081</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Li-Kuan Wang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86 13488702143</phone>
      <email>wanglikuan3@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myles PS, Williams DL, Hendrata M, Anderson H, Weeks AM. Patient satisfaction after anaesthesia and surgery: results of a prospective survey of 10,811 patients. Br J Anaesth. 2000 Jan;84(1):6-10.</citation>
    <PMID>10740539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naran S, Steinbacher DM, Taylor JA. Current Concepts in Orthognathic Surgery. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2018 Jun;141(6):925e-936e. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0000000000004438. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29794714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laskin DM, Carrico CK, Wood J. Predicting postoperative nausea and vomiting in patients undergoing oral and maxillofacial surgery. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2020 Jan;49(1):22-27. doi: 10.1016/j.ijom.2019.06.016. Epub 2019 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>31230771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips C, Brookes CD, Rich J, Arbon J, Turvey TA. Postoperative nausea and vomiting following orthognathic surgery. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2015 Jun;44(6):745-51. doi: 10.1016/j.ijom.2015.01.006. Epub 2015 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25655765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dobbeleir M, De Coster J, Coucke W, Politis C. Postoperative nausea and vomiting after oral and maxillofacial surgery: a prospective study. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2018 Jun;47(6):721-725. doi: 10.1016/j.ijom.2017.11.018. Epub 2018 Jan 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29301675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaikh SI, Nagarekha D, Hegade G, Marutheesh M. Postoperative nausea and vomiting: A simple yet complex problem. Anesth Essays Res. 2016 Sep-Dec;10(3):388-396. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27746521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Han XY, Liu H, Liu CH, Wu B, Chen LF, Zhong BH, Liu KL. Synthesis of the optical isomers of a new anticholinergic drug, penehyclidine hydrochloride (8018). Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2005 Apr 15;15(8):1979-82.</citation>
    <PMID>15808451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang Z, Zhuang Y, Ouyang F, Zhang A, Zeng B, Gu M. Penehyclidine enhances the efficacy of tropisetron in prevention of PONV following gynecological laparoscopic surgery. J Anesth. 2012 Dec;26(6):864-9. doi: 10.1007/s00540-012-1443-1. Epub 2012 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22878869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dong-Xin Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Chairman, Department of Anaesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Penehyclidine</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</keyword>
  <keyword>Bimaxillar Surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

