<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04457830</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NTP-F520-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04457830</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Efficacy and Safety of F520 in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Peripheral T Cell Lymphoma (PTCL).</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Open-label, Single-arm, Multicenter Study of the Efficacy and Safety of F520 in Relapsed/Refractory Peripheral T Cell Lymphoma (PTCL).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shandong New Time Pharmaceutical Co., LTD</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shandong New Time Pharmaceutical Co., LTD</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is a multi-center, prospective, open-label, two-stage optimized design, single-arm, phase
      II clinical study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of F520 for the treatment of relapsed
      and refractory peripheral T cell lymphoma (PTCL), and to evaluate the immunogenicity of F520.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>F520</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of F520 as defined by objective response rate (evaluated by IRC) in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of F520 as defined by objective response rate (evaluated by investigator) in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Completed response rate (CRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of F520 as defined by completed response rate (evaluated by investigator/IRC) in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the duration of response (DOR) of F520 in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the duration from the first administration to death because of any reason in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of F520 as defined by progression-free survival, in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of F520 as defined by disease control rate, in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response (TTR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of F520 as defined by time to response in patients with relapsed or refractory PTCL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral T Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F520</intervention_name>
    <description>3mg/kg every 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 18 years or older, male or female;

          2. Histologically confirmed relapsed or refractory PTCL patients who had received
             systemic treatment at least once but had failed to; Relapsed / refractory is defined
             as follows:

             Relapsed: patients who have new lesions at the primary site or other sites after
             reaching CR in the previous treatment; Refractory: patients who fail to reach PR in 2
             cycles or CR in 4 cycles after first-line or above systemic treatment; if the best
             effect or end cause is PD, the number of cycles is not required;

          3. ECOG score of 0-2;

          4. Life expectancy≥3 months;

          5. Agree to provide archived tumor tissue samples or fresh tissue samples, including
             enough samples to complete PD-L1 test;

          6. Computed tomography (ct) scans should show the presence of at least one of two
             vertical orientations; The tumor lesions that could be measured were defined, with the
             longest diameter of intranode lesion &gt; 1.5cm, the shortest diameter of intranode
             lesion &gt; 1.0cm and the longest diameter of extranode lesion &gt; 1.0cm;

          7. The functions of important organs meet the following requirements (drugs with any
             blood component and cell growth factor are not allowed to be used within 14 days
             before the first administration):

             routine blood tests: hemoglobin ≥ 90 g/L, neutrophil ≥ 1.5 ×109/L, platelet ≥
             75×109/L; Total bilirubin (TBIL) ≤ 1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN),
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 times the
             upper limit of normal (ULN); If there is liver metastasis, TBIL ≤ 3 × ULN, ALT and AST
             ≤ 5 × ULN; Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5×ULN; Thyroid function indicators:
             thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) are within the normal range or thyroid-stimulating
             hormone (TSH) are not within the normal range and free thyroxine (FT3/FT4) are within
             the normal range;

          8. Sign the written informed consent, and be able to follow the visit and related
             procedures specified in the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosed as vascular immunoblastic t-cell lymphoma (AITL) or adult t-cell
             lymphoma/leukemia(ATLL);

          2. Patients with active central nervous system (CNS) infiltration, including invasion of
             brain parenchyma, meninges or compression of spinal cord;

          3. Diagnosed as cutaneous extranodal nasal type T-cell lymphoma;

          4. Immunohistochemistry confirmed PD-1 positive;

          5. Patients with complicated diseases, including autoimmune disease, type I diabetes,
             hypothyroidism requiring hormone replacement (except Hashimoto's thyroiditis) and
             severe mental disease;

          6. The patients received systemic corticosteroids (prednisone &gt; 10 mg/day or equivalent
             dose) within 2 weeks before the first administration or patients who need systemic
             corticosteroids therapy during the study;

          7. The patients received radiotherapy, chemotherapy, hormone therapy, surgery, targeted
             therapy or systemic treatment of antibody drugs within 4 weeks before the first
             administration; the patients used monoclonal antibody coupled radionuclide or
             cytotoxin therapy within 10 weeks before the first administration; the toxicity of the
             previous anti-tumor treatment did not recover to ≤ level 1 (except hair loss);

          8. Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt; 180mmHg and/or diastolic blood
             pressure &gt; 100mmHg);

          9. Previous history of organ transplantation or allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
             transplantation;

         10. The patients who had autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation within 3
             months before the first administration;

         11. Patients receiving any attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks before the first
             administration or during the study;

         12. Patients who are allergic to macromolecular protein or anti-PD-1 antibody;

         13. Patients who with previous or concurrent malignancies (except skin basal cell
             carcinoma and cervical carcinoma in situ, which have been cured for more than 3
             years);

         14. Had uncontrollable or serious cardiovascular diseases, the heart of New YorkNYHA
             standard grade 3-4 history of chronic heart failure, unstable angina, myocardial
             infarction and other cardiovascular diseases within 6 months before the first
             administration;

         15. HIV positive patients, or active hepatitis (hepatitis B: hepatitis B five items and
             HBV-DNA, transaminase, etc., hepatitis C: HCV antibody and HCV RNA);

         16. Patients who had been previously treated with any other investigational drugs/devices
             within 4 weeks before the first administration;

         17. Patients with drug abuse history or alcohol addiction history within 6 months before
             the first administration;

         18. Patients who were previously treated with anti PD-1 antibody, anti PD-L1 antibody,
             anti PD-L2 antibody, anti-137 or anti CTLA-4 antibody (or any other antibodies acting
             on T cell co-stimulation or checkpoint pathway);

         19. Patients with current or previous interstitial lung diseases (except for interstitial
             lung disease caused by radiotherapy and chemotherapy and currently without symptoms);

         20. Active infections requiring systemic treatment;

         21. Patients with active pulmonary tuberculosis;

         22. pregnant or lactating women, female patients with pregnancy plan or male patients with
             such plan from the study period to 6 months after the last medication, who are
             unwilling to use an effective contraceptive measure (such as IUD or condom) approved
             by medicine during the trial period;

         23. Subjects who are considered unsuitable for participating in this study for various
             reasons at the discretion of the investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell, Peripheral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

