<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04133272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>21611/2014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04133272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Registry of Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</brief_title>
  <acronym>RED</acronym>
  <official_title>Registry of Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome That Collects Clinical, Functional, Genetic, Genealogical, Imaging, Surgical, Quality of Life Data. Data Are Linked to Patients Biological Sample</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Luca Sangiorgi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Ortopedico Rizzoli</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RED is a retrospective and prospective registry, finalized to care and research. It is
      articulated in main sections - strongly related and mutually dependent on each other -
      corresponding to different data domains: personal information, clinical data, genetic data,
      genealogical data, surgeries, etc.

      This approach has been individuated in order to corroborate and integrate data from different
      resources and aspects of the diseases and to correlate genetic background and phenotypic
      outcomes, in order to better investigate diseases pathophysiology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The common way to collect patient information is frequently chaotic and inconvenient
      (sometimes even unsafe), particularly when dealing with rare diseases. The need to simplify
      the diagnostic process and to overcome the difficulties of data storage and analysis,
      suggested in 2013 to implement the Registry of Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome (RED).

      The RED relies on an IT Platform named Genotype-phenotype Data Integration platform
      -GeDI.This solution, realized by a collaboration among Medical Genetic Department and a local
      software-house (NSI - Nier IT Solution), is a General Data Protection Regulation
      (GDPR)-compliant, multi-client, web-accessible system and it has been designed according to
      current medical informatics standards (Orphanet code, ICD-10, Human Genome Variants Society,
      Findability Accessibility Interoperability Reusability Principles). GeDI is continuously
      implemented to improve management of persons with Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome and to help
      researchers in analysing collected information. RED is articulated in main sections:

      Personal data: it comprises general information, birth details and residence data Patient
      data: including the patients internal code, the hospital code and other details on patients
      Diagnosis: the diagnosis, the status (affected, suspect, etc.), age at diagnosis,
      comorbidities, allergies, etc.

      Genogram: a tool to design family transmission of the disease, flanked by info on diseases
      status of all included relatives Clinical events: records 23 signs and symptoms of
      Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome (representing the main Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome features) and 12
      additional items to describe the disease Genetic Analysis and Alteration: including
      technique, sample information, duration of analysis, etc. In addition, this section comprises
      detailed information on detected pathological variants (gene, international reference, DNA
      change, Protein change, genomic position, etc.) Visits: it includes the typology of the visit
      (genetic, orthopaedic, rehabilitation, paediatric, etc.), the date of the visit, treatment,
      prescription, imaging, etc.

      Surgeries: this section contains information on the surgeries type, the age of the patients,
      the site/localization of the procedures, etc.

      Documents: this repository is allowed to store all type of documents (radiological reports,
      imaging, consents, clinical reports, etc.) Consents: this section comprises a complete
      overview of all collected consents, including the date of collection.

      Samples: it comprises the type of samples (DNA, tissue, whole peripheral blood, etc.)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2033</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>15 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Natural History and Epidemiology in terms of clinical, genetic and functional evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>25 years</time_frame>
    <description>To maintain an established registry in order to assess epidemiology and natural history (such as incidence, prevalence, etc.).
Collection of:
physical examinations data: assessment of type of the disease (according to Orphanet types)
orthopaedic and functional data: stature (cm), weight (kg), Beighton score, pain score (numeric scale), presence cardiac lesion (ultrasound)
surgical procedures: type, number and site of surgeries disease-related and age at surgeries
genetics background: target gene, type of mutation, type of variant detected, clinical significance
family history: inheritance in maternal or paternal line
Clinical, orthopaedic and functional features are updated at each follow up. Clinical reports, medical charts and imaging are the primary source of data.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genotype-Phenotype Correlation among clinical features and molecular background</measure>
    <time_frame>25 years</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcome comprises the correlation between genotype and phenotype. This includes, but is not limited to clinical features and genetic background. This will be pursued using the information collected during visits and follow-ups and the genetic information resulting from molecular investigations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal study of disease (including prospective and retrospective data)</measure>
    <time_frame>25 years</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome aims to investigate the Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome trend during time. This will be evaluated within the families and among the families.
Main clinical features, such as height (cm), pain (numeric scale) and other variables will be collected both retrospectively and prospectively. An evaluation of these parameters will be performed at each visit to keep trace on the progression of the clinical manifestations.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>The group comprises all patients affected by Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, including prenatal and fetal diagnosis of Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole peripheral blood, DNA, lymphocytes
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients affected by Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome. The Registry will include also data on
        foetuses (prenatal and abortion)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome patients, including prenatal and fetal diagnosis of
             Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any condition unrelated to Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luca Sangiorgi, MD, PhD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istituto Ortopedico Rizzoli</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Irccs Istituto Ortopedico Rizzoli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <state>Emilia Romagna</state>
        <zip>40136</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ritelli M, Rovati C, Venturini M, Chiarelli N, Cinquina V, Castori M, Colombi M. Application of the 2017 criteria for vascular Ehlers-Danlos syndrome in 50 patients ascertained according to the Villefranche nosology. Clin Genet. 2020 Feb;97(2):287-295. doi: 10.1111/cge.13653. Epub 2019 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>31600821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghali N, Sobey G, Burrows N. Ehlers-Danlos syndromes. BMJ. 2019 Sep 18;366:l4966. doi: 10.1136/bmj.l4966. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31533917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Black CM, Gathercole LJ, Bailey AJ, Beighton P. The Ehlers-Danlos syndrome: an analysis of the structure of the collagen fibres of the skin. Br J Dermatol. 1980 Jan;102(1):85-96.</citation>
    <PMID>7378285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beighton P. Ehlers-Danlos syndrome. Ann Rheum Dis. 1970 May;29(3):332-3.</citation>
    <PMID>5432600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bénistan K, Gillas F. Pain in Ehlers-Danlos syndromes. Joint Bone Spine. 2020 May;87(3):199-201. doi: 10.1016/j.jbspin.2019.09.011. Epub 2019 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>31562935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hausser I. Diagnosis of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome: data deficiency still does not allow establishment of a complete history of the disease and its pathomechanisms. Br J Dermatol. 2020 Mar;182(3):535-536. doi: 10.1111/bjd.18373. Epub 2019 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>31432500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jesudas R, Chaudhury A, Laukaitis CM. An update on the new classification of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome and review of the causes of bleeding in this population. Haemophilia. 2019 Jul;25(4):558-566. doi: 10.1111/hae.13800. Epub 2019 Jun 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31329366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Baets S, Calders P, Verhoost L, Coussens M, Dewandele I, Malfait F, Vanderstraeten G, Van Hove G, Van de Velde D. Patient perspectives on employment participation in the &quot;hypermobile Ehlers-Danlos syndrome&quot;. Disabil Rehabil. 2019 Jul 9:1-10. doi: 10.1080/09638288.2019.1636316. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>31287330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Copetti M, Morlino S, Colombi M, Grammatico P, Fontana A, Castori M. Severity classes in adults with hypermobile Ehlers-Danlos syndrome/hypermobility spectrum disorders: a pilot study of 105 Italian patients. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2019 Oct 1;58(10):1722-1730. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/kez029.</citation>
    <PMID>30783660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mu W, Muriello M, Clemens JL, Wang Y, Smith CH, Tran PT, Rowe PC, Francomano CA, Kline AD, Bodurtha J. Factors affecting quality of life in children and adolescents with hypermobile Ehlers-Danlos syndrome/hypermobility spectrum disorders. Am J Med Genet A. 2019 Apr;179(4):561-569. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.a.61055. Epub 2019 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>30703284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istituto Ortopedico Rizzoli</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Luca Sangiorgi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Haed of Medical Genetic Department and Clinical Bioinformatic Laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Disease Registry</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Genotype-Phenotype Correlation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

