<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04137354</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EC/2019/1289</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04137354</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Iron and Vitamin A in School Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>IronVitA</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Intermittent Iron and Vitamin A Supplementation on Nutritional Status and Development of Schoolchildren in Arba Minch Zuria District, Ethiopia.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Ghent</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Flemish Interuniversity Council (VLIR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Arba Minch University, Ethiopia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Ghent</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The WHO recommended intermittent iron supplementation as a strategy for prevention of anemia
      and iron deficiency among school age children. Several aspects of cognitive development,
      co-supplementation with other micronutrients, severe adverse events especially in the context
      of malaria were missing.

      The investigators will evaluate the effectiveness of intermittent iron and vitamin A
      supplementation on cognitive development and anemia and iron status of Rural Ethiopian school
      children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Iron deficiency is the commonest micronutrient deficiency worldwide and the major cause of
      specific anemia - iron deficiency anemia. Iron is an essential mineral with lots of functions
      in the human body; its deficiency is associated with cognitive impairment, emotional
      alteration, and altered homeostasis in myelination and neurotransmission. Vitamin A
      deficiency can lead to anemia, weakened resistance to infection, blindness, and death. Animal
      model studies showed that vitamin A could affect cognition. Cognitive skills, influenced by
      cognitive development of the individual, are related with academic performance of the student
      and long-term success. One target of the Sustainable Development Goals (SDG 4) is to ensure
      inclusive and equitable quality education and promote lifelong learning opportunities for
      all. Poor health and undernutrition of children in Low- and Middle-Income Countries (LMIC)
      are the major limitations to reach their potential school performance and learning skills.
      The evidence on the role of intermittent iron supplementation in preventing anemia is strong
      but several aspects of cognitive development, co-supplementation with other micronutrients
      such as vitamin A are missing.

      The aim of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of intermittent iron and high-dose
      vitamin A supplementation integrated within school nutritional plan on anemia, iron status
      and cognitive development of school children (7 - 10 year old) who live in areas with high
      rates of food insecurity in Ethiopia.

      Method: The study will be carried out at primary schools in Arba Minch Zuria District,
      Ethiopia in children aged from 7 to 10 years. Eligible children (a total of 504 children)
      will be randomly assigned to one of the four groups: 1) Control placebo receiving placebo
      vitamin A and placebo iron supplement; 2) Vitamin A group will receive a high dose vitamin A
      capsule (200,000 IU) and placebo iron supplement.;3) Iron group will receive weekly iron
      supplementation (42 mg of elemental iron) and placebo vitamin A; and 4)Iron-vitamin A group
      will receive a combined weekly iron supplementation and high dose vitamin A.

      Iron supplements (42mg of elemental iron)/placebo will be given to school chidlren weekly for
      10 months and 200,000 IU of vitamin A/placebo will be given at baseline and after 5 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In randomized placebo-control trial eligible primary school children in the Arba Minch HDSS will be randomly assigned to four groups of treatment in a factorial 2x2 design:
A control placebo receiving placebo vitamin A at baseline and after 5 months, and placebo iron supplement weekly;
A high dose vitamin A at baseline and after 5 months and weekly placebo iron supplement;
Weekly iron supplementation for 10 months and placebo vitamin A at baseline and after 5 months;
Combined weekly iron supplementation and high dose vitamin A at baseline and after 5 months.
At the end of the study, and if the results are positive, children who receive the placebo iron supplement will receive weekly iron supplementation (42mg of elemental iron once a week) for 10 months. Children in all the treatment groups remain eligible to benefit from the standard health care and nutrition programs provided at school, such as deworming at the beginning of the school year</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Iron supplements and their placebo: Both iron and placebo supplements will be produced by Metagenics (Belgium) for the context of this study. Placebo tablets will have the same taste, and shape of the iron tablets, the colour is slightly different because of the characteristics of the products but the blinding is ensured. The blister/ the tablets will be packed and only coded.
Vitamin A and its placebo: Vitamin A capsule is oral liquid, red, oil-based preparation of retinyl palmitate that contains the equivalent of 100,000 IU (110μmol) of vitamin A and stabilized with 20IU of vitamin E. The placebo supplement will have the same oil composition except that it will not contain vitamin A equivalent. Placebo oil and vitamin A preparation will be transferred to two colored (red and orange) Eppendorf® Safe-Lock microcentrifuge tubes volume 0.6 mL by a researcher who is not involved in the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory span</measure>
    <time_frame>Memory span of the children will be assessed at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Digit span (forward and backward) is a standardized test that assess the working memory of the children, one indicator of cognitive development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Spatial exploration and awareness</measure>
    <time_frame>Spatial exploration and awareness of the children will be assessed at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Vision search using cancellation task of the children, the second indicator of cognitive development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reasoning ability</measure>
    <time_frame>The reasoning ability of the children will be assessed at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Raven's colored progressive matrices, the third indicator of cognitive development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Hemoglobin concentrations of children will be assessed at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hemoglobin concentrations (g/dL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma ferritin</measure>
    <time_frame>Plasma ferritin is assessed in all children at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Iron status as indicated plasma ferritin (micro_g/L) is a test to evaluate iron stores</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Soluble transferrin receptor</measure>
    <time_frame>Soluble transferrin receptor is assessed in all children at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Soluble transferrin receptor (mg/L) is an indicator for iron deficiency especially in high inflammation settings</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum concentrations in Vitamin A (retinol)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retinol concentrations will be assessed in all children at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Retinol concentrations in serum is an indicator of vitamin A status of children</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum concentrations in vitamin B12</measure>
    <time_frame>Vitamin B12 concentrations will be assessed in all children at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum concentrations in vitamin B12</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of soil-transmitted helminths</measure>
    <time_frame>The prevalence of soil-transmitted helminths will be assessed at 4.5 months and at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of worm parasites and egg density in the stools. Three common parasites and their eggs will be investigated, i.e. Ascaris lumbricoides (round worm), Trichuris trichiura (whipworm) and Ancyclostoma duodenale or Necater americanus (hookworms).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of Schistosome infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Prevalence of Schistosome infection will be assessed at 4.5 months and at 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of Schistosoma mansoni infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the iron/placebo supplements</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for the whole period of the intervention of 9 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to the tablets of Iron/Placebo will be assessed through teacher's reports. Teachers are the ones who are providing the supplements in a weekly basis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">504</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia, Iron Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Vitamin A Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Development</condition>
  <condition>Helminthic Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Iron&amp;Vitamin A Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children randomly assigned to the placebo iron &amp; vitamin A control group will receive weekly three placebo tablets that are identical to the iron tablets (blinded) for the whole duration of the study (9 months of the school year). They will also receive placebo vitamin A at baseline and at mid-line (after 4.5 months).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin A &amp; Placebo Iron Supplements</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children is this group will receive weekly three placebo tablets that are identical to the iron tablets (blinded) for the whole duration of the study (9 months of the school year). They will also receive a high dose vitamin A capsule (200,000IU) at baseline and after 4.5 months (at mid-line)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent Iron Supplements &amp; Placebo Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children is this group will receive weekly three tablets of iron (42mg of elemental iron once a week) for 9 months (equivalent to a one school year).
They will also receive placebo vitamin A at baseline and at mid-line (after 4.5 months).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent Iron Supplements &amp; High dose Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combined weekly iron supplementation (42mg of elemental iron once a week) for 9 months and high dose vitamin A (200,000IU) at baseline and after 4.5 months (mid-line).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intermittent placebo iron supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo iron supplements are also three tablets containing the same ingredients as for iron tablets and will be given to the children on a weekly basis for the whole duration of the intervention (i.e. the school year of 9 months)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Iron&amp;Vitamin A Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin A &amp; Placebo Iron Supplements</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control iron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intermittent iron supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Three iron tablets containing 42 mg of elemental iron will be provided to the children on a weekly basis for the whole duration of the intervention (i.e. the school year of 9 months)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent Iron Supplements &amp; High dose Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent Iron Supplements &amp; Placebo Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Experimental iron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Vitamin A</intervention_name>
    <description>Children will receive in a colorful Eppendorf tube 400 micro-liter of corn oil stabilized with vitamin A twice during the intervention period of 9 months, at baseline (after enrollment) and at mid-line (4.5 months).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Iron&amp;Vitamin A Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent Iron Supplements &amp; Placebo Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control Vitamin A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-dose Vitamin A supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Children will receive in a colorful Eppendorf tube 400 micro-liter of oil-based preparation of retinyl palmitate that contains the equivalent of 100,000 IU (110μmol) of vitamin A and stabilized with 20IU of vitamin E twice during the intervention period of 9 months, at baseline (after enrollment) and at mid-line (4.5 months).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent Iron Supplements &amp; High dose Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin A &amp; Placebo Iron Supplements</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Experimental Vitamin A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  One or both their parents signed informed consent form;

          -  Their parents planned to stay during the period of the study (for the full academic
             year) in the kebele; and

          -  They accept of the intervention package including blood draw and home visits. School
             children with severe anemia (Hb concentration &lt;80 g/L) will be treated by conventional
             protocol for three months at nearby health centres. After reassessing their
             haemoglobin concentrations, they can be assigned to their intervention groups if they
             become eligible as described above.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronically ill children like diagnosed diabetic and asthma

          -  Severely under nourished children (defined as body mass index z-score &lt;-3 standard
             deviations of the median WHO reference population)

          -  Those who are treated for tuberculosis or suspected to have tuberculosis

          -  Children with diagnosed haemoglobinopathy (sickle cell and thalassemias)

          -  Children with night blindness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stefaan De Henauw, Md. PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Ghent</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Souheila Abbeddou, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00329 3322423</phone>
    <email>Souheila.Abbeddou@UGent.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Befikadu Tariku Gutema, MSc.</last_name>
    <phone>00251912361811</phone>
    <email>befikadutariku.gutema@ugent.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arba Minch University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arba Minch</city>
        <country>Ethiopia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Befikadu Tariku Gutema, MSc.</last_name>
      <phone>00251912361811</phone>
      <email>befikadutariku.gutema@ugent.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eshetu Zerihun, MSc.</last_name>
      <phone>00251917835302</phone>
      <email>eshetamu@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ethiopia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guideline: Intermittent Iron Supplementation in Preschool and School-Age Children. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2011.</citation>
    <PMID>24479203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De-Regil LM, Jefferds ME, Sylvetsky AC, Dowswell T. Intermittent iron supplementation for improving nutrition and development in children under 12 years of age. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011 Dec 7;(12):CD009085. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD009085.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22161444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friis H, Mwaniki D, Omondi B, Muniu E, Magnussen P, Geissler W, Thiong'o F, Michaelsen KF. Serum retinol concentrations and Schistosoma mansoni, intestinal helminths, and malarial parasitemia: a cross-sectional study in Kenyan preschool and primary school children. Am J Clin Nutr. 1997 Sep;66(3):665-71.</citation>
    <PMID>9280190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmermann MB, Biebinger R, Rohner F, Dib A, Zeder C, Hurrell RF, Chaouki N. Vitamin A supplementation in children with poor vitamin A and iron status increases erythropoietin and hemoglobin concentrations without changing total body iron. Am J Clin Nutr. 2006 Sep;84(3):580-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16960172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mwaniki D, Omondi B, Muniu E, Thiong'o F, Ouma J, Magnussen P, Geissler PW, Michaelsen KF, Friis H. Effects on serum retinol of multi-micronutrient supplementation and multi-helminth chemotherapy: a randomised, controlled trial in Kenyan school children. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2002 Jul;56(7):666-73.</citation>
    <PMID>12080408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Ghent</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>VakgroepVolksgezondheidEnEerstelijnszorg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. Stefaan De Henauw</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intermittent Iron supplementation</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin A</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Development</keyword>
  <keyword>Anemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Helminthiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Night Blindness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Iron-Deficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinol palmitate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All the data that can affect the main or the secondary outcomes will be used in the analyses and shared as necessary.
Data on helminthic infection will use characteristics of the attended schools, villages and of the child (date of birth).</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

