<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04130165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB19-0542</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04130165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Matching Donor Human Milk On Maternal Secretor Status (MMOMSS) Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MMOMSS</acronym>
  <official_title>Optimizing the Prebiotic Profile of Donor Human Milk for Preterm Infants: Feasibility of a New Donor Milk Matching Strategy Based on Maternal Secretor Status</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the impact of matching donor human milk to the maternal secretor
      status of very early preterm infants (&lt;32 weeks gestation) on the gut microbiome. Half of
      enrolled infants will receive donor human milk which is matched their mother's secretor
      status and half will receive standard (unmatched) donor human milk, which is standard care in
      the neonatal intensive care unit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: The gut microbiome is established early in life and plays an important role in
      developing the immune system and metabolism. Infants born prematurely (before 37-weeks
      gestation) account for 1 in 10 births worldwide and are especially vulnerable to serious
      microbiome-mediated illnesses such as necrotizing enterocolitis and metabolic diseases.
      Breastfeeding is the most important factor shaping the infant gut microbiome, providing human
      milk oligosaccharides (HMOs) that serve as prebiotics for beneficial gut bacteria. Donor
      human milk (DHM) is considered the best alternative when mothers own milk (MOM) is not
      available. HMO profiles are highly variable between mothers and there is currently no
      &quot;matching&quot; process to optimize pairing of DHM and recipient infants. The strongest factor
      influencing HMO composition is maternal secretor status, determined by the expression of a
      specific gene (α-1, 2-fucosyltransferase-2). About 20% of Caucasians are non-secretors and
      the impact of feeding DHM from secretor donors to infants of non-secretor mothers is unknown.
      The investigators aim to explore if matching DHM based on maternal secretor status impacts
      the development of the gut microbiome in preterm infants.

      Method: The investigators will use a pilot, randomized, controlled trial to compare two
      groups of very preterm infants (&lt;32 weeks gestation): 1) infants receiving DHM matched to
      their mother's secretor status and 2) infants receiving standard issue (i.e. unmatched) DHM.
      Mothers &lt;32 weeks gestation admitted to the antenatal unit at FMC or the antenatal community
      care program will be screened for eligibility. Enrolled mothers will be randomized to either
      the intervention (n=30; matched DHM) or control group (n=30; standard unmatched DHM). Infants
      of mothers assigned to the intervention group will receive &quot;matched&quot; DHM based on maternal
      secretor status, determined after randomization. Infant fecal samples will be collected
      weekly from soiled diapers until infants are transferred to a level II NICU or are no longer
      receiving donor milk. Samples of MOM and DHM will also be collected to analyse milk for HMO
      and nutrient content. Microbial DNA will be analyzed using 16S sequencing. Additionally, for
      a subset of samples selected based on 16S results, researchers will perform shotgun
      metagenomics to identify microbial population structures and functional capacity. Microbial
      composition from intervention (matched DHM), control (unmatched DHM) and reference (exclusive
      MOM) groups will be compared to determine differences in microbial diversity and taxonomy.

      Impact on healthcare: If promising, this intervention will be tested in a much larger cohort
      of preterm infants from NICUs across Canada. Our research could revolutionize how milk banks
      and neonatal intensive care units provide DHM to preterm infants. Finally, this research will
      expand on our understanding of the prebiotic effects of HMOs on infant microbiome and may
      inform future prebiotic/probiotic supplementation regimens.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Pilot Randomized Control Trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcome assessor (lab technician/research assistant) will not be aware of the group allocation or nutritional intake of the infant while completing data analysis.
We cannot blind participants or care providers as provision of matched donor human milk will require preparation which deviates from standard protocol, and the bedside nurse will need to conduct this preparation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal microbiome composition</measure>
    <time_frame>sampled weekly until infant transferred from level III NICU, they are no longer receiving donor human milk or up to 60 days, whichever comes first.</time_frame>
    <description>16S RNA sequencing of fecal bacteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Growth - weight</measure>
    <time_frame>sampled weekly until infant transferred from level III NICU, they are no longer receiving donor human milk or up to 60 days, whichever comes first.</time_frame>
    <description>measured in grams</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Growth - length</measure>
    <time_frame>sampled weekly until infant transferred from level III NICU, they are no longer receiving donor human milk or up to 60 days, whichever comes first.</time_frame>
    <description>measured in centimetres</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Growth - head circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>sampled weekly until infant transferred from level III NICU, they are no longer receiving donor human milk or up to 60 days, whichever comes first.</time_frame>
    <description>measured in centimetres</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Days to full enteral feeds</measure>
    <time_frame>Infant feeds are recorded daily, until infant transferred from level III NICU, they are no longer receiving donor human milk or up to 60 days, whichever comes first.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the number of days it takes from birth until the infant is taking 120 mL/kg/day (full feeds).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured when infant is discharged or transferred from unit, or up to 60 days, whichever comes first.</time_frame>
    <description>Time, measured in days, from admission (birth) to discharge or 'step-down' to level II NICU</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Donor human milk composition - human milk oligosaccharide concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Sampled from milk donations to the milk bank, up to 52 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Individual human milk oligosaccharides concentrations - measured in mol/mL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Donor human milk composition - nutritional composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Sampled from milk donations to the milk bank, up to 52 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Micro-nutrients - measured in kcal/mL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mothers own milk composition - Human milk oligosaccharide concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Sampled from one feeding of infant at 2 weeks post-birth.</time_frame>
    <description>Human milk oligosaccharides concentrations - measured in mol/mL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mothers own milk - nutritional composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Sampled from one feeding of infant at 2 weeks post-birth.</time_frame>
    <description>Micro-nutrients - measured in kcal/mL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Microbial Colonization</condition>
  <condition>Preterm Birth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matched donor human milk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants randomized to the matched donor human milk arm, will receive donor human milk which is matched to their mother's secretor status.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard issue donor human milk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants randomized to the standard issue donor human milk arm, will receive donor human milk which is prepared without consideration of secretor status as per standard practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matched donor human milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Milk from donor mothers will be sorted according to their secretor status. This milk will be provided to infants in the intervention (experimental) arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matched donor human milk</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestation up to 31 6/7 weeks at hospital admission (to guarantee at least 14 days
             intervention, since DHM fortification ends at 34+0 weeks adjusted gestational age).

          -  Provision of consent for infant to receive DHM.

          -  Mother has provided signed and dated informed consent and authorization to use
             protected health information, as required by national and local regulations.

          -  In the investigator's opinion, the subject mother understands and is able to comply
             with protocol requirements, instructions, and protocol-stated restrictions, and is
             likely to complete the study as planned.

        Exclusion Criteria (Infant):

          -  Diagnosed with clinically significant major congenital malformation

          -  Intestinal perforation or stage 2 necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC)

          -  Unlikely to survive the study period

          -  Receiving extended courses of antibiotics (most infants are expected to receive up to
             48hr antibiotic prophylaxis at birth according to standard NICU protocol; this
             criterion will only exclude infants receiving prolonged courses of antibiotics)

          -  Presence prior to enrollment of intestinal perforation or stage 2 necrotizing
             enterocolitis (NEC) prior to tolerating fortified feeds
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meghan B Azad, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Calgary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.azadlab.ca</url>
    <description>Lab Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azad MB, Robertson B, Atakora F, Becker AB, Subbarao P, Moraes TJ, Mandhane PJ, Turvey SE, Lefebvre DL, Sears MR, Bode L. Human Milk Oligosaccharide Concentrations Are Associated with Multiple Fixed and Modifiable Maternal Characteristics, Environmental Factors, and Feeding Practices. J Nutr. 2018 Nov 1;148(11):1733-1742. doi: 10.1093/jn/nxy175.</citation>
    <PMID>30247646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bode L. Human milk oligosaccharides: every baby needs a sugar mama. Glycobiology. 2012 Sep;22(9):1147-62. doi: 10.1093/glycob/cws074. Epub 2012 Apr 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22513036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marx C, Bridge R, Wolf AK, Rich W, Kim JH, Bode L. Human milk oligosaccharide composition differs between donor milk and mother's own milk in the NICU. J Hum Lact. 2014 Feb;30(1):54-61. doi: 10.1177/0890334413513923. Epub 2013 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24282194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parra-Llorca A, Gormaz M, Alcántara C, Cernada M, Nuñez-Ramiro A, Vento M, Collado MC. Preterm Gut Microbiome Depending on Feeding Type: Significance of Donor Human Milk. Front Microbiol. 2018 Jun 27;9:1376. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2018.01376. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29997594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis ZT, Totten SM, Smilowitz JT, Popovic M, Parker E, Lemay DG, Van Tassell ML, Miller MJ, Jin YS, German JB, Lebrilla CB, Mills DA. Maternal fucosyltransferase 2 status affects the gut bifidobacterial communities of breastfed infants. Microbiome. 2015 Apr 10;3:13. doi: 10.1186/s40168-015-0071-z. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25922665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Manitoba</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meghan Azad</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>preterm infants</keyword>
  <keyword>human milk</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>donor human milk</keyword>
  <keyword>breastmilk</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>At this time we plan to share IPD within our research team only. We will consider sharing with other researchers in the future</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

