<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04138147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MD/19.03.162</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04138147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Superficial Cervical Plexus Versus Retrolaminar Block in Parotid Surgeries</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Superficial Cervical Plexus Block Versus Cervical Retrolaminar Block Both Combined With Auriculotemporal Nerve Block in Parotid Surgeries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The parotid gland receives sensory and autonomic innervation. Sensory innervation is supplied
      by the auriculotemporal nerve (gland) and the great auricular nerve (fascia). The
      parasympathetic innervation to the parotid gland begins with the glossopharyngeal nerve. This
      nerve synapses with the otic ganglion. The auriculotemporal nerve then carries
      parasympathetic fibers from the otic ganglion to the parotid gland. Parasympathetic
      stimulation increase saliva production. Sympathetic innervation from the superior cervical
      ganglion, part of the paravertebral chain
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Detailed Description:

      The aim of this study will be comparing efficacy of superficial cervical plexus block with
      cervical retro laminar block both combined with auriculotemporal nerve block in parotid
      surgeries.

      Technique of ultrasound guided auriculotemporal nerve block:

      The patient will be placed in a supine position with each side facing up. The
      temporomandibular joint will be identified after palpitation. A high frequency linear
      ultrasound transducer (7-12 megahertz) will be attached to ultrasound machine (SIEMENS ACUSON
      P300, Germany) will be placed between the tragus and temporomandibular joint. Color Doppler
      imaging will be used to identify the superficial temporal artery. The injection needle will
      be inserted anterior to the tragus posterior to the temporal artery (out-of-plane approach) 1
      to 1.5 cm till reaching the periosteum. The reason of out-of-plane approach is that the
      superficial temporal artery is in the needle entry of in-plane procedure during
      auriculo-temporal nerve block. Following negative aspiration local anesthetic will be
      injected in fractionated doses following intermittent aspiration.

      Technique of ultrasound guided superficial cervical plexus block:

      Standard precautions for the ultrasound guided nerve blocks performance will be done which
      include standard monitoring, the skin overlying the injection site will be free of signs of
      infection and after proper skin sterilization with an antiseptic solution and the probe
      surface in contact with the skin will be covered with a sterile adhesive dressing Patients
      will be in the supine position with the head turned slightly away from the side to be blocked
      to facilitate operator access. The anesthesiologist will be at the patient's side at the
      level of the shoulder. Posterior in-plane approach to the superficial cervical plexus block
      will be done. In this approach, a high-frequency linear transducer (7-12 Megahertz) will be
      attached to ultrasound machine (SIEMENS ACUSON P300), the transducer will be placed in a
      transverse orientation across the neck with the probe marker facing medial (toward the
      thyroid cartilage). A 22-gauge needle will then be inserted at the posterior border of the
      sternocleidomastoid muscle at the level of the cricoid cartilage and advanced underneath the
      muscle belly toward the carotid artery. The needle tip will be positioned to inject local
      anesthetic deep to the sternocleidomastoid muscle along its tapering posterolateral border
      but superficial to the prevertebral fascia. Deeper injection should be avoided because it can
      result in a deep cervical plexus block. As much as 10 ml of local anesthetic will be used for
      this block.

      Technique of ultrasound guided cervical retrolaminar block:

      The patients will be in the lateral position. Patient neck will be slightly flexed forward,
      the anesthesiologist will stand behind the patient. Firstly, landmark will be the
      identification of cervical vertebrae number 7 as it is the largest and most prominent spinous
      process by palpation in axial plane. Then the high-frequency linear transducer (7-12
      Megahertz) which attach to ultrasound machine (SIEMENS ACUSON P300), Ultrasound scanning will
      be performed while the probe in transverse position in the mid sagittal plane of cervical
      vertebrae number 7 spinous process. Then counting up the spinous processes till reaching the
      spinous process of cervical vertebrae number 4 and then the probe will be moved laterally 1
      cm to image the left or right muscles. Identification of the echogenic (bright, reflective)
      laminae will be seen, above it muscles will be imaged. The splenius capitis lies deep to the
      trapezius and is a broad, flat muscle. The semispinalis capitis will be easily recognized as
      a long, strap-like muscle divided into 2 sections by an aponeurotic intersection. The deep
      neck muscle group has a distinctive tear drop shape (semispinalis cervicis, multifidus, and
      rotatores).

      An in-plane approach by using a 22 gauge, 50 mm, echogenic needle. The needle will be
      introduced to reach the lamina. After negative aspiration the local anesthetic will be
      injected through the needle under real-time ultrasound visualization. The criteria for
      assessment of correct spread of the injectate will creating a plane/hypo-echoic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The time of first analgesic request post-operative.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours postoperative.</time_frame>
    <description>The time of first analgesic request in hours.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total post-operative opioid requirement.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours postoperative.</time_frame>
    <description>Total post-operative morphine requirement in milligrams..</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients required rescue post-operative opioid analgesia..</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours postoperative.</time_frame>
    <description>in number.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative pain scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours postoperative.</time_frame>
    <description>by Visual analogue scale (VAS): (where 0 means no pain- while 100 mm is the worst pain) at 0, 1, 2, 6, 12 and 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-operative fentanyl consumption.</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative (2 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>in micro grams.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate (HR).</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative (2 hours), postoperative for 24 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>in beat/minutes, recorded basal, intraoperative: after the block 15 min and 30 min then every 30 minutes till the end of surgery, then postoperative at 0, 1, 2, 6, 12 and 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean arterial blood pressure (MAP).</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative (2 hours), postoperative for 24 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Non invasive mean arterial pressure, in mmHg, recorded intraoperative: basal, after the block at 15 min and 30 min then every 30 minutes till the end of surgery, then postoperative at 0, 1, 2, 6, 12 and 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-operative atracurium consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative (2 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>in milligrams.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The concentration of isoflurane.</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative (2 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>in percent, recorded after the block every 30 minutes till the end of surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensory block assessment.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour post-operative.</time_frame>
    <description>Define the number of blocked dermatomes at post anesthesia care unit by skin pinprick. sensation at dermatomal distribution.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The block procedural duration.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>In minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative complication rate (nausea, vomiting and headache)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours postoperative.</time_frame>
    <description>In number.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of diaphragmatic dysfunction.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour postoperative.</time_frame>
    <description>Using ultrasound assessment,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Supportive Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Superficial cervical plexus with auriculotemporal nerve blocks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cervical retrolaminar with auriculotemporal nerve blocks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Superficial cervical plexus with auriculotemporal nerve blocks</intervention_name>
    <description>Superficial cervical plexus block using 10 ml bupivacaine 0.5%. Auriculotemporal nerve block using 3 ml bupivacaine 0.5%.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Superficial cervical plexus with auriculotemporal nerve blocks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cervical retrolaminar with auriculotemporal nerve blocks</intervention_name>
    <description>Cervical retrolaminar block using 10 ml bupivacaine 0.5%. Auriculotemporal nerve block using 3 ml bupivacaine 0.5%.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cervical retrolaminar with auriculotemporal nerve blocks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status grade I and grade II.

          -  Elective parotid surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusal.

          -  Coagulopathy.

          -  Psychiatric diseases.

          -  Local skin infection and sepsis at site of the block.

          -  Known intolerance to the study drugs.

          -  Body Mass Index &gt; 40 Kg/m2.

          -  Central or peripheral neurological disease.

          -  Previous neck surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alaa M Mazy</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Oncology Center, Mansoura University, Egypt.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ghada S Mohammed, Master</last_name>
    <phone>00201090085600</phone>
    <email>dr_adamghada@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alaa M Mazy, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+201140065052</phone>
    <email>alaa_mazy@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oncology Center, Mansoura University (OCMU)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansoura</city>
        <state>Dakahlia</state>
        <zip>35516</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alaa Mazy, MD</last_name>
      <phone>01140065052</phone>
      <email>alaa_mazy@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ghada M Mohammed, Master</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nahla S El-Ebahnasawy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alaa M Mazy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tarek A Ibrahim, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cervical plexus,</keyword>
  <keyword>Retrolaminar,</keyword>
  <keyword>Auriculotemporal,</keyword>
  <keyword>Parotid</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>after publication.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>2 years.</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

