<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04134910</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B3118-W</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04134910</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Role of Disc Nutrition in the Etiology and Clinical Treatment of Disc Degeneration</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Disc Nutrition in the Etiology and Clinical Treatment of Disc Degeneration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to examine the effects of physical therapy on the
      spinal discs. Back pain is the number one cause of disability in the US, and the spine is the
      most common location of chronic pain in Veterans. Physical therapy is often very effective at
      improving patients' back pain, but it does not work for everyone, and it is not understood
      how physical therapy alters the tissues within the spine. With this research the
      investigators hope to learn if the investigative team can measure changes to the spinal discs
      on MRI scans that might predict if a patient's back pain will improve with physical therapy
      or not.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Low back pain, which is frequently associated with intervertebral disc degeneration, is the
      most common cause of adult disability in the United States. Among active service members, the
      incidence of disc degeneration more than doubled from 2001 to 2010, with over 68,000 days of
      lost duty time attributed to disc degeneration.2 The most common location of chronic pain in
      Veterans is the spine. The incidence of back pain in the general public has remained
      relatively stable over the past decade, however, there has been more than a 50% increase in
      the number of Veterans diagnosed with back pain. The intervertebral discs are the largest
      avascular structures in the body, and therefore cells within the disc rely on transport from
      the small vessels in the adjacent vertebral endplate to receive nutrients and expel waste
      products. Despite the immense social and economic burden of back pain, the etiology of disc
      degeneration remains poorly understood. Because of the avascular nature of the disc, it has
      been speculated that poor disc nutrition characterized by reduced trans-endplate transport
      into the disc could contribute to the initiation and progression of degeneration. If a
      reduction in trans-endplate transport of nutrients and waste products is a primary
      contributor to the initiation and progression of the degenerative cascade, then enhancing
      disc nutrition may have a therapeutic effect. Physical therapy and exercise can be very
      effective in managing back pain for certain patients, yet it is not fully understood why
      certain patients respond to physical therapy and others do not, and what effects such
      interventions have on disc nutrition and disc health. The goal of this study is to undertake
      a pilot study to determine the feasibility and preliminary outcomes of utilizing quantitative
      MRI in human patients to quantify changes in disc health and trans-endplate transport over
      the course of physical therapy.

      To do so, patients with low back pain and concomitant disc degeneration, who have not had
      prior spinal surgery, will be recruited. Recruited patients will undergo MRI T2-mapping and
      post-contrast enhanced T1-mapping of their lumbar spines at 1.5T to measure disc health and
      nutrition, respectively. Patients will then begin a 6 week physical therapy treatment
      regimen, after which the same MRI scans will be performed again on each patient. Pain and
      disability level of patients will be assessed via the visual analog scale (VAS) and Oswestry
      Disability Index (ODI) questionnaires, both pre- and post-treatment. Lumbar active range of
      motion will also be quantified at the initial and final in-office physical therapy session.
      Inclinometers will be placed at the thoracolumbar junction and sacrum, and the patient asked
      to bend forward and backward. Lumbar flexion will be quantified as the difference in motion
      between the two inclinometers.

      Significant differences T1 and T2 values in the disc, as well as VAS and ODI scores and
      lumbar range of motion, before and after physical therapy will be assessed via a paired
      t-test, with significance defined as p&lt;0.05. Univariate linear correlations between the
      changes in T1 or T2 values and changes in VAS, ODI scores and lumbar range of motion will be
      performed to determine if altered disc health or nutrition with physical therapy is
      significantly correlated with improvements in pain and disability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 3, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 3, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Disc T2 relaxation time</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will undergo MRI scanning to obtain T2-maps of the lumbar spine before and after 6 weeks of physical therapy. T2 relaxation times of the disc tissues are calculated from the images.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Visual Analog Scale (VAS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will complete a visual analog scale (VAS) for their back pain before and after 6 weeks of physical therapy. This is a scale from 0 (no pain) to 15 (the worst imaginable pain).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Lumbar Range of Motion</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lumbar range of motion will be measured using inclinometers placed on the subject's upper and lower back, at both the index and final in-office physical therapy visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Disc T1 relaxation time</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will undergo MRI scanning to obtain post-contrast enhanced T1 maps of the lumbar spine before and after 6 weeks of physical therapy. To obtain the T1 maps, an intravenous catheter will be placed, and 0.1 mmols/kg of Omniscan will be administered. T1 MRIs will be acquired prior to and 2 hours following Omniscan administration. T1 relaxation times of the disc tissues are calculated from the images.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Oswestry Disability Index (ODI) score</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will complete the ODI questionnaire before and after 6 weeks of physical therapy. This is a scale from 0 (no disability) to 50 (bed bound).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Intervertebral Disc Degeneration</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be prescribed a 6-week physical therapy regimen consisting of one 45 minute in office visit per week, and home exercises performed daily. The in-office visits with a physical therapy provider will consist of the application of manual therapy, particularly high-velocity, low amplitude thrust mobilization in the anterior/posterior direction of the lumbar spine. In office visits will also include supervised repeated motion of the lumbar spine into extension (McKenzie therapy, 3 sets of 10 repetitions, in prone and standing positions) Patients will be instructed to complete these repeated extension exercises at home daily for the 6 week period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be prescribed a 6-week physical therapy regimen consisting of one 45 minute in office visit per week, and home exercises performed daily. The in-office visits with a physical therapy provider will consist of the application of manual therapy, particularly high-velocity, low amplitude thrust mobilization in the anterior/posterior direction of the lumbar spine. In office visits will also include supervised repeated motion of the lumbar spine into extension (McKenzie therapy, 3 sets of 10 repetitions, in prone and standing positions) Patients will be instructed to complete these repeated extension exercises at home daily for the 6 week period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current activity limiting low back pain

          -  With symptoms of any duration

          -  With or without symptoms extending distal to the buttocks

          -  Medically stable

          -  Candidate for physical therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented history of prior spinal surgery

          -  Contraindications to MRI including:

               -  claustrophobia

               -  pregnancy

               -  implanted electronic devices

                    -  pacemakers, cochlear implant, insulin pumps, etc

               -  metallic foreign bodies

                    -  i.e. shrapnel

               -  documented history of contraindications to gadodiamide (Omniscan) administration:

                    -  chronic severe kidney disease

                    -  acute kidney injury

                    -  impaired elimination of gadolinium based contrast agents

                    -  pre-existing renal insufficiency

                    -  a prior hypersensitivity reaction to MRI contrast
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah E. Gullbrand, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Corporal Michael J. Crescenz VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah E Gullbrand, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(215) 823-5800</phone>
    <email>sgullb@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Corporal Michael J. Crescenz VA Medical Center, Philadelphia, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah E Gullbrand, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-823-5800</phone>
      <email>sgullb@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah E. Gullbrand, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>spine</keyword>
  <keyword>intervertebral disc</keyword>
  <keyword>physical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intervertebral Disc Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

