<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04130893</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-36 AURIX</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04130893</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Response of the Autonomic Nervous System to Auricular Stimulation of the Vagus Nerve (x)</brief_title>
  <acronym>AURIX</acronym>
  <official_title>Response of the Autonomic Nervous System to Auricular Stimulation of the Vagus Nerve (x)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hôpital Européen Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aix Marseille Université</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hôpital Européen Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      While invasive vagal stimulation has proven its therapeutic effectiveness over the past 20
      years, particularly in the treatment of epilepsy or depression, its implementation is
      hampered by the high cost, high technicality and sometimes significant side effects.
      Non-invasive vagal stimulation, most often electric, is a less expensive therapeutic
      alternative and easier to implement, although the level of evidence is lower than that of
      invasive stimulation.

      Some so-called traditional therapies, such as acupuncture, also stimulate certain parts of
      the ear by mechanical means, most often by puncturing the ear or the concha. In these
      traditional therapies, more than one hundred stimulation points have been described, each
      precisely positioned according to an empirical topography.

      However, electrical non-invasive stimulation recognizes only three areas of interest on the
      ear, which are the areas of sensitive innervation, namely the afferences of the vagus nerve
      in the concha, which is the only one used in practice, the large occipital nerve on the lobe
      and part of the helix, and the auriculotemporal nerve on the rest of the auricular flag.

      In this study, we would like to explore the justification for the topographic precision,
      adopted by traditional therapies, for non-invasive vagal stimulation on the concha.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Main objective: to measure the physiological impact of two auricular stimuli on the same
      innervation territory but with opposite actions according to traditional therapies.

      An identical physiological response on both stimulation points would be an argument against
      the topographical precision adopted by traditional therapies; conversely, a different
      physiological response would suggest the existence of a somatotopy nestled in the same
      innervation territory.

      Secondary objectives:

        -  Determine, by sinus variability analysis, the intensity of the sympathetic and
           parasympathetic cardiac response of mechanical stimulation of the ear concha.

        -  Determine the existence of a blockage of the sympathetic reaction on cutaneous
           vasoconstriction after mechanical stimulation of the ear concha.

        -  Measure the relationship between sinus variability and paradoxical skin vasodilation
           after exposure to cold, as considered in the protocol.

      To explore the justification for the topographical precision adopted by traditional
      therapies, we designed an experiment that consists of studying the autonomous, sympathetic
      and parasympathetic response to two stimuli performed over two different times.

      The sympathetic stimulation will be done by immersing the right hand up to the wrist in a tub
      of cold water maintained at 5°C Mechanical parasympathetic stimulation will be performed on
      the ear in two different locations, by placing an adapted needle through an introducer to
      respect a standardized insertion depth.

      The autonomous response will be measured by sinus variability, which responds to a double
      innervation, sympathetic and parasympathetic, and by the capillary skin response, which
      responds only to a sympathetic innervation.

      The capillary skin response is measured by the amplitude and latency of the paradoxical
      vasodilation reflex following thermal stimulation, in this case the immersion of a limb's tip
      in cold water.

      The study will consist of 3 sessions, as shown in the figure below. This is a prospective
      crossover study.

      During the first session, the inclusion and non-inclusion criteria will be checked, then a
      water immersion test will be carried out to ensure the good tolerance of this test and then
      determine the basic values.

      In the absence of acclimatization, the paradoxical vasodilation reflex is highly
      reproducible. During the second and third sessions, a mechanical stimulation will be done to
      the ear during the skin immersion test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 20, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 18, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study will consist of 3 sessions, It is a prospective crossover study. During the first session, the inclusion and non-inclusion criteria will be checked, then the cold water hand immersion test will be carried out to ensure the good tolerance of this test and then determine the basic values.
During the second and third sessions, Two different auricular stimuli will be done to the ear during the hand immersion test.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin temperature changes</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>measured by thermocouples placed on the following fingers: thumb, middle finger and ear of the right hand. The values and times of the minimum and maximum temperatures (latency and amplitude of (CIVD) Cold-Induced VasoDilatation waves) are measured</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain reported by the participant</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by visual analogue scale; this scale ranges from 0 to 10; 0 being no pain, 10 being excruciating pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sinus variability</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>measured by cardiofrequency meter(ACTIWAVE ®)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Vasoconstriction Disorder of Extremities</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A stimulation of G13 then G15</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The first session is similar between the two arms: Cold water hand immersion only At the Second session: Cold water hand immersion + G13 auricular stimulation At the Third session: Cold water hand immersion + G15 auricular stimulation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B: stimulation of G15 then G13</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The first session is similar between the two arms: Cold water hand immersion only At the Second session: Cold water hand immersion + G15 auricular stimulation At the Third session: Cold water hand immersion + G13 auricular stimulation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stimulation of G13 then G15</intervention_name>
    <description>Study participant randomized into arm A will undergo a stimulation of point G13 at session N°2, then stimulation of point G15 at session N°3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A stimulation of G13 then G15</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stimulation of G15 then G13</intervention_name>
    <description>Study participant randomized into arm B will undergo a stimulation of point G15 at session N°2, then stimulation of point G13 at session N°3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B: stimulation of G15 then G13</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy volunteers, male and female, aged 18 to 60 years

          -  BMI (Body mass index) &lt;=30

          -  Not participating in another clinical study with an investigational product

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Drug treatment for cardiological, neurological or anticoagulant purposes

          -  History of diabetes, known neuropathy, high blood pressure, heart rhythm disorders,
             syncope or palpitation

          -  Known cryoglobulinemia

          -  Subject with Raynaud's syndrome

          -  Intra-auricular device of the piercing type,

          -  Psychoactive substance use, excessive alcohol consumption (&gt;2 units per day
             chronically or &gt;6 units per day recreationally) and tobacco (&gt;5 cigarettes per day)

          -  Subject unable to read French

          -  Subject covered by Articles L1121-5 to 1121-8 of the Public Health Code, namely:

          -  Pregnant, postpartum and breastfeeding women

          -  Persons deprived of their liberty by a judicial or administrative decision

          -  Persons undergoing psychiatric care under Articles L3112-1 and L3113-1 who are not
             covered by the provisions of Article L1121-8

          -  Minors

          -  Persons of full age who are subject to a legal protection measure or who are unable to
             express their consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emmanuel SAGUI, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpital Européen Marseille</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emmanuel SAGUI, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0671286865</phone>
    <email>dr.emmanuel.sagui@gmx.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wahiba BIDAUT, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>0685098699</phone>
    <email>wahibag@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Européen Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <state>Paca</state>
        <zip>13003</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ghania HARZI, CRA</last_name>
      <phone>(33)4 13 42 77 82</phone>
      <email>g.harzi@hopital-europeen.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emmanuel SAGUI, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laurent GRELOT, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ear acupuncture, auricular acupuncture</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

