<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04130724</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RO-0001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04130724</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterization of a Portable Solid-State Breath Acetone Testing Device for Real-Time Ketosis Status</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterization of a Portable Solid-State Breath Acetone Testing Device for Real-Time Ketosis Status and Comparison to Blood Ketone Testing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Readout, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Readout, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to characterize the performance and utility of a novel
      breath acetone meter developed by Readout, Inc.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between breath acetone (BrAce) and blood beta-hydroxybutyrate (BHB) concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood BHB and BrAce measurements will be taken simultaneously during at least five (5) measurement sessions each day. After aggregating data from all study participants, the correlation between these two measurements will be determined using regression analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reliability of the Readout breath acetone device</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Multiple BrAce measurements will be taken during each measurement session using the Readout BrAce device and repeatability will be analyzed using alpha reliability coefficients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Utility of a single ketone measurement compared to multiple measurements throughout the day</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The utility of a single BrAce measurement compared to multiple measurements throughout the day will be assessed by comparing a single measurement for a given user with the time-weighted average of all measurements taken that same day. The probability that a single measurement differs from the time-weighted average of all measurements during the same day will be computed for various difference thresholds.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time dynamics of breath acetone compared to blood beta-hydroxybutyrate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The time dynamics of blood BHB versus BrAce will be explored by performing a correlation calculation between the two measurement methods for various time shifts.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Full-day ketone exposure as measured by breath acetone and blood beta-hydroxybutyrate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The full-day ketone exposure as measured by BrAce will be compared with the full-day ketone exposure as measured by blood BHB (12 AM on day 1 to 12 AM on day 2) by first performing linear interpolation between data points on a given day and then calculating the daily area under the curve (AUC) for BrAce and blood BHB. The correlation between blood and breath AUC will be determined by performing regression analysis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Ketogenic Dieting</condition>
  <condition>Ketosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketogenic diet</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects consuming either a ketogenic (&lt;30g carbohydrate per day) or a low-carb (&lt;100g carbohydrate per day) diet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-carbohydrate diet</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects consuming a high carbohydrate (&gt;100g carbohydrate per day) diet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood ketone testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketone testing will be done using a blood beta-hydroxybutyrate (BHB) test at least five (5) times per day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-carbohydrate diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ketogenic diet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blood ketone testing using the Abbott Precision Xtra meter.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Breath ketone testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketone testing will be done using a breath acetone (BrAce) test at least five (5) times per day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-carbohydrate diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ketogenic diet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Breath ketone testing using the Readout breath acetone device.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals who are interested in the ketogenic diet or in tracking their ketones.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ketogenic diet cohort: currently following a ketogenic or low-carbohydrate diet
             defined as less than 30 grams per day (ketogenic) or less than 100 grams per day
             (low-carbohydrate) as estimated by the individual. Subjects must have been following
             the diet before the beginning of the study period and must continue with the diet
             throughout the duration of the trial.

          -  High-carbohydrate diet cohort: currently following a diet that does not restrict
             dietary carbohydrate. Carbohydrate consumption should be greater than 100 grams per
             day as estimated by the individual. Subjects must have been following the diet before
             the study period and must continue with the diet throughout the duration of the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type-1 diabetes

          -  Insulin-dependent type-2 diabetes

          -  History of diabetic ketoacidosis

          -  Currently taking Warfarin or other blood thinners

          -  Currently taking a sodium-glucose cotransporter-2 (SGLT2) inhibitor

          -  Currently taking Disulfiram

          -  Unwilling to maintain their diet during the study period

          -  Unwilling to test blood and breath ketones five times per day

          -  Non-English speaking

          -  Persons who are unable or unwilling to follow the study protocol or who, for any
             reason, the research team considers not an appropriate candidate for this study,
             including non-compliance with screening appointments or study visits.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James McCarter, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Readout, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Emerging Technologies</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallberg SJ, McKenzie AL, Williams PT, Bhanpuri NH, Peters AL, Campbell WW, Hazbun TL, Volk BM, McCarter JP, Phinney SD, Volek JS. Effectiveness and Safety of a Novel Care Model for the Management of Type 2 Diabetes at 1 Year: An Open-Label, Non-Randomized, Controlled Study. Diabetes Ther. 2018 Apr;9(2):583-612. doi: 10.1007/s13300-018-0373-9. Epub 2018 Feb 7. Erratum in: Diabetes Ther. 2018 Mar 5;:.</citation>
    <PMID>29417495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhanpuri NH, Hallberg SJ, Williams PT, McKenzie AL, Ballard KD, Campbell WW, McCarter JP, Phinney SD, Volek JS. Cardiovascular disease risk factor responses to a type 2 diabetes care model including nutritional ketosis induced by sustained carbohydrate restriction at 1 year: an open label, non-randomized, controlled study. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2018 May 1;17(1):56. doi: 10.1186/s12933-018-0698-8.</citation>
    <PMID>29712560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evert AB, Dennison M, Gardner CD, Garvey WT, Lau KHK, MacLeod J, Mitri J, Pereira RF, Rawlings K, Robinson S, Saslow L, Uelmen S, Urbanski PB, Yancy WS Jr. Nutrition Therapy for Adults With Diabetes or Prediabetes: A Consensus Report. Diabetes Care. 2019 May;42(5):731-754. doi: 10.2337/dci19-0014. Epub 2019 Apr 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31000505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knowler WC, Barrett-Connor E, Fowler SE, Hamman RF, Lachin JM, Walker EA, Nathan DM; Diabetes Prevention Program Research Group. Reduction in the incidence of type 2 diabetes with lifestyle intervention or metformin. N Engl J Med. 2002 Feb 7;346(6):393-403.</citation>
    <PMID>11832527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Gaal L, Scheen A. Weight management in type 2 diabetes: current and emerging approaches to treatment. Diabetes Care. 2015 Jun;38(6):1161-72. doi: 10.2337/dc14-1630. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25998297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boden G, Sargrad K, Homko C, Mozzoli M, Stein TP. Effect of a low-carbohydrate diet on appetite, blood glucose levels, and insulin resistance in obese patients with type 2 diabetes. Ann Intern Med. 2005 Mar 15;142(6):403-11.</citation>
    <PMID>15767618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shimazu T, Hirschey MD, Newman J, He W, Shirakawa K, Le Moan N, Grueter CA, Lim H, Saunders LR, Stevens RD, Newgard CB, Farese RV Jr, de Cabo R, Ulrich S, Akassoglou K, Verdin E. Suppression of oxidative stress by β-hydroxybutyrate, an endogenous histone deacetylase inhibitor. Science. 2013 Jan 11;339(6116):211-4. doi: 10.1126/science.1227166. Epub 2012 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23223453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson JC. Measuring breath acetone for monitoring fat loss: Review. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2015 Dec;23(12):2327-34. doi: 10.1002/oby.21242. Epub 2015 Nov 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26524104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Musa-Veloso K, Likhodii SS, Cunnane SC. Breath acetone is a reliable indicator of ketosis in adults consuming ketogenic meals. Am J Clin Nutr. 2002 Jul;76(1):65-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12081817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

