<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04139460</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>University Hospital Olomouc</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04139460</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CRT-P or CRT-D in Dilated Cardiomyopathy</brief_title>
  <acronym>CRT-REALITY</acronym>
  <official_title>CRT-P or CRT-D in Patients With Dilated Cardiomyopathy and Heart Failure Without LGE-CMR High-risk Markers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Olomouc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Olomouc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The ICD-Reality study is a non-commercial, investigator-led, multicenter, prospective,
      randomized, controlled trial. We aim to determine the effect of CRT-D or CRT-P implantation
      in non-ischemic cardiomyopathy and heart failure patients.

      The reason why we initiated this trial is the lack of evidence-based treatment for the
      significant number of these patients. In these patients, 5-year mortality remains as high as
      20% despite recent therapeutic advances. Based on currently available evidence, because of a
      significant decrease in mortality due to modern pharmacotherapy, it is not certain which of
      these patients should receive a CRT-P and who should receive a CRT-D. No dedicated and
      adequately powered trial has addressed this important question.

      We hypothesize that patients with symptomatic HF, LVEF ≤35%, without left ventricular
      mid-wall fibrosis on LGE-CMR, will not benefit from CRT-D implantation compared with CRT-P
      only implantation.

      If our hypothesis is confirmed, this could provide evidence for the management of these
      patients with a significant impact on common daily praxis and health care expenditures.

      We aim to enroll 600 patients in the trial. 924 patients are needed to be screened for these
      600 patients to be randomized.

      Patients with non-ischemic HF visiting an out-patient department and possibly eligible for
      the trial will have their pharmacotherapy optimized.

      Patients with a significant amount of fibrosis will be excluded from the study and treated
      according to local practice with an emphasis on ICD implantation to prevent SCD.

      After fulfilling all eligibility criteria, including maximally tolerated pharmacotherapy,
      subjects will be randomized by the physicians who enrolled them in a 1:1 ratio to receive
      CRT-D or CRT-P implantation.

      All patients will be followed-up for at least 3 years after the implantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial goals The ICD-Reality study is an investigator-led, multicenter, prospective,
      randomized, controlled trial. We aim to determine the effect of CRT-D or CRT-P implantation
      in non-ischemic cardiomyopathy and heart failure patients. The reason why we initiated this
      trial is the lack of evidence-based treatment for the significant number of these patients.
      In these patients, 5-year mortality remains as high as 20% despite recent therapeutic
      advances. Based on currently available evidence, because of a significant decrease in
      mortality due to modern pharmacotherapy, it is not certain which of these patients should
      receive an ICD. We hypothesize that patients with symptomatic HF, LVEF ≤35%, without left
      ventricular mid-wall fibrosis on LGE-CMR, will not benefit from CRT-D implantation compared
      with CRT-P only implantation. If our hypothesis is confirmed, this could provide evidence for
      the management of these patients with a significant impact on common daily praxis and health
      care expenditures.

      Clinical hypothesis:

      Patients with symptomatic HF, with LVEF ≤35% and without LV mid-wall fibrosis on late
      gadolinium enhancement cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging (CMR), will not benefit from
      CRT-D implantation compared with CRT-P only implantation.

      Estimated number of patients needed to be screened and randomized:

      600 patients are needed to be randomized according to the study power analysis. Since 35 % of
      patients are estimated to be LG-E positive and thus excluded from randomization, 924 patients
      are needed to be screened.

      Pre-screening:

      Patients with non-ischemic HF visiting an out-patient department and possibly eligible for
      the trial will have their pharmacotherapy optimized. A screening visit in an out-patient
      department will be scheduled in 1-2 months after pharmacotherapy optimization since the
      qualifying LVEF and NT-proBNP level has to be measured after a maximal tolerated
      pharmacotherapy of heart failure has been achieved.

      Screening:

      After the signing of informed consent, screening examination will be performed. The informed
      consent will be obtained by attending physician in every center and a signed original will be
      stored in each individual center for the whole duration of the study. The screening
      examination will include medical history, documentation of underlying cardiac disease. The
      following co-morbidities will be specifically documented: peripheral arterial disease,
      cerebral vascular disease, pulmonary disease, diabetes mellitus, hypertension, sleep apnea,
      tobacco use, and any malignant disease within the last 5 years. Physical exam with vital
      signs, NYHA functional class, pulse rate, resting blood pressure will be performed.
      Cardiovascular pharmacological treatment will be documented. Standard laboratory parameters
      are recorded, including creatinine, estimated glomerular filtration rate, liver tests, TSH,
      NT-proBNP. Transthoracic echocardiography will be done to confirm LVEF ≤35% using biplane
      Simpson's method. Documented will be LV end-systolic and end-diastolic diameters and volumes,
      thickness of ventricular septum and LV posterior wall, stroke volume, cardiac output, indexed
      left atrial volume, presence and grade of valvular heart disease, right ventricle diameter,
      TAPSE, presence and grade of pulmonary hypertension. Selective coronarography will be
      performed if it was not done before to exclude patients with a severe coronary heart disease.
      LGE-CMR imaging will be performed by an operator blinded to all other clinical data to
      evaluate left ventricular mid-wall fibrosis.

      Patients with a significant amount of fibrosis will be excluded from the study and treated
      according to local practice with an emphasis on ICD implantation to prevent SCD.

      Randomization:

      After fulfilling all eligibility criteria, including maximally tolerated pharmacotherapy,
      subjects will be randomized by the physicians who enrolled them in a 1:1 ratio to receive
      CRT-D or CRT-P implantation. Randomization will be carried out by physicians enrolling
      patients through a stand-alone web-based CRF managed by an independent biomedicine and
      statistics center, independent on all randomizing personnel. The web-CRF-based allocation
      sequence will be based on computer-generated random numbers and will be concealed until the
      type of intervention is assigned.

      Treatment:

      After randomization, devices will be implanted as soon as possible (within 2 weeks). The ICD
      will be programmed with anti-tachycardia pacing and shock therapy as per common praxis.

      Follow-up:

      All patients will be followed-up for at least 3 years after the implantation. After the
      implantation, all patients will be examined every 6 months in an out-patient department with
      the assessment of medical history, vital signs, physical exam, and NT-proBNP as in the
      screening visit. A device control will be performed every 6 months.

      After device implantation the concomitant care and all possible concomitant interventions
      will be carried out as per common praxis.

      Patients will be evaluated for possible end-points. Deaths and hospitalizations for heart
      failure, stroke or arrhythmias will be recorded throughout the study duration.

      Quality of life (QoL) is assessed at baseline and annually during follow-up. Patients will
      fill out the SF-36 Questionnaire for general QoL, the MacNew Questionnaire for disease
      specific QoL.

      An Endpoint Classification Committee will adjudicate hospitalizations and deaths for
      causality. An independent Data Monitoring Committee will periodically review mortality data
      throughout the study.

      For safety reasons, all patients will be followed using a daily ECG monitoring and analysis.
      ECG from the Home-monitoring units will be evaluated in a dedicated center. This center will
      evaluate the ECGs sent from the Home-monitoring units with respect to patient safety and the
      study end-points. If the Home-monitoring unit reveals any rhythm disturbance they will
      contact the patient's physician and make a record in the CRF. If a sustained ventricular
      tachyarrhythmia is documented on a Home-monitoring in a CRT-P patient, a decision will be
      made and documented about a possible crossover to CRT-D as soon as possible.

      Patients who will deviate from intervention protocols (e.g. crossover to CRT-D implantation)
      will continue to be followed-up.

      Blinding:

      Trial participants will be blinded to the device type for the whole duration of the trial.

      The randomizing and implanting physicians will not be blinded to the type of the device.
      These physicians will not take care in the subsequent patients' follow-up and sign a
      declaration of confidentiality.

      The same will be true for the physicians / technicians attending to the device interrogation
      during follow-up visits. The device type will be hidden and physicians will sign a
      declaration of confidentiality. The patients' documentation will not reveal the device type.

      A maximum effort will be done to hide the type of the implanted device. The implantation will
      be intramuscular and the device interrogation follow-up visits will not reveal the device
      type.

      The physicians attending the follow-up visits and entering all patients' data into web-based
      CRF will be blinded to the implanted device type.

      In case of an emergency with a need to reveal the type of the device, i.e. lead fracture,
      infection in the place of implantation, ventricular tachycardia, the site principal
      investigator will decide to unblind the patient. This will be documented in the CRF.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, randomized, interventional parallel-design trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Trial participants will be blinded to the device type for the whole duration of the trial.
The randomizing and implanting physicians will not be blinded to the type of the device. These physicians will not take care in the subsequent patients' follow-up and sign a declaration of confidentiality.
The same will be true for the physicians / technicians attending to the device interrogation during follow-up visits. The device type will be hidden and physicians will sign a declaration of confidentiality. The patients' documentation will not reveal the device type.
A maximum effort will be done to hide the type of the implanted device. The implantation will be intramuscular and the device interrogation follow-up visits will not reveal the device type.
The physicians attending the follow-up visits and entering all patients' data into web-based CRF will be blinded to the implanted device type.
The outcomes assessors will also be blinded to the implanted device type.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-hospitalization for heart failure</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ventricular tachycardia</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate, sustained ventricular tachycardia documentation during follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiac events (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate of MACE, defined as a composite of nonfatal stroke, nonfatal myocardial infarction, and cardiovascular death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sudden cardiac death</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate of sudden cardiac death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular death</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate of cardiovascular death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resuscitated cardiac arrest or sustained ventricular tachycardia</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate of resuscitated cardiac arrest or sustained ventricular tachycardia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Device-related complications</measure>
    <time_frame>0-3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Event rate of any complication requiring hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The impact in terms of overall quality of life by the SF-36 Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 measures eight scales: physical functioning, role physical, bodily pain, general health, vitality, social functioning, role emotional, and mental health. The SF-36 consists of eight scaled scores, which are the weighted sums of the questions in their section. Each scale is directly transformed into a 0-100. The lower the score the more disability. The higher the score the less disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The impact in terms of overall quality of life by the MacNew Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after device implantation</time_frame>
    <description>The MacNew consists of 27 items which fall into three domains: 13-item physical limitations domain scale, 14-item emotional function domain scale, 13-item social function domain scale. The maximum possible score in any domain is 7 (high QoL). The minimum is 1 (low QoL). Missing responses do not contribute to the score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">924</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy, Dilated, 3B</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Implantation of cardiac resynchronization therapy with a defibrillator (CRT-D)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Implantation of cardiac resynchronization therapy pacemaker (CRT-P)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CRT-D</intervention_name>
    <description>After randomization, devices will be implanted as soon as possible (within 2 weeks). The ICD will be programmed with anti-tachycardia pacing and shock therapy as per common praxis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-D</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CRT-P</intervention_name>
    <description>After randomization, devices will be implanted as soon as possible (within 2 weeks).</description>
    <arm_group_label>CRT-P</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age at the time of screening

          -  Documented non-ischemic HF with an LVEF ≤ 35

          -  QRS≥130ms; NYHA class II-IV

          -  Signed written informed consent

          -  NT-proBNP above 200 pg/ml

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncorrected congenital heart disease or valve obstruction

          -  obstructive cardiomyopathy

          -  active myocarditis

          -  constrictive pericarditis

          -  untreated hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism

          -  adrenal insufficiency

          -  active vasculitis due to collagen vascular disease

          -  Presence on the urgent waiting list for a heart transplant (UNOS category 1A or 1B, or
             equivalent)

          -  Patients on the non-urgent waiting list for a heart transplant (UNOS category 2 or 7,
             or equivalent) are eligible for inclusion in the study

          -  Recipient of any major organ transplant (e.g., lung, liver, heart)

          -  Receiving or has received cytotoxic or cytostatic chemotherapy and/or radiation
             therapy for treatment of a malignancy within 6 month before randomization or clinical
             evidence of current malignancy, with the following exceptions: basal or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin, cervical intraepithelial neoplasia, prostate cancer (if stable
             localized disease, with a life expectancy of &gt; 2.5 years in the opinion of the
             investigator)

          -  Known to be human immunodeficiency virus positive with an expected survival of less
             than 5 years due to HIV

          -  Chronic kidney disease with glomerular filtration rate &lt;30 ml/min

          -  Chronic dialysis treatment

          -  Recent (within 3 months) history of alcohol or illicit drug abuse disorder, based on
             self-report

          -  Any condition (e.g., psychiatric illness) or situation that, in the investigator's
             opinion, could put the subject at significant risk, confound the study results, or
             interfere significantly with the subject's participation in the study

          -  Unwilling to participate

        Additional information related to inclusion and exclusion criteria:

          -  The qualifying LVEF and NT-proBNP level has to be measured after a maximal tolerated
             pharmacotherapy of heart failure has been achieved.

          -  A non-ischemic cause of HF has to be determined by coronary angiography. Patients
             could be included even if they will have one or two coronary arteries with stenosis,
             if the extent of coronary artery disease will not be considered to be sufficient to
             account for the reduced LVEF. Patients with a significant coronary heart disease (CAD)
             will be excluded.

          -  Patients with an existing conventional pacemaker could be included if they will be
             willing to have the device changed or upgraded.

          -  Patients with any form of atrial fibrillation will not be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Milos Taborsky, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Olomouc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tomas Skala, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+420 588 44 3212</phone>
    <email>tomasskala@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Irena Opavska, Mgr.</last_name>
    <phone>+420 588 44 3201</phone>
    <email>irena.opavska@fnol.cz</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University hospital Olomouc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Olomouc</city>
        <state>Česká Republika</state>
        <zip>77900</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Irena Opavska, Mgr.</last_name>
      <phone>+420 588 44 3201</phone>
      <email>irena.opavska@fnol.cz</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Beata Brosova, Mgr.</last_name>
      <phone>+420 588 44 3201</phone>
      <email>Beata.Brosova@fnol.cz</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tomas Skala, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Milos Taborsky, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Felker GM, Thompson RE, Hare JM, Hruban RH, Clemetson DE, Howard DL, Baughman KL, Kasper EK. Underlying causes and long-term survival in patients with initially unexplained cardiomyopathy. N Engl J Med. 2000 Apr 13;342(15):1077-84.</citation>
    <PMID>10760308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ponikowski P, Voors AA, Anker SD, Bueno H, Cleland JG, Coats AJ, Falk V, González-Juanatey JR, Harjola VP, Jankowska EA, Jessup M, Linde C, Nihoyannopoulos P, Parissis JT, Pieske B, Riley JP, Rosano GM, Ruilope LM, Ruschitzka F, Rutten FH, van der Meer P; Authors/Task Force Members; Document Reviewers. 2016 ESC Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure: The Task Force for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Developed with the special contribution of the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the ESC. Eur J Heart Fail. 2016 Aug;18(8):891-975. doi: 10.1002/ejhf.592. Epub 2016 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27207191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Køber L, Thune JJ, Nielsen JC, Haarbo J, Videbæk L, Korup E, Jensen G, Hildebrandt P, Steffensen FH, Bruun NE, Eiskjær H, Brandes A, Thøgersen AM, Gustafsson F, Egstrup K, Videbæk R, Hassager C, Svendsen JH, Høfsten DE, Torp-Pedersen C, Pehrson S; DANISH Investigators. Defibrillator Implantation in Patients with Nonischemic Systolic Heart Failure. N Engl J Med. 2016 Sep 29;375(13):1221-30. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1608029. Epub 2016 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27571011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bänsch D, Antz M, Boczor S, Volkmer M, Tebbenjohanns J, Seidl K, Block M, Gietzen F, Berger J, Kuck KH. Primary prevention of sudden cardiac death in idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy: the Cardiomyopathy Trial (CAT). Circulation. 2002 Mar 26;105(12):1453-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11914254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strickberger SA, Hummel JD, Bartlett TG, Frumin HI, Schuger CD, Beau SL, Bitar C, Morady F; AMIOVIRT Investigators. Amiodarone versus implantable cardioverter-defibrillator:randomized trial in patients with nonischemic dilated cardiomyopathy and asymptomatic nonsustained ventricular tachycardia--AMIOVIRT. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 May 21;41(10):1707-12.</citation>
    <PMID>12767651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kadish A, Dyer A, Daubert JP, Quigg R, Estes NA, Anderson KP, Calkins H, Hoch D, Goldberger J, Shalaby A, Sanders WE, Schaechter A, Levine JH; Defibrillators in Non-Ischemic Cardiomyopathy Treatment Evaluation (DEFINITE) Investigators. Prophylactic defibrillator implantation in patients with nonischemic dilated cardiomyopathy. N Engl J Med. 2004 May 20;350(21):2151-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15152060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bardy GH, Lee KL, Mark DB, Poole JE, Packer DL, Boineau R, Domanski M, Troutman C, Anderson J, Johnson G, McNulty SE, Clapp-Channing N, Davidson-Ray LD, Fraulo ES, Fishbein DP, Luceri RM, Ip JH; Sudden Cardiac Death in Heart Failure Trial (SCD-HeFT) Investigators. Amiodarone or an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator for congestive heart failure. N Engl J Med. 2005 Jan 20;352(3):225-37. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2005 May 19;352(20):2146.</citation>
    <PMID>15659722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stavrakis S, Asad Z, Reynolds D. Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillators for Primary Prevention of Mortality in Patients With Nonischemic Cardiomyopathy: A Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2017 Jun;28(6):659-665. doi: 10.1111/jce.13204. Epub 2017 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28316104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shen L, Jhund PS, Petrie MC, Claggett BL, Barlera S, Cleland JGF, Dargie HJ, Granger CB, Kjekshus J, Køber L, Latini R, Maggioni AP, Packer M, Pitt B, Solomon SD, Swedberg K, Tavazzi L, Wikstrand J, Zannad F, Zile MR, McMurray JJV. Declining Risk of Sudden Death in Heart Failure. N Engl J Med. 2017 Jul 6;377(1):41-51. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1609758.</citation>
    <PMID>28679089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bristow MR, Saxon LA, Boehmer J, Krueger S, Kass DA, De Marco T, Carson P, DiCarlo L, DeMets D, White BG, DeVries DW, Feldman AM; Comparison of Medical Therapy, Pacing, and Defibrillation in Heart Failure (COMPANION) Investigators. Cardiac-resynchronization therapy with or without an implantable defibrillator in advanced chronic heart failure. N Engl J Med. 2004 May 20;350(21):2140-50.</citation>
    <PMID>15152059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hawkins NM, Grubisic M, Andrade JG, Huang F, Ding L, Gao M, Bashir J. Long-term complications, reoperations and survival following cardioverter-defibrillator implant. Heart. 2018 Feb;104(3):237-243. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2017-311638. Epub 2017 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>28747313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haugaa KH, Tilz R, Boveda S, Dobreanu D, Sciaraffia E, Mansourati J, Papiashvili G, Dagres N. Implantable cardioverter defibrillator use for primary prevention in ischaemic and non-ischaemic heart disease-indications in the post-DANISH trial era: results of the European Heart Rhythm Association survey. Europace. 2017 Apr 1;19(4):660-664. doi: 10.1093/europace/eux089.</citation>
    <PMID>28431077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Disertori M, Masè M, Ravelli F. Myocardial fibrosis predicts ventricular tachyarrhythmias. Trends Cardiovasc Med. 2017 Jul;27(5):363-372. doi: 10.1016/j.tcm.2017.01.011. Epub 2017 Feb 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28262437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gulati A, Jabbour A, Ismail TF, Guha K, Khwaja J, Raza S, Morarji K, Brown TD, Ismail NA, Dweck MR, Di Pietro E, Roughton M, Wage R, Daryani Y, O'Hanlon R, Sheppard MN, Alpendurada F, Lyon AR, Cook SA, Cowie MR, Assomull RG, Pennell DJ, Prasad SK. Association of fibrosis with mortality and sudden cardiac death in patients with nonischemic dilated cardiomyopathy. JAMA. 2013 Mar 6;309(9):896-908. doi: 10.1001/jama.2013.1363. Erratum in: JAMA. 2013 Jul 3;310(1):99.</citation>
    <PMID>23462786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farrington CP, Manning G. Test statistics and sample size formulae for comparative binomial trials with null hypothesis of non-zero risk difference or non-unity relative risk. Stat Med. 1990 Dec;9(12):1447-54.</citation>
    <PMID>2281232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gart JJ, Nam J. Approximate interval estimation of the ratio of binomial parameters: a review and corrections for skewness. Biometrics. 1988 Jun;44(2):323-38. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3291957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gart JJ, Nam JM. Approximate interval estimation of the difference in binomial parameters: correction for skewness and extension to multiple tables. Biometrics. 1990 Sep;46(3):637-43. Erratum in: Biometrics 1992 Sep;48(3):979.</citation>
    <PMID>2242407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kutyifa V, Geller L, Bogyi P, Zima E, Aktas MK, Ozcan EE, Becker D, Nagy VK, Kosztin A, Szilagyi S, Merkely B. Effect of cardiac resynchronization therapy with implantable cardioverter defibrillator versus cardiac resynchronization therapy with pacemaker on mortality in heart failure patients: results of a high-volume, single-centre experience. Eur J Heart Fail. 2014 Dec;16(12):1323-30. doi: 10.1002/ejhf.185. Epub 2014 Nov 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25379962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barra S, Providência R, Boveda S, Duehmke R, Narayanan K, Chow AW, Piot O, Klug D, Defaye P, Gras D, Deharo JC, Milliez P, Da Costa A, Mondoly P, Gonzalez-Panizo J, Leclercq C, Heck P, Virdee M, Sadoul N, Le Heuzey JY, Marijon E. Device complications with addition of defibrillation to cardiac resynchronisation therapy for primary prevention. Heart. 2018 Sep;104(18):1529-1535. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2017-312546. Epub 2018 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29540431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dichtl W, Wolber T, Paoli U, Brüllmann S, Stühlinger M, Berger T, Spuller K, Strasak A, Pachinger O, Haegeli LM, Duru F, Hintringer F. Appropriate therapy but not inappropriate shocks predict survival in implantable cardioverter defibrillator patients. Clin Cardiol. 2011 Jul;34(7):433-6. doi: 10.1002/clc.20910. Epub 2011 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21678454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petrie MC, Connelly DT, Gardner RS. Who needs an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator? Controversies and opportunities after DANISH. Eur J Heart Fail. 2018 Mar;20(3):413-416. doi: 10.1002/ejhf.1135. Epub 2018 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>29327793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ware JE Jr, Sherbourne CD. The MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36). I. Conceptual framework and item selection. Med Care. 1992 Jun;30(6):473-83.</citation>
    <PMID>1593914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dixon T, Lim LL, Oldridge NB. The MacNew heart disease health-related quality of life instrument: reference data for users. Qual Life Res. 2002 Mar;11(2):173-83.</citation>
    <PMID>12018740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Olomouc</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tomas Skala, MD, PhD, FESC</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Non-ischemic cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Implantable cardioverter-defibrillator</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac resynchronization therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic resonance imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Late gadolinium enhancement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Dilated</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All collected IPD are to be shared.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will become available 6 months after the study results are published.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The requests to gain access to IPD will be reviewed by National principal investigator.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

