<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04131712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>43499</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Massage Therapy Foundation</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04131712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Massage as a Mechanotherapy for Muscle Wasting in Healthy Young Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Massage as a Mechanotherapy for Muscle Wasting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Esther Dupont-Versteegden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oklahoma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether massage can attenuate the loss of muscle
      mass in humans after a short period of disuse.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The loss of skeletal muscle mass is a common symptom associated with diseases such as cancer,
      AIDS, diabetes, and congestive heart failure, and with aging. Muscle atrophy is associated
      with poor disease prognosis and decreased quality of life and therefore, maintaining muscle
      size and reducing the loss of muscle during disuse atrophy is of vital significance.
      Mechanical stimulation of muscle, such as during resistance exercise, stimulates protein
      synthesis that increases muscle protein content, and muscle size. The investigators have
      shown that mechanical stimulation applied to skeletal muscle in the form of massage is an
      effective mechanotherapy in rats, since it leads to a shift in protein turnover favoring
      anabolism, attenuation of muscle loss and enhanced regrowth after disuse-induced atrophy.
      Whether the same positive effect of massage occurs in humans is currently unknown, but would
      be extremely beneficial for skeletal muscle and overall health in case where resistance
      exercise is contraindicated or not feasible. In addition to the direct anabolic effects on
      the massaged rat muscle, the investigators have shown an equally beneficial response on the
      homologous muscle in the contralateral non-massaged limb. This novel finding indicated the
      existence of indirect mechanisms that could have profound systemic effects beyond the
      massaged muscle. Extracellular vesicles (EVs) are lipid membrane-bound vesicles released from
      cells with the ability to modulate function of cells from which they are released, as well as
      in cells with which they fuse. As such EVs are likely mediators of the well-documented but
      poorly-understood effects of massage in humans on the brain and other organs, such as relief
      of pain, anxiety or depression or changes in immunity. Therefore, the goal of this proposal
      is to determine anabolic effects of massage in human muscle, and to identify whether EVs
      released with massage are candidates for beneficial effects of this mechanotherapy on muscle
      as well as other organs. In Aim 1 the investigators will address the following hypothesis:
      Massage acts as a mechanotherapy by attenuating muscle atrophy through a shift in protein
      biogenesis towards anabolism in humans. Using a novel massage device we will apply mechanical
      load to muscle undergoing atrophy through unilateral lower limb suspension and muscle size as
      well as protein synthesis and degradation will be determined. In Aim 2 the investigators will
      test the hypothesis that massage attenuates the loss of EVs during atrophy by enhancing EV
      biogenesis in muscle. The investigators will measure EVs and their miRNA cargo in the serum,
      and markers of EV biogenesis in muscle of human subjects from Aim 1. Results from this study
      will indicate not only whether mechanotherapy, such as massage, can attenuate atrophy and
      enhance anabolic processes during disuse, but also determine whether EVs are a candidate
      mechanism for the overall health benefits of massage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 14, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 14, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Primary outcome assessors are blinded to treatment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in myofiber Cross Sectional Area (CSA).</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>The ability of massage to attenuate the atrophic response to disuse will be determined. Muscle biopsies of the vastus lateralis will be used to quantify myofiber cross-sectional area. The percent change in myofiber size between day 7 and day -2 was used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in myofibrillar protein synthesis (MyoKsyn).</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>The ability of massage to attenuate the atrophic response to disuse due to protein synthesis will be determined. Muscle biopsies of the vastus lateralis will be used to quantify protein synthesis rates. The percent change in myofibrillar protein synthesis between day 7 and day -2 was used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in serum extracellular vesicle number (EV #).</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>The ability of massage to attenuate the loss in EV number will be determined. Serum will be used to quantify EV numbers. The percent change in EVs between day 7 and day -2 was used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in the expression of muscle Rab27b mRNA.</measure>
    <time_frame>9 days</time_frame>
    <description>The ability of massage to attenuate the loss in Rab27b protein expression will be determined. Muscle biopsies of the vastus lateralis will be used to quantify muscle Rab27b expression. The percent change in muscle Rab27b expression between day 7 and day -2 was used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Atrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ambulatory Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following baseline assessments, participants will be randomized into the ambulatory group for the remainder of the study. Atrophy will not be induced and massage intervention will not be applied.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ambulatory Massage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following baseline assessments, participants will be randomized into the ambulatory group for the remainder of the study. No atrophy induction. Four massage treatments will be applied every other day until the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immobilization Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following baseline assessments, participants will be randomized into the unilateral lower limb suspension group undergoing atrophy for the remainder of the study. Massage intervention will not be applied.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immobilization Massage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following baseline assessments, participants will be randomized into the unilateral lower limb suspension group undergoing atrophy for the remainder of the study. Four massage treatments will be applied every other day until the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Massage</intervention_name>
    <description>A custom-made cyclic compressive loading (CCL) device will be used to apply a mechanical load to the left thigh of the participants. Massage application using a 35 Newton load will be applied for 15 minutes every other day over the course of 7 days for a total of four massages.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ambulatory Massage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Immobilization Massage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women 18-30 years of age.

          -  All races and ethnic backgrounds.

          -  Non-smoker and generally healthy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have a current lower extremity musculoskeletal injury or compromised musculoskeletal
             function that would not allow the safe use of crutches or a brace.

          -  Previous lower extremity surgeries or injury.

          -  Activities of daily living require long periods of standing or driving a manual
             transmission car.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) under 27.

          -  Evidence or signs and symptoms of metabolic syndrome or disorder (diagnosis of
             diabetes or insulin resistance, elevated BP, high fasting blood sugar, abnormal
             cholesterol or triglyceride levels).

          -  Thyroid disorder.

          -  Acute or chronic infections.

          -  Use of systemic steroids, anabolic steroids, or growth hormone.

          -  Chronic aspirin or NSAID use (unless it can be safely stopped prior to the biopsies),
             and any other use of an anticoagulant (e.g., Coumadin) or history of bleeding
             including history of hypo- or hyper-coagulation disorders.

          -  Lidocaine allergy (1% lidocaine is the local anesthetic used during the muscle biopsy
             procedure).

          -  Any other condition or events considered exclusionary by the PI and/or physician, such
             as non-compliance.

          -  Pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Esther Dupont-Versteegden, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Douglas Long, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>859-323-5438</phone>
    <email>delong2@uky.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Esther Dupont-Versteegden, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>859-218-0592</phone>
    <email>eedupo2@uky.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Esther Dupont-Versteegden</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ph.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Massage</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle</keyword>
  <keyword>Extracellular Vesicles</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrophy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

