<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04132232</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SIGS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04132232</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Smoking Reduction In Gravid Substance Use Disorders</brief_title>
  <acronym>SIGS</acronym>
  <official_title>Smoking Reduction In Gravid Women With Substance Use Disorders (SIGS): A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to encourage smoking cessation in women with substance use disorders
      by providing knowledge of expired carbon monoxide. We hypothesize that women who are provided
      knowledge of their expired carbon monoxide and the associated percent fetal carboxyhemoglobin
      will have a greater success at quitting smoking during pregnancy than women who are not
      provided this information.

      A secondary aim of the study is to correlate expired carbon monoxide throughout pregnancy
      with infant birth weight.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled trial. Pregnant smokers who are substances users who meet
      inclusion criteria will be offered participation in the study at their first obstetrical
      appointment. Patients who consent to participate will be randomized.

      At the enrollment/randomization visit, women will be randomized to either the intervention
      (knowledge of and interpretation carbon monoxide levels and associated percent fetal
      carboxyhemoglobin) or control group (no information on carbon monoxide and associated percent
      fetal carboxyhemoglobin). Allocation will be computer generated. This will be done after the
      patient meets all inclusion criteria. If randomization to the intervention arm, the patient
      will be notified of carbon monoxide and associated fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels at each
      obstetrical visit and counseled on how it affects maternal and fetal health.

      If randomized to the control arm, the patient will have expired carbon monoxide and
      associated fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels measured at each obstetrical visit but blinded to
      these results. These patients will not be notified of the levels, nor counseled on what
      levels mean for maternal or fetal health.

      See below for intervention and control protocols.

      Maternal demographic (age, race, socioeconomic status), medical history (other medical
      problems, medications, height, weight) and obstetric history (parity, gestational age) data
      will be abstracted from the patient's chart and supplemented with a patient questionnaire at
      the enrollment/randomization visit. The primary outcome is the expired maternal carbon
      monoxide level at the last obstetric visit or at delivery. This will be determined by the
      Smokerlyzer device used to measure this. Secondary aims of the study will be to evaluate how
      maternal carbon monoxide levels correlate with fetal growth, cigarette use per day, patient
      satisfaction and neonatal birth weight.

      All patients will have the following performed at the enrollment/randomization visit and
      subsequent prenatal visits:

      a. The order of events for all patients will be as follows: i. Blood pressure evaluation ii.
      Weight iii. Fundal height iv. Patient will be asked the number of cigarettes used per day v.
      Patient will exhale into Smokerlyzer device to obtain expired carbon monoxide and associated
      percent fetal carboxyhemoglobin vi. Patients will be provided smoking cessation resources and
      counseling on smoking cessation in pregnancy

      Intervention Protocol

        1. Intervention group will undergo Smokerlyzer ® exhaled carbon monoxide measurements at
           enrollment, each prenatal visit, and at their last (&gt;36 week) prenatal visit or at
           delivery if not captured in clinic.

        2. Women will be informed of their exhaled carbon monoxide measurement at each visit as
           well as the correlation to fetal carboxyhemoglobin.

        3. At each visit, the intervention group will receive counseling on fetal impact of smoking
           based on fetal carboxyhemoglobin level and institutional and state information on
           smoking cessation will be provided.

        4. The patient will then proceed to the remainder of the obstetrical visit.

      Control Protocol

        1. Women in the control group will undergo Smokerlyzer ® exhaled carbon monoxide
           measurements at enrollment, each prenatal visit and at their final (&gt;36 week) prenatal
           visit or at delivery if not captured in clinic.

        2. Both levels (maternal carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin) will be recorded by
           the co-investigatory, but NOT disclosed to the patient

        3. At each visit, control group will be provided institutional and state information on
           smoking cessation if they report continued smoking.

        4. The patient will then proceed to remainder of the obstetrical visit.

      For both groups:

      At the time of delivery, maternal and neonatal outcome data will be recorded from the chart,
      including gestational age at delivery, mode of delivery, indications for delivery, birth
      weight, Apgar score, cord blood gas, length of stay, and neonatal complications, if any. A
      survey will be completed for both intervention and standard care groups after delivery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Will not discuss percent fetal carboxyhemoglobin to control group versus disclosing percent fetal carboxyhemoglobin to intervention group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expired maternal carbon monoxide level</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
    <description>1. Prevalence of smoking ≥ 10 cigarettes/day in each group at final measurement by exhaled carbon monoxide level at last prenatal visit prior to delivery, as measured by exhaled carbon monoxide</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expired maternal carbon monoxide level at delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
    <description>2. Prevalence of smoking ≥ 10 cigarettes/day in each group at final measurement by exhaled carbon monoxide level at delivery, as measured by exhaled carbon monoxide</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant birthweight</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>APGAR at 5 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average number of cigarettes smoked/day in each group, as measured by exhaled carbon monoxide at final measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of smoking ≥10 cigarettes/day in each group at delivery, per patient report</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average number of cigarettes smoked/day in each group, per patient report</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average exhaled carbon monoxide at final measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average percent fetal carboxyhemoglobin at final measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Small for gestational age at birth (&lt;10th percentile)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant birth weight as a function of carboxyhemoglobin in pregnancy (first and last measured; average of all measurements in intervention group)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction at final prenatal visit, measured by PANAS scales (positive and negative affect scales) and select questions at last visit or delivery on Stop Smoking Service Client Satisfaction Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Tobacco Smoking in Mother Complicating Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Tobacco Use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Tobacco Smoking</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient will exhaled into the Smokerlyzer® device will at each visit
Exhaled carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels will be disclosed to the patient
Risks of adverse perinatal outcomes related to maternal carboxyhemoglobin and fetal carboxyhemoglobin level will be provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient will exhale into the Smokerlyzer® device at each visit.
Exhaled carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin level will NOT be disclosed to the patient
No risks of adverse perinatal outcomes related to maternal carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels will be provided</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>knowledge of expired maternal carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels</intervention_name>
    <description>Will use the Smokerlyzer® device at each visit and be provided information on exhaled carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin. Risks of adverse perinatal outcomes related to maternal carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin level will be provided.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>adverse outcomes related to expired maternal carbon monoxide and fetal carboxyhemoglobin levels</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        i. Age 16-45

        ii. Singleton gestation

        iii. Gestational age at enrollment &lt;24 weeks

        iv. Substance use disorder defined as modified National Institute on Drug Abuse ASSIST ≥4

        v. Cigarette smoker using ≥10 cigarettes/day interested in quitting

        Exclusion criteria:

        i. Known or suspected fetal growth restriction at enrollment

        ii. Known fetal anomaly, aneuploidy, or demise

        iii. Not interested in smoking cessation or reduction during pregnancy

        iv. E-cigarette use
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant women and neonates: male and females</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa Dimperio</last_name>
    <phone>205-934-3276</phone>
    <email>ldimperio@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lorie Harper, MD</last_name>
    <phone>205-934-5611</phone>
    <email>lmharper@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.covita.net/product/microbaby-smokerlyzer/</url>
    <description>Smokerlyzer product website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandberg A, Sköld CM, Grunewald J, Eklund A, Wheelock ÅM. Assessing recent smoking status by measuring exhaled carbon monoxide levels. PLoS One. 2011;6(12):e28864. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0028864. Epub 2011 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22194931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bedfont. Smokerlyzer range user manual. http://www.bedfont.com/file.php?f=ZmlsZSMjMTgxMg. Updated 2019. Accessed Sept 16, 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomez C, Berlin I, Marquis P, Delcroix M. Expired air carbon monoxide concentration in mothers and their spouses above 5 ppm is associated with decreased fetal growth. Prev Med. 2005 Jan;40(1):10-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15530575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstein AO, Gans SP, Ripley-Moffitt C, Kotsen C, Bars M. Use of Expired Air Carbon Monoxide Testing in Clinical Tobacco Treatment Settings. Chest. 2018 Feb;153(2):554-562. doi: 10.1016/j.chest.2017.11.002. Epub 2017 Nov 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29137909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riaz M, Lewis S, Coleman T, Aveyard P, West R, Naughton F, Ussher M. Which measures of cigarette dependence are predictors of smoking cessation during pregnancy? Analysis of data from a randomized controlled trial. Addiction. 2016 Sep;111(9):1656-65. doi: 10.1111/add.13395. Epub 2016 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26997495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jha P, Ramasundarahettige C, Landsman V, Rostron B, Thun M, Anderson RN, McAfee T, Peto R. 21st-century hazards of smoking and benefits of cessation in the United States. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jan 24;368(4):341-50. doi: 10.1056/NEJMsa1211128.</citation>
    <PMID>23343063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>QuickStats: Number of Deaths from 10 Leading Causes,* by Sex - National Vital Statistics System, United States, 2015. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017 Apr 21;66(15):413. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6615a8.</citation>
    <PMID>28426642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Middleton ET, Morice AH. Breath carbon monoxide as an indication of smoking habit. Chest. 2000 Mar;117(3):758-63.</citation>
    <PMID>10713003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McClure JB. Are biomarkers a useful aid in smoking cessation? A review and analysis of the literature. Behav Med. 2001 Spring;27(1):37-47.</citation>
    <PMID>11575171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>11. Bedfont. Smokerlyzer range user manual. http://www.bedfont.com/file.php?f=ZmlsZSMjMTgxMg. Updated 2019. Accessed Sept 16, 2019.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shahab L, West R, McNeill A. A randomized, controlled trial of adding expired carbon monoxide feedback to brief stop smoking advice: evaluation of cognitive and behavioral effects. Health Psychol. 2011 Jan;30(1):49-57. doi: 10.1037/a0021821.</citation>
    <PMID>21299294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bize R, Burnand B, Mueller Y, Rège-Walther M, Camain JY, Cornuz J. Biomedical risk assessment as an aid for smoking cessation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Dec 12;12:CD004705. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004705.pub4. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2019 Mar 26;3:CD004705.</citation>
    <PMID>23235615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reynolds CME, Egan B, Kennedy RA, O'Malley E, Sheehan SR, Turner MJ. The implications of high carbon monoxide levels in early pregnancy for neonatal outcomes. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2019 Feb;233:6-11. doi: 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2018.11.020. Epub 2018 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>30529257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ecker J, Abuhamad A, Hill W, Bailit J, Bateman BT, Berghella V, Blake-Lamb T, Guille C, Landau R, Minkoff H, Prabhu M, Rosenthal E, Terplan M, Wright TE, Yonkers KA. Substance use disorders in pregnancy: clinical, ethical, and research imperatives of the opioid epidemic: a report of a joint workshop of the Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine, American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, and American Society of Addiction Medicine. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2019 Jul;221(1):B5-B28. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2019.03.022. Epub 2019 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>30928567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rubymel J Knupp</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Maternal-Fetal Medicine Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smoking in pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>substance use disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>carbon monoxide</keyword>
  <keyword>fetal carboxyhemoglobin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pregnancy Complications</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carbon Monoxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

