<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04138030</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>(6114) 2019/ETH11826</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04138030</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Conventional Endoscopic Mucosal Resection Versus Cold Snare Endoscopic Mucosal Resection of Colonic Lateral Spreading Lesions - A Randomised Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Conventional Versus Cold Snare Endoscopic Mucosal Resection of Colonic Lateral Spreading Lesions - A Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Western Sydney Local Health District</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western Sydney Local Health District</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Comparing the complete resection rate and subsequent adenoma recurrence rate at surveillance
      colonoscopy of 15-40mm laterally spreading adenomas for conventional EMR vs. cold snare EMR.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the third most common malignancy worldwide and the fourth leading
      cause of cancer related death, with rates being highest in Western countries. Colonoscopy is
      considered the golden standard in colorectal cancer screening and endoscopic resection of
      precursor lesions (polyps) has been shown to reduce colorectal cancer death. Polyps extending
      over 10mm, also referred to as lateral spreading lesions (LSL) if non-pedunculated, more
      often demonstrate advanced histological features and are considered to be at greater risk for
      malignant transition as compared to their smaller counterparts. Incomplete endoscopic
      resection of advanced adenomas may lead to adenoma recurrence and contribute to the
      development of so called 'interval cancers', which occur during the 6 - 36 month period
      following complete colonoscopy. Interval cancers account for up to 6% of newly diagnosed CRC
      cases, highlighting the importance of complete resection.

      Endoscopic mucosal resection (EMR) is a well-established inject and resect method for the
      removal of LSLs using chromo-gelofusin based submucosal lift and subsequent cauterisation
      assisted snare excision. Lesions up to 25mm in size may be removed enbloc, whereas larger
      lesions are generally removed in a piecemeal fashion. Contrary to enbloc resection, piecemeal
      EMR is historically associated with relatively high recurrence rates of 15-20%. A recent four
      centre trial led by Westmead Hospital published in gastroenterology (impact factor 20.8) has
      shown that application of snare-tip soft coag (STSC) to the EMR defect margins considerably
      improves recurrence rates to around 7% in adenomatous LSL. Common complications of EMR such
      as intra-procedural bleeding (IPB) or clinically significant post-procedural bleeding (CSPB),
      deep mural injury (DMI) and post-polypectomy coagulation syndrome (PPCS) are largely related
      to the use of cauterisation for tissue transection. Although complication rates have improved
      and effects can often be managed endoscopically, further optimization of the EMR safety
      profile is needed in the background of an aging target population with multiple
      co-morbidities and widespread use of anticoagulants.

      Cold snare polypectomy (CSP) has become the standard of care for removal of subcentimeter
      polyps. CSP relies on the use of dedicated stiff thin wire snares that are able to swiftly
      cut through mucosal tissue without the need for cauterisation, leaving intact the muscularis
      mucosa and the deeper submucosal layers, virtually excluding the risk of perforation. The
      absence of delayed cauterisation effect significantly reduces the risk of post-polypectomy
      bleeding, even in patients on anticoagulant therapy. Complete resection rates of polyps
      ranging from 6 to 10mm in size were found to be non-inferior in CSP as compared to
      cauterisation based resection. Moreover, resecting a sufficient margin of normal mucosa
      surrounding the polyp (i.e. &gt;1mm) yields an excellent 98% complete resection rate in polyps
      &lt;10mm in size without increasing the risk of delayed bleeding. Meta-analysis demonstrated a
      significantly shorter procedure time when applying the cold snare resection technique in
      small polyps. Snare size limitations of dedicated cold snares however do not allow for
      en-bloc resection of polyps &gt;10mm.

      Recently, cold snare piecemeal EMR was shown to be safe and effective for the removal of
      large sessile serrated polyps (SSP). Combined evidence from a limited number of small single
      centre mostly retrospective studies investigating cold snare piecemeal polypectomy in
      adenomas over 10mm demonstrated recurrence rates of around 11% whilst maintaining an
      excellent safety profile with minimal complication rates. However, recurrence rates rise to
      22% in the subgroup of polyps over 20mm. Thus far cold snare piecemeal polypectomy of
      lateral-spreading adenomas has not yet been compared to conventional EMR in prospective
      randomized fashion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 27, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 27, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Complete resection rate (CRR) as determined by endoscopic assessment (no visible residual adenoma) and histological assessment (biopsies of resection margin)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adenoma recurrence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>4-6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adenoma recurrence rate (ARR) at SC1 as determined by endoscopic assessment (no visible recurrent adenoma) and histological assessment (scar biopsies)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to perform polypectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Time needed to perform polyp resection measured from first snare positioning until complete resection is achieved based on endoscopic assessment, and total procedure time from insertion of the scope until all specimens have been collected and the scope withdrawal is completed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-procedural and post-procedural complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Intra-procedural and post-procedural complications rates (IPB / CSPB / DMI / PPCS) as previously described</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenoma Colon</condition>
  <condition>Colon Adenoma</condition>
  <condition>Colon Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional Endoscopic Mucosal Resection (EMR), if necessary, to 15-40mm laterally spreading adenomas.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cold Snare Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cold Snare Endoscopic Mucosal Resection (EMR), if necessary, to 15-40mm laterally spreading adenomas.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of injected chromogelofusine solution to raise a lesion prior to polypectomy snare closed over a polyp with electrocautery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Conventional EMR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cold Snare Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of injected chromogelofusine solution to raise a lesion prior to polypectomy snare closed over a polyp without electrocautery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cold Snare Endoscopic Mucosal Resection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CSP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient undergoing colonoscopy who is older than 18 years of age, has a written
             consent for trial participation and has at least one LSL meeting to the following
             description:

               -  Localisation in the colon or rectum

               -  Benign adenomatous surface features (Kudo III / IV, JNET 2a)

               -  Granular or non-granular topography

               -  Paris classification 0-IIa/IIb +/- Is

               -  If present, sessile component may be no greater than 10mm in size.

               -  Polyp size ranging from 15 to 40mm

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current use of antiplatelet (excluding aspirin) or anticoagulants which have not
             appropriately been interrupted according to the guidelines.

          -  Known bleeding disorder or coagulopathy.

          -  Pregnancy

          -  History of inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Previously attempted or otherwise non-lifting lesions

          -  Endoscopic features suggestive of submucosal invasion (Kudo Vi/n, JNET 2b / 3) or
             concurrent CRC

          -  Lesions involving the ileocaecal valve (ICV) or the anorectal junction (ARJ)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Bourke</last_name>
    <phone>00612 9633 5953</phone>
    <email>reception@citywestgastro.com.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westmead Endoscopy Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westmead</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2145</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathleen Goodrick, BN</last_name>
      <phone>88905555</phone>
      <email>kathleen.goodrick@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western Sydney Local Health District</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Michael Bourke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Polypectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

