<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04133389</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-03-019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04133389</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Believing People Can Change: A Randomized Controlled Trial of an Incremental Theory Intervention in Adolescence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Believing People Can Change: An Examination of the Role of Implicit Theory, Attributional Style and Psychological Flexibility in Depression and Wellbeing, &amp; a Randomized Controlled Trial of an Incremental Theory Intervention in Adolescence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Guelph</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Guelph</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the effectiveness of a brief educational intervention that teaches youth
      that they can grow and change, known as &quot;growth mindset.&quot; Similar growth mindset
      interventions have improved youths' well-being and academic skills, and reduced risk for
      depression. In this study, youths' depressive symptoms and well-being will be measured before
      the intervention and then again 4 months after the intervention to determine if the
      intervention had a positive impact for youth experiencing transitions (firs and last years of
      high school).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adolescents experience many major life transitions during high school, including changes in
      educational settings, living arrangements, and social and romantic relationships. While these
      transitions may be experienced as positive new beginnings for some youth, others experience
      them as stressful and challenging. Further, the developmental period of adolescence is
      characterized by an increased risk for the development of mental illnesses such as
      depression. In the context of widely-accepted cognitive models of adolescent depression,
      adolescents with pre-existing vulnerabilities for depression (e.g., negative self beliefs)
      may be more prone to experience certain life transitions as especially stressful, and this
      vulnerability/environment combination is likely to bring about depressive symptomatology for
      vulnerable youth. Thus, there is a pressing need to better understand factors that not only
      protect youth from mental illness during transitions, but also factors that promote
      resilience and well-being. Indeed, high schools are eager to address student mental illness
      and find better ways of promoting mental health and well-being in schools.

      This project employs clinical, cognitive, developmental, and positive psychology theories in
      an attempt to better understand factors that may be important for adolescent mental illness
      and mental health during this important time of transition. Specifically, we aim to examine
      the utility of a brief online educational intervention for promoting adolescent mental health
      during important life transitions.

      One important factor that appears to be associated with wellbeing and resilience is that of
      beliefs about growth and response to failure. Individuals often respond to challenge by
      either a) retreating and/or making negative attributions about themselves or others, or b)
      view challenge as an opportunity for learning and growth, and not consider failure to be an
      indication of personal shortcomings. The difference between these two responses to challenge
      reflects beliefs about the malleability of personal characteristics; these beliefs are
      referred to as &quot;implicit theories&quot; or more colloquially &quot;mindset&quot;. Those who hold &quot;entity&quot;
      theories (fixed mindset) believe personal characteristics are stable and unchanging, while
      those with a malleable or &quot;incremental theories&quot; (growth mindset) believe personal
      characteristics are changeable and can be developed through effort and learning . Research
      has broadly suggested that those with entity theories may be more prone to experience
      difficulties and be at risk for mental illness, while those with incremental theories
      experience greater resilience and well-being.

      Previous research has indicated that incremental theory can be taught via educational
      interventions, and increasing belief in incremental theory has been associated with positive
      effects. Further, integrating positive psychology into educational institutions to foster
      youth development has been recommended by many researchers. Youth spend substantial amounts
      of time in school, making schools an appropriate setting for interventions that aim to
      promote well-being and prevent mental illness. Thus, this study will test the effects of a
      brief implicit theory intervention on well-being and depressive symptoms.The intervention is
      similar to previous implicit theory interventions and teaches youth an incremental theory of
      socially relevant characteristics (i.e., that people can change and that personal attributes
      are malleable).

      Implicit theory of personality (ie, beliefs about the malleability of personal attributes and
      socially relevant characteristics) has also been associated with depressive symptoms in
      youth. In a study of grade 9 students, researchers found that a brief intervention that
      taught incremental theory of personality (that personal attributes can grow and change) was
      associated with stability of reported levels of depressive symptoms over 9 months. In this
      intervention, students read a compelling article that demonstrated incremental theory of
      either personality (experimental) or athletic ability (control), then students were asked to
      summarize the lesson of the article and apply their own experience. Over time (9 months)
      those in the control condition showed an increase in depressive symptoms while those exposed
      to the incremental theory of personality did not show the same increase, and incidence of
      clinically significant depressive symptoms remained stable. The increase seen in the control
      group was noted to be proportional to that commonly experienced by those transitioning to
      high school, suggesting the intervention may have promise for successfully ameliorating
      developmentally typical increases in depressive symptoms. Although this brief intervention
      was associated with significant positive outcomes, replication and application to other
      samples at risk for depressive symptoms (such as youth transitioning out of high school and
      to post secondary education) is warranted. Towards this end, the current study will examine
      the impact of an intervention that teaches incremental theory on well-being and depressive
      symptoms in students in the first and last years of high school.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 6, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 6, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The current study is a two-wave randomized controlled trial that employs a 2 (group - between participants) by 2 (time - within participants) mixed measures design to assess a brief online implicit theory of personality intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will not be informed that there are different versions of the educational program and thus will be blind to group allocation. Randomization will be fully automated by the online intervention administration system such that researchers will also be blind to group allocation during intervention administration as well as during pre- and post-intervention data collection. Because randomization is automated, neither researchers nor participants will be able to predict randomization assignments. Outcomes will be measured quantitatively thus no assessment of primary outcomes will take place. However, assessors of the manipulation check (which codes for participant engagement in the intervention) will not be masked and thus will be aware of allocation (experimental or control).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months (Oct 2019 - Feb 2020)</time_frame>
    <description>Score on the Beck Depression Inventory-II. The BDI-II consists of 21 items using a 4-point Likert scale from 0 to 3, however the current study will use only 19 items. The item querying suicidal ideation will be removed, as this may be triggering, and researchers would not be able to follow up with those who would highly endorse this item. The item querying sexual interest will be removed, as this may not be equally applicable across the sample. Scores on each item are summed to determine summary scores from 0-57. Higher scores indicate higher levels of depressive symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived happiness</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months (Oct 2019 - Feb 2020)</time_frame>
    <description>score on the Subjective Happiness Scale (SHS). This measure consists of four items measured on a 7-point Likert scale; responses are averaged to create a summary score (minimum=1, maximum=7) and higher scores reflect higher levels of subjective happiness.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Life satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months (Oct 2019 - Feb 2020)</time_frame>
    <description>score on the Brief Multidimensional Student Life Satisfaction Scale (BMSLSS). The BMSLSS includes five items that assess global life satisfaction as a reflection of five life domains: family, school, friends, self, and living environment. The BMSLSS uses a 7-point Likert scale that ranges from delighted to terrible. The score of each item will be averaged to create a single score (minimum=1, maximum=7) such that higher scores represent higher levels of life satisfaction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implicit theory of personality</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post administration of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Score on the Implicit Personality Theory Questionnaire. This is a three-item measure that uses a 6-point Likert scale that ranges from strongly agree to strongly disagree to measure the extent individuals believe one's personality can change. The score of each item will be averaged to create a single score (minimum=1, maximum=6) such that higher values will be associated with higher levels of entity beliefs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implicit theory of a person (general)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post administration of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Score on the Implicit Person Measure. This is a three item measure with a 6-point Likert scale ranging from strongly agree to strongly disagree. Scores on each item will be averaged to create a single score (minimum=1, maximum=6), and higher average scores will be associated with more entity beliefs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implicit theory of personality</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months (Oct 2019 - Feb 2020)</time_frame>
    <description>Score on the Implicit Personality Theory Questionnaire. This is a three-item measure that uses a 6-point Likert scale that ranges from strongly agree to strongly disagree to measure the extent individuals believe one's personality can change. The score of each item will be averaged to create a single score (minimum=1, maximum=6) such that higher values will be associated with higher levels of entity beliefs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implicit theory of a person (general)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months (Oct 2019 - Feb 2020)</time_frame>
    <description>Score on the Implicit Person Measure. This is a three item measure with a 6-point Likert scale ranging from strongly agree to strongly disagree. Scores on each item will be averaged to create a single score (minimum=1, maximum=6), and higher average scores will be associated with more entity beliefs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">576</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Happiness</condition>
  <condition>Life Satisfaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Growth Mindset of Personality</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Growth Mindset of Athletic Ability</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Growth mindset of personality educational intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a brief online educational intervention that teaches growth mindset of personality. The intervention includes pictures, text, videos, and questions administered through Qualtrics survey software.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Growth Mindset of Personality</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Growth mindset of athletic ability educational intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a brief online educational intervention that teaches growth mindset of athletic ability. The intervention includes pictures, text, videos, and questions administered through Qualtrics survey software.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Growth Mindset of Athletic Ability</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A student at one of the recruited schools in grade 9 or 12

          -  Age 13-18 years

          -  Able to read and write fluently in English

          -  Have parent/guardian consent, and provide participant consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not a registered student at one of the recruited schools

          -  Less than 13 or more than 18 years old

          -  Unable to read and write fluently in English

          -  Does not have parent/guardian consent or does not consent to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margaret Lumley, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Guelph</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Guelph</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guelph</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N1G 2W1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abela, J. R. Z., &amp; Hankin, B. L. (2008). Depression in children and adolescents: Causes, treatment, and prevention. In J. R. Z. Abela &amp; B. L. Hankin (Eds.), Handbook of depression in children and adolescents (pp. 3-5). New York, NY, US: The Guilford Press.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abramson, L. Y., Metalsky, G. I., &amp; Alloy, L. B. (1989). Hopelessness depression: A theory-based subtype of depression. Psychological review, 96(2), 358.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abramson LY, Seligman ME, Teasdale JD. Learned helplessness in humans: critique and reformulation. J Abnorm Psychol. 1978 Feb;87(1):49-74.</citation>
    <PMID>649856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dweck, C. S., Chiu, C. Y., &amp; Hong, Y. Y. (1995). Implicit theories and their role in judgments and reactions: A word from two perspectives. Psychological inquiry, 6(4), 267-285.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dweck, C. S., &amp; Leggett, E. L. (1988). A social-cognitive approach to motivation and personality. Psychological review, 95(2), 256.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furlong, M. J., Gilman, R., &amp; Huebner, E. S. (2014). Handbook of Positive Psychology in Schools, 2nd Ed New York. NY: Taylor &amp; Francis.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenberg MT, Weissberg RP, O'Brien MU, Zins JE, Fredericks L, Resnik H, Elias MJ. Enhancing school-based prevention and youth development through coordinated social, emotional, and academic learning. Am Psychol. 2003 Jun-Jul;58(6-7):466-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12971193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hankin BL, Abramson LY, Moffitt TE, Silva PA, McGee R, Angell KE. Development of depression from preadolescence to young adulthood: emerging gender differences in a 10-year longitudinal study. J Abnorm Psychol. 1998 Feb;107(1):128-40.</citation>
    <PMID>9505045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong, Y. Y., Chiu, C. Y., Dweck, C. S., Lin, D. M. S., &amp; Wan, W. (1999). Implicit theories, attributions, and coping: A meaning system approach. Journal of Personality and Social psychology, 77(3), 588.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masten, A., Herbers, J., Cutuli, J., &amp; Lafavor, T. (2008). Promoting competence and resilience in the school context. Professional School Counseling, 12(2), 76-84.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merikangas KR, He JP, Burstein M, Swanson SA, Avenevoli S, Cui L, Benjet C, Georgiades K, Swendsen J. Lifetime prevalence of mental disorders in U.S. adolescents: results from the National Comorbidity Survey Replication--Adolescent Supplement (NCS-A). J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2010 Oct;49(10):980-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jaac.2010.05.017. Epub 2010 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>20855043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petersen AC, Compas BE, Brooks-Gunn J, Stemmler M, Ey S, Grant KE. Depression in adolescence. Am Psychol. 1993 Feb;48(2):155-68. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8442570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rindfuss RR. The young adult years: diversity, structural change, and fertility. Demography. 1991 Nov;28(4):493-512. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1769399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seligman, M. E., Ernst, R. M., Gillham, J., Reivich, K., &amp; Linkins, M. (2009). Positive education: Positive psychology and classroom interventions. Oxford review of education, 35(3), 293-311.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeager, D. S., &amp; Dweck, C. S. (2012). Mindsets that promote resilience: When students believe that personal characteristics can be developed. Educational psychologist, 47(4), 302-314.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Blackwell LS, Trzesniewski KH, Dweck CS. Implicit theories of intelligence predict achievement across an adolescent transition: a longitudinal study and an intervention. Child Dev. 2007 Jan-Feb;78(1):246-63.</citation>
    <PMID>17328703</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burnette JL, Russell MV, Hoyt CL, Orvidas K, Widman L. An online growth mindset intervention in a sample of rural adolescent girls. Br J Educ Psychol. 2018 Sep;88(3):428-445. doi: 10.1111/bjep.12192. Epub 2017 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>28960257</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Miu, A. S., &amp; Yeager, D. S. (2015). Preventing symptoms of depression by teaching adolescents that people can change: Effects of a brief incremental theory of personality intervention at 9-month follow-up. Clinical Psychological Science, 3(5), 726-743.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Guelph</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Margaret Lumley</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Growth mindset</keyword>
  <keyword>Implicit theory</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescence</keyword>
  <keyword>Mental Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Well-being</keyword>
  <keyword>students</keyword>
  <keyword>Secondary Schools</keyword>
  <keyword>Educational intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share individual participant data as this has not been approved by our Research Ethics Board</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

