<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04136782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Shengjing-LCG005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04136782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Albumin-bound Paclitaxel and Carboplatin Versus Epirubicin and Docetaxel for Triple-negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Albumin-bound Paclitaxel Combined With Carboplatin Versus Epirubicin Combined With Docetaxel as Neoadjuvant Therapy for Triple-negative Breast Cancer: a Multicenter Randomized Controlled Phase IV Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shengjing Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shengjing Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the efficacy of albumin-bound paclitaxel combined with carboplatin versus
      epirubicin combined with docetaxel as neoadjuvant therapy for triple-negative breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Triple-negative breast cancer is named because of lack of expression of estrogen receptor,
      progesterone receptor, and proto-oncogene HER2. This type of breast cancer is highly
      heterogeneous, is more likely to recur locally and develop distant metastasis, and has high
      invasiveness and low survival rate. Because both endocrine therapy and targeted therapy are
      ineffective for triple-negative breast cancer, so the main currently available treatment is
      chemotherapy. Some patients may choose anti-angiogenic therapy. The prognosis of
      triple-negative breast cancer is worse than that of other types of breast cancer due to fewer
      treatment options. Guidelines and Specifications for Diagnosis and Treatment of Breast Cancer
      (2017 edition) compiled by Committee of Breast Cancer Society of Chinese Anti-Cancer
      Association suggest that neoadjuvant therapy should be recommended for patients with
      large-sized tumors (maximum diameter greater than 5 cm), axillary lymph node metastasis,
      human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER-2) positive, triple-negative breast cancer, and
      breast-conserving intention. The guidelines also suggest that neoadjuvant therapy for
      triple-negative breast cancer should apply anthracyclines and taxanes. Guidelines of Chinese
      Society of Clinical Oncology (CSCO) Breast Cancer 2018.V1 propose that the treatment regimen
      of triple-negative breast cancer should apply anthracyclines and taxanes. The treatment
      regimens of taxanes, anthracyclines, and cyclophosphamides in combination (1A) or taxanes
      combined with anthracyclines (2A) are strongly recommended. In 2015, St Gallen recommended
      anthracyclines and taxanes as the main chemotherapeutic drugs for triple-negative breast
      cancer. However, the pathologic complete remission (pCR) rate of paclitaxel combined with
      anthracycline as neoadjuvant therapy was still less than 50%. In the GALGB40603 study, the
      pCR rate of breast and axillary lymph nodes increased from 41% to 54% with carboplatin based
      on standard chemotherapeutic drugs anthracycline combined with taxanes. The Gepar Sixto-GBG
      66 study also suggested that carboplatin could increase the pCR rate in triple-negative
      breast cancer patients. Compared with other dosage forms of paclitaxel, albumin-bound
      paclitaxel can produce higher paclitaxel concentration in local tumors, and the injection
      time is shorter. At present, the drug has been approved by the Food and Drug Administration
      of the United States for adjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer with metastasis or
      recurrence within 6 months that fails to respond to combined chemotherapy. However, little is
      currently reported on albumin-bound paclitaxel combined with carboplatin versus anthracycline
      combined with paclitaxel in China. A multicenter randomized controlled phase IV clinical
      trial will be conducted to investigate the efficacy of albumin-bound paclitaxel combined with
      carboplatin versus epirubicin combined with docetaxel as neoadjuvant therapy for
      triple-negative breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic complete remission rate</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Pathologic complete remission will be evaluated 5 years after treatment according to the regression of tumors. Tumor regression will be assessed according to RECIST 1.1. Complete remission (CR)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast-conserving rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients with breast conservation after 6 months of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of osteoporosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for 5 successive years</time_frame>
    <description>Osteoporosis is considered to be present when a patient's bone density or bone mineral content is more than 2.5 standard deviations below the mean value of normal adult bone density. Patients will be screened for osteoporosis once every 6 months for 5 successive years. Incidence of osteoporosis = number of patients developing osteoporosis/total number of patients ×100%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of bone-related events</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for 5 successive years</time_frame>
    <description>Bone pain, fracture and other bone related events. Patients will be screened for bone-related events once every 6 months for 5 successive years. Incidence of bone-related events = number of patients having bone-related events/total number of patients × 100%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of other distant organ metastasis related events</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for 5 successive years</time_frame>
    <description>Metastasis to other distant organs such as the lung, liver, bone marrow, brain, and ovary. Patients will be screened for other distant organ metastasis related events once every 6 months for 5 successive years. Incidence of other distant organ metastasis related events = number of patients having other distant organ metastasis related events/total number of patients × 100%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 years after disease onset.</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the start of the enrollment to the recurrence of the disease or the death of the patient due to disease progression. DFS will be analyzed according to the specific situation within 5 years after disease onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 years after disease onset.</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the start of the enrollment to the death of the patient: OS will be analyzed according to the specific situation within 5 years after disease onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>in 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Any untoward medical occurrence in a patient and which does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trial group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>55 cases of triple-negative breast cancer will be assigned into a trial group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>55 cases of triple-negative breast cancer will be assigned into a control group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albumin-bound paclitaxel combined with carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Albumin-bound paclitaxel combined with carboplatin: Albumin-bound paclitaxel (Abraxis BioScience, LLC., Mclrose Park, IL, USA; certificate number: H20091059) will be intravenously administered at 125 mg/m2 for 30 minutes on days 1 and 8 of each 21-day session of treatment. There will be six 21-day sessions of treatment. At the same time, carboplatin (Qilu Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Jinan, Shandong Province, China; National Drug Approval Number: H20020181) will be intravenously administered at AUC = 2 mg•min/mL for 120 minutes on days 1 and 8 of each 21-day session of treatment. Carboplatin must be hydrated for 3 days before use to prevent nephrotoxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Trial group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Albumin-bound paclitaxel+carboplatin group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epirubicin combined with docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Epirubicin (Pfizer Pharmaceutical (Wuxi) Co., Ltd., China; National Drug Approval Number: H20000496) will be intravenously administered at 90 mg/m2 for 120 minutes on day 1 of each 21-day session of treatment. At the same time, docetaxel (Sanofi-aventis Deutschland GmbH, Frankfurt am Main, Germany; National Drug Approval Number: J20150083) will be intravenously administered at 75 mg/m2 for 120 minutes. Drug administration will be performed once every other 3 weeks for four times.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epirubicin+docetaxel group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients developing breast cancer as confirmed by X-ray examination, cancer tissue
             negative for estrogen receptor, progesterone receptor and HER2, and tumor stage
             II-III;

          -  estimated survival &gt; 3 months;

          -  presence of clinically measurable lesions;

          -  Karnofsky functional status score ≥ 70;

          -  normal routine blood test results, normal liver and kidney function, and near normal
             electrocardiographic manifestations;

          -  age at 18-70 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  stage IV breast cancer patients with bone metastasis or other distant metastasis;

          -  severe renal insufficiency;

          -  older adult patients with severe organic diseases such as heart and lung diseases, who
             are not estimated to be able to tolerate chemotherapy;

          -  those who have received antineoplastic therapy;

          -  those who have received neoadjuvant chemotherapy but fail in 2 cycles of neoadjuvant
             chemotherapy and switch to other regimens or terminate chemotherapy;

          -  those with history of other malignant tumors;

          -  those with severe heart, liver, and kidney organ dysfunction or poor health who cannot
             tolerate chemotherapy, or those who cannot tolerate chemotherapy and switch to other
             therapeutic regimens;

          -  those with mental and nervous system diseases who cannot comply with treatment;

          -  those with dexamethasone intolerance or those who are highly allergic to any drug in
             neoadjuvant chemotherapy;

          -  pregnant or lactating women;

          -  those who are participating in other trials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Caigang Liu, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shengjing Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xi Gu, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+86 18940255116</phone>
    <email>jadegx@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Hospital Affiliated to Harbin Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harbin</city>
        <state>Heilongjiang</state>
        <zip>150081</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xuesong Chen</last_name>
      <phone>+8615804500816</phone>
      <email>cxs1978@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xuesong Chen</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Hospital of Jilin University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changchun</city>
        <state>Jilin</state>
        <zip>130041</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yingchao Zhang</last_name>
      <email>zhang_yc@jlu.edu.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yingchao Zhang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dalian Municipal Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dalian</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>116033</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wenbin Guo</last_name>
      <phone>+8613079850586</phone>
      <email>drguowb@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wenbin Guo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Panjin Liaohe Oilfield Gem Flower Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Panjin</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>124010</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hongbin Han</last_name>
      <phone>+8613704236001</phone>
      <email>rose_030201@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hongbin Han</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shengjing Hospital of China Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110004</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Caigang Liu</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18940254967</phone>
      <email>liucg@sj-hospital.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rong Wu</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18940251156</phone>
      <email>wur@sj-hospital.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Caigang Liu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rong Wu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Fourth Affiliated Hospital of China Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110032</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wei Tu</last_name>
      <phone>+8618900913000</phone>
      <email>cmu4htw@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wei Tu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liaoning Cancer Hospital &amp; Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110042</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hong Xu</last_name>
      <phone>+8618900917779</phone>
      <email>xh4015@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hong Xu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shengjing Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Caigang Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adjuvant chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>paclitaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>albumin-bound paclitaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>carboplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>docetaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>epirubicin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epirubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

