<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04131829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2000023688</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH116038-01A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1K24MH121571-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04131829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Network Changes Accompanying and Predicting Responses to Pharmacotherapy in OCD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brain Network Changes Accompanying and Predicting Responses to Pharmacotherapy in OCD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed randomized, double-blind research study will use functional magnetic resonance
      neuroimaging using state-of-the-art HCP acquisition protocols and analytic pipelines, to
      identify predictors and correlates of response to an accepted first-line pharmacological
      treatment for obsessive-compulsive disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study intends to recruit 2 groups:

        1. Matched healthy control participants will be imaged with one fMRI at baseline as a
           no-treatment comparison group; and

        2. a randomized, double-blind group of unmedicated OCD participants who will be assigned to
           begin either immediate or placebo-delayed treatment, and who will be imaged with fMRIs
           at baseline and over the course of treatment with a selective serotonin reuptake
           inhibitor (SSRI), fluoxetine.

      Hypothesis-driven analyses and exploratory analyses will be performed in parallel.

      This study will address the following Specific Aims:

        1. Identification of neural dysconnectivity associated with OCD symptomatology.

        2. Characterizing neural markers of clinical response to SSRI pharmacotherapy.

        3. Mapping neural predictors of clinical response to pharmacotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>80 OCD patients and 40 healthy participants matched on demographics will be recruited and asked to complete Structural (sMRI) and Functional (fMRI) Magnetic Resonance Imaging. Patients with OCD will be randomized to immediate monotherapy or 6-week placebo-delayed monotherapy, with fluoxetine.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Obsessive-compulsive severity change</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Yale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS);72,73 -This is a checklist and Clinician administered - 10 item severity scale, from none to extreme. Total severity score range is 0 to 40. This will be presented as % improvement in Y-BOCS as a continuous measure of treatment response, rather than an artificially dichotomized measure of 'response', in all analyses. This the primary outcome measure of change across the study treatment and scans.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tic severity change</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Yale Global Tic Severity Scale (YGTSS) will be used to measure Tic severity. It is a clinician administered instrument with a score from 0 to 25- 25 being the most severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obsessive-compulsive Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Obsessive Compulsive Inventory-Revised (OCI-R);81 18 items scored 0 to 4, combined into 6 subscales (of 3 items each) and a total score (up to 72).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI);83 21 item self report on a 4 point Likert scale - 0 (not at all) to 3 (severely).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obsessive-compulsive concerns</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Dimensional Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (DOCS);84 20 questions, asks about 4 categories of obsessive-compulsive concerns (each consists of 5 items scored on a Likert scale of 0-no symptoms to 4 - extreme symptoms) over the previous month.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beliefs Conviction and Insight</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Brown Assessment of Beliefs Scale (BABS);85 clinician rated, semi-structured measure of degree of conviction and insight concerning beliefs in 7 areas, covering the past week, and scored from 0 to 4 (least to most severe), with the total score based on first 6 items with a range of 0 to 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Magical ideation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Magical Ideation Scale (MIS);86 30 item true / false scale, assessing erroneous beliefs based on magical thinking.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensory phenomena</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>University of São Paulo Sensory Phenomena Scale (USP-SPS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>&quot;Not Just Right&quot; experiences and sensations in OCD</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Not Just Right Experiences Questionnaire Revised (INC).88 19 Questions: Rate 10 NJR Experiences; Choose most recent one; Identify how long ago it occurred; then complete 7 dimensional ratings of that NJRE: frequency, intensity, immediate distress, delayed distress, rumination, urge to respond, and responsibility to do something about the NJRE, from 1 (absence) to 7 (extreme level /or within the past day).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The healthy control group will be an age matched sample of unmedicated healthy adults who will be recruited and imaged once at baseline and the data compared with that of OCD subjects at baseline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OCD Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The OCD group will comprise of unmedicated individuals with clinically significant OCD symptoms. OCD Subjects will be randomized, double-blind, to receive immediate or delayed (by 6 weeks as a placebo lead-in) pharmacotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluoxetine - immediate treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Following the Baseline assessment, OCD subjects will be randomized to receive either immediate fluoxetine monotherapy or delayed fluoxetine, after a 6-week placebo lead-in.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OCD Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fluoxetine, prozac</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluoxetine - delayed treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Following the Baseline assessment, OCD subjects will be randomized to receive either immediate fluoxetine monotherapy or delayed fluoxetine, after a 6-week placebo lead-in.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OCD Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fluoxetine, prozac</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria for all groups will include: (i) Adults, Men and women will be
             included, in a 1:1 ratio; and efforts will be made to recruit racial and ethnic
             subgroups. Groups will be further matched on age, handedness; and later, in analysis,
             on educational status and smoking history.

        (ii) signed informed consent, approved by the Yale Human Investigations Committee; and
        (iii) ability and willingness to participate in all study procedures, including clinical
        assessments and fMRI scans.

          -  Additional inclusion criteria:

          -  OCD Participants:

             (i) a DSM diagnosis of OCD, established as detailed above; (ii) a baseline Y-BOCS of
             ≥16; (iii) no current psychoactive medication, with the exception of the occasional
             use of a PRN medication for sleep; (iv) treatment seeking, and clinically appropriate
             for fluoxetine pharmacotherapy; (v) for women of childbearing potential, not pregnant
             or intending to become pregnant, and willing to use reliable birth control over the
             course of the study, either prescribed contraceptive (oral contraceptive, injectable,
             or implant) or one barrier method (e.g. diaphragm with spermicide, intrauterine
             device, cervical cap). Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum
             pregnancy test at screening and negative urine pregnancy tests at the study baseline
             and on each scan day appointment prior to the MRI scan.

          -  Healthy Control Participants:

             (i) no current DSM diagnosis (by clinician interview confirmed by SCID or MINI); (ii)
             no documented or clinically suspected family history in a first- or second- degree
             relative of OCD, Tourette syndrome, hoarding disorder, body dysmorphic disorder, or a
             compulsive grooming disorder.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria for all groups will include:

             (i) any unstable medical, psychiatric, or neurological condition (including active or
             otherwise problematic suicidality) that may necessitate urgent treatment; (ii) any
             substance use disorder within the past 6 months; (iii) use of psychotropic medications
             within the past 8 weeks, with the exception of occasional use of a sleep aid or
             analgesic; (iv) use of an as-needed sleep aid or prescription analgesic within 3 days
             of the scan; (v) any history of a primary psychotic disorder or of mania; (vi) any
             evidence of substance use on urine toxicology testing; (vii) any major neurological
             disease or history of major head trauma, including concussion with extended loss of
             consciousness; (viii) pregnancy; (ix) any metal in the body or other contraindication
             to MRI scanning; (x) severe claustrophobia, back pain, or other condition that may
             make an extended MR scan difficult or lead to excessive movement during the scan.

          -  Additional exclusion criteria:

          -  OCD Participants:

             (i) past allergy or adverse reaction to fluoxetine or another SSRI, or other clinical
             contraindication to fluoxetine pharmacotherapy; (ii) documented nonresponse to a past
             trial of fluoxetine of appropriate dose (≥40 mg/dy) and duration (≥12 weeks).

        (iii) Patients taking Coumadin or Monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) will be excluded
        from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Pittenger, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Professor of Psychiatry; Director, Yale OCD Research Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yale OCD Research Clinic</last_name>
    <phone>1-855-623-9253</phone>
    <email>ocd.research@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephen Kichuk, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>203-974-7534</phone>
    <email>stephen.kichuk@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale OCD Research Clinic - CMHC/CNRU, 34 Park ST</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06519</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Baker, BA</last_name>
      <phone>855-623-9253</phone>
      <email>ocd.research@yale.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stephen Kichuk, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>203-974-7534</phone>
      <email>stephen.kichuk@yale.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Compulsive Personality Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluoxetine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

