<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04132635</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QK-MP-201903</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04132635</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial to Evaluate the Combination Efficacy of Artificial Dermis and Growth Factor in Chronic Wounds Ulcer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-label, Multicenter Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Combination Efficacy of Double-layer Artificial Dermis and Growth Factor in the Treatment of Chronic Wounds Ulcer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Double layer artificial dermis repair material has been widely used in scar plastic, burn,
      trauma, chronic wounds and other aspects of wound repair and reconstruction. In the course of
      clinical application, we found that for chronic wounds, the combination of artificial dermis
      and growth factor can shorten the wound healing cycle, and have a positive impact on the
      economy and psychology of patients. In order to verify this effect, we plan to carry out this
      study to evaluate whether double-layer artificial dermis repair material combined with growth
      factor treatment can improve wound closure rate and shorten closure cycle compared with
      single artificial dermis for chronic wound.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>average closure time</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of the treatment period to the time when the survival rate of skin grafting reaches 100% or 12 weeks visit (whichever comes first), record the average time when all the subjects who reach the complete closure of the wound</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total wound closure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning of the treatment period to the survival rate of skin grafting reaching 100% or 12 weeks visit (whichever comes first), record the total number of patients who have reached the complete closure of the wound during this period</time_frame>
    <description>The total wound closure rate = (the number of patients who achieved complete wound closure within 12 weeks / the total number of patients in the group) * 100%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Wound</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>artificial dermis with growth factor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>artificial dermis only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>artificial dermis</intervention_name>
    <description>artificial dermis will be used after fully debridement of the wound</description>
    <arm_group_label>artificial dermis only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>artificial dermis with growth factor</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>growth factor</intervention_name>
    <description>growth factor</description>
    <arm_group_label>artificial dermis with growth factor</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients diagnosed as chronic wounds ulcer;

          2. The affected limb has sufficient blood perfusion. The ankle brachial index was
             0.65-1.3, or the partial pressure of oxygen was more than 40 mmHg, or Doppler
             ultrasound showed enough blood flow.

          3. After debridement, the distance between the wound and the edge of other ulcers was
             &gt;2cm.

          4. After debridement, the area of exposed bone or tendon was &gt;4cm2.

          5. The wound was completely debridement without obvious necrosis, infection control or
             osteomyelitis control.

          6. The duration of ulcer wound was at least 30 days.

          7. Sign the informed consent voluntarily.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Poor control of diabetes (fasting blood glucose ≥ 8.0mmol/l, HbA1c ≥ 12%);

          2. The researchers think that there are factors affecting wound healing, such as the use
             of corticosteroids, immunosuppressants and other drugs, chemotherapy or radiotherapy
             within one year.

          3. To receive or plan to receive drugs or treatment, the researchers believe that these
             drugs or treatment will interfere with or affect the speed and quality of wound
             healing;

          4. Unstable Charcot's foot or Charcot's joint disease with bone protrusion;

          5. Patients with severe lymphedema, coagulation disorders, autoimmune diseases,
             cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, and severe hepatopulmonary and renal
             diseases;

          6. Those who have received hyperbaric oxygen treatment within 5 days before enrollment,
             or who have received or plan to receive growth factor, tissue-engineered skin or other
             skin substitutes treatment within 30 days;

          7. Those who have participated in or are participating in other clinical studies within
             30 days before screening;

          8. Pregnant, or lactating women;

          9. Poor general condition or other conditions not suitable for the use of double-layer
             artificial leather repair materials;

         10. Be allergic to collagen or chondroitin sulfate;

         11. Other cases that researchers think are not suitable for the participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mitogens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

