<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04134741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PopeJohnPaulIIStateSchHigherEd</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04134741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Effectiveness of Neuromuscular Training in Treatment of Lumbar Spine in Football Players</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Effectiveness of Neuromuscular Training According to the Concept of Kinetic Control in Treatment of Lumbar Spine and Knee Pain and in Reduction of Risk of Injury in Female Football Players</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The project aims to assess the effectiveness of neuromuscular training according to the
      concept of Kinetic Control (KC) in prevention and treatment of lumbar spine and knee pain and
      in reduction of risk of injury in female football players.

      The study was designed as single-blind Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) and conducted on a
      group of 18 female football players from University Club of the Academic Sports Association
      of Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska. Participants were
      randomly divided into two 9-person groups: A - used standard training and neuromuscular
      training (Kinetic Control) and B - used only standard training.

      Main hypothesis:

      The application of neuromuscular therapy (KC) reduces the risk of injuries and pain of the
      lumbar spine and the knee and improves the static and dynamic balance.

      Research questions:

        1. Will the application of the KC training reduce the risk and frequency of spine and knee
           injuries in females football players?

        2. Will the KC training lead to reduction of the intensity of lumbar spine and knee pain?

        3. Will the application of the KC training lead to increase in the torque strength of knee
           flexors and extensors and improved stability of the knee?

        4. Will the application of the neuromuscular training (KC) lead to reduction of the
           disability level and improved functional level?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The research was conducted upon acquiring an approval of the Bioethical Commission of Pope
      John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska, no. 3/2018.

      The study was designed as single-blind Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) and conducted on a
      group of 18 female football players from University Club of the Academic Sports Association
      of Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska. Participants were
      randomly divided into two 9-person groups: A - used standard training and neuromuscular
      training (Kinetic Control) and B - used only standard training.

      None of the physiotherapists were personally involved in the preparation and the manner of
      performing the test. Before commencing the tests, each participant was familiarised with
      their course, expressed their informed written consent for the participation and random
      assignment to the specified tested group.

      The random placement was performed with the use of computer software.

      The players participate in two training cycles over a year: from July to December and from
      January to June. Therefore, the above mentioned training regime will be performed twice.

      A medical interview takes place before the training cycle. Physical examination, back pain
      functional scale (BPFS) and tests on the dynamographic platform will be performed two times -
      before and after each season.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The players were placed at random in the studied groups, 9 participants in each group: A - group with additional Kinetic Control neuromuscular training; and B - group with standard training.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>None of the physiotherapists were personally involved in the preparation and the manner of performing the test.
The random placement was performed with the use of computer software.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analogue scale of pain (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Visual analogue scale of pain (VAS) was carried out at the beginning of each season and after 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analogue scale of pain (VAS) evaluates intensity of pain in the scale from 0 to 10. Maximum score means the highest level of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Laitinen's pain questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Modified Laitinen's pain questionnaire was carried out at the beginning of each season and after 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Laitinen's pain questionnaire took into account four indicators evaluated in the scale from 0 to 4: the intensity of pain, the frequency of its occurrence, the use of analgesic medications and limitation of the participant's motor activity. A research participant could have been granted from 0 to 16 points, the maximum score means the highest level of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stratford's back pain functional scale (BPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Stratford's back pain functional scale (BPFS) was carried out at the beginning of each season and after 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>In Stratford's scale (BFPS), the research participants assessed twelve actions related to everyday life activity in the scale from 0 to 5. The result fell within a range from 0 to 60 points, where the higher final result, the lower level of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single leg small knee bend test</measure>
    <time_frame>Single leg small knee bend test was carried out at the beginning of each season and after 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test is performed in the standing position with feet a hip distance apart and parallel inner sides. The participant is then asked to transfer their body weight on one leg and raise the other leg over the ground. The body weight should be placed over the metatarsus. The participant is then asked to slightly bend the knee whilst keeping the heel on the ground. A photo is taken with a camera. Subsequently, computer software is used to determine the axis of the bent limb. The participant undergoes the test twice. If the test is not performed properly the first time, the participant is instructed how to perform the movement and the test is repeated.
Proper test performance for the first time scores 2 points. Proper test performance after the guidance of the physical therapist scores 1 point and improper test performance twice scores 0 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tests on the GAMMA dynamometric platform</measure>
    <time_frame>Tests on the GAMMA dynamometric platform were carried out at the beginning of each season and after 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the load of lower limbs in the standing position for 30 seconds with eyes open. 1-1.15 was assumed as the proper load distribution ratio.
Assessment of the load of lower limbs in the standing position for 30 seconds with eyes closed. 1-1.15 was assumed as the proper load distribution ratio.
Assessment of the load of lower limbs in the squat test. The platform marks the load of lower limbs in three phases - standing up, stabilisation and squatting. 1-1.15 was assumed as the proper load distribution ratio in each phase.
Assessment of the load of lower limbs in the jumping test. The platform marks the load of lower limbs in three phases - jumping up, landing and stabilisation. 1-1.15 was assumed as the proper load distribution ratio in each phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of muscle force torque on a UPR-02A chair</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurement of muscle force torque on a UPR-02A chair were carried out at the beginning of each season and after 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test was performed under isometric conditions and included two measurements of each muscle group, for both the left and the right lower limb. The tested limb was stabilised at the 30-degree bend at the knee in order to measure the flexors and at the 60-degree bend in order to measure the extensors, assuming the 0 degree angle as full extension at the knee. In addition, the torso and distal thighs were stabilised with a belt. During the test, upper limbs were crossed on the chest. The axis of the torque measuring device was placed at the level of the knee joint gap (joint rotation axis). The measurements were taken in the following sequence: extension of the right limb, flexion of the right limb, extension of the left limb and flexion of the left limb.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Injury Leg</condition>
  <condition>Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Sport Injury</condition>
  <condition>Training Group, Sensitivity</condition>
  <condition>Prevention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kinetic Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The players participated in the classic training and for 4 weeks (3 times a week) underwent the Kinetic Control neuromuscular training with assistance of a physical therapist.
The duration of one training was 20-30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional Training Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Players participated in the classic training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kinetic Control</intervention_name>
    <description>The Kinetic Control training included a functional examination of motor disorders and individual training. The KC training included active exercises, active exercises with torso muscle resistance and exercises involving lower limbs.
The duration of one training was 20-30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kinetic Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neuromuscular training</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  female players not taking nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) for at least a
             week before the start of the study,

          -  written consent for the participation in the study.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  female players with acute inflammation (neuralgia) and massive intervertebral disk
             herniation requiring a surgery,

          -  female players who suffered from a lumbar spine and/or knee injury up to 6 months
             before the start of the study,

          -  female players with acute knee inflammation and after knee surgeries.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kamil Zaworski, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anna Kręgiel, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Krystyna Gawlik, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joanna Baj-Korpak, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pope John Paul II State School of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pope John Paul II State School Of Higher Education in Biała Podlaska</name>
      <address>
        <city>Biała Podlaska</city>
        <zip>21-500</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Poland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>soccer</keyword>
  <keyword>football</keyword>
  <keyword>female</keyword>
  <keyword>sport injury</keyword>
  <keyword>kinetic control</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Athletic Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

