<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04133532</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCMBB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04133532</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Metoprolol in Post Alcohol Septal Ablation Patients With Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Metoprolol in Post Alcohol Septal Ablation Patients With Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Motol</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Motol</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this trial, the investigators will assess the effect of metoprolol in patients with
      hypertrophic cardiomyopathy who underwent alcohol septal ablation. The investigators will
      evaluate the quality of life, exercise tolerance, echocardiographic parameters and laboratory
      marker of heart failure and myocardial injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this trial, the investigators will assess the effect of metoprolol in patients with
      hypertrophic cardiomyopathy who underwent alcohol septal ablation.

      The investigators will evaluate the quality of life, exercise tolerance, echocardiographic
      parameters and laboratory marker of heart failure and myocardial injury.

      The investigators will enroll 50 patients that will meet all the inclusion criteria and will
      agree to participate in the trial. In patients with preceding beta-blocker medication, it
      will be discontinued and a washout period of one month will be provided. The investigators
      will assess baseline characteristics and then divide patients randomly into two arms based on
      their date of birth (even/odd days of the month).

      Arm A will be given metoprolol 50 mg daily for three months, after this period the effect
      will be evaluated and metoprolol discontinued. A month-long washout period will follow and
      after an additional three months without metoprolol medication, patients will be reevaluated.

      Arm B will be without metoprolol for three months and will be evaluated thereafter. Then the
      patients will be given metoprolol 50 mg daily for three months followed by a reevaluation.

      The investigators will evaluate the effect of metoprolol by multiple methods at the end of
      the 5th and 9th months of the trial. Quality of life will be assessed by a questionnaire (The
      Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire), exercise tolerance by a spiroergometry (VO2 max).
      A conventional echocardiographic examination and an examination focused on exercise-induced
      left ventricular outflow tract obstruction will be performed. The investigators will also
      measure NTproBNP from a blood sample as a laboratory marker of heart failure and high
      sensitive troponin as a marker of myocardial injury.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>We will enroll 50 patients and divide them into two arms. Initially, arm A will be given metoprolol and arm B will not. We will evaluate the two groups after a sufficient time period (three months) and after that, patients will cross-over to the other treatment strategy for three months followed by a final evaluation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in exercise tolerance with and without metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, after three months of metoprolol medication, after three months without metoprolol medication</time_frame>
    <description>VO2max during bicycle ergometer exercise test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of quality of life with and without metoprolol: The Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>After three months of metoprolol medication, after three months without metoprolol medication</time_frame>
    <description>The Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire, score 0-100 (higher score means better outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of concentration of biomarker of heart failure with and without metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>After three months of metoprolol medication, after three months without metoprolol medication</time_frame>
    <description>N-Terminal Pro-Brain Natriuretic Peptide concentration in blood sample</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of concentration of a biomarker of myocardial injury with and without metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>After three months of metoprolol medication, after three months without metoprolol medication</time_frame>
    <description>High sensitivity troponin concentration in blood sample</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in exercise induced pressure gradient in left ventricular outflow tract with and without metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>After three months of metoprolol medication, after three months without metoprolol medication</time_frame>
    <description>mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in left ventricular diastolic function at rest with and without metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>After three months of metoprolol medication, after three months without metoprolol medication</time_frame>
    <description>Echocardiographic parameters of the transmitral flow and tissue Doppler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>metoprolol-no metoprolol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After a washout period of one month following discontinuation of preceding beta-blocker medication patients will be given metoprolol 50 mg daily. The effect will be evaluated after three months of treatment. After that, another one-month washout period will commence followed by three months without metoprolol medication. Then, a final reevaluation will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>no metoprolol-metoprol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After a one-month washout period following discontinuation of preceding beta-blocker medication patients will continue another three months without a metoprolol medication. After that, an evaluation will be performed. Then they will be given metoprolol 50 mg daily for three months followed by a reevaluation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metoprolol</intervention_name>
    <description>metoprolol 50 mg daily for three months</description>
    <arm_group_label>metoprolol-no metoprolol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>no metoprolol-metoprol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients post alcohol septal ablation

          -  Pressure gradient in left ventricular outflow tract &lt;30 mmHg

          -  Written consent to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of atrial fibrillation

          -  Symptoms of Class III or IV of New York Heart Association functional classification

          -  Permanent pacemaker implant

          -  Age above 75
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Josef Veselka, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Motol University Hospital, Department of Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hana Hnátová, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00420603574669</phone>
    <email>hanka.hnat@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Motol University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha</city>
        <state>Czech Republic</state>
        <zip>15000</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>224431111</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gersh BJ, Maron BJ, Bonow RO, Dearani JA, Fifer MA, Link MS, Naidu SS, Nishimura RA, Ommen SR, Rakowski H, Seidman CE, Towbin JA, Udelson JE, Yancy CW; American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines; American Association for Thoracic Surgery; American Society of Echocardiography; American Society of Nuclear Cardiology; Heart Failure Society of America; Heart Rhythm Society; Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions; Society of Thoracic Surgeons. 2011 ACCF/AHA guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines. Circulation. 2011 Dec 13;124(24):e783-831. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0b013e318223e2bd. Epub 2011 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22068434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maron BJ, McKenna WJ, Danielson GK, Kappenberger LJ, Kuhn HJ, Seidman CE, Shah PM, Spencer WH 3rd, Spirito P, Ten Cate FJ, Wigle ED; Task Force on Clinical Expert Consensus Documents. American College of Cardiology; Committee for Practice Guidelines. European Society of Cardiology. American College of Cardiology/European Society of Cardiology clinical expert consensus document on hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. A report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation Task Force on Clinical Expert Consensus Documents and the European Society of Cardiology Committee for Practice Guidelines. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 Nov 5;42(9):1687-713. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14607462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>HARRISON DC, BRAUNWALD E, GLICK G, MASON DT, CHIDSEY CA, ROSS J Jr. EFFECTS OF BETA ADRENERGIC BLOCKADE ON THE CIRCULATION WITH PARTICULAR REFERENCE TO OBSERVATIONS IN PATIENTS WITH HYPERTROPHIC SUBAORTIC STENOSIS. Circulation. 1964 Jan;29:84-98.</citation>
    <PMID>14105035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen LS, Braunwald E. Amelioration of angina pectoris in idiopathic hypertrophic subaortic stenosis with beta-adrenergic blockade. Circulation. 1967 May;35(5):847-51.</citation>
    <PMID>6067064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fananapazir L, Chang AC, Epstein SE, McAreavey D. Prognostic determinants in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Prospective evaluation of a therapeutic strategy based on clinical, Holter, hemodynamic, and electrophysiological findings. Circulation. 1992 Sep;86(3):730-40.</citation>
    <PMID>1516184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilligan DM, Chan WL, Joshi J, Clarke P, Fletcher A, Krikler S, Oakley CM. A double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trial of nadolol and verapamil in mild and moderately symptomatic hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1993 Jun;21(7):1672-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8496536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nistri S, Olivotto I, Maron MS, Ferrantini C, Coppini R, Grifoni C, Baldini K, Sgalambro A, Cecchi F, Maron BJ. β Blockers for prevention of exercise-induced left ventricular outflow tract obstruction in patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Am J Cardiol. 2012 Sep 1;110(5):715-9. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2012.04.051. Epub 2012 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22633205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fifer MA, Vlahakes GJ. Management of symptoms in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Circulation. 2008 Jan 22;117(3):429-39. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.694158. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18212300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desai MY, Bhonsale A, Patel P, Naji P, Smedira NG, Thamilarasan M, Lytle BW, Lever HM. Exercise echocardiography in asymptomatic HCM: exercise capacity, and not LV outflow tract gradient predicts long-term outcomes. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2014 Jan;7(1):26-36. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2013.08.010. Epub 2013 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24290569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital, Motol</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hana Hnátová</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>medical doctor, resident in cardiology department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>NTproBNP</keyword>
  <keyword>Left ventricular outflow tract obstruction</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Diastolic dysfunction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metoprolol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

