<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04139941</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8162-2/2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04139941</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation Study of HCV RDTs in Fresh Samples</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Diagnostic Accuracy Study of Rapid Diagnostic Tests (RDTs) Detecting Antibodies Against Hepatitis C Virus (HCV) in Freshly Collected Whole Blood, Plasma and Serum</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Foundation for Innovative New Diagnostics, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute of Tropical Medicine, Belgium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Foundation for Innovative New Diagnostics, Switzerland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the sensitivity and specificity performance of three Hepatitis C Virus
      (HCV) rapid diagnostic tests (RDTs) in freshly collected fingerstick whole blood, as well as
      serum and plasma (Premier Medical Corporation First Response HCV RDT; Beijing Wantai HCV RDT;
      AccessBio Care Start HCV under development). Performance is compared to the SD Bioline HCV
      RDT, as well as a composite reference standard, consisting of two enzyme Immunoassay and a
      line immunoassay.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection is a major public health burden, with an estimated 71
      million patients being infected globally. If undiagnosed, HCV infection can lead to severe
      liver damage, including hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). The World Health Organization (WHO)
      recently set a target to eliminate HCV by 2030. The first critical step in reaching this
      target is to accurately identify people infected with HCV. Globally, significant gaps remain
      in diagnosis of HCV, with four out of five people infected still unaware of their status,
      largely due to lack of access to testing services.

      In resource-limited settings (RLS), laboratory-based testing remains a mainstay for HCV
      screening and confirmatory testing. Such laboratory-based assays rely on transportation of
      temperature-sensitive samples from clinic sites to centralized laboratories, high-tech
      equipment and highly skilled laboratory technicians, limiting the scope of access to testing
      and resulting in long turn-around times for results. In recent years, new technologies have
      been developed to decentralize HCV screening and confirmatory testing using point-of-care
      (POC) assays to overcome these barriers and improve patient outcomes.

      Rapid diagnostic tests (RDT) for screening for HCV are affordable, accurate, easy to use by
      healthcare workers, and robust in field settings. Although a number of HCV RDTs are on the
      market, currently only two have received WHO pre-qualification (PQ) status, demonstrating
      their accuracy and reliability for use in the field in RLS. Data on a number of other RDTs
      indicate their suitability for use. More data is needed, however, in field settings for these
      HCV RDTs, to demonstrate their accuracy and quality in end-user studies and to provide
      evidence for WHO PQ approval.

      Based on the results of a recent FIND laboratory evaluation assessing the performance of 13
      HCV RDTs using archived plasma samples, we have selected three candidate HCV RDTs (&quot;study
      RDTs&quot;) for further evaluation in field settings (e.g. primary healthcare facilities). The
      performance of these RDTs measured in frozen plasma specimens indicated that they have a high
      potential to meet WHO PQ performance criteria in freshly collected samples. In addition, the
      manufacturers each demonstrate evidence of engagement to pursue both CE-mark status and the
      WHO PQ process, showing commitment to delivering quality-assured tests to the market.

      The data generated during this study will be used to inform national and international
      stakeholders on HCV RDT performance in field settings and shared with manufacturers to
      support the evidence package for WHO PQ and/or CE-marking.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity of HCV RDTs compared to a composite reference standard</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, on average 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>1.1 Point estimates of sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predicative values (with 95% confidence intervals) and Cohen's Kappa Coefficient (κ) of inter-rater agreement for each RDT, using a combination of two EIAs (Enzyme Immunoassay) and an LIA (Line immunoassay) as a composite reference standard for the detection of anti-HCV antibodies in fingerstick whole blood, EDTA plasma and serum.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity of HCV RDTs compared to an HCV RDT pre-qualified by WHO as reference standard</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, on average 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>2.1 Point estimates of sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predicative values (with 95% confidence intervals) and Cohen's Kappa Coefficient (κ) of inter-rater agreement for each RDT, using the WHO-PQ RDT as reference standard for the detection of anti-HCV antibodies in fingerstick whole blood, EDTA plasma and serum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operational characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, on average 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>2.2 Operational characteristics and usability of study RDTs:
- Rate of invalid test results /errors: Percentage of invalid test results/errors by RDT, site and error type</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operational characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, on average 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Operational characteristics and usability of study RDTs:
- Technical appraisal rating on kit instructions, labelling and test conduct, on a Likert scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1540</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C Virus Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with known or unknown HCV status</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Test for HCV antibodies with an RDT</intervention_name>
    <description>Fingerstick whole blood, plasma and serum of each participant is tested with three investigational HCV RDTs and one reference HCV RDT. Plasma is also used for testing with the composite reference standard, HCV viral load and genotyping. All participants are also tested for HIV with an HIV RDT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with known or unknown HCV status</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Left-over and unused back up samples of plasma and serum will be stored at a bio-repository
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        -  General population

          -  HCV high-risk individuals
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Known or unknown HCV serology

          -  No history of past or present HCV treatment

          -  Willing to undergo the information and consenting procedure and subsequently have
             enough time to participate in the study

          -  Willing to provide 13 ml venepuncture blood sample and a minimum of four whole blood
             fingerstick samples

          -  Willing to perform an HIV test

          -  Individuals can already be registered at the local site or register for the first time
             when enrolling in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants not able to consent themselves (incapable)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sihanouk Hospital Centre of Hope</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phnom Penh</city>
        <country>Cambodia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Center for Disease Control &amp; Public Health/Lugar Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tbilisi</city>
        <zip>0198</zip>
        <country>Georgia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cambodia</country>
    <country>Georgia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymised data will be shared with the manufacturers who's RDTs are being evaluated</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>end of study</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

