<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04257162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SOLTI-1804</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04257162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HER2-PREDICT: Translational Study of Tumor Samples From DS8201-A-U301 and DS8201-A-U302 Trials.</brief_title>
  <acronym>HER2-PREDICT</acronym>
  <official_title>HER2-PREDICT: Translational Study of Tumor Samples From DS8201-A-U301 and DS8201-A-U302 Trials.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SOLTI Breast Cancer Research Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SOLTI Breast Cancer Research Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, observational study. Patients who will participate, are participating
      or have participated in Daichi Sankyo INC sponsored Ds8201-A-U301 and Ds8201-A-U302 trials
      will be asked to participate to HER2-PREDICT study offering them a new informed consent.

      In order to identify mRNA ERBB2 levels, we will evaluate by gene expression tumor samples
      from these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, observational study. Patients who will participate, are participating
      or have participated in Daichi Sankyo INC sponsored Ds8201-A-U301 and Ds8201-A-U302 trials
      will be asked to participate to HER2-PREDICT study offering them a new informed consent.

      After signing the informed consent form:

        -  For patients who have already begun dosing in Daichi Sankyo INC sponsored Ds8201-A-U301
           and Ds8201-A-U302 trials, an archival metastatic biopsy will be requested for inclusion
           purposes.

        -  For patients who have not yet dosed in Daichi Sankyo INC sponsored Ds8201-A-U301 and
           Ds8201-A-U302 trials eligible patients will undergo a fresh biopsy of a metastatic site.
           If not feasible, archival sample from metastatic site will be accepted. Blood samples
           will be collected from eligible patients for biomarker analyses.

      In both cases, a breast tumor sample will be acceptable for those patients who are diagnosed
      with de novo metastatic breast cancer.

      Exceptionally, for those patients who do not have a metastatic sample or the possibility of
      obtaining it in the cases mentioned above, the possibility of sending a sample of the primary
      tumor for inclusion purposes may be requested. SOLTI will confirm if the patient can be
      included.

      In order to identify mRNA ERBB2 levels, we will evaluate by gene expression tumor samples
      from these patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 13, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>To identify the optimal ERBB2 mRNA cut-point predictive of DS-8201 response
Correlation of mRNA ERBB2 levels (as a continuous variable) in baseline FFPE tumor samples with overall response in the DS8201a-treated cohorts.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>identify the optimal ERBB2 mRNA cut-point predictive of DS-8201 response</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Samples from patients Ds8201-A-U301 and Ds8201-A-U302 trials</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor and Blood sample collection</intervention_name>
    <description>After signing the informed consent form:
For patients who have already begun dosing in Daichi Sankyo INC sponsored Ds8201-A-U301 and Ds8201-A-U302 trials, an archival metastatic biopsy will be requested for inclusion purposes.
For patients who have not yet dosed in Daichi Sankyo INC sponsored Ds8201-A-U301 and Ds8201-A-U302 trials eligible patients will undergo a fresh biopsy of a metastatic site. If not feasible, archival sample from metastatic site will be accepted. Blood samples will be collected from eligible patients for biomarker analyses.
In both cases, a breast tumor sample will be acceptable for those patients who are diagnosed with de novo metastatic breast cancer.
Exceptionally, for those patients who do not have a metastatic sample or the possibility of obtaining it in the cases mentioned above, the possibility of sending a sample of the primary tumor for inclusion purposes may be requested. SOLTI will confirm if the patient can be included.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women ≥18 years old who will participate, are participating or previously participated
             in Daichi Sankyo INC. sponsored Ds8201-A-U301, Ds8201-A-U302 trials, consented for the
             obtention of a fresh biopsy or for the donation of an archival metastatic biopsy may
             be enrolled.

               1. a breast tumor sample will be acceptable for those patients who are diagnosed
                  with de novo metastatic breast cancer.

               2. Exceptionally, for those patients who do not have a metastatic sample or the
                  possibility of obtaining it in the cases mentioned above, the possibility of
                  sending a sample of the primary tumor for inclusion purposes may be requested.
                  SOLTI will confirm if the patient can be included.

          2. The participant (or legally acceptable representative if applicable) provides written
             informed consent for the study.

          3. Fulfill all inclusion and exclusion criteria of the Ds8201-A-U301 or U302 trials prior
             to inclusion.

          4. Availability of FFPE tumor block, collected prior to the inclusion in Ds8201-A- U301
             or U302 trial, with an associated pathology report. The tumor tissue should be of good
             quality based on total and viable tumor content.

               1. Acceptable samples include core needle biopsies for deep tumor tissue or
                  excisional, incisional, punch, or forceps biopsies for cutaneous, subcutaneous,
                  or mucosal lesions or biopsies from bone metastases.

               2. Fine needle aspiration, brushing, cell pellet from pleural effusion and lavage
                  samples are not acceptable.

          5. Must be able to provide blood sample(s).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1. Not having participated or not willing to participate to the Daichi Sankyo INC.
        sponsored Ds8201-A-U301, Ds8201-A-U302 trials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jordi Canes Ruiz</last_name>
    <phone>933436302</phone>
    <email>jordi.canes@gruposolti.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínic de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aleix Prat</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

