<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04259528</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00032913</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04259528</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endoscopic Ultrasound Findings in Esophageal Atresia Following Surgical Repair</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endoscopic Ultrasound Findings in Esophageal Atresia Following Surgical Repair</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Children with esophageal atresia who undergo surgical repair are at risk for anastomotic
      stricture following surgery. Esophageal stricture can be treated with serial endoscopic
      dilation but may ultimately need surgical resection if the stricture proves refractory to
      therapy. Several risk factors have been reported for development of recalcitrant stricture,
      but to date, no studies have specifically examined the relationship between anastomotic
      thickness and echotexture at time of initial postoperative endoscopy and treatment outcomes.
      Other risk factors that have been implicated in the development of recalcitrant stricture
      include gastroesophageal reflux disease, anastomotic leak, long-gap esophageal atresia, and
      gestational age. Moreover, it is poorly understood how esophageal layers alter and progress
      with repeated therapeutic dilation. The investigator hypothesize that the initial thickness
      and echotexture will help determine therapeutic outcome. It will also help us understand the
      progression of esophageal echotexture following therapeutic dilation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Predict post surgical primary repair outcome in patients with esophageal atresia using endoscopic ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients with esophageal atresia following surgical repair will undergo an endoscopic ultrasound procedure to measure esophageal layer thickness and to describe esophageal echo-texture characteristics at the anastomotic site</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Atresia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with esophageal stricture following surgical repair</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with esophageal atresia following surgical repair who developed an esophageal stricture</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pediatric endoscopic ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>endoscopic ultrasound at the esophageal stricture site to assess echo texture and esophageal layers</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with esophageal stricture following surgical repair</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Patients ages 0-21 years old at time of evaluation with a suspected diagnosis of
        esophageal stricture secondary to esophageal atresia (with or without Tracheoesophageal
        fistula) post surgical repair

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with pre-diagnosis of eosinophilic esophagitis

          -  Patients with pre-diagnosis of congenital esophageal stricture

          -  Patients diagnosed with esophageal stricture secondary to caustic ingestion

          -  Patient is diagnosed with an esophageal perforation at time of endoscopy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>michael manfredi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>osama baghdadi, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>6173556058</phone>
    <email>osama.baghdadi@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kouchi K, Yoshida H, Matsunaga T, Ohtsuka Y, Nagatake E, Satoh Y, Terui K, Mitsunaga T, Ochiai T, Arima M, Ohnuma N. Endosonographic evaluation in two children with esophageal stenosis. J Pediatr Surg. 2002 Jun;37(6):934-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12037771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amae S, Nio M, Kamiyama T, Ishii T, Yoshida S, Hayashi Y, Ohi R. Clinical characteristics and management of congenital esophageal stenosis: a report on 14 cases. J Pediatr Surg. 2003 Apr;38(4):565-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12677567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tambucci R, Angelino G, De Angelis P, Torroni F, Caldaro T, Balassone V, Contini AC, Romeo E, Rea F, Faraci S, Federici di Abriola G, Dall'Oglio L. Anastomotic Strictures after Esophageal Atresia Repair: Incidence, Investigations, and Management, Including Treatment of Refractory and Recurrent Strictures. Front Pediatr. 2017 May 29;5:120. doi: 10.3389/fped.2017.00120. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28611969</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Khan KM, Foker JE. Use of high-resolution endoscopic ultrasonography to examine the effect of tension on the esophagus during primary repair of long-gap esophageal atresia. Pediatr Radiol. 2007 Jan;37(1):41-5. Epub 2006 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17043852</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael A. Manfredi, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Director of Esophageal and Airway Treatment Center, Assistent Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Atresia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

