<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04255693</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RLS-GERD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04255693</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Real-life Study of Changes of Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Manifestations Due to Behavioural and Diet Adherence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Real-life Study of Changes of Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Manifestations Due to Behavioural and Diet Adherence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal State Budgetary Scientific Institution &quot;Federal Research Centre of Nutrition, Biotechnology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal State Budgetary Scientific Institution &quot;Federal Research Centre of Nutrition, Biotechnology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is aimed to investigate the role of long-term diet adherence on manifestations of
      gastroesophageal reflux disease
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The role of diet in the treatment of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) is still under
      discussion. Some studies support the evidence that specific components of food plays a role
      in triggering symptoms or may have an impact on reflux oesophagitis. Still, only limited data
      are present on the long-term real-life effects of diet and behaviour on the disease
      manifestations and outcomes. This specific study aims to investigate the role of diet in
      real-life cohort of patients in whom diagnosis of GERD is initially confirmed with the use of
      modern techniques (questionnaires, endoscopy, oesophageal pH-impedance recordings). To make
      the study possible, it is planned to form a cohort of patients with different manifestations
      of gastroesophageal reflux disease: non-erosive GERD (NERD), reflux-oesophagitis (EE),
      hypersensitive oesophagus. Each form of GERD is to be established in accordance to modern
      concept of GERD (i.e. Lyon consensus). In addition to standard-of-care examinations, diet
      assessment will be performed with the use of computer-based food frequency questionnaire
      (FFQ), which allows to analyse frequently used foods, food products in terms of frequency of
      consumption and sizes of the portions. Assessment of diet will be performed at the enrolment
      and than with a period of three months during three years. Based on the results, it would be
      possible to assess the effect of long-term adherence to diet, change of the composition of
      it, and perform a multifactorial statistical analysis with the consideration of other
      confounders: change in BMI, physical activity, smoking, concomitant medications, etc.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>According to the initial assessment, the patients will be allocated to the following subgroups: NERD, Erosive oesophagitis, hypersensitive oesophagus. Each patient will be provided with the standard recommendations on the diet and physical activity according to the initial assessment (calculated energy expenditures, physical activity, physical status and body composition) in addition to the standard drug treatment.
Repeated examinations will be performed to assess the disease status and change (if any) of diet.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The personnel involved to the assessment of outcomes (changes in diet, changes on endoscopy, changes on symptoms) will be blinded to the results of each other.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heartburn frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>a week</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days a week when the symptom is present</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heartburn severity</measure>
    <time_frame>a day</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective description reported by the patient, assessed with the use of visual analogue scale, from 0 to 5, where 0 is &quot;not at all severe&quot; and 5 is &quot;very severe&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade of erosive oesophagitis</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end-point, 2 years after enrolment</time_frame>
    <description>Grade of oesophagitis will be assessed according to the Los-Angeles classification</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease</condition>
  <condition>GERD</condition>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Erosion</condition>
  <condition>Erosive Esophagitis</condition>
  <condition>Non-erosive Reflux Disease</condition>
  <condition>Non-Erosive Gastro-Esophageal Reflux Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The data of all the patients will be assessed from the viewpoint of changes in the disease flow (severity and frequency of symptoms, grade of oesophagitis). They will be compared to the changes of the major factors that could influence the disease flow: adherence to anti-secretory agents, presence of concomitant medications and their doses, adherence to diet, change in physical activity. These will be compared to the initial data. Thus, it would be possible to make a multivariate comparison and try to establish the influence (and, possibly, weight) of each of the con-founder on the disease flow.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>To this arm patients with no change in the disease manifestations will be assigned, based on the end-point evaluation. The same as in the &quot;experimental&quot; groups factors will be analysed to establish the difference.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>diet adherence</intervention_name>
    <description>This type of &quot;intervention&quot; is to be established in a-posteriori analysis by the assessment of a fact whether a subject kept to use his &quot;usual&quot; diet or it contained substantial changes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No diet adherence</intervention_name>
    <description>A-posteriori established &quot;intervention&quot; based on the examinations at the end-point</description>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Change in physical activity</intervention_name>
    <description>The changes in physical activity will be assessed a-posteriori based on the examination at the end-point versus baseline data</description>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No change in physical activity</intervention_name>
    <description>The changes in physical activity will be assessed a-posteriori based on the examination at the end-point and comparison to the baseline data</description>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of antisecretory agents</intervention_name>
    <description>This &quot;intervention&quot; will be established a-posteriori, based on the examination at the end-point and compared to the baseline data. The need for the use of anti-secretory agents depends on the form of GERD and will be on the treating physician discretion. It is principal to account the use of anti-secretory agents (H2-histamine receptors blockers, proton pump inhibitors) as a major factors that may influence the outcomes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No use of antisecretory agents</intervention_name>
    <description>This &quot;intervention&quot; will be established a-posteriori, based on the examination at the end-point and compared to the baseline data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Change in disease manifestations</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No change in disease flow</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  willingness to participate (based on the signed informed consent form);

          -  presence of gastroesophageal reflux disease, based on the following: a) typical
             symptoms, like heartburn and/or regurgitation (for primary selection, symptoms should
             be present at least weekly, be actual for at least 3 months prior to the enrolment,
             and the patient should report the history of symptoms which lasts for at least 6
             months); b) previous response to the intake of proton pump inhibitors; c) data of
             24-hours oesophageal pH-impedance monitoring with detected pathological
             gastroesophageal reflux according to the Lyon consensus definitions;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant or breast-feeding females;

          -  abdominal or chest surgery (except appendectomy or cholecystectomy in case they are
             not followed by adhesive disease of the abdominal organs);

          -  constant use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents (NSAIDs), sporadic use of
             NSAIDs will be allowed in case the course of treatment was discontinued at least 2
             weeks prior to the enrolment, in case that constant use of NSAIDs happen to be
             necessary after the enrolment, the patients may continue in the study but doses,
             frequency and duration of treatment should be carefully documented;

          -  history or current evidence of cancer of any aetiology and location besides skin
             cancer in situ successfully treated before the enrolment;

          -  severe patient's conditions which may lead to misinterpretation of data, or in case of
             patient's enrolment may put him at risk of exacerbation of co-morbid conditions, or in
             cases when on discretion of the investigator patient's condition would not allow him
             to complete the course of the observation. These conditions include, but not limited
             to: heart failure (class III-IV by NYHA), uncontrolled hypertension, severe
             neurological disorders, decompensated liver cirrhosis (Child-Pugh B or C), severe
             depression or other psychological disorders;

          -  the patient may stop his participation in the study at any time by informing the site
             personal about his/her decision to withdraw the consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sergey Morozov, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal State Budgetary Scientific Institution &quot;Federal Research Centre of Nutrition, Biotechnology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sergey Morozov, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+74996131091</phone>
    <email>morosoffsv@mail.ru</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vasily Kropochev, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+74997943572</phone>
    <email>followkropochev@yandex.ru</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Federal State Budgetary Scientific Institution &quot;Federal Research Centre of Nutrition, Biotechnology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>115446</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergey Morozov, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+79104681801</phone>
      <email>morosoffsv@mail.ru</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vasily Kropochev</last_name>
      <phone>+74997943572</phone>
      <email>followkropochev@yandex.ru</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gyawali CP, Kahrilas PJ, Savarino E, Zerbib F, Mion F, Smout AJPM, Vaezi M, Sifrim D, Fox MR, Vela MF, Tutuian R, Tack J, Bredenoord AJ, Pandolfino J, Roman S. Modern diagnosis of GERD: the Lyon Consensus. Gut. 2018 Jul;67(7):1351-1362. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2017-314722. Epub 2018 Feb 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29437910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vakil N, van Zanten SV, Kahrilas P, Dent J, Jones R; Global Consensus Group. The Montreal definition and classification of gastroesophageal reflux disease: a global evidence-based consensus. Am J Gastroenterol. 2006 Aug;101(8):1900-20; quiz 1943.</citation>
    <PMID>16928254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Savarino E, Bredenoord AJ, Fox M, Pandolfino JE, Roman S, Gyawali CP; International Working Group for Disorders of Gastrointestinal Motility and Function. Expert consensus document: Advances in the physiological assessment and diagnosis of GERD. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017 Nov;14(11):665-676. doi: 10.1038/nrgastro.2017.130. Epub 2017 Sep 27. Review. Erratum in: Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2018 Apr 06;:.</citation>
    <PMID>28951582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roman S, Gyawali CP, Savarino E, Yadlapati R, Zerbib F, Wu J, Vela M, Tutuian R, Tatum R, Sifrim D, Keller J, Fox M, Pandolfino JE, Bredenoord AJ; GERD consensus group. Ambulatory reflux monitoring for diagnosis of gastro-esophageal reflux disease: Update of the Porto consensus and recommendations from an international consensus group. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2017 Oct;29(10):1-15. doi: 10.1111/nmo.13067. Epub 2017 Mar 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28370768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Commisso A, Lim F. Lifestyle Modifications in Adults and Older Adults With Chronic Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease (GERD). Crit Care Nurs Q. 2019 Jan/Mar;42(1):64-74. doi: 10.1097/CNQ.0000000000000239. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30507666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinucci I, Natilli M, Lorenzoni V, Pappalardo L, Monreale A, Turchetti G, Pedreschi D, Marchi S, Barale R, de Bortoli N. Gastroesophageal reflux symptoms among Italian university students: epidemiology and dietary correlates using automatically recorded transactions. BMC Gastroenterol. 2018 Jul 17;18(1):116. doi: 10.1186/s12876-018-0832-9.</citation>
    <PMID>30016938</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal State Budgetary Scientific Institution &quot;Federal Research Centre of Nutrition, Biotechnology</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sergey Morozov</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Leading researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GERD</keyword>
  <keyword>NERD</keyword>
  <keyword>erosive esophagitis</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>food</keyword>
  <keyword>adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>influence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis, Peptic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Deidentified individual participants data may be shared by request. Patients personal data (name, contacts, etc) will be blinded beforehand, according to the law.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The data will be available when the study is accomplished. They will be available for the request for 2 years after the date of the study completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>By request, when the reason for IPD sharing is reasonable and clear</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://ion.ru</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

