<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04259632</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MED-2019-28331</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04259632</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prolonged Daily Fasting as a Viable Alternative to Caloric Restriction in At-Risk Obese Humans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prolonged Daily Fasting as a Viable Alternative to Caloric Restriction in At-Risk Obese Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: Obesity is reaching epidemic proportions, affecting 36% of the adult population in
      the United States. There is intense interest in dietary management to treat obesity and its
      associated complications. The first line of obesity treatment is caloric restriction (CR),
      although recidivism is common. For moderate CR, attrition rates of 20% are often reported,
      therefore weight loss options beyond CR are urgently needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim#1: Evaluate the effect of TRE with ad libitum intake on weight and body composition.

      H 1.1: Individuals in the TRE and CR groups will have similar weight loss, which will be
      greater than weight loss achieved in the non-TRE group (primary outcome).

      H 1.2: TRE will result in greater loss of loss of total body fat (quantified by DXA) and
      greater loss of hepatic/visceral fat/ectopic fat (quantified by MRI) than CR.

      Aim#2: Assess the effect of TRE with ad libitum intake on caloric balance. H 2.1: TRE will
      reduce caloric intake compared with non-TRE [gold-standard interviewer administered 24-hour
      dietary recall (primary outcome)] with similar reduction as with CR, H.2.2: Compared with
      non-TRE, TRE will result in selection of more nutrient dense foods during a supervised meal
      within their eating window; this selection will be similar to CR. H 2.3 TRE will not alter
      physical activity, but will increase fat oxidation compared with CR and non-TRE.

      Aim#3: Assess the effect of TRE with ad libitum intake on metabolic flexibility.

      H 3.1: TRE will enhance metabolic flexibility compared with CR and non-TRE as measured by
      indirect calorimetry [RQ:Respiratory quotient before and during 2 step 6,6-2H2
      hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp: primary outcome].

      H 3.2: TRE will improve insulin sensitivity compared with non-TRE and similar to CR.

      H 3.3: TRE will augment greater fasting lipolysis compared to CR and non-TRE as measured by
      [U-13C] palmitate and enhance lipolysis suppression during the 2 step 6,6-2H2
      hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp.

      If these hypotheses are confirmed, this project has significant impact. First, it will
      advance understanding of the mechanisms underpinning this innovative intervention. Second,
      TRE can be a practical means of implementing prolonged fasting on a large scale, thereby
      transforming the treatment of obesity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be measured by standard scale and reported in kilograms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Whole Body Percent Fat</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition will be measured by dual energy x-ray absorptometry (DXA). Parameters of body composition will be calculated by integrated DXA software. Whole body percent fat will be reported as a percentage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Visceral Fat</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition will be measured by dual energy x-ray absorptometry (DXA). Parameters of body composition will be calculated by integrated DXA software. Visceral fat will be reported in grams.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Lean Mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition will be measured by dual energy x-ray absorptometry (DXA). Parameters of body composition will be calculated by integrated DXA software. Lean mass will be reported in kilograms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fat Mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition will be measured by dual energy x-ray absorptometry (DXA). Parameters of body composition will be calculated by integrated DXA software. Fat mass will be reported in kilograms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caloric Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Two interviewer-administered 24-hour dietary recalls will be collected from each participant at baseline and 12 weeks. The recalls will be conducted over the telephone and will be unannounced to minimize measurement reactivity. Diet data will be collected using the Nutrition Data System for Research (NDSR) to calculate Calories. Calories will be averaged across the 2 recalls at each time point. Outcome will be reported as difference between average caloric intake at baseline and 12 weeks. Outcome will be reported in kilocalories (Calories).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary Quality of Supervised Meal</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will consume a supervised meal at a public cafeteria. Participants will self-select their meal. Study staff will measure foods before the meal and all leftover food after the meal. This dietary data will be entered into the Nutrition Data System for Research (NDSR) software to calculate diet quality using the National Cancer Institutes Health Eating Index (HEI-2015). Possible total index points range from 0-100, with a higher score indicating greater consistency of the diet with the Dietary Guidelines for Americans.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Physical Activity: Sedentary</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to wear an accelerometer (Actigraph Link) for 2 weeks at baseline and 2 weeks post intervention. Physical activity will be calculated as the percent of time spent doing sedentary activity over the 2 week accelerometer usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Physical Activity: Light Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to wear an accelerometer (Actigraph Link) for 2 weeks at baseline and 2 weeks post intervention. Physical activity will be calculated as the percent of time spent doing light activity over the 2 week accelerometer usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Physical Activity: Moderate-Vigorous Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to wear an accelerometer (Actigraph Link) for 2 weeks at baseline and 2 weeks post intervention. Physical activity will be calculated as the percent of time spent doing moderate-vigorous activity over the 2 week accelerometer usage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Time Restricted Eating (TRE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the TRE group, we will restrict the eating window to 8 hours, where they will eat ad libitum. This is the same interval established by Dr. Panda and by our preliminary data. This interval will be entered into the mCC app and participants will be asked to adhere to this eating window during the intervention. All eating occasions will be logged using the mCC app. Only water and medications will be allowed outside of the eating window.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caloric Restriction (CR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to CR will meet with the study dietitian prior to the intervention and be counseled on options to reduce their caloric intake by 15%, while maintaining their eating window. The 15% reduction was selected as our preliminary data and recent literature suggest that TRE with ad libitum intake reduces caloric intake by ~270 to 300 cal/day. The 15% CR is similar to the 11.9% CR achieved by the CALERIE-2 study, which is a 2 year study of CR.26 All eating occasions will be logged using the mCC app. The weekly dietitian review of the mCC information will include maintenance of the eating window and examination of dietary intake to determine compliance with the 15% CR.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unrestricted Eating (non-TRE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the unrestricted eating (non-TRE) group, participants will eat ad libitum per their usual habits. They will receive initial counseling about mCC logging. All eating occasions will be logged using the mCC app.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Time Restricted Eating (TRE)</intervention_name>
    <description>daily eating window restricted to 8 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Time Restricted Eating (TRE)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caloric Restriction (CR)</intervention_name>
    <description>15% daily caloric deficient</description>
    <arm_group_label>Caloric Restriction (CR)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI ≥30 and ≤ 55 kg/m^2

          -  Own a smartphone compatible with the myCircadianClock (mCC) phone application

          -  Self-reported habitual wakening between 5-9 am

          -  Self reported sleep duration of 6-9 hours

          -  Self reported absence of known sleep apnea

          -  Weight must be stable [+/- 5 pounds] for at least 3 months prior to the study

          -  Eating window (time between 1st food intake and last food take) ≥14 hours using mCC

          -  Insulin resistance based on HOMA-IR≥ 2.5 from screening visit results

          -  Able to understand English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medication use that may affect lipid levels (i.e. lipid lowering agents, diuretics)

          -  Shift work (i.e. working from 11pm to 7am)

          -  Clinically significant medical issues (diabetes, cardiovascular disease, uncontrolled
             pulmonary disease)

          -  A history of abnormal laboratory results, such as hematologic (platelets &lt; 100),
             hepatic (LFTs &gt; 2X nl), renal (Cr &gt; 1.5)

          -  MRI contraindication (metal in body, claustrophobia)

          -  Eating window &lt; 14 hours per day

          -  Unable to consistently document food intake using the mCC app (need at least 2 eating
             occasions&gt; 6 hours apart on a given day for at least 50% of days)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Illiteracy

          -  Concern for active eating disorder per screening questionnaire

          -  Self-reported eating disorder or history of eating disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa Chow, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-624-5150</phone>
    <email>chow0007@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

