<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04252326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DrNazlı2020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04252326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices of Healthcare Workers on Drug Hypersensitivity Reactions in Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>KAPHWDHRC</acronym>
  <official_title>The Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices of Healthcare Workers on Drug Hypersensitivity Reactions in Children: A Tertiary Center Experience</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adverse drug reactions are an important public health consern that affects physician
      prescriptions and practice. The responsibilities of healthcare professionals in monitoring,
      prevention, treatment and reporting of drug hypersensitivity reactions and drug allergies are
      essential for patient safety. Providing drug safety must be one of the main goals to be
      achieved for every member of our society. In our study, we planned to evaluate the knowledge,
      attitudes, and behaviors of healthcare workers in our country about drug hypersensitivity
      reactions in pediatric patients and to determine the risk factors that may affect them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study was carried out in a capital-located university hospital with a capacity of 1150
      beds. Healthcare workers who are authorized to intervene in children (0-18 age group)
      including medical doctors, nurses and dentists were enrolled to study. In the evaluation of
      the knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of the participants about drug hypersensitivity
      reactions in children, a study questionnaire was developed by pediatric allergy and
      immunology specialists and pediatric nurses by considering the other studies on the same
      subject.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>we planned to evaluate the knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of healthcare workers in our country about drug hypersensitivity reactions in pediatric patients</measure>
    <time_frame>It is planned to fill the questionnaire in 2 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>The knowledge level domain, consisted of 24 questions including mechanism of drug hypersensitivity reactions, clinical findings, diagnosis and treatment. The answer format was 3 options (yes/no /don't know). A triple variable scale was used for knowledge level (0 to 2: 0, false; 1, true; 2, do not know).
The attitude domain consisted of 5 questions including the effect of DHRs on the patient's quality of life and advanced training and current diagnostic tests for the needs in this regard. A five-point Likert-type scale was used for the questions to determine the level of agreement or disagreement (1 to 5; 1 strongly disagree; 2, disagree; 3, uncertain; 4, agree; 5, strongly agree)
The practice domain consisted of 9 questions including taking history and practice in drug allergy and advanced training in DHR. A Likert-type scale was used to determine the level of practices (1 - 5: 1, never; 2, very rarely; 3, sometimes; 4, often; 5, always).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>we planned to evaluate the knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of healthcare workers in our country about drug hypersensitivity reactions in pediatric patients</measure>
    <time_frame>It is planned to fill the questionnaire in 2 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>The knowledge level domain, consisted of 24 questions including mechanism of drug hypersensitivity reactions, clinical findings, diagnosis and treatment. The answer format was 3 options (yes/no /don't know).
2. The attitude domain consisted of 5 questions including the effect of DHRs on the patient's quality of life and advanced training and current diagnostic tests for the needs in this regard. A five-point Likert-type scale was used for the questions to determine the level of agreement or disagreement The practice domain consisted of 9 questions including taking history and practice in drug allergy and advanced training in DHR. A Likert-type scale was used to determine the level of practices</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>to determine the risk factors that may affect the knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of healthcare workers in our country about drug hypersensitivity reactions in pediatric patient</measure>
    <time_frame>It is planned to fill the questionnaire in 2 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Participants'demographic questions regarding the age, gender, profession, duration in the profession, title and educational status of the participants may effect their surveys scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">354</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Drug Reactions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices on Drug Hypersensitivity Reactions in Children</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nurse</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices on Drug Hypersensitivity Reactions in Children</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dentist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices on Drug Hypersensitivity Reactions in Children</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Doctors, Nurses and Dentists filled survey about adverse drug reractions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dentist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Nurse</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The study included healthcare workers including medical doctors, nurses and dentists who
        perform interventions on children (0-18 years of age).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nazlı Ercan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Health Sciences University, Gülhane Training and Research Hospital, Gn. Dr. Tevfik Sağlam Cd No:11</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <state>Etlik</state>
        <zip>06010</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dorji C, Tragulpiankit P, Riewpaiboon A, Tobgay T. Knowledge of Adverse Drug Reaction Reporting Among Healthcare Professionals in Bhutan: A Cross-Sectional Survey. Drug Saf. 2016 Dec;39(12):1239-1250.</citation>
    <PMID>27743333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Seid MA, Kasahun AE, Mante BM, Gebremariam SN. Healthcare professionals' knowledge, attitude and practice towards adverse drug reaction (ADR) reporting at the health center level in Ethiopia. Int J Clin Pharm. 2018 Aug;40(4):895-902. doi: 10.1007/s11096-018-0682-0. Epub 2018 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>30094559</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nazlı ERCAN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pediatric Allergy and Immunology Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthcare workers</keyword>
  <keyword>Adverse drug reactions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Drug Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Drug-Related Side Effects and Adverse Reactions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

