<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04251975</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2131-Masked-OSA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04251975</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Masked Hypertensive Patients With Obstructive Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <acronym>Masked-OSA</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Intervention With Continuous Positive Pressure (CPAP) on Nocturnal Blood Pressure (BP) in Patients With Masked Hypertension and Sleep Apnea</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The general objective is to evaluate the effect of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP)
      treatment in patients with masked hypertension.

      The secondary objectives are: i) To evaluate the prevalence of different circadian patterns
      of BP in ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM) (dipper / non-dipper); ii) To assess in
      these patients the relationship between compliance with CPAP treatment and the response to
      nocturnal BP; iii) To identify variables of the ABPM, and biomarkers that are related to the
      unfavourable pattern of nocturnal BP response in these patients treated with CPAP; iv) To
      evaluate the change in the profile of biomarkers with the treatment.

      Methodology: Open, parallel, prospective, randomized and controlled study in which an ABPM
      will be performed in individuals with masked hypertension referred to the sleep unit and
      diagnosed of OSA (AHI≥ 30) without sleepiness (Epworth≤18).

      A total of 64 subjects with OSA and masked hypertension will be recruited. It will be
      collected blood for the determination of biomarkers. Subsequently, they will be randomized to
      receive treatment with CPAP (32) or conservative treatment (32). After 3 months of
      initiation, ABPM and biological determinations will be repeated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recruitment: It will be recruited subjects with masked hypertension. For that, normotensive
      subjects (Blood pressure (BP)&lt;140/90mmHg in the office) referred to the sleep unit of the
      Hospital Santa Maria (Spain) who are diagnosed of severe OSA (AHI≥30) by a sleep study and
      who do not present significant somnolence (Epworth≤18) will be proposed to participate in the
      study. Then, it will be performed an ABPM during-24 hours, and those subjects with an
      abnormal ABPM results and normal BP in the office will be included, are those subjects called
      masked hypertensive.

      Definition of the groups: Patients will be randomized to receive one of the following
      treatments:

        1. CPAP: Patients who will receive CPAP treatment. The CPAP titration will be carried out
           with an automatic or manual CPAP according to usual clinical practice.

        2. Conservative treatment: Patients who will receive conservative treatment based on
           hygienic-dietetic measures.

      Randomization: It will be carried out with an automated platform

      Duration of the treatment: All patients randomized to CPAP will begin treatment as soon as
      possible after randomization, and will continue treatment until the study ends (3 months).

      Patients who interrupt treatment will be excluded from the study. ABPM and blood sample
      collection will be performed on all included patients at the beginning of the study and at 3
      months under treatment (CPAP or conservative care).

      Follow-up: All patients will be evaluated at the beginning of the study, at first month and
      at three months during the follow-up period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is an open-label, parallel, prospective, randomized and controlled trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of CPAP treatment on BP in masked hypertensive patients with severe OSA</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in mmHg in the blood pressure of the ambulatory blood pressure monitoring parameters after the treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of the different circadian BP patterns (dipper/no-dipper) in the ABPM of masked hypertensive subjects diagnosed with severe OSA without significant somnolence (Epworth≤18)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of each circadian patterns will be calculated from the baseline ambulatory blood pressure monitoring data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between CPAP use and blood pressure change in ABPM</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The relation between CPAP compliance (hours/night) and changes in mean nighttime BP (mmHg) between baseline and at 3-months in ABPM measurements will be assesed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ambulatory blood pressure parameters that could be related to the response to CPAP treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Using all the ABPM variables we will proceed to the identification of variables that are related to the change in mean nocturnal BP in patients treated with CPAP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the biomarkers' profile (mRNAs) after CPAP treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Using the blood samples obtained in the baseline and 3 months visit it will be evaluated possible changes in the biomarkers profile after CPAP treatment.
Learning Phase: complete profile analysis (754 miRNAs) will be carried out in 24 patients Learning Phase: complete profile analysis (754 miRNAs) will be carried out in 24 patients representative of the change in BP in treated patients. The miRNAs associated with the change in BP will be identified from the 754 miRNAs potentially present in serum and plasma.
Validation Phase: Specific primers will be designed for the real-time PCR amplification of the genes for which we have found a significant association The miRNAs found will be analyzed after 3 months of treatment. Analysis of biomarkers. Immunoassay techniques will evaluate the following markers before and after treatment: angiotensin I, II and III, plasma renin activity, atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP), brain natriuretic peptide (BNP) and endogenous ouabain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Masked Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPAP treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group of patients who will receive CPAP treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative measures</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group of patients who will receive conservative treatment based on hygienic-dietetic measures</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPAP treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>In this group of patients (CPAP group) will be prescribed CPAP treatment at an optimal pressure. It will be performed a CPAP titration with an automatic or manual CPAP according to usual clinical practice</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPAP treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men and women over 18 years of age

          2. Referred to the sleep unit for suspected OSA

          3. Being masked hypertensive and presenting an AHI≥ 30 in the sleep study

          4. Signature of the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous CPAP treatment

          2. Significant somnolence defined by an Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) score higher than
             18

          3. Psychophysical inability to complete questionnaires

          4. Previous diagnosis or suspicion of another sleep disorder

          5. Presence of more than 50% of central apneas or Cheyne-Stokes respiration

          6. Having a serious chronic disease: neoplasia, renal failure, severe chronic obstructive
             pulmonary disease, chronic depression and other chronic limiting diseases

          7. Medical history that may interfere with the objectives of the study or, in the opinion
             of the researcher, may compromise the conclusions

          8. Any medical, social or geographical factor that may endanger the patient's compliance

          9. Having a profession of high risk (professional driver).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ferran Barbé Illa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CIBERES, SEPAR</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ferran Barbé Illa, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(+34) 97370 53 72</phone>
    <email>febarbe.lleida.ics@gencat.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ferran Barbe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Pulmonology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obstructive sleep apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>Masked hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Masked Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

