<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04256707</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KCP-330-027</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>XPORT-STP-027</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04256707</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bioequivalence and the Tolerability and Antitumor Activity of Selinexor Combination Treatment</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPRINT</acronym>
  <official_title>Open-Label, Phase 1 Study Evaluating the Bioequivalence of Different Formulations of Selinexor, and the Tolerability and Antitumor Activity of Selinexor Combination Treatment (SPRINT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karyopharm Therapeutics Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karyopharm Therapeutics Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, two-part, two-arm, open-label study in patients with NSCLC who have had 1
      or 2 prior lines of treatment, with 1 line containing a CPI, or patients with CRC who have
      had 2 prior lines of treatment (oxaliplatin- and irinotecan-based) and no prior
      immunotherapy. The study will comprise 2 treatment periods (Monotherapy and Combination
      Therapy). During the Monotherapy Period, the bioequivalence/relative bioavailability of
      different formulations of selinexor will be evaluated using a 2-sequence crossover design.
      During the Combination Therapy Period, the safety and preliminary anti-tumor activity of
      selinexor in combination with docetaxel (for patients with NSCLC) or pembrolizumab (for
      patients with CRC) will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Monotherapy Period

      For the Monotherapy Period of Study KCP-330-027, patients will be allocated to one of two
      test formulation treatment arms for once weekly dosing over a period of 3 weeks. A third test
      formulation of 100-mg oral suspension will be allocated on Week 3 to 6 patients in total out
      of the 38 patients planned to be enrolled. Approximately 38 patients will be enrolled, with a
      maximum of 20 patients for each disease type (NSCLC or CRC). In the CRC Cohort, at least 10
      patients should have the KRAS mutation. Patients will be randomized to 1 of the 2 treatment
      arms; disease type (NSCLC or CRC) will be a randomization factor. The number of patients
      enrolled may be adjusted based on the results of the interim analysis performed after the
      first 16 pharmacokinetics (PK) evaluable patients have completed Week 2.

      For Weeks 1 and 2 (and Week 3 for patients receiving the 100-mg oral suspension), following
      an overnight fast of at least 10 hours, patients will be fed a standard low-fat meal 30
      minutes prior to administration of once weekly selinexor. Patients should finish the meal in
      30 minutes or less; however, selinexor dose should be administered 30 minutes after start of
      the meal. Blood sampling for selinexor PK analyses will be collected predose (≤10 minutes
      before taking selinexor), 15 min (±3 min), 30 min (±3 min), 1 hour (±5 min), 1.5 hours (±7
      min), 2 hours (±10 min), 3 hours (±10 min), 4 hours (±10 min), 5 hours (±10 min), 6 hours
      (±10 min), 8 hours (±20 min), 10 hours (±20 min; optional timepoint), 24 hours (±30 min), 30
      hours (±30 min), and 48 hours (±1 hour) post selinexor dose. Practitioners must record the
      actual clock time for selinexor dose and each sample drawn.

      If a patient experiences emesis during the first 6 hours of the PK sampling, the results will
      be excluded from the PK analysis dataset.

      Safety will be evaluated through reporting of treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs),
      physical examinations (PE), and clinical laboratory testing.

      Computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) will be performed at screening.

      Patients who complete the Monotherapy Period will be considered for continuation to the
      Combination Therapy Period if they do not meet any exclusion criteria for reassessment. If a
      patient experiences significant toxicity related to selinexor and can't start the combination
      therapy immediately following monotherapy, dose interruption and weekly retesting are allowed
      for up to 21 days after the End of Monotherapy Treatment Visit. Patients requiring &gt;21 days
      to recover from toxicities related to selinexor should be discussed with the Sponsor's
      Medical Monitor for documented approval to continue to the Combination Therapy Period.
      Reassessment may be extended then and following Medical Monitor approval up to 28 days.

      Combination Therapy Period Patients enrolled in the Combination Therapy Period will receive
      combination treatment with selinexor once weekly and either docetaxel (NSCLC patients) or
      pembrolizumab (CRC patients) every 3 weeks until progressive disease (PD) or intolerable
      toxicity.

      Safety will be assessed through the continuous reporting of AEs, regularly scheduled clinical
      laboratory tests (hematologic and chemical), and physical examinations.

      Tumor assessment will be performed with either CT or MRI (CT with contrast preferred; for
      each patient, the imaging method should remain the same throughout the study).

      Patients will be followed for up to 1 year after the 30-Day Safety Visit (approximately 30
      days after the last dose of combination therapy). Patients who discontinued due to PD will be
      followed for survival, and patients who discontinued for reasons other than PD will have
      tumor assessments until PD or until the start of new anti-neoplastic therapy and will be
      followed for survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 14, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two part study (monotherapy period and combination therapy period).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monotherapy Period: Determine the bioequivalence of two selinexor tablet formulations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Bioequivalence for selinexor 20 mg and 100 mg tablets will be assessed at 100 mg weekly based on blood samples collected predose and 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 24, 30, and 48 hours post-selinexor dose on Days 1 and 8. The following pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters will be evaluated: area under the concentration-time curve (AUC) from time 0 to time of last concentration measured (AUC0-t), AUC from time 0 extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-inf), and maximum plasma concentration (Cmax).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Combination Therapy Period: Evaluate safety and tolerability of selinexor in combination with docetaxel in patients with NSCLC or pembrolizumab in patients with CRC</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for up to 1 year after the 30-Day Safety Visit (approximately 30 days after the last dose of combination therapy)</time_frame>
    <description>The safety and tolerability of selinexor in combination with docetaxel or pembrolizumab will be assessed in patients with NSCLC or CRC, respectively, based on AE reports, physical examination results (including vital signs), and clinical laboratory results by means of the occurrence, nature and severity of AEs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma (NSCLC)</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer (CRC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monotherapy: Formulation Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Week 1: selinexor 5 x 20-mg tablet daily;
Week 2: selinexor 1 x 100-mg tablet daily;
Week 3: selinexor 100-mg oral suspension OR 5 x 20-mg tablet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monotherapy: Formulation Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Week 1: selinexor 1 x 100-mg tablet daily;
Week 2: selinexor 5 x 20-mg tablet daily;
Week 3: selinexor 100-mg oral suspension OR 5 x 20-mg tablet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy: NSCLC Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Selinexor 60 mg oral dose once weekly and docetaxel 75 mg/m² IV once every 3 weeks (NSCLC patients)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy: CRC Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Selinexor 80 mg oral does once weekly and pembrolizumab 200 mg IV every 3 weeks (CRC patients)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Selinexor</intervention_name>
    <description>100-mg once weekly in the following 3 formulations:
5 × 20-mg tablets (Tablet A)
1 × 100-mg tablet (Tablet B)
A 100-mg dose of a suspension (Suspension C)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy: CRC Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy: NSCLC Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Monotherapy: Formulation Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Monotherapy: Formulation Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xpovio®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>75 mg/m² IV once every 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy: NSCLC Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxotere®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg IV every 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination Therapy: CRC Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients are eligible to be included in the study only if they meet all of the following
        criteria:

          1. Are ≥18 years of age.

          2. Have histologically confirmed advanced or metastatic NSCLC or CRC (patients with
             either KRAS mutation or wild type are eligible; however, at least 10 patients with CRC
             must have KRAS-mutant disease).

          3. Patients must have evidence of measurable disease per Response Evaluation Criteria in
             Solid Tumors (RECIST v1.1).

          4. Have received prior therapy as follows:

               1. For patients with NSCLC, have received at least 1 but no more than 2 prior
                  line(s) of systemic anti-cancer treatment with 1 regimen including a checkpoint
                  inhibitor (CPI).

               2. For patients with CRC, have received 2 prior lines of systemic anti-cancer
                  treatment (oxaliplatin- and irinotecan-based); no prior therapy with
                  immunotherapy.

          5. Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             screening and agree to use highly effective (dual methods of) contraception throughout
             the study and for 1 week following the last dose of study drug; and male patients must
             use an effective barrier method of contraception throughout the study and for 1 week
             following the last dose of study drug if sexually active with a female of childbearing
             potential.

          6. Willing to provide written informed consent in accordance with federal, local, and
             institutional guidelines and comply with all requirements of the trial.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients are excluded from the study if any of the following criteria apply:

          1. Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of ≥2.

          2. Have a life expectancy of &lt;12 weeks, as determined by the Investigator.

          3. Have inadequate hepatic function defined as total bilirubin, aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST), or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; upper limit of normal
             (ULN). Patients with mild hepatic dysfunction (total bilirubin of 1 - 1.5 × ULN or
             AST/ALT of 1 - 2 × ULN) may be included in the study if approved by the Sponsor's
             Medical Monitor.

          4. Have inadequate hematopoietic function defined as absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt;1.5
             × 10⁹/L; platelet count (PLT) &lt;100 × 10⁹/L; or hemoglobin (Hb) &lt;9 g/dL.

          5. Had transfusions or hematopoietic growth factors &lt;7 days of Day 1 dosing.

          6. Have inadequate renal function defined as a calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) of
             &lt;20 mL/min using the formula of Cockcroft and Gault.

          7. Have any other medical condition especially any gastrointestinal (GI) dysfunctions or
             GI disease that could interfere with the absorption of selinexor (e.g., inability to
             swallow tablets, malabsorption syndrome, a history of GI surgery which may result in
             intestinal blind loop, significant gastroparesis, unresolved nausea, vomiting, or
             diarrhea [National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
             Events (CTCAE) Grade &gt;1]) or have any general inability to swallow and retain oral
             medications.

          8. Unstable cardiovascular function:

               1. symptomatic ischemia, or

               2. congestive heart failure of New York Heart Association Class ≥3, or

               3. myocardial infarction within 3 months of Day 1 dosing.

          9. Received strong cytochrome P450 3A (CYP3A) inhibitors OR strong CYP3A inducers ≤7 days
             prior to Day 1 dosing.

         10. Ongoing infection requiring parenteral antibiotics, antivirals, or antifungals on Day
             1 dosing.

         11. Insufficient time since or not recovered from procedures or anti-cancer therapy,
             defined as:

               1. Not recovered from major surgery ≤21 days prior to Day 1 dosing. Minor
                  procedures, such as biopsies, dental work, or placement of a port or intravenous
                  line for infusion are permitted.

               2. Have ongoing clinically significant anti-cancer therapy-related toxicities CTCAE
                  Grade &gt;1. In specific cases, patients whose toxicity has stabilized or with Grade
                  2 non-hematologic toxicities can be allowed following documented approval by the
                  Sponsor's Medical Monitor.

               3. Had last dose of previous anti-cancer therapy ≤14 days prior to Day 1 dosing.

         12. Inability or unwillingness to undergo a series of PK sampling.

         13. Inability or unwillingness to take supportive medications such as anti-nausea and
             anti-anorexia agents as recommended by the NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in
             Oncology for antiemesis and anorexia/cachexia (palliative care).

         14. Serious psychiatric or medical conditions that could interfere with participation in
             the study or in the opinion of the Investigator would make study involvement
             unreasonably hazardous.

         15. In the opinion of the Investigator, patients who are significantly below their ideal
             body weight.

         16. Known allergy to selinexor (all patients), docetaxel (NSCLC Cohort only), or
             pembrolizumab (CRC Cohort only).

         17. Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.

         18. Patients with CRC who are to receive pembrolizumab:

               1. had a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or are receiving systemic steroid therapy
                  (&gt;10 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent) or any other form of immunosuppressive
                  therapy.

               2. are diagnosed with endocrinopathies, such as abnormal thyroid function. Patients
                  on stable hormone replacement therapy are allowed.

               3. have active autoimmune disease requiring systemic treatment during the past 2
                  years. Type 1 diabetes mellitus, hypothyroidism only requiring hormone
                  replacement, skin disorders (such as vitiligo, psoriasis, or alopecia) not
                  requiring systemic treatment, or conditions not expected to recur in the absence
                  of an external trigger are permitted.

             The following exclusion criteria define patients to be excluded from the Combination
             Therapy Period upon completion of the Monotherapy Period:

         19. Have PLT &lt;100 × 10⁹/L, ANC &lt;1.0 × 10⁹/L (for patients with NSCLC who are to receive
             docetaxel, ANC &lt;1.5 × 10⁹/L), or Hb &lt;9 g/dL.

         20. Have an ECOG performance status of ≥3.

         21. Have not recovered or stabilized from nonhematologic toxicities related to selinexor,
             with recovery defined as Grade 1 or baseline for nonhematologic AEs. Patients with
             certain Grade 2 nonhematologic toxicities can be allowed following approval by the
             Sponsor's Medical Monitor.

             Note: Dose interruption between the Monotherapy Period and the Combination Therapy
             Period is allowed for recovery from AEs. Patients requiring &gt;21 days after the End of
             Monotherapy Treatment visit to recover from toxicities related to selinexor should be
             discussed with the Sponsor's Medical Monitor for approval to continue to the
             Combination Therapy Period.

         22. For patients with CRC who are to receive pembrolizumab, have received live-attenuated
             vaccine against an infectious disease (e.g., influenza) ≤14 days prior to Cycle 1 Day
             1 (C1D1).

         23. For patients with NSCLC who are to receive docetaxel, have a bilirubin &gt;ULN or AST
             and/or ALT &gt;1.5 × ULN concurrent with alkaline phosphatase &gt;2.5 × ULN.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Kauffman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Karyopharm Therapeutics Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Kauffman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 658-0600</phone>
    <email>mkauffman@karyopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sharon Shacham, PhD, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 658-0600</phone>
    <email>sshacham@karyopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Soroka University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beer-Sheva</city>
        <zip>84101</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nir Peled</last_name>
      <email>peled.nir@gmail.com; drnp@012.net.il; nirp@clalit.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nir Peled</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rambam Health Care Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <zip>3109601</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corinne Maurice-Dorr</last_name>
      <phone>972.4.7776473</phone>
      <email>c_maurice-dror@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Corinne Maurice-Dorr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheba Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel-Hashomer</city>
        <zip>5265601</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Talia Golan</last_name>
      <phone>972.3.5305338</phone>
      <email>Talia.Golan@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Talia Golan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-small cell lung carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>selinexor</keyword>
  <keyword>docetaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>KPT-330</keyword>
  <keyword>bioequivalence</keyword>
  <keyword>relative bioavailability</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

