<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04250311</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMH-407-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04250311</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial of Efficacy and Safety of ММН-407 in the Treatment of Influenza in Outpatient Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, Randomized Clinical Trial in Parallel Groups to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of ММН-407 in the Treatment of Influenza in Outpatient Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Materia Medica Holding</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Materia Medica Holding</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is:

      • to evaluate the efficacy and safety of MMH-407 in the treatment of influenza in outpatient
      adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design: a multicenter, placebo-controlled, double-blind, randomized clinical trial in
      parallel groups.

      The study will include both male and female patients aged 18-64 years with clinical signs of
      influenza within the first 24 hours of the onset of illness.

      The influenza diagnosis must be supported by a positive rapid test (detection of influenza
      virus antigens in nasal epithelial cells). After the patients provide signed Participant
      Information Sheet and Informed Consent form, their medical history and body temperature will
      be recorded and physical examination and rapid diagnostic test performed. Patients who test
      positive will be assessed for 7 influenza-associated symptoms: cough, sore throat, headache,
      nasal congestion, feverishness or chills, muscle or joint pain, fatigue.

      4-point Flu Symptom Severity scale will be used: 0 = no symptom; 1 = mild symptom; 2 =
      moderate symptom; 3 = severe symptom.

      Nasopharyngeal swabs will be obtained from these patients for subsequent real-time reverse
      transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) influenza A/B testing and laboratory tests
      performed.

      If a patient meets all inclusion criteria and does not meet any of the exclusion criteria at
      Visit 1 (Day 1), he/she will be randomized into one of the treatment groups: Group 1: ММН-407
      for 5 days, or Group 2: Placebo on the ММН-407 regimen for 5 days.

      The patients will use electronic patient diaries to daily record their morning and evening
      axillary temperature (taken using a Geratherm mercury-free thermometer) and severity of 7
      influenza-associated symptoms (using the Flu Symptom Severity scale). In addition to this,
      the patients will record doses of antipyretic drugs taken (when applicable) and any worsening
      of their health status (when applicable, to assess treatment safety and collect adverse
      events data).

      In total, patients will be observed for 14 days (screening and randomization − up to 24
      hours, treatment − 5 days, subsequent observation − up to 2 days; and a follow-up 'telephone'
      visit − Day 14).

      During the study, 3 visits from patient to the physician's office and a follow-up telephone
      visit will be accomplished: 1) patient visits − Days 1, 3 and 7 (Visits 1, 2, and 3) at the
      medical centre; 2) telephone visit from the physician (Visit 4) - Day 14.

      During Visits 2 and 3, the physician will perform a physical examination, record the changes
      in patients' symptoms and the use of concomitant medications and check the completion of
      patient diaries. At Visit 2, nasopharyngeal swabs for RT-PCR will be collected. Visit 3 will
      involve an assessment of treatment compliance and laboratory tests. The telephone visit is
      intended to provide information on a patient's health status, presence/absence of secondary
      bacterial complications and the use of antibiotics.

      During the study, subjects will be allowed to use symptomatic therapy and medications for
      their co-morbidities, except for the medicines listed in the &quot;Prohibited Concomitant
      Medications&quot; section.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to improvement of influenza symptoms.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1-14 of observation.</time_frame>
    <description>Based on patient diaries. In the morning and in the evening, the patients rate the severity of their symptoms on a 4-point scale (7 symptoms of influenza): headache, fever/chill, aches in the muscles/joints, weakness/drowsiness, cough, sore throat, and nasal congestion, where the absence of symptoms is 0, mild symptoms − 1, moderate symptoms − 2, and severe symptoms is 4. &quot;Improvement of influenza symptoms&quot; means no or mild symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients reporting improvement of influenza symptoms.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1-14 of observation period.</time_frame>
    <description>Based on patient diaries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of illness.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1- 6 of the observation period.</time_frame>
    <description>Total symptom score AUC (to be estimated from each of the seven symptom subscores).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with negative virus shedding.</measure>
    <time_frame>On day 3 of the observation period.</time_frame>
    <description>Negative influenza RT-PCR on nasopharyngeal swabs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dosing frequency of antipyretics according to indications.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1-3 of the treatment period.</time_frame>
    <description>A decrease dosing frequency of antipyretics while taking MMN-407 is one of the criteria for effectiveness.Based on patient diaries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects reporting worsening of illness.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 4 -14 of the observation period.</time_frame>
    <description>Worsening of illness is bacterial complication of influenza that require the use of antibiotics or hospitalization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence and nature of adverse events (AE).</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1-5 of the treatment period.</time_frame>
    <description>AE severity, causal relationship to the study drug and outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with treatment-related changes in vital signs: body temperature, pulse rate (heart rate), respiration rate (breathing rate), and blood pressure.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1- 5 of the treatment period.</time_frame>
    <description>Based on medical records. Vital signs will be measured in a medical setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with clinically significant abnormal laboratory data.</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1- 5 of the treatment period.</time_frame>
    <description>Вased on medical records.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">314</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MMH-407</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral administration. Single dose: 1 tablet. First 24 hours of therapy: 1 tablet every 30 minutes for the first 2 hours, followed by 3 more tablets taken at regular intervals during the rest of the day. Days 2 to 5: 1 tablet 3 times daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral administration. Single dose: 1 tablet. First 24 hours of therapy: 1 tablet every 30 minutes for the first 2 hours, followed by 3 more tablets taken at regular intervals during the rest of the day. Days 2 to 5: 1 tablet 3 times daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MMH-407</intervention_name>
    <description>MMH-407: For oral use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MMH-407</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo: For oral use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients of male and female gender aged 18 to 64 years.

          2. Uncomplicated, moderate influenza supported by all the symptoms:

               -  axillary temperature ≥38.1°С on physician examination;

               -  at least one moderate general symptom of influenza infection (headache,
                  fever/chill, aches in the muscles/joints, weakness/drowsiness);

               -  at least one moderate respiratory symptom of influenza infection (cough, sore
                  throat, or nasal congestion).

          3. Positive influenza rapid test (detection of virus antigens in the nasal epithelium).

          4. First 24 hours of the onset of illness.

          5. Patients who agree to use a reliable method of birth control during the study.

          6. Patients who have provided signed Participant Information Sheet and Informed Consent
             form to participate in a clinical trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Severe influenza infection that requires hospitalization.

          2. Suspected pneumonia or bacterial infection (including otitis media, sinusitis, urinary
             tract infection, meningitis, sepsis, etc.) that requires the use of antibiotics,
             starting from the first day of illness.

          3. Suspected early manifestations of a condition that, on its first onset, produces
             symptoms similar to those of influenza (other infectious diseases and/or
             influenza-like syndrome associated with the first onset of a systemic connective
             tissue disorder or another condition).

          4. Patients who require the use of antivirals that are not permitted during the study.

          5. Current season influenza vaccination.

          6. Prior history or diagnosis of primary or secondary immunodeficiency

          7. Patients with any known or suspected malignant neoplasm.

          8. An exacerbated or decompensated chronic disease interfering with the subject's
             participation in the clinical trial.

          9. Malabsorption syndrome, including congenital or acquired lactase deficiency (or any
             other disaccharidase deficiency), and/or galactosemia.

         10. Current allergy to or intolerance of the active substances or any of the excipients in
             the medications used in the treatment.

         11. Pregnancy, breast-feeding, childbirth within less than 3 months prior to the inclusion
             in the trial, or unwillingness to use contraceptive methods during the study

         12. Prior history of non-adherence to medication; mental disorder; or alcohol or substance
             abuse, which, in the investigator's opinion, will compromise compliance with study
             procedures.

         13. Use of any of the &quot;Prohibited Concomitant Medications&quot; within 2 weeks prior to study
             entry.

         14. Patients who, as judged by the investigator, will fail or be unwilling to comply with
             the observation requirements or adhere to the dosing regimen during the study.

         15. Participation in other clinical studies within 3 months prior to the inclusion in this
             study.

         16. Patients who are related to any of the on-site research personnel directly involved in
             the conduct of the study or are an immediate relative of the investigator. 'Immediate
             relative' means husband, wife, parent, son, daughter, brother, or sister (regardless
             of whether they are natural or adopted).

         17. Patients who work for OOO &quot;NPF &quot;Materia Medica Holding&quot; (i.e. company employees,
             temporary contract workers, designated officials responsible for carrying out the
             research or any immediate relatives of the aforementioned).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mikhail Putilovskiy, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+74952761571</phone>
    <phone_ext>302</phone_ext>
    <email>PutilovskiyMA@materiamedica.ru</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Hospital # 5</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barnaul</city>
        <zip>656045</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tatiana Martynenko, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tatiana Martynenko, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Belgorod State National Research University, Hospital Therapy Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belgorod</city>
        <zip>308015</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oksana Belousova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Oksana Belousova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Road Clinical Hospital at Chelyabinsk station of JSC Russian Railways</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chelyabinsk</city>
        <zip>454000</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yuliya Shapovalova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yuliya Shapovalova, MD, Phd</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central City Hospital # 7</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ekaterinburg</city>
        <zip>620137</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Kuzmicheva, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Kuzmicheva, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Clinical Hospital # 9 of the Ministry of Health of the Udmurt Republic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izhevsk</city>
        <zip>426063</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrey Ezhov, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrey Ezhov, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kazan State Medical University, Internal Medicine Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kazan</city>
        <zip>420012</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rustem Khamitov, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rustem Khamitov, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kazan State Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kazan</city>
        <zip>420012</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Khazova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Khazova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kirov State Medical University, Clinic of Kirov State Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kirov</city>
        <zip>610027</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Bakulina, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Bakulina, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kirov State Medical University, Hospital Therapy Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kirov</city>
        <zip>610027</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Svetlana Malchikova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Svetlana Malchikova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kuban State Medical University, Infectious Diseases and Phthisiopulmonology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Krasnodar</city>
        <zip>350063</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marina Avdeeva, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marina Avdeeva, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Clinical Hospital of the Russian Academy of Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>117593</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aleksandr Gofman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aleksandr Gofman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Polyclinic # 5 of the Office of the President of the Russian Federation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>119121</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olga Kropova, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olga Kropova, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Clinical Hospital named after M.E. Zhadkevich Moscow City Health Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>121374</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Svetlana Berns, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Svetlana Berns, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moscow State Medical and Dental University named after A.I. Evdokimov, Pulmonology Laboratory</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>127473</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kirill Zykov, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kirill Zykov, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Clinical Hospital # 10 of the Kanavinsky District of Nizhny Novgorod</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nizhny Novgorod</city>
        <zip>603011</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ekaterina Makarova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ekaterina Makarova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Road Clinical Hospital at the station Nizhny Novgorod of JSC Russian Railways</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nizhny Novgorod</city>
        <zip>603140</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalia Eremina, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Natalia Eremina, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Podolsk City Clinical Hospital # 3</name>
      <address>
        <city>Podolsk</city>
        <zip>142105</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marina Chernogorova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marina Chernogorova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ryazan State Medical University named after academician I.P. Pavlov, Department of Outpatient Therapy and Preventive Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ryazan</city>
        <zip>390026</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Evgeniy Filippov, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evgeniy Filippov, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vvedensky City Clinical Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>191180</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nataliya Kuzubova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nataliya Kuzubova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Polyclinic # 25 of the Nevsky District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>193312</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Pavlysh, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Pavlysh, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Center &quot;Reavita Med SPb&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>194354</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Veronika Popova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Veronika Popova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Road Clinical Hospital of JSC Russian Railways</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>195271</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Viktor Shunkov, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Viktor Shunkov, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Polyclinic # 51</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>196211</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Irina Sedavnykh, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Irina Sedavnykh, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Polyclinic # 34</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>197198</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yuliya Drozdova, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yuliya Drozdova, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Polyclinic # 43</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>198207</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergey Rodygin, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sergey Rodygin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City Polyclinic # 4</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>199178</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Galina Dey, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Galina Dey, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Samara City Hospital # 4</name>
      <address>
        <city>Samara</city>
        <zip>443056</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Makova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Makova, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scientific Medical Center for General Therapy and Pharmacology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stavropol</city>
        <zip>355000</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olga Ukhanova, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olga Ukhanova, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tver State Medical University, Department of Hospital Therapy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tver</city>
        <zip>170100</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nikolay Bazhenov, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nikolay Bazhenov, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bashkir State Medical University, Internal Medicine Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ufa</city>
        <zip>450008</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Khalida Gantseva, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Khalida Gantseva, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Volgograd State Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Volgograd</city>
        <zip>400131</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Olga Magnitskaya, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olga Magnitskaya, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Altai State Medical University, Department of Faculty Therapy with a course of immunology and allergology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barnaul</city>
        <state>Москва</state>
        <zip>656038</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Irina Osipova, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Irina Osipova, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

