<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04254562</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H00017845</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHS-2019-ACL-NIDILRR-RTEM-0334</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04254562</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Helping Youth on the Path to Employment</brief_title>
  <acronym>HYPE</acronym>
  <official_title>Helping Youth on the Path to Employment: Creating Economic Self-sufficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Colorado State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Disability, Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Helping Youth on the Path to Employment (HYPE): Creating economic self-sufficiency, a
      randomized-controlled implementation efficacy hybrid trial, will test a manualized
      intervention combining educational and employment supports for young adults with mental
      health conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previous controlled trials in mature adult subjects has consistently demonstrated that
      Supported Employment interventions (i.e., Individual Placement and Supports) elicit benefit
      for those with mental health conditions in getting and keeping productive work. Similarly,
      previous research demonstrates that Supported Education has efficacy in helping young adults
      with mental health conditions in their academics. However, to date, no evidence-based
      practice exists which combines both supported education and supported employment
      interventions into a single model that has efficacy and utility for young adults with serious
      mental health conditions. Supported Education has been fruitful for navigating academics, but
      hasn't demonstrated efficacy for supporting young adults with their careers, and Supported
      Employment programs, like IPS, have shown poor efficacy for helping young adults, as it was
      designed to assist mature adults. Therefore, the HYPE Model will become the first
      evidence-informed intervention to combine Supported Employment and Supported Education
      paradigms in an effort to help young adults with mental health conditions successfully
      navigate college so they can move into a primary labor market career and attain economic
      self-sufficiency.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 23, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 23, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The Research/Recruitment Specialist, responsible for data collection, will be blinded to the treatment conditions and will not know which participants are allocated to which condition. All data collection personnel and evaluators will be blinded. Thus, HYPE is a single-blind randomized trial.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of students making satisfactory academic progress</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of students making satisfactory academic progress (SAP), defined as a student completing two-thirds of the courses they enroll in each semester and achieving a GPA of 2.0 or greater</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of students with disruptions toward completion of college degree.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of students with disruptions toward completion of college degree, defined as withdrawal from postsecondary institutions, academic probation, not meeting satisfactory academic progress, or a leave of absence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in frequency of educational barriers</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The average frequency of educational barriers experienced by participants, defined as the specific challenges participants face in their pursuit of postsecondary education and whether and how their use of accommodations through campus disability services has or would be helpful for them. This will be measured with the Educational Barriers Questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in levels of perceived Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in levels of perceived stress throughout the study in the experimental condition, measured by the perceived stress scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Academic Self-Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in academic self-efficacy among students across the study will be measured with the college self-efficacy scale and is defined as assess the degree to which participants' feel confident in their ability to complete tasks in college</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reliance on Social Security Benefits</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes on students' reliance on Social Security benefits will be measured via self-report on the Baseline and Follow-up Demographics surveys</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Mental Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Educational Problems</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group: HYPE Services</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental arm will be receiving the HYPE intervention for 12 months and followed for an additional 24 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group: Enhanced Academic Services</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control arm will receive a special personalized packet of resources available on campus as &quot;enhanced academic services as usual.&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weekly Meetings with a Supported Employment/Supported Education Specialist</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive intervention for 12 months which includes weekly meetings with a Supported Employment/Supported Education Specialist (HYPE Specialist). During the weekly meetings, the HYPE Specialist will review each participant's education and employment goals, and deliver individualized support relevant to those goals which include use of structured HYPE tools and worksheets as needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group: HYPE Services</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Focused Skill and Strategy Training (FSST)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive a 12 week Focused Skill and Strategy Training (FSST), a structured cognitive remediation intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group: HYPE Services</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Services as Usual</intervention_name>
    <description>One hour meetings every semester to review individual academic needs and review list of available on campus resources to best meet the student's needs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group: Enhanced Academic Services</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be between 18-30 years of age

          -  able to speak and read English fluently

          -  cognitively capable of providing informed consent and participating in study
             activities;

          -  enrolled in a minimum of six credits at a campus-based accredited college (two year or
             four-year programs)

          -  intending to enroll in a minimum of four semesters of college courses with the
             expectation of being continuously enrolled

          -  have had at least one prior academic disruption during a college academic semester -
             (e.g., withdrawal from postsecondary institutions; academic probation; not meeting
             satisfactory academic progress; or a prior leave of absence) prior to study enrollment

          -  currently have a diagnosed mental health condition by a licensed mental health
             provider under the DSM-V Axis 1 diagnoses (schizophrenia or other psychotic disorders,
             anxiety disorders, mood disorders, eating disorders, attention deficits and disruptive
             behavior disorders) or have been deemed eligible for ADA protections due to a
             disabling mental health condition - (e.g., receiving state vocational agency services,
             SSI/DI benefits, or postsecondary accommodations).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  have received or are receiving supports consistent with HYPE in the past year;

          -  have had no impact to academic success in college (i.e. disruption);

          -  have a secondary autism spectrum disorder, traumatic brain injury, or other
             neurodevelopmental or neurocognitive disorder affecting cognition;

          -  are currently incarcerated prisoners;

          -  are unable to speak or read English fluently;

          -  are under age 18 or require a legal guardian to provide informed consent;

          -  lack the cognitive capability to provide informed consent on their own
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle Mullen, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMass Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michelle Mullen, MS</last_name>
    <phone>508-856-2865</phone>
    <email>michelle.mullen@umassmed.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amanda Costa, BS</last_name>
    <phone>508-856-2865</phone>
    <email>amanda.costa@umassmed.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colorado State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Collins</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80523</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James E Graham, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>970-491-1356</phone>
      <email>je.graham@colostate.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James E Graham, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMass Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01545</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda Costa, BA</last_name>
      <phone>508-856-2865</phone>
      <email>amanda.costa@umassmed.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelle Mullen, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michelle Mullen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Supported Employment</keyword>
  <keyword>Supported Education</keyword>
  <keyword>Mental Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Remediation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Yes, individual deidentified participant data will be shared to ICPSR per funder (NIDILRR) regulations. Datasets will include: screening data (eligible participants only), baseline data, follow-up time 1 data, follow-up time 2 data, follow-up time 3 data, transcript data. Each dataset will share the same unique identifier (study ID) as well as date the data was collected. Codebooks (PDF format) and data dictionaries (CSV or TXT) will also be shared.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be shared within 3 years of the completion of the study (estimated 2024-2027)</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>If individuals outside of the study team (e.g. grad students) want data access they need to submit a formal request and if approved, be added to the IRB protocol &amp; complete all necessary human subjects research certifications. They will be required to sign data use agreements. Any external researchers must sign a user agreement form before obtaining data. Data resulting from this project will be distributed at no cost. The user agreement is a UMMS requirement and this procedure is similar to those used by similar projects. The user agreement includes a detailed description of limitations on the redistribution/use of the data. External users are also required to limit publications to topics indicated in the agreement. Publications resulting from using data will reference the source as provided in agreement form; recommended citations will be provided. An investigator/Project Director will monitor dataset use to ensure data are handled properly and utilized for original purposes.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

