<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04253756</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU-2019-1363</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04253756</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Trial Examining Plasma Exchange Using the Becton Dickinson (BD) Catheter In an Outpatient Apheresis Unit</brief_title>
  <acronym>REPLACE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial Examining Plasma Exchange Using the Becton Dickinson (BD) Catheter In an Outpatient Apheresis Unit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Becton, Dickinson and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized pilot study of therapeutic apheresis procedures (TAP) using the current
      standard of care catheter (SOC) vs the BD Nexiva Diffusics Catheter. It is a single blinded,
      randomized study. Data will be used to refine and power a full randomized control trial. For
      this study, a sample of 33 encounters in each group (total of 66 encounters). The specific
      aim is to test the hypothesis that the 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics Catheter provides the
      same efficacy and lower pain level with no increase in adverse events for patients undergoing
      apheresis treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TAP treats a wide range of disease processes and, in all cases, requires inlet and return
      venous access to perform the procedure. The goal of TAP is to return the patient to baseline
      and maintain independence and function. A larger needle (18 gauge) can cause more discomfort
      to the patient as well as additional scarring. A smaller needle may present less discomfort
      and scarring to the patient. The goal in the outpatient clinic is to minimize disruption to
      the patient's routine and help the patient maintain normal activities of daily living.

      To accomplish these goals, the outpatient clinic is open Monday thru Friday offering 4
      different appointment times. All patients that are referred to the clinic for TAP, first
      receive a vein evaluation to see if the patient is a candidate for peripheral IV therapy. At
      the clinic, approximately 68% of the patients TAP's are performed peripherally. This
      eliminates the risk of a central line infection and any alteration in activities of daily
      living, such as bathing(Kramer, 2016), (Shang, Ma, Poghosyan, Dowding, &amp; Stone, 2014),(Keller
      et al., 2018; McDiarmid, 2015).

      The hypothesis, is that the 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics catheter provides the same efficacy
      as current practice with no increase in adverse events for patients undergoing therapeutic
      apheresis. The results from the study will be significant because if the 20 gauge needle is
      equally effective for TAP, it can increase the number of patients that would be candidates
      for peripheral therapy. Therefore, decreasing the need for central venous access, which place
      the patient at an increased risk of infection. The study is a comparison of 2 types of
      infusion catheters. The standard of care is an 18-gauge autogard catheter (control group)
      which will be compared to the 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics (intervention).

      P - patients who require therapeutic apheresis procedures (TAP) I - use of 20 guage (20G) BD
      diffusics catheter during apheresis C - use of 18 G standard of care IV catheter during
      apheresis O - no difference in efficacy and no increase in safety events
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 27, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary hypothesis is that the 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics catheter has no increase in adverse events for patients undergoing therapeutic apheresis as compared to the standard of care when using plasma exchange.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants With Treatment-Related Adverse Events using 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics for TAP procedures, as assessed by standard care minimum threshold of ratio of return and inlet rates.
An adverse event will be determined if the high return pressure alarm is displayed by the exchange machine. When the alarm is triggered the operator will decrease the inlet speed to accommodate the return pressure. The minimum inlet threshold is determine by the procedure type. The minimum inlet threshold for plasma exchange 50ml/sec. If the minimum threshold has been reached, and the return pressure alarm is not resolved the catheter will be replaced with standard of care. The inlet rates average will be compared with historical inlet rate averages from the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary hypothesis is that the 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics catheter has no increase in adverse events for patients undergoing therapeutic apheresis as compared to the standard of care using red cell exchange.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants With Treatment-Related Adverse Events using 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics for TAP procedures, as assessed by standard care minimum threshold of ratio of return and inlet rates.
An adverse event will be determined if the high return pressure alarm is displayed by the exchange machine. When the alarm is triggered the operator will decrease the inlet speed to accommodate the return pressure. The minimum inlet threshold is determine by the procedure type. The minimum inlet threshold for red cell exchange 35ml/sec. If the minimum threshold has been reached and the return pressure alarm is not resolved the catheter will be replaced with standard of care. The inlet rates average will be compared with historical inlet rate averages from the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary hypothesis is that the 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics catheter has no increase in adverse events for patients undergoing therapeutic apheresis as compared to the standard of care when using photopheresis.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants With Treatment-Related Adverse Events using 20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics for TAP procedures, as assessed by standard care minimum threshold of ratio of return and inlet rates.
An adverse event will be determined if the high return pressure alarm is displayed by the exchange machine. When the alarm is triggered the operator will decrease the inlet speed to accommodate the return pressure. The minimum inlet threshold is determine by the procedure type. The minimum inlet threshold for photopheresis is 20ml/sec. If the minimum threshold has been reached and the return pressure alarm is not resolved the catheter will be replaced with standard of care. The inlet rates average will be compared with historical inlet rate averages from the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasma Exchange</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>18-gauge autogard catheter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics</intervention_name>
    <description>The BD Nexiva Diffusics catheters are suitable for use with power injectors when a direct connection is made.</description>
    <arm_group_label>20-gauge BD Nexiva Diffusics</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult (≥18 years old)

          -  Speaks and reads English

          -  A patient of the Apheresis clinic at University of Texas Southwestern University
             Hospital and Clinics

          -  Scheduled to receive TAP (therapeutic plasma exchange, red blood cell exchange and
             extracorporeal Photopheresis) as standard of care

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prisoners

          -  Persons under the age of 18 years

          -  Patient who are actively involved in chemotherapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tomas Armendariz, BSN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tomas Armendariz, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>2146454241</phone>
    <email>tomas.armendariz@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sonja Stutzman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>2146486719</phone>
    <email>sonja.stutzman@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zale Lipshy Pavilion</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sonja Stutzman, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-6719</phone>
      <email>sonja.stutzman@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spires SS, Rebeiro PF, Miller M, Koss K, Wright PW, Talbot TR. Medically Attended Catheter Complications Are Common in Patients With Outpatient Central Venous Catheters. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2018 Apr;39(4):439-444. doi: 10.1017/ice.2018.8. Epub 2018 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>29444733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Golestaneh L, Mokrzycki MH. Vascular access in therapeutic apheresis: update 2013. J Clin Apher. 2013 Feb;28(1):64-72. doi: 10.1002/jca.21267. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23420596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalantari K. The choice of vascular access for therapeutic apheresis. J Clin Apher. 2012;27(3):153-9. doi: 10.1002/jca.21225. Epub 2012 Apr 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22535654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keller SC, Williams D, Rock C, Deol S, Trexler P, Cosgrove SE. A new frontier: Central line-associated bloodstream infection surveillance in home infusion therapy. Am J Infect Control. 2018 Dec;46(12):1419-1421. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2018.05.016. Epub 2018 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>29908838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klimek L, Bergmann KC, Biedermann T, Bousquet J, Hellings P, Jung K, Merk H, Olze H, Schlenter W, Stock P, Ring J, Wagenmann M, Wehrmann W, Mösges R, Pfaar O. Visual analogue scales (VAS): Measuring instruments for the documentation of symptoms and therapy monitoring in cases of allergic rhinitis in everyday health care: Position Paper of the German Society of Allergology (AeDA) and the German Society of Allergy and Clinical Immunology (DGAKI), ENT Section, in collaboration with the working group on Clinical Immunology, Allergology and Environmental Medicine of the German Society of Otorhinolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery (DGHNOKHC). Allergo J Int. 2017;26(1):16-24. doi: 10.1007/s40629-016-0006-7. Epub 2017 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>28217433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shang J, Ma C, Poghosyan L, Dowding D, Stone P. The prevalence of infections and patient risk factors in home health care: a systematic review. Am J Infect Control. 2014 May;42(5):479-84. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2013.12.018. Epub 2014 Mar 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24656786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Putensen D, Leverett D, Patel B, Rivera J. Is peripheral access for apheresis procedures underutilized in clinical practice?-A single centre experience. J Clin Apher. 2017 Dec;32(6):553-559. doi: 10.1002/jca.21508. Epub 2016 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27630072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tomas Armendariz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Plasma exchange</keyword>
  <keyword>Photopheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>Red blood Cell exchanges</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

