<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04251052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NRG-CC008</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-07791</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NRG-CC008</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NRG-CC008</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NRG-CC008</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UG1CA189867</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04251052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare Two Surgical Procedures in Women With BRCA1 Mutations to Assess Reduced Risk of Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Non-Randomized Prospective Clinical Trial Comparing the Non-Inferiority of Salpingectomy to Salpingo-oophorectomy to Reduce the Risk of Ovarian Cancer Among BRCA1 Carriers [SOROC]</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NRG Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NRG Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial studies how well two surgical procedures (bilateral salpingectomy and bilateral
      salpingo-oophorectomy) work in reducing the risk of ovarian cancer for women with BRCA1
      mutations. Bilateral salpingectomy involves the surgical removal of fallopian tubes, and
      bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy involves the surgical removal of both the fallopian tubes and
      ovaries. This study may help doctors determine if the two surgical procedures are nearly the
      same for ovarian cancer risk reduction for women with BRCA1 mutations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To compare the non-inferiority of bilateral salpingectomy (BLS) with delayed oophorectomy
      to bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy (BSO) to reduce the risk of ovarian cancer among women
      with deleterious BRCA1 germline mutations.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To prospectively assess estrogen deprivation symptoms in BLS patients as measured by the
      Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Endocrine Symptom (FACT-ES) subscale compared to
      women in the BSO arm.

      II. To determine if health-related quality of life (QOL) (FACT) is negatively impacted by
      menopausal symptoms (menopausal symptom checklist-Menopausal Symptom Checklist [MSCL]),
      sexual dysfunction (Female Sexual Function Index [FSFI]), and cancer distress (Impact of
      Events Scale [IES]) in women who have undergone BLS, in comparison to normative data
      (MSCL/FACT-ES) and data from BSO patients.

      III. To assess medical decision making, as measured by the Shared Decision Making
      Questionnaire (SDM-Q-9) and Decision Regret Scale (DRS), and determine factors associated
      with the risk of reducing surgical treatment choice.

      IV. To assess adverse events, graded using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
      (CTCAE) version (v)5.0.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Sexual dysfunction, as measured by selected Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement
      Information System (PROMIS) screener and external sexual function items.

      II. To estimate the cost-effectiveness of BLS compared to BSO for ovarian cancer risk
      reduction.

      III. To determine the association between health related (HR)-QOL with menopausal symptoms,
      as measured by the MSCL, sexual dysfunction, as measured by FSFI/PROMIS screener and external
      sexual function items, and cancer distress as measured by the IES.

      TRANSLATIONAL RESEARCH OBJECTIVE:

      I. To bank tissue and blood biospecimens for future research (pending funding).

      OUTLINE: Patients are assigned to 1 of 2 groups.

      GROUP I: Patients undergo bilateral salpingectomy. Patients may then undergo oophorectomy
      after initial surgery.

      GROUP II: Patients undergo bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy.

      After completion of study, patients are followed up at 10-60 days, 6, 12, and 24 months, and
      then annually for up to 20 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2036</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2032</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to development of incident high-grade serous carcinomas (HGSC), specifically ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed using a stratified log rank test, stratifying for age. The effects of other covariates, such as familial history of gynecologic cancer, time to crossover for bilateral salpingectomy (BLS) patients, and age at study entry, will be adjusted for in Cox proportional hazard models. Patients who crossover will be analyzed according to the initial surgery received at study enrollment as this will reflect actual practice.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Endocrine Symptom (FACT-ES). The FACT total score (calculated from the physical, functional, social and emotional well-being subscales) and ES subscale will be assessed. Higher scores indicate better QOL for the FACT-ES and better functioning for the FSFI total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estrogen deprivation symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the FACT-ES. The FACT total score (calculated from the physical, functional, social and emotional well-being subscales) and ES subscale will be assessed. Higher scores indicate better QOL for the FACT-ES and better functioning for the FSFI total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI). Higher scores indicate better functioning for the FSFI total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Menopausal symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the Menopausal Symptom Checklist (MSCL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer distress</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the Impact of Events Scale (IES).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical decision making</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the Shared Decision Making Questionnaire (SDM-Q-9) to determin factors associated with the risk of reducing surgical treatment choice. The SDM-Q-9 total score at each time point of collection will be compared between arms using a t-test with a significance level of 0.05. A linear model will be used to assess the association of the SDM-Q-9 total score with treatment arm and patient characteristics such as age and race.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical decision making</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by the Decisional Regret Scale to determine factor associated with the risk of reducing surgical treatment choice. The Decisional Regret Scale total score at each time point of collection will be compared between arms using a t-test with a significance level of 0.05. A linear model will be used to assess the association of the Decisional Regret Scale total score with treatment arm and patient characteristics such as age, race, crossover from BLS arm, and hysterectomy status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be graded according to National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (v)5.0. Counts and frequencies will be provided for the worst grade adverse event (AE) experienced by the patient by treatment arm. The distribution of AE grade in the BLS arm will be compared to the BSO arm using a chi-square test, or Fisher's exact test if cell frequencies are &lt; 5, at the one-sided 0.05 significance level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by European Quality of Life Five Dimension Five Level Scale Questionnaire (EQ-5D-5L). A Markov model will be used to model cost.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual dysfunction by PROMIS screener</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by selected Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) screener. Each item will be analyzed separately and compared between treatment arms using a chi-square test.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Section dysfunction by PROMIS external sexual function items</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured by selected PROMIS external sexual function items. Each item will be analyzed separately and compared between treatment arms using a chi-square test.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between Health related (HR)-QOL and patient reported symptoms.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Will examine the correlation between HR-QOL, as measured by the FACT, with menopausal symptoms, as measured by the MCL, sexual dysfunction, as measured by FSFI, and PROMIS screener and external sexual function items and cancer distress as measured by the IES. Pearson correlation coefficients will be used for correlating the FACT total score with the FSFI overall score and IES total distress score. Spearman correlation coefficients will be used to assess the correlation between FACT total score and the MSCL symptoms, FSFI, and PROMIS items.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2262</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (bilateral salpingectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo bilateral salpingectomy. Patients may then undergo oophorectomy after initial surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bilateral Salpingectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo bilateral salpingectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (bilateral salpingectomy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bilateral Salpingectomy with Oophorectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (bilateral salpingectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (bilateral salpingectomy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have declined or elected to defer risk-reducing salpingo-oophorectomy
             (RRSO) after proper counselling to clearly explain the standard of care for BRCA1
             mutation carriers (for the BLS with delayed oophorectomy arms) or patients who are
             undergoing RRSO (for the RRSO arm)

          -  At least one intact ovary and fallopian tube

          -  Positive Clinical Laboratory Improvement Act (CLIA)-approved test results for
             pathogenic or likely pathogenic germline BRCA1 mutation in the patient herself.
             Documentation of the result is required

          -  Premenopausal; defined as &lt; 12 months of amenorrhea. However, for those patients with
             &gt;= 12 months of amenorrhea who may be pre-menopausal or patients with a prior
             hysterectomy with at least one retained ovary/tube, levels of follicle stimulating
             hormone (FSH), luteinizing hormone (LH), and in the premenopausal range per local
             institutional standards will be acceptable

          -  Concurrently planned or prior hysterectomy is permitted as long as at least one
             fallopian tube and one ovary had been retained

          -  Transvaginal ultrasound (TVUS) and CA-125 within 180 days of registration

          -  The patient or a legally authorized representative must provide study-specific
             informed consent prior to study entry

          -  Patient must have negative urine pregnancy test within 14 days prior to registration
             based on local institutional policies

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with a history of any prior cancer who have received chemotherapy within the
             past 12 months, hormonal therapy in the past 90 days, or radiotherapy to abdomen or
             pelvis at any prior time

          -  Prior history of ovarian cancer, including low malignant potential neoplasms (LMP),
             primary peritoneal carcinoma, or fallopian tube carcinoma

          -  Patients medically unfit for the planned surgical procedure

          -  Patients with abnormal screening tests (TVUS, CA-125) suspicious for occult or gross
             pelvic malignancy or neoplasm within the past 180 days

               -  An abnormal TVUS is defined as morphologic or structural variations suspicious
                  for ovarian malignancy or complex cystic lesions (simple cysts &lt; 5 cm in maximal
                  diameter are not exclusionary)

               -  An abnormal CA-125 is defined as a level &gt; 50 U/ml in this study population of
                  premenopausal women if they are not current users of oral contraceptives; an
                  abnormal CA-125 is defined as a level &gt; 40 U/ml for premenopausal women who are
                  current users of oral contraceptives

          -  Women who are currently pregnant or plan to become pregnant in the future
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Douglas A Levine</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NRG Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

