<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04258384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>37068608-6100-15-1685</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04258384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Turkish Cross-Cultural Adaptation, Validity and Reliability of VMPCI</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Turkish Cross-Cultural Adaptation, Validity and Reliability of Vanderbilt Multidimensional Pain Coping Inventory</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yeditepe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yeditepe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was planned to adapt the Vanderbilt Multidimensional Pain Coping Inventory into
      Turkish, to investigate its cultural adaptation, validity and reliability. The study was
      completed with 352 volunteers who fulfilled the criteria to be included in the Rheumatology
      Clinic of Istanbul Haydarpaşa Numune Training and Research Hospital. Data collection tools
      used in the study; Demographic Data Form, Mcgill and Melzack Pain Questionnaire, Short
      Form-36 (SF-36), Vanderbilt Multidimensional Pain Coping Inventory (VMPCI), Pain Coping
      Inventory (PCI), Pain Coping Scale were used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a chronic, progressive, inflammatory, autoimmune disease of
      unknown etiology, mainly affecting synovial joints, causing loss of function. The main reason
      that directs RA patients to medical treatment is pain. Chronic pain causes limitation of
      movement, sleep problems, fatigue, stress and depression, as well as physiological and
      psychological problems that cause negative effects on the quality of life of the individual.
      The patient's thoughts, expectations, and methods of coping with pain are effective in pain
      control. In order to identify and treat the painful condition, individual coping methods of
      the patient and the effectiveness of these methods should be evaluated. This study was
      planned to adapt the Vanderbilt Multidimensional Pain Coping Inventory into Turkish, to
      investigate its cultural adaptation, validity and reliability. The study was completed with
      352 volunteers who fulfilled the criteria to be included in the Rheumatology Clinic of
      Istanbul Haydarpasa Numune Training and Research Hospital. Data collection tools used in the
      study; Demographic Data Form, Mcgill and Melzack Pain Questionnaire, Short Form-36 (SF-36),
      Vanderbilt Multidimensional Pain Coping Inventory (VMPCI), Pain Coping Inventory (PCI), Pain
      Coping Scale were used. The language validity of the Turkish form of the scale was provided
      by the translation-back translation method. Expert opinion was obtained for scale of
      validity. In order to evaluate the reliability of the Turkish version of the scale; internal
      consistency coefficient, test retest and parallel form methods were used. After all these
      analyzes, the reliability and validity of the Turkish version of the VMPCI scale was
      obtained. In addition to this study, the descriptive characteristics of the sample, SF-36
      scale, Mcgill and Melzack Pain Questionnaire results were examined alone and together with
      the sub-dimensions of the scale.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vanderbilt Multidimensiyonel Pain Coping Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Patients are asked to mark their preferred behaviors and the thoughts of the hospital when their pain is moderate or high intensity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic Data Form</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This form prepared by the researcher includes the socio-demographic characteristics of the patients who will participate in the study, the history of the disease, findings related to the characteristics related to pain and exacerbations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF36</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The scale includes 36 questions that evaluate 8 sub-scales of health as physical function, physical role difficulty, pain, general health, vitality, social function, emotional role function, mental health topics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>McGill Melzack Pain Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>It consists of four parts. In the first part, it is desired to mark the shape of the pain on the figure and use the letters &quot;D&quot; if deep pain is heard, &quot;Y&quot; if the pain is superficial, and &quot;D - Y&quot; if the two conditions are experienced at the same time. In the second part, there are twenty word groups that define pain in terms of sensory, perceptual and evaluation. Each of the word groups consists of two-six words that describe pain in different ways. In the third part, there is a time relationship of pain. It includes phrases to understand the continuity and frequency of pain and to identify situations that increase or decrease pain. The last section contains words that indicate the severity of pain. With this questionnaire used in the study, it was aimed to determine the location of the pain, the feeling of the patient, the relationship of pain time, the severity of the pain and the level of livable pain for the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Coping Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The scale determines how chronic pain patients cope with organic or psychogenic pain. It consists of self-coping, helplessness, conscious cognitive interventions, and medical remedy sub-scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Coping Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>It evaluates how often patients with chronic pain use behavioral and cognitive methods to deal with pain. Active as transforming pain, moving away and reducing demand; There are six passive sub-dimensions as retreat, anxiety and rest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">352</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient</arm_group_label>
    <description>The study included individuals whose native language is Turkish, who are literate, over the age of 18, diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis, without cognitive impairment and communication problems, and who want to participate in the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>survey application</intervention_name>
    <description>Data collection tools used in the study; Demographic Data Form, Mcgill and Melzack Pain Questionnaire, Short Form-36 (SF-36), Vanderbilt Multidimensional Pain Coping Inventory (VMPCI), Pain Coping Inventory (PCI), Pain Coping Scale were used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study included individuals whose native language is Turkish, who are literate, over the
        age of 18, diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis, without cognitive impairment and
        communication problems, and who want to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:The study included individuals whose native language is Turkish, who are
        literate, over the age of 18, diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis, without cognitive
        impairment and communication problems, and who want to participate in the study.

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who do not meet the inclusion criteria are excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul Gelisim University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Istanbul/ Avcılar</state>
        <zip>34320</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid Arthritis, pain, coping, validity, reliability</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

