<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04256252</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014TD-NMOSD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04256252</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab at Low dosE for neuromyelitiS optiCa spectrUm disordEr (RESCUE)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rituximab at Low dosE for neuromyelitiS optiCa spectrUm disordEr (RESCUE): a Prospective, Multicenter, Open-label, Follow-up Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tang-Du Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tang-Du Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this research, a prospective, multicenter(Tangdu Hospital of Fourth Military Medical
      University, Xi'an Gaoxin Hospital of Xi'an Medical College, Xianyang Central Hospital, Baoji
      Central Hospital, Xi'an Central Hospital, The First Hospital of Xi'an, The Fourth Hospital of
      Xi'an) open-label, follow-up clinical trial will carry out to evaluate the efficacy and
      safety of low-dose rituximab in treating NMOSD in Northwest China.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder (NMOSD) is a group of autoimmune inflammatory
      demyelinating disease of the central nervous system primarily characterized with recurrent
      optic neuritis and longitudinally extensive transverse myelitis, leading to blindness and
      paralysis. Incremental disability due to clinical attacks make it essential to prevent
      relapses with immunosuppressive therapy. Since the serological pathogenic marker
      anti-aquaporin 4 immunoglobulin G (anti-AQP4 IgG) has been identified, NMOSD has unveiled its
      autoimmune features with close connections to B cell-mediated humoral immunity. Rituximab, a
      chimeric monoclonal antibody directly against human CD20 molecular on the surface of B cells,
      has been reported to deplete peripheral CD20+ B cells and to be highly effective for treating
      NMOSD, and therefore been recommended as first-line therapy for this disorder. Unfortunately,
      there are still no consensus statements on dosing and follow-up regimens, which needs
      investigations to explore the efficacy and safety of different rituximab strategies. Previous
      studies have provided pilot evidence supporting the use of low-dose rituximab in preventing
      relapses in Chinese patients with NMO/NMOSD, however, prospective multicenter studies are
      still needed to determine the effectiveness of the modified strategy in treating NMOSD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Annualized relapse rate at last follow-up visit</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>All the enrolled patients are followed up and annualized relapse rate is determined at last follow-up visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Expanded disability status scale (EDSS) score at last follow-up visit</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>All the enrolled patients are followed up and expanded disability status scale (EDSS) score is determined at last follow-up visit. In general, the minimum and maximum scores of EDSS are 0 and 10, respectively, with higher scores meaning a worse outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rituximab-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rituximab-related adverse events (AEs) are evaluated and the rate of AEs is recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lesions in spinal cords</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes of lesions in spinal cord were evaluated by MRI scanning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating B cell monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequencies of total B cell (CD19+) and memory B cell (CD19+CD27+) in lymphocytes were assessed by flow cytometry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Switch treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Other immunosuppressive agents switched from rituximab and reasons for the switch are recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuromyelitis Optica Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intravenous rituximab was administered at a fixed dose of 100 mg once weekly for 3 weeks, followed by maintenance treatment with 100 mg rituximab every 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>A scheduled therapeutic regimen with low-dose rituximab was performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Age between 16 and 75 years old;

        Meet the 2007 or 2015 revised diagnostic criteria for NMOSD;

        At least two relapses in recent two years and/or at least one attack or relapse in recent
        one years;

        Expanded disability status scale (EDSS) score ≤7.0;

        Willingness to sample collection, imaging study and other disease-related examinations and
        assessments;

        Results of pregnancy tests for female patients with fertility during the screening period
        should be negative and effective contraception was used by the patient and her spouse
        during the study period;

        Patients with informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Other immunosuppressive agents are being used or have been discontinued for less than 3
        months;

        White blood cell count (WBC) &lt;3 ×109/L, neutrophil count &lt;1.5 ×109/L, hemoglobin (HGB) &lt; 85
        g/L, and platelet count (PLT) &lt; 80×109/L;

        Concomitant active liver disease or persistent elevation of transaminases more than three
        times above the normal upper limit;

        Serious cardiovascular, kidney, blood and endocrine diseases, or history of malignant
        tumors, or severe infection;

        Other chronic active immune diseases or stable conditions but requiring immunosuppressants
        or glucocorticoids, such as rheumatoid arthritis, scleroderma, Sjögren's syndrome,
        ulcerative colitis, AIDS, genetic or drug-induced immune deficiency;

        Pregnant or lactating patients and those with family planning during the study period;

        Allergy to rituximab and other components;

        Inability to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hongzeng Li</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Tang-Du Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tang-Du Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hongzeng Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neuromyelitis Optica Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituximab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuromyelitis Optica</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

