<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04259710</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HMO0523-18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04259710</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Do Implementation Intentions Increase Average Daily Step Count.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pedometer Program:Every Step Counts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease is the second major cause of death for women in Israel and the leading
      cause of death among women worldwide. Women have higher mortality rates after a coronary or
      cerebrovascular event compared to men, and receive less attention for prevention and
      treatment of heart disease.

      The risk factors for heart disease among women in Israel are high: 53% of women in the State
      of Israel are overweight or obese and 48% of women do not exercise.

      Increasing physical activity can lower the risk of developing cardiovascular disease in
      women. The literature suggests that even minor changes in behavior can reduce the morbidity,
      mortality and costs to the health care system.

      Pedometers have proven to be an effective tool for increasing physical activity, and have the
      potential to create change in health habits. The pedometer measures steps and is a simple
      measure that gives an estimate of the extent of exercise in terms of steps. The device is
      simple and user-friendly and serves as an indicator of movement as a result of health
      choices. The literature shows that when pedometers are integrated into a support program,
      they provide an incentive to increase physical activity. Supporting software includes, among
      other things - choosing personal goals, close tracking, and self-tracking and re balancing
      systems. &quot;Implementation intention&quot; is a strategy in the form of an &quot;if-then plan&quot; that can
      increase the likelihood of attaining one's goals. It is different than specifying a goal
      intentions as it specifies the when, where and how portions of goal-directed behavior. This
      study seeks to compare the increase in steps in participants randomly assigned in a 2:2:1
      allocation to a goal-setting pedometer intervention, a goal-setting plus implementation
      intentions pedometer intervention vs pedometer only.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Goals-

        1. Increasing step count as measured by a pedometer in hospital employees. The overall goal
           is for each participant to reach 10,000 steps a day at the end of the 12 weeks of
           intervention.

        2. Comparison of increase in steps in participants who undergo an implementation intentions
           intervention in addition to a goal setting intervention to those who receive the goal
           setting intervention alone, to those assigned to pedometer without goal setting
           intervention. The goal setting intevention includes setting weekly goals with the
           investigator, and receiving weekly tips.

           The implementation intention group will fill out an action planning form 3 times during
           the course of the intervention.

           The pedometer only group will receive a pedometer and instructions as to it's use.

        3. Examining the effect of self-efficacy on increasing the amount of steps among program
           participants.

        4. Examining the effect of the program on a measure of burnout in the workplace among
           program participants.

        5. Examining the impact of a program designed to increase physical activity (through
           walking) on self-report of nutrition behavior.

        6. Examining the correlation between emotional self-regulation as measured on a self-report
           measure and success in increasing steps.

        7. Examining the effect of the program on physiological measures: BMI, blood pressure,
           pulse, and waist circumference.

      Target population- Hadassah Medical Center employee and volunteers

      sample size- 180 Hadassah employee and volunteers to be enrolled in the program, using the
      first to enroll method. The sample size was calculated based on an expected 1000 step
      difference between the intervention groups with implementation intentions vs the group
      without implementation intentions. change in the number of steps per day between the control
      group and the intervention groups, as shown in previous studies. Under a 2350 Sd assumption,
      a sample size of 87 participants in each group would provide a power of 80% to detect a 5%
      significance level change.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 21, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Stage 1: Comparison of intervention groups to pedometer only group. Stage 2: Comparison of intervention with implementation intentions to intervention alone</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Step count</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Average step count over 5 days of the last week of participation in the protocol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>systolic and diastolic blood pressure at final visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>weight and height will be combined to report BMI in kg/m^2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>cm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage increase in steps</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>(average daily steps on final visit) - (average daily steps on first visit)/(average daily steps on first visit)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>self report of burnout</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Shiron-Melamed burnout questionnaire 14 item scale, scores range from 14 to 98 with higher scores reflecting more burnout</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>resting heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>heart rate measured over 60 seconds at rest</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>physical activity self efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Schwarzer physical activity self efficacy scale, range 4-20, higher score = higher self efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Sedentary Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>participants will be given a pedometer and instructed how to use it, but will not participate in the goal setting intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer and intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>participants will be given a pedometer and participate in a weekly goal setting meeting with the investigator and will receive weekly tips.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer, intervention and implementation intentions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>participants will be given a pedometer and participate in the weekly goal setting as above. In addition, 3 times during the intervention they will fill out a form that encourages performance of implementation intentions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Goal-setting intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The participant will meet weekly with the investigator, report steps and set goals for the following week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer and intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer, intervention and implementation intentions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Goal setting with implementation intentions</intervention_name>
    <description>In addition to the standard goal-setting intervention, the participant will fill out a form that directs them to perform implementation intentions at weeks 1, 5 and 9.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer, intervention and implementation intentions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pedometer only</intervention_name>
    <description>the participant will be given a pedometer and instructed how to use it.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pedometer only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hadassah employees, volunteers and retirees

          -  able to commit to 12 week program

          -  no medical contraindication to physical activity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unable to walk

          -  unable to maintain and use the pedometer

          -  unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>participant eligibility is based on self-representation of gender identity.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donna R Zwas, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lori` Sloman, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>972-54-494-2639</phone>
    <email>lori@hadassah.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elisheva Leiter, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>972-54-3329044</phone>
    <email>elisheva@hadassah.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Medical Organization, Jerusalem, Israel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Donna R Zwas, PhD,MPH</last_name>
      <phone>011-972-2-6779451</phone>
      <email>dannaz@hadassah.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hadas Lemberg, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>00 972 2 6777572</phone>
      <email>lhadas@hadassah.org.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Donna R Zwas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Cardiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

