<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04253288</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>K160101J</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04253288</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Registration of mOrbidity and Mortality, individUal radioSensitivity and Radiation Technique (PROUST)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROUST</acronym>
  <official_title>The French Registry Of Morbidity And Mortality Reviews (MMR) Meetings: Prospective Registration Of Clinical, Dosimetric And Individual Biological Radiosensitivity Data Of Patients With Severe Radiation Toxicity (PROUST STUDY)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Recently, an increasing international interest has arisen in using morbidity and
      mortality rates to monitor the quality of hospital cares (1, 2). Many hospitals have
      integrated the morbidity and mortality review (MMR) meetings into their governance processes,
      by making them mandatory and more accountable for taking corrective action (3-5).

      Quality of radiotherapy (RT) delivery is highly operator dependent. The operator is a team of
      professionals including radiation oncologists, planning dosimetrists, physicists and
      technicians. Because of this complex, multi-step process, there is margin for error, which
      may affect outcomes and toxicity. Some deviations may have minimal effects on outcome, while
      others may have a profound effect and compromise long-term results. For the morbidity after
      RT, MMR is identified as one of the most adapted process to highlight whether and how these
      meetings provide assurance within the organizations' governance processes in radiation
      departments.

      In France, many teams have not reached a formalized procedure for a systematic MMR.
      Furthermore, implementation of MMR in RT departments is very heterogeneous and not always
      meets the criteria defined by the Health Authorities (HAS) (6).

      Systemic analysis conducted during the MMR is a comprehensive analysis of the situation,
      taking into account all technical and human elements. The diagnosis and type of morbidity
      depends on the irradiated volume, the dose delivered to the organ at risk and the individual
      radiosensitivity.

      Follow-up after RT is important to evaluate outcome results and late toxicity. In general,
      late effects consist of tissue fibrosis and vascular damage, which can result in cosmetic and
      functional deterioration. Some of the radiation-induced sequelea may require particular
      management including hospitalization (lung fibrosis, gastro-intestinal and genito-urinary
      toxicities,..), while for other ones, only local treatments are needed (mucosal toxicity,
      skin fibrosis…). The challenge for clinicians in the frame of the MMR is to make sure that
      there is no controversy about the delivered RT quality and investigate other potential causes
      such as particular intrinsic radiosensitivity of the patient for a given standard treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study consist of a prospective registration in a dedicated database (PROUST) of severe
      radiation toxicity that aims to implement MMR procedure in the French radiotherapy
      departments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Database of MMR boards</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The PROUST national database of MMR boards, will be an opportunity to structure data collection on severe and durable radiation toxicity with an objective evaluation taking into account individual radiosensitivity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Database of MMR boards</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The PROUST national database of MMR boards, will be an opportunity to structure data collection on severe and durable radiation toxicity with an objective evaluation taking into account individual radiosensitivity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Database of MMR boards</measure>
    <time_frame>at 9 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The PROUST national database of MMR boards, will be an opportunity to structure data collection on severe and durable radiation toxicity with an objective evaluation taking into account individual radiosensitivity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Database of MMR boards</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The PROUST national database of MMR boards, will be an opportunity to structure data collection on severe and durable radiation toxicity with an objective evaluation taking into account individual radiosensitivity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Database of MMR boards</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The PROUST national database of MMR boards, will be an opportunity to structure data collection on severe and durable radiation toxicity with an objective evaluation taking into account individual radiosensitivity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>The rating scale NCI/CTCAE v4.03 will be used to differentiate between major and minor complications. Only major complications (grade &gt; 3) will be included in the database.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Associated treatments to radiation</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 0, 3 Months, 6 Months, 9 Months,12 Months, 15 Months, 18 Months, 21 Months and 24 Months</time_frame>
    <description>All drugs used either administered concurrently or sequentially with RT will be recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow-up and management strategy</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 0, 3 Months, 6 Months, 9 Months,12 Months, 15 Months, 18 Months, 21 Months and 24 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients included in the database will have a planned follow-up every 3 to 6 months after inclusion during at least 2 years.The follow-up will be adjusted according to institution policy of the oncologic follow-up in case of regression of the clinical symptoms of toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evolution of life's quality</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 0, 3 Months, 6 Months, 9 Months,12 Months, 15 Months, 18 Months, 21 Months and 24 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation of the quality of life will be conducted using the Short-Form 36 questionnaire. This generic scale contains 36 items divided into eight dimensions, each corresponding to a different aspect of health and for a comprehensive assessment of the quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Radiotherapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with severe radiation toxicity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who received radiotherapy and developed abnormal radiation-induced toxicity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morbidity Mortality Review (MMR)</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardization of Morbidity Mortality Review (MMR) in radiotherapy centers
National database from MMR board meetings which include clinical , radiation technique and biological parameters of intrinsic radiosensitivity of patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with severe radiation toxicity</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>National database from MMR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Patients who received RT alone or associated to other anti-cancer treatments

          -  Significant and durable toxicity grade &gt; 3 whatever the organs concerned by radiation
             exposure

          -  Completion of baseline clinical and dosimetric data collection

          -  Patients with no psychological, familial, sociological or geographical condition
             potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule

          -  Signed informed consent to participate in the study must be obtained from patients
             after they have been fully informed on the nature and interest to investigated
             radiosensitivity by the investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No formal MMR meeting in the center where the patient has been treated

          -  No clinical and/or dosimetric available data

          -  No quality of life questionnaire completion whatever the cause

          -  Patients who do not agree to have at least one of the planed biologic tests, namely,
             skin biopsy and blood samples.

          -  Absence of affiliation to National French social security system

          -  Patient deprived of freedom or under legal protection (guardianship,curatorship)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yazid BELKACEMI, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique Hôpitaux de Paris (AP-HP)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yazid BELKACEMI, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(0)149814522</phone>
    <phone_ext>+ 33</phone_ext>
    <email>yazid.belkacemi@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David SCHMITZ</last_name>
    <phone>(0) 1 49 81 36 24</phone>
    <phone_ext>+ 33</phone_ext>
    <email>david.schmitz@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MMR</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation toxicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiosensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Late effects</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Datas are own by Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris, please contact sponsor for further information</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

