<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04255225</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UIUC_IRB_16912</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04255225</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Making Activity Time for Cognitive Health</brief_title>
  <acronym>MATCH</acronym>
  <official_title>Making Activity Time for Cognitive Health (MATCH)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 75% of cancer survivors experience some degree of cognitive deficit throughout
      their cancer experience, with upwards of one third of breast cancer survivors reporting
      impairments up to a decade after treatment. Chemotherapy and adjuvant therapy to remove
      cancerous tissue can result in deficits in attention, speed of processing, memory, and
      quality of life. Physical activity has been associated with a number of health benefits for
      breast cancer survivors including improvements in cognitive function. The investigators
      recently reported on the beneficial effects of acute exercise, or single sessions of physical
      activity, on processing speed and spatial working memory in breast cancer survivors,
      suggesting that acute bouts of physical activity may mitigate select domains of CRCI.
      Specifically, survivors in this study demonstrated faster processing speed, and trended
      towards faster and more accurate spatial working memory, after thirty minutes of
      moderate-intensity walking compared to seated rest. But half an hour of walking may be
      challenging to certain subgroups of survivors, particularly those who are deconditioned or
      with significant barriers to longer walks. With a renewed focus on un-bouted physical
      activity and avoiding inactivity during survivorship, it is important to better understand
      the dose or volume of exercise responsible for providing breast cancer survivors with the
      greatest cognitive benefits. The investigators examined the effects of varying durations of
      exercise (e.g., 10, 20 and 30 minutes) on cognitive function in breast cancer survivors to
      identify the optimal length of acute exercise. Findings from this study will inform new
      guidelines for acute exercise after cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in working memory by walking as a function of walking duration (10, 20 or 30 minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>All participants will complete both a walking and a sitting session, but the duration of these sessions will be determined randomly. Prior to each session, participants will complete a cognitive battery consisting of a working memory task (Spatial Working Memory domain). They will then complete the same cognitive battery immediately after the session. Accuracy ranges from 0-100% and reaction time ranges from 0-5000 milliseconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in attention by walking as a function of walking duration (10, 20 or 30 minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>All participants will complete both a walking and a sitting session, but the duration of these sessions will be determined randomly. Prior to each session, participants will complete a cognitive battery consisting of an attention task (Flanker task). They will then complete the same cognitive battery immediately after the session. Accuracy ranges from 0-100% and reaction time ranges from 0-5000 milliseconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive flexibility by walking as a function of walking duration (10, 20 or 30 minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>All participants will complete both a walking and a sitting session, but the duration of these sessions will be determined randomly. Prior to each session, participants will complete a cognitive battery consisting of a cognitive flexibility task (Task Switching Paradigm). They will then complete the same cognitive battery immediately after the session. Accuracy ranges from 0-100% and reaction time ranges from 0-5000 milliseconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in processing speed by walking as a function of walking duration (10, 20 or 30 minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>All participants will complete both a walking and a sitting session, but the duration of these sessions will be determined randomly. Prior to each session, participants will complete a cognitive battery consisting of a processing speed task (Letter Comparison task). They will then complete the same cognitive battery immediately after the session. Accuracy ranges from 0-100% and reaction time ranges from 0-5000 milliseconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lifestyle physical activity as a predictor of change in cognitive function (executive function domains: working memory, attention/inhibition/cognitive flexibility and processing speed) after acute exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators are interested in determining what lifestyle factors are associated with significant change in cognition (processing speed, working memory, attention/inhibition, cognitive flexibility) from pre- to post-acute exercise. Lifestyle physical activity will be measured via accelerometer in units of average minutes per day. Higher values indicate greater levels of lifestyle physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental health as a predictor of change in cognitive function (executive function domains: working memory, attention/inhibition/cognitive flexibility and processing speed) after acute exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators are interested in determining what mental health factors are associated with significant change in cognition (processing speed, working memory, attention/inhibition, cognitive flexibility) from pre- to post-acute exercise. Mental health factors of interest are anxiety and depression as measured via the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) questionnaire. Scores range from 0-21 with higher scores indicating increased anxiety and depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index as a predictor of change in cognitive function (executive function domains: working memory, attention/inhibition/cognitive flexibility and processing speed) after acute exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators are interested in determining is body mass index associated with significant change in cognition (processing speed, working memory, attention/inhibition, cognitive flexibility) from pre- to post-acute exercise. Body mass index will be measured using the standard kilograms/meters^2. Increased body mass index indicates worsened health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in anxiety levels after one bout of exercise as assessed by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a short anxiety questionnaire before and after a 30 minute bout of aerobic exercise. The investigators will then compare the pre- and post- values to examine if any changes are present. Scores on the HADS range from 0-21 with higher scores indicating increased anxiety and depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Cancer-related Problem/Condition</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>10-minute Treadmill Walking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will walk on the treadmill and perform a battery of cognitive tasks immediately prior and immediately after the walking session. Participants will be randomized the length of time spent walking on the treadmill: 10, 20 or 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>20-minute Treadmill Walking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will walk on the treadmill and perform a battery of cognitive tasks immediately prior and immediately after the walking session. Participants will be randomized the length of time spent walking on the treadmill: 10, 20 or 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>30-minute Treadmill Walking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will walk on the treadmill and perform a battery of cognitive tasks immediately prior and immediately after the walking session. Participants will be randomized the length of time spent walking on the treadmill: 10, 20 or 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walking for 10 minutes</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will walk on a treadmill for 10 minutes at a moderate intensity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>10-minute Treadmill Walking</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walking for 20 minutes</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will walk on a treadmill for 20 minutes at a moderate intensity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>20-minute Treadmill Walking</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walking for 30 minutes</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will walk on a treadmill for 30 minutes at a moderate intensity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>30-minute Treadmill Walking</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women over the age of 18

          -  diagnosis of breast cancer

          -  no longer undergoing treatment

          -  fluent in English

          -  no history of dementia or organic brain syndrome

          -  not currently pregnant

          -  able to walk unassisted

          -  no health reasons that would prevent ability to exercise

          -  not currently enrolled in another exercise research study

          -  reported trouble with memory/concentration

          -  physician's consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  male

          -  no diagnosis of breast cancer

          -  under 18 years of age

          -  currently undergoing treatment for breast cancer

          -  inability to communicate in English

          -  history of dementia or organic brain syndrome

          -  pregnant

          -  unable to walk unassisted

          -  other health reasons that may prevent ability to exercise

          -  enrolled in another exercise research study

          -  no reported trouble with memory or concentration

          -  non-consent of physician
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>All participants will be female breast cancer survivors.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Edward McAuley</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Shahid and Ann Carlson Khan Professor in Applied Health Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

