<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04253366</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DE-17-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04253366</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Investigation to Evaluate the Ability of MammoWave in Breast Lesions Detection</brief_title>
  <acronym>DE-17-17</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicentric, Single Arm, Prospective, Stratified Clinical Investigation to Evaluate the Ability of MammoWave in Breast Lesions Detection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Umbria Bioengineering Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Umbria Bioengineering Technologies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicentric, single arm, prospective, stratified by breast density clinical
      investigation using Mammowave that is a device, which uses microwaves instead of ionizing
      radiation (X-ray)for breast lesions(BL) detection. Specifically, Mammowave employs a novel
      technique which generates images by processing very low power (&lt;1 mW) microwaves. The exam
      takes few minutes per breast and is performed with the patient lying in a comfortable facing
      down position. Mammowave is safe to be used at any age, in any condition (pregnancy, specific
      illness) and for unlimited number of times.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The number of participants will be 500 (for all the sites). The Study will be composed of two
      phases: a preliminary phase to 'optimize the imaging algorithm for each apparatus installed
      at each centre', where 15 healthy volunteers in each centre will be examined by MammoWave. In
      the second phase, the remaining people will be enrolled (Breast Lesions pts will be about 70%
      of total) and examined by MammoWave by the clinical investigator, and results will be
      compared with the effective diagnosis already obtained by standard clinical methods. BL
      includes malignant lesions (BC) and benign lesions, and may be palpable or non-palpable
      lesions. BL includes also isolated clustered microcalcifications.

      At the end of the study, in each centre the clinical investigators will compare MammoWave
      output against the radiologist study output obtained using conventional exams.

      In addition, at the end of the study, the MammoWave output will be centrally reviewed in
      blind by an independent radiologist in order to confirm the data and confirm centrally the
      comparisons performed locally. The primary goal of the clinical study is to assess
      Mammowave's ability in BL detection and differentiation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Clinical investigation with Medical Device class IIa</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MammoWave sensitivity (number of 'true positive' results)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>MammoWave sensitivity (number of 'true positive' results) compared to Reference Standard</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MammoWave specificity and sensitivity (against Reference Standard)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>MammoWave specificity and sensitivity (against Reference Standard like Mammography, MRI and/or Echography)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of correct BL localization in terms of quadrant (against Reference Standard)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of correct BL localization in terms of quadrant comparing to Reference Standard like Mammography, MRI and/or Echography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute and rate agreement between different evaluator (i.e. local radiologist versus central)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Absolute and rate agreement between different evaluator local radiologist versus central, in order to avoid mistakes in the MammoWave output.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity for each breast density group</measure>
    <time_frame>During the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity of MammoWave according to different types of breast density groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity for patients which had recent mammography</measure>
    <time_frame>During the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity for patients which had performed recently mammography exam.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>During the baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction questionnaire output according to their experience performing MammoWave test based on 12 questions:
n° 2 &quot;Multiple Choice questions&quot;
YES, NO, explain (with open-ended text area) regarding:
The effective execution of MammoWave
The willing to promote MammoWave
n° 5 &quot;5 point Numeric Rating scale&quot; ranging from 1 to 5 (1=Not at all, 5= A lot) regarding the subjective evaluation of MammoWave.
n° 5 &quot;3 point Numeric Rating scale&quot; ranging from 1 to 3 (1=less, 3= more) regarding the comparative evaluation of MammoWave vs Conventional tests (Mammography, Ultrasound, Magnetic Resonance Imaging).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients perform standard breast screening and also MammoWave exam.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical investigation device class IIa not marked CE</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients should perform MammoWave exam. A short visit should be performed and during this visit a qualitative differentiation would be performed between patients with high density breast, and patients with low density breast. After the patients will be ready for the MammoWave exam. The exam will be composed of two phases: the data acquisition and the data processing. During the acquisition that should takes about 10 minutes the patients would be lying in a prone position, on a bed which is part of the MammoWave. The upper part of MammoWave has a container cup shape, which contains the breast, which also has the function of separate it from the internal parts of the device. After patient is on the bed and MammoWave would start to perform the acquisition. Once the acquisition is completed, the data will be processed through an imaging algorithm, which is integrated in the device. The final output will be composed by one or more images, plus one or more parameters describing the images.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed Informed consent Form

          2. Women

          3. Adult ≥18 years old

          4. Having a radiologist study output obtained using conventional exams (such as breast
             specialist visit and mammography and/or ultrasound and/or magnetic resonance imaging)
             within the last month.

          5. Patients willing to comply with study protocol and recommendations.

          6. Patients with intact breast skin (i.e. without bleeding lesion, scar).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients that are enrolled in another clinical study

          2. Patients who belong to any vulnerable group.

          3. Patients with implanted electronics.

          4. Patients who have undergone biopsy less than one week before MammoWave scan

          5. Patients with breast implants

          6. Patients with nipple piercings (unless they are removed before MammoWave exam).

          7. Participation in other studies in the last month before screening

          8. Pregnancy or breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women in order to performe breast screening</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gianluigi Tiberi</last_name>
    <phone>0039 3490564302</phone>
    <email>gianluigi@ubt-tech.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sabatino Tiberi</last_name>
    <email>s.tiberi@ubt-tech.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>Milano</state>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniela BERNARDI, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>00393398023851</phone>
      <email>dnlbernardi@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria S. Martino Di Genova</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <zip>16132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alberto TAGLIAFICO</last_name>
      <phone>010/555 3067</phone>
      <email>Alberto.Tagliafico@unige.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Virgen de la Salud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toledo</city>
        <zip>16132</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cristina ROMERO CASTELLANO, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>0034925269200</phone>
      <email>cromeroc@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 31, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

