<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04257695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-10910</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23DA044327</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04257695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Testing an Intervention to Facilitate Tapering in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>TapPro</acronym>
  <official_title>Developing and Pilot Testing an Intervention to Increase Opioid Tapering in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study proposes to pilot test an intervention to facilitate opioid pain reliever (OPR)
      tapering in primary care. The intervention will incorporate a clinician embedded within
      primary care to follow tapering dose schedules to support providers as well to deliver a
      psychosocial curriculum to support and engage patients. In a pilot randomized controlled
      trial (RCT), the study will examine the preliminary efficacy and feasibility of the
      manualized, protocol-based tapering intervention (&quot;TapPro&quot;) compared to usual care. As there
      is no standard definition or outcome for tapering, the primary efficacy outcome is a decrease
      in OPR dose over six months. Separately, the study proposes a clinically meaningful dose
      reduction (greater than or equal to 30 percent) as a secondary outcome. The central
      hypotheses' are that a tapering intervention with patient and provider support is feasible in
      a primary care setting and can result in greater dose reduction when compared to usual care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In a 24-week randomized controlled trial based in a primary care outpatient clinic, the study
      will recruit 60 patients on moderate to high dose chronic opioid therapy for whom providers
      recommend opioid tapering and randomize 1:1 to an opioid tapering protocolized intervention
      (TapPro) or to usual care. Over six months, participants in the TapPro arm will see a
      clinician in the clinic on a monthly basis and will be in contact over the telephone monthly
      in order to facilitate opioid prescribing and tapering and a pain self-care and coping
      curriculum. In the control arm, participants will see their primary care providers as per
      usual and decisions on opioid prescribing and tapering will be made by the primary care
      providers. Participants will be assessed throughout the study with questionnaires, urine drug
      screens, prescription database review, and medical record review.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in opioid dose over six months</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measure analysis of opioid dosage over six months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid dose reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Dichotomous outcome assessing whether participant reached a thirty percent or greater opioid dose reduction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measure analysis of pain severity, as per the PEG pain screening tool. The PEG is a 3 item scale that assesses pain intensity and interference on a 0 to 10 scale where 0 equals &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 is &quot;pain as bad as you can imagine&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain interference</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of pain interference, as per the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) pain interference subscale. The BPI pain interference subscale is scored as the mean of 7 interference items, scored from 0 (does not interfere) to 10 (completely interferes).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain related self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of pain related self-efficacy, as per the Pain Self-Efficacy Scale. The Pain Self-Efficacy scale consists of 10 questions that assess a patient's confidence in performing tasks in spite of pain. It is scored from 0 (not at all confident) to 6 (completely confident). Higher scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of life score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of two different quality of life scores, as per the EQ-5D and the Assessment of Quality of Life 8-item scale (AQoL-8D). The EQ-5D measures quality of life in 5 different domains in 5 questions. The AQoL-8D measures quality of life in 8 different domains in 35 questions. Higher scores denote greater quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of depression scores, as per the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D). This is a 20 item questionnaire that assesses the frequency of several depressive symptoms, rated from 0 (rarely or none of the time) to 3 (most or all of the time). Lower scores mean fewer depressive symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of anxiety scores, as per the Brief symptom anxiety subscale. This is a 40 item questionnaire that assesses the frequency of symptoms of anxiety. It is scored from 1 (almost never) to 4 (almost always). Lower scores mean less anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain catastrophizing</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of the Pain Catastrophizing Scale. This is a 13 item scale scored from 0 (not at all) to 4 (all the time) about symptoms associated with pain catastrophizing. Lower scores denote less pain catastrophizing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of sleep quality, as per the Adult Sickle Cell Quality of Life Measurement Information System (ASCQ-ME) Sleep Impact Short Form. This is a 5 item survey of sleep symptoms, scored from 1 (always) to 5 (never), with higher scores meaning more problems with sleep.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Misuse</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analysis of opioid misuse, as per the Current Opioid Misuse Measure (COMM) score. It is a 17 item survey, rated from 0 (never) to 4 (very often), assessing behaviors associated with opioid misuse. Higher scores are associated with greater opioid misuse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to six months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Opioid Knowledge score, as per the Survey for Pain Attitudes, Knowledge, and Beliefs (SOPA+KB). This is an 18 question survey that assesses agreement with several pain statements, rated from 1 (do not agree) to 4 (completely agree). Higher scores denote better knowledge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Retention in care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Dichotomous outcome -more than or equal to 1 visit with primary care physician (PCP) during six month study period AND more than or equal to 1 visit with PCP during next six months</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of patients attending clinic visits</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients who attend their clinic visits</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Use</condition>
  <condition>Analgesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TapPro</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Monthly in-person clinic visits with a clinician over six months with monthly telephone follow-up calls. At each visit, a protocol adapted from the Prescription Opioid Taper Study will be provided to participants, who will learn about pain coping, distraction techniques, diaphragmatic breathing, sleep techniques, and progressive muscle relaxation techniques. All are specifically designed for patients with chronic pain on chronic opioid therapy. Telephone follow-up will assist in reinforcing techniques and strategies learned. During in-person visits, taper parameters will be discussed and the provider will work through a dose reduction schedule, if participants are in agreement. At each in-person visit, data on pain severity and interference and readiness to taper will be collected. Additionally, urine drug screens will be obtained. At the conclusion of each in-person visit, the clinician will prescribe opioids if clinically indicated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the usual care arm will continue seeing their primary care providers as indicated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TapPro</intervention_name>
    <description>Manualized intervention administered by a clinician to facilitate opioid tapering during clinical visits.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TapPro</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Chronic prescription opioid use (more than 3 monthly prescriptions from one
             prescribing provider within prior 6 months);

          2. Morphine milligram equivalents (MME) greater than or equal to 50;

          3. Poorly controlled pain (PEG pain score greater than or equal to 5/10);

          4. Providers considering opioid taper, but not yet started.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any malignancy, as per ICD-10 diagnosis;

          2. Any terminal illness with lower than 1 year life expectancy, as per medical record
             review;

          3. Moderate or severe opioid use disorder, as per MINI score;

          4. Inability to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hector R Perez, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Melanie Prinz, BA</last_name>
    <phone>718-920-3601</phone>
    <email>melanie.prinz@einsteinmed.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melanie Prinz, BA</last_name>
      <phone>718-920-3601</phone>
      <email>melanie.prinz@einsteinmed.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hector R Perez, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hector R. Perez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>opioid</keyword>
  <keyword>tapering</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>As this is a pilot study, we have elected to not allow for data to be available to other researchers for secondary analyses.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

