<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04257903</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TUFT-BAEK 2019/114</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04257903</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Different Treatment Modalities for Myofascial Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Different Treatment Methods in Patients With Myofascial Pain Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Trakya University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Trakya University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Myofascial pain dysfunction syndrome (MPDS) is the most common reason for pain and limited
      function of the masticatory system. The low-level laser therapy (LLLT) and occlusal splint
      therapy (OST) are therapeutic options for MPDS. This study aims to evaluate the effect of
      LLLT and OST on pain relief and mandibular movement improvement in patients with myofascial
      pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Myofascial pain dysfunction syndrome in the masticatory muscles is the most common
      temporomandibular disorder. Patients suffer from pain and muscle tenderness and may present
      with or without restricted mouth opening. The etiology of myofascial pain dysfunction
      syndrome is multifactorial including psychological factors, occlusion imbalance, and
      parafunctional habits. Treatments for myofascial pain dysfunction syndrome include education,
      self-care, physical therapy, use of intra-oral appliances, short-term pharmacotherapy,
      behavioral therapy, and relaxation techniques.

      Temporomandibular disorder is most often treated using occlusal splints safely to reduce
      temporomandibular joint load, and subsequently, clinical symptoms, as a reversible therapy.
      Occlusal splints need to be used for at least three months to eliminate temporomandibular
      disorders.

      One of physical therapy is laser treatment. Laser treatment on tissues provides a clinical
      effect called biostimulation, where the basic mechanism occurs at the molecular level.

      The low-level laser has non-invasive and inoffensive characteristics at appropriate
      parameters.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Visual Analogue Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one month after the beginning of treatment and two months after the beginning of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity during muscle palpations. Scores are ranging from 0 to 10. Higher scores mean a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline maximum unassisted mouth opening</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one month after the beginning of treatment and two months after the beginning of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Value of Maximum unassisted mouth opening as a centimeter. Scores are ranging from 0 to 45 centimeters. Higher scores mean a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Myofascial Pain</condition>
  <condition>Splints</condition>
  <condition>Low-Level Laser Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Occlusal Splint Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <description>The data of patients who previously received occlusal splint therapy were evaluated. Participants in the study received occlusal splint therapy, but the investigator did not assign this intervention specifically to the study participants. Participants received occlusal splint therapy as part of routine medical care, and a researcher studied the effect of occlusal splint therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Level Laser Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <description>The data of patients who previously received Low-Level Laser Therapy were evaluated. Participants in the study received Low-Level Laser Therapy, but the investigator did not assign this intervention specifically to the study participants. Participants received Low-Level Laser Therapy as part of routine medical care, and a researcher studied the effect of Low-Level Laser Therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Thracian region
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of myofascial pain syndrome according to The Research Diagnostic Criteria
             for Temporomandibular Disorder.

          -  Individuals between the ages of 18-60

          -  Occlusion of individuals with posterior teeth

          -  Forms of individuals who do not have any systemic disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Disc displacement with or without reduction, with or without limited mouth opening,
             arthralgia, arthritis, arthrosis

          -  Inflammatory connective tissue disease (such as rheumatoid arthritis)

          -  Psychiatric diseases

          -  Tumor

          -  Heart diseases

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Diseases that may cause pain symptoms in other orofacial regions (toothache,
             neuralgia, migraine)

          -  Having received any treatment for headache or bruxism in the last 2 years

          -  Skin infections on the masseter and temporal muscles
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Trakya University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Merkez</city>
        <state>Edirne</state>
        <zip>22030</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Trakya University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aysegul Kurt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myofacial Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Occlusal Splint</keyword>
  <keyword>Low-Level Laser Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

