<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04254627</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GWICTIC-EMphase1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDMRP-PC16GW170044</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04254627</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tumor Necrosis Factor (TNF) and Glucocorticoid Antagonist for Gulf War Illness (GWI)-Associated Multi-symptom Disease Homeostasis Reset</brief_title>
  <official_title>TNF and Glucocorticoid Antagonist for GWI-associated Multi-symptom Disease Homeostasis Reset</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nova Southeastern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RTI International</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rochester General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nova Southeastern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gulf War Illness is a condition that affects multiple major organ systems, resulting in a
      diverse array of symptoms that include debilitating fatigue, memory and cognition
      difficulties, headaches, sleep disturbances, gastrointestinal problems, skin rashes, and
      musculoskeletal/joint pain. This phase I single-site, open-label two-arm study will assess
      the safety and mechanistic efficacy of a sequential etanercept-mifepristone intervention for
      Gulf War Illness. The results of this phase I study will be compared to those from an
      existing short-duration study to identify the optimal duration and dosage for use in a future
      phase II study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a study in male Veterans 45-70 years of age who meet the modified Kansas and Centers
      for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) criteria for GWI (Gulf War Illness) and have high
      physiologic stress. This phase I single-site, open-label, two-arm study will focus on
      optimizing the dosage of a sequential etanercept-mifepristone intervention for GWI. Twenty
      participants will be assessed at baseline, 6, 12, 13, 16 and 24 weeks. The investigators will
      use systems biology methods to perform computational modelling of physiological responses to
      supervised maximal exercise challenge studies on a fitness bicycle at baseline, 16 weeks and
      24 weeks. These analyses will assess the impact of the treatment on homeostatic networks: the
      changes in levels of physiological parameters and the changes in inter-correlations among the
      measured parameters (e.g., cytokines), cross-sectionally and over time. Participants will
      also undergo subjective assessments of functional health, symptom severity, pain, fatigue,
      and cognition at baseline, 6, 12, 13, 16, and 24 weeks. Participants will be observed through
      the treatment period and for 3 months after completion to assess immediate effects and
      durability of the response. The results of this phase I study will be compared to those from
      an existing short-duration study to identify the optimal duration and dosage for use in a
      future phase II study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 9, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety - incidence and severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety is assessed by the incidence and severity of adverse events, by relation to the study intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanistic effects on biomarker relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mechanistic effects on biomarker network dynamics are measured by the change in median summary score for network-level distance between the Gulf War Illness biomarker profile at rest and model-predicted stable (healthy) states. These summary scores have a minimum value of zero and reflect the overall difference between the multidimensional relationships of the immune, autonomic, and neuroendocrine systems of ill participants at rest, relative to predicted values for stable (healthy) states. The analysis will be completed using the results of physical measures and biomarker assays performed on blood draws taken at rest prior to exercise challenges at baseline and 16 weeks. These include a Gulf War Illness-specific nanostring gene expression platform, an 18-multiplex cytokine assay, flow cytometry, neuropeptide, sex and stress hormone panels, and physical autonomic measures. Decreases in summary scores between baseline and 16 weeks indicate a better outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Homeostatic network correction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The degree of correction of the homeostatic network toward normal is measured by the median summary score for network-level differences in connectivity of biomarker networks at multiple times during dynamic exercise challenges. These summary scores have a minimum value of zero and reflect overall changes within the immune, autonomic, and neuroendocrine systems during exercise, relative to predicted values for stable (healthy) states. The analysis will use the results of physical measures and blood draws taken before, during, and after exercise challenges at baseline and 16 weeks. The biomarker assays and physical measures include a Gulf War Illness-specific nanostring gene expression platform, an 18-multiplex cytokine assay, flow cytometry, neuropeptide, sex and stress hormone panels, and physical autonomic measures at multiple times during each exercise challenge and 24 hours afterward. Decreases in summary scores between baseline and 16 weeks indicate a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Gulf War Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive etanercept 50 mg weekly for 12 weeks. After completion of the etanercept course, participants will be randomized between two Arms of mifepristone. Participants randomized to Arm 1 will receive one week of mifepristone at 300 mg daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone 600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive etanercept 50 mg weekly for 12 weeks. After completion of the etanercept course, participants will be randomized between two Arms of mifepristone. Participants randomized to Arm 2 will receive one week of mifepristone at 600 mg (2x300 mg) daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etanercept</intervention_name>
    <description>Etanercept 50 mg weekly injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone 600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Enbrel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mifepristone</intervention_name>
    <description>Mifepristone 300 mg pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mifepristone 600 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mifeprex</other_name>
    <other_name>RU-486</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  45-70 years old

          -  Male sex

          -  In good health by medical history prior to 1990

          -  Davidson Trauma scale score of 50 or higher

          -  Meets modified Kansas and CDC case definition criteria for Gulf War Illness. The
             modified Kansas definition, which includes the CDC criteria, includes the following:

               1. Fatigue after exercise as predominant component (a history of exercise
                  intolerance or exercise-induced worsening of symptoms)

               2. Allowance for normal illnesses of aging, such as hypertension and diabetes, if
                  the conditions are treated and are in demonstrable stable and normal ranges at
                  the time of screening and assessment

               3. Allowance of stable comorbid conditions such as PTSD (post traumatic stress
                  disorder), MDD (major depressive disorder), and TBI (traumatic brain injury) that
                  have not required hospitalization in the 5 years prior to recruitment. Severe TBI
                  is excluded.

          -  Able to provide consent to study

          -  Protective titers for influenza and pneumococcal pneumonia, or updated vaccination for
             these infections

          -  Patients of childbearing potential must practice effective contraception during the
             study, and be willing to continue contraception for at least 6 months after
             intervention

          -  Agrees to participate in follow-up visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current treated or untreated major depression with psychotic or melancholic features,
             schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, delusional disorders, dementias of any type, and
             alcoholism or drug abuse (as determined by self-report, Structured Clinical Interview
             for DSM disorders (SCID-I), and Ham-D)

          -  Known allergy to mifepristone, misoprostol, or medicines that contain misoprostol,
             such as Cytotec or Arthrotec

          -  Current alcohol or tobacco use (self-report)

          -  Current organ failure (as determined by metabolic panel and self-report)

          -  Current treated or untreated rheumatologic and inflammatory disorders, as determined
             by medical diagnosis of one or more of the following: osteoarthritis, rheumatoid
             arthritis (RA), lupus, spondyloarthropathies -- ankylosing spondylitis (AS) and
             psoriatic arthritis (PsA), Sjogren's syndrome, gout, scleroderma, infectious
             arthritis, and polymyalgia rheumatic

          -  Chronic active infections such as HIV, hepatitis B, and hepatitis C (as determined by
             antibody tests; note that HIV testing may not be permitted by all phase II study
             sites)

          -  History of organ transplant (self-report)

          -  Current primary sleep disorders such as insomnias, sleep related breathing disorders,
             etc. (self-report)

          -  History of tuberculosis exposure (determined by purified protein derivative (PPD)
             positivity)

          -  Any allergic disease (self-report) such as food/drug allergies and allergic asthma

          -  Use of medications that could affect immune function (e.g., steroids,
             immunosuppressants) or limit the interpretation of the exercise challenge (e.g., beta
             blockers) (self-report)

          -  Renal insufficiency with serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Hepatic insufficiency (bilirubin &gt;2.5mg/dL or transaminases &gt;5x the ULN) Patients with
             Gilberts syndrome are eligible for the study if other liver function tests are normal,
             regardless of bilirubin level

          -  Currently have no exclusionary diagnoses that could reasonably explain the symptoms of
             their fatiguing illness and their severity, using the exclusion criteria best
             described in the Ambiguities in case definition paper for Chronic Fatigue Syndrome
             (CFS), as described in detail in Reeves, et all 2003, which clarifies exclusionary
             conditions.

          -  Are scheduled for a surgery

        Prohibited concomitant or prior therapies:

          -  Immunosuppressant drugs, including glucocorticoid taper, topical/inhaled
             glucocorticoids

          -  Currently on dialysis

          -  Recipient of bone marrow or organ transplant

          -  Previous or current treatment with angiogenic growth factors, cytokines, gene or stem
             cell therapy

          -  Participating in another interventional clinical trial of an investigational therapy
             within 30 days of consent

          -  Any herbal medicine

          -  Blood thinners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Klimas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nova Southeastern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanpreet Cheema, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(954) 262-2871</phone>
    <email>acheema@nova.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nova Southeastern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davie</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33314</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zena Kirby</last_name>
      <phone>954-262-2870</phone>
      <email>zkirby@nova.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Amanpreet Cheema, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(954) 262-2871</phone>
      <email>acheema@nova.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nancy Klimas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gulf War Illness</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etanercept</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mifepristone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data collected during this trial include a wealth of clinical and biomarker data. Due to the small sample size of the trial, the scope of data sharing may be limited because of the risk of compromising participant privacy. For data that can be shared without compromising participant privacy, de-identified limited access data files will be prepared. Additional options to protect privacy of the participants includes altering the data in ways that will not compromise analyses, and requiring outside researchers to adhere to strict confidentiality requirements. All public-release datasets will conform to HIPAA requirements for protecting participant identity.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Individual Patient Data (IPD) will be released for public sharing after publication of the per-protocol analyses.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>De-identified limited access data sets will be created for public data sharing with investigators proposing analyses related to GWI and related chronic health conditions. To protect the confidentiality and privacy of the subjects, investigators granted access to these data must adhere to strict requirements. These requirements will include, but are not limited to: oversight by an Institutional Review Board (IRB), secure data storage facilities, and agreement not to further release the data. This information will be incorporated into a standard Data Distribution Agreement to which investigators must adhere.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

