<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04252742</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20190008</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-003646-33</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04252742</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Erenumab - Comprehensive Assessment of Efficacy in (High-Frequency) Episodic Migraine</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMBRACE</acronym>
  <official_title>Comprehensive Assessment of Erenumab Efficacy in Subjects With High Frequency Episodic Migraine With at Least 1 Previously Failed Preventive Treatment: a Global, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Phase 4 Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on headache duration of at least moderate pain
      intensity
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 14, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 14, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean monthly hours of at least moderate headache pain intensity, with pain intensity measured by the 11-point NRS scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on headache duration of at least moderate pain intensity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean physical functioning as measured by the Migraine Functional Impact Questionnaire (MFIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on functional impairment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on the Impact of usual activities as measured by the Migraine Functional Impact Questionnaire (MFIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on functional impairment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline on the Impact of emotional functioning as measured by the Migraine Functional Impact Questionnaire (MFIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on functional impairment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean monthly function as impact on social functioning as measured by the Migraine Functional Impact Questionnaire (MFIQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on functional impairment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean monthly hours of at least moderate pain intensity per migraine attack, with pain measured by the 11-point NRS scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on duration of migraine pain of at least moderate intensity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in mean monthly peak migraine pain intensity as assessed by the 11-point Numeric Rating Scale (NRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over months 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the treatment benefit of erenumab on peak migraine pain intensity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">576</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erenumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 4-month DBTP has 2 phases:
Main DBTP (M-DBTP, months 1 to 3) that will assess the effect of erenumab on metrics such as time spent in at least moderate pain, peak migraine severity, and functional impairment.
Exploratory DBTP (E-DBTP, month 4) that will assess the impact of erenumab on the acute response to treatment with oral triptans as well as non-ictal burden.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 4-month DBTP has 2 phases:
Main DBTP (M-DBTP, months 1 to 3) that will assess the effect of erenumab on metrics such as time spent in at least moderate pain, peak migraine severity, and functional impairment.
Exploratory DBTP (E-DBTP, month 4) that will assess the impact of erenumab on the acute response to treatment with oral triptans as well as non-ictal burden.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erenumab</intervention_name>
    <description>140 mg, 2 consecutive injections of 70 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erenumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>2 consecutive injections</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key inclusion criteria include:

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years upon entry into initial screening.

          -  Documented history of migraine with or without aura according to the International
             Headache Society (IHS) International Classification of Headache Disorders, Third
             Edition (ICHD-III) for greater than or equal to 12 months.

          -  History of treatment failure with at least 1 preventive treatment for migraine.
             Failure of preventive treatment for migraine is defined as treatment discontinuation
             due to lack of efficacy, adverse event, or general poor tolerability.

        Key exclusion criteria include:

          -  History of hemiplegic migraine, cluster headache, or other trigeminal autonomic
             cephalalgia.

          -  Has any medical contraindication to the use of an oral triptan.

          -  Previously treated with any agent (monoclonal antibody or small molecule) targeting
             the calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) pathway (ligand or receptor) in the
             preventive setting.

          -  No therapeutic response with greater than 4 of the defined medication categories after
             an adequate therapeutic trial.

          -  Use of triptans administered via a non-oral (e.g. subcutaneous [SC] or intranasal
             delivery systems) or sublingual route at the time of screening, during the run-in and
             baseline periods, and throughout the study duration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amgen Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>866-572-6436</phone>
    <email>medinfo@amgen.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Erenumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual patient data for variables necessary to address the specific research question in an approved data sharing request</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data sharing requests relating to this study will be considered beginning 18 months after the study has ended and either 1) the product and indication (or other new use) have been granted marketing authorization in both the US and Europe or 2) clinical development for the product and/or indication discontinues and the data will not be submitted to regulatory authorities. There is no end date for eligibility to submit a data sharing request for this study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Qualified researchers may submit a request containing the research objectives, the Amgen product(s)and Amgen study/studies in scope, endpoints/outcomes of interest, statistical analysis plan, data requirements, publication plan, and qualifications of the researcher(s). In general, Amgen does not grant external requests for individual patient data for the purpose of re-evaluating safety and efficacy issues already addressed in the product labelling. Requests are reviewed by a committee of internal advisors, and if not approved, may be further arbitrated by a Data Sharing Independent Review Panel. Upon approval, information necessary to address the research question will be provided under the terms of a data sharing agreement. This may include anonymized individual patient data and/or available supporting documents, containing fragments of analysis code where provided in analysis specifications. Further details are available at the link below.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://www.amgen.com/datasharing</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

