<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03923959</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LancasterGH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03923959</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of TXA Prior to Surgery in the Geriatric Hip Fracture Population</brief_title>
  <acronym>TAHFT</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Tranexamic Acid Prior to Surgery in the Geriatric Hip Fracture Population for the Reduction of Post-Operative Blood Transfusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lancaster General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lancaster General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall design of the study is a prospective, double-blinded, randomized study in the
      geriatric hip fracture population comparing those who receive intravenous tranexamic acid
      prior to incision to those who receive a placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A significant portion of the geriatric hip fracture population have comorbidities including
      chronic kidney disease, congestive heart failure, ischemic heart disease, stroke, etc. These
      patients may be anemic prior to the surgery, and are at increased risk for further blood loss
      as a result of the fracture and surgical operation. However, intra-operative or
      post-operative blood transfusions also increase the risk of renal and cardiac complications
      in this population.

      Tranexamic acid (TXA) is an anti-fibrinolytic medication that has transformed total joint
      replacement management regarding blood loss prevention. Geriatric patients requiring emergent
      hip fracture repair may significantly benefit from routine administration of TXA prior to the
      procedure to decrease the risk of blood loss. Thus, treatment may further reduce the
      percentage of patients who experience blood transfusions and complications associated with
      transfusions.

      The investigators will examine if administration of TXA prior to incision in the geriatric
      hip fracture patient population decreases the risk of intra-operative or post-operative blood
      transfusions compared to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A prospective, double-blinded, randomized study in the geriatric hip fracture population comparing those who receive intravenous tranexamic acid prior to incision to those who receive a placebo.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>All OR pharmacists are un-blinded to subject randomization.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Transfusions</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the percentage of patients that receive acute post-operative transfusions in the group administered intravenous tranexamic acid compared to the group administered placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complication Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Determine if participants randomized to TXA experienced increased risk of complications compared to placebo. Complications include number of deep vein thrombosis events, pulmonary emboli events, myocardial infarction events, and cerebral vascular events within 12 weeks post hip fracture surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Determine differences between the groups in 30 day readmission rates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>90 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Death within 90 days post hip surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 cc normal saline with 1g of tranexamic acid in solution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 cc normal saline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid Injectable Solution</intervention_name>
    <description>100 cc normal saline mixed with 1g of tranexamic acid in solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cyklokapron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>100 cc normal saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provision of written informed consent

          2. Age &gt; or = to 65 years

          3. Hip fracture location within the femoral neck, intertrochanteric, and subtrochanteric
             regions

          4. Indication for one of the following surgical interventions: hemiarthroplasty, total
             hip replacement, sliding plate and screw fixation, or intramedullary fixation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Indication for closed reduction or percutaneous screw

          2. Allergy to TXA

          3. Cerebrovascular accident/stroke, active coronary disease/myocardial infarction, or
             deep vein thrombosis/pulmonary emboli within one (1) month of the fracture

          4. Presence of hypercoaguable disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory Tocks, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn Medicine / Lancaster General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cathleen C Forney, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>717-544-1402</phone>
    <email>cathleen.forney@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>MIke Horst, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>717-544-5999</phone>
    <email>michael.horst@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lancaster General Heatlh / Penn Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lancaster</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17602</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cathleen Forney, MBA</last_name>
      <phone>717-544-1777</phone>
      <email>cforney2@lghealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>MIke Horst, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>7175445999</phone>
      <email>mahorst@lghealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farrow LS, Smith TO, Ashcroft GP, Myint PK. A systematic review of tranexamic acid in hip fracture surgery. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2016 Dec;82(6):1458-1470. doi: 10.1111/bcp.13079. Epub 2016 Sep 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27492116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eubanks JD. Antifibrinolytics in major orthopaedic surgery. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2010 Mar;18(3):132-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20190103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ponnusamy KE, Kim TJ, Khanuja HS. Perioperative blood transfusions in orthopaedic surgery. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2014 Nov 5;96(21):1836-44. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.N.00128. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25378512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kagoma YK, Crowther MA, Douketis J, Bhandari M, Eikelboom J, Lim W. Use of antifibrinolytic therapy to reduce transfusion in patients undergoing orthopedic surgery: a systematic review of randomized trials. Thromb Res. 2009 Mar;123(5):687-96. doi: 10.1016/j.thromres.2008.09.015. Epub 2008 Nov 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19007970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carson JL, Duff A, Poses RM, Berlin JA, Spence RK, Trout R, Noveck H, Strom BL. Effect of anaemia and cardiovascular disease on surgical mortality and morbidity. Lancet. 1996 Oct 19;348(9034):1055-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8874456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fillingham YA, Ramkumar DB, Jevsevar DS, Yates AJ, Shores P, Mullen K, Bini SA, Clarke HD, Schemitsch E, Johnson RL, Memtsoudis SG, Sayeed SA, Sah AP, Della Valle CJ. The Efficacy of Tranexamic Acid in Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Network Meta-analysis. J Arthroplasty. 2018 Oct;33(10):3083-3089.e4. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2018.06.023. Epub 2018 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>30007789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fillingham YA, Ramkumar DB, Jevsevar DS, Yates AJ, Shores P, Mullen K, Bini SA, Clarke HD, Schemitsch E, Johnson RL, Memtsoudis SG, Sayeed SA, Sah AP, Della Valle CJ. The Safety of Tranexamic Acid in Total Joint Arthroplasty: A Direct Meta-Analysis. J Arthroplasty. 2018 Oct;33(10):3070-3082.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2018.03.031. Epub 2018 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>29699826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carling MS, Jeppsson A, Eriksson BI, Brisby H. Transfusions and blood loss in total hip and knee arthroplasty: a prospective observational study. J Orthop Surg Res. 2015 Mar 28;10:48. doi: 10.1186/s13018-015-0188-6.</citation>
    <PMID>25889413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alshryda S, Mason J, Sarda P, Nargol A, Cooke N, Ahmad H, Tang S, Logishetty R, Vaghela M, McPartlin L, Hungin AP. Topical (intra-articular) tranexamic acid reduces blood loss and transfusion rates following total hip replacement: a randomized controlled trial (TRANX-H). J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2013 Nov 6;95(21):1969-74. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.L.00908.</citation>
    <PMID>24196467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alshryda S, Mason J, Vaghela M, Sarda P, Nargol A, Maheswaran S, Tulloch C, Anand S, Logishetty R, Stothart B, Hungin AP. Topical (intra-articular) tranexamic acid reduces blood loss and transfusion rates following total knee replacement: a randomized controlled trial (TRANX-K). J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2013 Nov 6;95(21):1961-8. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.L.00907.</citation>
    <PMID>24196466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benoni G, Lethagen S, Nilsson P, Fredin H. Tranexamic acid, given at the end of the operation, does not reduce postoperative blood loss in hip arthroplasty. Acta Orthop Scand. 2000 Jun;71(3):250-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10919295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajesparan K, Biant LC, Ahmad M, Field RE. The effect of an intravenous bolus of tranexamic acid on blood loss in total hip replacement. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2009 Jun;91(6):776-83. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.91B6.22393.</citation>
    <PMID>19483232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>North WT, Mehran N, Davis JJ, Silverton CD, Weir RM, Laker MW. Topical vs Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Double-Blind, Randomized Controlled Trial. J Arthroplasty. 2016 May;31(5):1022-6. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2015.11.003. Epub 2015 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26703193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kayupov E, Fillingham YA, Okroj K, Plummer DR, Moric M, Gerlinger TL, Della Valle CJ. Oral and Intravenous Tranexamic Acid Are Equivalent at Reducing Blood Loss Following Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Randomized Controlled Trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2017 Mar 1;99(5):373-378. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.16.00188.</citation>
    <PMID>28244907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imai N, Dohmae Y, Suda K, Miyasaka D, Ito T, Endo N. Tranexamic acid for reduction of blood loss during total hip arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2012 Dec;27(10):1838-43. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2012.04.024. Epub 2012 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22704229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fillingham YA, Kayupov E, Plummer DR, Moric M, Gerlinger TL, Della Valle CJ. The James A. Rand Young Investigator's Award: A Randomized Controlled Trial of Oral and Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Total Knee Arthroplasty: The Same Efficacy at Lower Cost? J Arthroplasty. 2016 Sep;31(9 Suppl):26-30. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2016.02.081. Epub 2016 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27113948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gomez-Barrena E, Ortega-Andreu M, Padilla-Eguiluz NG, Pérez-Chrzanowska H, Figueredo-Zalve R. Topical intra-articular compared with intravenous tranexamic acid to reduce blood loss in primary total knee replacement: a double-blind, randomized, controlled, noninferiority clinical trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2014 Dec 3;96(23):1937-44. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.N.00060.</citation>
    <PMID>25471907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levine BR, Haughom BD, Belkin MN, Goldstein ZH. Weighted versus uniform dose of tranexamic acid in patients undergoing primary, elective knee arthroplasty: a prospective randomized controlled trial. J Arthroplasty. 2014 Sep;29(9 Suppl):186-8. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2014.01.038. Epub 2014 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24997651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. Research electronic data capture (REDCap)--a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. J Biomed Inform. 2009 Apr;42(2):377-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010. Epub 2008 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18929686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 22, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Blood</keyword>
  <keyword>Transfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Hip</keyword>
  <keyword>Fracture</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Trauma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

