<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03921502</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03921502</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial Comparing ERCP vs ERCP and Transmural Gall Bladder Drainage</brief_title>
  <acronym>PECAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Multicentre Double-blind Clinical Trial Comparing ERCP vs ERCP and Transmural Gall Bladder Drainage in Non-surgical Patients With Symptomatic Choledocholithiasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital del Río Hortega</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Ramon y Cajal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital General Universitario de Alicante</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital del Río Hortega</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cholelithiasis occurs in 10-20% of the general population. Up to 18% of these subjects will
      present symptoms. In patients with symptomatic choledocholithiasis who are not candidates for
      surgery with indication for ERCP, transmural drainage of the gallbladder reduces the risk of
      recurrence.

      The investigators propose a multicentric double-blind randomized trial. Our primary objective
      is to assess whether ERCP associated with transmural gallbladder drainage is able to reduce
      biliary disease income compared with ERCP in patients not candidates for surgery with
      symptomatic choledocholithiasis and cholelithiasis during one year of follow-up. Also the
      investigators will analyze the proportion of technical success and complications.

      The study population includes all patients older than 75 years with symptomatic
      choledocholithiasis. An estimated 75 subjects per group (ERCP alone and ERCP and transmural
      drainage) are needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Introduction Cholelithiasis occurs in 10-20% of the general population (1). Up to 18% of
           these subjects will present symptoms and, of these, 1.5% will present an episode of
           pancreatitis, cholecystitis or acute cholangitis (2). In this way, the pathology
           associated with biliary lithiasis is the first digestive cause of hospital admission
           (3).

           The treatment of the pathology associated with biliary lithiasis therefore deals with
           two problems, controlling the acute process and preventing new episodes. In general,
           laparoscopic cholecystectomy is the recommended method to reduce the risk of recurrence.

        2. Hypothesis

           Conceptual hypothesis:

           In patients with symptomatic choledocholithiasis who are not candidates for surgery with
           indication for ERCP, transmural drainage of the gallbladder reduces the risk of
           recurrence.

           Operational hypothesis:

           In subjects&gt; 75 years with symptomatic choledocholithiasis, performing an ERCP with
           sphincterotomy and transmural drainage of the gallbladder vs. ERCP with sphincterotomy
           reduces the risk of admission due to complications of cholelithiasis during a 1-year
           follow-up period.

        3. Objectives.

           Primary objective:

           - To assess whether ERCP associated with transmural gallbladder drainage is able to
           reduce biliary disease income compared with ERCP in patients not candidates for surgery
           with symptomatic choledocholithiasis and cholelithiasis during one year of follow-up.

           Secondary objectives:

             -  Describe the proportion of technical successes and complications associated with
                transmural biliary drainage, ERCP and those associated with admission.

             -  Compare the proportion of income from non-biliary causes in both groups.

             -  Compare mortality during admission and during follow-up in both groups.

             -  To compare the incidence of biliary and non-biliary admissions during the follow-up
                year in both groups.

             -  Compare the hospital costs of the index income and those generated in the 12 months
                of follow-up between the patients assigned to the control group and the
                experimental group.

        4. Design Multicentric double-blind randomized trial

        5. Methods Study population The study population includes all patients older than 75 years
           with symptomatic choledocholithiasis. This includes the pictures of acute cholangitis,
           obstructive jaundice or biliary colic secondary to choledocholithiasis. Participation in
           the study will be offered to all consecutive patients who meet inclusion criteria and do
           not present exclusion criteria diagnosed in the participating centers once the project
           is started until the estimated sample size is completed (see below). Given that in these
           patients the usual clinical practice is the realization of an ERCP, they will be
           identified from the ERCP requests received in the endoscopy units.

      Intervention Patients who meet the inclusion criteria and do not present any exclusion
      criteria will be invited to participate in the study. Between the formalization of the
      request and the endoscopic exploration the informed consent will be completed according to
      the law 41/2002 of autonomy of the patient without that for that reason the relationship with
      his doctor is altered or there is any prejudice in his treatment.

        1. Endoscopic act

           It will be held at the Rio Hortega University Hospital, the University General Hospital
           of Alicante or the Ramón y Cajal University Hospital. First, ERCP will be performed.
           Subsequently, an endoscopic ultrasound will be performed to rule out local causes of
           exclusion. If there is no contraindication, randomization and placement of transmural
           vesicular drainage will be carried out if assigned to the intervention group:

             -  Control group: An ERCP with biliary sphincterotomy will be performed. The
                performance of other techniques (balloon extraction, dilation, placement of biliary
                prosthesis ...) is at the expense of the endoscopist. The procedure will be
                performed under direct sedation with propofol controlled by the endoscopist team,
                and with CO2 (carbon dioxide) insufflation.

             -  Intervention group: ERCP with biliary sphincterotomy will be performed. The
                performance of other techniques (balloon extraction, dilation, placement of biliary
                prosthesis ...) is at the expense of the endoscopist. After this, transmural
                drainage of the gallbladder will be performed by placing a LAMS (lumen apposing
                metal stent) Axios (Boston Scientific) usually 15x10 mm or 10x10 mm to allow direct
                cholecystoscopy with a conventional gastroscope or transnasal gastroscope. The
                placement of the drainage will be performed in the same endoscopic act, by means of
                an Olympus® sectorial echoendoscope, assisted with X-rays, which allows puncturing
                the vesicle from the gastric antrum or the duodenal bulb to generate a
                cholecysto-gastrostomy or cholecysto-duodenostomy respectively. After the puncture
                of the vesicle from the most optimal anatomical point, it will be tutored with
                guidance and a Hot Axios® LAMS will be placed on it to generate the anastomosis
                between the aforementioned structures. After the placement of the prosthesis, it
                will be subject to the decision of the endoscopist to perform cholescystoscopy to
                perform the maneuvers it deems appropriate (extraction of stones, taking biopsies,
                resection of polyps ...). The performance of both procedures will be performed
                under direct sedation with propofol controlled by the endoscopist team, and with
                CO2 insufflation, according to the usual practice of the HURH (Universitary
                Hospital Río Hortega) Endoscopy Unit.

        2. Hospitalization:

      After the procedure, the hospital management is in the hands of its responsible physicians in
      plant at the requesting center. A report will be delivered that does not show if the patient
      has had the LAMS implanted or not. Therefore, physicians responsible for plant management
      will not receive information about the assigned group or whether transmural vesicular
      drainage has been performed.

      C.3) Follow-up:

      It will be held in each of the participating centers. It will consist of 4 face-to-face
      visits (after 1 day, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months after the procedure) and 2 phone calls
      (7 days after the procedure and 9 months). In the case of institutionalized patients or those
      with serious mobility problems, in-person visits may be made by telephone in an exceptional
      manner. The physician responsible for the follow-up will be blinded as to the procedure
      performed (it will not be specified if transmural drainage was performed in the endoscopic
      report, nor will images of the drainage be included in the discharge report available in the
      electronic medical record until after the completion of the study or if complications are
      suspected). During the follow-up visits, it will be confirmed that the prosthesis remains
      normalized by abdominal ultrasound.

      Sample size Assuming a proportion of readmissions of biliary cause of 25% in the control
      group and 7% in the experimental group, with an alpha risk of 5% and a power of 80% and using
      the arc transformation sine given the proportion of the experimental group, an estimated 60
      subjects per group are needed. Given the age of the patients to be included and the mortality
      associated with the underlying disease, a proportion of losses of 20% is estimated, which
      would require 75 patients per group. The annual number of ERCP performed at the Río Hortega
      university hospital ranges from 1,000 to 1100. Assuming also a number of examinations to be
      carried out in the collaborating centers, with the inclusion and exclusion criteria exposed,
      a recruitment interval of 12-18 months is estimated.

      Randomization It will be done once the patient agrees to participate in the work and has
      verified the absence of exclusion criteria. To avoid imbalances between the groups, it will
      be stratified by baseline diagnosis (cholangitis vs others), given that the mortality during
      admission associated with acute cholangitis is significantly greater than in the rest of the
      included conditions. Within each stratum a pure randomization will be carried out by means of
      a sequence generated by computer where the probability of belonging to each group will be
      0.5. For each stratum, there will be a total of n numbered closed opaque envelopes (where n =
      total sample size) that will be stored in the endoscopy unit and will be opened consecutively
      as participants are included.

      Adverse effects monitoring The adverse effects identified during the study will be classified
      according to the classification of ASGE (for adverse endoscopic effects) for those associated
      with hospitalization. According to the interval from the procedure they will be divided
      between postprocedure (in the first 7 days from the same) and late (after this time). Its
      relationship with the procedure will be classified as definitive, probable, possible or
      improbable.

      Data Collect The data collection will be done by the main researcher or collaborating
      researchers through a data collection notebook (CRD) anonymously and dissociated from the
      clinical information by means of a patient identification code.

      6. Data management Data from the data collection notebooks will be merged by the main
      researcher or collaborating researchers anonymously, encrypted and decoupled from the
      clinical information by means of a patient identification code (ID), in a database made
      through the application RedCap available through the Spanish Association of Gastroenterology
      and the data will be downloaded in the form of an Excel file (Microsoft Corporation,USA). The
      responsible researcher will define an ID for each participant. The data entered in the
      database will be anonymous and the database will be protected with a password to which only
      the researchers will have access.

      The unified file will be kept in the Río Hortega University Hospital and will be maintained
      until the end of the study. Regarding the application of the Organic Law on Data Protection
      15/1999 and Royal Decree 1720/2007 that develops it, it should be noted that the protocol
      defined in the project oriented to epidemiological analysis, determines that the files will
      record information completely anonymized.

      7. Statistical analysis It will be done through the STATA program (StataCorp, 2013. Stata
      Statistical Software: Release 13. College Station, StataCorp LP).

      Descriptive analysis In the quantitative variables the arithmetic average and the standard
      deviation will be calculated (the variables that do not follow a normal distribution will be
      described with median, minimum, maximum and interquartile range), and the categorical ones
      will be expressed as percentages and their 95% confidence intervals .

      Hypothesis contrast The analysis of the primary objective, the hospital admission of biliary
      cause, will be carried out through the Z test of homogeneity without using the correction of
      Yates. The confidence interval of the difference between the two groups will also be
      estimated. An intention-to-treat analysis will be performed, regardless of the endoscopic
      treatment received after randomization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multicentric double-blind randomized trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The patient and the physician responsible for the follow-up will be blinded as to the procedure performed (it will not be specified if transmural drainage was performed in the endoscopic report, nor will images of the drainage be included in the discharge report available in the electronic medical record until after the completion of the study or if complications are suspected).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of paticipants readmitted due to biliary pathology</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of participants readmitted due to biliary pathology (cholecystitis, cholangitis, pancreatitis, hepatic abscess...) in each group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with technical success</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with correct placement of the stent from the gastric or duodenal lumen to the gallbladder, together with the documentation of bile flow and / or contrast through it.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of dead participants</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of deaths in each group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital costs (euros)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital costs (euros) during the period of follow up, including the baseline admission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Bile Duct; Obstruction, With Calculus</condition>
  <condition>Choledocholithiasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ERCP with sphincterotomy + gall bladder drainage with LAMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>An ERCP with biliary sphincterotomy will be performed. The performance of other techniques (balloon extraction, dilation, placement of biliary prosthesis ...) is at the expense of the endoscopist. After this, transmural drainage of the gallbladder will be performed by placing a LAMS Axios (Boston Scientific) usually 15x10 mm or 10x10 mm to allow direct cholecystoscopy with a conventional gastroscope or transnasal gastroscope. The placement of the drainage will be performed in the same endoscopic act, by means of an Olympus® sectorial echoendoscope, assisted with X-rays, which allows puncturing the vesicle from the gastric antrum or the duodenal bulb to generate a cholecysto-gastrostomy or cholecysto-duodenostomy respectively. After the puncture of the vesicle from the most optimal anatomical point, it will be tutored with guidance and a Hot Axios® PAL will be placed on it to generate the anastomosis between the aforementioned structures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ERCP with sphincterotomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>An ERCP with biliary sphincterotomy will be performed. The performance of other techniques (balloon extraction, dilation, placement of biliary prosthesis ...) is at the expense of the endoscopist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gall bladder transmural drainage with LAMS</intervention_name>
    <description>Placing a PAL Axios (Boston Scientific) usually 15x10 mm or 10x10 mm to allow direct cholecystoscopy with a conventional gastroscope or transnasal gastroscope. The placement of the drainage will be performed in the same endoscopic act, by means of an Olympus® sectorial echoendoscope, assisted with X-rays, which allows puncturing the vesicle from the gastric antrum or the duodenal bulb to generate a cholecysto-gastrostomy or cholecysto-duodenostomy respectively. After the puncture of the vesicle from the most optimal anatomical point, it will be tutored with guidance and a Hot Axios® PAL 15x10 mm or 10x10 mm will be *placed on it to generate the anastomosis between the aforementioned structures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ERCP with sphincterotomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ERCP with sphincterotomy + gall bladder drainage with LAMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Symptomatic choledocholithiasis (choledocholithiasis demonstrated radiologically or
             highly suspected by clinical data (acute cholangitis or obstructive jaundice),
             analytical and imaging according to the criteria of high probability of
             choledocholithiasis established in the clinical guidelines (ASGE Guide).

          -  Discarded for surgical treatment due to age, comorbidity or refusal of the patient.

          -  Age&gt;75 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Charlson comorbidity scale adjusted to age &lt;4.

          -  Prior ERCP.

          -  Previous episodes of cholangitis, pancreatitis or lithiasic cholecystitis.

          -  Hepatobiliary surgery or previous superior digestive tract.

          -  Ascitis.

          -  Inability to tolerate sedation of endoscopy, perforation of the digestive tract or
             other contraindication to endoscopy.

          -  Coagulopathy with INR (international normalized ratio) &gt; 1.5 not correctable or
             thrombocytopenia &lt;50000 / mm3 not correctable.

          -  Other diagnoses at admission (acute cholecystitis, acute pancreatitis, biliopancreatic
             neoplasia).

          -  Hemodynamic instability.

          -  Urgent procedure performed after hours

          -  No availability of expert material / endoscopist in drainage.

          -  Anatomical impossibility of performing biliary drainage (absence of vesicular
             distension, contact between gallbladder and stomach or duodenum, contact area &lt;10 mm).

          -  Baseline ECOG (Easthern Cooperative Oncology Group) &gt; = 4

          -  Expectancy of survival &lt;6 months.

          -  Refusal to participate.

          -  Distance between the gallbladder and upper digestive tract&gt; 1cm, scleroatrophic
             vesicle, lack of stable acoustic window for drainage

          -  ERCP failed (inhability to dain common bile duct)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>75 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ana Y Carbajo López, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Río Hortega</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marina de Benito Sanz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>983420400</phone>
    <phone_ext>84326</phone_ext>
    <email>mbenitosa@saludcastillayleon.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Manuel Pérez-Miranda Castillo, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>983420400</phone>
    <phone_ext>84408</phone_ext>
    <email>mperezmiranda@saludcastillayleon.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Rio Hortega</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <zip>47012</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marina De Benito, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee TH, Park DH, Lee SS, Seo DW, Park SH, Lee SK, Kim MH, Kim SJ. Outcomes of endoscopic transpapillary gallbladder stenting for symptomatic gallbladder diseases: a multicenter prospective follow-up study. Endoscopy. 2011 Aug;43(8):702-8. doi: 10.1055/s-0030-1256226. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21425042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choi JH, Lee SS, Choi JH, Park DH, Seo DW, Lee SK, Kim MH. Long-term outcomes after endoscopic ultrasonography-guided gallbladder drainage for acute cholecystitis. Endoscopy. 2014 Aug;46(8):656-61. doi: 10.1055/s-0034-1365720. Epub 2014 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>24977397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walter D, Teoh AY, Itoi T, Pérez-Miranda M, Larghi A, Sanchez-Yague A, Siersema PD, Vleggaar FP. EUS-guided gall bladder drainage with a lumen-apposing metal stent: a prospective long-term evaluation. Gut. 2016 Jan;65(1):6-8. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2015-309925. Epub 2015 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26041748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahaleh M, Perez-Miranda M, Artifon EL, Sharaiha RZ, Kedia P, Peñas I, De la Serna C, Kumta NA, Marson F, Gaidhane M, Boumitri C, Parra V, Rondon Clavo CM, Giovannini M. International collaborative study on EUS-guided gallbladder drainage: Are we ready for prime time? Dig Liver Dis. 2016 Sep;48(9):1054-7. doi: 10.1016/j.dld.2016.05.021. Epub 2016 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27328985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de la Serna-Higuera C, Pérez-Miranda M, Gil-Simón P, Ruiz-Zorrilla R, Diez-Redondo P, Alcaide N, Sancho-del Val L, Nuñez-Rodriguez H. EUS-guided transenteric gallbladder drainage with a new fistula-forming, lumen-apposing metal stent. Gastrointest Endosc. 2013 Feb;77(2):303-8. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2012.09.021. Epub 2012 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23206813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCarthy ST, Tujios S, Fontana RJ, Rahnama-Moghadam S, Elmunzer BJ, Kwon RS, Wamsteker EJ, Anderson MA, Scheiman JM, Elta GH, Piraka CR. Endoscopic Transpapillary Gallbladder Stent Placement Is Safe and Effective in High-Risk Patients Without Cirrhosis. Dig Dis Sci. 2015 Aug;60(8):2516-22. doi: 10.1007/s10620-014-3371-4. Epub 2014 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25287001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itoi T, Sofuni A, Itokawa F, Tsuchiya T, Kurihara T, Ishii K, Tsuji S, Ikeuchi N, Tsukamoto S, Takeuchi M, Kawai T, Moriyasu F. Endoscopic transpapillary gallbladder drainage in patients with acute cholecystitis in whom percutaneous transhepatic approach is contraindicated or anatomically impossible (with video). Gastrointest Endosc. 2008 Sep;68(3):455-60. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.02.052. Epub 2008 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>18561927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sodergren MH, Markar S, Pucher PH, Badran IA, Jiao LR, Darzi A. Safety of transvaginal hybrid NOTES cholecystectomy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Surg Endosc. 2015 Aug;29(8):2077-90. doi: 10.1007/s00464-014-3915-x. Epub 2014 Nov 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25424364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGillicuddy EA, Schuster KM, Barre K, Suarez L, Hall MR, Kaml GJ, Davis KA, Longo WE. Non-operative management of acute cholecystitis in the elderly. Br J Surg. 2012 Sep;99(9):1254-61. doi: 10.1002/bjs.8836. Epub 2012 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22829411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-Alonso FJ, de Lucas Gallego M, Bonillo Cambrodón D, Algaba A, de la Poza G, Martín-Mateos RM, Bermejo F. Gallstone-related disease in the elderly: is there room for improvement? Dig Dis Sci. 2015 Jun;60(6):1770-7. doi: 10.1007/s10620-014-3497-4. Epub 2015 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25577265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trust MD, Sheffield KM, Boyd CA, Benarroch-Gampel J, Zhang D, Townsend CM Jr, Riall TS. Gallstone pancreatitis in older patients: Are we operating enough? Surgery. 2011 Sep;150(3):515-25. doi: 10.1016/j.surg.2011.07.072.</citation>
    <PMID>21878238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prevalence of gallstone disease in an Italian adult female population. Rome Group for the Epidemiology and Prevention of Cholelithiasis (GREPCO). Am J Epidemiol. 1984 May;119(5):796-805.</citation>
    <PMID>6720676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itoi T, Tsuyuguchi T, Takada T, Strasberg SM, Pitt HA, Kim MH, Belli G, Mayumi T, Yoshida M, Miura F, Büchler MW, Gouma DJ, Garden OJ, Jagannath P, Gomi H, Kimura Y, Higuchi R; Tokyo Guideline Revision Committee. TG13 indications and techniques for biliary drainage in acute cholangitis (with videos). J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci. 2013 Jan;20(1):71-80. doi: 10.1007/s00534-012-0569-8.</citation>
    <PMID>23307008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Working Group IAP/APA Acute Pancreatitis Guidelines. IAP/APA evidence-based guidelines for the management of acute pancreatitis. Pancreatology. 2013 Jul-Aug;13(4 Suppl 2):e1-15. doi: 10.1016/j.pan.2013.07.063.</citation>
    <PMID>24054878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riall TS, Zhang D, Townsend CM Jr, Kuo YF, Goodwin JS. Failure to perform cholecystectomy for acute cholecystitis in elderly patients is associated with increased morbidity, mortality, and cost. J Am Coll Surg. 2010 May;210(5):668-77, 677-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2009.12.031.</citation>
    <PMID>20421027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peery AF, Crockett SD, Barritt AS, Dellon ES, Eluri S, Gangarosa LM, Jensen ET, Lund JL, Pasricha S, Runge T, Schmidt M, Shaheen NJ, Sandler RS. Burden of Gastrointestinal, Liver, and Pancreatic Diseases in the United States. Gastroenterology. 2015 Dec;149(7):1731-1741.e3. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2015.08.045. Epub 2015 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26327134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McSherry CK, Ferstenberg H, Calhoun WF, Lahman E, Virshup M. The natural history of diagnosed gallstone disease in symptomatic and asymptomatic patients. Ann Surg. 1985 Jul;202(1):59-63.</citation>
    <PMID>4015212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kratzer W, Mason RA, Kächele V. Prevalence of gallstones in sonographic surveys worldwide. J Clin Ultrasound. 1999 Jan;27(1):1-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9888092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital del Río Hortega</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marina de Benito Sanz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Choledocholithiasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Gall Bladder drainage</keyword>
  <keyword>LAMS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Choledocholithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholestasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calculi</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>April 12, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/02/NCT03921502/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

