<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03923582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00006904</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03923582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Training for Health Professionals In Tanzania</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Sexual Health Training for Health Professionals in Tanzania</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Muhimbili University of Health and Allied Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Conduct a social ecological needs assessment of sexual health care delivery in Tanzania and
      develop a theoretically-sound, empirically-based, health training curriculum for health
      students tailored to the Tanzanian/East African/Sub-Saharan context.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As documented in the US Surgeon General's Call to Action to Promote Sexual Health and
      Responsible Sexual Behavior, training of health providers in sexual health care is critical
      to addressing a broad array of the nation's sexual and reproductive health concerns. Yet
      rigorous trials evaluating the effects of sexual health curricula on provider behavior are
      rare. In sub-Saharan Africa, an environment which has some of the world's highest rates of
      HIV, sexually transmitted infections, teen pregnancy, and unwanted pregnancy, and where
      female genital cutting, criminalization of key populations, and rates of sexual dysfunction
      in both men and women are common, investigators could find no formalized training of health
      providers in sexual health care. Sexual health education, even of health providers, is
      somewhat controversial in Africa. So, a rigorous study of its effects is needed, if such
      education is to be widely adopted. Recently, at Muhimbili University of Health and Allied
      Health Sciences (MUHAS) in Dar es Salaam, we adapted a World Health Organization sexual
      health curriculum training for primary healthcare providers in the Americas, for
      implementation in Tanzania. Participants were 87 nursing, midwifery, and allied health
      science students. Pre-Post evaluations show the curriculum to be highly acceptable, needed
      and desired by students, feasible in implementation, and effective in improving student
      knowledge, attitudes, and competence providing sexual health care to patients. The logical
      next step in this line of research is to conduct the first rigorous trial of a sexual health
      training curriculum for health professionals in Tanzania. There are three specific aims. Aim
      1 is to conduct a social ecological needs assessment of sexual health care delivery in
      Tanzania. To determine whether midwifery, nursing, medical, and allied health science
      students would benefit from one curriculum or separate curricula tailored by discipline, we
      will conduct focus groups of midwives, nurses, doctors, and allied health workers and
      students (3 from each discipline). In Aim 2, Investigators will further adapt a sexual health
      training curriculum/a tailored to the Tanzanian/East African/Sub-Saharan context, pilot test
      it, and train local faculty to implement it. Aim 3 is to evaluate the effectiveness of the
      sexual health curriculum. The team will conduct a randomized, controlled, single blinded
      trial of the curriculum against a waitlist control assessing effects on sexual health
      knowledge, attitudes, and sexual history and counseling skills (n=206 students per arm; 410
      in total). Hypotheses will test if the curriculum is effective, and whether such curricula
      are more effective for one discipline than another. If effective, MUHAS has committed to
      implement the curriculum for all their health students. Given MUHAS is preeminent in health
      student education across Africa, the curriculum assessed in this study has high potential to
      be widely adopted as a new standard of training for health professionals across Africa.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Development and testing of a health curriculum for Midwifery Nursing, Medical and Allied Health students.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A randomized, controlled, single blinded trial, stratified by health profession, of the intervention vs waitlist control.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative data from focus groups and key informant interviews</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The first outcome from Aim 1 will be internal documents to guide Aim II. Aim 1 involves focus group and key informant interviews of nursing and medical students, health professionals, and community leaders. Once transcribed, translated, and analyzed, the qualitative data from these interviews will inform the development of the curriculum in Aim 2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Papers resulting from focus groups and key informant interviews</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>The focus group and key informant interviews conducted as part of Aim 1 will generate data that will be used to write papers on: (a) the capacity of the Tanzanian health delivery system related to sexual health services; (b) the cultural context of providing sexual health care in Tanzania; (c) sexual health training needs of health workers in Tanzania, (d) barriers and facilitators of delivery of sexual health services, (e) differences in sexual health training needs by discipline, and (f) policy implications.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of a culturally sensitive curriculum</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>In Aim 2, a curriculum will be developed using data generated by Aim 1. The curriculum will be tailored to the Tanzanian context and developed to fit the needs of midwifery, nursing, and medical students.The effectiveness of the curriculum will be evaluated through a pre-pilot and pilot of the curriculum with 25 students. The curriculum will be revised at each stage, and pilot participants will be given a pre-test needs assessment and a post-test evaluation of the curriculum to measure the effectiveness of the curriculum.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating the effectiveness of the curriculum - Data analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 48</time_frame>
    <description>Curriculum evaluation will be conducted through a randomized, controlled, single blinded trail stratified by health profession of the intervention versus wait list control. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be used to assess the overall effectiveness of the sexual health curriculum on the attitudes, knowledge, and skills of healthcare professionals after it has been implemented. Data will be collected using the methods described in the secondary outcome measures and assessed using repeated measures of ANOVA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effectiveness of the curriculum - Demographics and knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 36</time_frame>
    <description>As part of the RCT, health professionals' knowledge, attitude change, and skills will be assessed first. Demographics, professional specifications, and sex knowledge will be measured using pen and paper surveys. Responses will be measured on the Likert scale. These pen and paper surveys will be entered onto the U of M site using double data entry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effectiveness of the curriculum - Communication, confidence, and attitudes</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 36</time_frame>
    <description>Communication abilities, content confidence, and attitudes will be recorded using pen and paper surveys and measured by the Sexual health Education of Professionals Scale (SHEPS). These pen and paper surveys will be entered onto the U of M site using double data entry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effectiveness of the curriculum - Skills</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 36</time_frame>
    <description>The primary behavioral changes that will be measured is the student's ability to ask appropriate sexual questions, take a sexual history and counsel sexual problems. These skills will be measured by videotaping participants at pretest and a 3-month follow-up. Videos of participants will be rated by co-investigators to assess the students' performance over time. Videos will be randomized so raters are blind to whether video is a pre-test or follow-up. Two raters will assess each video clip and rate the students' performance as: 1=harmful; 2=poor; 3=neutral; 4=good; and 5=excellent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">410</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</condition>
  <condition>Training</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ecological needs assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>To conduct a needs assessment of sexual health care delivery in Tanzania. To determine whether midwifery, nursing, medical and allied health science students would benefit from one curriculum or separate curricula tailored by discipline. We will conduct focus groups and key informant interviews of all three groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Develop a sexual health training curriculum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>We will further adapt a sexual health training curriculum tailored to Tanzanian/East African/Sub-Saharan context and pilot test it and train local faculty to implement it.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>To evaluate the effectiveness of the sexual health curriculum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>We will conduct a randomized, controlled, single blinded trial of the curriculum against a waitlist control assessing effects on sexual health knowledge, attitudes and sexual history and counseling skills.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Curriculum Training</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a randomized, controlled, single blinded, trial, stratified by health profession, of the intervention versus waitlist control assessing knowledge, attitude change and skill development. At the end of the intervention as compared with waitlist controls…
Participants will significantly increase knowledge about sexual health and sexual health care.
Participants will significantly improve attitudes about provision of sexual health services, sexual health communication skills, and comfort in addressing sexual health care in routine care.
Participants' sexual health communication, history taking, and counseling skills will be significantly improved as assessed by independent evaluators blinded to trial assignment.
Secondary analyses will assess whether at post-test, sexual health knowledge, attitudes and skills will vary by health discipline, and test for differential intervention effects by discipline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>To evaluate the effectiveness of the sexual health curriculum</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Year 04 nursing student

          -  Graduate student in nursing

          -  Year 04 midwifery student

          -  Year 04 student in community health work or community health education

          -  Year 02 public health student where students conduct field placements in the community

          -  Year 04 medical student, where students are on 'clinical' rotating in the community.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Students who will not be able to attend MUHAS all days of the seminar or be on the
             MUHAS campus for the follow-up dates.

          -  Students who express severe reservations about attending (e.g., due to religious
             objections).

          -  Students who express fear of violence due to attending (e.g., from a spouse or
             relative).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>B.R. Simon Rosser, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>612-624-0358</phone>
    <email>rosser@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael Ross, PhD</last_name>
    <email>mwross@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>B.R. Simon Rosser, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>612-624-0358</phone>
      <email>rosser@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross MW, Leshabari S, Rosser BRS, Trent M, Mgopa L, Wadley J, Kohli N, Agardh A. Evaluation of an assessment instrument for a sexual health curriculum for nurses and midwifery students in Tanzania: The sexual health education for professionals scale (SHEPS). Appl Nurs Res. 2018 Apr;40:152-156. doi: 10.1016/j.apnr.2018.01.005. Epub 2018 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29579491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Only group data will be analyzed.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

