<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03921086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HASS-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03921086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypertension And Surgery Study: Evaluating the Implementation of a Hypertension Guideline Protocol</brief_title>
  <acronym>HASS-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Hypertension And Surgery Study 2: A Multicentre, Cross-sectional Quality Improvement Project: Evaluating the Implementation of a Hypertensive Guideline Protocol by Perioperative Clinicians.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cape Town</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cape Town</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      HASS-2 is a multi-center, cross-sectional quality improvement project: evaluating the
      implementation of a hypertension guideline protocol by perioperative clinicians, as a model
      for improving various aspects of public health. The study will also describe the co-morbid
      risk profile of these newly identified or poorly controlled hypertensive patients. In
      addition, as a sub-study, these patients will be followed up at monthly intervals for 3
      months after discharge, in order to quantify the rates of compliance with their prescribed
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Globally, cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death. Hypertension is the commonest
      risk factor underlying cardiovascular disease, and, uncontrolled, is a risk for myocardial
      infarction, heart failure, stroke and renal disease. Hypertension is common, affecting over 1
      billion people worldwide. In modern practice, failure to treat hypertension is regarded as
      poor medicine, and potentially indefensible.Hypertension remains a global health problem and
      one that is usually identified and treated in the primary health care setting. However, in
      South Africa, which is a resource-limited environment, it can burden an already strained
      primary health care system. The prevalence of hypertension in the adult population of South
      Africa is approximately 30%. With urbanisation, an ageing population, amongst other
      developing trends, this number is projected to increase significantly in the future.The
      perioperative period therefore presents a unique opportunity for clinicians to identify,
      educate and appropriately initiate or escalate management of these patients, thereby
      alleviating the burden on the primary health care system.

      A short-term quality improvement intervention has the potential to improve quality of care in
      cardiovascular disease, in a low- to middle-income country like South Africa. This can be
      done by educating health care providers and implementing a guideline which will lead to
      improved, standardised and sustained quality of care for patients with hypertension. This
      will lead to a reduction in blood pressure, and further improve long-term morbidity and
      mortality of patients, and ultimately reduce the burden on an already strained health care
      system. Such guidelines could be modified to address other public health care challenges.

      Within the African context, South Africans are recognised as being at a significant risk of
      cardiovascular disease, with the population having the highest prevalence of smoking,
      dyslipidemia, elevated fasting glucose and abdominal obesity, features of metabolic syndrome.

      Metabolic syndrome found in hypertensive patients increases their risk of morbidity and
      mortality. This, in addition to the added physiological stress of surgery, may dramatically
      increase cardiovascular risk and complications in this cohort.

      Prescribed medications for chronic conditions such as hypertension require a consistent level
      of patient compliance to the treatment regime. Compliance has been defined as &quot;the extent to
      which a person's behaviour (in terms of taking medications, following diets or executing
      lifestyle changes) coincides with medical or health advice&quot;. Non-compliance can result in
      significant implications for not only the patient's health outcomes, but a considerable
      wastage of resources in an already limited setting. The World Health Organisation has
      highlighted the considerable economic and health benefits associated with improving
      compliance with treatments for conditions such as diabetes, hyperlipidaemia and hypertension.
      Similar to other non-communicable diseases, the ultimate goal of managing hypertension is
      achieve target control and prevent complications.The secondary aim of the HASS-2 study is to
      quantify the rates of compliance to antihypertensive medication following discharge from the
      patient's respective hospitals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 14, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 16, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Initiate anti-hypertensive therapy in surgical patients who are identified as hypertensive at the time of their admission. Identify the co-morbidities of these patients (diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, renal impairment, obesity and ECG changes)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing physician compliance with prescription of in-hospital drugs according to hypertension algorithm</measure>
    <time_frame>Five day period</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who have drugs prescribed in-hospital</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing physician compliance with prescription of discharge drugs according to hypertension algorithm</measure>
    <time_frame>Five day period</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who have drugs prescribed at hospital discharge</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing patient compliance with antihypertensive medication dispensing following discharge.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three and six months following discharge.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who have drugs dispensed following hospital discharge</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">106</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Non-Compliance, Medication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypertensive patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Newly diagnosed or poorly controlled hypertensive patients will be initiated on appropriate therapy as per a specific algorithm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antihypertensive medication according to the study's algorithm</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with stage 1 hypertension will receive monotherapy and risks of hypotension are negligible. A single antihypertensive lowers blood pressure (BP) on average by 10/5 mmHg.
Patients with stage 2 hypertension will be initiated on two medications and this is recommended by all international hypertension guidelines and studies have shown prompt BP control with minimal side effects.
For borderline patients, the investigators will elect to not treat them for blood pressure ranges of BP: 135-140/85-90 mmHg and give them a letter on discharge to be followed up at their local clinic. The letter will detail that they are potentially hypertensive patients and need to be followed up closely in future.
Patients with Stage 3 hypertension will be referred to the in-hospital physician as per the algorithm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypertensive patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult (older than 18 years)

          -  Elective surgery at preoperative in-hospital visit

          -  All stage 1 and stage 2 hypertensive patients as defined by the South African
             Hypertension Practice Guideline 2014

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusal

          -  Day case surgery

          -  Obstetric and cardiac surgery

          -  Patients with severe hypertension (&gt;180/110 mmHg) as defined by the South African
             Hypertension Practice Guideline 2014
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruce Biccard, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cape Town</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groote Schuur Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mitchells Plain Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Somerset Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Victoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>George Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>George</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Paarl Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paarl</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Worcester Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7599</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cape Town</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bruce Biccard</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antihypertensive Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

