<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03924440</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09/19/2016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03924440</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ovulation Double Check (Proov) Verification and Usability Testing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterization and Use of Urine Pregnanediol Rapid Test and Its Use for Confirming Ovulation - Proov (Ovulation Double Check) Test</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MFB Fertility</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MFB Fertility</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Ovulation Double Check test is a Class I, 510K exempt medical device. It is manufactured
      and packaged in an FDA-registered and cGMP compliant facility. This device measures the level
      of Pregnanediol (PdG), the major urine metabolite of progesterone, in the urine of women. PdG
      has been shown to increase significantly after ovulation has occurred. This test will be used
      in a home setting as a point-of-care device, providing couples additional information about
      menstrual cycling and possible fertile periods. The investigators have successfully developed
      prototype devices that can accurately measure PdG in urine. Now the investigators need to
      supply these prototype devices to end users to verify the assay is working correctly and
      determine if the device was designed properly in order for home users to 1) use the test
      properly, 2) read the test results properly, and 3) interpret the results correctly.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lack of or insufficient ovulatory events is the primary cause of infertility worldwide and
      with 12% of couples within the US being diagnosed with infertility each year (according to
      the CDC), thus being able to confirm ovulation is an essential component of infertility
      evaluations in women. The gold standards for confirming ovulation include transvaginal
      ultrasounds and serum progesterone blood draws. Both of these techniques are too invasive,
      too expensive, and/or inaccessible to most women. Therefore a non-invasive, inexpensive,
      home-based testing system to confirm ovulation is desired. Several recent studies have
      identified urinary pregnanediol levels as an accurate way to confirm ovulation. However,
      until now, urine pregnanediol levels were always measured via a lab setting. Here the
      investigators describe the development of a urine pregnanediol (PDG) rapid test and its use
      at confirming ovulation in a home environment. Study Protocol One hundred and ninety six
      women were recruited to take part in a prospective, blinded cohort home environment study.
      The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee at Solutions IRB. Detailed
      information about the study was provided to each volunteer, and informed consent was obtained
      prior the study commencement. Inclusion criteria were non-pregnant women residing within the
      United States, aged 18- 45, and not currently on hormonal birth control. Importantly, women
      were not excluding due to average cycle length, weight (BMI), breastfeeding status,
      poly-cyctic ovarian syndrome (PCOS) or any other cause of infertility or lifestyle factor.
      Participants were asked to predict ovulation by monitoring changes in cervical mucus and/or
      tracking luteinizing hormone (LH) via home test kits. Participants were asked to self-report
      their peak fertility day, which was defined as the first LH surge day and/or day of peak
      cervical mucus (stretchy and eggwhite in consistence).

      Participants collected first morning urine as various times during their cycle, including,
      prior to, during, and after peak fertility signs were observed. Participants were provided
      PDG rapid response test strips and self-administered the tests and recorded the results. Test
      results were reported back the investigators via a log sheet. Log sheets recorded testing
      date, day of cycle, date of peak fertility (if known), personal assessment of results
      (positive result vs negative result) and a place to tape the completed test strip.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number if participants with positive PDG test results</measure>
    <time_frame>A single menstrual cycle, up to 45 days.</time_frame>
    <description>PDG test results are recorded to determine when PDG test results were positive</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">196</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovulation Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDG Test strip Users</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants were asked to predict ovulation by monitoring changes in cervical mucus and/or tracking luteinizing hormone (LH) via home test kits. Participants were asked to self-report their peak fertility day, which was defined as the first LH surge day and/or day of peak cervical mucus (stretchy and eggwhite in consistence).
Participants collected first morning urine as various times during their cycle, including, prior to, during, and after peak fertility signs were observed. Participants were provided PDG rapid response test strips and self-administered their tests and recorded their results. Test results were reported back researchers via a log sheet. Log sheets recorded testing date, day of cycle, date of peak fertility (if known), personal assessment of results (positive result vs negative result) and a place to tape the completed test strip.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Proov (Ovulation Double Check) Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Rapid response urine progesterone test strips, Proov (formerly named Ovulation Double Check</description>
    <arm_group_label>PDG Test strip Users</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria were non-pregnant women residing within the United States, aged 18-34,
        and not currently on hormonal birth control. Importantly, women were not excluding due to
        average cycle length, weight (BMI), breastfeeding status, poly-cyctic ovarian syndrome
        (PCOS) or any other cause of infertility or lifestyle factor.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Female (mandatory)

          2. Not currently pregnant or nursing (pregnancy affects PdG levels)

          3. Aged 18-34 (advanced age can hinder PdG levels)

          4. Cycle length of 26-39 days (long or short cycles have inconsistent PdG levels)

          5. Currently use other fertility monitoring tools (this allows us to compare Proov -
             Ovulation Double Check test results with other fertility tracking methods)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Male

          2. Pregnant

          3. Nursing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Women only due to ovulation tracking diagnostic studied</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>34 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Beckley, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MFB Fertility</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nonoxynol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

