<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03927404</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1809327674</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>W81XWH-16-2-0059</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03927404</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of Adaptive Vacuum Suspension to Improve Prosthetic Fit and Residual Limb Health</brief_title>
  <acronym>DoD</acronym>
  <official_title>Development of Adaptive Vacuum Suspension to Improve Prosthetic Fit and Residual Limb Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate residual limb circulation and skin health associated
      with the use of a prosthetic vacuum socket. A conventional non-vacuum prosthetic socket will
      be compared to a vacuum prosthetic socket.

      The prosthetic suspension plays a pivotal role in an amputee's comfort. It can also
      significantly impact an amputee's limb health. If the prosthesis is not held securely to the
      amputee's limb, relative movement between the limb and prosthetic interface can cause
      bruising, skin irritation and skin breakdown. These poor outcomes are uncomfortable and can
      lead to much more serious health conditions. A positive solution to creating secure and
      comfortable suspension is the use of a vacuum suspension socket. The vacuum pressure assists
      in preventing movement in the socket. The clinical benefits associated with vacuum suspension
      include volume retention, increased proprioception, secure suspension, and frequently
      reported observations of wound healing. However, the long term effects of vacuum suspension
      on circulation remain undetermined or undocumented. This study examines a vacuum suspension
      system on the health of the residual limb (amputated limb). A vacuum socket creates a vacuum
      between the rigid prosthetic socket and prosthetic liner which is sealed to the socket.
      Therefore, vacuum is not directly applied to the skin of the residual limb.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are a total of 3 study visits, including socket fitting visits, a baseline visit, and a
      final visit. During the socket visit, which may consist of a three visits plus socket
      adjustments (as needed by the participant) on separate days (up to 4 weeks), limb shape
      capture, measurement or tracing, diagnostic static fitting and diagnostic static fitting, and
      delivery of a definitive &quot;research&quot; socket will be done. At the baseline visit, participants
      will perform seated tasks, standing tasks, and treadmill walking tasks. Residual limb health
      measurements will be taken before and after the activity period, including surface electrical
      capacitance, Transepidermal Water Loss (TEWL) measurement, hyperspectral imaging, Hitachi
      Aloka ultrasound imaging, Laser Speckle Imaging (LSI)/Blood Flow, and digital imaging during
      the baseline visit as well. The final visit, using the research socket, will consist of the
      same tasks and measurements as the baseline visit.

      After completion of the study, participants will be given the choice to keep the research
      socket or return to using their original prosthesis as normal. The study prosthetist will be
      available to review and adjust the fit of their standard of care prosthesis at this time.
      Note: Due to physical change and limb volume fluctuation over the study period, it is
      possible that at the end of the study the standard of care prosthesis will not fit your
      residual limb as it does at the beginning of the study. At the completion of the study, it is
      recommended that the subject follow up with their primary care prosthetist for socket
      evaluation and fitting.

      There may be risks that are not known about at this time. Side effects, risks, and
      discomforts may result from study participation.

        -  Prosthesis placement: While the goal of this project is to create a more comfortable
           prosthesis, it is possible that the subject could experience discomforts commonly
           associated with prosthesis use, such as perspiration, dry skin, rash, itching, blisters,
           high pressure in the socket, looseness in the socket, and mechanical rubbing that leads
           to ulceration.

        -  Treadmill task:There is a risk of falling during the research activities. This risk is
           mitigated by the ability of participants to self-select pace for the treadmill task and
           observation of treadmill activities by research staff.

        -  Transcutaneous Oxygen Measurement (TcOM) and skin temperature: The PeriFlux System 5000
           uses non-invasive probes that will measure the skin temperature and transcutaneous
           Oxygen Measurement and poses minimal risk to the subject. The probe head is affixed to
           the residual limb by an adhesive sticker. Removal of the sticker after data acquisition
           may cause minor discomfort similar to removing a small band-aid.

        -  Hyperspectral Imaging: This non-invasive imaging technique poses minimal risk to the
           subject. A small fiduciary marker sticker is placed on the subject's limb to calibrate
           camera settings. Removal of the sticker after imaging may cause minor discomfort similar
           to removing a small band-aid.

        -  Laser Speckle Imaging (LSI): LSI is a non-invasive blood flow imaging technique. Laser
           speckle imaging is very routinely used for blood perfusion measurement in clinical
           applications. We do not anticipate any radiation exposure. Laser applications such as
           for LSI for diagnostic purposes are of Class 1 (&lt;0.4 mW) are considered harmless for the
           eye and skin.&quot;

        -  Hitachi Aloka Ultrasound:Ultrasound imaging is a noninvasive technique and is a minimal
           risk procedure.

        -  TEWL and Surface Electrical Capacitance Measurements: TEWL and Surface Electrical
           Capacitance measurements are noninvasive and propose less than minimal risk.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a 16 weeks longitudinal study where subjects will serve their own control. A baseline measurement will be done prior to start of intervention that will continue for 16 weeks and a final measurement will be taken at the end of 16 weeks.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Residual limb health at 16 weeks after use</measure>
    <time_frame>16 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in overall limb health in 16 wks</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperspectral Imaging at 16 wks</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in Hyperspectral Imaging at 16 wks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laser speckle flowmetry tissue perfusion values at 16wks</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in Laser speckle flowmetry tissue perfusion values at 16wks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TEWL measurement at 16 wks</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in Transepidermal Water Loss (TEWL) value in 16 wks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Lower Limb Amputation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adaptive Vacuum test Prosthesis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental socket system uses an active vacuum pump to push air out of the socket. The level of vacuum is controlled by hardware that automatically detects the socket fit based on in-socket motion and adjusts vacuum as needed to eliminate this motion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active vacuum test prosthesis</intervention_name>
    <description>The experimental socket system uses an active vacuum pump to push air out of the socket. The level of vacuum is controlled by hardware that automatically detects the socket fit based on in-socket motion and adjusts vacuum as needed to eliminate this motion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adaptive Vacuum test Prosthesis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Limb logic system</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages of 18 and above

          -  Unilateral transtibial or transfemoral amputee

          -  Ambulate at a K2 level or higher

          -  At least 3 months post-amputation per physician discretion

          -  Residual limb length greater than 6.5 inches in length

          -  Able to follow directions and give informed consent on their own

          -  Must be able to ambulate without assistance

          -  Adequate arterial blood flow as evidenced by a TcOM &gt;30mmHg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Conditions that prevent wearing a prosthetic socket

          -  Cognitive deficits or mental health problems that would limit ability to consent and
             participate fully in the study protocol

          -  Women who are pregnant or who plan to become pregnant in the near future
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chandan Sen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Mohnacky, RDN</last_name>
    <phone>(317)-278-2715</phone>
    <email>jmohnack@iu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tammy Garrett, RN</last_name>
    <phone>(317) 278-2716</phone>
    <email>tjgarret@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IU Health Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mohnacky Jennifer, RDN</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-2715</phone>
      <email>jmohnack@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tammy Garrett, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(317) 278-2716</phone>
      <email>tjgarret@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sashwati Roy, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gayle Gordillo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein RA, Heinemann AW, McFarland LV. Quality of life for veterans and servicemembers with major traumatic limb loss from Vietnam and OIF/OEF conflicts. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2010;47(4):373-85.</citation>
    <PMID>20803405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz AE, Baade SP, Kuiken TA. Expert opinions on success factors for upper-limb prostheses. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2007;44(4):483-9.</citation>
    <PMID>18247245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zachariah SG, Saxena R, Fergason JR, Sanders JE. Shape and volume change in the transtibial residuum over the short term: preliminary investigation of six subjects. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2004 Sep;41(5):683-94.</citation>
    <PMID>15558398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernie GR, Holliday PJ. Volume fluctuations in the residual limbs of lower limb amputees. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1982 Apr;63(4):162-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7082139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanders JE, Fatone S. Residual limb volume change: systematic review of measurement and management. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2011;48(8):949-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22068373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krueger CA, Wenke JC, Ficke JR. Ten years at war: comprehensive analysis of amputation trends. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2012 Dec;73(6 Suppl 5):S438-44. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318275469c.</citation>
    <PMID>23192067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramasamy A, Hill AM, Phillip R, Gibb I, Bull AM, Clasper JC. The modern &quot;deck-slap&quot; injury--calcaneal blast fractures from vehicle explosions. J Trauma. 2011 Dec;71(6):1694-8. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318227a999.</citation>
    <PMID>21808204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bui KM, Raugi GJ, Nguyen VQ, Reiber GE. Skin problems in individuals with lower-limb loss: literature review and proposed classification system. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2009;46(9):1085-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20437314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris AM, Althausen PL, Kellam J, Bosse MJ, Castillo R; Lower Extremity Assessment Project (LEAP) Study Group. Complications following limb-threatening lower extremity trauma. J Orthop Trauma. 2009 Jan;23(1):1-6. doi: 10.1097/BOT.0b013e31818e43dd.</citation>
    <PMID>19104297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chandan Sen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Vice President of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transfemoral Amputees</keyword>
  <keyword>Transtibial Amputees</keyword>
  <keyword>Prosthesis</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

