<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03923348</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-71</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03923348</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pelvic Floor Muscle Training With Leva System for Urge Incontinence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pelvic Floor Muscle Training With the Leva® System for Treatment of Urge Predominant Urinary Incontinence: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Christ Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Renovia, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Christ Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot non-comparative study to assess the effectiveness of pelvic floor muscle
      training guided by the leva® system for improving change in subject-reported
      incontinence-related quality of life and urgency urinary incontinence (UUI) episode frequency
      based on voiding diaries in women at 8 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our study aims to investigate a new alternative to formal pelvic floor physical therapy that
      may provide subjects with a more accessible, private method of undergoing pelvic floor muscle
      training (PFMT) with real-time biofeedback on performance. The leva® Pelvic Digital Health
      System by Renovia Inc is a novel tool for subjects with urinary incontinence to train and
      strengthen pelvic floor muscles via directional mechano-transductive feedback on performance
      in the privacy of their own homes. We hypothesize that women using the leva® System will
      experience significant improvements in subjective urge-related incontinence symptoms. In
      addition, changes in incontinence-related quality of life and UUI episode frequency will be
      determined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow Recruitment and Re-prioritizing of Sponsor-funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 4, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 4, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Non-blinded non-comparative pilot trial in which subjects with pure urge urinary incontinence (UUI) or urge-predominant mixed urinary incontinence (U-MUI) who are candidates for pelvic floor physical therapy or other first line treatments for UUI/U-MUI use the leva® system twice-daily at home in addition to behavioral therapies for 8 weeks.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urogenital Distress Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline UDI score to 8 weeks and 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI) is a 19-item questionnaire assessing subjective symptoms of pelvic floor disorders including incontinence. The 19 items fall into one of three subscales (Irritative symptoms, Obstructive symptoms, and Stress Symptoms). . The subject responds to each item by choosing from one of four answer options from 0 to 3 with higher scores indicating a greater severity of symptom. For scoring, first each subscale score is calculated by finding the mean score of items within the subscale section, subtracting 1, and multiplying that by 100/3. Next, the subscale scores are summed to determine the overall UDI score with possible scores ranging from 0-300. High scores indicate greater symptoms severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incontinence Impact Questionnaire Short Form (IIQ-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline IIQ-7 score to 8 weeks and 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Validated short-form version of the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire used to describe incontinence-related quality of life. It consists of 7 items assessing four general areas including travel, social, emotional, and physical activities. For each item, the subject responds by choosing from one of four answer options from 0 to 3 with higher scores indicating a greater severity of symptom. Scores are generated by finding the mean score for each item and multiplying that by 100/3. Higher scores indicate greater negative impact on quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urge Urinary Incontinence Episode Frequency on a Three-Day Voiding Diary</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline urge urinary incontinence episode frequency to 8 weeks and 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A voiding diary is considered standard of care in the work-up of a patient with incontinence to better characterize real-life drinking and voiding habits. The number of urge urinary incontinence episodes is determined by adding up the incontinence episodes recorded by the patient that were associated with an urge to get to the bathroom. More incontinence episodes means a greater severity of incontinence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Urge Urinary Incontinence</condition>
  <condition>Mixed Urinary Incontinence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leva Users</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with pure urge urinary incontinence (UUI) or urge-predominant mixed urinary incontinence (U-MUI) who are candidates for pelvic floor physical therapy or other first line treatments for UUI/U-MUI use the leva® system twice-daily at home in addition to behavioral therapies for 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leva device</intervention_name>
    <description>The leva® Pelvic Digital Health System by Renovia Inc is a novel tool for subjects with urinary incontinence to train and strengthen pelvic floor muscles via directional mechano-transductive feedback on performance in the privacy of their own homes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Leva Users</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-85 years old

          -  Urinary incontinence for ≥ 3 months

          -  Reporting at least &quot;moderate bother&quot; on Item 2 on the UDI-6, &quot;Do you experience urine
             leakage in related to the feeling of urgency&quot; (on new patient paperwork)

          -  If mixed urinary incontinence, Medical Epidemiologic Social Aspect of Aging Urinary
             Incontinence Questionnaire (MESA) score indicating urge-predominant MUI (Urge subscale
             % &gt; Stress subscale %)

          -  Presence of ≥ 1 UUI episode on 3-d bladder diary (see Appendix 2)

          -  Is the baseline bladder diary consistent with the patient's typical habits?

          -  Not currently taking anti-muscarinic or beta3 agonist therapy (after at least 2 week
             wash-out period)

          -  Brink Score &gt; 3 (see below)

          -  Access to smartphone technology, including iOS or Android™

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-English speakers

          -  Severely impaired mobility or cognition

          -  Spinal cord injury or advanced/severe neurologic condition including Multiple
             Sclerosis, Parkinson's Disease

          -  Concomitant prolapse beyond the hymen or repair of prolapse in the previous 6 months

          -  Received intravesical botulinum injection within the previous 12 months

          -  History of implanted nerve stimulator for incontinence

          -  History of prior sling or vaginal mesh placement

          -  Previous diagnosis of Interstitial cystitis

          -  Active pelvic organ malignancy

          -  History of pelvic radiation

          -  Urethral obstruction

          -  Urinary retention or prolonged catheter use

          -  Less than 12 months post-partum are currently pregnant, or plan to become pregnant in
             the following 12 months

          -  Untreated symptomatic urinary tract infection

          -  Unevaluated hematuria

          -  Medical instability

          -  Not available for follow-up in 6 months

          -  Participation in other research trials that could influence results of this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne M Stachowicz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Urogynecology Fellow</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Christ Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Milsom I, Coyne KS, Nicholson S, Kvasz M, Chen CI, Wein AJ. Global prevalence and economic burden of urgency urinary incontinence: a systematic review. Eur Urol. 2014 Jan;65(1):79-95. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2013.08.031. Epub 2013 Aug 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24007713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monteiro S, Riccetto C, Araújo A, Galo L, Brito N, Botelho S. Efficacy of pelvic floor muscle training in women with overactive bladder syndrome: a systematic review. Int Urogynecol J. 2018 Nov;29(11):1565-1573. doi: 10.1007/s00192-018-3602-x. Epub 2018 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>29644384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kammerer-Doak D, Rizk DE, Sorinola O, Agur W, Ismail S, Bazi T. Mixed urinary incontinence: international urogynecological association research and development committee opinion. Int Urogynecol J. 2014 Oct;25(10):1303-12. doi: 10.1007/s00192-014-2485-8. Epub 2014 Aug 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25091925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamin E, Parrillo LM, Newman DK, Smith AL. Pelvic Floor Muscle Training: Underutilization in the USA. Curr Urol Rep. 2016 Feb;17(2):10. doi: 10.1007/s11934-015-0572-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26757904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenblatt P, Pulliam S, McKinney J, Sutherland R, Iglesias R. The leva incontinence system for the treatment of mild to moderate urinary incontinence: A pilot study. Female Pelvic Med Reconstr Surg.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shumaker SA, Wyman JF, Uebersax JS, McClish D, Fantl JA. Health-related quality of life measures for women with urinary incontinence: the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire and the Urogenital Distress Inventory. Continence Program in Women (CPW) Research Group. Qual Life Res. 1994 Oct;3(5):291-306.</citation>
    <PMID>7841963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uebersax JS, Wyman JF, Shumaker SA, McClish DK, Fantl JA. Short forms to assess life quality and symptom distress for urinary incontinence in women: the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire and the Urogenital Distress Inventory. Continence Program for Women Research Group. Neurourol Urodyn. 1995;14(2):131-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7780440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dyer KY, Xu Y, Brubaker L, Nygaard I, Markland A, Rahn D, Chai TC, Stoddard A, Lukacz E; Urinary Incontinence Treatment Network (UITN). Minimum important difference for validated instruments in women with urge incontinence. Neurourol Urodyn. 2011 Sep;30(7):1319-24. doi: 10.1002/nau.21028. Epub 2011 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21563210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jimenez-Cidre MA, Lopez-Fando L, Esteban-Fuertes M, Prieto-Chaparro L, Llorens-Martinez FJ, Salinas-Casado J, Castro-Diaz D, Müller-Arteaga C, Adot-Zurbano JM, Rodriguez-Escobar F, Gutierrez C, Arlandis-Guzman S, Bonillo-Garcia MA, Madurga-Patuel B, Leva-Vallejo M, Franco de Castro A, Peri-Cusi L, Conejero-Sugrañes J, Jimenez-Calvo J, Rebollo P, Mora A. The 3-day bladder diary is a feasible, reliable and valid tool to evaluate the lower urinary tract symptoms in women. Neurourol Urodyn. 2015 Feb;34(2):128-32. doi: 10.1002/nau.22530. Epub 2013 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>24264859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hundley AF, Wu JM, Visco AG. A comparison of perineometer to brink score for assessment of pelvic floor muscle strength. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2005 May;192(5):1583-91.</citation>
    <PMID>15902162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brink CA, Sampselle CM, Wells TJ, Diokno AC, Gillis GL. A digital test for pelvic muscle strength in older women with urinary incontinence. Nurs Res. 1989 Jul-Aug;38(4):196-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2748352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Christ Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anne Stachowicz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Fellow Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>female urinary incontinence</keyword>
  <keyword>urge urinary incontinence</keyword>
  <keyword>urgency</keyword>
  <keyword>frequency</keyword>
  <keyword>overactive bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>pelvic floor muscle training</keyword>
  <keyword>biofeedback</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enuresis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence, Urge</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

