<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03922061</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHRMS 19-0048</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03922061</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Safety, Reactogenicity and Immunogenicity of Fractional-dose Inactivated Polio Vaccine (fIPV) Given Intradermally With Double Mutant Enterotoxigenic Escherichia Coli Heat Labile Toxin (dmLT) Adjuvant</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Evaluation of the Safety, Reactogenicity and Immunogenicity of Fractional-dose Inactivated Polio Vaccine (fIPV) Given Intradermally With Double Mutant [LT(R192G/L211A)] Enterotoxigenic Escherichia Coli Heat Labile Toxin (dmLT) Adjuvant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Vermont</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Vermont</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Polio is a serious disease that can cause paralysis and death. It is caused by a virus and
      can be prevented by vaccine. The World Health Organization's (WHO) Global Polio Eradication
      Initiative is trying to get rid of all polio disease around the world. Researchers want to
      help by testing a new vaccine.

      In many countries, people are vaccinated with oral polio vaccine (OPV) given by mouth during
      childhood. OPV is good at giving immunity (protection from polio) in the body and the
      gastrointestinal (GI) tract. Immunity in the GI tract is called mucosal immunity. The
      downsides of using OPV are that it can be shed into the environment in people's feces after
      vaccination where it can infect people who are not vaccinated, and it can cause paralysis in
      2-4 of every one million children vaccinated with OPV. The United States (U.S.) stopped
      giving any OPV to people for vaccinations in the 1990's. Since then, a polio vaccine called
      inactivated polio vaccine (IPV) is given as an injection for routine childhood immunizations
      in the U.S. You cannot get polio infection from IPV and it will not be shed into the
      environment.

      In 2016, the WHO started a plan to help other countries gradually get rid of OPV. The
      downside of using IPV by itself is that, unlike OPV, it doesn't give enough mucosal immunity
      to protect people living in places where there is still polio. There are also supply
      shortages of IPV, which is a problem if there are outbreaks of polio. For the supply of IPV
      to help more people, it is safe and effective to use a tiny dose of IPV injected under the
      top layer of skin (intradermal or ID injection) rather than getting the full dose in the
      muscle. This is called a fractional dose of IPV, or fIPV.

      To help stop using OPV globally, a better fIPV vaccine is needed. fIPV vaccine needs a
      substance to help stimulate a mucosal immune response. dmLT is a substance that has been
      shown to stimulate a mucosal immune response. It has been shown to be safe and effective in
      both humans and animals, both by itself and when given with other vaccines.

      This study will test a mixture of fIPV-dmLT given intradermally (under the outer layer of the
      skin). This is the first study done in humans to give this combination intradermally. The IPV
      vaccine has already been approved by the FDA. The fIPV-dmLT vaccine has not been approved by
      the FDA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This single site study conducted at The University of Vermont will enroll 30 healthy male and
      female adult volunteers aged 18-45 years with no history of oral polio vaccination for a
      Phase I randomized controlled double-blind trial evaluating the safety, reactogenicity and
      immunogenicity of a single dose of fIPV-dMLT versus a single dose of fIPV administered
      intradermally. Study volunteers will be screened with eligible volunteers enrolled who will
      randomized to receive a single dose of fIPV-dmLT or fIPV (2:1) on study day 0. The primary
      study objective is to determine the safety and reactogenicity of a single dose of adjuvanted
      fIPV-dmLT vaccine in healthy adults, as assessed by the frequency of systemic and local
      injection site adverse reactions (ARs) defined as vaccine-related adverse events (AEs),
      graded by severity, occurring within 28 days of dosing. Secondary objectives are to determine
      the safety of a single dose of adjuvanted fIPV-dmLT vaccine in healthy adults, as assessed by
      the percentage of subjects with at least one vaccine-related serious adverse event (SAE)
      occurring within 28 days of dosing. In addition, the systemic immune response to a single
      dose of vaccine in healthy adults, as assessed by poliovirus-specific serum neutralizing
      antibody responses in fIPV-dmLT recipients versus fIPV only recipients will be examined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 4, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 4, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>frequency of systemic and local injection (safety and reactogenicity)</measure>
    <time_frame>Events occuring within 28 days of dosing</time_frame>
    <description>frequency of systemic and local injection site adverse reactions (ARs) defined as vaccine-related adverse events (AEs), graded by severity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>percentage of subjects with at least one serious adverse event (secondary-safety)</measure>
    <time_frame>Events occuring within 28 days of dosing</time_frame>
    <description>percentage of subjects with at least one serious adverse event (SAE) occurring within 28 days of dosing will be summarized with severity, relationship to vaccine, and outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Any timepoint up to day 28 post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants showing at least a 4-fold boost in polio-specific serum neutralizing antibodies compared to baseline (Day 0) in fIPV-dmLT recipients vs. fIPV alone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Polio</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fIPV-dmLT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>fractional-dose inactivated polio vaccine (fIPV) given intradermally with double mutant [LT(R192G/L211A)] Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli heat labile toxin (dmLT) adjuvant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fIPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>fractional-dose inactivated polio vaccine (fIPV) given intradermally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dmLT</intervention_name>
    <description>double mutant [LT(R192G/L211A)] Enterotoxigenic Escherichia coli heat labile toxin (dmLT)</description>
    <arm_group_label>fIPV-dmLT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fIPV</intervention_name>
    <description>fractional-dose inactived polio vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>fIPV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>fIPV-dmLT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult male or female age 18-45 years, inclusive

          2. Signed informed consent form prior to initiation of any study activity

          3. Good general health as determined by review of medical history and physical exam

          4. Agrees to complete all study visits and procedures for the duration of the study

          5. Receipt of childhood vaccine series of Inactivated Polio Vaccine with verification of
             immunization record. American College of Immunization Practices (AICP) required that
             OPV use be discontinued by January 2000. Therefore, polio vaccines given after January
             2000 in the U.S. are known to be IPV. If the documentation is unclear of the type of
             polio vaccine given between 1998 and 2000, additional confirmation of the type should
             be attempted to determine eligibility.

          6. Agrees to storage of specimens for future research

          7. Females of child bearing potential only: willing to use effective contraception from
             the following reliable methods through the first 28 days of the study: hormonal birth
             control, condoms with spermicide, diaphragm with spermicide, surgical sterilization,
             and intrauterine device. All female subjects will be considered as having childbearing
             potential except for those who have had a hysterectomy or tubal ligation or have no
             internal female organs. Transgender men who have internal female organs will be
             considered of childbearing potential and should be willing to use effective
             contraception during the trial. Exception: females who have sex with females
             (exclusively) and have no intention of conceiving a child during the study will not be
             required to use contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of receipt of any oral polio vaccine. Subjects will be required to present
             their childhood immunization record during the screening process. Subjects will be
             excluded if the immunization record indicates receipt of any dose of oral polio
             vaccine or if only 'polio vaccine' is listed on the record without specifying whether
             oral or inactivated polio vaccine was administered.

          2. Currently lactating, breastfeeding or pregnant.

          3. Clinical laboratory values ≥ Grade 2 on hematology or comprehensive metabolic panel,
             as defined in this protocol.

          4. Febrile illness (≥38.0°C (100.4°F) or acute gastroenteritis within 48 hours prior to
             administration of IP

          5. History of antimicrobial treatment in the 2 weeks before administration of IP

          6. Receipt of a live vaccine within 28 days or a killed vaccine within 14 days prior to
             inoculation, or anticipated receipt of any vaccine during the 28 days following
             inoculation.

          7. History of a severe allergic reaction or anaphylaxis

          8. History of Guillian-Barre Syndrome

          9. Known history of hypersensitivity to any component of IPV to include:
             2-phenoxyethanol, formaldehyde, neomycin, streptomycin, and polymyxin B

         10. Self-reported or suspected immunodeficiency, or receipt of immunosuppressive therapy
             within the preceding 6 months, or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy. An
             immunosuppressive dose of corticosteroids (excluding topical or nasal) is defined as
             &gt;10 mg of prednisone equivalent per day for &gt;14 days.

         11. Asplenia

         12. Receipt of blood products within the past 6 months, including transfusions or
             immunoglobulin, or anticipated receipt of any blood products or immunoglobulins during
             the 28 days following inoculation

         13. Anticipated receipt of any investigational agent in the 28 days before or after
             receipt of investigational product

         14. Abnormal routine bowel habits as defined by fewer than three stools per week in the
             past 6 months

         15. Regular use (weekly or more often) of laxatives, anti-diarrheal, anti-constipation, or
             antacid therapy

         16. Evidence of clinically significant neurologic, cardiac, pulmonary, hepatic,
             rheumatologic, autoimmune, or renal disease based on history and physical exam. This
             includes any chronic medical condition (examples include diabetes mellitus,
             hypertension, autoimmune disorders, cardiovascular and renal diseases).

         17. Behavioral, cognitive, or psychiatric disease that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, affects the subject's ability to understand and cooperative with the
             requirements of the study protocol.

         18. Any other condition that, in the opinion of the study clinician, would jeopardize the
             safety or rights of a subject participating
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelly Cowan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Vermont</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beth Kirkpatrick, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Vermont</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kelly Cowan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>802-847-8600</phone>
    <email>kelly.cowan@uvmhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mary Claire Walsh, PA</last_name>
    <phone>802-656-7764</phone>
    <email>mary-claire.walsh@med.uvm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Vermont</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly Cowan, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>802-847-8600</phone>
      <email>kelly.cowan@uvmhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Vermont</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kelly Cowan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>inactivated polio vaccine (IPV)</keyword>
  <keyword>fractional-dose inactivated polio vaccine (fIPV)</keyword>
  <keyword>double mutant [LT(R192G/L211A)] Enterotoxigenic E coli heat toxin (dmLT)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Poliomyelitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

