<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03926520</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018P003142</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03926520</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT) for Agitation in Alzheimer's Dementia (AD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Electroconvulsive Therapy Plus Usual Care Versus Simulated-ECT Plus Usual Care for the Acute Management of Severe Agitation in Alzheimer's Dementia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brent Forester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pine Rest Christian Mental Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Zucker Hillside Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore the efficacy of ECT treatments plus usual care (ECT+UC), relative to
      a placebo simulated ECT plus usual care (S-ECT+UC) in reducing severe agitation in patients
      with moderate to severe Alzheimer's Disease. The study will also determine the
      tolerability/safety outcomes of ECT+UC relative to S-ECT+UC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a single blind, randomized, Simulated-ECT (S-ECT) controlled trial of
      electroconvulsive therapy (ECT). The purpose is to determine the efficacy and safety of ECT
      for severe agitation in moderate to severe stage Alzheimer's Disease (AD), while also
      examining the durability of the acute treatment effect in an exploratory maintenance
      naturalistic design. The investigators will study only inpatients with severe agitation and
      moderate to severe dementia, associated with high care costs and poor quality of life, who
      typically have already failed prior trials of psychotropic medications. The first aim is to
      compare the relative efficacy of up to 9 ECT treatments plus usual care (ECT+UC) versus
      Simulated ECT (S-ECT+UC) in reducing severe agitation in 200 participants with moderate to
      severe AD. The second aim is to compare the relative tolerability/safety outcomes of ECT+UC
      versus S-ECT+UC in the same group of participants. The exploratory aim is to understand the
      stability of agitation reduction (CMAI) and global functioning (ADCS-CGIC) with assessments
      at 1,3, and 6 months following the acute phase, and then for a fourth visit 12 months after
      the acute phase. Establishing safety and efficacy of ECT for severe agitation in AD provides
      an opportunity to decrease long-term care placement, decrease the risk of mortality, decrease
      caregiver burden, and enhance quality of life for patients and their caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CMAI total score</measure>
    <time_frame>The CMAI will be collected through study completion, about 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>The CMAI measures the efficacy of ECT+UC in reducing severe agitation in AD subjects than S-ECT. The CMAI is a 29-item scale with each item ranging from 1-7 in frequency with 7 being the highest and therefore worst outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alzheimer's Disease Cooperative Study-Clinical Global Impression of Change Scale (ADCS-CGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>The ADCS-CGIC will be collected through study completion, about 13 months</time_frame>
    <description>The ADCS-CGIC gives a discrete score that ranges from 1-7 with 7 being the worst outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>The NPI will be collected for one month</time_frame>
    <description>The NPI is composed of several domains in which subscores on frequency and severity will be derived. The higher the frequency and/or severity within each domain, the worse the condition of the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Agitation Scale (PAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The PAS will be collected for one month</time_frame>
    <description>The PAS assesses four behavioral domains. Each domain has an intensity score ranging from 0-4 with 4 being the worst outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Agitation,Psychomotor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ECT+UC group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S-ECT+UC group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Stimulus method of delivery will be RUL electrode placement, and ultra-brief (UB) pulse width (0.25-0.37ms). At the first ECT session, seizure threshold (ST) will be determined by titration with the empirical dose titration method and subsequent treatments will be approximately 6 times the ST. Following other NIMH sponsored multicenter ECT studies (PRIDE, U01 MH055495), stimulus settings will be adjusted as needed during the ECT course based on seizure quality and treatment efficacy. Participants will be administered anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ECT+UC group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simulated Electroconvulsive Therapy (S-ECT)</intervention_name>
    <description>The participant is brought to the ECT suite for the length a session would normally take (approximately 2 hours). While in the ECT suite, conducting gel will be placed on the scalp of the S-ECT subjects to parallel the ECT procedures in the ECT active group. A Band-Aid will also be placed on the arm of the S-ECT subjects to parallel the Band-Aid placed at the IV site for the ECT active group. Participants will not be administered anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>S-ECT+UC group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of Alzheimer's Dementia according to NIA-AA Criteria for dementia [55]

          2. MMSE &lt; 15

          3. Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory Short Version (CMAI) score of ≥4 on at least one
             item, a score of 3 on at least two items, or a score of 2 on at least three items.

          4. At least one failed pharmacological intervention to manage behavioral symptoms

          5. Medically stable for safe administration of ECT verified by standard physical
             examination, urinalysis and serum chemistries

          6. Comprehension of English language

          7. Authorized legal representative able and willing to give informed consent

          8. Age 55 - 89 years old (inclusive)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current diagnosis of co-morbid delirium, measured by the Confusion Assessment Measure
             (CAM) and by clinical diagnosis

          2. Diagnosis of Non-AD Dementia

          3. Lifetime or current diagnosis of Schizophrenia, Bipolar Disorder or Schizoaffective
             Disorder

          4. Current episode of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)

          5. Active substance use disorder within past 6 months

          6. Treatment with ECT or other neurostimulation therapies (e.g., TMS or vagal nerve
             stimulation) within the past 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily P Kilpatrick, BA</last_name>
    <phone>617-855-3136</phone>
    <email>ekilpatrick@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Aniqa T Rahman, BA</last_name>
    <phone>617-855-3257</phone>
    <email>arahman@mclean.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 30, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 30, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brent Forester</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ECT</keyword>
  <keyword>Agitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

