<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03923426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C3591031</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EZTEAM STUDY</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03923426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Real-World Observational Study Of Zavicefta to Characterize Use Patterns</brief_title>
  <acronym>EZTEAM</acronym>
  <official_title>Real-World Observational Study of Zavicefta (Registered) (Ceftazidime-avibactam) to Characterize Use Patterns, Effectiveness and Safety - EZTEAM Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-interventional medical chart review study aiming to examine the treatment
      patterns, effectiveness, and safety of ceftazidime-avibactam in approximately 12 countries
      (including but not limited to Austria, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Spain, United Kingdom,
      Russia, Argentina, Colombia, Brazil, and Mexico), with possible expansion to other countries
      as ceftazidime-avibactam is launched. Eligible patients are adults who have been treated with
      ceftazidime-avibactam in routine practice at participating sites since 01 January, 2018
      onwards or since the date of launch in the country if it is posterior to 01 January, 2018. As
      this is an observational study, patients will be treated based on the standard of care at the
      discretion of their physician. No drugs will be supplied for this study and patients will
      receive treatment through standard local practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This observational study will include approximately 700 hospitalized patients with a
      gram-negative infection, who have received at least one dose of ceftazidime-avibactam.

      Patients will be recruited in approximately 62 sites across 12 countries in Europe (including
      Russia) and Latin America. Patients will be followed from ceftazidime-avibactam initiation
      until 60 days post hospital discharge, mortality, withdrawal from the study, or
      loss-to-follow-up, whichever occurs first.

      Data will be abstracted from medical records using an electronic case report form (eCRF).
      Baseline data include patient socio-demographics, medical history, and clinical and
      microbiological characteristics of the infection treated.

      Follow-up data will include details of treatment over time and clinical, microbiological, and
      healthcare resource utilization outcomes.

      Evaluation of clinical success will be performed in patients with at least ≥72 hours of
      exposure to ceftazidime-avibactam.

      Safety will be evaluated in all patients exposed to at least one dose of the product.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 27, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients for each indication and reason for use of ceftazidime-avibactam</measure>
    <time_frame>Drug initiation until 60 days post-hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Usage patterns including the treatment line, dose, frequency of dose, duration, and polytherapy regimens.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients for each usage pattern of ceftazidime-avibactam.</measure>
    <time_frame>Drug initiation until 60 days post-hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Usage patterns including treatment line, dose, frequency of dose, duration, and polytherapy regimens.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients treated with ceftazidime-avibactam with defined microbiologic evidence of infection.</measure>
    <time_frame>Drug initiation until 60 days post-hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Sources of infection including community-acquired infection (CAI), hospital-acquired infection (HAI) and healthcare-associated infection (HCAI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients treated with ceftazidime-avibactam with a defined source of infection.</measure>
    <time_frame>Drug initiation until 60 days post-hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Sources of infection including community-acquired infection (CAI), hospital-acquired infection (HAI) and healthcare-associated infection (HCAI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients and their respective clinical outcomes of treatment with ceftazidime-avibactam</measure>
    <time_frame>Drug initiation until 60 days post-hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment Success, Length of Stay in Hospital, In-Hospital mortality 30-60 day post discharge, and Hospital Re-Admissions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients and their respective safety outcomes of treatment with ceftazidime-avibactam</measure>
    <time_frame>Drug initiation until 60 days post-hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment Success, Length of Stay in Hospital, In-Hospital mortality 30-60 day post discharge, and Hospital Re-Admissions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zavicefta Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-interventional - Retrospective Chart Review</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Hospitalized patients with ≥72 hours of exposure to ceftazidime-avibactam at 42 European
        sites. Patients will be identified over a 12-month period and information about treatment
        will be abstracted from medical records after treatment completion. Patients will be
        followed from ceftazidime-avibactam initiation until 60 days post hospital discharge,
        mortality, withdrawal, or loss-to-follow-up, whichever occurs first.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Hospitalized patient ≥18 years old or considered an adult in accordance with the age
             of majority in the participant's country of residence at the time of treatment with
             ceftazidime-avibactam.

          2. Patient received ≥1 dose of ceftazidime-avibactam in routine practice at participating
             site since 01 January, 2018 onwards or since the date of launch in the country if it
             is after 01 January, 2018.

          3. Patient underwent microbiologic sampling ≤5 days before the initiation of
             ceftazidime-avibactam (irrespective of results and actual bacteriological
             identification).

          4. Patient has all required essential data elements which include:

               1. Start and stop dates of ceftazidime-avibactam,

               2. Start and stop dates of prior antibiotic therapy used for the index infection,

               3. Type of combined antibiotic therapy (if applicable) and start and stop dates of
                  any antibiotic combined with ceftazidime-avibactam.

          5. Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the patient (or a legally acceptable representative) has been informed of all
             pertinent aspects of the study where required by local regulations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients must not meet any of the following exclusion criteria to be eligible:

          1. The patient is enrolled in any clinical trial of an investigational product. Patients
             who are enrolled in non-interventional studies (NISs) (e.g. registries) are eligible
             for inclusion.

          2. The patient has received ceftazidime-avibactam in a compassionate care program
             setting.

          3. The patient was exposed to ceftazidime-avibactam before use for the index infection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-718-1021</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials.gov_Inquiries@pfizer.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AKH - Medizinische Universität Wien</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Angers - Hôpital Hôtel Dieu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Angers</city>
        <zip>49100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://pmiform.com/clinical-trial-info-request?StudyID=C3591031</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ceftazidime-avibactam</keyword>
  <keyword>Zavicefta</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Pfizer will provide access to individual de-identified participant data and related study documents (e.g. protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP), Clinical Study Report (CSR)) upon request from qualified researchers, and subject to certain criteria, conditions, and exceptions. Further details on Pfizer's data sharing criteria and process for requesting access can be found at: https://www.pfizer.com/science/clinical_trials/trial_data_and_results/data_requests.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

