<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03927391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REDOSE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03927391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Reduced Dose Enzalutamide in Frail (m)CRPC Patients on Cognitive Side Effects</brief_title>
  <acronym>REDOSE</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of a Reduced Dose on Cognitive Side Effects of Enzalutamide in Frail (Metastatic) Castration-resistant Prostate Cancer Patients (REDOSE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer is the most commonly diagnosed cancer among men in Western countries. When
      the disease recurs as castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) it is associated with a
      median overall survival of approximately 2 years with significant decrement in quality of
      life due to additional cancer-specific and treatment-induced morbidity. Palliative agents
      currently used in the CRPC setting include the 2nd generation hormonal agents abiraterone
      acetate and enzalutamide but also radium-223, docetaxel and cabazitaxel. Choices for
      treatment strategies are based on multiple factors such as age, co-morbidity and drug
      toxicity profile. The side effect profile of enzalutamide is associated with central nervous
      system (CNS side effects) such as fatigue and depression. The mechanism for these side
      effects is not yet fully understood, but it was shown in rodent studies that enzalutamide and
      its active metabolite penetrate into the CNS. This might cause the CNS side effects that were
      later seen in the phase 1 study where fatigue was found to be a dose-dependent adverse event.
      After dose reductions the symptoms resolved. This was also found in a retrospective study of
      Japanese metastatic CRPC (mCRPC) patients (n=345) in which the side effects malaise and
      nausea decreased remarkably after dose reduction. However, no exposure-response relation was
      observed in the study of Gibbons et al. Additionally, based on the data of the phase 1 trial
      of enzalutamide it can be suggested that a minimum trough concentration of 5.0 mg/L could be
      considered as a target for exposure to enzalutamide. In particular, frail (m)CRPC patients
      are more prone to develop CNS side effects on enzalutamide. The investigator's hypothesis is
      that dose reduction to 75% (120mg) can be safely done to treat (m)CRPC in these patients with
      preserving optimal efficacy and less CNS side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Normal enzalutamide dose versus reduced dose in two patient groups</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcome assessor does not know the treatment arm</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the change in the CNS side effect fatigue* in frail (m)CRPC patients treated with a reduced dose of enzalutamide (120mg OD) compared to the standard dose of enzalutamide (160mg OD) after 6 weeks of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>*fatigue is measured by the self-reported FACIT-fatigue questionnaire version 4 (Dutch version). Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue. 13-items are scored on a 5-point scale. All items except items 7 (I have energy) and 8 (I am able to do my usual activities) are reverse-scored before item scores are summed to obtain a total score (range 0-52). Higher scores reflect less fatigue.4 (Dutch version): Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue. 13-items are scored with a total score ranging 0-52. Higher scores reflect less fatigue.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the decrease in the CNS side effect fatigue in frail (m)CRPC patients treated with a reduced dose of enzalutamide (120mg OD) compared to the standard dose of enzalutamide (160mg OD) after 12 weeks, and 24 weeks of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>fatigue is measured by the self-reported FACIT-fatigue questionnaire version 4 (Dutch version). Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue. 13-items are scored on a 5-point scale. All items except items 7 (I have energy) and 8 (I am able to do my usual activities) are reverse-scored before item scores are summed to obtain a total score (range 0-52). Higher scores reflect less fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the impact of cognition impairment in quality of life in frail (m)CRPC patients treated with a reduced dose of enzalutamide (120mg OD) compared to the standard dose of enzalutamide (160mg OD).</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of cognition impairment in quality of life is measured by the self-repored FACT-cog questionnaire. FACT-cog: Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - For patients with Cognitive function issues. There are 4 subscale scores (perceived cognitive impairments (range 0-72), impact of perceived cognitive impairments on quality of life (range 0-16), comments from others (range 0-16) and percieved cognitive abilities (range 0-28). All subscale scores are summed to derive a total score. The higher the score, the better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine cognition impairment in frail (m)CRPC patients treated with a reduced dose of enzalutamide (120mg OD) compared to the standard dose of enzalutamide (160mg OD).</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>cognition impairment is measured by the MoCA test. Montreal Cognitive Assessment, is a test for cognition. It covers 8 tasks: attention and concentration, executive functions, memory, language, visuospatial abilities, abstract thinking, calculating abilities and orientation. The maximum score is 30 points. The higher the score, the better the cognition is.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate changes in depression score in frail (m)CRPC patients treated with a reduced dose of enzalutamide (120mg OD) compared to the standard dose of enzalutamide (160mg OD).</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Geriatric depression scale 15 (GDS-15): 15 question using an ordinal score (yes/no). Total score: maximum 15 points. A score of 0 to 5 is normal. A score greater than 5 suggests depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To correlate exposure (Ctrough) of enzalutamide and n-desmethylenzalutamide to the CNS side effects.</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlations of Ctrough and CNS side effects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the percentage (%) of subjects that remained on the allocated dose level until the end of the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>% subjects that without dose reductions or dose increments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effect of dose reduction on treatment efficacy according to prostate cancer working group 3 (PCWG3).</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Effect of dose reduction (120mg) on treatment efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasms, Castration-Resistant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>reference (normal) dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Normal dose of enzalutamide (160mg once daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>test (reduced) dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Reduced dose of enzalutamide (120mg once daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>enzalutamide treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>reference (normal) dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>test (reduced) dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Frailᵃ male patients with prostate cancer who will start treatment with enzalutamide
             within label

          -  Age at least 18 years

          -  Patient who are able and willing to give written informed consent prior to screening

          -  Patients from whom it is possible to collect blood samples

          -  Patients who are willing to answer the questionnaires and test

          -  Life expectancy of &gt; 6 months

          -  Capable of understanding and answering Dutch tests and questionnaires, as determined
             by the investigator

        ᵃ Frail is defined as:

          -  a score on the comprehensive G8 assessment with cut-off ≤14 points and

          -  score ≥grade 1 for Central Nervous Disorders according to the Common Toxicity Criteria
             Adverse Event (CTCAE) criteria, of one of the following: Fatigue, Concentration
             impairment, cognitive disturbance, amnesia, depressed level of consciousness, memory
             impairment, hypersomnia.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  change in dose of opioids/sedatives/benzodiazepines during last 2 weeks before study)

          -  Use of psychostimulants such as methylphenidate within 1 week of start of study

          -  Diagnosed with medical conditions that affect cognition: Dementia, Alzheimer disease,
             Parkinson's disease, psychiatric disorders that affect cognition other than depression
             or anxiety complaints related to the disease

          -  Active infection or other comorbidities that may contribute to REDOSE, February 2019
             Page 7 of 53 fatigue or cognition change within 4 weeks of study entry

          -  Clinical relevant anaemia

          -  MoCa score &lt;20

          -  Hypersensitivity to the active substance or to any of the excipients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Prostate cancer is only prevalent in the male population</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>n van Erp</last_name>
    <phone>+31243610000</phone>
    <email>nielka.vanerp@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CWZ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rik Somford, Dr</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboudumc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nielka van Erp, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Inge van Oort, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Niven Mehra, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Franciscus Gasthuis en Vlietland hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Hamberg, Dr</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>enzalutamide</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive side effects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms, Castration-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

