<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04209361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Dentists and child abuse</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04209361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Knowledge, Attitude and Practice of Dentists at Military Hospitals Regarding Child Abuse and Neglect.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Knowledge, Attitude and Practice (KAP) of Dentists at Military Hospitals Regarding Child Abuse and Neglect: A Cross-sectional Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gaining information about the knowledge, attitude and practice of dentists regarding child
      abuse and neglect will help identifying the points of weakness, improving their knowledge and
      assessing the need for additional training in relation to child protection. Thus,
      highlighting the importance of reporting cases of suspected child abuse which in turn may
      improve the status of abused children and save them from horrible situations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Children are considered to be more vulnerable than other society members because of their
      young age and lack of adequate skills. The annual report of United Nations Children's Fund
      (UNICEF) stated that a number of children have lost their lives as a result of maltreatment
      and violence.

      Child abuse is a meaningful problem that exists among different cultural and socio-economic
      groups. Child abuse includes several conditions that threaten and harms lives of children. It
      is considered to be one of the largest causes of pediatric mortality.

      The World Health Organization (WHO) defines CAN as 'Every kind of physical, sexual, emotional
      abuse, neglect or negligent treatment, commercial or other exploitation resulting in actual
      or potential harm to the child's health, survival, development, or dignity in the context of
      a relationship of responsibility, trust or power'.

      The American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry (AAPD) defined dental neglect, as 'willful
      failure of a parent or guardian to seek and follow through with whatever treatment is
      necessary to ensure a level of oral health essential for adequate chewing function and
      freedom from pain and infection'.

      The Child Abuse Committee of the Council on Clinical Affairs developed that definition and it
      was approved in 1983.

      In West and Central Africa, children are susceptible to various hazards since birth including
      human trafficking, child labor, child marriage, conflict and other emergencies.

      Frequently, abusive injuries comprise the face and oral cavity thus, dental providers may be
      the first to encounter these injuries. Many surveys revealed that 50 -77% of child abuse
      cases involving head and neck regions, consequently placing oral health care workers in an
      important position to detect, diagnose, document, and report to convenient authorities.

      As approximately 50% of injuries due to child abuse occur in head and neck region, medical
      and dental professionals are in a good position for early detection and diagnosis of physical
      child abuse. Almost 15% of child abuse related injuries are confined to the head region
      Therefore, dentists have a significant role in improving the status of abused children and
      saving them from their dire situation.

      Research has shown that guardians or parents who abuse their children regularly change their
      child's physicians, but very rarely change their dentists, thus dentists are considered to be
      in the most ideal position for detection of physical abuse in children. The American Dental
      Association reported the first documented evidence of dentists failing to report child
      maltreatment in 1967, declaring that none of 416 reported cases of child abuse was reported
      by a dentist in New York State.

      In Egypt, few studies have discussed the problem of child abuse. Cases in most of these
      studies were collected from emergency, clinical departments, social welfare, criminal records
      or autopsies. Child abuse among Egyptian primary-school children was studied in 1994 and
      1999. No data were collected regarding the prevalence of abuse among older preparatory-school
      and secondary school children.

      Also few data are available about the knowledge, attitudes and practices of primary health
      care professionals toward prevention and treatment of childhood unintentional injuries.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>knowledge, attitude and practice of dentists at military hospitals regarding child abuse and neglect.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Obtaining information about the knowledge, attitude and practice of dentists regarding child abuse and neglect by a printed questionnaire with binary and multiple choice questions as measuring units.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Child Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Child Maltreatment</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Data will be obtained through a printed questionnaire for assessment of knowledge, attitude and practice of dentists at military hospitals regarding child abuse and neglect. The collected data will be saved and tabulated on a computer and finally will be statistically analyzed.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Dentists working in military hospitals.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Army officer dentists at military hospitals.

          -  Civilian dentists at military hospitals.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under graduate students and interns.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Begad Hamdy Ahmed, Bachelor</last_name>
    <phone>01006097223</phone>
    <email>Begad.Hamdy@dentistry.cu.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Afifi ZE, El-Lawindi MI, Ahmed SA, Basily WW. Adolescent abuse in a community sample in Beni Suef, Egypt: prevalence and risk factors. East Mediterr Health J. 2003 Sep-Nov;9(5-6):1003-18.</citation>
    <PMID>16450531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Badam RK, Sownetha T, Babu DBG, Waghray S, Reddy L, Garlapati K, Chavva S. Virtopsy: Touch-free autopsy. J Forensic Dent Sci. 2017 Jan-Apr;9(1):42. doi: 10.4103/jfo.jfds_7_16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28584475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bunney PE, Zink AN, Holm AA, Billington CJ, Kotz CM. Orexin activation counteracts decreases in nonexercise activity thermogenesis (NEAT) caused by high-fat diet. Physiol Behav. 2017 Jul 1;176:139-148. doi: 10.1016/j.physbeh.2017.03.040. Epub 2017 Mar 28.</citation>
    <PMID>28363838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Definition of Dental Neglect. Pediatr Dent. 2017 Sep 15;39(6):13.</citation>
    <PMID>29179302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fisher-Owens SA, Lukefahr JL, Tate AR; AMERICAN ACADEMY OF PEDIATRICS, SECTION ON ORAL HEALTH; COMMITTEE ON CHILD ABUSE AND NEGLECT; AMERICAN ACADEMY OF PEDIATRIC DENTISTRY, COUNCIL ON CLINICAL AFFAIRS, COUNCIL ON SCIENTIFIC AFFAIRS; AD HOC WORK GROUP ON CHILD ABUSE AND NEGLECT. Oral and Dental Aspects of Child Abuse and Neglect. Pediatrics. 2017 Aug;140(2). pii: e20171487. doi: 10.1542/peds.2017-1487.</citation>
    <PMID>28771417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hazar Bodrumlu E, Avşar A, Arslan S. Assessment of knowledge and attitudes of dental students in regard to child abuse in Turkey. Eur J Dent Educ. 2018 Feb;22(1):40-46. doi: 10.1111/eje.12242. Epub 2016 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27735105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jahanimoghadam F, Kalantari M, Horri A, Ahmadipour H, Pourmorteza E. A Survey of Knowledge, Attitude and Practice of Iranian Dentists and Pedodontists in Relation to Child Abuse. J Dent (Shiraz). 2017 Dec;18(4):282-288.</citation>
    <PMID>29201972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaur H, Chaudhary S, Choudhary N, Manuja N, Chaitra TR, Amit SA. Child abuse: Cross-sectional survey of general dentists. J Oral Biol Craniofac Res. 2016 May-Aug;6(2):118-23. doi: 10.1016/j.jobcr.2015.08.002. Epub 2015 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>27195209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deshpande A, Macwan C, Poonacha KS, Bargale S, Dhillon S, Porwal P. Knowledge and attitude in regards to physical child abuse amongst medical and dental residents of central Gujarat: a cross-sectional survey. J Indian Soc Pedod Prev Dent. 2015 Jul-Sep;33(3):177-82. doi: 10.4103/0970-4388.160344.</citation>
    <PMID>26156270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>begad hamdy ahmed own</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Child abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Dentists</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

