<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04209322</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRF003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04209322</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Pulsed Radiofrequency for Sciatica and Disc Herniation</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRATS</acronym>
  <official_title>Trial of Pulsed Radiofrequency for Sciatica and Disc Herniation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Roma La Sapienza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Roma La Sapienza</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Transforaminal epidural injection of treatments, commonly steroids (TFESI), is offered to
      people with sciatica and might improve symptoms, reduce disability and speed up return to
      normal activities (NICE guidelines) Imaging-guided TFESI has traditionally been performed in
      the sciatica context because injection is administered directly to the nerve root, which
      relieves the pain markedly; however, the maintenance time is usually short.

      Treatment with radiofrequency for pain management is in clinical use since decades primarily
      with nerve lesioning (thermoablation) once the specific pain tributary nerve is identified.

      Pulsed radiofrequency (PRF) with neuromodulation intention (not lesioning) has been shown to
      be effective in reducing some types of chronic pain, both degenerative and neuropathic.

      Pulsed radiofrequency has been also extensively used in the context of acute and subacute
      sciatica due to disc herniation without sufficient level of evidence. In a prospective RCT,
      comparing prf directed to dorsal root ganglia and Tfesi in patients with sciatica did not
      allow conclusions on efficacy because of limitations of the trial. In that trial, only few
      participants completed the study due to violation of trial protocol translating the results
      as not consistent.

      One retrospective trial, in which the use of Prf in addition to tfesi was evaluated in
      patients with acute and subacute sciatica, demonstrated rapid pain relief onset and prolonged
      maintenance; the overall efficacy was superior to that of the single method treatment (either
      tfsei or prf).

      The investigators conducted a randomized, double-blind, controlled trial (Pulsed
      Radiofrequency in Addition to Tfesi for Sciatica [PRATS]) to determine if PRF in addition to
      TFESI leads to better outcomes in the management of patients with acute and subacute sciatica
      due to disc herniation, compared to TFESI alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators conducted a multicenter, prospective, randomized trial among patients with
      6 to 12 weeks of sciatic pain to determine whether a strategy of PRF in addition to TFESI
      leads to better outcomes during the first year than does a strategy of TFESI only means for
      sciatica treatment.

      Eligible patients were 18 to 75 years of age, had a radiologically confirmed disk herniation,
      and had received a diagnosis from an attending neurologist of an incapacitating lumbosacral
      radicular syndrome that had lasted for 6 to 12 weeks. Correlation of magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) findings with symptoms was registered. Patients presenting with cauda equina
      syndrome, muscle paralysis, or insufficient strength to move against gravity were excluded.
      Other exclusion criteria were cardiac pace-maker implant, pregnancy, or severe coexisting
      disease. The occurrence of another episode of symptoms similar to those of the current
      episode during the previous 12 months, previous spine surgery and spondylolisthesis were not
      considered contraindications but bony stenosis.

      A computer-generated permuted-block scheme was used for randomization, with patients
      stratified according to center. A few hours before randomization, the patients were evaluated
      again, and those who had recovered from their symptoms at that time were excluded from the
      trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>multicenter, prospective, randomized trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Leg-Pain Intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome was the average leg-pain intensity score over the course of the previous 1 week (on a numerical pain-rating scale from 0 to 10, with 0 indicating no pain and 10 the worst possible pain; clinically important difference, 2 points), as assessed at 1 week, 4 weeks, 12 weeks and 52 weeks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Roland Morris disability questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>extent of disability as measured on the Roland Disability Questionnaire for Sciatica (scores range from 0 to 23, with higher scores indicating greater disability; clinically important difference, 8 points), as assessed at 4 weeks, 12 weeks and 52 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oswestry Disability Index questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>extent of disability as measured on the Oswestry Disability Index (on a % scale from 0 to 100, version 2.0, MODEMS; clinically important difference, 10 points), as assessed at 4 weeks, 12 weeks and 52 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain change questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>global perceived effect (post-treatment symptoms as compared with baseline, on a scale from −5 [vastly worse] to 0 [unchanged], to +5 [completely recovered])</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Data regarding treatment-related side-effects will be registered.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>workplace absenteeism questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The cumulative number of days of workplace absenteeism due to sciatica</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction on current condition</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective evaluation of current condition, expressed in terms of percentage, with 0% indicating completely disappointed and 100% indicating completely satisfied</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Sciatica</condition>
  <condition>Lumbar Disc Herniation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pulsed Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aseptic technique was adopted. Imaging guided (CT) catheter needle (active tip electrode) was inserted and a sensory stimulation test was carried out using an RF generator. The catheter needle was then advanced toward the DRG until the patient reported a tingling sensation and/or dysesthesia at less than 0.3V. PRF treatment was administered at 5 Hz and a 2 ms pulsed width for 10 minutes at 45V under the constraint that the electrode tip temperature not exceed 42°C. Finally, patients received 1 mL lidocaine 20 mg/ml mixed with 40 mg triamcinolone acetonide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transforaminal Epidural Steroid Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aseptic technique was adopted. Imaging guided (CT) catheter needle (active tip electrode) was inserted and a sensory stimulation test was carried out using an RF generator. The catheter needle was then advanced toward the DRG until the patient reported a tingling sensation and/or dysesthesia at less than 0.3V. After 10 minutes await (as per pRF), patients received 1 mL lidocaine 20 mg/ml mixed with 40 mg triamcinolone acetonide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pulsed Radiofrequency</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-surgical treatment of lumbar disc herniation causing sciatica using pulsed radiofrequency (10 minutes) directed to the interested dorsal root ganglia (percutaneous technique); after radiofrequency application, using the same needle, steroid was administered (as per the control arm). The procedure was guided by CT imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pulsed Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transforaminal Epidural Steroid Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Percutaneous injection of steroid in the nerve root foramen. The procedure was guided by CT imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transforaminal Epidural Steroid Injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible patients had radiologically confirmed disk herniation, and had received a
             diagnosis from an attending neurologist of an incapacitating lumbosacral radicular
             syndrome that had lasted for 6 to 12 weeks. Correlation of magnetic resonance imaging
             (MRI) findings with symptoms was required.

          -  The occurrence of another episode of symptoms similar to those of the current episode
             during the previous 12 months, previous spine surgery and spondylolisthesis were not
             considered contraindications

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients presenting with cauda equina syndrome, muscle paralysis, or insufficient
             strength to move against gravity were excluded. Other exclusion criteria were cardiac
             pace-maker implant, pregnancy, or severe coexisting disease.

          -  Vertebral canal stenosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Sana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aprilia</city>
        <state>LT</state>
        <zip>04011</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alessandro Napoli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Roma La Sapienza</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alessandro Napoli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associated Professor of Radiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sciatica</keyword>
  <keyword>lumbar disc herniation</keyword>
  <keyword>radiofrequency</keyword>
  <keyword>non invasive treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sciatica</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hernia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data are available to all authors for 5 years after main study completion</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

