<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04201444</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHUBX 2018/60</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04201444</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hair Cortisol and Cushing's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>HAIRCUSH</acronym>
  <official_title>Usefulness of Hair Cortisol/Cortisone Concentrations for the Monitoring of Medical Treatment in Patients With Cushing's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Bordeaux</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Bordeaux</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The biochemical tools usable to assess the control of hypercortisolism in patients with
      Cushing's disease receiving medical treatments are debatable. The aim of the study is to
      compare the results of the measurement of cortisol and cortisone using high-performance
      liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) in scalp hair (so called &quot;Hair
      Cortisol&quot;) to that of 24h urinary free cortisol (UFC) and late night salivary cortisol (LNSC)
      for the monitoring of medical therapy in patients with Cushing's disease (CD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Selective surgical removal of the pituitary corticotroph adenoma is the ideal treatment of
      Cushing's disease. However, surgery may not be feasible or is unsuccessful in roughly 25% of
      patients. In addition, a recurrence of the disease is observed after a transient remission in
      15 to 25% of patients. Several therapeutic alternatives are available, amongst which medical
      treatment is commonly used. Drugs that are available in France to control hypercortisolism
      target the pituitary adenoma secretion (pasireotide and cabergoline) or inhibit adrenal
      steroidogenesis (ketoconazole and metyrapone). Usual criteria to monitor the treatment and
      titrate the drug dosage include evaluation of relevant clinical endpoints and measurement of
      UFC. However, limitations of UFC for this purpose, include difficulties in obtaining a
      complete 24 urine collection and the fact that UFC assess only short-term cortisol in a
      disease characterized by high variability over time in the intensity of hypercortisolism.
      Elsewhere, a mild to moderate hypercortisolism may persist despite a normal UFC. Several
      groups, including ours, have shown that LNSC is useful tool to diagnose overt and mild
      hypercortisolism and may be more sensitive than UFC to diagnose mild hypercortisolism.
      Despite being more convenient to collect than 24h urine, LNSC also suffers from only
      measuring time-point cortisol. Rare studies have examined whether LNSC could be an adequate
      biomarker for monitoring response to medical therapy in patients with CD and its usefulness
      to monitor drug treatment in CD is yet unknown (one study comparing UFC to LNSC in CD
      patients treated with pasireotide-LAR has been presented but is not yet published).
      Accordingly, the 2015 guidelines of the endocrine society recommend future research to
      accurately monitor patients for their response to medical therapy to guide dose optimization.
      More recently, the measurement of salivary cortisone in 3 saliva samples (SCx3) drawn at
      approximately 8 hours intervals and starting at 7-8 am have been shown to be a reliable
      estimate of cortisol production over 24h in normal subjects. Whether this parameter could be
      used as a substitute of UFC in patients treated with anticortisolic drugs remains unstudied.

      Hair cortisol concentration is a non-invasive way to measure cortisol exposure over much
      longer periods of time (weeks and months) than previously possible with samples of blood,
      saliva or urine. Several studies have shown that measurement of cortisol in a single scalp
      hair sample has a diagnostic accuracy for CS similar to currently used first-line tests and
      may also be used to identify overtreatment in patients receiving hydrocortisone replacement
      for adrenal insufficiency. To date, no data is available concerning hair Cortisol measurement
      in comparison with other usual biological tools in patients with CD receiving a medical
      treatment.

      Since 2016, the departments of endocrine biology and clinical endocrinology of Bordeaux
      university hospital (CHU) have developed the measurement of cortisol and cortisone in scalp
      hair using LC-MS/MS and have established normative values using several cohorts of control
      patients.

      The purpose of the study is to take advantage of the ability of hair cortisol to measure
      long-term cortisol exposure to assess the response to medical therapy in patients with CD.
      More specifically, the working hypothesis is that some patients with a normal UFC may still
      suffer from an occult mild hypercortisolism that will be identified only by hair cortisol. To
      study this hypothesis, the investigators will compare the results of hair cortisol to that
      multiple measurement of UFC, LNSC and SCx3 during a three-month period in patients with CD
      already treated with medical treatments and considered as &quot;controlled&quot; on the basis of
      previous UFC measurements.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate cortisol chronic tissue impregnation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Hypercortisolism will be controlled using 3 cm scalp hair sample in which Hair Cortisol will be measured in patients with Cushing Disease (CD) receiving a medical treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Hair Cortisol (Hcort) measure for Cushing Disease control</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Compare Hair Cortisol to UFC (Urinary Free Cortisol), LNSC (late night salivary cortisol) and SC (salivary cortisone) in patients with CD receiving a medical treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare cortisol tissue impregnation thanks to Hair Cortisol measurements in patients with CD receiving a medical treatment and patients control</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the results of Hair Cortisol measurements in patients with CD receiving a medical treatment and patients treated with weight-adjusted hydrocortisone replacement doses after bilateral adrenalectomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare cortisol tissue impregnation thanks to Hair Cortisol measurements in patients cured from CD and patient with bilateral adrenalectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the results of Hair Cortisol measurements in patients cured from CD and patients with bilateral adrenalectomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Hair Cortisol intra-individual variability</measure>
    <time_frame>At day 0 and day 90</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the dosage of within-patient variability of Hair Cortisol for patients with CD receiving a medical treatment and control groups : patients cured from CD and patients with bilateral adrenalectomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate UFC intra-individual variability</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the within-patient variability of UFC in patients with CD receiving a medical treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction assessed by Cushing's QOL</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Correlate a quality of life assessment with the results of Hair Cortisol, UFC and LNSC thanks to QOL questionnaire : cushing's QOL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate LNSC intra-individual variability</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the dosage of within-patient variability of LNSC in patients with CD receiving a medical treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate SC intra-individual variability</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after inclusion day</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the dosage of within-patient variability of SC in patients with CD receiving a medical treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cushing Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Remission control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bilateral surrenalectomy control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with Cushing Disease (CD) receiving a medical treatment: n = 30 Plasmatic cortisol UFC Urine biocollection Salive biocollection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remission control group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in remission of CD and having recovered a normal pituitary function for at least 12 months following pituitary surgery (normal UFC associated to: cortisol suppression following dexamethasone suppression test, or normal LNSC, or midnight serum cortisol &lt; 200 nmol/L) n = 15 Plasmatic cortisol UFC Urine biocollection Salive biocollection Haircortisol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Remission control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bilateral surrenalectomy control group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with previous CD, treated with bilateral adrenalectomy and receiving weight adjusted doses of hydrocortisone for at least 6 months. Last daily dose of Hydrocortisone should be administered no later than 5 pm. n = 15 Plasmatic cortisol UFC Urine biocollection Salive biocollection Haircortisol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bilateral surrenalectomy control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        In the three groups:

          -  Age &gt; 18

          -  Cushing's disease medical history: histology confirming an ACTH staining adenoma, or
             ACTH-dependant Cushing syndrome with MRI confirmation of pituitary adenoma, or
             pituitary secretion of ACTH confirmed with petrosal sinus gradient

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Hair length ≥ 3 cm

        In patient group:

          -  Persistent CD diagnosed on usual criteria in expert centers including overt
             hypercortisolism with at least 2 UFC &gt; 1.5 N prior to the start of medical treatment

          -  Previous treatment with pasireotide, cabergoline, metyrapone, ketoconazole (alone or
             in association) AND hypercortisolism considered as controlled for at least 3 months
             based on 2 normal UFC.

        In remission control group:

        o Patients cured of CD and having recovered a normal pituitary function for at least 12
        months following pituitary surgery (normal UFC associated to: cortisol suppression
        following dexamethasone suppression test, or normal LNSC, or midnight serum cortisol &lt; 200
        nmol/L)

        In bilateral surrenalectomy control group:

        o Patients with previous CD, treated with bilateral adrenalectomy and receiving weight
        adjusted doses of hydrocortisone for at least 6 months. Last daily dose of Hydrocortisone
        should be administered no later than 5 pm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        In the three groups:

          -  Renal Failure (Cl &lt; 30 mL/min)

          -  Non-compliant patients

          -  Hair length &lt; 3 cm

          -  Severe depression and psychosis

          -  Drug addiction and active alcoholism

          -  Myocardial infarction or cerebrovascular accident &lt; 3 months

          -  Intense physical activity (marathon runner)

          -  Night-shifters

          -  Obesity with BMI &gt; 35 kg/m2

          -  Type 1 diabetes

          -  Type 2 diabetes with HbA1C &gt; 9 %

        In patient group:

          -  Patients receiving mifepristone and/or mitotane

          -  Patients treated with anticortisolic agents during the titration process

          -  Patients requiring additional hydrocortisone supplementation or exogenous
             corticosteroids

          -  Pituitary radiotherapy &lt; 5 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antoine TABARIN, Pr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Bordeaux</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Antoine TABARIN, Pr</last_name>
    <phone>5.57.65.62.77</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>antoine.tabarin@chu-bordeaux.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah CAZENAVE</last_name>
    <phone>5.57.65.62.77</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>sarah.cazenave@chu-bordeaux.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Endocrinologie - CHU Caen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <zip>14000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yves REZNIK, Pr</last_name>
      <email>reznik-y@chu-caen.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'endocrinologie - HCL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gérald RAVEROT, Pr</last_name>
      <email>gerald.raverot@chu-lyon.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Endocrinologie, Diabète et Maladies Métaboliques - APHM</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thierry BRUE, Pr</last_name>
      <email>Thierry.BRUE@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CIC d'Endocrinologie, Maladies Métaboliques et Nutrition - CHU de Nantes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <zip>44000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bertrand CARIOU, Pr</last_name>
      <email>bertrand.cariou@univ-nantes.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Endocrinologie - APHP Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jerome BERTHERAT, Pr</last_name>
      <email>jerome.bertherat@ch.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Endocrinologie et des Maladies de la Reproduction - APHP Bicêtre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacques YOUNG, Pr</last_name>
      <email>jacques.young@bct.ap-hop-paris.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'endocirnologie, diabète, nutrition, Hôpital Haut Lévêque - CHU de Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antoine TABARIN, Pr</last_name>
      <phone>5.57.65.62.77</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>antoine.tabarin@chu-bordeaux.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>UFC</keyword>
  <keyword>LNSC</keyword>
  <keyword>Hair cortisol</keyword>
  <keyword>medical treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>ACTH-Secreting Pituitary Adenoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary ACTH Hypersecretion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

