<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04205851</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KIN-1901-1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04205851</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Study With KIN-1901 in Healthy Subjects and Subjects With Ankylosing Spondylitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Ascending Single- and Multiple-Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of Subcutaneous Gimsilumab in Healthy Subjects and Subjects With Ankylosing Spondylitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kinevant Sciences GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kinevant Sciences GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is intended to treat ankylosing spondylitis (AS). AS is a form of arthritis that
      primarily affects the spine. It is characterized by inflammation of the spinal joints that
      can lead to severe pain, and in more advanced cases, ankylosis (sections of the spine fuse in
      a fixed, immobile position). The study will be an ascending single and multiple-dose study to
      evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics of subcutaneous
      KIN-1901 in healthy subjects and subjects with AS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      KIN-1901 is a fully human immunoglobulin monoclonal antibody (mAb) directed towards a
      proinflammatory cytokine that is believed to have a role in inflammation and autoimmunity,
      and is found in synovial fluid from patients with spondyloarthritis. Therefore,
      neutralization of this cytokine activity by specific monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) could be
      beneficial in treating certain spondyloarthropathies such as ankylosing spondylitis (AS).

      The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of escalating
      single-dose or once-weekly repeat-dose subcutaneous (SC) administration of KIN-1901 in
      healthy subjects (Cohorts 1 through 4) and in subjects with AS (Cohort 5). The secondary
      objective of the study is to evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK) of escalating single-dose and
      once-weekly repeat-dose SC administration of KIN-1901 in healthy subjects (Cohorts 1 through
      4) and in subjects with AS (Cohort 5). The following exploratory objectives will also be
      evaluated: (1) To explore the pharmacodynamic (PD) effects of escalating single-dose and
      once-weekly repeat-dose SC administration of KIN-1901 in healthy subjects (Cohorts 1 through
      4), (2) To explore the PD effects and changes in disease activity by Assessment in Ankylosing
      Spondylitis Criteria ASAS 20/40 (and components) and Ankylosing Spondylitis Disease Activity
      Score-CRP (ASDAS-CRP) of once-weekly repeat-dose SC administration of KIN-1901 in subjects
      with AS (Cohort 5), (3) To assess biomarkers of efficacy and safety after once-weekly
      repeat-dose SC administration of KIN-1901 in subjects with AS (Cohort 5).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 12, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 7, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 7, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, double-blind (Sponsor unblind), multi-cohort, placebo-controlled design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in QTcF interval</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in clinical chemistry parameter hsCRP determined by laboratory testing</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of serum anti-drug antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
    <description>Time to Cmax</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 57 days (Cohort 1 and 2); Up to 78 days (Cohorts 3, 4, and 5)</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the concentration-time curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <condition>Rheumatic Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>KIN-1901</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single or repeat (once weekly for 4 weeks) KIN-1901 subcutaneous injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single or repeat (once weekly for 4 weeks) placebo subcutaneous injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KIN-1901</intervention_name>
    <description>KIN-1901 is a fully human monoclonal antibody (mAb).</description>
    <arm_group_label>KIN-1901</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Main Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with study
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          2. Age requirements:

               -  Cohorts 1 through 4 (healthy): Male or female age ≥ 18 years and ≤ 50 years.

               -  Cohort 5 (AS): Male or female age ≥ 18 years and ≤ 75 years.

          3. Females must agree to use a highly effective birth control method (&lt;1% failure rate
             per year) throughout the study, reproductive status of non-childbearing based on
             medical history, or is postmenopausal:

               -  Non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal female with medical history
                  of bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy (removal of the ovaries) or
                  hysterectomy; hysteroscopic sterilization,

               -  Postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea; with follicle
                  stimulating hormone (FSH) confirmation.

               -  Woman of Childbearing potential (WCBP) who is already using an established method
                  of highly effective contraception or agrees to use one of the allowed BC methods
                  for at least 28 days prior to the start of dosing (as determined by the
                  Investigator Brochure or Investigator or designee) to sufficiently minimize the
                  risk of pregnancy throughout study participation (until completion their study
                  follow-up visit).

          4. Males who are sexually active must agree to use one of the allowed birth control
             methods. Male subjects must also agree to sufficiently minimize the risk of pregnancy
             throughout study participation (until completion their follow-up visit).

          5. Body Mass Index (BMI):

               -  Cohorts 1-4 (healthy): BMI 18.5 to 31 kg/m2 at Screening

               -  Cohort 5 (AS): BMI 18 to 33 kg/m2 at Screening

             Additional Inclusion Criteria for Cohort 5 (AS) only:

          6. AS diagnosis fulfilling the Modified New York criteria for AS.

          7. Active AS, as defined by the Bath Ankylosing Spondylitis Disease Activity Index
             (BASDAI) ≥ 4 despite NSAID, corticosteroid or DMARD therapy.

          8. BASDAI, item 2, spinal pain score ≥ 4 (out of 10).

          9. AS diagnosis confirmed by Sacroiliac (SI) imaging within the last 2 years (confirmed
             by central reader during Screening).

         10. Does not have a history of complete spinal ankylosis.

         11. CRP &gt; ULN at Screening.

         12. Two prior failures to NSAID therapy (sub-optimal clinical response following four
             weeks at maximum tolerated dose) or intolerance to NSAID therapy.

        Main Exclusion Criteria:

        An individual will NOT be eligible for inclusion in this study if any of the following
        criteria apply.

          1. Clinically significant illness which required medical treatment within 8 weeks or a
             clinically significant infection within 4 weeks prior to Screening.

          2. Disease diagnosis that may influence the outcome of the study; such as psychiatric
             disorders or disorders of the gastrointestinal tract, liver, kidney, respiratory
             system, endocrine system, hematological system, neurological system, cardiovascular
             system within 4 weeks prior to randomization, or individuals who have preexisting
             metabolic congenital abnormality(ies).

          3. Positive Quantiferon test.

          4. Use of prescription and non-prescription drugs:

               -  Cohorts 1 through 4 (healthy): Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs,
                  including vitamins, herbal and dietary supplements within 14 days or 5 half-lives
                  (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of study treatment, unless in the
                  opinion of an Investigator and Medical Monitor the medication will not interfere
                  with the study procedures or compromise subject safety or permitted under Section
                  5.10.1.

               -  Cohort 5 (AS):

               -  Current or prior treatment regimen that includes a biologic therapy (e.g.,
                  anti-TNF-alpha, anti-IL-17A, anti-IL-6, or anti-IL-12/23)

               -  Use of parenteral and/or intra-articular steroids or immunosuppressants within 6
                  weeks prior to the first dose of study treatment.

             Oral steroids are permitted if the dosage is ≤10 mg/day prednisone (or equivalent) and
             is stable for a minimum of 4 weeks before the first dose of study treatment and
             remains unchanged throughout the study.

             Also note:

             Oral NSAID treatment is permitted if the dosage is stable for a minimum of 2 weeks
             before the first dose of study treatment and remains unchanged throughout the study.

             Oral sulfasalazine treatment is permitted if the dosage is ≤ 3 g/d (max) and is stable
             for a minimum of 4 weeks before the first dose of study treatment and remains
             unchanged throughout the study.

             Oral methotrexate use is permitted if used for a minimum of 3 months, the dosage is ≤
             20 mg/week, and is the dose stable for a minimum of 4 weeks (including dosage of
             concomitant folate) before the first dose of study treatment and remains unchanged
             throughout the study.

             Subcutaneous methotrexate use is permitted if the dosage is ≤ 20 mg/week and is stable
             for a minimum of 4 weeks (including dosage of concomitant folate) before the first
             dose of study treatment and remains unchanged throughout the study.

          5. Individual who received an investigational product (including placebo) 30 days prior
             to the start of dosing (5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of
             the investigational product), whichever is longer.

          6. Weight loss or gain of &gt;10% between screening and up to the start of dosing.

          7. Hemoglobin level ≤ 12 g/dL at Screening.

          8. Positive result for HIV (HIV-1/HIV-2 Antibodies), HBsAg or HCVAb screening tests.

          9. Known or suspected history of drug abuse (amphetamines, barbiturates, cannabinoids,
             cocaine, opiates and phencyclidine) or alcohol misuse* within 6 months prior to
             Screening, or a positive urine drug test and/or alcohol breathalyzer test at Screening
             or baseline.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Altasciences Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3P 3P1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spondylitis, Ankylosing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spondylitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spondylitis, Ankylosing</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rheumatic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Collagen Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

