<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04207164</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1045762</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04207164</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Translation and Psychometric Testing of the Norwegian Foot Functional Index Revised, Short Version.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Translation, Cross-culture Adaption of Foot Functional Index Revised, Short Version (FFI-RS) Into Norwegian. Testing of Psychometric Properties.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oslo University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to translate into Norwegian and cross-culturally adapt the Foot
      Functional Index- revised, short version (FFI-RS) according to international guidelines.
      Furthermore, the reliability and the validity, responsiveness as well as floor and ceiling
      effect of the Norwegian version of the FFI-RS will be determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Foot Functional Index, revised short version is a foot specific patient reported outcome
      measurement (PROM) which covers pain, stiffness, activity limitations, disability as well as
      psychosocial issues.

      The aim of this study is to translate into Norwegian and cross-culturally adapt Foot
      Functional Index revised, short version (NFFI-RS). Furthermore, the reliability, validity,
      interpretability and responsiveness will be determined.

      The Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation at Oslo University Hospital has an
      ongoing double blind, randomized sham-controlled trial (RCT) comparing the effect of radial
      extracorporeal shock wave therapy (rESWT), sham rESWT, standardized exercise program and
      usual care for patients with longstanding plantar fasciopathy (NCT03472989). The testing of
      the psychometric properties of the NFFI-RS will include totally hundred patients, both from
      the mentioned RCT as well as patients with other foot diagnosis recruited from our
      department.

      The translation of the original FFI-RS into Norwegian has been done following the official
      guidelines.

      In the test-retest study fifty patients will complete the NFFI-RS at a one week interval.

      Smallest detectable change, measurement error, floor and ceiling effects as well as internal
      consistency will be calculated by using the baseline data. To decide the construct validity
      we will test the various hypothesis at baseline.

      To calculate the responsiveness and the minimal clinically important change three months data
      will be assessed. Hypothesis testing for correlation with Patient Global Impression of Change
      Scale will be used to assess the minimal clinically important change and responsiveness of
      the NFFI-RS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Foot Functional Index revised short version ( FFI-RS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 week, 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>FFI-RS is a foot specific pain and function score. We will evaluate the reliability of the FFI-RS by testing the internal consistency (Cronbach's Alpha). Furthermore test-retest will be done with a second FFI-RS recording after one week (ANOVA and intraclass correlation coefficient). We will evaluate construct validity with other instruments (RAND and NRS). To test the responsiveness of FFI-RS, we will evaluate the change in FFI-RS from baseline to 3 months with Patient Global Impression of Change score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Rating Scale (NRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Change in heel pain (during Activity last week). NRS is a patient reported pain intensity scale ranging from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst possible pain). NRS will by used for evaluating the construct validity of FFI-RS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RAND-12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Health related quality of life (12 items). RAND-12 will be used for evaluating the construct validity of FFI-RS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Impression Of Change Scale (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>7-point scale ranging from &quot;very much improved&quot; to &quot;very much worse&quot;. PGIC will be used for evaluating the responsiveness of FFI-RS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Foot Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Plantar Fascitis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with foot pain attending the Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation at
        Oslo University Hospital (OUS), Norway will be included. Some of the patients will have the
        diagnosis Plantar Fasciopathy (PF) and is a part of the ongoing RCT from the same
        department at OUS: &quot;The effectiveness of radial extracorporeal shock wave therapy (rESWT),
        sham rESWT, standardised exercised exercise programme or usual care for patients with
        plantar fasciopathy.&quot; (NCT03472989)(2017/1325 Regional Comimittee for Medical and Health
        Research Ethics,Norway).

        Rest of the study population will be patients with othe foot complaints.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with pain localized in the foot

          -  Patients understanding oral and written Norwegian

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients without pain in the foot

          -  Patients not understanding oral and written Norwegian
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aasne F Hoksrud, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Oslo University Hospital, Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marianne Mørk, PT Msc</last_name>
    <phone>+4792019107</phone>
    <email>mamork@studmed.uio.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Aasne F Hoksrud, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+4747417204</phone>
    <email>aahoks@us-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo University Hospital, Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0450</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marianne Mørk, Msc PT</last_name>
      <phone>004792019107</phone>
      <email>mamork@studmed.uio.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Aasne F Hoksrud, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>004747417204</phone>
      <email>aahoks@ous-hf.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Budiman-Mak E, Conrad KJ, Roach KE. The Foot Function Index: a measure of foot pain and disability. J Clin Epidemiol. 1991;44(6):561-70.</citation>
    <PMID>2037861</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Budiman-Mak E, Conrad K, Stuck R, Matters M. Theoretical model and Rasch analysis to develop a revised Foot Function Index. Foot Ankle Int. 2006 Jul;27(7):519-27.</citation>
    <PMID>16842719</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hays RD, Morales LS. The RAND-36 measure of health-related quality of life. Ann Med. 2001 Jul;33(5):350-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11491194</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Beaton DE, Bombardier C, Guillemin F, Ferraz MB. Guidelines for the process of cross-cultural adaptation of self-report measures. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2000 Dec 15;25(24):3186-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11124735</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ferreira-Valente MA, Pais-Ribeiro JL, Jensen MP. Validity of four pain intensity rating scales. Pain. 2011 Oct;152(10):2399-404. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2011.07.005.</citation>
    <PMID>21856077</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Terwee CB, Bot SD, de Boer MR, van der Windt DA, Knol DL, Dekker J, Bouter LM, de Vet HC. Quality criteria were proposed for measurement properties of health status questionnaires. J Clin Epidemiol. 2007 Jan;60(1):34-42. Epub 2006 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>17161752</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marianne Mørk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physical Therapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Foot Functional Index revised,</keyword>
  <keyword>Translation and cultural adaption</keyword>
  <keyword>Reliability</keyword>
  <keyword>Validity</keyword>
  <keyword>Responsiveness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fasciitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fasciitis, Plantar</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

