<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04205383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Nimao/2018-03/SB-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04205383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GROSS-HIST : Quantification of the Main Circulating Histones During Normal Pregnancy and Pregnancies With Placenta-mediated Complications</brief_title>
  <acronym>GROSS-HIST</acronym>
  <official_title>Quantification of the Main Circulating Histones During Normal Pregnancy and Pregnancies With Placenta-mediated Complications</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nīmes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nīmes</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pregnancy generates an increased thrombotic risk, and placental-mediated diseases are a risk
      factor for cardiovascular diseases, in particular: pre-eclampsia (PE), intrauterine growth
      retardation (IUGR), retroplacental hematomas (HRP), late intrauterine fetal deaths (LIFD) of
      placental origin and preterm deliveries of vascular origin. They are responsible for
      significant maternal-fetal morbidity/mortality. Data published in 2007 by the Haute Autorité
      de Santé (HAS) show that hypertension and pre-eclampsia are, in France, at the origin of 3 to
      8% of the risk of perinatal mortality.

      During pregnancy, a transitional organ of foetal origin, the placenta, is established, which
      is essential for the maintenance and harmonious development of the pregnancy. The chorionic
      villus, in contact with maternal blood in the intervilleous chamber, is the structural and
      functional unit of the placenta. After the initial implantation phase, the trophoblastic cell
      constituting the main part of the placental villi differs in two ways: (A) into &quot;citrus
      cytotrophoblasts&quot; whose cells will fuse to generate the multinucleated outer layer giving the
      syncytiotrophoblast that ensures fetal-maternal exchanges and endocrine functions of the
      placenta; (B) into &quot;invasive extra-city cytotrophoblasts&quot; essential for the effective
      anchoring of the placenta in the decidualized uterine mucosa and for the remodelling of the
      terminal uterine spiral arteries, whose resistance to blood flow must collapse to allow
      effective oxygenation of the villi. Extra-city trophoblasts change from an epithelial
      phenotype to an endothelial phenotype. They may thus be exposed to pro-thrombotic factors
      such as endothelial cells. A lack of trophoblastic invasion and incomplete remodelling of the
      spiral uterine arteries are responsible for placental hypo-perfusion, hypoxia and the
      occurrence of placenta-mediated pathologies (pre-eclampsia, intrauterine growth retardation,
      retroplacental hematoma, fetal loss and fetal death in utero). The most common
      placental-mediated disease is pre-eclampsia (5% of births). It corresponds to a complication
      occurring from the second trimester of pregnancy and which is clinically characterized by
      high blood pressure, oedema and proteinuria. It is responsible for premature deliveries and
      is a major cause of intrauterine growth restriction.

      To date, there is no specific and early biomarker for the occurrence of placental vascular
      pathologies. Recent developments raise, for example, the question of circulating angiogenesis
      inhibitory factors (sFlt1, sEng) in pre-eclampsia. With regard to treatment, early
      administration of low-dose aspirin before 16 weeks of pregnancy seems to reduce the risk of
      pre-eclampsia, hence the importance of having very early markers of the disease. Discovering
      such markers is therefore one of the major challenges in strengthening women's follow-up and
      avoiding subsequent complications. For fetal losses and retroplacental hematoma, the
      administration of low molecular weight heparin has been shown to be effective. However, these
      treatments are not specific to placental vascular pathologies. Thus, understanding and
      exploring the cellular and molecular mechanisms of vascular-placental interface dysfunctions
      remains necessary to enable targeted management of patients feeding the general principle of
      precision medicine.

      Compare the concentrations of (i) circulating histones involved in inflammation,
      proliferation, migration or cell differentiation (H3-citrullinated histone, acetylated
      histones (Pan-histones), H1 histone) and (ii) free HMGB1 protein between the three patient
      groups (&quot;GrossN&quot;, &quot;GrossC&quot;, &quot;VolS&quot;).

      The histones H3-citrullinated, acetylated histones (Pan-histones), H1 histone as well as the
      free HMGB1 protein will be quantified. This choice corresponds to the histones involved in
      inflammation, proliferation, migration or cell differentiation and can be quantified to date.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 5, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating levels : Protein HMGB1 ng/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>until the patient gives birth, up to 7 months on average</time_frame>
    <description>Protein HMGB1 ng/ml</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating levels : Citrullined Histone H3 U/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>until the patient gives birth, up to 7 months on average</time_frame>
    <description>Citrullined Histone H3 U/ml</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating levels : Histone H1 U/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>until the patient gives birth, up to 7 months on average</time_frame>
    <description>Histone H1 U/ml</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating levels : Acetylated Histones U/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>until the patient gives birth, up to 7 months on average</time_frame>
    <description>Acetylated Histones U/ml</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating levels : Histone H3 U/ml</measure>
    <time_frame>until the patient gives birth, up to 7 months on average</time_frame>
    <description>Histone H3 U/ml</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">115</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy Complications</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pregnancy</arm_group_label>
    <description>pregnant women with normal pregnancy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pregnancy with complications</arm_group_label>
    <description>pregnant women with placental-mediated complications of pregnancy type complications</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy volunteer</arm_group_label>
    <description>healthy, non-pregnant women volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>biological analyses</intervention_name>
    <description>The histones H3-citrullinated, acetylated histones (Pan-histones), H1 histone as well as the free HMGB1 protein will be quantified. This choice corresponds to the histones involved in inflammation, proliferation, migration or cell differentiation and can be quantified to date.</description>
    <arm_group_label>healthy volunteer</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>pregnancy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>pregnancy with complications</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        pregnant patient with a complication of the placental vascular pathology type
        (pre-eclampsia, eclampsia, HELLP syndrome, retroplacental hematoma, fetal death in utero)
        or venous thromboembolic disease (deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism).

        AND pregnant woman, without complications (normal pregnancy), absence of identified chronic
        pathology, absence of a history of neoplastic pathology, absence of a history of
        thromboembolic disease, absence of a history of chronic infectious pathology, absence of
        acute pathology (benign infectious type) intercurrent within the previous 2 weeks.

        AND

        - female, healthy volunteer, non-pregnant, no identified chronic pathology, no history of
        neoplastic pathology, no history of thromboembolic disease, no history of chronic
        infectious pathology, no history of acute (benign infectious type) intercurrent pathology
        within the previous 2 weeks.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  General inclusion criteria :

          -  The patient must have given her free and informed consent and signed the consent

          -  The patient must be a member or beneficiary of a health insurance plan

          -  Only women are included

          -  The patient is at least 18 years old

          -  Inclusion criteria for the target population:

          -  pregnant patient with a complication of the placental vascular pathology type
             (pre-eclampsia, eclampsia, HELLP syndrome, retroplacental hematoma, fetal death in
             utero) or venous thromboembolic disease (deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism).

        OR pregnant woman, without complications (normal pregnancy), absence of identified chronic
        pathology, absence of a history of neoplastic pathology, absence of a history of
        thromboembolic disease, absence of a history of chronic infectious pathology, absence of
        acute pathology (benign infectious type) intercurrent within the previous 2 weeks.

        OR

        - female, healthy volunteer, non-pregnant, no identified chronic pathology, no history of
        neoplastic pathology, no history of thromboembolic disease, no history of chronic
        infectious pathology, no history of acute (benign infectious type) intercurrent pathology
        within the previous 2 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  General non-inclusion criteria :

          -  The patient is participating in another study

          -  The patient is in an exclusion period determined by a previous study

          -  The patient is under the protection of justice, under guardianship or curatorship

          -  Patient refuses to sign consent

          -  It is impossible to give informed information about

          -  The patient does not read French fluently

        Criteria for non-inclusion regarding interfering diseases or associated conditions:

          -  The patient is undergoing hormonal ovarian stimulation treatment as part of medically
             assisted reproduction

          -  The patient is pregnant OR

          -  The patient is breastfeeding OR

          -  The patient has been giving birth for less than 3 months .
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUNimes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nîmes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 19, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 19, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pregnancy Complications</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

