<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04200339</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTN0060-A1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UG1DA015831</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04200339</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adolescent SCreening To Help Eliminate Misuse</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASC-THEM</acronym>
  <official_title>Adolescent SCreening To Help Eliminate Misuse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Emmes Company, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Friends Research Institute, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to evaluate the performance of three substance use
      screening instruments (S2BI, BSTAD, and TAPS Tool) against a criterion standard of Diagnostic
      Statistical Manual - 5 (DSM-5) substance use disorder (SUD) diagnoses in an adolescent
      population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks to evaluate the psychometric properties of three substance use screening and
      brief assessment tools for adolescents against criterion standard of Diagnostic and
      Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5) substance use disorder
      diagnoses in a population of adolescents presenting for any type of visit (i.e. an annual
      health maintenance visit, follow-up, or sick visit) at one of four primary care sites; or,
      for an initial evaluation at a substance use disorders program for youth. The three tools to
      be tested are the Brief Screener for Tobacco, Alcohol and Drugs (BSTAD); Screening to Brief
      Intervention (S2BI) screening tool; and the Tobacco, Alcohol, Prescription medications, and
      other Substance (TAPS) Tool. BSTAD and S2BI were developed specifically for use with
      adolescents and each has been validated in a single trial. These tools use past-year
      &quot;frequency of use&quot; questions to determine risk level for a substance use disorder. The TAPS
      tool includes both screening and brief assessments and while it has been studied more
      extensively in adult primary care patients, its validity with adolescents is not known. For
      youth, alcohol, marijuana and tobacco use, and particularly early initiation, are associated
      with greater risk of substance use disorders, use of illicit drugs, misuse of opioids, and
      opioid use disorders. Thus, identifying and addressing substance use early is an important
      form of prevention that can be delivered in medical care settings for this age group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SUD assessment evaluation for performance</measure>
    <time_frame>single visit</time_frame>
    <description>The focus of this study is to evaluate the performance of each tool (S2BI, BSTAD, and TAPS Tool) in identifying substance use and substance use disorders at previously identified cut points for alcohol, marijuana and tobacco/nicotine for each tool. The properties that will be evaluated include sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV), negative predictive value (NPV), positive likelihood ratio (LR+) and negative likelihood ratio (LR-)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SUD assessment evaluation for criterion measures</measure>
    <time_frame>single visit</time_frame>
    <description>We will examine each substance from each tool against the corresponding substance on the criterion standard measure. For example, the tobacco item on the BSTAD would be compared to the tobacco item on the WMH CIDI.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1125</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adolescents</arm_group_label>
    <description>Adolescents between the ages of 12 and 17 years old (inclusive).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Recruitment and study procedures may occur either in-person or remotely. We will recruit
        participants to enroll in the study from approximately five health care sites. These will
        include 1) an outpatient adolescent substance use disorders program at a pediatric hospital
        (ASAP, Boston Children's Hospital), 2) the adolescent medicine program at a federally
        qualified health center (FQHC) in Boston (Martha Elliot Health Center (MEHC), Boston
        Children's Hospital), and 3) three community-based primary care pediatrics practices that
        participate in the Pediatric Physicians' Organization at Children's (PPOC). The FQHC is
        considered one of the four primary care sites participating in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Be between the ages of 12-17 years, inclusive, at the time of screening.

          2. Presenting for any type of appointment at one of four primary care sites; or,
             presenting for an initial substance use disorders evaluation at the youth substance
             use disorders program site.

          3. Be willing and able to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previously enrolled in the current study, as determined by the Chart Review
             Log/Clinical Staff Referral Log and through self-report of potentially eligible
             participants.

          2. Inability to comprehend spoken or written English.

          3. Inability to self-administer any type of computer tool due to physical limitations.

          4. Physical or emotional illness that interferes with participation on the day of the
             appointment, as determined by either the clinical team or research team.

          5. Per participant self-report, treated in a residential/inpatient substance use
             disorders treatment program within the past 12 months.

          6. For patients at primary care sites, current, self-reported enrollment in a substance
             use disorders treatment program at time of recruitment.

          7. Per participant self-report, participant is currently in the custody of the Department
             of Youth Services, the Department of Children and Families, or living with a foster
             family.

          8. Per participant self-report, currently pregnant or parenting.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sharon Levy, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>617-355-2727</phone>
    <email>sharon.levy@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julie Lundstead, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>857-218-4317</phone>
    <email>Julie.Lundstead@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Childrens Hopsital - Adolecents Substance Use and Addiction Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alyssa Fuller, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-919-6777</phone>
      <email>Alyssa.Fuller@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sharon Levy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Adolescent Substance Use and Addiction Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolecents</keyword>
  <keyword>SBIRT</keyword>
  <keyword>Substance Use</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This study will comply with the NIH Data Sharing Policy and Implementation Guidance(https://grants.nih.gov/grants/policy/data_sharing/data_sharing_guidance.htm). Investigators will also register and report results of the trial in ClinicalTrials.gov, consistent with the requirements of the Policy on the Dissemination of NIH-Funded Clinical Trial Information and the Clinical Trials Registration (https://grants.nih.gov/policy/clinical-trials/reporting/understanding/nih-policy.htm).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>upon completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Public:
Prior to downloading any study data, the user will be prompted to complete a registration agreement for data use. Users will have to register a name and valid e-mail address in order to download data and to accept their responsibility for using data in accordance with the NIDA Data Share Agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://datashare.nida.nih.gov/</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

