<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04206488</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108712</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>70033093THR1001</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-003783-46</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04206488</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of JNJ-70033093 and Digoxin in Healthy Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-center, Open-label, Fixed-sequence, Study Evaluating the Two-way Drug-drug Interaction Between JNJ-70033093 and Digoxin in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the potential pharmacokinetic (PK) interaction
      between JNJ-70033093 and digoxin in healthy participants after single dose administration and
      at steady state.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    on hold due to precautionary measure taken due to the recent development in Europe with regards
    to the COVID-19 pandemic
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 9, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 28, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax) Geometric Mean Ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin) Relative to Treatment A (JNJ-70033093)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 21</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax is the maximum observed plasma concentration. Cmax geometric mean ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + digoxin) relative to Treatment A (JNJ-70033093) will be reported to assess the effect of digoxin on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of JNJ-70033093.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax Geometric Mean Ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin) Relative to Treatment B (Digoxin)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 21</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax is the maximum observed plasma concentration. Cmax geometric mean ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin) relative to Treatment B (digoxin) will be reported to assess the effect of JNJ-70033093 on the PK of digoxin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve from Time 0 to 24 Hours Postdose (AUC [0-24 hours]) Geometric Mean Ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin) Relative to Treatment A (JNJ-70033093)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>AUC (0-24) is the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to 24 hours postdose. AUC (0-24) geometric mean ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + digoxin) relative to Treatment A (JNJ-70033093) will be reported to assess the effect of digoxin on the PK of JNJ-70033093.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC (0-24) Geometric Mean Ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin) Relative to Treatment B (Digoxin)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>AUC (0-24) is the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to 24 hours postdose. AUC (0-24) geometric mean ratio of Treatment C (JNJ-70033093 + digoxin) relative to Treatment B (digoxin) will be reported to assess the effect of JNJ-70033093 on the PK of digoxin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs) as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 63 Days</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical study participant administered a medicinal (investigational or non-investigational) product does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the treatment. Therefore, it can be any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not related to that medicinal product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Vital Sign Abnormalities as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 63 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with vital sign (tympanic temperature, resting [supine] pulse rate, and blood pressure) abnormalities will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with 12-lead Electrocardiogram (ECG) Abnormalities as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 63 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with 12-lead ECG abnormalities will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Laboratory Abnormalities as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 63 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with laboratory abnormalities (hematology, coagulation tests, clinical chemistry, and urinalysis) will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change From Baseline in Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 21</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change from baseline in aPTT will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive JNJ-70033093 as oral capsules (Treatment A) in Period 1, followed by digoxin tablets as loading dose and maintenance doses (Treatment B) in Period 2, and then digoxin tablets along with JNJ-70033093 (Treatment C) in Period 3. There will be a washout period of minimum 5 days (and maximum 7 days) between the last dosing day of Period 1 and the first dosing day of Period 2. There is no washout between Periods 2 and 3 (that is, the last day of Treatment B is to be followed by the first day of Treatment C).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-70033093</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive JNJ-70033093 orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-986177</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Digoxin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive digoxin orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>JNJ-70033093 + Digoxin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lanoxin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy on the basis of physical examination, medical history, vital signs,
             Electrocardiogram (ECG), and laboratory test results, including serum chemistry, blood
             coagulation, hematology, and urinalysis performed at screening. If there are
             abnormalities, the investigator may decide that the abnormalities or deviations from
             normal are not clinically significant, in which case the participant may be included.
             This determination must be recorded in the participant's source documents and
             initialed by the investigator

          -  Normal renal function at screening as evidenced by an estimated glomerular filtration
             rate (eGFR) of greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 90 milliliter per minute (mL/min) per
             1.73 meter square (m^2) calculated with the Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology
             Collaboration (CKD-EPI) formula

          -  A woman of childbearing potential must have a negative serum beta human chorionic
             gonadotropin (beta-hCG) test at screening and a negative urine (beta-hCG) test on Day
             -1 of Period 1

          -  Contraceptive use by men or women should be consistent with local regulations
             regarding the use of contraceptive methods for participants participating in clinical
             studies. Before screening, a woman must either be: a) Not of childbearing potential b)
             Of childbearing potential c) Women must have no history of excessive menstrual
             bleeding or hemorrhage following pregnancy delivery

          -  Body mass index (BMI; weight [kilogram {kg}] per height square (height^2 [meter^2])
             between 18.0 and 30.0 kilogram per meter square (kg/m^2) (inclusive), and body weight
             not less than 55 kg

          -  A 12-lead ECG consistent with normal cardiac conduction and function at screening and
             on Day 1 of Period 1, including: a) Sinus rhythm, b) Heart rate between 55 and 90
             beats per minute (bpm), c) Corrected QT (QTc) interval of less than or equal to (&lt;=)
             450 milliseconds (ms) for male participants and &lt;= 470 ms for female participants (QT
             interval will be corrected for heart rate using the Fridericia correction, d) QRS
             interval of less than (&lt;) 110 ms, e) PR interval &lt;200 ms, f) Morphology consistent
             with healthy cardiac conduction and function

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is a woman who is pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant
             during this study or within 34 days after the last study drug administration

          -  History of or current clinically significant medical illness including (but not
             limited to) cardiac arrhythmias or other cardiac disease, hematologic disease,
             coagulation disorders (including any abnormal bleeding or blood dyscrasias), lipid
             abnormalities, significant pulmonary disease, including bronchospastic respiratory
             disease, gastrointestinal disease, diabetes mellitus, renal or hepatic insufficiency,
             thyroid disease, neurologic or psychiatric disease, infection, or any other illness
             that the investigator considers should exclude the participant or that could interfere
             with the interpretation of the study results

          -  History of clinically significant ECG abnormalities, sinus node disease, or incomplete
             atrioventricular (AV) block or a family history of prolonged QT interval syndrome

          -  Positive blood screen for hepatitis C virus antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen
             (HBsAg), or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) type 1 and type 2 antibody

          -  Use of any prescription or nonprescription medication (including vitamins and herbal
             supplements), except for oral contraceptives, hormonal replacement therapy (HRT), and
             paracetamol, within 14 days before the first dose of the study drug is scheduled

          -  Received an experimental drug/placebo or used an experimental medical device within 3
             months or within a period less than 5 times the drug's half-life (whichever is longer)
             prior to the planned first dose of study drugs or is enrolled in an investigational
             study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Pharmacology Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Merksem</city>
        <zip>2170</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Digoxin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data sharing policy of the Janssen Pharmaceutical Companies of Johnson &amp; Johnson is available at www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency. As noted on this site, requests for access to the study data can be submitted through Yale Open Data Access (YODA) Project site at yoda.yale.edu</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>https://www.janssen.com/clinical-trials/transparency</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

