<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04209179</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PCO104UG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04209179</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Study Investigating the Safety, Tolerability, PK and PD of PCO371 in Patients With Hypoparathyroidism</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Multiple Ascending Oral Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of PCO371 in Patients With Hypoparathyroidism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chugai Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chugai Pharmaceutical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, placebo-controlled, randomized, double-blind, multiple-ascending dose
      study in patients with hypoparathyroidism.

      The total duration of study medication treatment will be 13 weeks and includes a Fixed-Dose
      Treatment period and a Dose Titration Treatment period. The Fixed-Dose Treatment period
      consists of multiple daily dosing at a fixed dose level. Once patients have completed the
      Fixed-Dose Treatment period, patients will enter the Dose Titration Treatment period where
      PCO371 (or placebo), oral calcium and oral active vitamin D can each be titrated according to
      the patient's albumin-corrected serum calcium level.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs) will be assessed including the number and rate of TEAEs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Selected adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Hypercalcemia and hypocalcemia will be assessed including the number and rate of these.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant change in the safety parameters; vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormal change in vital signs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant change in the safety parameters; body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormal change in body weight.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant change in the safety parameters; physical examination findings</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormal change in physical examination findings.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant change in the safety parameters; laboratory test value</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormal change in laboratory test value including hematology, biochemistry, coagulation, urinalysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant change in the safety parameters; electrocardiogram results</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormal change in electrocardiogram results including PQ (PR), RR, QRS, QT, pulse, QTcB, QTcF and ECG abnormalities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic data of PCO371; Plasma concentrations of PCO371</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma concentrations versus time data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic data of PCO371; AUC0-last</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>AUC0-last of PCO371</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic data of PCO371; Cmax of PCO371</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax of PCO371</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic data of PCO371; Tmax of PCO371</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax of PCO371</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic data of PCO371; T1/2 of PCO371</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>T1/2 of PCO371</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic data in serum or plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time profile of serum/plasma concentrations in albumin corrected total calcium (Ca), 25 hydroxy vitamin D, 1,25-dihydroxy vitamin D, phosphate, magnesium, and cAMP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic data in urine</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary excretion of Ca, phosphate, magnesium, protein, sodium, potassium, chloride, and cAMP (via 24-hour urine collection)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic data; nephrogenous cAMP concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time profile of nephrogenous cAMP concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic data; bone turnover markers in serum or plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time profile of serum/plasma concentrations in bone turnover markers (i.e. bone-specific alkaline phosphatase, type 1 pro-collagen amino-terminal peptide, C-terminal telopeptide of type 1 collagen, and osteocalcin)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoparathyroidism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PCO371 Low Dose and Low administration frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PCO371 low dose and low administration frequency by oral administration for the first period ( Fixed-Dose treatment period). PCO371 will be titrated in the following period (Dose Titration Treatment period).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PCO371 High Dose and Low administration frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PCO371 high dose and low administration frequency by oral administration for the first period ( Fixed-Dose treatment period). PCO371 will be titrated in the following period (Dose Titration Treatment period).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PCO371 High Dose and High administration frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PCO371 high dose and high administration frequency by oral administration for the first period ( Fixed-Dose treatment period). PCO371 will be titrated in the following period (Dose Titration Treatment period).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo by oral administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PCO371</intervention_name>
    <description>PCO371 capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>PCO371 High Dose and High administration frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PCO371 High Dose and Low administration frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PCO371 Low Dose and Low administration frequency</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able and willing to provide written informed consent, to use the device for PRO and
             electronic diary and to comply with the requirements of the protocol.

          2. Adult males or females ≥18 years of age

          3. History of hypoparathyroidism for more than 1-year post initial diagnosis

          4. PTH level is inappropriately low

          5. Dose of thyroid replacement therapy must have been stable for ≥3 months prior to first
             dose if receiving thyroid replacement therapy

          6. Receiving treatment with active vitamin D therapy (calcitriol ≥0.25 μg/day or
             alfacalcidol ≥0.5 μg/day)

          7. Receiving Oral calcium treatment (≥1000 mg/day)

          8. No significant changes in the diet from 4 weeks prior to Screening and for the
             duration of the study.

          9. Fasting albumin-corrected serum calcium concentration between 8.0 and 9.0 mg/dL at 2
             consecutive visits during the Run-In period, and no more than 25% change in daily
             doses of oral Ca and active vitamin D between the 2 consecutive visits during the
             Run-In period.

         10. On Day 1, fasting albumin-corrected serum calcium level between 7.5 and 9.0 mg/dL

         11. Serum magnesium level ≥ lower limit of normal and ≤ 1.2 x laboratory upper limit of
             normal

         12. Serum 25[OH] vitamin D level within the laboratory normal range

         13. Estimated glomerular filtration rate ≥ 45 mL/min/1.73 m2

         14. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative highly sensitive urine or serum
             pregnancy test result

         15. For women of childbearing potential: agreement to use a highly effective contraceptive
             method during the treatment period and for 28 days after the last dose of study drug.
             Hormonal contraceptive methods must be supplemented by a barrier method (preferably
             male condom) and agreement to refrain from egg donation during the treatment period
             and for 28 days after the last dose of study drug.

         16. For men: agreement to remain abstinent or use contraceptive measures. Men must refrain
             from donating sperm during this same period.

         17. Ability to comply with the study protocol, in the investigator's judgment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or breastfeeding or intending to become pregnant during the study or within
             28 days after the last dose of PCO371

          2. Known or suspected history of hypoparathyroidism resulting from an activating mutation
             in the Ca-sensing receptor gene or impaired responsiveness to PTH
             (pseudohypoparathyroidism)

          3. Clinically significant hypomagnesemia. Adequately treated hypomagnesemia is permitted

          4. Any disease that might affect calcium metabolism or calcium-phosphate homeostasis
             other than hypoparathyroidism

          5. History of a major bone fracture within 3 months prior to Screening

          6. Any history of clinically significant bleeding disorder or clinically significant
             abnormal clotting times

          7. History of thyroid cancer unless documented to be disease free for ≥1 year

          8. History of any other cancer in the past 3 years from Screening with the exception of
             thyroid cancer , completely removed nonmelanoma skin cancer, basal cell skin
             carcinoma, and cancer in situ of the cervix

          9. Dependence on monthly or more frequent parenteral calcium infusions to maintain
             calcium homeostasis

         10. Disease processes that may adversely affect gastrointestinal absorption

         11. Use of oral bisphosphonates within 6 months of Screening and/or intravenous
             bisphosphonate preparations within 12 months of Screening. Any use of zoledronic acid
             prior to Screening.

         12. Use of other drugs known to influence calcium and bone metabolism such as calcitonin,
             fluoride tablets or cinacalcet hydrochloride within 4 weeks prior to Screening.

         13. Patients who have taken inducers of CYP3A4, Pgp,or BCRP within 1 month before IMP
             administration or taken inhibitors of CYP3A4, P-gp, or BCRP within 2 weeks before IMP
             administration (or either 6 times the t1/2 of the drugs mentioned above, whichever is
             longer).

         14. Use of loop or thiazide diuretics within 14 days prior to first dose of IMP

         15. Use of anti-coagulants, anti-platelet medications, and aspirin within 2 weeks (or
             within 6 times the t1/2 of the drug mentioned above, whichever is longer) prior to IMP
             administration

         16. History of radiotherapy to the skeleton within 5 years

         17. Presence of open epiphyses at the distal radius and ulna as well as carpals,
             metacarpals, phalanges, and pelvis

         18. ALT, AST, or ALP &gt; 2.5 × ULN at Screening

         19. Patients with documented active HBV, active HCV infection or any other known active
             virus infection considered to be clinically relevant by the investigator.

         20. Evidence of active alcohol, drug, or other substance abuse or addiction

         21. History of a seizure that is unrelated to hypocalcemia within 6 months prior to
             Screening

         22. Insulin dependent diabetes mellitus or poorly controlled Type II diabetes mellitus
             (defined as hemoglobin A1c [HbA1c] &gt;8%)

         23. Chronic/severe cardiac disease

         24. Active gout or history of active gout within 6 months prior to first dose of study
             medication

         25. History of clinically significant cognitive deficit that would, at the discretion of
             the investigator, interfere with a patient's ability to participate in the trial.

         26. Any disease or condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, has a high
             probability of precluding the patient from completing the study or where the patient
             could not or would not appropriately comply with study requirements

         27. Participation in any clinical trials or has taken any IMP (including placebo) either
             within 2 months or 5 times the t1/2 of the IMP, whichever is longer, prior to first
             dose of IMP for this study

         28. Previous treatment with PTH-like drugs, including PTH(1-84), PTH(1-34) or other
             N-terminal fragments or analogs of PTH or PTH-related proteins within 2 months or 5
             times the t1/2 of the treatment (whichever is longer) prior to Screening.

         29. Patients with hypersensitivity to PCO371 or to any component of this drug product
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sponsor Chugai Pharmaceutical Co. Ltd</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>clinical-trials@chugai-pharm.co.jp</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Clinical trials information</last_name>
    <phone>only use Email</phone>
    <email>clinical-trials@chugai-pharm.co.jp</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amber Anaya</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>(614) 688-6257</phone>
      <email>amber.anaya@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypoparathyroidism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Qualified researchers may request access to individual patient level data through the clinical study data request platform (www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com). For further details on Chugai's Data Sharing Policy and how to request access to related clinical study documents, see here (www.chugai-pharm.co.jp/english/profile/rd/ctds_request.html).</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

