<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04207177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MicrobioTac-MPA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04207177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunosuppressive Drugs and Gut Microbiome: Pharmacokinetic- and Microbiome Diversity Effects</brief_title>
  <acronym>MicrobioTac</acronym>
  <official_title>Immunosuppressive Drugs and Gut Microbiome: Pharmacokinetic- and Microbiome Diversity Effects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oslo University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Kidney transplant recipients of living- and deceased donor grafts and treated with both
      mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) and tacrolimus (Tac) will be included. A 12-hour pharmacokinetic
      (PK) investigation of both mycophenolate (MPA) and Tac will be performed in pharmacokinetic
      steady state conditions between 3 to 8 weeks and one year after transplantation. Feces
      samples will be collected before (if possible), 1 week after transplantation and at the day
      of the 12-hour PK investigations. Data on dietary intake and physical activity will be
      obtained in association with the feces sampling in all patients. Patients will be invited to
      a follow-up visit one year after transplantation where the 12-hour PK investigation, feces
      sampling, dietary and activity data collection is repeated. Standard follow-up data after
      renal transplantations, such as acute rejection episodes, infections, renal function, post
      transplant diabetes mellitus (PTDM), protocol biopsies, adherence to immunosuppressive drugs,
      graft loss and death will be collected for all patients up to 5 years after transplantation
      according to standard schedule at the transplant center.

      A subgroup of kidney transplant recipients scheduled for living donor transplantation will be
      included before transplantation for pre-transplant investigations in addition to the
      investigations after transplantation. These patients will be randomized to either receive one
      week of treatment with MMF or Tac before transplantation. Feces samples and a 12-hour PK
      investigation will be performed after one week of treatment (before transplantation).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The analyses of feces samples will be performed by utilizing shotgun, next generation
      sequencing in order to determine the bacterial, fungal sand viral microbiome. Drug
      concentrations will be analyzed with high performance Liquid chromatography With double mass
      spectrometry detector (HPLC-MS/MS) technology and both free and total plasma MPA
      concentrations, total mycophenolate glucoronide (MPAG) concentrations and total whole blood
      Tac and methylated Tac-metabolite concentrations will be determined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The main study is based on treatment allocation outside of thsi protocol but a subgroup of living donor recipients will be randomized to wither one week tacrolimus or mycophenolate mofetil treatment before transplantation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>investigate the association between microbiome diversity and 12-hour mycophenolate area under the curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Association between microbiome diversity measures and AUC of mycophenolate for a dose interval (AUC0-tau)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>investigate the association between microbiome diversity and 12-hour mycophenolate Maximum concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Association between microbiome diversity measures and Cmax of mycophenolate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>association between microbiome diversity and 12-hour tacrolimus AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Association between microbiome diversity measures and AUC0-tau of tacrolimus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of mycophenolate mofetil treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated mycophenolate AUC changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and mycophenolate AUC0-tau, with one week of mycophenolate mofetil treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>investigate the effects of tacrolimus treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated tacrolimus AUC changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and tacrolimus AUC0-tau with one week of tacrolimus treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>investigate if Torque Teno Virus (TTV) is a clinical useful &quot;immunometer&quot;, i.e. reflect overall immunosuppression of the recipient</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Associations between TTV viral load (DNAemia) and acute rejection episodes (biopsy proven)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between microbiome diversity measures and Cmax of tacrolimus</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Association between microbiome diversity measures and Cmax of tacrolimus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between microbiome diversity measures and absolute bioavailability (F) of tacrolimus</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Association between microbiome diversity measures and F of tacrolimus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of mycophenolate mofetil treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated mycophenolate Cmax changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and mycophenolate Cmax with one week of mycophenolate mofetil treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of mycophenolate mofetil treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated mycophenolate time to Cmax (Tmax) changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and mycophenolate Tmax with one week of mycophenolate mofetil treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of mycophenolate mofetil treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated mycophenolate time to terminal phase elimination rate constant (kel)changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and mycophenolate kel with one week of mycophenolate mofetil treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of tacrolimus treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated tacrolimus time to Cmax (Tmax) changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and tacrolimus Cmax with one week of tacrolimus treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of tacrolimus treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated tacrolimus time to Cmax (Tmax) changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and tacrolimus Tmax with one week of tacrolimus treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effects of tacrolimus treatment on gut microbiome changes in treatment naïve patients and associated tacrolimus time to terminal phase elimination rate constant (kel) changes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in microbiome diversity measures and tacrolimus kel with one week of tacrolimus treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>investigate if Torque Teno Virus (TTV) is a clinical useful &quot;immunometer&quot;, i.e. reflect overall immunosuppression of the recipient</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Associations between TTV viral load (DNAemia) and opportunistic vial infections in need of drug treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>investigate if Torque Teno Virus (TTV) is a clinical useful &quot;immunometer&quot;, i.e. reflect overall immunosuppression of the recipient</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Associations between TTV viral load (DNAemia) and opportunistic bacterial infections requiring hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>integrate the updated knowledge on mycophenolate and tacrolimus pharmacokinetics following renal transplantation in a combined population pharmacokinetic model for individualized dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Relative predictive error (PE%) of the developed pharmacokinetic model</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>integrate the updated knowledge on mycophenolate and tacrolimus pharmacokinetics following renal transplantation in a combined population pharmacokinetic model for individualized dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Relative root mean squared error (RMSE%) of the developed pharmacokinetic model</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant; Complications</condition>
  <condition>Immune Suppression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate mofetil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the subgroup of living donor recipients included before transplantation this group will be treated with mycophenolate mofetil (750 mg BID) for one week</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tacrolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the subgroup of living donor recipients included before transplantation this group will be treated with tacrolimus (BID, dose by weight) for one week</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate Mofetil 500 mg Tab</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily dosing of MMF only for a week before transplantation in this subgroup. All patients will get maintenance treatment With MMF in combination With tacrolimus and steroids after transplantation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate mofetil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MMF-arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily dosing of tacrolimus only for a week before transplantation in this subgroup. All patients will get maintenance treatment With tacrolimus in combination With MMF and steroids after transplantation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tacrolimus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tac-arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  De novo standard risk kidney transplant recipients.

          -  Patients scheduled to receive tacrolimus and mycophenolate mofetil as part of their
             immunosuppressive therapy following transplantation (clinical decision not influenced
             by this study).

          -  First kidney transplant only.

          -  Adult patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Pregnant or lactating female patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karsten Midtvedt, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karsten Midtvedt, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004723070000</phone>
    <phone_ext>1894</phone_ext>
    <email>kmidtved@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anders Åsberg, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>004723070000</phone>
    <phone_ext>1937</phone_ext>
    <email>aaasbe@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0424</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karsten Midtvedt, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>004723070000</phone>
      <phone_ext>1894</phone_ext>
      <email>knidtved@ous-hf.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anders Åsberg, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>004723070000</phone>
      <phone_ext>1937</phone_ext>
      <email>aaasbe@ous-hf.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anders Åsberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Not allowed by Norwegian Law to share data without specific contract. Upon contact With the responsible investigator it is however possible to share data under a specified contract</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

