<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04201743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>199608</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04201743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Amniotic Membrane Injection Comparing Two Doses (1 mL and 2mL Injection) in the Treatment of Osteoarthritis of the Knee</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Double-Blinded, Randomized Controlled Trial of an Amniotic Membrane Injection Comparing Two Doses (1 mL and 2mL Injection) in the Treatment of Osteoarthritis of the Knee</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Illinois Center for Orthopaedic Research and Education</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Illinois Center for Orthopaedic Research and Education</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the dose effect of a single injectable acellular
      amniotic membrane derived allograft injection for the treatment of knee osteoarthritis and to
      confirm whether the use of 2 mL of the same amniotic injection offers a statistically
      significant advantage over the 1 mL injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is a prospective, double blinded, Randomized Controlled Trial study. Data will be
      prospectively collected of all injectable acellular amniotic membrane derived allograft knee
      performed at our institute (1 vs 2 mL).

      60 subjects will be enrolled in this study. Subjects will be randomized 1:1 in treatment
      arms.

      Each of the patient will be treated with one time injection to the knee. Methods for
      collecting data will be through validated patient-reported outcome tools (KOOS, VAS and WOMAC
      questionnaire) that the patient will complete pre-injection and at specified time intervals
      after injection: 90 days, 180 days and 365 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Data will be prospectively collected on all injectable acellular amniotic membrane derived allograft knee performed at our institute.
Inclusion criteria will be all patients age between 21 and 80 years with a diagnosis of osteoarthritis (OA) defined as Grade 1 to 3 on the Kellgren Lawrence grading scale.
Methods for collecting data will be through validated patient-reported outcome tools that the patient will complete pre-injection and at specified time intervals after injection: 90 days, 180 days and 365 days.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Efficacy Endpoints using Validated patient-reported outcome tools questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)- assess five outcomes: pain, symptoms, activities of daily living, sport and recreation function, and knee-related quality of life. It is a 0-100 scale, with zero representing extreme knee problems and 100 representing no knee problems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Efficacy Endpoints using Validated patient-reported outcome tools questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)- assess the condition of patients with osteoarthritis of the knee and hip, including pain, stiffness, and physical functioning of the joints. it is a 0 (worst)-96 scale (best).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Efficacy Endpoints using Validated patient-reported outcome tools questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)- assess pain, It is a 0-100 scale. A higher score indicates greater pain intensity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory Endpoint using Validated patient-reported outcome tools questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>90, 180 and 365 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)- assess five outcomes: pain, symptoms, activities of daily living, sport and recreation function, and knee-related quality of life. It is a 0-100 scale, with zero representing extreme knee problems and 100 representing no knee problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory Endpoint using Validated patient-reported outcome tools questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>90, 180 and 365 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)- assess the condition of patients with osteoarthritis of the knee and hip, including pain, stiffness, and physical functioning of the joints. it is a 0 (worst)-96 scale (best).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory Endpoint using Validated patient-reported outcome tools questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>90, 180 and 365 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)- assess pain, It is a 0-100 scale. A higher score indicates greater pain intensity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 mL NyDYN injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 patients (out of 60) will be doubled blinded randomized to this arm and get 1 mL NyDYN injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 mL NyDYN injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 patients (out of 60) will be doubled blinded randomized to this arm and get 2 mL NyDYN injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acellular amniotic membrane derived allograft injection (NuDYN)</intervention_name>
    <description>Injectable acellular amniotic membrane derived allograft (NuDYN) through routine follow-up with physical examination, pain, function and quality of life measurements and compare dose effects (1 mL versus 2 mL of NuDYN injection) in the treatment of knee osteoarthritis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1 mL NyDYN injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2 mL NyDYN injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age of 21 to 80 years

          -  Diagnosis of osteoarthritis (OA) defined as Grade 1 to 3 on the Kellgren Lawrence
             grading scale

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a diagnosis of osteoarthritis (OA) defined as Grade 4 on the Kellgren
             Lawrence grading scale

          -  BMI greater than 40 kg/m2

          -  Subject has active infection at the injection site

          -  Symptomatic OA of the contralateral knee or of either hip that is not responsive to
             acetaminophen (Tylenol) and requires other therapy.

          -  Subject has rheumatoid arthritis, psoriatic arthritis or has been diagnosed with any
             other disorder that is the primary source of their knee pain, including but not
             limited to: osteonecrosis, radiculopathy, bursitis, tendinitis, tumor or cancer

          -  Subject has documented history of gout or pseudo-gout

          -  Subject has an autoimmune disease or known history of having Acquired Immunodeficiency
             Syndromes (AIDS) or HIV

          -  Subject has received any of the following to the target knee:

               1. Intra-articular hyaluronic acid (HA) injection within 12 weeks prior to screening

               2. Intra-articular cortisone (steroid/corticosteroid) injection into the knee joint
                  within 12 weeks of treatment

               3. Steroid or platelet rich plasma (PRP) injection within 12 weeks prior to
                  screening

               4. Has had or is planning to have major surgery or arthroscopy in the target knee
                  within 26 weeks of treatment

          -  History of partial or total knee arthroplasty

          -  Subject has used an investigational drug, device or biologic within 12 weeks prior to
             treatment

          -  Subject has a history of immunosuppressive or chemotherapy in the last 5 years

          -  Subject has had prior radiation at the site

          -  Subject is currently taking narcotic medication for any reason.

          -  Subject is pregnant or plans to become pregnant within 365 days of treatment

          -  Subject has any significant medical condition that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would interfere with protocol evaluation and participation

          -  Subject is a worker's compensation patient

          -  Subject is a prisoner
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronak Patel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Illinois Center for Orthopedic Research and Education (iCORE)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ronak Patel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>630-728-8961</phone>
    <email>ronak.patel@hoasc.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hinsdale Orthopaedic Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westmont</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60559</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riboh JC, Saltzman BM, Yanke AB, Cole BJ. Human Amniotic Membrane-Derived Products in Sports Medicine: Basic Science, Early Results, and Potential Clinical Applications. Am J Sports Med. 2016 Sep;44(9):2425-34. doi: 10.1177/0363546515612750. Epub 2015 Nov 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26585668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vines JB, Aliprantis AO, Gomoll AH, Farr J. Cryopreserved Amniotic Suspension for the Treatment of Knee Osteoarthritis. J Knee Surg. 2016 Aug;29(6):443-50. doi: 10.1055/s-0035-1569481. Epub 2015 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26683979</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Illinois Center for Orthopaedic Research and Education</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ronak M. Patel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>President</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Knee</keyword>
  <keyword>Amniotic membrane</keyword>
  <keyword>Allograft</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

