<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04207866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>348-2019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04207866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Auditory Training Via Teleconference</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Teleconferencing in the Provision of Auditory Training Services</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multi-channel cochlear implants have been highly successful in restoring speech understanding
      to individuals with severe-to-profound hearing loss. Optimal programs facilitate access to
      sound but do not necessarily result in optimal performance. Practiced listening with auditory
      inputs is required to retrain the brain to hear using a cochlear implant. In some cases
      exposure to sound in everyday listening is sufficient; however, in others there is a need for
      the provision of auditory training (AT) by a trained professional. In these cases it is
      important to have regular visits with a specialist to: 1) facilitate auditory training
      exercises; 2) work with the family/friends to encourage optimal communication strategies in
      the home; 3) evaluate and assess achievement of listening goals.

      This study seeks to evaluate the feasibility of providing auditory training services remotely
      for patient populations located outside of Toronto. This study also seeks to evaluate
      interindividual perspectives regarding access and benefits of these services across remote
      and in person sessions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Individuals with severe-to-profound hearing impairment, who no longer benefit from hearing
      aids, are candidates for cochlear implantation. In many cases these devices provide access to
      sound and are successful in restoring speech understanding; however, there are instances
      where individuals might need additional assistance in the form of auditory training (AT).
      This study will involve comparison of two groups of individuals. Participants will be
      randomly assigned to the standard of care group OR the remote care group. Individuals who
      meet eligibility criteria will be contacted to assess their willingness to participate in
      additional auditory training (AT) sessions. These sessions will be conducted either
      face-to-face or via the Ontario Telehealth network as per random assignment. AT sessions will
      occur over the first 3 months following activation of the cochlear implant. Outcomes will be
      assessed using performance measures and questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study is a prospective observational study with sequential enrolment of 40 cochlear implant recipients. The subjects will be continuously included in the study, and will be included in the teleconferencing or on-site groups based on willingness to travel and distance from the hospital. Individuals will first be assessed by an Audiologist to determine listening goals and provide structure for auditory training sessions in house. Follow-up sessions will involve TC or FTF sessions whereby the patient will work with a CDA on skills targeted to help the patient achieve listening goals. A review session may also occur with the Audiologist following several TC or FTF sessions to assess progress and reassess current goals.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Teleconferencing for AT Services: In house questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>In house questionnaire assessing benefits of using remote network for provision of services. Questionnaires asks several questions related to quality of audio-visual signal, ease of use, duration of appointments and whether or not the participants outcomes were achieved. Responses are on a likert scale (Strongly agree (1), agree, neutral, disagree, strongly disagree (5)). Higher scores mean a poorer outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speech performance</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>A battery of tests is used within the standard of care provided to cochlear implant recipients. These tests are used as a gauge of performance with the device in the real world. The first test is the Arizona Biologic (AzBio) test which is assessed in quiet and at +5 dB SNR. It is scores in percentage of words correct. Higher scores are correlated with better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speech performance</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>A battery of tests is used within the standard of care provided to cochlear implant recipients. These tests are used as a gauge of performance with the device in the real world. The second test is the Hearing in Noise (HINT) test which is assessed in quiet and at +5 dB SNR. It is scores in percentage of words correct. Higher scores are correlated with better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speech performance</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>A battery of tests is used within the standard of care provided to cochlear implant recipients. These tests are used as a gauge of performance with the device in the real world. The third test is the Consonant-Nucleus-Consonant (CNC) word test which is assessed in quiet and at +5 dB SNR. It is scores in percentage of words correct. Higher scores are correlated with better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Connection reliability of OTN</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Given that the remote connection can be impacted by power supply etc. a count of signal interference/breakdowns will be made over the course of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Perspectives on Auditory Training Benefits</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete an in-house questionnaire addressing perceived benefits of the services they received as well as an assessment of audiovisual quality, disturbances in the appointment etc. for the teleconferencing group. The questionnaire uses a likert scale using descriptors of agreement (i.e. Strongly agree (1), agree, neutral, disagree, strongly disagree (5)). A higher score indicates poorer outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Client Oriented Scale of Improvement (COSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The COSI is a well recognized subjective questionnaire used to assess pre/post-treatment improvement in listening. It will be used to assess the participants perceived benefit of treatment prior to their first Auditory training appointment and again once they are done receiving these services. It asks the listener to generate up to 5 listening goals. It then uses subjective assessment to assess their improvement as a % of change. Reporting is also completed using a likert scale with descriptors (Worse, No difference, slightly better, better, much better). Higher percentage and greater degree of change are associated with better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Hearing Impairment, Sensorineural</condition>
  <condition>Auditory; Nerve</condition>
  <condition>Cochlear Implants</condition>
  <condition>Rehabilitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Remote AT services</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental group will consist of participants who access auditory therapy services from a remote location. Services will be conducted with this group via teleconferencing over the Ontario Health Network.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>In House AT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive auditory therapy services face-to-face at the treatment site.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teleconferencing</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of video/audio stream to provide auditory training at a remote site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Remote AT services</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Auditory training services</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will engage in regular visits with a specialist to: 1) facilitate auditory training exercises; 2) work with the family/friends to encourage optimal communication strategies in the home; 3) evaluate and assess achievement of listening goals.
Auditory training assess/reviews skills associated with but not necessarily limited to: 1) developing strategies to repair communication breakdowns; 2) listening in quiet; 3) listening in noise; 4) listening to a degraded signal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>In House AT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Remote AT services</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly implanted subjects who might need additional auditory training supports (e.g.
             long-term deafened, limited communication partners etc.)

          -  Post-lingual onset of hearing loss

          -  No cognitive deficits

          -  English must be their native language

          -  Willingness to use teleconferencing methods to obtain AT services and residing &gt;1 hr
             away by car from the hospital

          -  Willingness to attend these appointments with a communication partner wherever
             possible

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Onset of hearing loss prior to two years of age (prelingual hearing loss)

          -  Ossification or any other cochlear anomaly that might prevent complete insertion of
             the electrode array, as confirmed by medical examination and imaging including MRI

          -  Hearing loss of retro-cochlear or central origin

          -  Additional handicaps that would prevent participation in evaluations

          -  Unrealistic expectations on the part of the subject, regarding the possible benefits,
             risks, and limitations that are inherent to the surgical procedure(s) and prosthetic
             device

          -  Active middle ear infection

          -  Unwillingness or inability of the candidate to comply with all investigational
             requirements

          -  History of radiation

          -  Patient concerns regarding their own technological skills and ability to use
             teleconferencing methods
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kassandra H Kaminskas, M.Cl.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre - Clinical Audiologist</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Varia Sajeniouk, B.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>416-480-6100</phone>
    <phone_ext>85392</phone_ext>
    <email>varia.sajeniouk@sunnybrook.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bush ML, Thompson R, Irungu C, Ayugi J. The Role of Telemedicine in Auditory Rehabilitation: A Systematic Review. Otol Neurotol. 2016 Dec;37(10):1466-1474. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27755363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cullington H, Kitterick P, DeBold L, Weal M, Clarke N, Newberry E, Aubert L. Have Cochlear Implant, Won't Have to Travel: Introducing Telemedicine to People Using Cochlear Implants. Am J Audiol. 2016 Oct 1;25(3S):299-302. doi: 10.1044/2016_AJA-16-0018.</citation>
    <PMID>27768192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 23, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 23, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kassandra Kaminskas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Audiologist - Cochlear Implant Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Auditory Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Teleconferencing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deafness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

