<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04204616</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RD.06.SPR.202699</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04204616</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Long-term Study of Nemolizumab (CD14152) in Participants With Prurigo Nodularis (PN)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Multicenter, Long-Term Study to Assess the Safety and Efficacy of Nemolizumab (CD14152) in Subjects With Prurigo Nodularis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Galderma R&amp;D</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Galderma R&amp;D</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to assess the long-term safety of nemolizumab (CD14152)
      in participants with prurigo nodularis (PN).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 5, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Adverse Events by Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 64 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical event that occurs in a participant administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product. An assessment of severity grade will be made by investigator as follow: mild (an AE that is easily tolerated by the participant, causes minimal discomfort, and does not interfere with everyday activities), moderate (An AE that is sufficiently discomforting to interfere with normal everyday activities; intervention may be needed) and severe (an AE that prevents normal everyday activities; treatment or other intervention usually needed).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with an Investigator Global Assessment (IGA) Success Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with an IGA success (defined as IGA of 0 [Clear] or 1 [Almost clear] and a greater than or equal to [&gt;=] 2-point improvement from baseline) at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with an Improvement of &gt;=4 from Baseline in Peak Pruritus (PP) Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with an improvement of &gt;= 4 from baseline in PP NRS up to Week 52 will be reported. The PP NRS has a scale of 0 to 10, with 0 being &quot;no itch&quot; and 10 being &quot;worst itch imaginable&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Low Disease Activity State at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with low disease activity state (that is, IGA &lt;=2) at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Prurigo Nodularis Activity (PN-A) Success at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with PN-A success (defined as score of 0 [Clear] or 1 [Almost clear]) at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Prurigo Nodularis Stage (PN-S) Success at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with PN-S success (defined as score of 0 [Clear] or 1 [Almost clear]) at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Pruriginous Lesions with Excoriations/Crusts at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of pruriginous lesions with excoriations/crusts at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Healed Prurigo Lesions at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of healed prurigo lesions at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Number of Lesions in Representative Area at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in number of lesions in representative area at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with PP NRS &lt;2 up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with PP NRS &lt;2 up to Week 52 will be reported. PP NRS is a scale of 0 to 10, with 0 being &quot;no itch&quot; and 10 being &quot;worst itch imaginable&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change from Baseline in PP NRS up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change from baseline in PP NRS up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Average Pruritus (AP) NRS &lt;2 up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with AP NRS less than (&lt;) 2 up to Week 52 will be reported. AP NRS has a scale of 0 to 10, with 0 being &quot;no itch&quot; and 10 being &quot;worst itch imaginable&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with an Improvement of &gt;=4 from Baseline in AP NRS up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with an improvement of &gt;=4 from baseline in AP NRS up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change from Baseline in AP NRS up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change from baseline in AP NRS up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with an Improvement of &gt;=4 from Baseline in Sleep Disturbance (SD) NRS up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with an improvement of &gt;=4 from baseline in Sleep Disturbance (SD) NRS up to Week 52 will be reported. SD NRS has a scale of 0 to 10, with 0 being &quot;no sleep loss related to the symptoms of my skin disease (prurigo nodularis)&quot; and 10 being &quot;I did not sleep at all due to the symptoms of my skin disease (prurigo nodularis)&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change from Baseline in SD NRS up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change from baseline in SD NRS up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Prurigo Nodularis (PN)-associated Pain Frequency up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in PN-associated pain frequency up to Week 52 will be reported. The pain frequency will be assessed on a scale of 0 to 5 where 0 = never, 1 = less than once a week, 2 = 1-2 days a week, 3 = 3-4 days a week, and 4 = 5-6 days a week.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in PN-associated Pain Intensity up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in PN-associated pain intensity up to Week 52 will be reported. The pain intensity will be assessed on a scale of 0 to 10, with 0 being &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 being &quot;the worst unbearable pain&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Reporting low Disease Activity Based on Patient Global Assessment of Disease (PGAD) at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants reporting low disease activity (clear, almost clear, or mild) based on Patient Global Assessment of Disease (PGAD) at each visit up to Week 52 to be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Satisfied with Study Treatment Based on Patient Global Assessment of Treatment (PGAT) at Each Visit up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants satisfied with study treatment (good, very good, or excellent) based on Patient Global Assessment of Treatment (PGAT) at each visit up to Week 52 will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) up to Week 52 will be reported. The DLQI is a validated 10-item questionnaire covering domains including symptoms/feelings, daily activities, leisure, work/school, personal relationships, and treatment. The participant will rate each question ranging from 0 (not at all) to 3 (very much). A higher total score indicates a poorer quality of life (QoL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in EuroQoL 5-Dimension (EQ-5D) up to Week 52</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in EuroQoL 5-Dimension (EQ-5D) up to Week 52 will be reported. The EQ-5D instrument is a validated questionnaire, completed by the participant that consists of 2 parts. The first part consists of 5 multiple choice QoL questions and the second is a 100 point Visual Analog Scale (VAS) with 0 being &quot;Worst imaginable health state&quot; and 100 being &quot;Best imaginable health state&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">353</enrollment>
  <condition>Prurigo Nodularis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nemolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nemolizumab administered via subcutaneous injection (SC)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nemolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Nemolizumab 30 mg will be administered as SC injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nemolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CD14152</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who may benefit from study participation in the opinion of the
             investigator and participated in a prior nemolizumab study for PN

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential must agree either to be strictly
             abstinent throughout the study and for 12 weeks after the last study drug injection,
             or to use an effective and approved method of contraception throughout the study and
             for 12 weeks after the last study drug injection

          -  Participant willing and able to comply with all of the time commitments and procedural
             requirements of the clinical study protocol, including periodic weekly recordings by
             the participant using an electronic handheld device provided for this study

          -  Understand and sign an informed consent form (ICF) before any investigational
             procedure(s) are performed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who, during their participation in a prior nemolizumab study, experienced
             an adverse event (AE) which in the opinion of the investigator could indicate that
             continued treatment with nemolizumab may present an unreasonable risk for the
             participant

          -  Pregnant women (positive pregnancy test result at screening or baseline visit),
             breastfeeding women, or women planning a pregnancy during the clinical study

          -  Any medical or psychological condition that may put the participant at significant
             risk according to the investigator's judgment, if he/she participates in the clinical
             study, or may interfere with study assessments (example, poor venous access or
             needle-phobia)

          -  Planning or expected to have a major surgical procedure during the clinical study

          -  Participants unwilling to refrain from using prohibited medications during the
             clinical study

          -  History of alcohol or substance abuse for 2 years prior to the screening visit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Galderma Research &amp; Development</last_name>
    <phone>817-961-5000</phone>
    <email>clinical.studies@galderma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prurigo</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurodermatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

