<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04205838</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-000604</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-02887</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>19-000604</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04205838</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anakinra in Preventing Severe Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-Cell Related Encephalopathy Syndrome in Patients With Recurrent or Refractory Large B-cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>IL-1 Receptor Antagonist to Prevent Severe Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-Cell Related Encephalopathy Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well anakinra works in preventing severe chimeric antigen
      receptor T-cell-related encephalopathy syndrome after chimeric antigen receptor T-cell
      therapy in patients with large B-cell lymphoma that has come back or has not responded to
      treatment. Immunosuppressive therapy, such as anakinra, is used to decrease the body?s immune
      response, which may prevent severe chimeric antigen receptor T-cell-related encephalopathy
      syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine if it is feasible to accrue a sufficient number of study participants at one
      site, in order to justify expanding the trial to three additional sites (pilot study).

      II. To estimate the efficacy of anakinra in prevention of severe immune effector
      cell-associated neurotoxicity syndrome. syndrome (ICANS) (full study).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate the impact that anakinra has on the efficacy of chimeric antigen receptor
      (CAR) T-cell therapy for relapsed/refractory lymphoma.

      II. To estimate the rate of subsequent ICANS development in patients who receive anakinra for
      grade &gt;= 3 cytokine release syndrome (CRS) in the absence of ICANS.

      III. To estimate the duration of neurotoxicity in patients who receive anakinra.

      IV. To estimate the duration of severe neurotoxicity in patients who receive anakinra.

      V. To determine if anakinra causes persistent hepatotoxicity in patients receiving CAR T-cell
      for refractory lymphoma.

      VI. to evaluate the overall toxicity of anakinra in patients receiving CAR T-cell therapy for
      refractory lymphoma.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate CRS and ICANS grade by using the American Society for Blood and Marrow
      Transplantation (ASBMT) 2018 consensus grading for adults.

      II. To investigate changes in inflammatory markers including IL-1 and IL-6 in the peripheral
      blood during episodes of ICANS.

      III. To describe the electroencephalogram (EEG) changes that characterize ICANS.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive standard lymphodepleting therapy including fludarabine and cyclophosphamide
      on days -5 to -3, then receive axicabtagene ciloleucel CAR T-cell infusion. Patients with
      clinical evidence of ICANS of any grade, or CRS &gt;= grade 3 receive anakinra subcutaneously
      (SC) every 6-12 hours for 12-36 doses over 9 days in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study, patients are followed up at 30, 90, and 100 days, then at 6
      months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 4, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who met the eligibility criteria to receive and did receive anakinra</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The study will be considered feasible if 8 study participants are enrolled over 12 months at University of California, Los Angeles.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of severe chimeric antigen receptor T-cell-related encephalopathy syndrome (ICANS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be defined as grade &gt;= 3 neurotoxicity by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (v)4.03. The proportion of patients developing severe ICANS and the corresponding 90% binomial exact confidence interval (CI) will be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be defined as a complete response or partial response per the International Working Group criteria malignancy lymphoma based on positron emission tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT) scan. To account for the adaptive nature of Simon?s two-stage design, final analysis of the objective response rate will report the uniformly minimum variance unbiased estimator and the corresponding p-value and 95% CI for the ORR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who received anakinra and develop ICAN</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who received anakinra in the absence of ICANS and then develop ICANS of any grade out of the total number of participants who received anakinra in the absence of ICANS will be evaluated. Will be summarized using descriptive statistics such as proportion, mean, standard deviation, median, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of neurotoxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day of CRES of any grade to complete resolution of CRES, assessed up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as number of days that elapse from first day of ICANS of any grade to complete resolution of ICANS. Will be summarized using descriptive statistics such as proportion, mean, standard deviation, median, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of neurotoxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>From first day of ICANS of &gt;= grade 3 to improvement of ICANS to &lt; grade 3, assessed up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as number of days that elapse from first day of ICANS of &gt;= grade 3 to improvement of ICANS to &lt; grade 3 based on CTCAE v4.03. Will be summarized using descriptive statistics such as proportion, mean, standard deviation, median, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistent hepatotoxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be defined as grade &gt; 2 aspartate aminotransferase (AST)/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) increased for at least 4 weeks duration according to CTCAE v4.03. Will be summarized using descriptive statistics such as proportion, mean, standard deviation, median, as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be based on CTCAE v4.03. Will be summarized using descriptive statistics such as proportion, mean, standard deviation, median, as appropriate. All AEs will be listed, documenting the course, outcome, severity, and relationship to the study treatment. Incidence rates of AEs and the proportion of subjects prematurely withdrawn from the study due to AEs will be shown.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>ICANS grade</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will evaluate ICANS grade by using the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2018 consensus grading for adults.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cytokine release syndrome (CRS) grade</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will evaluate CRS grade by using the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2018 consensus grading for adults.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 6 days following initiation of anakinra</time_frame>
    <description>Peak median serum blood and cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) levels of IL-1 and IL-6 will be summarized using descriptive statistics or contingency tables, as appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: Slowing of EEG activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Slowing of EEG activity including waveform, spectrum, spectrogram, and power in the slow (0.1-1 Hz), delta (1 to 4 Hz), theta (4 to 8 Hz) bands.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: focal slowing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: Focal regional slowing of the EEG activity within the frontal, temporal, parietal, or occipital region in the delta (&lt;4Hz) and/ or theta (4-8 Hz) band.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: periodic discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized or lateralized or bilateral independent or multifocal periodic discharges (repetitive discharges with similar morphology and recurring at regular or near-regular inter-discharge intervals)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: rhythmic activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized or lateralized or bilateral independent or multifocal Rhythmic delta activity (&lt;/= 4 Hz).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: Generalized or lateralized or bilateral independent or multifocal spike</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized or lateralized or bilateral independent or multifocal spike (duration of the wave &lt;70ms) or sharp (duration of the wave 70-200ms) discharges.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Electroencephalogram (EEG) that characterize ICANS: seizures</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Electrographic seizure occurrence: Percentage of subjects who experience electrographic seizure while undergoing continuous-EEG monitoring.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma, Not Otherwise Specified</condition>
  <condition>High Grade B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Progressive Disease</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent High Grade B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Primary Mediastinal (Thymic) Large B-Cell Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Transformed Follicular Lymphoma to Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory High Grade B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Primary Mediastinal (Thymic) Large B-Cell Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Transformed Follicular Lymphoma to Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (anakinra, CAR T-cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive standard lymphodepleting therapy including fludarabine and cyclophosphamide on days -5 to -3, then receive axicabtagene ciloleucel CAR T-cell infusion. Patients with clinical evidence of ICANS of any grade, or CRS &gt;= grade 3 receive anakinra SC every 6-12 hours for 12-36 doses over 9 days in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anakinra</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (anakinra, CAR T-cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kinaret</other_name>
    <other_name>Kineret</other_name>
    <other_name>rIL-1ra</other_name>
    <other_name>rIL1RN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Axicabtagene Ciloleucel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given via infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (anakinra, CAR T-cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KTE C19</other_name>
    <other_name>KTE-C19</other_name>
    <other_name>KTE-C19 CAR</other_name>
    <other_name>Yescarta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given via infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (anakinra, CAR T-cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(-)-Cyclophosphamide</other_name>
    <other_name>2H-1,3,2-Oxazaphosphorine, 2-[bis(2-chloroethyl)amino]tetrahydro-, 2-oxide, monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Carloxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Ciclofosfamida</other_name>
    <other_name>Ciclofosfamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Cicloxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Clafen</other_name>
    <other_name>Claphene</other_name>
    <other_name>CP monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>CTX</other_name>
    <other_name>CYCLO-cell</other_name>
    <other_name>Cycloblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cycloblastine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophospham</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamid monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamide Monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamidum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphan</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphane</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphanum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclostin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclostine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytophosphan</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytophosphane</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Fosfaseron</other_name>
    <other_name>Genoxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Genuxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Ledoxina</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Neosar</other_name>
    <other_name>Revimmune</other_name>
    <other_name>Syklofosfamid</other_name>
    <other_name>WR- 138719</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given via infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (anakinra, CAR T-cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluradosa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine Phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given via infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prevention (anakinra, CAR T-cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-F-ara-AMP</other_name>
    <other_name>9H-Purin-6-amine, 2-fluoro-9-(5-O-phosphono-.beta.-D-arabinofuranosyl)-</other_name>
    <other_name>Beneflur</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
    <other_name>SH T 586</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with relapsed or refractory large B-cell lymphoma that has progressed on two
             prior lines of therapy, who meet the indication for the Food and Drug Administration
             (FDA)-approved therapy axicabtagene ciloleucel

          -  Large B-cell lymphoma includes diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) not otherwise
             specified, primary mediastinal large B-cell lymphoma, high grade B-cell lymphoma, and
             DLBCL arising from follicular lymphoma

          -  The above includes patients with progressive or stable disease as the best response to
             the most recent treatment regimen or disease progression within 12 months after
             autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation

          -  Patients with central nervous system (CNS) involvement of large B-cell lymphoma that
             originated outside of the CNS will be included (not primary CNS lymphoma)

          -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT)/aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 upper
             limit of normal

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt; 30 mL/min based on Cockcroft-Gault formula

          -  Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) who have an undetectable viral load
             will be included

          -  Deemed competent to make medical decisions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who receive CAR T-cell therapy with a product other than axicabtagene
             ciloleucel

          -  Primary CNS lymphoma

          -  Transformed DLBCL from chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)

          -  Burkitt?s lymphoma

          -  Bridging chemotherapy completed &lt; 7 days prior to CAR T-cell lymphodepleting
             chemotherapy

          -  In patients who receive bridging chemotherapy, positron emission tomography
             (PET)-computed tomography (CT) or CT of chest, abdomen, pelvis was not done after
             bridging chemotherapy prior lympho-depleting therapy

          -  Most recent PET-CT or CT of all known disease is sites done more than 6 weeks prior to
             CAR T-cell infusion

          -  Any individual CNS tumor mass &gt; 2 cm

          -  History of autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation administered less than
             100 days prior to CAR T-cell infusion

          -  History of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation

          -  Treatment with alemtuzumab within 6 months prior to leukapheresis, or treatment with
             clofarabine or cladribine within 3 months prior to leukapheresis

          -  Less than 3 half-lives elapsed since receiving immune checkpoint inhibitor
             (pembrolizumab, ipilimumab, nivolumab, atezolizumab, etc.)

          -  Presence of uncontrolled fungal, bacterial, or viral infection that require
             intravenous (IV) antimicrobial treatment

          -  History of autoimmune disease resulting in end-organ damage, or autoimmune disease
             requiring systemic immunosuppressants or disease-modifying antirheumatic drug (DMARDs)
             within the past 6 months

          -  Hypersensitivity to E. Coli-derived proteins

          -  Patients with HIV who have a detectable viral load

          -  Pregnant or nursing

          -  Fertile women who decline use of contraception during the study period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John M Timmerman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA / Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Caspian Oliai, MD</last_name>
    <phone>310-206-8477</phone>
    <phone_ext>30870</phone_ext>
    <email>coliai@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA / Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Caspian Oliai</last_name>
      <phone>310-794-4820</phone>
      <email>COliai@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John M. Timmerman, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin 1 Receptor Antagonist Protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

