<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03827811</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PandrTB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03827811</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacometrics to Advance Novel Regimens for Drug-resistant Tuberculosis-PandrTB Tuberculosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>PandrTB</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacometrics to Advance Novel Regimens for Drug-resistant Tuberculosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cape Town</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Partners in Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harvard Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medicines Sans Frontieres</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cape Town</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PandrTB is a study of the pharmacokinetics(PK) and pharmacodynamics(PD) of bedaquiline,
      delamanid, clofazimine, linezolid, moxifloxacin, levofloxacin and pyrazinamide used in novel
      combinations to treat multidrug-resistant tuberculosis(MDR-TB).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PandrTB is an observational study nested in the endTB trial, a randomized study that will
      evaluate five 9-month, injectable-sparing regimens that could transform the treatment of
      MDR-TB. As part of PandrTB: the plasma concentrations of the experimental arm drugs (the new
      and repurposed drugs bedaquiline, delamanid, clofazimine and linezolid, as well as
      levofloxacin, moxifloxacin and pyrazinamide) will be measured; MICs will be determined in
      baseline isolates; and MGIT cultures, additional to those in the endTB study, will be
      performed at weeks 6 and 10. Nonlinear mixed-effects models will describe the population PK
      of the drugs and a pharmacodynamic (PD) model of treatment response of Mycobacterium
      tuberculosis(Mtb) load over time. Recursive partitioning methods will evaluate baseline MICs
      and PK measures as drivers of treatment response (as described by the parameters of the PD
      model of initial treatment response of Mtb load over time, and the endTB trial endpoints:
      time to culture conversion, longer-term outcomes, and acquisition of phenotypic resistance).
      Thus the key drugs and plasma drug exposure thresholds for activity will be defined, and
      exposure-dependent synergy or antagonism identified. The risks of toxicities (as assessed in
      the endTB study) will be estimated, by plasma drug exposure and important comorbidity
      (including HIV infection). In this way, the PK-efficacy and PK-toxicity analyses will allow
      definition of target plasma drug exposures. Simulations will predict optimal doses. To
      advance the understanding of drug penetration, we will develop approaches to measure free
      drug plasma concentrations. Drug-drug interactions will be described. Thus PandrTB will
      inform how best to use these new and repurposed drugs in combination, to create the most
      effective and least toxic regimens while minimizing the development of further drug
      resistance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug exposure (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>drug exposures derived using population PK models</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of decline of viable M.tubercolosis in sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>A pharmacodynamic biomarker model of response to treatment will be used to derive the rate of decline of Mtb in MIGT cultures. The effect of PK on this measure will be evaluated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collecting adverse events as a measure of safety</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of pharmacokinetics on drug and regimen saftey will be evaluated using recursive partitioning methods.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">625</enrollment>
  <condition>Multi-drug Resistant Tuberculosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PandrTB cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>endTB participants on experimental regimen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood will be stored for evaluation of genetic variants associated with drug
      concentrations and effects.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adults and adolescents (≥15 years) will be enrolled. There is increasing recognition that
        adolescents have been neglected in the development of treatments for diseases like HIV and
        TB, given that they comprise and important population. Minors are included in the endTB
        clinical trial and it would be wrong to exclude them from a PK study designed to optimize
        doses.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All patients enrolled to the experimental arms of the endTB study and provide their written
        informed consent to participate in the PandrTB study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helen McIlleron, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cape Town</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Helen McIlleron, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>27214066779</phone>
    <email>helen.mcilleron@uct.ac.za</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marilyn Solomons</last_name>
    <phone>0244066779</phone>
    <email>marilyn.solomons@uct.ac.za</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Partners in Health Lesotho House 233 Corner Lancers and Caldwell Roads</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maseru</city>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Lesotho</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sesomo Mohale</last_name>
      <phone>+266 22312399</phone>
      <email>smohale@pih.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mpho Maketekete</last_name>
      <phone>+266 22312399</phone>
      <email>mkhesa@pih.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Dr Holtzman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peru-1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara Perea</last_name>
      <email>sperea_ses@pih.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jimmy Garlarza</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peru_2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara Perea</last_name>
      <email>sperea_ses@pih.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jimmy Galarza</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Khayelitsha Town 2 Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7764</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nelisiwe Ntuli</last_name>
      <email>msfocb-khayelitsha-endtb@brussels.msf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sehaam Jaffer</last_name>
      <email>sehaam.jaffer@uct.ac.za</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Lesotho</country>
    <country>Peru</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report/en/</url>
    <description>World Health Organization. Global tuberculosis report 2016. Geneva: WHO; 2016</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horsburgh CR, Rusen ID, Mitnick CD. Optimizing MDR-TB clinical trials: insights from the first global MDR-TB Clinical Trials Landscape Meeting. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2016 Dec 1;20(12):1-3. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.16.0568.</citation>
    <PMID>28240564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diacon AH, Pym A, Grobusch MP, de los Rios JM, Gotuzzo E, Vasilyeva I, Leimane V, Andries K, Bakare N, De Marez T, Haxaire-Theeuwes M, Lounis N, Meyvisch P, De Paepe E, van Heeswijk RP, Dannemann B; TMC207-C208 Study Group. Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis and culture conversion with bedaquiline. N Engl J Med. 2014 Aug 21;371(8):723-32. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1313865.</citation>
    <PMID>25140958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahuja SD, Ashkin D, Avendano M, Banerjee R, Bauer M, Bayona JN, Becerra MC, Benedetti A, Burgos M, Centis R, Chan ED, Chiang CY, Cox H, D'Ambrosio L, DeRiemer K, Dung NH, Enarson D, Falzon D, Flanagan K, Flood J, Garcia-Garcia ML, Gandhi N, Granich RM, Hollm-Delgado MG, Holtz TH, Iseman MD, Jarlsberg LG, Keshavjee S, Kim HR, Koh WJ, Lancaster J, Lange C, de Lange WC, Leimane V, Leung CC, Li J, Menzies D, Migliori GB, Mishustin SP, Mitnick CD, Narita M, O'Riordan P, Pai M, Palmero D, Park SK, Pasvol G, Peña J, Pérez-Guzmán C, Quelapio MI, Ponce-de-Leon A, Riekstina V, Robert J, Royce S, Schaaf HS, Seung KJ, Shah L, Shim TS, Shin SS, Shiraishi Y, Sifuentes-Osornio J, Sotgiu G, Strand MJ, Tabarsi P, Tupasi TE, van Altena R, Van der Walt M, Van der Werf TS, Vargas MH, Viiklepp P, Westenhouse J, Yew WW, Yim JJ; Collaborative Group for Meta-Analysis of Individual Patient Data in MDR-TB. Multidrug resistant pulmonary tuberculosis treatment regimens and patient outcomes: an individual patient data meta-analysis of 9,153 patients. PLoS Med. 2012;9(8):e1001300. Epub 2012 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22952439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dheda K, Esmail A, Limberis J, Maartens G. Selected questions and controversies about bedaquiline: a view from the field. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2016 Dec 1;20(12):24-32. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.16.0065. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28240569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Heeswijk RP, Dannemann B, Hoetelmans RM. Bedaquiline: a review of human pharmacokinetics and drug-drug interactions. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2014 Sep;69(9):2310-8. doi: 10.1093/jac/dku171. Epub 2014 May 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24860154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta R, Wells CD, Hittel N, Hafkin J, Geiter LJ. Delamanid in the treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2016 Dec 1;20(12):33-37. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.16.0125. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28240570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis JM, Sloan DJ. The role of delamanid in the treatment of drug-resistant tuberculosis. Ther Clin Risk Manag. 2015 May 13;11:779-91. doi: 10.2147/TCRM.S71076. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25999726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gler MT, Skripconoka V, Sanchez-Garavito E, Xiao H, Cabrera-Rivero JL, Vargas-Vasquez DE, Gao M, Awad M, Park SK, Shim TS, Suh GY, Danilovits M, Ogata H, Kurve A, Chang J, Suzuki K, Tupasi T, Koh WJ, Seaworth B, Geiter LJ, Wells CD. Delamanid for multidrug-resistant pulmonary tuberculosis. N Engl J Med. 2012 Jun 7;366(23):2151-60. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1112433.</citation>
    <PMID>22670901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Donnell MR, Padayatchi N, Metcalfe JZ. Elucidating the role of clofazimine for the treatment of tuberculosis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2016 Dec 1;20(12):52-57. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.16.0073. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28240574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamprecht DA, Finin PM, Rahman MA, Cumming BM, Russell SL, Jonnala SR, Adamson JH, Steyn AJ. Turning the respiratory flexibility of Mycobacterium tuberculosis against itself. Nat Commun. 2016 Aug 10;7:12393. doi: 10.1038/ncomms12393.</citation>
    <PMID>27506290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Deun A, Maug AK, Salim MA, Das PK, Sarker MR, Daru P, Rieder HL. Short, highly effective, and inexpensive standardized treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2010 Sep 1;182(5):684-92. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201001-0077OC. Epub 2010 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>20442432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tang S, Yao L, Hao X, Liu Y, Zeng L, Liu G, Li M, Li F, Wu M, Zhu Y, Sun H, Gu J, Wang X, Zhang Z. Clofazimine for the treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: prospective, multicenter, randomized controlled study in China. Clin Infect Dis. 2015 May 1;60(9):1361-7. doi: 10.1093/cid/civ027. Epub 2015 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25605283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. NDA 204-384 Sirturo™ (bedaquiline 100 mg tablets) for the treatment of adults (≥ 18 years) as part of combination therapy of pulmonary multi-drug resistant tuberculosis (MDRTB). 2012 Nov 28;1-69</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cox H, Ford N. Linezolid for the treatment of complicated drug-resistant tuberculosis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2012 Apr;16(4):447-54. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.11.0451. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22325685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nuermberger E. Evolving strategies for dose optimization of linezolid for treatment of tuberculosis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2016 Dec 1;20(12):48-51. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.16.0113. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28240573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zvada SP, Denti P, Sirgel FA, Chigutsa E, Hatherill M, Charalambous S, Mungofa S, Wiesner L, Simonsson US, Jindani A, Harrison T, McIlleron HM. Moxifloxacin population pharmacokinetics and model-based comparison of efficacy between moxifloxacin and ofloxacin in African patients. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014;58(1):503-10. doi: 10.1128/AAC.01478-13. Epub 2013 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24189253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cox HS, Sibilia K, Feuerriegel S, Kalon S, Polonsky J, Khamraev AK, Rüsch-Gerdes S, Mills C, Niemann S. Emergence of extensive drug resistance during treatment for multidrug-resistant tuberculosis. N Engl J Med. 2008 Nov 27;359(22):2398-400. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc0805644. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2010 Oct 21;363(17):1682.</citation>
    <PMID>19038891</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cegielski JP, Dalton T, Yagui M, Wattanaamornkiet W, Volchenkov GV, Via LE, Van Der Walt M, Tupasi T, Smith SE, Odendaal R, Leimane V, Kvasnovsky C, Kuznetsova T, Kurbatova E, Kummik T, Kuksa L, Kliiman K, Kiryanova EV, Kim H, Kim CK, Kazennyy BY, Jou R, Huang WL, Ershova J, Erokhin VV, Diem L, Contreras C, Cho SN, Chernousova LN, Chen MP, Caoili JC, Bayona J, Akksilp S; Global Preserving Effective TB Treatment Study (PETTS) Investigators. Extensive drug resistance acquired during treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis. Clin Infect Dis. 2014 Oct 15;59(8):1049-63. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciu572. Epub 2014 Jul 23.</citation>
    <PMID>25057101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang YA, Shim TS, Koh WJ, Lee SH, Lee CH, Choi JC, Lee JH, Jang SH, Yoo KH, Jung KH, Kim KU, Choi SB, Ryu YJ, Kim KC, Um S, Kwon YS, Kim YH, Choi WI, Jeon K, Hwang YI, Kim SJ, Lee HK, Heo E, Yim JJ. Choice between Levofloxacin and Moxifloxacin and Multidrug-Resistant Tuberculosis Treatment Outcomes. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2016 Mar;13(3):364-70. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201510-690BC.</citation>
    <PMID>26871879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson JL, Hadad DJ, Boom WH, Daley CL, Peloquin CA, Eisenach KD, Jankus DD, Debanne SM, Charlebois ED, Maciel E, Palaci M, Dietze R. Early and extended early bactericidal activity of levofloxacin, gatifloxacin and moxifloxacin in pulmonary tuberculosis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2006 Jun;10(6):605-12.</citation>
    <PMID>16776446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gumbo T, Chigutsa E, Pasipanodya J, Visser M, van Helden PD, Sirgel FA, McIlleron H. The pyrazinamide susceptibility breakpoint above which combination therapy fails. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2014 Sep;69(9):2420-5. doi: 10.1093/jac/dku136. Epub 2014 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24821594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andries K, Villellas C, Coeck N, Thys K, Gevers T, Vranckx L, Lounis N, de Jong BC, Koul A. Acquired resistance of Mycobacterium tuberculosis to bedaquiline. PLoS One. 2014 Jul 10;9(7):e102135. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0102135. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25010492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pasipanodya JG, McIlleron H, Burger A, Wash PA, Smith P, Gumbo T. Serum drug concentrations predictive of pulmonary tuberculosis outcomes. J Infect Dis. 2013 Nov 1;208(9):1464-73. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jit352. Epub 2013 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23901086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chigutsa E, Pasipanodya JG, Visser ME, van Helden PD, Smith PJ, Sirgel FA, Gumbo T, McIlleron H. Impact of nonlinear interactions of pharmacokinetics and MICs on sputum bacillary kill rates as a marker of sterilizing effect in tuberculosis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2015 Jan;59(1):38-45. doi: 10.1128/AAC.03931-14. Epub 2014 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25313213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Modongo C, Pasipanodya JG, Magazi BT, Srivastava S, Zetola NM, Williams SM, Sirugo G, Gumbo T. Artificial Intelligence and Amikacin Exposures Predictive of Outcomes in Multidrug-Resistant Tuberculosis Patients. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2016 Sep 23;60(10):5928-32. doi: 10.1128/AAC.00962-16. Print 2016 Oct.</citation>
    <PMID>27458224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Srivastava S, Pasipanodya JG, Meek C, Leff R, Gumbo T. Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis not due to noncompliance but to between-patient pharmacokinetic variability. J Infect Dis. 2011 Dec 15;204(12):1951-9. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jir658. Epub 2011 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22021624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drusano GL, Sgambati N, Eichas A, Brown DL, Kulawy R, Louie A. The combination of rifampin plus moxifloxacin is synergistic for suppression of resistance but antagonistic for cell kill of Mycobacterium tuberculosis as determined in a hollow-fiber infection model. mBio. 2010 Aug 10;1(3). pii: e00139-10. doi: 10.1128/mBio.00139-10.</citation>
    <PMID>20802826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chirehwa MT, Rustomjee R, Mthiyane T, Onyebujoh P, Smith P, McIlleron H, Denti P. Model-Based Evaluation of Higher Doses of Rifampin Using a Semimechanistic Model Incorporating Autoinduction and Saturation of Hepatic Extraction. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2015 Nov 9;60(1):487-94. doi: 10.1128/AAC.01830-15. Print 2016 Jan. Erratum in: Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2016 May;60(5):3262.</citation>
    <PMID>26552972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McIlleron H, Rustomjee R, Vahedi M, Mthiyane T, Denti P, Connolly C, Rida W, Pym A, Smith PJ, Onyebujoh PC. Reduced antituberculosis drug concentrations in HIV-infected patients who are men or have low weight: implications for international dosing guidelines. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2012 Jun;56(6):3232-8. doi: 10.1128/AAC.05526-11. Epub 2012 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22411614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chigutsa E, Visser ME, Swart EC, Denti P, Pushpakom S, Egan D, Holford NH, Smith PJ, Maartens G, Owen A, McIlleron H. The SLCO1B1 rs4149032 polymorphism is highly prevalent in South Africans and is associated with reduced rifampin concentrations: dosing implications. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2011 Sep;55(9):4122-7. doi: 10.1128/AAC.01833-10. Epub 2011 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21709081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Savic RM, Ruslami R, Hibma JE, Hesseling A, Ramachandran G, Ganiem AR, Swaminathan S, McIlleron H, Gupta A, Thakur K, van Crevel R, Aarnoutse R, Dooley KE. Pediatric tuberculous meningitis: Model-based approach to determining optimal doses of the anti-tuberculosis drugs rifampin and levofloxacin for children. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2015 Dec;98(6):622-9. doi: 10.1002/cpt.202. Epub 2015 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26260983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shenje J, Ifeoma Adimora-Nweke F, Ross IL, Ntsekhe M, Wiesner L, Deffur A, McIlleron HM, Pasipanodya J, Gumbo T, Mayosi BM. Poor Penetration of Antibiotics Into Pericardium in Pericardial Tuberculosis. EBioMedicine. 2015 Sep 16;2(11):1640-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2015.09.025. eCollection 2015 Nov.</citation>
    <PMID>26870790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenaerts A, Barry CE 3rd, Dartois V. Heterogeneity in tuberculosis pathology, microenvironments and therapeutic responses. Immunol Rev. 2015 Mar;264(1):288-307. doi: 10.1111/imr.12252. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25703567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin SM, Prideaux B, Lyon ER, Zimmerman MD, Brooks EJ, Schrupp CA, Chen C, Reichlen MJ, Asay BC, Voskuil MI, Nuermberger EL, Andries K, Lyons MA, Dartois V, Lenaerts AJ. Bedaquiline and Pyrazinamide Treatment Responses Are Affected by Pulmonary Lesion Heterogeneity in Mycobacterium tuberculosis Infected C3HeB/FeJ Mice. ACS Infect Dis. 2016 Apr 8;2(4):251-267. Epub 2016 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27227164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin SM, Gruppo V, Brooks E, Gilliland J, Scherman M, Reichlen MJ, Leistikow R, Kramnik I, Nuermberger EL, Voskuil MI, Lenaerts AJ. Limited activity of clofazimine as a single drug in a mouse model of tuberculosis exhibiting caseous necrotic granulomas. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014 Jul;58(7):4026-34. doi: 10.1128/AAC.02565-14. Epub 2014 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24798275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horita Y, Doi N. Comparative study of the effects of antituberculosis drugs and antiretroviral drugs on cytochrome P450 3A4 and P-glycoprotein. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014 Jun;58(6):3168-76. doi: 10.1128/AAC.02278-13. Epub 2014 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24663015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Te Brake LH, Russel FG, van den Heuvel JJ, de Knegt GJ, de Steenwinkel JE, Burger DM, Aarnoutse RE, Koenderink JB. Inhibitory potential of tuberculosis drugs on ATP-binding cassette drug transporters. Tuberculosis (Edinb). 2016 Jan;96:150-7. doi: 10.1016/j.tube.2015.08.004. Epub 2015 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26682943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Svensson EM, Dooley KE, Karlsson MO. Impact of lopinavir-ritonavir or nevirapine on bedaquiline exposures and potential implications for patients with tuberculosis-HIV coinfection. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014 Nov;58(11):6406-12. doi: 10.1128/AAC.03246-14. Epub 2014 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25114140</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Svensson EM, Aweeka F, Park JG, Marzan F, Dooley KE, Karlsson MO. Model-based estimates of the effects of efavirenz on bedaquiline pharmacokinetics and suggested dose adjustments for patients coinfected with HIV and tuberculosis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2013 Jun;57(6):2780-7. doi: 10.1128/AAC.00191-13. Epub 2013 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23571542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pandie M, Wiesner L, McIlleron H, Hughes J, Siwendu S, Conradie F, Variava E, Maartens G. Drug-drug interactions between bedaquiline and the antiretrovirals lopinavir/ritonavir and nevirapine in HIV-infected patients with drug-resistant TB. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2016 Apr;71(4):1037-40. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkv447. Epub 2016 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26747099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mallikaarjun S, Wells C, Petersen C, Paccaly A, Shoaf SE, Patil S, Geiter L. Delamanid Coadministered with Antiretroviral Drugs or Antituberculosis Drugs Shows No Clinically Relevant Drug-Drug Interactions in Healthy Subjects. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2016 Sep 23;60(10):5976-85. doi: 10.1128/AAC.00509-16. Print 2016 Oct.</citation>
    <PMID>27458223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chigutsa E, Patel K, Denti P, Visser M, Maartens G, Kirkpatrick CM, McIlleron H, Karlsson MO. A time-to-event pharmacodynamic model describing treatment response in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis using days to positivity in automated liquid mycobacterial culture. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2013 Feb;57(2):789-95. doi: 10.1128/AAC.01876-12. Epub 2012 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23183433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Svensson E. A model-based analysis to describe bedaquiline's exposure-response relationship and predict the impact of drug-drug interactions. 9th Int workshop on Clinical Pharmacology of Tuberculosis Drugs 2016, Liverpool October 2016; Abstract O_01.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taubel J, Naseem A, Harada T, Wang D, Arezina R, Lorch U, Camm AJ. Levofloxacin can be used effectively as a positive control in thorough QT/QTc studies in healthy volunteers. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2010 Apr;69(4):391-400. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2125.2009.03595.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20406223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naidoo A, Chirehwa M, McIlleron H, Naidoo K, Essack S, Yende-Zuma N, Kimba-Phongi E, Adamson J, Govender K, Padayatchi N, Denti P. Effect of rifampicin and efavirenz on moxifloxacin concentrations when co-administered in patients with drug-susceptible TB. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2017 May 1;72(5):1441-1449. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkx004.</citation>
    <PMID>28175315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cape Town</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helen Margaret McIlleron</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MDR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Multidrug-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

