<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03829488</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15.02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ACTRN12617000358347</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03829488</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Better Evidence for Selecting Transplant Fluids</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEST-Fluids</acronym>
  <official_title>An Investigator-initiated, Pragmatic, Registry-based, Multi-centre, Double-blind, Randomised Controlled Trial Evaluating the Effect of Plasmalyte Versus 0.9% Saline on Early Kidney Transplant Function in Deceased Donor Kidney Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Queensland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Australian Government Department of Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health Research Council, New Zealand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baxter Healthcare Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Queensland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      End-stage kidney disease (ESKD) is a significant, expensive health problem. Kidney
      transplantation improves survival, quality of life, and is much cheaper than dialysis
      treatment for ESKD. However sometimes kidney transplants from a deceased donor function
      poorly after surgery, and a period of continued dialysis is needed, a condition known as
      delayed graft function (DGF). In addition to complicating recovery, DGF can adversely affect
      long-term kidney function and the health of the recipient.

      Intravenous fluids given during and after transplantation (usually 0.9% sodium chloride or
      saline) are critical to preserve kidney transplant function, but there is evidence that 0.9%
      saline may not be the safest fluid to use due to its high chloride content.

      BEST Fluids is a randomised controlled trial that aims to find out whether using a balanced
      low-chloride solution - Plasma-Lyte 148® - as an alternative to normal saline in deceased
      donor kidney transplantation, will improve kidney transplant function, reduce the impact of
      DGF, and improve long-term outcomes for patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      End-stage kidney disease is a significant public health problem worldwide, and its treatment
      imposes a high healthcare burden and cost. Kidney transplantation is considered the best
      treatment for ESKD, offering improved survival and quality of life at significantly lower
      cost that dialysis. However, many kidney transplants fail prematurely due in part due to
      injury sustained at the time of transplantation. Delayed graft function (DGF), i.e. the
      requirement for dialysis early after transplantation, affects approximately 30% of deceased
      donor kidney transplants, and increases the risk of graft failure and mortality.

      Intravenous fluids are a critical, albeit inexpensive, aspect of care that impacts early
      transplant function with normal (0.9%) saline the current standard care at most centres.
      However, normal saline may in fact be harmful in the setting of kidney transplantation due to
      its high chloride content relative to plasma, causing metabolic acidosis, acute kidney injury
      and thus potentially increasing the risk of DGF. Utilising a balanced low-chloride
      crystalloid solution such as Plasma-Lyte 148® (Plasmalyte) as an alternative to 0.9% saline
      may therefore improve outcomes after kidney transplantation.

      The BEST-Fluids study is an investigator-initiated, pragmatic, registry-based, multi-centre,
      double -blind randomised, controlled trial. The primary objective of the study is to evaluate
      the effect in deceased donor kidney transplant recipients of intravenous therapy with
      Plasmalyte versus 0.9% saline, commencing pre-operatively and continuing until intravenous
      fluids are no longer required or 48 hours post-transplant (whichever is earliest), on DGF,
      defined as the requirement for dialysis in the first seven days post-transplant.

      Patients admitted for a deceased donor kidney transplant at participating centres will be
      invited to participate in the study prior to transplant surgery. Following informed consent,
      participants will be randomised to receive either blinded Plasmalyte or blinded 0.9% saline
      for all intravenous fluid therapy purposes until 48 hours post-transplant. The volume and
      rate of fluid therapy will be determined by treating clinicians; all other treatments will be
      as per local standard of care. Participants will be enrolled, randomised and followed up
      using ANZDATA, the Australia &amp; New Zealand Dialysis &amp; Transplant Registry.

      The trial was prospectively registered with Australia New Zealand Clinical Trials Registry
      (ANZCTR) on 08/03/2017 (ACTRN12617000358347).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 7, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of participants with Delayed Graft Function</measure>
    <time_frame>7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Delayed Graft Function defined as receiving treatment with any form of dialysis in the first seven days after transplant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Kidney Transplant Function</measure>
    <time_frame>a. Duration of Delayed Graft Function - 12 Weeks; b. Rate of recovery of kidney transplant graft function - 2 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Early Kidney Transplant Function, a ranked composite of
Duration of Delayed Graft Function Description: Participants who require dialysis within seven days post-transplant, the time from transplant to the final dialysis treatment in days (up to 84 days/12 weeks) will be ranked from best to worst (longer times are worse).
Rate of recovery of kidney transplant graft function Description: for participants who do not require dialysis, graft function assessed using the creatinine reduction ratio on post-transplant day two (CRR2) will be ranked from best to worst (smaller reductions are worse).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of dialysis sessions</measure>
    <time_frame>First 28 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The number of dialysis sessions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total duration of dialysis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The total duration of dialysis in days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Creatinine reduction ratio from day 1 to day 2 post-transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to Day 2 post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Creatinine reduction ratio from day one to day two measured using serum assay, for those who do not require dialysis within the first 7 days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in serum creatinine of greater than or equal to 10%</measure>
    <time_frame>First 7 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of subjects with a reduction in serum creatinine of greater than or equal to 10% on three consecutive days in the first 7 days post-transplant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum creatinine trends over 52 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum creatinine trends measured over 52 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of serum potassium greater than or equal to 5.5 mmol/L</measure>
    <time_frame>First 48 hours post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Serum potassium greater than or equal to 5.5 mmol/L measured by serum assay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak potassium level</measure>
    <time_frame>First 48 hours post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Peak potassium level, measured by serum assay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment for hyperkalaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>First 48 hours post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment for hyperkalaemia with dialysis, Ca2+-gluconate, insulin, beta-agonists, sodium bicarbonate or ion exchange resins in the first 48 hours post-transplant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of significant fluid overload</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of significant fluid overload defined as &gt;5% weight gain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aggregate urine output</measure>
    <time_frame>Until day 2 post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregate urine output until day 2 post-transplant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Requirement for inotropic support (use of vasopressors or other drugs to maintain adequate blood pressure)</measure>
    <time_frame>Intra- and post-operatively to Day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Requirement for inotropic support both intra- and post-operatively to Day 2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of acute rejection episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of acute rejection episodes in the first 52 weeks as reported by ANZDATA routine data capture and as assessed by treating physicians</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of renal transplant biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>First 28 days post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Number of renal transplant biopsies performed in the first 28 days post-transplant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death from all causes</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Death from all causes up to 52 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Graft survival and death-censored graft survival as reported by ANZDATA and assessed by treating physician</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Graft function</measure>
    <time_frame>4, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Graft function (estimated glomerular filtration rate; eGFR) at 4, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 7, day 28, week 12, week 26, and week 52</time_frame>
    <description>Health-related quality of life measured using EuroQol EQ-5D-5L for adults, and EQ-5D-Y in children under 18 years. EQ-5D has descriptive and visual analogue scale (VAS). Descriptive system consists of five dimensions mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. VAS records patient's self-rated health on vertical visual analogue scale with endpoints best to worst health with 0 being worst and 100 being best health.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay over 12 months using linked data state and country based health data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare resource use</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Healthcare resource use over 12 months using linked data state and country based health data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cost-effectiveness over 12 months using linked data state and country based health data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Delayed Graft Function</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant; Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plasma-Lyte 148 (approx. pH 7.4) IV Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Plasma-Lyte 148 (approx. pH 7.4) IV Infusion intravenous fluid therapy will be used for all maintenance, replacement and resuscitation purposes from randomization onwards until 48 hours post-transplant, or until fluid therapy is no longer required, if earlier.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.9% SODIUM CHLORIDE 9g/L injection BP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.9% saline intravenous fluid therapy will be used for all maintenance, replacement and resuscitation purposes from randomization onwards until 48 hours post-transplant, or until fluid therapy is no longer required, if earlier.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plasma-Lyte 148 (approx. pH 7.4) IV Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Plasma-Lyte 148 (approx. pH 7.4) IV Infusion is a sterile, clear, non-pyrogenic isotonic solution and when administered intravenously is a source of water, electrolytes and calories. Plasma-Lyte 148 intravenous infusion is indicated as a source of water &amp; electrolytes or as an alkalinising agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Plasma-Lyte 148 (approx. pH 7.4) IV Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plasma-Lyte 148®</other_name>
    <other_name>Plasmalyte</other_name>
    <other_name>Balanced crystalloid solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.9% SODIUM CHLORIDE 9g/L injection BP</intervention_name>
    <description>Sodium chloride (0.9% saline) infusion is a sterile, non-pyrogenic solution of sodium chloride in Water for Injections. The concentration of sodium chloride is 154mmol/L. Sodium chloride (0.9%) intravenous infusion is indicated for extra-cellular fluid replacement and in the management of metabolic alkalosis in the presence of fluid loss, and for restoring or maintaining the concentration of sodium and chloride ions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>0.9% SODIUM CHLORIDE 9g/L injection BP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.9% saline</other_name>
    <other_name>Normal saline</other_name>
    <other_name>Isotonic saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult or child with End-Stage Kidney Disease, of any cause, on maintenance dialysis,
             or who has pre-dialysis stage 5 chronic kidney disease with an estimated Glomerular
             Filtration Rate of &lt;15 mL/min/1.73m2, AND

          2. Planned deceased donor kidney transplant from a brain-death (DBD) or circulatory-death
             (DCD) organ donor within 24 hours, AND

          3. Written informed consent, or consent given by their parent or guardian (if age &lt;18),
             or other authorised person

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Planned live donor kidney transplant (except where this is cancelled in favour or
             transplantation from a deceased donor)

          2. Planned multi-organ transplant (dual or en-bloc kidney transplants are not excluded)

          3. Children of weight &lt;20 kg, or a child that the treating physician believes should not
             be included in a study of blinded fluids due to their small body size

          4. Known hypersensitivity to the trial fluid preparations or packaging
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Collins, MBChB,FRACP,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Auckland District Health Board &amp; The University of Auckland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Chadban, BMed(hons),FRACP,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sydney Local Health District &amp; The University of Sydney</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Collins, MBChB,FRACP,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+64 9 367 0000</phone>
    <email>michael.collins@adhb.govt.nz</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sydney Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Randwick</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2031</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebecca Spicer</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2031</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zoltan Endre</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Chadban</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westmead Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2145</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philip O'Connell</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queensland Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4101</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven McTaggart</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4102</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Magid Fahim</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Adelaide Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Adelaide</city>
        <state>South Australia</state>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Toby Coates</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3065</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Goodman</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Austin Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurence Weinberg</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monash Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3168</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Kanellis</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fiona Stanley Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murdoch</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6150</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jagadish Jamboti</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perth</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wai Lim</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Auckland City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <zip>1142</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Collins</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Starship Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <zip>1142</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chanel Prestidge</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christchurch Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Christchurch</city>
        <zip>8011</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Irvine</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wellington Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wellington</city>
        <zip>6021</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carolyn Clark</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://aktn.org.au/best-fluids</url>
    <description>Australasian Kidney Trials Network Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delayed Graft Function</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plasma-lyte 148</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Yes Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in the primary publication, after de-identification (text, tables, figures and appendices) will be available for individual participant data meta-analysis.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 2 years and ending 5 years following main publication. Proposals may be submitted up to 5 years following article publication. After 5 years, the data will be available in our University's data warehouse but without investigator support other than deposited metadata.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>An independent review board will assess proposals based on the following criteria: sound science, benefit-risk balancing and research team expertise.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

