<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03820713</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AOS-CL1000-02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CL-PL-057-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03820713</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Feasibility, Safety, Initial Efficacy and Clinical Usability of FuseX Anti-Adhesion System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective, Randomized, Double Blinded, Parallel, Controlled, Two-arm, Two-center Evaluation of the Feasibility, Safety, Initial Efficacy and Clinical Usability of FuseX Anti-Adhesion System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eio Biomedical Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eio Biomedical Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of the feasibility, safety, initial efficacy and usability of FuseX Anti-Adhesion
      system toward further studies that will be powered to proved its safety and efficacy. In
      addition, this initial study will serve to yield blood bank and surgeon feedback towards
      improving the system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, randomized, double blinded, parallel, controlled, two-arm, two-center</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-emergent adverse event incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days from the first surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events related to treatment requiring any invasive procedure in the test group (who used blood plasma concentrate prepared using FuseX Anti-Adhesion System) compared to control group (who used normal saline processed by the same FuseX Anti-Adhesion System).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall adverse event incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the second surgery but not longer than 7 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall adverse event incidence will be evaluated by the presence and severity of adverse events and serious adverse events in the test group (who used blood plasma concentrate prepared using FuseX Anti-Adhesion System) vs. control group (who used normal saline processed by the same FuseX Anti-Adhesion System).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of new formed adhesions in the target region</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Severity of new formed adhesions having its source in the target region will be assessed by a blinded surgeon during the second surgery by grading the adhesion severity for each region on a scale from 0 (no adhesions) to 3 (strong vascularized adhesions that require sharp dissection and cannot be separated without tissue damage). The peritoneal cavity will be divided into 9 separate scoring regions. A peritoneal adhesion index (PAI) (sum of scores for all the regions) will be calculated per each patient.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Usability as assessed by Surgeon questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>a. Ease of application will be scored on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = very hard to 5 = very easy). b. Percentage of coverage the entire defined surgical field. c. mL of the materials used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Usability as assessed by Operator questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>a. Ease of device use will be scored on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = very hard to 5 = very easy). b. Device operation time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of general surgical complications; incidence of minor adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Until the second surgery but not longer than 7 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of general surgical complications including but not limited to:
Septic shock, cardiovascular events, respiratory tract infections and pulmonary atelectasis, urinary tract infections, thromboembolic events
Superficial Surgical Site Infections (SSI) - soft tissue infection, cellulitis, incisional abscess, wound dehiscence
Deep SSI - abdominal abscess, pelvic abscess, peritonitis. Incidence of minor adverse events such as nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, ileus, allergic reactions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Usability of the device Instructions for Use (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Usability of the device user manual will be scored on a 5-point Likert scale (1 = very hard to 5 = very easy).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Reduction of Postoperative Adhesions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment group receives a concentrate of coagulation factors. The device concentrates coagulation factors from donor plasma; the concentrate is applied to the surgical site intended to reduce the incidence, extent and severity of postoperative adhesions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group receives an identical syringe and applicator generated by processing normal saline 0.9% instead of plasma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Concentrate of plasma coagulation factors</intervention_name>
    <description>The plasma concentrate of coagulation factors is applied to the surgical site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.9% saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Control group receives an identical syringe and applicator generated by processing normal saline 0.9% instead of plasma.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

        PREOPERATIVE INCLUSION

        Preoperatively the patient must:

          1. Understand and be able to follow the requirements of the protocol including signing
             and dating an Ethics Committee approved Informed Consent prior to undergoing any
             protocol related procedures

          2. Patients undergoing any of the above procedures

          3. Male or female subjects &gt; 18 years of age

          4. Subjects for whom a second abdominal surgery is planned within less than 12 months of
             the first surgical procedure

          5. BMI&lt;40

        INTRAOPERATIVE INCLUSION

        During surgery the patient must require having one of the following surgeries performed on
        their person:

          1. Planned or emergency colonic resection surgery with temporary stoma creation due to
             colonic perforation, acute diverticulitis or colonic obstruction.

          2. Surgery for low rectal cancer - low anterior resection. This surgery includes
             resection of lower part of rectum, colo-anal anastomosis and protective ileostomy
             creation. Usually patient undergo second stage procedure closure of ileostomy in 1-3
             months.

          3. Total proctocolectomy and a pelvic pouch with diverting ileostomy in cases of surgery
             for Ulcerative colitis. In this kind of surgery there is the intention to close the
             temporary ileostomy in 1-3 months.

          4. Creation of stoma due to infectious process or trauma in the peritoneum (such as
             Fournier gangrene, laceration of rectum, etc.)

        Exclusion Criteria

        PREOPERATIVE EXCLUSION

        Preoperatively a patient must not:

          1. be unable to give their own written informed consent,

          2. be currently enrolled in another clinical study with drug or device related to
             adhesions or has participated in such a study within the last 30 days,

          3. have received or is expected to receive any other investigational product or technique
             belonging to the group of hemostats, adhesion reduction devices or other products,
             meshes, or other types of implants in the abdominal cavity within 30 days prior to or
             during enrolment,

          4. subjects who have received or will receive (approximately within the next eight
             months) abdominal/pelvic irradiation for reasons other than rectal carcinoma.

          5. BMI≥40

          6. Subjects who have received selective factor Xa inhibitors and/or direct thrombin
             inhibitors within 24 hours prior to surgery.

          7. Patients taking immune system suppressants deemed by the surgeon to interfere with
             wound healing, Patients taking daily doses of corticosteroids exceeding 20mg within
             the prior 30 days are to be excluded. Patients requiring perioperative corticosteroid
             supplementation are not to be excluded.

          8. Patients with a known history of severe multiple drug allergies

          9. Patients who have a life expectancy of less than 6 months because of a medical
             condition or disease state

         10. Any patient with a medical condition or other serious condition which will interfere
             with compliance and/or ability to complete this study protocol or who in the opinion
             of the investigator would not be a good candidate for enrollment

        INTRAOPERATIVE EXCLUSION

          1. Patients for whom it is known, prior to the initial procedure, that loop ileostomy or
             colostomy closure is not feasible for any reason

          2. Patients with peritoneal carcinomatosis

          3. Patients with endometriosis

          4. Use of hernia mesh in the first surgery.

          5. Subjects treated with hemostatic agents in which the sealant remains in the patient's
             body (e.g. Fibrin sealant).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rafael Miller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EIO Biomedical Ltd., Medical Adviser</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaunas Clinical Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaunas</city>
        <zip>LT-47144</zip>
        <country>Lithuania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of Lithuanian University of Health Sciences Kauno Klinikos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaunas</city>
        <zip>LT-50009</zip>
        <country>Lithuania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Lithuania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tissue Adhesions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

