<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03828994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00068846 Phase II</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01NR013507-03</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03828994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Technology Based Community Health Nursing(TECH-N) to Prevent Recurrent STIs After PID II</brief_title>
  <official_title>Technology Based Community Health Nursing(TECH-N) to Prevent Recurrent STIs After PID</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are enrolling 150 young women 13-25 years old diagnosed with pelvic
      inflammatory disease (PID) in Baltimore to receive community health nurse (CHN) clinical
      support visits and short messaging system communication support for 30 days. The
      investigators' intervention group(TECH-PN) will receive additional testing and treatment in
      the field. The investigators hypothesize that repackaging the recommended Centers for Disease
      Control and Prevention (CDC) follow-up visit using a technology-enhanced community health
      nursing intervention (TECH-N) with integration of an evidence-based sexually transmitted
      infection (STI) prevention curriculum will reduce rates of short-term repeat infection by
      improving adherence to PID treatment and reducing unprotected intercourse and be more
      cost-effective compared with outpatient standard of care (and hospitalization).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pelvic Inflammatory Disease (PID) is a common, serious reproductive disorder that is
      associated with significant adverse reproductive health outcomes such as ectopic pregnancy,
      tubal infertility, chronic pelvic pain, and significant reductions in health-related quality
      of life for affected patients. The Technology Enhanced Community Health (TECH) Nursing Study
      has further demonstrated that the biological milieu associated with PID is more complicated
      than the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) treatment guidance indicates,
      leaving women without adequate treatment for Mycoplasma genitalium (MG) and Trichomonas
      vaginalis (TV). The broad-spectrum antibiotics recommended by the CDC for syndromic PID
      management are suboptimal because: 1) MG is often resistant to doxycycline (standard therapy)
      and macrolides such as Azithromycin (alternative therapy) and 2) metronidazole (effective for
      TV) is an optional add-on to standard PID treatment that is inconsistently prescribed at
      diagnosis. Further MG was not officially considered in CDC STI treatment guidelines until
      release until 2015, testing is only available in large research laboratories, and the paucity
      of data from randomized trials limits the scope of the CDC's recommendations. Finally, while
      there are no public health control programs in the United States for MG and TV, recurrent and
      persistent infection with MG and TV is associated with ongoing inflammation in the female
      genital tract and increased risk for secondary STI and HIV infection due to unhealthy shifts
      in vagina microbiota. The goals of this study are to leverage novel STI diagnostics (new MG
      macrolide resistance testing and TV testing) with the investigators' demonstrated ability to
      reach vulnerable youth to treat adolescents and young adult women with mild-moderate PID with
      precision based on the actual diagnoses rather than suboptimal syndromic management. The
      investigators will add genomic analysis of vaginal specimens to assess compositional changes
      in the five vaginal Lactobacilli community state types associated with optimal vaginal health
      to determine if TECH-precision-nursing (TECH-PN) protocols for field treatment tailored to
      STI results reduces the inflammatory response observed with active vaginal infections. The
      investigators hypothesize that by further repackaging the investigators' previous successful
      TECH-N intervention protocol and translating bench science into precision healthcare, the
      investigators will further reduce the risk of recurrent infection, potentially restore
      vaginal health for PID- affected patients, and add new knowledge that advances public health
      control of STIs and has the potential to reduce the observed STI disparities after PID in
      urban youth.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of STI Trichomonas vaginalis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Trichomonas infection assessed with APTIMA vaginal swab, tested using the GEN-PROBE transcription mediated amplification (TMA) research assay.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of STI Mycoplasma genitalium</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mycoplasma infection assessed with APTIMA vaginal swab, tested using the GEN-PROBE transcription mediated amplification (TMA) research assay.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaginal health as assessed by proportion of high Lactobacilli community state-type 1 properties (CST)</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Vaginal microbiota will be identified with a 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing analysis. The proportion of rRNA assigned to the bacterial genera Lactobacillus will be measured for each sample. CST (I, II, II, IV) will be assigned based on taxa identified.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Pelvic Inflammatory Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TECH-PN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive community health nurse visits, text-messaging support, additional testing and field based visits with a nurse practitioner.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TECH-N</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive enhanced standard of care with community health nurse visits and text-messaging support.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tech-PN</intervention_name>
    <description>text messaging(daily medication reminders and tri-weekly messages following the 14-day treatment period)
enhanced community health nurse visits on day 3-5, 14 and 30
field based treatment visits
clinical assistance with notification, testing and treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>TECH-PN</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Mild-moderate PID

          -  Outpatient treatment disposition

          -  Permanently reside in the Baltimore Metropolitan area

          -  Willing to sign informed consent &amp; be randomized

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant

          -  Concurrent diagnosis of Sexual Assault

          -  Unable to communicate/complete study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Trent, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Huettner</last_name>
    <phone>410-302-3103</phone>
    <email>shuettn1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maria Trent, MD, MPH</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steve Huettner</last_name>
      <phone>410-302-3103</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Study Pager</last_name>
      <phone>410-283-0796</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jennifer Anders, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charlotte A Gaydos, DrPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arlene Butz, ScD, MSN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maunank Shah, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Rothman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rebecca Brotman, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacques Ravel, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anders J, Hill A, Chung SE, Butz A, Rothman R, Gaydos C, Perin J, Trent M. Patient Satisfaction and Treatment Adherence for Urban Adolescents and Young Adults with Pelvic Inflammatory Disease. Trauma Emerg Care. 2018 Jan;3(1). doi: 10.15761/TEC.1000152. Epub 2017 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>29756068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trent M, Chung SE, Gaydos C, Frick KD, Anders J, Huettner S, Rothman R, Butz A. Recruitment of Minority Adolescents and Young Adults into Randomised Clinical Trials: Testing the Design of the Technology Enhanced Community Health Nursing (TECH-N) Pelvic Inflammatory Disease Trial. Eur Med J Reprod Health. 2016 Aug;2(1):41-51.</citation>
    <PMID>27617108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Butz AM, Gaydos C, Chung SE, Johnson BH, Huettner S, Trent M. Care-Seeking Behavior After Notification Among Young Women With Recurrent Sexually Transmitted Infections After Pelvic Inflammatory Disease. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2016 Oct;55(12):1107-12. doi: 10.1177/0009922816662863. Epub 2016 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27507807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muñoz Buchanan CR, Chung SE, Butz A, Perin J, Gaydos C, Trent M. Perceived Social Support, Parental Notification, and Parental Engagement after Pelvic Inflammatory Disease among Urban Adolescent and Young Adults. Pediatr Neonatal Nurs. 2016;4(1):12-16. Epub 2016 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28280783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tabacco L, Chung SE, Perin J, Huettner S, Butz A, Trent M. Relationship Status and Sexual Behaviors in Post-Pelvic Inflammatory Disease (PID) Affected Urban Young Women: A Sub-Study of a Randomized Controlled Trial. Int Arch Nurs Health Care. 2018;4(1). pii: 088. doi: 10.23937/2469-5823/1510088. Epub 2018 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>30221216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haggerty CL, Totten PA, Tang G, Astete SG, Ferris MJ, Norori J, Bass DC, Martin DH, Taylor BD, Ness RB. Identification of novel microbes associated with pelvic inflammatory disease and infertility. Sex Transm Infect. 2016 Sep;92(6):441-6. doi: 10.1136/sextrans-2015-052285. Epub 2016 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26825087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell CM, Haick A, Nkwopara E, Garcia R, Rendi M, Agnew K, Fredricks DN, Eschenbach D. Colonization of the upper genital tract by vaginal bacterial species in nonpregnant women. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2015 May;212(5):611.e1-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2014.11.043. Epub 2014 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25524398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Molenaar MC, Singer M, Ouburg S. The two-sided role of the vaginal microbiome in Chlamydia trachomatis and Mycoplasma genitalium pathogenesis. J Reprod Immunol. 2018 Nov;130:11-17. doi: 10.1016/j.jri.2018.08.006. Epub 2018 Aug 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30149363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang Y, Zhang Y, Zhang Q, Chen H, Feng Y. Characterization of pelvic and cervical microbiotas from patients with pelvic inflammatory disease. J Med Microbiol. 2018 Oct;67(10):1519-1526. doi: 10.1099/jmm.0.000821. Epub 2018 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>30113305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zheng X, O'Connell CM, Zhong W, Poston TB, Wiesenfeld HC, Hillier SL, Trent M, Gaydos C, Tseng G, Taylor BD, Darville T. Gene Expression Signatures Can Aid Diagnosis of Sexually Transmitted Infection-Induced Endometritis in Women. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2018 Sep 20;8:307. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2018.00307. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>30294592</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pelvic Inflammatory Disease(PID)</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Health Nursing</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Text Messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile health (mhealth)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Inflammatory Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

