<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03829553</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RJBC-HFRNI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03829553</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypofractionated Irradiation At Regional Nodal Area for Breast Cancer Vs Existed Standard Treatment</brief_title>
  <acronym>HARVEST</acronym>
  <official_title>Hypofractionated Versus Conventional Intensity-Modulated Radiation Therapy for Breast Cancer Patients With an Indication for Regional Nodal Irradiation: A Randomized Multi-center Phase III Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ruijin Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RenJi Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of the Fourth Military Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ruijin Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objective of this trial is to investigate the efficacy and safety of
      hypofractionated radiotherapy of 3 or 4 weeks by comparing with conventional radiotherapy of
      5 or 6 weeks using intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) in breast cancer patients
      with an indication for regional nodal irradiation (RNI) following mastectomy or breast
      conserving surgery. Patients will be randomized to hypofractionated radiotherapy or
      conventional radiotherapy delivered to chest wall or whole breast and regional lymph regions
      (including supraclavicular and internal mammary lymph nodes). Eligible breast cancer patients
      will be followed for at least 5 years to evaluate the difference in 5-year locoregional
      recurrence, over survival, distant metastasis, toxicity and life quality between two groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Investigators hypothesize that hypofractionated radiotherapy is equally effective and safe as
      conventional radiotherapy in breast cancer patients with an indication for regional nodal
      irradiation. Eligible breast cancer patients are randomized 1:1 into the following two
      groups: hypofractionated radiotherapy of 2.67 Gy for 16 fractions (and sequential tumor bed
      boost of 2.67 Gy for 4 fractions in patients with intact breast) and conventional
      radiotherapy of 2Gy for 25 fractions (and sequential tumor bed boost of 2 Gy for 5 fractions
      in patients with intact breast). The dose was prescribed to ipsilateral chest wall or whole
      breast and regional lymph regions (including supraclavicular and internal mammary lymph
      nodes). All patients are treated with IMRT. The primary endpoint is locoregional recurrence.
      Patients will be followed at least 5 years after radiotherapy to evaluated over survival,
      distant metastasis, toxicity and life quality.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Locoregional recurrence (LRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>any first recurrence confirmed by histology or cytology within the ipsilateral chest wall and/or regional nodes area (including supraclavicular, infraclavicular or internal mammary lymph nodes)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distant metastasis free survival (DMFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to any recurrence of tumor at distant sites or death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Invasive recurrence-free survival (IRFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to any invasive recurrence of tumor or death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>over survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to the date of death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with excellent or good Cosmetic outcomes following breast conserving surgery-Harvard/NSABP/RTOG scoring scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to 5 years after completion of radiotherapy, the cosmetic outcomes will be evaluated before radiotherapy, every week during radiotherapy, 4 weeks after the last fraction received, every 6 months during the first 2 years and annually thereafter. The cosmetic outcomes are evaluated based on the Allegheny General Modification of the Harvard/(National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project) NSABP/ (Radiation Therapy Oncology Group) RTOG scoring scale which graded patients into the following four classifications: excellent, when compared to the untreated breast, there is a minimal or no difference in the size or shape of the treated breast; good, slight difference in the size or shape of the treated breast; fair, obvious difference in the size or shape of the treated breast; and poor, marked change in the size or shape of the treated breast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with ≥Grade1 Acute Radiation-induced Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Within time from beginning of radiotherapy to 3 months after completion of radiotherapy, any acute radiation-induced toxicity will be assessed every week during radiotherapy, 4 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after the last fraction received using the (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events) CTCAE 3.0 and recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with ≥Grade1 Late Radiation-induced Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Within time from 6 months after completion of radiotherapy to 5 years after completion of radiotherapy, any late toxicity will be assessed every 6 months during the first 2 years and annually thereafter using the RTOG/(European Organization for Research on Treatment of Cancer) EORTC Late Radiation Morbidity Scoring Schema and CTCAE 3.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life-EORTC QLQ-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to 5 years after completion of radiotherapy, Quality of life will be assessed before radiotherapy, every week during radiotherapy, 4 weeks after the last fraction received, every 6 months during the first 2 years and annually thereafter using self-administered questionnaire EORTC QLQ-C30</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life-EORTC QLQ-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to 5 years after completion of radiotherapy, Quality of life will be assessed before radiotherapy, every week during radiotherapy, 4 weeks after the last fraction received, every 6 months during the first 2 years and annually thereafter using self-administered questionnaire EORTC QLQ-C30</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life-EORTC QLQ-BR23</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to 5 years after completion of radiotherapy, Quality of life will be assessed before radiotherapy, every week during radiotherapy, 4 weeks after the last fraction received, every 6 months during the first 2 years and annually thereafter using self-administered questionnaire EORTC QLQ-BR23</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life-EORTC QLQ-BR23</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The time from the date of randomization to 5 years after completion of radiotherapy, Quality of life will be assessed before radiotherapy, every week during radiotherapy, 4 weeks after the last fraction received, every 6 months during the first 2 years and annually thereafter using self-administered questionnaire EORTC QLQ-BR23</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">801</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypofractionated radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with an indication for regional nodal irradiation will received 2.67 Gy for 16 fractions to chest wall or whole breast and regional lymph regions (including supraclavicular and internal mammary lymph nodes) and sequential tumor bed boost of 2.67 Gy for 4 fractions following breast conserving surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with an indication for regional nodal irradiation will received 2 Gy for 25 fractions to chest wall or whole breast and regional lymph regions (including supraclavicular and internal mammary lymph nodes) and sequential tumor bed boost of 2 Gy for 5 fractions following breast conserving surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypofractionated radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>4005 cGy/ 15 fractions / 3 weeks to ipsilateral chest wall or whole breast and regional lymph regions (including supraclavicular and internal mammary lymph nodes) and sequential tumor bed boost of 2.67Gy for 4 fractions in patients with intact breast</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypofractionated radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Experimental Arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>5000 cGy/ 25 fractions / 5 weeks ipsilateral chest wall or whole breast and regional lymph regions (including supraclavicular and internal mammary lymph nodes) and sequential tumor bed boost of 2Gy for 5 fractions in patients with intact breast</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Active Comparator Arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Aged 18-75 years old

          -  Underwent radical surgery with either mastectomy or breast conserving surgery and
             axillary lymph node dissection (ALND)

          -  Ipsilateral clinically diagnosed and histologically confirmed invasive breast cancer
             pT1-3

          -  &gt;=1 pathologically positive axillary lymph nodes

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status scoring ≥80

          -  Surgery wound healed without infection

          -  Anticipative overall survival &gt;5 years

          -  Pathologically surgical margin &gt;2mm

          -  ER (estrogen-receptor), PR (progesterone-receptor), HER2 (human epidermal growth
             factor receptor 2) and Ki67 testing can be performed on the primary breast tumor

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception for up to 1
             month before study treatment and the duration of study participation

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to participate the research and sign the consent
             form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Axillary dissection of less than 10 lymph nodes

          -  Pathologically positive ipsilateral supraclavicular lymph node

          -  Pathologically or radiologically confirmed involvement of ipsilateral internal mammary
             lymph nodes

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Treated with breast reconstruction surgery

          -  Severe non-neoplastic medical comorbidities

          -  History of non-breast malignancy within 5 years with the exception of lobular
             carcinoma in situ, basal cell carcinoma of the skin, carcinoma in situ of skin and
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix

          -  simultaneous contralateral breast cancer

          -  Previous radiotherapy to the neck, chest and/or ipsilateral axillary region

          -  Active collagen vascular disease

          -  Definitive pathological or radiologic evidence of distant metastatic disease

          -  Primary T4 tumor

          -  Interval between radical surgery (mastectomy or breast conserving surgery) and
             radiotherapy was more than 12 weeks or interval between last dose of adjuvant
             chemotherapy and radiotherapy was more than 8 weeks
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jia-Yi Chen</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Ruijin Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jia-Yi Chen</last_name>
    <phone>+86-021-64370045</phone>
    <phone_ext>602400</phone_ext>
    <email>chenjiayi0188@aliyun.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ruijin Hospital, Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200025</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jia-Yi Chen, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+86-021-64370045</phone>
      <phone_ext>602400</phone_ext>
      <email>chenjiayi0188@aliyun.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jia-Yi Chen, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>+86-021-64370045</phone>
      <phone_ext>602400</phone_ext>
      <email>chenjiayi0188@aliyun.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ruijin Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jiayi Chen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of Department of Radiation Oncology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>regional nodal irradiation</keyword>
  <keyword>IMRT</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypofractionated radiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

