<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03824327</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OSU-18215</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-00105</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016058</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03824327</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Papaverine and Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy (SBRT) for Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) or Lung Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial Combining Papaverine and Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy for Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer or Lung Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and how well papaverine hydrochloride and
      stereotactic radiation therapy body (SBRT) work in treating patients with non-small cell lung
      cancer. Papaverine hydrochloride may help radiation therapy work better by making tumor cells
      more sensitive to the radiation therapy. Stereotactic body radiation therapy uses special
      equipment to position a patient and deliver radiation to tumors with high precision. This
      method can kill tumor cells with fewer doses over a shorter period and cause less damage to
      normal tissue. Giving papaverine hydrochloride with SBRT may work in treating patients with
      non-small cell lung cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety and tolerability of concurrent papaverine hydrochloride (PPV), and
      lung SBRT in patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) or lung metastases.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess primary tumor control rate, local control rate, local-regional recurrence
      free-survival (LRRFS), disease-free survival (DFS), distant-metastasis-free survival (DMFS),
      and overall survival (OS).

      II. To assess whether blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) functional magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) studies can predict which patients may respond best to PPV + SBRT, and detect
      changes in oxygenation before and after PPV administration.

      III. To assess whether blood-based micro ribonucleic acid (miRNA) biomarkers can predict
      which patients may respond best to PPV + SBRT.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of papaverine hydrochloride.

      Patients undergo BOLD functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) and receive papaverine
      hydrochloride intravenously (IV) on day 1. Within 30-90 minutes, patients undergo a second
      BOLD fMRI. Patients then receive papaverine hydrochloride IV and within 30-90 minutes after
      dose undergo SBRT for a up to 4-5 sessions over 2 weeks.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 4-6 weeks, 3 and 6 months, 1
      and 2 years, then every 3 months for 2 years, and then every 6 months for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 7, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will employ the Bayesian optimal interval (BOIN) design to find the MTD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary tumor control</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 and 24 months after stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT) completion</time_frame>
    <description>Primary tumor control is defined as the absence of primary tumor failure. Will be calculated and 95% exact binomial confidence interval will be provided.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local control rate (primary tumor control + involved lobar control)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months after SBRT completion</time_frame>
    <description>Local control is defined as the absence of local failure. Will be calculated and 95% exact binomial confidence interval will be provided.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local-regional recurrence free-survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of entry onto study until the time of documented local-regional recurrence or death, assessed up to 12 months after SBRT completion</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distant metastasis-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from entry onto study until the time of documented metastatic recurrence or death, assessed up to 12 months after SBRT treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from entry onto study until the time of any documented disease recurrence or death, assessed up to 12 months after SBRT completion</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from study entry until time of death from any cause, assessed up to 12 months after SBRT completion</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) blood oxygen level-dependent (BOLD) response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured before and after papaverine hydrochloride (PPV) delivery by the percentage change in relaxation rate on MRI. Will also analyze biomarkers descriptively and graphically to assess trends in changes in these markers over time and the association with response. Exploratory comparisons of groups of patients based on response will involve the use of analysis of variance (ANOVA) for continuous data and categorical methods such as Fisher?s exact and chi-square tests for discrete data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in hypoxia-inducible micro ribonucleic acids (miRNAs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will analyze patient serum pre-and post-treatment for hypoxia-associated at pre- and post- SBRT treatment hypoxia-inducible microRNAs (miRs) using nanoString miRNA assay that could indicate the presence of tumor hypoxia. The changes in circulating biomarkers will be validated by alternative quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) based approaches. These results will be cross-validated with the BOLD data. Will also analyze biomarkers descriptively and graphically to assess trends in changes in these markers over time and the association with response. Exploratory comparisons of groups of patients based on response will involve the use of ANOVA for continuous data and categorical methods such as Fisher?s exact and chi-square tests for discrete data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Non-Small Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BOLD fMRI, papaverine hydrochloride, SBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo BOLD fMRI and receive papaverine hydrochloride IV on day 1. Within 30-90 minutes, patients undergo a second BOLD fMRI. Patients then receive papaverine hydrochloride IV and within 30-90 minutes after dose undergo SBRT for a up to 4-5 sessions over 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Oxygen Level Dependent Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo BOLD fMRI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BOLD fMRI, papaverine hydrochloride, SBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blood Oxygen Level Dependent Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>BOLD</other_name>
    <other_name>BOLD fMRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Papaverine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BOLD fMRI, papaverine hydrochloride, SBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cerebid</other_name>
    <other_name>Cerespan</other_name>
    <other_name>Pap H</other_name>
    <other_name>Pavabid</other_name>
    <other_name>Pavacap</other_name>
    <other_name>Therapav</other_name>
    <other_name>Vasal</other_name>
    <other_name>Vaso-Pav</other_name>
    <other_name>Vasospan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo SBRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (BOLD fMRI, papaverine hydrochloride, SBRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SABR</other_name>
    <other_name>SBRT</other_name>
    <other_name>Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiation Therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically proven NSCLC for whom SBRT to a single lesion has been
             chosen as the primary treatment modality (planned dose 50 Gy in 4-5 daily fractions).
             Patients with lung metastases from solid tumors are eligible.

          -  Patients must have a tumor =&lt; 5 cm as defined by computed tomography (CT) largest
             axial dimension. Presence of adjacent nodules considered neoplastic in the same lobe
             or other ipsilateral lobe are allowed as long as the nodule(s) can be encompassed in
             an SBRT gross tumor volume (GTV) of =&lt; 5 cm, within 1 isocenter. Multiple isocenters
             are not allowed

          -  No prior radiation resulting in overlapping fields

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Must be able to undergo correlative research MRIs

          -  No active connective tissue disease (scleroderma) or idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis
             (IPF)

          -  No history of complete atrioventricular block, hepatic dysfunction (e.g. cirrhosis),
             or priapism

          -  Within 30 days of registration: patients must have vital signs, history/physical
             examination, and laboratory studies (liver function tests, creatinine or creatinine
             clearance assessment)

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks in the opinion of investigator

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative pregnancy test within 14
             days of registration. Urine human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG) is an acceptable
             pregnancy assessment. Nursing women may participate only if nursing is discontinued,
             due to the possibility of harm to nursing infants from the treatment regimen

          -  Within 90 days of registration: pulmonary function tests (PFTs) including forced
             expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV-1) and diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon
             monoxide (DLCO)

          -  Albumin &gt;= 2.5 g/dL (within 30 days of study registration)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) (within 30 days of study
             registration)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN
             (within 30 days of study registration)

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN or calculated creatinine &gt;= 50 mL/min, calculated by the
             Cockcroft-Gault formula or 24-hour urine creatinine clearance &gt;= 50 mL/min (within 30
             days of study registration)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of another malignancy

               -  Exception: Subjects who have been disease-free for &gt;= 3 years, or subjects with a
                  history of localized prostate cancer, in situ carcinoma (e.g. breast, cervix,
                  oral cavity), differentiated thyroid neoplasm, completely resected non-melanoma
                  skin cancer, are eligible

          -  Any serious and/or unstable pre-existing medical disorder (aside from malignancy
             exception above), psychiatric disorder, or other conditions that could interfere with
             subject?s safety, obtaining informed consent or compliance to the study procedures, in
             the opinion of the investigator

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding: Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use
             adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior
             to study entry, the duration of study participation and for 4 months after the last
             dose of study treatment. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant
             while participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician
             immediately. No breastfeeding while patient is on study

          -  Patients with history of pneumonectomy

          -  Prior cytotoxic chemotherapy, molecularly-targeted agents (e.g. erlotinib,
             crizotinib), or immunotherapy unless &gt;= 2 weeks from last dose. Patients can start
             chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or other systemic therapy after completion of SBRT, but
             this should be planned for ≥ 2 weeks from last SBRT dose.

          -  History of active connective tissue disease (scleroderma), idiopathic pulmonary
             fibrosis, pneumonitis

          -  Hepatic insufficiency resulting in jaundice and/or coagulation defects, or not meeting
             laboratory values (albumin, total bilirubin, AST/ALT)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Terence Williams, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>The Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-293-5066</phone>
    <email>OSUCCCClinicaltrials@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Terence M. Williams</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-8415</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terence M. Williams</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.osu.edu</url>
    <description>The Jamesline</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Terence Williams</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Papaverine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

