<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03822741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHFudanU_NNICU10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03822741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Etiology and Treatment of Neonatal Seizure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gene Profiling and Individualized Treatment of Neonatal Seizure in China</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Fudan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Fudan University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Genetic diagnosis for neonates suffering from epilepsy has important implications for
      treatment, prognosis, and development of precision medicine strategies. Investigator
      performed exome sequencing (ES) or targeted sequencing on neonates with seizure onset within
      the first month of life. Investigator subgrouped our patients based on the onset age of
      seizure into neonatal and before 1 year (1-12 months), to compare the clinical and genetic
      features and treatment strategies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Seizure is one of the most common neurological conditions in neonates, and has substantial
      impact on patients'quality of life and social integration. Epileptic encephalopathy is
      characterized by refractory seizures, cognitive dysfunction, and poor prognosis. Despite the
      recent progress in technology, molecular diagnosis of neonates suffering from possible
      epileptic seizures can be challenging, due to genetic and phenotypic heterogeneities. A large
      number of specific pathogenic variations have been related to various forms of epilepsies.
      Next-generation sequencing (NGS) has significantly improved the molecular diagnosis for rare
      diseases. NGS focusing on genes known to be associated with human diseases is a practical
      approach as a first-tier assessment for patients with heterogeneous genetic background. In
      addition, currently medical therapy for seizure is not based on the etiology, but the
      clinical manifestations, and the main purpose is not to rescue the underlying diseases
      process, but just to reduce the likelihood of seizures occurrence. In this study,
      Investigator performed NGS on neonates with seizure onset before 1 year of age, to detect and
      quantify genetic variants, and assess existing therapeutic effects. Our findings will have
      important implications for the development of precision medicine strategies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 8, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mutation rate of common seizure genes</measure>
    <time_frame>From the oneset of seizure to the genetic sequencing finish, the process may last up to 3 months.</time_frame>
    <description>We'll get the genetic profiles of all neonates who had seizures during this period. The mutation rate of common variant gene was calculated by gene spectrum.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of seizure free</measure>
    <time_frame>From the onset of seizure to 6 months after the onset of seizure</time_frame>
    <description>After the onset of seizure, through clinical management and individualized intervention, we expect to observe the number and proportion of effective seizure treatments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Seizures</condition>
  <condition>Seizure Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Seizure Newborn</condition>
  <condition>Seizure Generalized</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Biological samples contain 2ml of blood, which is used to extract DNA from the blood for gene
      sequencing.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The subjects were treated in the Department of Neonatology of Children Hospital of Fudan
        University. All samples in this study were collected with appropriate informed consent and
        approval of the ethics committee of Children's Hospital, Fudan University. The methods used
        in this study were carried out in accordance with the approved guidelines.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  severe seizures in neonates or generalized epilepsy or intractable epilepsy in infancy
             with generalized tonic-clonic seizures,

          -  seizures onset before 1 year of age,

          -  epileptic syndromes/epileptic-encephalopathies with unknown etiology.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients were excluded if they had traumas, central nervous system infections,
             hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy, vascular events, systemic infections, and diagnosed
             metabolic disorders, and pathogenic copy-number variants were identified using
             array-based comparative genomic hybridization (CGH).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wenhao Zhou, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Fudan University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wenhao Zhou, Doctor</last_name>
    <email>zwhchfu@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lin Yang, Doctor</last_name>
    <email>yanglin_fudan@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children Hospital of Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>201102</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wenhao Zhou, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>(+86)021-64931003</phone>
      <email>zwhchfu@126.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>EpiPM Consortium. A roadmap for precision medicine in the epilepsies. Lancet Neurol. 2015 Dec;14(12):1219-28. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(15)00199-4. Epub 2015 Sep 20. Review. Erratum in: Lancet Neurol. 2016 Mar;15(3):241.</citation>
    <PMID>26416172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lemke JR, Riesch E, Scheurenbrand T, Schubach M, Wilhelm C, Steiner I, Hansen J, Courage C, Gallati S, Bürki S, Strozzi S, Simonetti BG, Grunt S, Steinlin M, Alber M, Wolff M, Klopstock T, Prott EC, Lorenz R, Spaich C, Rona S, Lakshminarasimhan M, Kröll J, Dorn T, Krämer G, Synofzik M, Becker F, Weber YG, Lerche H, Böhm D, Biskup S. Targeted next generation sequencing as a diagnostic tool in epileptic disorders. Epilepsia. 2012 Aug;53(8):1387-98. doi: 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2012.03516.x. Epub 2012 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22612257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Møller RS, Larsen LH, Johannesen KM, Talvik I, Talvik T, Vaher U, Miranda MJ, Farooq M, Nielsen JE, Svendsen LL, Kjelgaard DB, Linnet KM, Hao Q, Uldall P, Frangu M, Tommerup N, Baig SM, Abdullah U, Born AP, Gellert P, Nikanorova M, Olofsson K, Jepsen B, Marjanovic D, Al-Zehhawi LI, Peñalva SJ, Krag-Olsen B, Brusgaard K, Hjalgrim H, Rubboli G, Pal DK, Dahl HA. Gene Panel Testing in Epileptic Encephalopathies and Familial Epilepsies. Mol Syndromol. 2016 Sep;7(4):210-219. Epub 2016 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27781031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Striano P, Zara F. Epilepsy: Common and rare epilepsies share genetic determinants. Nat Rev Neurol. 2017 Apr;13(4):200-201. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2017.30. Epub 2017 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>28281535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Striano P, Vari MS, Mazzocchetti C, Verrotti A, Zara F. Management of genetic epilepsies: From empirical treatment to precision medicine. Pharmacol Res. 2016 May;107:426-429. doi: 10.1016/j.phrs.2016.04.006. Epub 2016 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27080588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang K, Li M, Hakonarson H. ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res. 2010 Sep;38(16):e164. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkq603. Epub 2010 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20601685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myers CT, Mefford HC. Advancing epilepsy genetics in the genomic era. Genome Med. 2015 Aug 25;7:91. doi: 10.1186/s13073-015-0214-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26302787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>seizure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Seizures</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

